<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-11-12T09:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-11-12T09:45:00-05:00" n="448" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d448">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">817.00/6085: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Eberhardt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Managua</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-11-12T09:00:00-05:45"><hi rend="italic">November 12,
                                        1928—9 a.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 1:55
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>385. [From] General McCoy. I beg to submit the following report upon the
                            election on November 4th. The results stated below are based upon
                            telegraphic returns and are not therefore to be regarded as final. All
                            of the 432 precincts have, however, reported and present indications are
                            that no material corrections will be necessary later. Our information
                            now appears sufficiently complete to warrant the following
                            observations:</p>
                        <p>No instance of disorder on election day occurred in any part of the
                            Republic. The voting proceeded smoothly and in many urban cantons was
                            practically completed by noon. In no reported case was it necessary to
                            keep the polls open beyond 4 p.m. The stain with which the fingers of
                            voters were marked was accepted in good humor and no efforts to remove
                            it and vote twice have been reported. Its use was undoubtedly helpful in
                            preventing fraud and inspiring popular acceptance of the results. The
                            total reported vote was 132, 949 and shows a Liberal Party majority of
                            19,471 votes for President and Vice President. Eighty-eight percent of
                            the persons registered voted. This high percent was practically uniform
                            in all the departments except Nueva Segovia and Jinotega, where the
                            average fell to 82 percent. The results of the election appear to have
                            been accepted in good part by all concerned. Surprisingly few votes were
                            the subject of objection at the polls. In the canvass of votes for
                            President, Vice President, and Senators, all such objections can be
                            disregarded without affecting the results and no question as to these
                            elections is expected to come before the National Board. Of the 9
                            Senators apparently elected the Liberals have secured 5 and the
                            Conservatives 4 and as a consequence the two parties will be equally
                            represented in the Senate with 12 seats each. All incoming Senators were
                            elected by decisive majorities in which challenged votes will have no
                            significance so far as can be foreseen. Of the 25 Deputies apparently
                            elected the Liberals have secured 17 and the Conservatives 8; 23 of the
                            number received majorities which appear conclusive. Two Deputies,
                            however, were elected by majorities of but one vote in each case. It was
                            anticipated that difficulties might arise in the final canvass of these
                            two districts. The election in one case, that of a Conservative from
                            Masaya, has already been confirmed unanimously by the departmental
                            board. The other election, that of a Liberal Deputy from Granada, has
                            been confirmed by departmental board, but not unanimously and will now
                            come before <pb facs="0628" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/> the National
                            Board. Indications are that the next Chamber will contain 23
                            Conservatives and 20 Liberals and that the united Congress, which will
                            proclaim the election of President and Vice President, will contain a
                            majority of 3 Conservatives in joint session. At present departmental
                            boards are engaged in canvassing the election results as reported by
                            precinct and in considering any complaints or protests that may be
                            presented. On November 12th the National Board will begin its final
                            review of the returns as submitted by the departmental boards. In view
                            of the apparent decisive majorities reported in all cases but those of
                            the two Deputies mentioned above it is not anticipated that final review
                            by the National Board will be prolonged. Upon the completion of the
                            canvass by the National Board, certificates of election will be issued
                            to the successful candidates. Under the Nicaraguan Constitution the
                            election of President and Vice President is proclaimed by the united
                            Houses of Congress after each body has passed on the election of its own
                            members and has organized for business. According to Nicaraguan practice
                            the elections and qualifications of Senators and Deputies are passed
                            upon by the hold-over members of the respective Houses, who meet in
                            preparatory sessions on December 10th to examine the credentials of the
                            newly elected members. While, as stated above, the Conservatives will
                            have probably a majority of 3 votes in joint session, present
                            indications are that the decision of the National Board of Elections
                            will be respected by the Congress. The satisfactory results above
                            outlined were without doubt due to the complete cooperation of all
                            American services and personnel. The protection and police arrangements
                            made and the wise precautions of the naval, marine and <hi rend="italic">guardia</hi> commanders, will be fully reported on later. Our
                            report on the election of Senators and Deputies will be communicated to
                            the preparatory bodies of the respective Houses on December 10th, and
                            our report on the election of President and Vice President will be
                            presented to the united Congress on or about December 15, the date fixed
                            by the Constitution for its formal installation. The date fixed for the
                            inauguration of the President is January 1st, 1929. Beginning November
                            18 my assistants will leave Nicaragua as rapidly as their services can
                            be spared. My present plan is to leave Nicaragua with my remaining
                            assistants as soon as the report on the election of President and Vice
                            President has been submitted to the united Congress. I request no
                            announcement be made nor action taken on withdrawal of troops, pending
                            cabled recommendations from here to be forwarded in a few days. Admiral
                                <pb facs="0629" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/> Sellers is here and in
                            consultation on the subject with the Minister, General Feland and
                            myself.</p>
                        <p>It is requested that the Bureau of Insular Affairs forward a synopsis of
                            the above, so far as it pertains to the elections held in Nicaragua, to
                            Governor General Stimson, Manila.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Eberhardt</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>