<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Norwegian Chargé ( (Steen))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d547</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">547</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1925-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1925-08-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1925-08-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1925-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="547"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d547">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.5721/42</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Norwegian Chargé</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Steen</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1925-08-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 13, 1925</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your note of
                    July 31, 1925, informing me that your Government will be glad to negotiate at
                    Washington the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Consular Rights, which this
                    Government desires to propose. I take pleasure in submitting to you for the
                    consideration of your Government the draft of such a treaty.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d547fn2">Draft treaty not printed. For text of treaty as signed, see
                            <ref target="#pg_646">p. 646</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0704" n="594" xml:id="pg_594"/>
                <p>The document embodies a consular convention as well as a treaty of friendship and
                    commerce. An attempt has been made to express the several articles in terms
                    which definitely set forth the principles involved. By this means it is sought
                    to avoid as far as possible danger of conflicting interpretations.</p>
                <p>Article VII makes full provision for the enjoyment of the most favored nation
                    treatment in its unconditional form, as applied to persons, vessels and cargoes,
                    and to articles the growth, produce or manufacture of the United States and
                    Norway. It will be seen that the most favored nation clause is applied to duties
                    on imports and exports and to other charges, restrictions and prohibitions on
                    goods imported and exported. In Article XXX it is provided that the Treaty shall
                    from the date of the exchange of ratifications supplant the Treaty of Commerce
                    and Navigation concluded by the United States and the King of Sweden and Norway
                    on July 4, 1827.<note n="3" xml:id="d547fn3">Miller, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Treaties</hi>, vol. 3, p. 283.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Your Government will of course understand that this Government reserves the right
                    to make minor changes in the proposals in the event that in the course of the
                    negotiations, occasion should arise for so doing.</p>
                <p>While the negotiations will be conducted at this capital, the American Legation
                    at Oslo will be kept fully informed in regard to the progress of the
                    negotiations and will be prepared to engage in conversations directly with the
                    Norwegian Foreign Office.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
