<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Persia ( (Philip) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d626</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">626</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-05-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recmU3mkCMXw0nKe9" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Foreign nationals</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="receNc7LQFkxnPn2F" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-05-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="626"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d626">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">791.003/140</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Persia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 18, 1928</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received June 14.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 599</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Adverting to previous telegraphic and other
                    correspondence exchanged with the Department relative to the consummation of a
                    provisional agreement to replace our capitulatory treaty with the Persian
                    Government which expired on May 10, 1928, and with particular reference to my
                    cable messages Nos. 55 and 56 of May 14, 2 P.M. and May 16, 3 P.M.,
                    respectively, I have the honor to transmit herewith the following enclosures: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>A copy of a note from the American Minister to the Persian Acting
                            Minister of Foreign Affairs, dated May 14, 1928, which constitutes a
                            provisional arrangement regarding Diplomatic, Consular, Tariff and other
                            relations between the United States and Persia.</item>
                        <pb facs="0832" n="722" xml:id="pg_722"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>A copy of a note from the Persian Acting Minister of Foreign Affairs
                            to the American Minister, dated May 14, 1928, to the same effect.</item>
                        <label>3 and 4.</label>
                        <item>Copies of notes of acknowledgment and cognizance exchanged between the
                            American Minister and the Persian Acting Minister of Foreign Affairs,
                            dated May 14, 1928.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>A copy and translation of a note from the Persian Acting Minister of
                            Foreign Affairs to the American Minister, dated May 14 [<hi
                                rend="italic">10?</hi>], 1928, which constitutes a provisional
                            declaration as to safeguards for citizens of the United States in Persia
                            in the absence of Consular jurisdictional privileges.</item>
                        <label>6 and 7.</label>
                        <item>Copies and translations of notes exchanged between the American
                            Minister and the Persian Acting Minister of Foreign Affairs, dated May
                            14, 1928, in regard to the philanthropic and educational work of
                            American Missionaries in Persia.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Desirous of complying with the Department’s instructions to supply it with these
                    copies without delay, I find it difficult in the short period now at my disposal
                    to submit adequate comments, either upon the various phases of the negotiations
                    which have led up to the signing of the notes herewith transmitted or upon the
                    difficulties under which they were conducted. This I shall hope to do at a later
                    date.</p>
                <p>The Department will kindly observe that the last paragraph of Section 2 of the
                    agreements exchanged on May 14th (enclosures 1 and 2 above) provide for the
                    settlement of the question of personal status and family law jurisdiction by
                    means of an early exchange of separate notes.</p>
                <p>I regretted that the Department was unable to approve the wording of the draft
                    mentioned in the third paragraph of my cable message No. 48 of May 7, 2 P.M., as
                    a means of reaching an accord with the Persian Government in the matter of
                    personal status and family law jurisdiction. Had such approval been possible at
                    the time, I have reason to believe that I would have been the first to arrive at
                    and sign an agreement with the Persian Government more satisfactory than had
                    then been accorded to the other powers.</p>
                <p>However, the last minute decision by the British Government to acknowledge
                    Persia’s new autonomous tariff had the effect of rendering the situation less
                    acute and of ameliorating the attitude of the Persian Government toward all
                    interested powers in the matter of most-favored-nation rights, etc. Our chief
                    strong point in this matter lay in the fact that having been assured of favored
                    nation rights in tariff matters our position was independent of such decision as
                    might be reached by the British Government. Whereas the German representative
                    together with those of practically all other powers, with the possible exception
                    of France, had not been so assured, and were awaiting the outcome of the
                    Anglo-Persian negotiations before taking definite action.</p>
                <pb facs="0833" n="723" xml:id="pg_723"/>
                <p>As soon as I am able to agree with the Persian Government upon what seems to be
                    an appropriate text as a basis for an exchange of notes relative to matters of
                    personal status and family law jurisdiction it will be at once submitted to the
                    Department for its consideration.</p>
                <p>With this exception, which I feel confident will offer no fundamental difficulty,
                    I consider that the understandings now arrived at and signed assure to American
                    citizens in Persia a treatment fully as favorable as that granted, or which may
                    be granted, to the nationals of other foreign countries.</p>
                <p>In my cable message No. 56 of May 16, 3 P.M. I informed the Department that I had
                    exchanged notes under date of May 14th (enclosures 6 and 7) relative to the
                    recognition by the Persian Government of the philanthropic and educational work
                    of American Missionaries in this country.</p>
                <p>The unannounced omission of such a statement from the Persian declaration on
                    safeguards caused me both surprise and indignation. Subsequently, I learned
                    that, for reasons of its own, the Persian Government had decided to eliminate
                    this from its general declarations, but that it was prepared to exchange
                    separate notes on the subject and that it had, in fact, done so in the case of
                    the British Minister. I consulted with Sir Robert Clive, who appears to be much
                    pleased with the result of his negotiations, and obtained from him copies of his
                    note regarding missionary interests and the section of his provisional treaty
                    which refers to personal status and family law jurisdiction. The text of my own
                    note regarding missionary interests is practically identical with the
                    former.</p>
                <p>With regard to the question of personal status, etc., all my colleagues with whom
                    I have discussed it seem to be of the opinion that, under the circumstances,
                    there is no particularly vital issue involved therein; that the practical result
                    will be that foreigners will administer their own laws of personal status, etc.,
                    in Persia, while Persians abroad will be only too desirous of seeking the
                    assistance of the tribunals of the country of their residence whenever
                    possible.</p>
                <p>It was only toward the close of my negotiations with Teimourtache and when his
                    hand had been palpably stiffened by success in other directions that he
                    developed a definite intention of insisting upon the unilateral nature of the
                    agreements under discussion.</p>
                <p>This, I understand, was due to the fact that according to the Persian laws all
                    bi-lateral agreements must be submitted to the Medjliss for its approval,
                    whereas those of a unilateral nature are not subject to parliamentary
                    discussion. At the same time, Teimourtache was equally insistent that my note
                    should represent the initiative action to which that of the Persian Government
                    would <pb facs="0834" n="724" xml:id="pg_724"/> be a reply. I took exception to
                    this and insisted in turn that if the notes were to be unilateral they must also
                    be identical as to the initiative taken. So acrimonious did the discussion of
                    this apparently trivial point become that a complete breach of negotiations was
                    for a time threatened. Finally the matter was adjusted by a mutual agreement to
                    exchange supplementary notes expressing mutual receipt and cognizance.</p>
                <p>This was rendered additionally necessary owing to the fact that Teimourtache,
                    under the advice of the French legal adviser of the Foreign Office, consistently
                    refused to embody in the note of the Persian Government reference to the
                    contents of Sub-section 1 of my text of the provision regarding the treatment of
                    Cuba, Panama Canal Zone, territories and possessions, etc. I understand that
                    this refusal was based entirely upon the supposition that a repetition of the
                    text of these reservations would be a departure from the unilateral nature of
                    the arrangement.</p>
                <p>I beg to mention also that Teimourtache requested the deletion from the text of
                    the word “arrangement” wherever employed in a sense descriptive of the main
                    document, and the substitution for it of the words “stipulation”, or
                    “stipulations”.</p>
                <p>Apparently, it was desired in this way to avoid the semblance of a more formal
                    instrument in the eyes of the Persian public.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hoffman Philip</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The American Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Persian Acting Minister for Foreign
                            Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 14, 1928</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that my
                        Government, animated by the sincere desire to terminate as soon as possible
                        the negotiations now in progress with the Imperial Government of Persia in
                        regard to the conclusion of a Treaty of Friendship, as well as
                        Establishment, Consular, Commercial and Tariff Conventions between the
                        United States of America and Persia, has instructed me to communicate to the
                        Imperial Government of Persia in its name the following provisional
                        stipulations:</p>
                    <p>1) After May 10, 1928, the diplomatic representation of Persia in the United
                        States, its territories and possessions, shall enjoy, on a basis of complete
                        reciprocity, the privileges and immunities derived from generally recognized
                        international law.</p>
                    <p>The Consular representatives of Persia, duly provided with exequatur, will be
                        permitted to reside in the United States, its territories and possessions,
                        in the districts where they have been formerly admitted.</p>
                    <pb facs="0835" n="725" xml:id="pg_725"/>
                    <p>They shall, on a basis of complete reciprocity, enjoy the honorary privileges
                        and personal immunities in regard to jurisdiction and fiscal matters secured
                        to them by generally recognized international law.</p>
                    <p>2) After May 10, 1928, Persian nationals in the United States, its
                        territories and possessions, shall, on a basis of complete reciprocity, be
                        received and treated in accordance with the requirements and practices of
                        generally recognized international law.</p>
                    <p>In respect to their persons and possessions, rights and interests, they shall
                        enjoy the fullest protection of the laws and authorities of the Country, and
                        they shall not be treated, in regard to the above mentioned subjects, in a
                        manner less favorable than the nationals of any other foreign country.</p>
                    <p>In general, they shall enjoy in every respect the same treatment as the
                        nationals of the Country, without, however, being entitled to the treatment
                        reserved alone to nationals to the exclusion of all foreigners.</p>
                    <p>Matters of personal status and family law will be dealt with in separate
                        notes to be concluded and exchanged at the earliest possible date.</p>
                    <p>3) After May 10, 1928, and as long as the present stipulations remain in
                        force, and on a basis of complete reciprocity, the United States will accord
                        to merchandise produced or manufactured in Persia upon entry into the United
                        States, its territories and possessions, the benefits of the tariff accorded
                        to the most favored nation; from which it follows that the treatment
                        extended to the products of Persia should not be less favorable than that
                        granted to a third country.</p>
                    <p>In respect to the regime to be applied to the Commerce of Persia in the
                        matter of import, export, and other duties and charges affecting commerce as
                        well as in respect to transit warehousing and the facilities accorded
                        commercial travelers’ samples; and also as regards commodities, tariffs and
                        quantities in connection with the licensing or prohibitions of imports and
                        exports, the United States shall accord to Persia, on a basis of complete
                        reciprocity, a treatment not less advantageous than that accorded to the
                        commerce of any other country.</p>
                    <p>It is understood that no higher or other duties shall be imposed on the
                        importation into or disposition in the United States, its territories or
                        possessions, of any article, the product or manufacture of Persia, than are
                        or shall be payable on like articles, the product or manufacture of any
                        foreign country; similarly, and on a basis of complete reciprocity, no
                        higher or other duties shall be imposed in the United States, its
                        territories or possessions, on the exportation of <pb facs="0836" n="726"
                            xml:id="pg_726"/> any articles to Persia than are payable on the
                        exportation of like articles to any foreign country.</p>
                    <p>On a basis of complete reciprocity, any lowering of duty of any kind that may
                        be accorded by the United States in favor of the merchandise of any other
                        country will become immediately applicable without request and without
                        compensation to the commerce of Persia with the United States, its
                        territories and possessions.</p>
                    <p>Providing that this understanding does not relate to: <list>
                            <label>1)</label>
                            <item>The treatment which the United States accords or may hereafter
                                accord to the commerce of Cuba, or any of the territories or
                                possessions of the United States, or the Panama Canal Zone, or to
                                the treatment which is or may hereafter be accorded to the commerce
                                of the United States with any of its territories or possessions, or
                                to the commerce of its territories or possessions with one
                                another;</item>
                            <label>2)</label>
                            <item>Prohibitions or restrictions authorized by the laws and
                                regulations in force in the United States, its territories or
                                possessions, aiming at the protection of the food supply, sanitary
                                administration in regard to human, animal or vegetable life, and the
                                enforcement of police and revenue laws.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The present stipulations shall become operative on the day of signature, and
                        shall remain respectively in effect until the entry in force of the Treaty
                        and Conventions referred to in the first paragraph of this note, or until
                        thirty days after notice of their termination shall have been given by the
                        Government of the United States to the Imperial Government of Persia, but
                        should the Government of the United States be prevented by future action of
                        its legislature from carrying out the terms of these stipulations the
                        obligations thereof shall thereupon lapse.</p>
                    <p>I shall be glad to have your confirmation of the understanding thus
                        reached.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hoffman Philip</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2—Translation<note n="46a"
                                xml:id="d626fn46a">Translation printed from Department of State
                                Executive Agreement Series No. 19.</note>]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Persian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Minister</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 14, 1928</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: I have the honor to advise you that
                        my Government, animated by the sincere desire to terminate as soon as
                        possible the negotiations now in progress with the Government of the United
                        States relative to the conclusion of a treaty of friendship, as well as
                        establishment, consular, customs, and commercial conventions, has <pb
                            facs="0837" n="727" xml:id="pg_727"/> directed me to communicate to you,
                        in its name, the following provisional stipulations:</p>
                    <p>1. On and after May 10, 1928, the diplomatic representation of the United
                        States of America in Persian territory shall enjoy, on condition of complete
                        reciprocity, the privileges and immunities sanctioned by generally
                        recognized international law.</p>
                    <p>The consular representatives of the United States of America in Persian
                        territory, duly provided with an exequatur, shall be permitted, on condition
                        of complete reciprocity, to reside there in the localities to which they
                        were admitted up to that time.</p>
                    <p>They shall enjoy, on the condition of complete reciprocity, the honorary
                        privileges and personal immunities in regard to jurisdiction and fiscal
                        matters sanctioned by generally recognized international law.</p>
                    <p>2. On and after May 10, 1928, the nationals of the United States in Persia
                        shall on the basis of complete reciprocity be admitted and treated in
                        accordance with the rules and practices of generally recognized
                        international law.</p>
                    <p>In respect of their persons and property, rights and interests, they shall
                        enjoy there the fullest protection of the laws and the territorial
                        authorities of the country, and they shall not be treated in regard to the
                        above-mentioned matters in a manner less favorable than the nationals of
                        other foreign countries.</p>
                    <p>They shall enjoy, in every respect, the same general treatment as the
                        nationals of the country, without being entitled, however, to the treatment
                        reserved to nationals alone, to the exclusion of all other foreigners.</p>
                    <p>Matters of personal status and family law shall be treated in special notes
                        to be drawn up and exchanged as soon as possible.</p>
                    <p>3. On and after May 10, 1928, and as long as the present provisions shall
                        remain in force, and on condition of complete reciprocity, merchandise
                        produced or manufactured in the United States, its territories and
                        possessions, on their entry into Persia, shall enjoy the tariff accorded to
                        the most favored nation, so that the treatment accorded to the United States
                        for its merchandise shall not be less favorable than the legal treatment
                        accorded to a third country.</p>
                    <p>In respect to the régime applicable to the commerce of the United States of
                        America, in the matter of import and export and other duties and charges
                        relating to commerce, as well as to transit, warehousing, and the facilities
                        accorded to commercial travelers’ samples, and as to facilities, tariffs,
                        and quantities in connection with the licensing and prohibition of imports
                        and exports, Persia shall accord to the United States, its territories, and
                        possessions, on condition of complete reciprocity, a treatment not less
                        favorable than that accorded to the commerce of any other foreign
                        country.</p>
                    <pb facs="0838" n="728" xml:id="pg_728"/>
                    <p>It is understood that other or higher duties shall not be applied to the
                        importation into or the sale in Persia of any articles, produced or
                        manufactured in the United States, its territories and possessions, than
                        those which would be payable on like articles produced or manufactured by
                        any other foreign country.</p>
                    <p>Similarly and on condition of complete reciprocity, no other or higher duties
                        shall be imposed in Persia on the exportation of any articles to the United
                        States, its territories or possessions, than those which would be payable on
                        the exportation of like articles to any other foreign country.</p>
                    <p>On condition of complete reciprocity, any lowering of duties of any kind that
                        may be granted by Persia in favor of the products of any other country shall
                        be immediately applicable, without request and without compensation, to the
                        commerce of the United States, its territories and possessions, with
                        Persia.</p>
                    <p>It is understood that these provisions do not refer to the prohibitions and
                        restrictions authorized by the laws and regulations in force in Persia for
                        protection of the food supply, sanitary administration in regard to human,
                        animal, or vegetable life, the interests of public safety and fiscal
                        interests.</p>
                    <p>The stipulations of the present note shall go into effect to-day and they
                        shall remain respectively in force until the entry into effect of the
                        corresponding treaty and conventions referred to in the first paragraph of
                        this note or until the expiration of a period of thirty days from the notice
                        which may be given to the Government of the United States by my Government
                        of its intention to terminate them, but in case my Government should be
                        prevented from fulfilling its engagements by the effect of a legislative
                        measure, these stipulations shall lapse.</p>
                    <p>I would be glad to have confirmation of our understanding on these
                        points.</p>
                    <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 3]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The American Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Persian Acting Minister for Foreign
                            Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 14, 1928</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to inform you, in the
                        name of my Government, that I have received and taken note of the contents
                        of your note of to-day’s date setting forth provisional stipulations in
                        regard to Diplomatic, Consular, tariff and other relations between the
                        United States and Persia.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hoffman Philip</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0839" n="729" xml:id="pg_729"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 4—Translation<note n="46b"
                                xml:id="d626fn46b">Translation printed from Department of State
                                Executive Agreement Series No. 19.</note>]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Persian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Minister</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 14, 1928</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: I have the honor, in the name of my
                        Government to acknowledge receipt of and place on record the contents of
                        your note of to-day’s date, specifying the provisional stipulations relative
                        to diplomatic, consular, customs and other relations between Persia and the
                        United States of America.</p>
                    <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 5—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Persian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Minister</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 10</hi> [<hi rend="italic">14?</hi>], <hi
                                    rend="italic">1928</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: In reply to requests that have been
                        formulated, and on the eve of the realization of its decision to abolish on
                        May 10, the regime heretofore known as the Regime of Capitulations, the
                        Imperial Persian Government animated by a desire to dissipate any concern
                        arising from a lack of familiarity with the new system to be applied to them
                        hereafter, which might be entertained by foreign nationals residing in
                        Persia, and desirous, through your intermediary, of placing your nationals
                        in possession of the dispositions taken in their behalf by legislation and
                        by the Persian Government, addresses to you for communication to your
                        nationals, the present decision.</p>
                    <p>It is unnecessary to state, that the Persian Government, itself, vitally
                        interested in securing to the citizens of Persia a maximum of guarantees and
                        to maintain in the accomplishment of this aim a judicial system as nearly
                        perfect as possible, has achieved very appreciable judicial reforms both in
                        regard to personnel and legislation.</p>
                    <p>Without mentioning legislation familiar to every one, a knowledge of legal
                        matters the equivalent of that represented by a degree in law is one of the
                        obligatory conditions to entry in the judicial career.</p>
                    <p>Regarding the situation of the nationals of the United States of America as
                        it results from this decision, the following measures, taken by the Persian
                        Government, will be applicable as of May 10, 1928:</p>
                    <p>(1) On a basis of complete reciprocity, they will be received and treated in
                        Persia in accordance with the rules and practices of international law, and
                        will enjoy the most entire protection of the Persian laws and authorities,
                        and will enjoy the same treatment as the nationals of Persia.</p>
                    <pb facs="0840" n="730" xml:id="pg_730"/>
                    <p>(2) In civil or commercial suits where one of the parties is a national of
                        the United States only written testimony shall be admitted.</p>
                    <p>In all suits, even criminal, sentences will be drawn up in writing and will
                        set forth the considerations of law and of fact on which they are based.</p>
                    <p>Parties to a suit, or persons authorized by them, will have the right to
                        obtain copy of the testimony and the judgment, on the condition of paying
                        the regular fees.</p>
                    <p>In criminal cases, since oral testimony is normally accepted, the interests
                        of the accused are safeguarded by Articles 215 and 216 of the Penal Code
                        which provides against false-witness.</p>
                    <p>(3) Only the Courts and Tribunals directly under the Ministry of Justice, and
                        no others, shall be competent in a suit where one of the parties is a
                        national of the United States.</p>
                    <p>Only the Criminal Courts directly under the Ministry of Justice may, in
                        general, pronounce a sentence of imprisonment in cases involving nationals
                        of the United States.</p>
                    <p>However, should a state of siege be proclaimed, and a suit has come before a
                        specially formed Tribunal this Tribunal will be able to take cognizance of
                        the suit in which a national of the United States is one of the parties.</p>
                    <p>Moreover, in fiscal matters and, in general, in a litigation between an
                        Administration and a national of the United States concerning a purely
                        administrative matter, the Administrative Courts retain their
                        competence.</p>
                    <p>(4) In any case a national of the United States will not be brought before
                        any but Lay Courts, and only Lay Laws will be applicable to him.</p>
                    <p>(5) Simple Police Courts shall be competent in the case of nationals of the
                        United States only in matters of minor importance punishable by a small
                        fine.</p>
                    <p>They may not give prison sentences unless the national of the United States
                        should himself request that the fine which he has been sentenced to pay be
                        commuted to imprisonment. In conformity with law simple Police Courts may
                        never pronounce a prison sentence of more than one week. It is understood
                        that they will never sentence the said foreign nationals to corporal
                        punishment.</p>
                    <p>(6) A national of the United States arrested in <hi rend="italic">flagranti
                            delicto</hi> for an act which is termed a misdemeanor or a crime may not
                        be kept in prison for more than 24 hours without being traduced before the
                        competent judicial authority.</p>
                    <p>Except in cases of <hi rend="italic">flagranti delicto</hi> no national of
                        the United States shall be arrested or imprisoned without an order emanating
                        from the competent judicial authority.</p>
                    <p>Neither the private house nor business premises of a national of the United
                        States shall be entered forcibly or perquisitioned unless a warrant has been
                        issued by the competent judicial authority, with guarantees against abuse
                        the character of which will be defined later.</p>
                    <p>(7) Nationals of the United States who have been arrested and imprisoned will
                        have the right, in conformity with the prison regulations, to communicate
                        with their nearest Consul, and their Consuls or their representatives will
                        have permission to visit them, upon conforming to prison regulations.</p>
                    <pb facs="0841" n="731" xml:id="pg_731"/>
                    <p>The Governmental authorities will immediately transmit such requests for
                        communication with prisoners to the addressee.</p>
                    <p>(8) The Imperial Government has envisaged a set of generous regulations
                        governing release on bail, which shall be granted in every instance except
                        in case of crime (as Crime is defined by the Penal Code).</p>
                    <p>The sum demanded for bail will be reasonably proportioned to the degree of
                        the misdemeanor.</p>
                    <p>When a person appeals from a sentence the same facilities for release on bail
                        as mentioned above shall be granted him until the sentence of the Appellate
                        Court shall have been handed down.</p>
                    <p>(9) Since, according to Persian law, Court proceedings are, in general, and
                        in all but exceptional cases, open to the public, therefore the parties
                        interested in the suit or in the welfare of the litigants have the right to
                        be present as spectators, in all but exceptional cases, without, however,
                        having the right to take active part in the trial in any way whatsoever.</p>
                    <p>(10) In penal matters the accused is entirely free to choose his counsel or
                        counsels, who may even be fellow nationals.</p>
                    <p>(11) The Imperial Government has decided to ameliorate the condition of the
                        prisons so that they may be more in conformity with modern requirements; and
                        a sum of money sufficient to establish prisons in Persia, meeting necessary
                        demands of hygiene, has been already appropriated.</p>
                    <p>Meanwhile, nationals of the United States condemned to imprisonment for more
                        than one month (Since imprisonment for one month or less may be commuted to
                        a fine) will be transferred on their request to a prison meeting the
                        necessary requirements of hygiene.</p>
                    <p>(12) In matters of taxation, nationals of the United States will be treated
                        on an equal footing with Persian nationals, and will not be subject to any
                        dues, fees, or other taxes whatsoever which Persian nationals are not
                        required to pay.</p>
                    <p>(13) With respect to judicial matters, all judgments given by former
                        Courts—even if they have not been executed—are considered as definitely
                        settled and in no case may be reviewed; also all definitive judgments
                        rendered by the former Courts must be executed. In short, all suits
                        terminated under the old judicial system are considered as definitively
                        settled and may not again be opened.</p>
                    <p>Unfinished proceedings before the Tribunal of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs
                        or before the Tribunals of Governors of Provinces shall be terminated before
                        these Tribunals unless the party of foreign nationality should demand prior
                        to the conclusion of hearings that the case be taken to the law Courts.</p>
                    <p>The time limit granted by the Imperial Government in which to wind up
                        unfinished litigation before these Tribunals is until May 10, 1929, at the
                        latest.</p>
                    <p>(14) All questions relating to security for costs, to the execution of
                        sentences, to the service of judicial and extra-judicial decrees, to
                        commissions rogatories, to orders for the payments of costs and expenses, to
                        free legal assistance, and to imprisonment for debt, are left to be
                        regulated by special conditions between Persia and the United States of
                        America.</p>
                    <pb facs="0842" n="732" xml:id="pg_732"/>
                    <p>(15) All Arbitration and stipulations of Arbitration being admitted under
                        Persian law in civil or commercial matters and the decisions thus handed
                        down being executory at the order of the President of the Court of First
                        Instance upon whom it shall be mandatory to issue such order except in a
                        case where the arbitral decision would be contrary to public order,
                        obviously, nationals of the United States of America will enjoy the full
                        benefits of these legal provisions.</p>
                    <p>(16) Nationals of the United States of America cannot be arrested nor their
                        personal liberty restrained, as a measure of provisional protection in civil
                        claims, except where the distraint to be made on his property actually
                        located in Persia would appear to involve serious risk to the debtor or
                        where no other measure of protection may be resorted to.</p>
                    <p>(17) In respect to immovable property and rights pertaining thereto, it is
                        understood that nationals of the United States of America shall be permitted
                        to occupy, acquire and possess property necessary to their residence and to
                        the conduct of their commercial or industrial activities.</p>
                    <p>(18) It being possible to exclude questions relating to personal status from
                        the jurisdiction of National Tribunals the procedure to be followed in such
                        matters will be dealt with and detailed in a special arrangement.</p>
                    <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 6—Translation<note n="47"
                                xml:id="d626fn47">The original was in French.</note>]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The American Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Persian Acting Minister for Foreign
                            Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 14, 1928</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Acting Minister</hi>: I should be very glad to
                        receive from Your Excellency an assurance on the part of the Imperial
                        Government that American missionaries in Persia will be permitted, as in the
                        past, to carry on their charitable and educational work.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hoffman Philip</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 7—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Persian Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Minister</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Philip</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-05-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 14, 1928</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: In reply to your request relative to
                        American missionaries, I have the honor to inform you that they will be
                        authorized to carry on their charitable and educational work on the
                        condition that it contravenes neither the public order nor the laws and
                        regulations of Persia.</p>
                    <p>Please accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pakrevan</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
