<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-04-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-04-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="661" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d661">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">653.116/36</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chargé in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Andrews</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-04-11"><hi rend="italic">April 11,
                                1928</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 898</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department makes reference to the
                            Legation’s telegram No. 7, February 24, 5 p.m., and to its despatch No.
                            1538 of July 1, 1926.<note n="12" xml:id="d661fn12">Despatch No. 1538
                                not printed.</note></p>
                        <p>The Department feels that acceptance by Portugal of the principle of
                            national treatment of shipping should be the occasion, on Mr. Dearing’s
                            return, for the expression of gratification. It may also afford a
                            desirable opportunity to propose a Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and
                            Consular Rights, which not only would give reciprocal effect to the
                            principle of national treatment of shipping, but would place on a more
                            definite and satisfactory basis the commercial relations between
                            Portugal and the United States.</p>
                        <pb facs="0885" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/>
                        <p>Accordingly, on Mr. Dearing’s return, unless he perceives objection to
                            such a course, it is desired that he utilize an early opportunity to
                            carry out the foregoing proposal. If the Foreign Office appears to be
                            receptive, he may appropriately furnish it with copies of recent
                            American commercial treaties, such as that of December 8, 1923, with
                                Germany,<note n="13" xml:id="d661fn13"><ref target="frus1923v02#pg_29"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1923, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p.
                                    29</ref>.</note> and the subsequent treaties with Estonia and
                                Hungary,<note n="14" xml:id="d661fn14"><ref target="frus1925v02#pg_70"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 1925,
                                    vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 70</ref> and <ref target="frus1925v02#pg_341">341</ref>.</note> and he may also
                            inform the Foreign Office that he will shortly be in a position to
                            submit a draft of treaty prepared especially for negotiation with
                            Portugal. On his telegraphic request, such draft will be mailed to the
                            Legation as soon as practicable.</p>
                        <p>It appears to the Department that careful preparatory work by the
                            Minister will be necessary in order to persuade the Foreign Office to
                            accept the American point of view for equality of treatment in respect
                            of commerce and of shipping. His judgment as to time and manner of
                            presentation is depended upon and he is requested to use all reasonable
                            endeavor to bring about the desired result.</p>
                        <p>There is enclosed for your strictly confidential information only, a copy
                            of a memorandum prepared in the Department on March 9, 1928, entitled
                            “Portugal’s Shipping Discriminations”.<note n="15" xml:id="d661fn15">Not
                                printed.</note></p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Nelson
                                    Trusler Johnson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>