<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Switzerland ( (Wilson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1928v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d760</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">760</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1928-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1928-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recSGyPwUYTaLPhEi" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038182"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Consular service</term>
                    <term ref="recOAfZ9FRSJKK76a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Income tax</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="760"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d760">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.542/18</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="15" xml:id="d760fn15">Date of receipt in the Department not
                        indicated.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-04-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 4, 1928</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 387</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my Strictly
                    Confidential despatch No. 335 of March 8th and other correspondence relative to
                    the negotiation of a new treaty with Switzerland and to state that, in
                    accordance with Mr. Motta’s suggestion, I called upon him after my return from
                    Geneva where I attended the session of the Preparatory Commission for
                    Disarmament. I had previously given careful consideration to the Swiss
                    counterdraft of a treaty, transmitted in my despatch No. 358 of March 18th.</p>
                <p>At the beginning of the interview, we arranged that I should have a more detailed
                    discussion with other members of the Foreign Office subsequently, in order to be
                    enabled to give to the Department such elucidation as is possible of the Swiss
                    viewpoint on such clauses of <pb facs="1019" n="909" xml:id="pg_909"/> the draft
                    as contained views divergent from those entertained by the American Government.
                    I will, of course, report subsequently after having made such a detailed
                    examination of the draft with the Swiss authorities.</p>
                <p>Mr. Motta asked me whether in general I felt that the Swiss draft offered a basis
                    on which we could reach an accord. I stated that until I had heard from my
                    Government I could not of course speak authoritatively in this connection but
                    that it seemed to me that my Government might feel reluctant to sign an
                    agreement which so radically curtailed the privileges of consular officers. Such
                    an undertaking on our part might, as he could well understand, form a precedent
                    which we would be very reluctant to see especially since we had always
                    maintained a very generous attitude towards foreign consular officers in the
                    United States and had endeavored to obtain the same treatment for our officers
                    abroad. Mr. Motta stated that the divergence of views between the two
                    governments was probably explained by the fact that whereas we had a consular
                    service of career, the Swiss depended almost entirely upon honorary vice consuls
                    who were Swiss citizens earning their livelihood in a foreign country. He
                    further added that whereas in a big country such immunities and privileges as
                    consular officers enjoyed would not be remarked by the public, in small places
                    such as the Swiss cities such immunities were at once remarked and caused
                    adverse criticism in the Swiss public. However, he added that of course the
                    Swiss Government was not wedded to any particular form of phraseology, they had
                    endeavored to set forth their viewpoint in the draft and would welcome any
                    counter suggestion or further endeavor to harmonize our views. It was suggested
                    in the conversation that if there were certain points on which we could not come
                    to an agreement, the debatable questions might be left out of the treaty and the
                    treaty could at least indicate those points on which our two governments were in
                    harmony.</p>
                <p>Since I have been at this post I have been struck by the fact that nearly all the
                    difficulties which we have with the Swiss Government arise from two causes,
                    first, from the difference of interpretation of nationality which brings about
                    cases where persons who are American citizens under our law are Swiss citizens
                    under Swiss law and therefore claimed for military service. The second category
                    of cases are those of taxation of American citizens residing for greater or less
                    periods within Switzerland. The various cantons subject our citizens to
                    taxation, both income tax and inheritance dues, in accordance with their own,
                    and diversified, interpretation of whether such citizens are or are not
                    “domiciled” in Switzerland.</p>
                <p>With the foregoing thoughts in mind I told Mr. Motta that I wished to consult him
                    quite unofficially regarding two matters which <pb facs="1020" n="910"
                        xml:id="pg_910"/> were not definitely covered by the treaty but which gave
                    rise to practically the only cases of dispute between this Legation and the
                    Federal Government. I had not consulted my own Government as to whether they
                    thought such matters might be covered but I would appreciate an expression of
                    his views as to whether such a draft of treaty as was now in discussion might
                    not be enlarged in such a way as to take care of these two debatable points.</p>
                <p>Relative to nationality, Mr. Motta was inclined to think that the divergent
                    conceptions of “jus sanguis” and “jus solis” were so deep between us that it
                    might be difficult to reach a formula mutually satisfactory. However, since the
                    draft of treaty was the first that had been undertaken since 1850 and offered an
                    opportunity for “general housecleaning” he would willingly go into this matter
                    with us if we so desired and endeavor with us to see whether the point could be
                    regulated.</p>
                <p>Regarding the question of domicile, Mr. Motta was more optimistic. He understood
                    thoroughly the hardship to American citizens of not having a single criterion of
                    what constituted domicile. He stated that the Federal Government had recently
                    carefully investigated its competence in matters of this kind and had decided
                    that it was competent to make a treaty governing domicile and taxation matters
                    which would be binding upon the individual cantons. He asked me whether I had
                    drafted my suggestion. I told him that I had not since I did not know how my
                    Government would view it but that something might perhaps be considered along
                    the line of domicile in accordance with the intent of the person there to remain
                    or eventually to return to his home land.</p>
                <p>Should the Department look with favor upon these two suggestions, I should
                    appreciate instructions to this effect and also a suggested phraseology to cover
                    either or both of the two points as the Department may desire. Both my own
                    experience and that of the consular officers in Switzerland indicates that a
                    solution of these two matters would be of high value to our citizens and do away
                    with these contentious points between our two governments.</p>
                <p>We did not discuss further the question of an acceptance of the obligation to
                    respect Swiss neutrality raised in my despatch 335 of March 8th. I consider it
                    advisable that we should not go further into this until I have some indication
                    of the Department’s attitude toward the general principle. In any case as I
                    suggested in my No. 335 if the Department is willing to consider this principle
                    such acquiescence on our part should, I believe, be withheld as a bargaining
                    asset on the other treaties.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh R. Wilson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
