<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-07-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="765" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d765">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.542/22</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-07-18"><hi rend="italic">July 18,
                                1928</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received August 6.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 518</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith a
                            French text and translation of a project handed to me by the Department
                            of Public Economy of the Swiss Government for a commercial treaty
                            between the United States and Switzerland. It will be noted that in
                            general <pb facs="1037" n="927" xml:id="pg_927"/> it follows the
                            commercial clauses of the draft treaty of commerce, amity, and consular
                            rights which we submitted to the Swiss Government in 1926.</p>
                        <p>Following the procedure which I had adopted in connection with the Swiss
                            draft for the treaty of establishment, I called on Dr. Walter Stücki,
                            Director of Public Economy, and explained to him that I was not
                            authorized to negotiate on the draft which he had submitted but that I
                            desired to ask him for certain elucidation on his draft.</p>
                        <p>It will be noted that the Swiss draft omits completely Article 13 of the
                            original draft submitted to them relative to right of transit; a similar
                            article, however, is included in Swiss Commercial Treaties with
                            neighboring countries. Mr. Stücki explained, when this was brought to
                            his attention, that of course the Swiss Government had no objection to
                            the idea expressed in the article; they had merely considered it
                            superfluous in view of the phraseology of their Article 1, paragraph 1,
                            (our Article 7, paragraph 1) which states that commerce will be free
                            between territories of the contracting parties. He added that they would
                            certainly construe this as giving all benefits which are provided under
                            our Article 13 above-mentioned.</p>
                        <p>I asked Mr. Stücki what had motivated the Swiss Government in its
                            insertion of paragraph 1 of “the additional stipulations”, relative to
                            most-favored-nation treatment for Swiss merchandise regardless of the
                            nationality of the vessel importing the goods. Dr. Stücki explained in
                            entire frankness that they had been encountering difficulties with the
                            Canadian Government on this very question; that the Canadian Government
                            had been subjecting merchandise imported in German bottoms to three
                            times the charges to which merchandise was subjected imported in British
                            or French bottoms. But certain of the Swiss merchants had old
                            established agreements with German shipping companies for carrying their
                            goods and it was inconvenient to alter this. No question of
                            discrimination had ever arisen as concerned the United States of
                            America. It was Dr. Stücki’s desire merely to select from the various
                            shipping clauses (which of course have no application to Switzerland)
                            the single matter which was of interest to them.</p>
                        <p>Paragraph 2 of the “additional stipulations” raises a point of exceeding
                            interest now that the nations of the world are beginning to negotiate
                            multilateral economic treaties. I had noticed that Dr. Stücki, who
                            represented Switzerland at the Export and Import Conference,<note n="29" xml:id="d765fn29">See <ref target="frus1928v01#pg_366">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 366</ref> ff.</note> had been
                            peculiarly insistent on the fact that a bilateral most-favored nation
                            obligation did not necessarily give to the contracting parties all the
                            privileges which one of the contracting parties might have conceded to
                            the other signatories under a multilateral treaty. Dr. Stücki explained
                            that in the last meeting of the Economic Committee of the <pb facs="1038" n="928" xml:id="pg_928"/> League of Nations he had been
                            named <hi rend="italic">Rapporteur</hi>, charged with making a report to
                            the Committee on this very question. He had not desired to make this
                            additional stipulation too lengthy an article and too complex but had
                            wished primarily to raise the question so that some sort of a formula
                            might be evolved. He explained that in his report to the Economic
                            Committee (which by the way has not yet been acted on) he had proposed
                            that in the event that a state which was not signatory to a multilateral
                            agreement and which, however, did not maintain those forms of
                            restrictions or customs or whatever restraint the multilateral treaty
                            was designed to eliminate, should enjoy the benefits of the most-favored
                            nation. It was only in the case where a non-signatory state refused to
                            accept the obligations of a multilateral treaty that it could not claim
                            the benefits thereof under the most-favored nation bilateral
                            agreement.</p>
                        <p>Relative to the Protocol, I again emphasized the fact that I was not
                            negotiating and had no authorization to do so. I pointed out, however,
                            that by this paragraph and particularly the last sentence thereof the
                            Swiss Government was proposing to us to submit to our Senate something
                            which was in direct conflict with our existing law. I then asked him
                            whether he really considered that this was of high importance to
                            Switzerland. Dr. Stücki replied that my question was almost as delicate
                            as the one which they raised by inserting the Protocol. Certainly as
                            evidenced by the Swiss press a great deal of hostility in Chambers of
                            Commerce and business circles has been shown against any idea of
                            examination into costs on Swiss territory by American agents, and the
                            Federal Council and the legislative bodies of Switzerland would
                            certainly want to know very definitely why mention of this had been
                            omitted by Mr. Stücki and would certainly be extremely desirous of
                            seeing some method adopted which could eliminate the possibility of such
                            examination. Naturally, Mr. Stücki did not consider this as <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> for acceptance of a commercial
                            convention with ourselves. Nevertheless, he did regard it as of high
                            importance and added that he understood that we were now engaged in some
                            sort of arrangement with the French Government relative to this matter
                            and stated that he would have to insist upon most-favored nation
                            treatment in this particular application of law. I am not entirely
                            familiar with the procedure which we have adopted toward the French
                            Government in this connection. It may be that some unofficial
                            arrangement has been reached which, if we accorded it to Switzerland,
                            would eliminate the necessity for the Protocol in the Convention.</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>Article 2, paragraph 1. I pointed out that the meaning was
                                somewhat obscure and there appeared to be a <hi rend="italic">non-sequitur</hi> of thought. Mr. Stücki agreed that the French
                                text was not entirely clear and stated that his office would work
                                over this text and try to improve it. He explained that what they
                                were trying to reach was exactly the meaning <pb facs="1039" n="929" xml:id="pg_929"/> conveyed by Article 4, paragraph 7, of the
                                Export and Import Convention of November 8, 1927.<note n="30" xml:id="d765fn30"><ref target="frus1928v01#pg_336">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 336</ref>, <ref target="frus1928v01#pg_339">339</ref>.</note></item>
                            <item>Article 3, paragraph 1. I call special attention to the question
                                of translation of this paragraph. It is of considerable difficulty
                                and should be examined with some care. In the last line I have
                                translated “les industriels (voyageurs de commerce)” as “wholesale
                                commercial travelers”, basing this translation on Dr. Stücki’s
                                explanation of his meaning.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Relative to the formal certificate (Annex A),<note n="31" xml:id="d765fn31">Not printed.</note> I asked Dr. Stücki whether
                            this was intended to be an official document. He stated that it was
                            official; that under the treaty of Customs Formalities to which
                            Switzerland was a party, facilities for commercial travelers had been
                            made as broad as possible and a certificate such as proposed to us was
                            now accepted by all states signatory to this Convention. In Switzerland
                            such documents were issued by special cantonal bureaus or by the
                            Department of Public Economy. The document bore the name and seal of the
                            authority issuing it. No visa or other further formality was required
                            for the user of this certificate.</p>
                        <p>The Department will note that very decided restrictions are put on retail
                            commercial travelers, as well as on peddlers and hawkers. Inasmuch as I
                            know of only one American commercial traveler who obtained a license to
                            visit Switzerland during the past year, as against some 250 German
                            commercial travelers, it would seem to be to our advantage that the
                            activities of commercial travelers should be rigidly confined to those
                            in the wholesale market.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Lyon, the Commercial Attaché, has in preparation a comparative
                            analysis of Switzerland’s contractual commercial relations. As soon as
                            this document is completed, I shall forward a copy to the Department,
                            inasmuch as I believe it will be found of value, in consideration of
                            this general question, to understand the practice and broad principles
                            which Swiss public economy is endeavoring to follow.</p>
                        <p>This Swiss draft is the final step in the preparation of the Swiss
                            counter-project, and I venture for your convenience to cite the
                            references to the various reports which I have made and which it may be
                            found advantageous to consider as a whole. The list follows: <list>
                                <item>335 of March 8, 1928;</item>
                                <item>358 of March 18, 1928;</item>
                                <item>387 of April 4, 1928;</item>
                                <item>415 of April 24, 1928;</item>
                                <item>423 of May 5, 1928.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <pb facs="1040" n="930" xml:id="pg_930"/>
                        <p>I shall take no further steps in this matter until the Department has had
                            the opportunity to reflect upon what has been submitted and instruct me
                            in the premises.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh R. Wilson</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Swiss Draft of a Treaty of Commerce</hi></head>
                            <p>The Federal Council of the Swiss Confederation and the President of
                                the United States, desirous of promoting the commercial relations
                                between Switzerland and the United States, have resolved to conclude
                                a treaty and have designated for this purpose as their
                                plenipotentiaries, to-wit:</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">who, after having communicated to each other their
                                full powers, found in good and due form, have agreed upon the
                                following articles:</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item>P. 1. Between the territories of the contracting parties there
                                    shall be freedom of commerce; the nationals of each of the
                                    contracting parties shall enjoy the treatment granted the
                                    nationals of the most favored nation respecting the free access
                                    of their goods to all places which are or may be open to foreign
                                    commerce. Nothing in this treaty shall be construed to restrict
                                    the right of either contracting party to decree, on such terms
                                    as it may see fit, prohibitions or restrictions of a sanitary
                                    character designed to protect human, animal, or plant life, or
                                    regulations for the enforcement of police or revenue
                                    laws.</item>
                                <item>P. 2. Each of the contracting parties binds itself
                                    unconditionally to impose no higher, more onerous, or other
                                    duties, charges, and conditions, and no prohibition on the
                                    importation of any article, the growth, produce or manufacture
                                    of the territory of the other party, arriving directly or
                                    indirectly, other than are or shall be imposed on the
                                    importation of any like article, the growth, produce or
                                    manufacture of any other foreign country; nor shall any duties,
                                    charges, conditions, or prohibitions on importations be made
                                    effective retroactively on imports already cleared through the
                                    customs or on goods declared for entry into consumption in the
                                    country.</item>
                                <item>P. 3. Each of the contracting parties also binds itself
                                    unconditionally to impose no other, higher, or more onerous,
                                    charges or other restrictions or prohibitions on goods exported
                                    to the territory of the other party than are imposed on goods
                                    exported to any other foreign country.</item>
                                <item>P. 4. Any advantage of whatsoever kind which either
                                    contracting party may extend, now or in the future, by treaty,
                                    law, decree, regulation, <pb facs="1041" n="931" xml:id="pg_931"/> practice or otherwise, to any article, the growth, produce,
                                    or manufacture of any other foreign country, shall immediately,
                                    without request, unconditionally, and without compensation be
                                    extended to the like article, the growth, produce or
                                    manufactured of the other contracting party.</item>
                                <item>P. 5. With respect to the amount and collection of duties of
                                    every kind on imports and exports, each of the contracting
                                    parties binds itself to give to the nationals and goods of the
                                    other party the advantage of every favor, privilege, or immunity
                                    which it shall have accorded to the nationals and goods of a
                                    third state, whether such favored state shall have been accorded
                                    such treatment gratuitously or in return for reciprocal
                                    compensatory treatment. Every such favor, privilege, or immunity
                                    which shall hereafter be granted the nationals or goods of a
                                    third state shall simultaneously, without request,
                                    unconditionally and without compensation be extended to the
                                    other contracting party for the benefit of itself, its
                                    nationals, or its goods.</item>
                                <item>P. 6. The stipulations of the present Article do not
                                    extend:</item>
                                <item>insofar as the United States is concerned to the treatment
                                    which is accorded the commerce of Cuba under the provisions of
                                    the Commercial Convention concluded by the United States and
                                    Cuba on December 11, 1902, or any other commercial convention
                                    which hereafter may be concluded between the United States and
                                    Cuba. Such stipulations moreover do not extend to the treatment
                                    accorded to the commerce between the United States and the
                                    Panama Canal Zone or any of the dependencies of the United
                                    States or to the commerce of the dependencies of the United
                                    States with one another, under existing or future federal laws.
                                    Insofar as Switzerland is concerned such stipulations do not
                                    extend to the privileges which have been or may be accorded to a
                                    bordering state with a view to facilitating frontier trade in a
                                    zone, not to exceed 15 kilometers beyond the frontier, nor to
                                    the obligations resulting from any customs union which the
                                    Confederation has concluded or may hereafter conclude.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">additional stipulations</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item>P. 1. It is agreed that the most-favored nation treatment to
                                    be accorded Swiss goods imported into the United States shall
                                    apply, without any restriction, irrespective of the nationality
                                    of the vessel by which they are carried.</item>
                                <item>P. 2. It is agreed that the most-favored nation treatment
                                    stipulated in the present article does not entitle either of the
                                    contracting parties to the benefits of the stipulations granted
                                    in multilateral international conventions to which the other
                                    party is not also an adherent.</item>
                            </list>
                            <pb facs="1042" n="932" xml:id="pg_932"/>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">protocol</hi></p>
                            <p>P. 1. Whenever doubts may arise regarding the valuation or the proof
                                of value of merchandise for importation, the injured contracting
                                party will call the fact to the attention of the other contracting
                                party. The Government of the party thus complained to will at once
                                institute a special inquiry and communicate the result thereof to
                                the complaining party. In no event will one of the contracting
                                parties proceed to institute an investigation on the territory of
                                the other contracting party through its own agencies.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi></p>
                            <p>The nationals and merchandise of each contracting party within the
                                territory of the other shall receive the same treatment as nationals
                                and merchandise of the country with regard to internal taxes,
                                transit dues, charges in respect to warehousing, and other
                                facilities and the amount of bounties and drawbacks.</p>
                            <p>This stipulation does not extend to merchandise, which is or may
                                become, in the territory of one of the contracting parties, a state
                                monopoly, as well as to the intention of applying to foreign
                                merchandise all the prohibitions and restrictions which have or may
                                be the result of national legislation relative to the production,
                                transportation, sale, or consumption within the country of similar
                                native merchandise.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item>P. 1. Without prejudicing the possibility of their receiving
                                    greater advantages as the result of the most-favored nation
                                    treatment, merchants, and other manufacturers of one of the
                                    contracting parties, as well as their commercial travellers,
                                    shall have the right, upon presenting a certificate delivered by
                                    the authorities of their country, and conforming to the laws and
                                    regulations in force, to purchase goods within the territory of
                                    the other contracting party, whether from dealers, in places of
                                    public sale, or at the residence of persons producing the said
                                    goods. They may also take orders from dealers or other persons
                                    engaged in business in which are used those types of merchandise
                                    they are offering. They may bring with them samples or models
                                    and, insofar as concerns their activity as described in the
                                    present paragraph, they shall not be subject either to taxes or
                                    special fees. Wholesale commercial travellers who are provided
                                    with a certificate have, however, the right to bring with them
                                    merchandise to the same extent as is authorized to wholesale
                                    commercial travellers within the country.</item>
                                <pb facs="1043" n="933" xml:id="pg_933"/>
                                <item>P. 2. Samples or models imported by the above-mentioned
                                    persons shall be admitted free of import and export dues, in
                                    conformity with the customs regulations and formalities drawn up
                                    to enforce their reexportation, or the payment of customs duties
                                    in the event of their not being re-exported within the period
                                    fixed by law.</item>
                                <item>P. 3. Re-exportation of samples or models belonging to
                                    commercial travellers may be effected through another customs
                                    house than the one of their import. The re-exporting office will
                                    be authorized to reimburse on its own authority the duties or
                                    taxes which have been provisionally paid, or deposited, or if
                                    the sum has been merely guaranteed to take the necessary steps
                                    to cancel the guarantee furnished.</item>
                                <item>P. 4. The contracting parties further agree that samples of
                                    objects in precious metals (jewelry, goldsmith work, clockwork)
                                    shall be exempted from the requirements of marking or stamping
                                    in the country of importation, provided that they are
                                    re-exported within the customary period.</item>
                                <item>P. 5. The certificate must be drawn up in conformity with the
                                    model of annex A. The contracting parties will reciprocally
                                    inform each other of the authorities competent to issue such
                                    certificates.</item>
                                <item>P. 6. The stipulations of the present article shall not be
                                    applicable to peddling, hawking, or retail travelling salesmen
                                    seeking orders from persons without business or trade, and the
                                    contracting parties in this matter reserve full legislative
                                    liberty.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item>P. 1. Subject to any limitation or restriction hereinabove set
                                    forth or hereinafter agreed upon, the territories of the
                                    contracting parties to which the provisions of this treaty
                                    extend shall be understood to comprise all areas of land, water,
                                    and air over which the parties respectively claim and exercise
                                    dominion as sovereign thereof, except the Panama Canal
                                    Zone.</item>
                                <item>P. 2. The present treaty shall likewise comprise the
                                    principality of Liechtenstein so long as the latter is bound to
                                    Switzerland by a treaty of customs union.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article V</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <item>P. 1. Differences which may arise regarding the interpretation
                                    or application of the present treaty and which shall not have
                                    been settled through diplomatic channels within a reasonable
                                    period shall be submitted at the request of one of the
                                    contracting parties to an arbitral <pb facs="1044" n="934" xml:id="pg_934"/> tribunal which, unless otherwise agreed
                                    upon, shall contain three members, each of the contracting
                                    parties naming one arbitrator and appointing by common accord
                                    the presiding arbitrator.</item>
                                <item>P. 2. If the Arbitral Tribunal has not been constituted within
                                    two months following notification of a request for arbitration,
                                    the procedure set forth in part 4 of the Convention of the Hague
                                    of October 18, 1907, for the pacific settlement of international
                                    disputes, shall obligatorily apply.</item>
                                <item>P. 3. In case doubt arises as to whether the difference of
                                    opinion bears upon the interpretation or the application of the
                                    treaty, this preliminary question will be submitted to
                                    arbitration under the same conditions as those stipulated in
                                    paragraph[s] 1 and 2 of the present article.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article VI</hi></p>
                            <p>The present treaty will be ratified as soon as possible and the
                                ratifications thereof shall be exchanged at . . . . . .</p>
                            <p>The treaty is concluded for a period of ten years from the date of
                                exchange of ratifications. If within one year before the expiration
                                of the aforesaid period neither contracting party denounces the
                                treaty, it shall remain in force until one year from such time as
                                either of the contracting parties shall have notified to the other
                                an intention of terminating it.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">In witness whereof</hi>, the above mentioned
                                plenipotentiaries have signed the present treaty in duplicate in the
                                French and English languages.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>