<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>249. Telegram From the Mission at the United Nations to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d249</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">249</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-10-22T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-10-22T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEKBMJ0utJPbJXo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Troop withdrawal</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-10-22T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-10-22T14:00:00-05:00" n="249"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d249">
                <head>249. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission at the United
                        Nations</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d249fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 770G.00/10–2260. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Niact1">Niact</gloss>;
                        Limit Distribution.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1960-10-22T15:00:00-04:00">October 22, 1960, 3 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1096. For Secretary. Re Congo: <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>s 716,
                        727:<note n="1" xml:id="d249fn1">See <ref target="#d246fn6">Document 246 and
                            footnote 6</ref> thereto.</note> Friday<note n="2" xml:id="d249fn2"
                        >October 21.</note> morning pursuant Department agreement, <persName
                        corresp="#p_WJJ2">Wadsworth</persName> called <gloss target="#t_SYG1"
                        >SYG</gloss> Hammarskjold to inform him he was sending him memorandum (for
                    text see <gloss target="#t_ourtel1">ourtel</gloss> 1095,<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d249fn3">
                        <ref target="#d248">Document 248</ref>.</note> worked out with Department
                    and based on <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>s) about which Secretary
                    had asked that he, Ambassador Bohlen and Barco see Hammarskjold. Appointment
                    fixed for Friday afternoon following end of First Committee session. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName> and Wieschhoff joined <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> for discussion with us.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. Constitutional situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Hammarskjold began by referring to US “aide-mémoire” (his term; we did not so
                    entitle it) making comments on various parts of it. He prefaced this by denying
                    that there had in any way been any change in his attitude, and insisting he had
                    “certainly been under no pressure.” Questioning what was meant by “views
                    recently expressed”, he concluded we had in mind his remarks of last
                        Saturday.<note n="4" xml:id="d249fn4">October 15.</note> He first said he
                    had not taken position indicated and then went into discussion of matter in
                    exactly same terms as contained previous report (<gloss target="#t_ourtel1"
                        >ourtel</gloss> 1021).<note n="5" xml:id="d249fn5">
                        <ref target="#d243">Document 243</ref>.</note> In addition to this
                    exposition his views, which we <pb facs="0577" n="547" xml:id="pg_547"/> will
                    not here repeat he expressed “complete” disagreement with our legal analysis
                    regarding constitutional situation, which had been complicated by attempts by
                        <persName corresp="#p_KJ8">Kasavubu</persName> to fire <persName
                        corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_LP3"
                        >Lumumba</persName>’s retaliation, in which Parliament had hand. Out of all
                    this confusion however <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> took position
                        <persName corresp="#p_KJ8">Kasavubu</persName> did remain as head of state.
                    But he said <persName corresp="#p_KJ8">Kasavubu</persName> had dropped <persName
                        corresp="#p_IJ1">Ileo</persName> by having suspended Parliament and
                    disavowed <persName corresp="#p_IJ1">Ileo</persName>’s government. Hence
                        <persName corresp="#p_IJ1">Ileo</persName> could be disregarded. Given
                    suspension of Parliament, sole unclouded authority in Congo, in Hammarskjold’s
                    view, is that of Chief of State. “Yet whatever fragments of Prime Minister’s
                    authority remain are, due largely to <persName corresp="#p_KJ8"
                        >Kasavubu</persName>’s way of handling it, in <persName corresp="#p_LP3"
                        >Lumumba</persName>”, said <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>. He was “more
                        <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>” than anyone else. While <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> could [not?] “deal with him as <gloss
                        target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss> he could not at same time be disregarded
                    completely. [”?]</p>
                <p>Hammarskjold at another point in conversation expanded on his legal view of
                    situation. He absolutely refused to accept theory that interpretation of <hi
                        rend="italic">Loi Fondamentale</hi>, in absence of any other indicated rule
                    of interpretation, should be based on Belgian practice. As he put it, Belgians
                    got Congolese to accept good deal of Belgian law in their <hi rend="italic">Loi
                        Fondamentale</hi>, “but there is no reason to think Belgians got them to
                    accept their (Belgian) constitutional practice.”</p>
                <p>In this way Hammarskjold refused to recognize our (and Belgian) arguments re
                    difference in caretaker status under Belgian and other continental practices.
                    Hammarskjold admitted he had said <persName corresp="#p_KJ8">Kasavubu</persName>
                    had acted legally in ending <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>’s
                    mandate from Chief of State, but maintained legal effect of this action was
                    “very controversial”. He went on to describe situation in this way: President
                    had “withdrawn his part of confidence” in <persName corresp="#p_LP3"
                        >Lumumba</persName>, but Parliament’s part of confidence was not withdrawn.
                    Hammarskjold then said they (<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>) do not regard
                    him as “legitimate” Prime Minister, since if they did, <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> would be able to deal with him. Reason <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> does not deal with <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>
                    is that <persName corresp="#p_KJ8">Kasavubu</persName>’s withdrawal of
                    confidence in him has “to that extent” taken away his authority. It is this very
                    fact of not dealing with <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> which has
                    been cause of extended criticism of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> by those who insist <persName corresp="#p_LP3"
                        >Lumumba</persName> is still Prime Minister. (At another point it was
                    mentioned <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> does deal with <persName
                        corresp="#p_KJ8">Kasavubu</persName> within limits his authority, for
                    instance writing letters to him.)</p>
                <p>Hammarskjold pursued same line in arguing against point in memorandum regarding
                    question of removing <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> from <gloss
                        target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>’s residence. Hammarskjold maintained there was no
                    justification for such step; Wieschhoff reiterated argument present residence
                    not real <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>’s residence in usually understood
                    sense, and no practical results would flow from removal. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName> backed up Wieschhoff in describing this
                    as impractical step. Hammarskjold said his policy “barred him from taking any
                    action on basis <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> is not <gloss
                        target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>”. But on opposite side of coin, he never dealt
                    with <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> as if he were <gloss
                        target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss> in any <pb facs="0578" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/>
                    formal sense, by any formal acts. Protection afforded is same as that for all
                    other “political dignitaries” who have asked for it. “They also are entitled
                    live in their own houses.”</p>
                <p>Hammarskjold said <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> must “keep clean on the
                    record, wherever it may lead”. “What in past actions or behavior seemed to
                    indicate an anti-<persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> line by <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> now seemingly indicated opposite.” In fact
                    there no change in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>’s line, he said; rather,
                    change is in behavior of individuals involved. He added that had <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> agreed to remove <persName corresp="#p_LP3"
                        >Lumumba</persName> from <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>’s residence,
                    assuming some justification could have been found, this action would have
                    created “partial martyrdom” for <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>,
                    which in turn would have strengthened hand of those in General Assembly who
                    advocate pro-<persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> move. By not so doing
                    he felt that issue will peter out.</p>
                <p>Hammarskjold also referred to question of warrant for arrest of <persName
                        corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> “as deputy” [sic] which on its face
                    thereby invalid, since it was for “political” action. Such arrests clearly being
                    used as form of political violence, he said. <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    required respect “due process” of law, he said, and consequently refused act
                    where obviously no due process.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Katanga and Belgium</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Turning to that part of our memo re Katanga he said Katanga’s unity with rest of
                    Congo is political, legal and economic necessity. If allowed to remain as
                    separate identity it will mean cold war comes to central Africa. Problem for
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> was how to get them back into picture
                    while remaining aloof from interference in internal affairs. This could only be
                    through diplomatic and political means. So long as Tshombe can turn to Belgium,
                    he will not go along with cooperation with central government. In this
                    Hammarskjold said he disagreed with some assertions in our memo but was not
                    explicit. He said troop withdrawal had not been end of it so far as Belgians
                    concerned. And while Tshombe is not on Belgian side he nevertheless hangs on to
                    them, creating psychological factor against Tshombe’s turning for reliance to
                    Leopoldville.</p>
                <p>With regard to US concern at <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>’s démarche to
                    Belgians, Hammarskjold said he has only asked of Belgians what US has already
                    asked—namely that all aid come through <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. In
                    measured tones Hammarskjold said Belgians had been anything but helpful in this
                    matter. He referred to “special interests” working on behalf of Belgium, and
                    spoke of “systematic return of Belgians to Leopoldville” under control of
                    Commissioners. He hinted at collusion with regard to return of these Belgians,
                    and mentioned “coup d’état arrangements” under cover of which “Belgian comeback”
                    might be staged.</p>
                <pb facs="0579" n="549" xml:id="pg_549"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">3. Other points in memo</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Hammarskjold stated that release of <persName corresp="#p_GA4">Gizenga</persName>
                    and Mpolo was decision of <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName>
                    himself and not <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. According his version, which
                    came from “the command”, <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName>’s
                    soldiers arrested not only these two <persName corresp="#p_LP3"
                        >Lumumba</persName> supporters but also two pro-<persName
                        corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> men. When <persName
                        corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> came to see <persName corresp="#p_DR4"
                        >Dayal</persName> (complaining for some unknown reason to <persName
                        corresp="#p_DR4">Dayal</persName> about it), he said he had had nothing to
                    do with it and it was up to <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> to
                    handle; whereupon latter decided only way to get his men back was to release all
                    four individuals.</p>
                <p>Hammarskjold said <gloss target="#t_ANC1">ANC</gloss> is major risk in whole
                    picture. There had recently been in “native quarter” of Leopoldville
                    considerable amount looting, raping (of children according to <persName
                        corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName>) and general pillage at hands <gloss
                        target="#t_ANC1">ANC</gloss>, which <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1"
                        >Mobutu</persName> once controlled. Such activity apparently explains
                    remarks attributed to <persName corresp="#p_DR4">Dayal</persName> in Friday
                    Washington Post story calling <gloss target="#t_ANC1">ANC</gloss> “rabble”. This
                    disintegration of authority is another reason why <gloss target="#t_SYG1"
                        >SYG</gloss> looks with less favor upon <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1"
                        >Mobutu</persName>. At this point Hammarskjold felt prompted to say <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> cannot choose men, nor their inclinations, but
                    rather must take objective stand. What is needed is constitutional authority
                    including that of Parliament, giving some semblance of legitimacy to Congo
                    Government. This would and should be case regardless whether such situation was
                    proor anti-<persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> said two separate and opposite versions of
                    story regarding Ndele existed. He did not elucidate upon them. According to
                        <persName>Bunche Ndele</persName> owes his life to intervention by
                    soldier(s) in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Command.</p>
                <p>According Hammarskjold there had been mistakes made. They were largely errors
                    committed by Ghana forces, and apparently by individuals within them and not a
                    part of some grand design. He said many steps taken correct these errors. He
                    said two brigadiers with Ghana forces seemed all right but Welbeck (Ghana
                    Chargé) and Djin were another story.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">4. Subsequent discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In general discussion which followed, Bohlen led off by stating that it seemed
                    apparent any re-assemblage of Parliament in near future out of question because
                    of fear by parliamentarians from provinces what might happen to them. Everything
                    pointed all too squarely to likely return to power, unless something done, of
                        <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>. On authority from Washington
                    Bohlen then said if <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> comes back
                    into power, US Government does not propose to stand idly by and allow Congo
                    become Communist satellite. In view of our strong support of <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> up to now
                    on Congo question, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> would have fully to weigh
                    possible drastic revision of our policy. Bohlen also <pb facs="0580" n="550"
                        xml:id="pg_550"/> referred to other information our possession indicating
                    things going on out there which indicate Russians have not given up hope of
                    returning at all.</p>
                <p>Bohlen also sought clarification from <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> or
                        <persName corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName> re nationality of soldiers in
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> force in Leopoldville, many of whom had in
                    one way or another cast doubt on their total loyalty to <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> cause. <persName corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName> said there
                    were Sudanese troops at airport (and also small number <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                        >UAR</gloss> troops); in city there were Ghana and Moroccan troops.</p>
                <p>After making absolutely clear US regarded present application <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>’s rule of impartiality as inevitably operating
                    in favor of <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>, and of consequences
                    this might have for US policy, Bohlen turned conversation on to positive line by
                    saying “What is important is to figure out where we go from here”. This is
                    endeavor in which US willing and anxious help out in any proper way. Anything to
                    change present pattern of paralysis would be desirable. Bohlen informally
                    suggested possibility, starting from fixed point that <persName corresp="#p_KJ8"
                        >Kasavubu</persName> is Chief of State, that he be urged appoint caretaker
                    government with perhaps <persName corresp="#p_BJM2">Bomboko</persName> as <gloss
                        target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1"
                        >Mobutu</persName> in background possibly as Chief of Staff. It would be
                    understood such government to be temporary, for interim only, pending
                    reassembling of Parliament for purposes ratifying such government. Wieschhoff
                    interjected at this point that this is what <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    had been trying to do for three weeks without success.</p>
                <p>Hammarskjold seemed to react favorably to idea moving on to some more
                    constructive aspect of discussion. He said Parliament is one thing which can do
                    anything in Congo. To have it meet there are two prerequisites: Security
                    measures in Leopoldville; and presence of Katanga del. This latter depends on
                    Tshombe’s views. (<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> nowhere near so confident,
                    from their reports of good outcome from <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1"
                        >Mobutu</persName>’s talks in Elisabethville.) Hammarskjold added that
                    problem is not just in Leopoldville—it is in provinces as well. He despaired of
                    abilities of leaders, saying each had missed every chance to do something
                    effective. Bohlen’s idea might work if there were some way to get it done. To
                    put such idea or any other into effect it was necessary to work through someone.
                    There was no one on whom to rely. There was complete lack of effective
                    personalities. He added without spelling it out that catalyst was also required
                    which could not be third government.</p>
                <p>In this connection Hammarskjold referred to good offices idea which came from res
                    adopted by special emergency <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. If such group
                    were not homogeneous it would fall apart and create more confusion. Hammarskjold
                    inclined doubt one would be formed but in any event he said he could not prevent
                    it since it would be subcom of his Advisory Committee, and decision to form such
                    group would be <pb facs="0581" n="551" xml:id="pg_551"/> theirs. His approach
                    thus far, in hopes preventing this development, had been “socratic”; he had
                    asked questions designed to frighten them away from taking such step, so far
                    with some success.</p>
                <p>Although Hammarskjold never gave concrete answer on possibility of caretaker govt
                    along lines suggested by Bohlen, he did say such group could not ignore
                        <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>. And he also noted that <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> could not be sure in any dealings it might have
                    with such govt that these were any more than on de facto basis.</p>
                <p>Referring to impasse into which <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>’s policy
                    appeared to have led it, Hammarskjold indicated that one way out of such
                    difficulty lay in possibility <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> taking stand
                    on particular issue. This would make it possible for execution of policy (by
                        <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>) to be lifted out of impasse. He felt
                        <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>’s inaction re seating rep of Congo
                    made his impartial behavior as between different govt’l figures absolutely
                    consistent with overall <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> stand. Way to change
                    it, he appeared to hint, would be by <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                    decision.</p>
                <p>Turning to question of Belgians (and Katanga), Hammarskjold referred to new note
                    he sent,<note n="6" xml:id="d249fn6">A note verbale to Loridan, October 19; for
                        text, see U.N. doc. S/4557, Part B, or <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of
                            the Secretaries-General,</hi> vol. V, pp. 215–217.</note> which
                    explained more clearly basis of his stand regarding withdrawal of technicians
                    and other. (For text see <gloss target="#t_ourtel1">ourtel</gloss> 1098)<note
                        n="7" xml:id="d249fn7">Not printed. (Department of State, Central Files,
                        343.170G/10–2260)</note>
                </p>
                <p>He described his policy as “two-pronged” approach. To restore authority to
                    Leopoldville, and thereafter to all Congo; also to bring Katanga into central
                    picture. He said he felt he had to try to switch Tshombe’s allegiance and
                    dependence away from Belgians and on to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. Now
                    Tshombe was not just dependent on Belgians, he was “overfed” by them. He had
                    said he only needed 50 technicians and Belgians had provided 100. Such matters
                    retain Belgian hold over Tshombe. Different Belgian attitude could have made all
                    difference in handling. Instead they appeared be hanging on at all costs.</p>
                <p>To Bohlen’s query whether if Belgian technicians were put under <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, situation would be better, Hammarskjold several
                    times avoided specific answer. Finally he admitted this would be better, and he
                    said for individual Belgians to be under <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    control in Congo as whole would not be excluded by his policy. Those who must go
                    were, as pointed out in his earlier note, Belgians directly or indirectly under
                    Belgian Govt control. This he interpreted as “govt-sponsored Belgians, who were
                    paid directly or indirectly by Belgian Govt. Wieschhoff cited as example way in
                    which indirect payment comes about, system where Belgian Govt gives subsidy to
                    Katanga govt which in turn from that subsidy pays for services of Belgian
                    “technicians”.</p>
                <pb facs="0582" n="552" xml:id="pg_552"/>
                <p>Hammarskjold admitted this could become difficult line to draw. He said it must
                    be calculated against alternative, retention of Belgian control which could be
                    very dangerous. Existence of such “curious in-between arrangements” required
                    that <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> “clean things up”. At this point he
                    digressed as if by illustration to refer to troops in southern Kasai province,
                    which were Belgian-officered troops working for Kalonji. It was argued these
                    officers had been “seconded” from “Katanga” army and so were still not Belgians.
                    Hammarskjold said “simple fact is there is Belgian element of control”. He
                    referred as illustration to threat posed to Tshombe before <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> forces entered Katanga: Union Miniere said they
                    would close down all mines, putting 20,000 people out of work if Tshombe let
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> forces enter. Hammarskjold had advised
                    Tshombe not to bend under this pressure but to say he would in such
                    circumstances turn to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> for necessary
                    technicians. Hammarskjold felt this was typical instance of Belgian control.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, meeting having to break off by <gloss target="#t_SYG1"
                    >SYG</gloss>’s subsequent appointment, <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>
                    agreed reality was what took place in area, and not within <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>—that latter was largely reflection of reality.
                    However he insisted <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> could have influence on
                    what happened in real world of Leopoldville. Bohlen, as parting remark,
                    summarized that net effect of situation would seem to be that instead of keeping
                    cold war out of Congo, situation had developed into one-sided cold war. Only US
                    had stayed out. Soviets surely had not, nor was it anything more than naive to
                    think they would stay out.</p>
                <p>Begin Bohlen comment: While we left no doubt as to seriousness with which we view
                    situation in Congo and <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> attitude towards it,
                    foregoing account of 2-hour conversation nevertheless demonstrates inconclusive
                    results insofar as any direct expression of future policy by Hammarskjold was
                    concerned. Our strongest impression is that he sees no clear course of action in
                    Leopoldville to deal with the present situation and has fallen back on a
                    completely do nothing “impartiality”, although he realizes that this may be
                    working in <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>’s favor. Although he
                    did not commit himself, he seemed interested in idea we put forth of having some
                    semblance of a caretaker government to be set up by <persName corresp="#p_KJ8"
                        >Kasavubu</persName> as an interim authority until such time as conditions
                    would permit an orderly convening of Parliament.</p>
                <p>Hammarskjold, however, refused, as will be noted, to make any commitment as to
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> attitude towards any such caretaker
                    government because of constitutional problem involving <persName
                        corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName>. However, I believe if we could produce
                    some coherent plan to bring about establishment by <persName corresp="#p_KJ8"
                        >Kasavubu</persName> of a caretaker government, with possibly <persName
                        corresp="#p_BJM2">Bomboko</persName> as Prime Minister and <persName
                        corresp="#p_MLGJD1">Mobutu</persName> as chief military authority
                    subordinate to it, we would have basis for further discussion with
                    Hammarskjold.</p>
                <pb facs="0583" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/>
                <p>As to letters to Belgium regarding Belgian technicians, we believe that being
                    unable to see clearly what can be done in regard to action in Congo, he is
                    taking this attitude in order to do something and in particular to gain favor
                    with African states. He spoke vaguely of necessity for consultation as to
                    disposition of these technicians and we believe this matter should also be
                    pursued further with him. Since [<hi rend="italic">Although</hi>?] it is our
                    impression that he can still be influenced in more moderate action than his
                    letters would imply, we see, however, very little real hope in changing
                    Hammarskjold’s present attitude unless serious and constructive alternative in
                    regard to caretaker government can be worked out and discussed with him. Such
                    govt to have any chance of succeeding, should have different <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> troops present in Leopoldville. Proposals to this
                    effect might usefully be made to <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> at
                    subsequent meeting with <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> which he himself
                    suggested be held soon. <hi rend="italic">End Bohlen comment.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Bohlen’s reiteration at several different points in our conversation that present
                    position of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in Leo worked in favor of
                        <persName corresp="#p_LP3">Lumumba</persName> and could in our view only
                    lead to his return to power with serious consequences, even failure, for <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> himself,
                    certainly seemed to have shaken <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>. He said he
                    agreed with our negative analysis, but did not seem have definite ideas where to
                    go next. At the least we feel he will be more receptive in future discussion to
                    specific proposals (a) for dealing with caretaker govt if one can be devised,
                    (b) shifting <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> troops, and, if these two factors
                    dealt with, (c) more stringent action re <persName corresp="#p_LP3"
                        >Lumumba</persName>.</p>
                <p>While we did not refer specifically to role being played by <persName
                        corresp="#p_DR4">Dayal</persName> (we showed <gloss target="#t_SYG1"
                        >SYG</gloss> Friday press reports on <persName corresp="#p_DR4"
                        >Dayal</persName>’s attitude toward <persName corresp="#p_MLGJD1"
                        >Mobutu</persName>) we continue to feel this is also major factor in
                    situation which <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> refused to face. Bohlen
                    alluded at different points in conversation to pressures from <gloss
                        target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, Ghana, Guinea and Morocco, which <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> admitted. We inferred from <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>’s reaction, however, that he did not seem to
                    feel this affected <persName corresp="#p_DR4">Dayal</persName>’s behavior. It
                    seems to us at very least important reduce as much as possible pressures on
                        <persName corresp="#p_DR4">Dayal</persName> by shifting <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> forces, and if possible try to find way either
                    having <persName corresp="#p_DR4">Dayal</persName> replaced, or neutralized by
                    addition of another <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> official in Leo.</p>
                <p>(For report of <gloss target="#t_UKDel1">UKDel</gloss> conversation with <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> on same subject see next fol tel.)<note n="8"
                        xml:id="d249fn8">Telegram 1097 from <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>,
                        October 22, reported that <persName corresp="#p_HD3">Hammarskjöld</persName>
                        stressed the need of reassembling Parliament and bringing about a
                        reconciliation of Tshombe with the central government. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid</hi>., 770G.00/10–2260) Barco summarized the Bohlen-<persName
                            corresp="#p_HD3">Hammarskjöld</persName> meeting in a telephone
                        conversation with <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> at 10:25
                        a.m. on October 22. According to a memorandum of the conversation by Mildred
                        Asbjornson, Barco said “they all felt that Hammarskjold does not have an
                        idea on how to improve the situation, but that Hammarskjold was thinking
                        more about the problem than he had before.” (Eisenhower Library, Herter
                        Papers, Telephone Conversations) Telegram 1137 from <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                            >USUN</gloss>, October 26, reported that both Wieschhoff and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName> had commented critically on the U.S.
                        approach, but <persName corresp="#p_WJJ2">Wadsworth</persName> concluded
                        that “despite what they apparently regarded as an affront in presentation of
                        U.S. point of view, it did have some impact.” (Department of State, Central
                        Files, 770G.00/10–2660)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Barco</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
