<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>311. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d311</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">311</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="rec101e79d141fc02f" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="new-states">New states</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="311"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d311">
                <head>311. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d311fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 770B.00/10–2558. Confidential.
                        Drafted by McBride.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1958-10-25">October 25, 1958</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Guinea</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH9">Hervé Alphand</persName>, French
                        Embassy</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName>M. Charles Lucet</persName>, Minister, French Embassy</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Robert H. McBride</persName>, <gloss target="#t_WE1"
                            >WE</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH9">Alphand</persName> asked regarding the US
                    attitude on the Guinea situation.<note n="1" xml:id="d311fn1">Lucet had conveyed
                        the French position on Guinea to <persName corresp="#p_SJC1"
                            >Satterthwaite</persName> the previous day. According to a memorandum of
                        conversation, he said the French considered that Guinea had “juridically
                        speaking become a separate entity” by its negative vote but that it was not
                        capable of exercising sovereignty. He said they did not object to U.S.
                        recognition of Guinea’s “new status” but hoped it would be qualified rather
                        than formal recognition as a fully sovereign state. It would be “very
                        premature” to consider establishment of diplomatic relations or admission to
                        the United Nations. <persName corresp="#p_SJC1">Satterthwaite</persName>
                        replied that he did not find the French position very clear. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 770B.00/10–2458)</note> The Secretary said
                    this had been simmering in his absence. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH9"
                        >Alphand</persName> said there was no question but that Guinea would be
                    independent and a member of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, but we did
                    not wish to go too fast. Guinea will be separated from the French Community and
                    will have to be recognized. However, we should study this problem and not rush
                    diplomatic representation nor <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership. In
                    response to the Secretary’s question, <persName corresp="#p_AH9"
                        >Alphand</persName> said France thought she would have to veto Guinea’s
                    membership in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> this year but would much
                    prefer in the Security Council to obtain five abstentions so that a veto would
                    not be required. He expressed the hope that the US would abstain the Security
                    Council if this matter arose and expressed the belief that the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> would abstain.</p>
                <pb facs="0709" n="679" xml:id="pg_679"/>
                <p>The Secretary expressed the view that in the case of Guinea and others, voting
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership was really a violation of the
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> charter since these states had
                    demonstrated no capacity as required by the charter. The result was the
                    weakening of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. However, he thought the
                    present trend had gone so far that it was questionable whether it could be
                    reversed. <persName corresp="#p_AH9">Alphand</persName> noted that all cases of
                    admission of new states in the past had taken a certain length of time noting
                    the cases of Libya, and the future case of Togo. Even Morocco and Tunisia had
                    waited until after the signature of the treaties of independence, an occurrence
                    which had not yet taken place in the case of Guinea. The conduct of foreign
                    affairs, defense, etc., had not yet been transferred to Guinea.</p>
                <p>The Secretary noted that the British were somewhat worried over non-recognition
                    because of the effect in Ghana and elsewhere. The Secretary added he had a basic
                    sympathy with the French position but noted that the precedents for delaying
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership were not good. <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH9">Alphand</persName> said he did not know when France would
                    turn Guinea loose entirely, but that the territories voting in favor of the
                    French Community obviously took precedence and that the whole question of the
                    relationship of the Community to Guinea must be developed. If the other
                    territories believed it was favored, they would be encouraged to follow the same
                    course with the resulting Balkanization of Black Africa, a development which
                    would be against the interests of the West as a whole.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
