<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-06-30T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-06-30T07:00:00-05:00" n="351" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d351">
                        <head>351. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in South
                                Africa</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d351fn0">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 745A.56311/6–3060. Secret.
                                Repeated to London, Capetown, Johannesburg, Durban, and Port
                                Elizabeth.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Pretoria</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-06-30T14:00:00+02:00">June 30,
                                    1960, 2 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>528. During extended weekend in country where we were both guests,
                                <persName corresp="#p_LEH2">Eric Louw</persName>, Minister External
                            Affairs, had three long talks with me about what he said are
                            deteriorating relations between our two countries.</p>
                        <p>He blamed US press and American committee on Africa for grossly
                            misleading American public on true state of affairs here, and went on to
                            add that State Department’s recent decision to admit Oliver Tambo<note n="1" xml:id="d351fn1">Deputy President of the African National
                                Congress; he fled South Africa at the end of March.</note> who he
                            says is Communist, was regarded by his government as unfriendly act.</p>
                        <p>He then cited South Africa’s firm anti-Communist position in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, her armed contributions during great and
                            Korean wars and his government’s present willingness to react favorably
                            to our desire to conclude agreement with US on <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> and Defense. He added that even though many South
                            Africans are commencing to think that a neutralist policy may be their
                            only alternative, his government will stand firmly with West against
                            Communism and that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_VHF1">Verwoerd</persName>
                            recently assured <persName corresp="#p_MHS2">Macmillan</persName> to
                            this effect.</p>
                        <p>He then asked me why South Africa was getting such bad press in America
                            and listened carefully while I told him that in my opinion his racial
                            policies will always provoke an indignant press in both England and
                            America, and that until present government decides on less rigid
                            attitudes toward non-whites he can expect nothing else.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_LEH2">Louw</persName> then criticized England for
                            selling his country Centurian tanks which have little local use and said
                            that after attending Prime Ministers conference he had sounded Belgians
                            and Czechs on possibility of purchasing arms from them.</p>
                        <p>Turning to matter of his country’s relations with emerging black states
                            of Africa he told me ruefully that <persName corresp="#p_NK2">Nkrumah</persName> had embarrassed him at London Prime Ministers
                            conference by publicly taking back his invitation for <persName corresp="#p_LEH2">Louw</persName> to visit Ghana. He also commented
                            somewhat bitterly on decision of new Congo Government withdraw their
                            invitation to <gloss target="#t_SA1">SA</gloss> attend their
                            independence day celebrations and added that he had had a gold cigarette
                            box made for new Congo Chief of State.</p>
                        <pb facs="0783" n="753" xml:id="pg_753"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_LEH2">Louw</persName> said that these new black
                            states are ganging up against Union and he thought it strange that an
                            ex-State Department advisor such as Ernest Gross<note n="2" xml:id="d351fn2">Department of State Legal Adviser, 1947–1949; he
                                was acting as Counsel for the Liberian Government on the question of
                                South West Africa.</note> would agree to act in behalf of such a
                            combine.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Although we have officially disagreed my
                            personal relations with <persName corresp="#p_LEH2">Louw</persName> have
                            always been good and I felt he was glad we could talk in relaxed
                            atmosphere of country rather than his office. While he did not directly
                            say so he inferred that Cabinet expected him tell me what he did. I also
                            felt for the first time he really listened to my warnings about his
                            country’s racial policies.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CPK1"><hi rend="strong">Crowe</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>