<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>10. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-01-06T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-01-06T01:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-01-06T01:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-01-06T01:00:00-05:00" n="10"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                <head>10. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d10fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET S. Top Secret; Priority;
                            <gloss target="#t_NODIS1">Nodis</gloss>. Received in the Department of
                        State at 3:56 a.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-01-06T14:00:00+08:00">January 6, 1965, 2 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2055. For the President—Section II of V Sections.<note n="2" xml:id="d10fn2"
                        >Sections I and III-V are <ref target="#d9">Documents 9</ref> and <ref
                            target="#d11">11</ref>–<ref target="#d13">13</ref>.</note> Ref. par.
                    7(1) <gloss target="#t_CAP1">CAP</gloss>-64375.<note n="3" xml:id="d10fn3">For
                        text, see <ref target="frus1964-68v01#d477">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. I, Document
                            477</ref>.</note> I fully understand and appreciate your concern with
                    respect to the problem of dependents. As we see it here, there are two aspects
                    to this—first, the actual physical danger to the dependents themselves and,
                    secondly, the psychological effects both on our friends here and on the enemy of
                    a decision to withdraw them. Although no one can exclude the possibility at any
                    time of accidental or deliberate injury being inflicted upon some of our
                    dependents, for the moment I am most concerned with the latter problem, that is,
                    the psychological effects on our friends and enemies.</p>
                <p>Immediate withdrawal in the present atmosphere would, I am certain, be
                    interpreted both here and in Hanoi and Peking as a sign of weakness and
                    desperation which could result in panic among our friends and great
                    encouragement to the enemy. (It would also adversely influence our ability to
                    obtain third country assistance from our less sturdy friends.) However, if the
                    withdrawal is directly related to other action against the <gloss
                        target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>, it can, if properly handled, be used to
                    reinforce the tonic effects such action will have for our friends and the
                    seriousness of purpose that we will desire to communicate to the enemy. I have,
                    for example, in mind the successful way in which we used the evacuation of our
                    dependents from Guantanamo during the Cuban crisis to reinforce the signals that
                    we were seeking to communicate to both Havana and Moscow.</p>
                <pb facs="0052" n="20" xml:id="pg_20"/>
                <p>At the same time, I entirely agree that until the time comes that we want to use
                    mandatory withdrawal of dependents to reinforce wider action we are taking
                    elsewhere, we should seek to do all we can to reduce the size of the problem. We
                    have already done much to reduce their numbers by voluntary and administrative
                    action. For some time <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> has hired no new
                    personnel with small children. <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> has also
                    been reducing the number of positions requiring two-year tours and thus, under
                    present <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> policy, the presence of dependents
                    if desired by their sponsor. All the agencies have also informally discouraged
                    the bringing of dependents and encouraged the voluntary return of those already
                    here. However, we can, and subject to your own thoughts, I propose to do much
                    more.</p>
                <p>We could have all agencies immediately initiate a policy of not permitting newly
                    assigned personnel or those returning from home leave to be accompanied by their
                    dependents. We could also initiate a policy of encouraging the advanced
                    departure of dependents whose sponsors are scheduled to leave Viet-Nam
                    permanently or on home leave orders in the next few months. Additionally, all
                    the agencies represented here could take a harder look at their staffing
                    patterns to see whether staff members, particularly those with dependents, could
                    be reduced without impairing our effectiveness. All of this will inevitably
                    result in some publicity but I think that this is manageable.</p>
                <p>With respect to the remaining dependents, I would propose that at the time we
                    initiate a retaliatory strike against the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> or
                    initiate Phase 2 action against the North we simultaneously announce and
                    undertake an evacuation of all remaining dependents. I suggest that such an
                    announcement should be carefully timed in relation to whatever else we will
                    publicly be saying at the time. I believe that an orderly evacuation of the
                    remaining dependents could be carried out at that time over a period of say
                    seven to ten days with minimum personal hardship and risk to them and without
                    the seriously adverse effects of doing it before that.</p>
                <p>Needless to say, if at any time civil disorders in Saigon or other developments
                    indicate an imminent and serious risk to dependents, I will have no hesitancy in
                    ordering their immediate evacuation.</p>
                <p>All of my principal colleagues strongly agree with the foregoing views except Jim
                    Killen who, while recognizing the political problems of immediate evacuation,
                    favors a complete evacuation initiated now phased over perhaps a two-month
                    period.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Taylor</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
