<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>119. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d119</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">119</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-02-15T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-02-15T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-02-15T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-02-15T07:00:00-05:00" n="119"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d119">
                <head>119. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d119fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET S. Top Secret; Immediate;
                            <gloss target="#t_NODIS1">Nodis</gloss>. Received in the Department of
                        State at 9:22 a.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-02-15T20:00:00+08:00">February 15, 1965, 8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2602. Ref. A. <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL1">Deptel</gloss> 1718.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d119fn2">
                        <ref target="#d115">Document 115</ref>.</note> B. <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 1724.<note n="3" xml:id="d119fn3">
                        <ref target="#d117">Document 117</ref>.</note> This cable reports my meeting
                    with Acting Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_OANH1">Oanh</persName>, General
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> and General <persName
                        corresp="#p_THIEU1">Thieu</persName> for the purpose of obtaining <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> agreement to the US program outlined in
                    paragraphs 1 to 3 inclusive of <gloss target="#t_REFTEL1">reftel</gloss> A. I
                    was accompanied by General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>
                    and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MML1">Manfull</persName>.</p>
                <p>At the outset, I indicated that I was approaching the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> on instructions to obtain concurrence for a joint <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>/US program in extension and replacement of the
                    one which we had previously discussed on December 7<note n="4" xml:id="d119fn4"
                        >Regarding this discussion, see <ref target="frus1964-68v01#d439">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. I, Document
                            439</ref>.</note> and January 25.<note n="5" xml:id="d119fn5">Apparently
                        an inaccurate reference. <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> was
                        presumably referring to his discussion of the reprisal program with
                            <persName corresp="#p_HUONG1">Huong</persName> on January 23, which is
                        described in Document 33.</note> To facilitate the discussion, I distributed
                    the following top secret unsigned memorandum: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> proposes the adoption of the
                            following program for immediate future actions: <list>
                                <item>“A. Intensification by all available means of the program of
                                    pacification within <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>.</item>
                                <item>“B. Execution of a joint <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                                    >GVN</gloss>/US program of measured and limited air action
                                    against selected military targets in the southern part of <gloss
                                        target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>. Air strikes under this program
                                    will be jointly planned and agreed.</item>
                                <item>“C. Announcement of this policy of measured action in general
                                    terms and presentation to the United Nations Security Council of
                                    the <pb facs="0303" n="271" xml:id="pg_271"/> case against the
                                        <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> as the aggressor,
                                    accompanied by an indication of readiness to discuss ways of
                                    bringing the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> aggression to
                                    an end.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Following the guidance contained in reftels, I then proceeded to comment on each
                    one of the foregoing three points. With regard to the intensification of
                    pacification, I noted the danger both in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> and
                    in the US that this air program would be regarded as a cheap and easy way out of
                    the pacification problems in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> and that it
                    behooves both parties to allay this misapprehension by intensified attention to
                    pacification and by strong statements to the people and the armed forces of
                        <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> that the in-country program must be
                    carried forward with increasing vigor.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> agreed with this evaluation but
                    cited the unspectacular nature of pacification operations and the requirement to
                    keep a strong central reserve of military units to cope with possible major
                    attacks by <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> on provincial centers. He asked my
                    opinion about the need for a partial mobilization, to which I replied that now
                    was the time to be sure that all national resources were brought into play as we
                    appeared to be moving toward some kind of climax.</p>
                <p>With regard to the second point, I stressed that on our side we would like to
                    impart a vigorous rhythm to the operations against the North but that much would
                    depend upon the ability of the Vietnamese Government to maintain its end. There
                    would be much more in the program than the military aspects; in particular,
                    there would be a need for a prompt strengthening of the foreign office, the
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> delegation and information activities.
                    Overall, there was the pressing need for a strong, permanent government.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> then asked what we meant by the
                    phrase “selected military targets in the southern part of the <gloss
                        target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>”? I explained that it meant the area in which
                    we had conducted our recent strikes and would extend over, at least, as much of
                    south <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> as could be reached with safety by
                        <gloss target="#t_VNAF1">VNAF</gloss>. I then made the point that, not
                    covered by this proposed agreement, were the US air operations in Laos, the 34–A
                    program which should continue to be conducted as at present, and any <gloss
                        target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> operations of the nature of the Tonkin
                    Gulf affair. I explained that the initial limitation of strikes to this southern
                    part of the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> would not necessarily be
                    permanent as, in the course, we would probably want to edge north to give
                    signals to Hanoi of increasing danger.</p>
                <p>On the subject of point three, the approach to the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss>, I explained the need for preemptive action and for taking the
                    initiative from those countries who might wish to call us before the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> bar as the guilty party. It was most important to
                    present the strongest possible case against Hanoi and we must work closely
                    together [to] this end. I emphasized that we expected to continue air strikes
                    throughout the duration of the discussions which might last several months. I
                    closed with a summary of our objectives which are to oblige Hanoi to cease
                    infiltration and all forms of <pb facs="0304" n="272" xml:id="pg_272"/> support
                    of <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and to collaborate in obtaining cessation
                    of <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> insurgency.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_OANH1"
                        >Oanh</persName> consulted briefly and <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1"
                        >Khanh</persName> indicated that they were completely in accord with the
                    three-point program. I indicated that I would report <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> concurrence to Washington.</p>
                <p>Before we broke up, <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> expressed
                    concern over the statements appearing in the world press which suggested that
                    our recent air strikes had been in retaliation solely for US losses on US bases
                    and indicated that this kind of talk caused him trouble in <gloss
                        target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>. I told him that we appreciated his difficulty
                    and would also like to stress the mutuality of our defensive actions. I
                    reiterated, as I had in my meeting with Prime Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_HUONG1">Huong</persName> on January 23, that retaliation should
                    take place whether the victims were Vietnamese, US nationals or both. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName>’s comment is a reminder to us that in
                    all government statements we should recognize the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> partnership and the mutual responsibility to protect the
                    nationals of both countries.</p>
                <p>Later when I queried <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> privately as
                    to whether he has considered bringing <persName corresp="#p_OANH1"
                        >Quat</persName> into the meeting per our suggestion, <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> replied that it would have been
                    improper to include <persName corresp="#p_Quat1">Quat</persName> since he was
                    not officially installed as Prime Minister. However, <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> said he would bring <persName
                        corresp="#p_Quat1">Quat</persName> up to date immediately following
                        <persName corresp="#p_Quat1">Quat</persName>’s investiture. Earlier we had
                    informed <persName corresp="#p_Quat1">Quat</persName> without mentioning subject
                    of meeting that we would suggest to <persName corresp="#p_OANH1">Oanh</persName>
                    and <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> that he participate but of
                    course decision rested with them.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Taylor</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
