<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-02-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                        <head>146. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG1" type="from">Bundy</persName>) to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d146fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File,
                                Memos to the President, <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                                    Bundy</persName>, Vol. VIII. Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-02-19">February 19,
                                    1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Answer to <persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Adlai Stevenson</persName>’s
                                memo</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I asked <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">George Ball</persName> to answer
                                <persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Adlai</persName>’s memorandum of
                            February 17 (Tab A)<note n="2" xml:id="d146fn2">See <ref target="#d145">Document 145</ref>.</note> and here is my own suggestion as to
                            what you might say to him if you wish to telephone him. In the current
                            situation, I do not think such a phone call is urgent.</p>
                        <pb facs="0370" n="338" xml:id="pg_338"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Stevenson</persName> suggests an early
                                Presidential statement. Your answer is that you believe in all
                                necessary statements of our policy and objectives—that you have
                                stated them repeatedly—and that you have told the Secretary of State
                                to hold a press conference or issue a statement at any time in the
                                next days or weeks that he may think it necessary. You yourself do
                                not wish to heat up the national or international atmosphere by
                                making a very loud noise right now, although you are free to change
                                your mind if the situation requires it.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>You do not wish to indicate our “readiness for exploratory talks”
                                at this time. Our position is not one in which we should now look as
                                if we were hunting negotiations. Both the Communists and our friends
                                in Saigon would interpret such a proposal as a sign of weakness and
                                readiness to withdraw.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>You share his view that we do not wish to get into the Security
                                Council right now.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>You do not think that we would now wish to organize a meeting of
                                the US, <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, France, China, the Soviet
                                Union, and North and South Vietnam. Such a committee would be
                                weighted against us, and there is no reason today to offer the
                                French the mediator role in this conspicuous way.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong">McG. B.</hi><note n="3" xml:id="d146fn3">Printed from a copy that bears these typed
                                initials.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>