<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>158. Memorandum From the Office of Current Intelligence to Director of
                    Central Intelligence to Director of Central Intelligence McCone</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d158</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">158</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-02-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-02-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-02-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="158"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d158">
                <head>158. Memorandum From the <gloss type="from">Office of Current
                        Intelligence</gloss> to Director of Central Intelligence <persName
                        corresp="#p_MCJA1" type="to">McCone</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d158fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, Vietnam, Vol. 29. Secret; No Foreign Dissem;
                        Background Use Only. <persName>Rusk</persName> called <persName
                            corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> at 1 p.m. on February 23 and told
                        him that, in anticipation of a meeting the President might call that
                        afternoon, a “wrap up” was needed of any evidence regarding Hanoi’s and
                        Beijing’s interest in negotiating a peaceful settlement of the Vietnam
                        conflict. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> called
                            <persName>Rusk</persName> back at 5:07 p.m. to tell him that <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> had produced a memorandum but it was still
                        in draft form. <persName>Rusk</persName> asked <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1"
                            >McCone</persName> to get it to <persName corresp="#p_SB1">Bromley
                            Smith</persName>’s office right away, since the President was holding a
                        meeting on that subject at 5:30 p.m. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1"
                            >McCone</persName> replied that he might not get it there by then and
                        summarized the memorandum’s principal conclusion. Whether a copy reached the
                        White House in time for the meeting has not been determined. (Department of
                        State, <persName>Rusk</persName> Files: Lot 72 D 192, Telephone Calls) For
                        more information on the meeting, see <ref target="#d157fn1">footnote 1,
                            Document 157</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_OCI1">OCI</gloss> No. 0930/65</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-02-23">February 23, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">THE CURRENT POSITION OF HANOI AND PEIPING ON A NEGOTIATED
                    SETTLEMENT IN VIETNAM</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>According to press reports from Paris the Vietnamese Communists have
                        recently urged the French to step up their efforts aimed at arranging a
                        negotiated settlement of the war in South Vietnam. These accounts are
                        probably leaks of discussions between French officials and Asian Communist
                        representatives which began in December and continued on into
                        February.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Our only information concerning these talks is what the French have chosen
                        to tell us. This has been short on specifics and long on speculation. We
                        have seen nothing in Communist statements or in Communist behavior which
                        would support the contention that either Hanoi or Peiping is interested in a
                        conference solution except on its own terms.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>All indications are that the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> is no
                        more flexible now than it ever was in regard to a negotiated settlement. On
                        10 February Hanoi specifically <pb facs="0392" n="360" xml:id="pg_360"/>
                        reiterated its standard demands, stressing the two key concepts on which the
                        Communists have always insisted—the necessity for withdrawal of US forces
                        from South Vietnam and the initiation of bilateral negotiations between the
                        Communist Liberation Front (NLSV) and the government in Saigon. <gloss
                            target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> officials, moreover, have privately taken
                        the same line in conversations with Western diplomats in Hanoi.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>’s terms which have not changed
                        substantially since they were first put forward in 1963, include: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>Withdrawal of US military personnel and equipment is a
                                precondition for any serious negotiations.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>The South Vietnamese government must abide by the military
                                provisions of the Geneva agreements: refrain from any military
                                alliances, permit no foreign military bases or foreign military
                                personnel in South Vietnam.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>The South Vietnamese people must be permitted to settle their
                                internal affairs without outside interference in accordance with the
                                program of the Front. This is interpreted as the formulation of a
                                coalition government with Front participation.</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>Consultation must take place between the two zones looking toward
                                eventual reunification.</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item>As of July 1964 Hanoi has included as a further condition an end
                                to US “provocations” against <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>
                                territory.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The recent activities of North Vietnamese agents in Paris suggest Hanoi is
                        seeking to stimulate French pressure for a US withdrawal as the first step
                        toward a negotiated settlement of the “impasse” in Indochina. These
                        maneuvers by the Communists appear designed mainly to encourage opposition
                        in France and elsewhere in the Free World to continued prosecution of the
                        war against the Viet Cong and to possible further US attacks against the
                            <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Such motives were suggested by the North Vietnamese response to French
                        initiatives during the Paris conversations. Although there was no give in
                        the position taken by the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>
                        representative, he stressed an interest in continuing the discussions,
                        doubtless with a view to keeping French hopes for a negotiated settlement
                        alive. Similar objectives probably lie behind the recent propaganda from
                        Hanoi, which has reported without comment the substance of French and
                        Cambodian calls for a new international conference on Indochina. There is,
                        however, no evidence available to us that the North Vietnamese are giving
                        serious consideration to a conference.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese have consistently backed Hanoi’s hard line concerning
                        negotiations and do not appear interested, at this time, even in the kind of
                        talks which might be exploited under some circumstances to give Communist
                        forces a breathing space.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese Communists are almost certainly optimistic concerning
                        developments in South Vietnam. The conversations initiated by <pb
                            facs="0393" n="361" xml:id="pg_361"/> the Chinese in Paris were
                        apparently designed to obtain a better reading on these questions, and at
                        the same time to stimulate new French pressure on the US to withdraw quietly
                        from the “hopeless” impasse in Indochina. In this endeavor Peiping is
                        playing skillfully on French ambitions for a larger role in Southeast Asia
                        as mediators of the Sino-US conflict.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>The remarks of the Chinese Charge in Paris, as reported by the French,
                        make it clear that Peiping—like Hanoi—has no desire for any agreement except
                        on Communist terms. The Chinese continue to insist that a unilateral US
                        withdrawal is the only basis for settlement.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Peiping’s latest public statement on the question of possible negotiations
                        ridicules the idea of talks. A key paragraph of the People’s Daily editorial
                        on 19 February claims that the US is hoping to gain at the conference table
                        what it cannot win on the battlefield and then dismisses the notion as “too
                        much wishful thinking.” The Chinese go on to say that peace can be had in
                        Vietnam at any time but only after the “US aggressors have withdrawn” to
                        permit the people in Vietnam to “settle their own problems.”</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
