<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-06-06T22:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-06-06T22:35:00-05:00" n="337" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d337">
                        <head>337. Telegram From the Commander, Military Assistance Command, Vietnam
                                (<persName corresp="#p_WGWC1" type="from">Westmoreland</persName>)
                            to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d337fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET S. Top Secret;
                                Immediate; <gloss target="#t_EXDIS1">Exdis</gloss>. Sent to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> personal for General <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> and sent to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> personal for Admiral
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SAUSG1">Sharp</persName>. Repeated to
                                    <gloss target="#t_CINCUSARPAC1">CINCUSARPAC</gloss> for General
                                Waters, <gloss target="#t_CINCPACAF1">CINCPACAF</gloss> for General
                                Harris, <gloss target="#t_CINCPACFLT1">CINCPACFLT</gloss> for
                                Admiral <persName>Johnson</persName>, and <gloss target="#t_CGFMFPAC1">C G FMFPAC</gloss> for General <hi rend="italic">Krulak</hi>. Sent to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> with a request to pass to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-06-07T11:35:00+08:00">June 7,
                                    1965, 11:35 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>MAC JOO 19118. Subj: US troop deployment to <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> (S). Ref: A. <gloss target="#t_COMUSMACV1">COMUSMACV</gloss> 041133Z <gloss target="#t_NOTAL1">notal</gloss>;
                            B. <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 2343 564–7; C. <gloss target="#t_COMUSMACV1">COMUSMACV</gloss> 260040Z May <gloss target="#t_NOTAL1">notal</gloss>; D. <gloss target="#t_USASCV1">USASCV</gloss><gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> 65–TS 101 311200Z
                            May <gloss target="#t_NOTAL1">notal</gloss>; E. <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> 052249Z (PASEP); F. <gloss target="#t_COMUSMACV1">COMUSMACV</gloss> 201207Z May 65.<note n="2" xml:id="d337fn2">None found.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>As indicated Ref A, a broad review of force requirements has been
                                conducted in light of the changing situation in Southeast Asia and
                                within <gloss target="#t_RVN1">RVN</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>There are indications that the conflict in Southeast Asia is in
                                the process of moving to a higher level. Some <gloss target="#t_PAVN1">PAVN</gloss> forces have entered <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> and more may well be on the way.
                                Additional jet fighters and some jet light bombers have been
                                deployed in the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Specifically, elements of the 325th <gloss target="#t_PAVN1">PAVN</gloss> division are in the northern zone of II Corps. It
                                is quite possible that the major portion, if not all of the division
                                is now deployed in the Kontum, Pleiku, Phu Bon area. Elements of the
                                304th <gloss target="#t_PAVN1">PAVN</gloss> division are suspected
                                to be in the panhandle and, therefore, capable of following the
                                325th. The recent heavy actions in Phuoc Long and Quang Ngai, and
                                    <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> initiatives in Pleiku, Kontum,
                                Phu Bon and Thua Thien are demonstrations of <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> strength and their apparent determination to employ
                                their forces aggressively. Recent events as well as captured <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> prisoners and documents suggest that
                                a summer campaign is now underway to destroy government forces and
                                concurrently, to first isolate and then attack district and province
                                towns.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>So far the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> have not employed
                                their full capabilities in this campaign. Only two of the nine Viet
                                Cong regiments have been heavily engaged (one in Phuoc Long and one
                                in Quang Ngai), and probably only a similar proportion of their
                                separate battalions has been committed. In most engagements, <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> main force units have displayed
                                improved training and discipline, heavier firepower from the new
                                family of weapons with which most main force units have been
                                equipped, and a willingness to take heavy losses in order to achieve
                                objectives.</item>
                            <pb facs="0766" n="734" xml:id="pg_734"/>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>In pressing their campaign, the Viet Cong are capable of mounting
                                regimental-size operations in all four <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> Corps areas, and at least battalion-sized attacks
                                in virtually all provinces. Known dispositions indicate major
                                actions are likely in the near future in the Binh Duong-Phuoc
                                Thanh-Phuoc Long area north of Saigon, in the Quang Ngai-Quang Tin
                                area in Central Vietnam, and in Kontum, Pleiku, Phu Bon and Binh
                                Dinh Provinces. Major attacks could occur also in other areas; the
                                Viet Cong have shown that they are capable of concentrating in
                                regimental strength with little or no warning. Whether or not the
                                304th Div is in, or moving toward <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> has a
                                “doorstep” capability to reinforce the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> with sizable forces.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> forces on the other hand are
                                already experiencing difficulty in coping with this increased <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> capability. Desertion rates are
                                inordinately high. Battle losses have been higher than expected; in
                                fact, four <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> battalions have
                                been rendered ineffective by <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                action in the I and II Corps zones. Therefore, effective fighting
                                strength of many infantry and ranger battalions is unacceptably low.
                                As a result, <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> troops are
                                beginning to show signs of reluctance to assume the offensive and in
                                some cases their steadfastness under fire is coming into doubt. In
                                order to bring existing battalions up to acceptable battlefield
                                strength, it will be necessary to declare at least a temporary
                                moratorium on the activation of new battalions. Thus, the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss><gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                force ratios upon which we based our estimate of the situation in
                                March have taken an adverse trend. You will recall that I
                                recommended the deployment of a U.S. division in II Corps to cover
                                the period of the <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss> buildup
                                and to weigh the force ratios in that important area. We assumed at
                                that time that the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> battalions
                                would be brought to full strength by now and that the force buildup
                                would proceed on schedule. Neither of these assumptions has
                                materialized.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>The problem of low battlefield strength in <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> has forced us to plan the use of
                                personnel now training in 11 new battalions as fillers for old
                                battalions. In effect, these 11 battalions will be deferred and
                                during the period from mid-July to early November no new <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> battalions will become available.
                                Thus the gap to be filled is both deeper and wider.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>In summary, the force ratios continue to change in favor of the
                                    <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>. I believe that the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> will commit whatever forces it
                                deems necessary to tip the balance and that the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> cannot stand up successfully to
                                this kind of pressure without reinforcement. Even if <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss><gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                intentions are debatable, their capabilities must be acknowledged
                                and faced. Additionally, it is prudent to consider possible enemy
                                air action, leading to <pb facs="0767" n="735" xml:id="pg_735"/>
                                significant escalation and a broadening of the arena of conflict. We
                                must be prepared to face such a contingency.<note n="3" xml:id="d337fn3">In telegram 2873 to Saigon, June 11, the
                                    Department of State noted that <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> had
                                    assessed the military appraisal of the situation in South
                                    Vietnam provided in telegram 19118. While agreeing that it was
                                    serious, the intelligence analysts questioned the implication
                                    that there was a serious danger of complete military collapse
                                    within a relatively short period of time. This impression, the
                                    Department noted, was not supported by reporting from Saigon,
                                    and telegram 19118 did not reinforce the impression with
                                    reference to a dramatic or unexpected development in the
                                    military situation. (Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>)</note></item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>In order to cope with the situation outlined above, I see no
                                course of action open to us except to reinforce our efforts in
                                    <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> with additional U.S. or
                                third country forces as rapidly as is practical during the critical
                                weeks ahead. Additionally, studies must continue and plans developed
                                to deploy even greater forces, if and when required, to attain our
                                objectives or counter enemy initiatives. Ground forces deployed to
                                selected areas along the coast and inland will be used both
                                offensively and defensively. U.S. ground troops are gaining
                                experience and thus far have performed well. Although they have not
                                yet engaged the enemy in strength, I am convinced that U.S. troops
                                with their energy, mobility, and firepower can successfully take the
                                fight to the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>. The basic purpose of
                                the additional deployments recommended below is to give us a
                                substantial and hard hitting offensive capability on the ground to
                                convince the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> that they cannot
                                win.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>In sub-paragraph “A” below, deployments and actions are
                                recommended on which decisions should be made now. In subpara “B” we
                                have identified further actions on which planning should start and
                                on which separate recommendations will be forthcoming: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>Actions recommended: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Deploy at once to I <gloss target="#t_CTZ1">CTZ</gloss> the remaining two BLTs of the 3d Mar
                                                Div and appropriate supporting division and air
                                                elements (approximately 8,000 personnel).
                                                Reconstitute the <gloss target="#t_SLF1">SLF</gloss>
                                                as a floating reserve.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>Deploy balance of increment 1 and all of increment
                                                2 (as defined in Ref C) of army logistic and other
                                                support units in accordance with schedule set out in
                                                Ref D. (Approximately 8,000 personnel.)</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>Deploy the US Army Air Mobile Division (and
                                                logistic increment 3) through Qui Nhon to An Ke,
                                                Pleiku and Kontum (approximately 21,000 personnel).
                                                Qui Nhon will be ready to receive the division
                                                approximately 1 August, upon the closure of
                                                increment 2 forces.</item>
                                            <label>(4)</label>
                                            <item>Concurrently with the Air Mobile Division, deploy
                                                I Corps Headquarters (approximately 1,500
                                                personnel).</item>
                                            <label>(5)</label>
                                            <item>Deploy the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                                Marine <gloss target="#t_RCT1">RCT</gloss> to Cam
                                                Ranh Bay as soon after 1 July as the unit can be
                                                readied for movement (approximately 4,000
                                                personnel). Deploy balance of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Division force
                                                (approximately 14,500 personnel) plus US logistic
                                                increment 4 (1,500 personnel), starting 15 September
                                                to the general area of Qui Nhon. (This answers Ref E
                                                in part—separate message on F86F will follow.)<note n="4" xml:id="d337fn4">Not found.</note></item>
                                            <pb facs="0768" n="736" xml:id="pg_736"/>
                                            <label>(6)</label>
                                            <item>Deploy additional tactical fighter squadrons to
                                                Cam Ranh Bay when expeditionary landing field
                                                complete at that location. Also provide naval
                                                aircraft carrier support of in-country operations as
                                                required; we believe this latter will engage one
                                                carrier full time.</item>
                                            <label>(7)</label>
                                            <item>Hold the 173d Airborne Brigade in-country until
                                                the Air Mobile Division has deployed and is ready
                                                for operations.</item>
                                            <label>(8)</label>
                                            <item>Continue air attacks against the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>. (Ref F
                                                applies.)</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>Additional deployment that may be required and on which
                                        planning should begin: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Three U.S. Army Hawk battalions to TN Bien Hoa,
                                                Qui Nhon and Cam Ranh in that priority.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>The remainder of the 1st Infantry Division or the
                                                101st Airborne Division begining 1 October.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>One additional <gloss target="#t_MAB1">MAB</gloss>
                                                to reinforce the III <gloss target="#t_MAF1">MAF</gloss>.</item>
                                            <label>(4)</label>
                                            <item>Tactical air units for support of increased U.S.
                                                force (additional airfields in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> and Thailand may be
                                                required).</item>
                                            <label>(5)</label>
                                            <item>Required combat and logistic support forces to
                                                include helicopter units to support the
                                                foregoing.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>Message has been discussed with Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> and
                                    <persName>Johnson</persName>. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> is prepared to comment
                                thereon during current visit to Washington.<note n="5" xml:id="d337fn5">Admiral <persName corresp="#p_SAUSG1">Sharp</persName> added his comments on these proposals in
                                        <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> telegrams
                                    072325Z to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>, June 7, and
                                    112210Z to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>, June 11. Sharp
                                    concurred in <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>’s assessment of the deteriorating
                                    military situation in Vietnam and agreed on the necessity of
                                    expanded deployment of U.S. forces to meet the threat. He
                                    expressed apprehension, however, over the proposed deployment of
                                    the U.S. Air Mobile Division to the central highlands. <persName corresp="#p_SAUSG1">Sharp</persName> argued that limited
                                    U.S. combat forces should be used to secure the more populous
                                    coastal areas of South Vietnam. (<gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> telegram 072325Z is in Department of State,
                                    Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET
                                        <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>; <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> telegram 112210Z is in Washington National
                                    Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 319, HQDA
                                    Message Center, Reel 12305)</note></item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>