<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>346. Memorandum From the Joint Chiefs of Staff to Secretary of Defense to
                    Secretary of Defense McNamara</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d346</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">346</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-06-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-06-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec0tfPbYHg7imwab" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067175"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Intelligence community</term>
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-06-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-06-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="346"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                <head>346. Memorandum From the <gloss type="from">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss> to
                    Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1" type="to">McNamara</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d346fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, Vietnam, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                        Memos, Vol. I. Top Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-06-11">June 11, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>US/Allied Troop Deployments to South Vietnam (<gloss target="#t_SVN1"
                            >SVN</gloss>)</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <gloss target="#t_JCSM1">JCSM</gloss>–457–65</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Joint Chiefs of Staff have reviewed US/Allied force requirements in
                            <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> in the light of recent developments
                        in Southeast Asia and the Republic of Vietnam (<gloss target="#t_RVN1"
                            >RVN</gloss>). Findings and recommendations resulting from this review
                        are set forth in the following paragraphs.</item>
                    <pb facs="0787" n="755" xml:id="pg_755"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>There are significant indications that the communists may be on the
                        threshold of moving the conflict in Southeast Asia to a new and higher level
                        of intensity. By <gloss target="#t_JCSM1">JCSM</gloss>–415–65, dated 27 May
                            1965,<note n="2" xml:id="d346fn2">See <ref target="#d318">Document
                                318</ref>.</note> as supplemented by <gloss target="#t_JCSM1"
                            >JCSM</gloss> 442–65, dated 7 June 1965,<note n="3" xml:id="d346fn3">In
                            this memorandum to the Secretary of Defense, the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                            indicated that they had reviewed Special National Intelligence Estimates
                            10–6–65, 10–6/1–65, and 10–7–65, and concluded that “these intelligence
                            estimates sustain the judgments advanced to you in <gloss
                                target="#t_JCSM1">JCSM</gloss>–415–65.” (Washington National Records
                            Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_OSD1"
                                >OSD</gloss> Files: FRC 70 A 1265, Vietnam 381)</note> the Joint
                        Chiefs of Staff advised you of their views that the deployment of increased
                        numbers of jet fighters, some jet light bombers, and <gloss target="#t_SA21"
                            >SA–2</gloss> surface-to-air missiles to North Vietnam shows a communist
                        decision to add a new dimension to the situation in Southeast Asia. Further,
                        with respect to land combat, the Viet Cong (<gloss target="#t_VC1"
                            >VC</gloss>) have been engaged in a build-up of their forces and are
                        capable of mounting regimental-size operations in all four corps areas and
                        at least battalion-size operations in virtually all provinces. Many <gloss
                            target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> units are well trained and equipped and some
                        are equipped with a new family of weapons. Elements of the 101st Regiment of
                        the 325th North Vietnamese Army (<gloss target="#t_PAVN1">PAVN</gloss>)
                        Division are in the northern zone of II Corps area, and it is possible that
                        elements of two other regiments of the division are now deployed within the
                        provinces of Kontum-Pleiku and Phu Bon or in nearby Laos. Elements of the
                        304th <gloss target="#t_PAVN1">PAVN</gloss> Division are suspected to be in
                        Southern Laos, capable of early movement into the <gloss target="#t_RVN1"
                            >RVN</gloss>. The communists recently have shown a willingness to take
                        heavy losses to achieve their objectives. So far, the <gloss target="#t_VC1"
                            >VC</gloss> have not employed their full capabilities. Only two of the
                        nine <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> regiments have been heavily engaged
                        and probably only a similar proportion of their separate battalions have
                        been committed. Recent events as well as captured <gloss target="#t_VC1"
                            >VC</gloss> prisoners and documents suggest that a summer campaign is
                        now underway to destroy government forces and, concurrently, first to
                        isolate and then attack district and province towns.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_RVN1">RVN</gloss> ground forces are in a precarious
                        position as to their capability to withstand such an offensive. As a result
                        of recent heavy engagements with the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_COMUSMACV1">COMUSMACV</gloss> reports that some <gloss
                            target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> units are beginning to show signs of
                        reluctance to take necessary offensive actions and, in some areas, their
                        steadfastness under fire is coming into doubt. Planned <gloss
                            target="#t_RVN1">RVN</gloss> force build-ups have been suspended until
                        November, because of the requirement to allocate available resources toward
                        reconstituting units recently combat-attired. Thus, it is estimated that a
                        further deterioration in the near term will occur through change of force
                        ratios in favor of the communist units in South Vietnam.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>While a formal appraisal in the form of a <gloss target="#t_SNIE1"
                            >SNIE</gloss> by the <gloss target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss> has not been
                        conducted, informal polling of the intelligence community <pb facs="0788"
                            n="756" xml:id="pg_756"/> indicates general agreement with the <gloss
                            target="#t_COMUSMACV1">COMUSMACV</gloss> views regarding the enemy and
                        friendly situation in Southeast Asia.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In this unstable military situation, appropriate countermeasures are
                        required. The Joint Chiefs of Staff consider that the ground forces
                        situation requires a substantial further build-up of US and Allied forces in
                        the <gloss target="#t_RVN1">RVN</gloss>, at the most rapid rate feasible on
                        an orderly basis. The Appendix hereto<note n="4" xml:id="d346fn4">Not
                            printed.</note> summarizes US and Allied forces required now for this
                        build-up, designed to provide a substantial and necessary increase in
                        offensive capability. The recommended deployments were discussed with
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> on 9 June
                            1965<note n="5" xml:id="d346fn5">No record of the discussion cited here
                            has been found.</note> and he foresees no political problems with the
                        Government of Vietnam in the introduction of these forces. Lists in the
                        appendix may be further refined by recommendations from <gloss
                            target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> and the Services.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>In addition to the above deployments, the Joint Chiefs of Staff consider
                        that air action against North Vietnam should be intensified to include
                        increased armed reconnaissance of LOCs and strikes against militarily
                        important targets. Such action is necessary to reduce <gloss
                            target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> capabilities to support the <gloss
                            target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_PAVN1"
                        >PAVN</gloss>, further punish the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>, and
                        further establish US intent to prevent a communist seizure of <gloss
                            target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>In addition to the actions recommended in <gloss target="#t_JCSM1"
                            >JCSM</gloss>–415–65, <gloss target="#t_JCSM1">JCSM</gloss>–442–65, and
                        paragraph 6, above, the Joint Chiefs of Staff recommend that the deployments
                        shown in the Appendix be approved now for implementation.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>For the Joint Chiefs of Staff:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Earle G. Wheeler</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Chairman<lb/>Joint Chiefs of Staff</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
