<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>59. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-02-03T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-02-03T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-02-03T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-02-03T09:00:00-05:00" n="59"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d59">
                <head>59. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d59fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15 VIETS. Top Secret; Flash;
                        Limdis. Repeated to the White House, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1"
                            >CINCPAC</gloss>. Received in the Department of State at 10:06
                        a.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-02-03T22:00:00+08:00">February 3, 1965, 10 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2391. <gloss target="#t_EMBTEL1">Embtel</gloss> 2382.<note n="2" xml:id="d59fn2">
                        <ref target="#d58">Document 58</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Although the info reported in <gloss target="#t_REFTEL1">reftel</gloss>
                        may not be a true blueprint of coming events, it does have enough
                        plausibility to warrant us deciding now what attitude we should take to a
                        new <gloss target="#t_GOVT1">govt</gloss> headed by <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName>. My following comments have in mind
                        such a takeover under circumstances suggested by <gloss target="#t_REFTEL1"
                            >reftel</gloss> but are generally applicable to the broad question of
                        whether we can do business with <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1"
                            >Khanh</persName> as the controlling partner of a de Gaulle-Pompidou
                        line-up. We know that he has yearned for such an alignment at least since
                        last August and his present alliance with the Buddhists, shaky though it may
                        be, may lead him to believe that now is the moment to try for it. What are
                        the likely consequences of such a move insofar as U.S. interests are
                        concerned?</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>First, let us assume that General <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1"
                            >Khanh</persName> succeeds and establishes himself as Chief of State
                        after the <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> model. His
                        ability to stay in power will depend largely upon two groups—the Buddhist
                        Institute leaders and the generals. To keep both groups in line appears to
                        present contradictory requirements. The Buddhist leaders will not long be
                        satisfied <pb facs="0159" n="127" xml:id="pg_127"/> with a <gloss
                            target="#t_GOVT1">govt</gloss> which does not comply with their behests
                        and such subservience is likely to offend many of the generals. If <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> does not play along with the
                        Buddhists, sooner or later they can be counted upon to take to the streets
                        and present <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> with the same
                        problem which he faced in August, 1964. At that time, he capitulated quickly
                        under Buddhist pressure to the disgust of ods [his?] generals. If this
                        situation were to be repeated, we would expect the generals to split on the
                        issue of Buddhist domination with unpredictable results other than confusion
                        approaching anarchy.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Let us suppose that <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName>, in
                        spite of these obvious difficulties, somehow succeeds in keeping the
                        generals in line while satisfying the Buddhists. In that case, the
                        Catholics, the Hoa Hao, the Cao Dai and the other elements generally
                        suspicious of <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> can be expected
                        to cause him trouble. Whether their opposition would be sufficient to
                        overthrow his <gloss target="#t_GOVT1">govt</gloss> may be doubtful but the
                        consequences could well be serious and possibly include bloody outbreaks of
                        religious strife.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>[Garble] combination in which <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1"
                            >Khanh</persName> is maintained as the governmental leader with Buddhist
                        support. We foresee a likely trend toward neutralism and anti-Americanism.
                        The Buddhists are suspect on both counts and are so notified [<hi
                            rend="italic">identified</hi>?] in the public mind. We know General
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName>’s deep feeling about the
                        necessity of Buddhist support and have long suspected him of wishing to
                        become the Sihanouk of South Vietnam able to treat the U.S. with similar
                        disregard.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In summary, I can see no good coming out of a <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> govt—not even that minimum
                        stability which would allow us to continue the struggle against the Viet
                        Cong and Hanoi at present levels of success. The probable outcomes as we
                        foresee them would be either civil disturbance approaching anarchy or a
                        neutralist <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> in a Sihanouk
                        role. Both are unacceptable solutions from the point of view of the
                        U.S.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>With this conviction in mind, we next raise the question of how to avoid a
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> govt? Only with the
                        acquiescence of the large majority of the influential generals can he accede
                        to head of state. We know that he is politicking now to see whether he can
                        get the necessary support. Unless the U.S. reps decide to let matters run
                        their course without an attempt to influence them and take the heavy
                        responsibility of doing nothing, it is most important that we communicate a
                        timely message to the generals to persuade them to withhold a vote of
                        confidence for <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> and to prevent
                        his coming to power. While the exact text of such a communication would have
                        to be tempered carefully to the character of each of the generals contacted,
                        the bare bones of such a message would be that the U.S. <gloss
                            target="#t_GOVT1">govt</gloss> will not recognize and will not support a
                            <gloss target="#t_GOVT1">govt</gloss> headed by General <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName>. It is our opinion that such word
                        conveyed at the proper time to selected generals and perhaps also to certain
                        civil leaders would accomplish our purpose.</item>
                    <pb facs="0160" n="128" xml:id="pg_128"/>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>There is, of course, always the possibility of an unfavorable reaction.
                        The generals might rally to support <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1"
                            >Khanh</persName> because of this “foreign pressure.” Then, if in spite
                        of our efforts, <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1">Khanh</persName> came into
                        power, we would have to do what we had promised, namely, withdraw
                        recognition from the <gloss target="#t_GOVT1">govt</gloss> and await
                        developments. It would not be necessary to withdraw all support at once
                        because we would still have the hope that <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1"
                            >Khanh</persName>’s opponents would shortly drag him down, although with
                        the danger of civil disorders which has been cited at the outset of this
                        paper.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In summary, I feel that the U.S. cannot win with <persName corresp="#p_KHANH1"
                        >Khanh</persName> as Chief of State and that every possible action should be
                    taken to prevent his accession to power. Our main weapon available for this
                    purpose is the use of the message referred to in para 6 above. If we fail, the
                    consequences will be no more serious than if we had not tried. This matter will
                    be made the first item of business with <persName>Bundy</persName>. After a full
                    discussion, I will forward appropriate recommendations.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Taylor</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
