<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-04-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-04-23T14:45:00-05:00" n="93" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d93">
                        <head>93. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>)
                            to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d93fn1">Source: National Archives,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Vietnam
                                Subject Files, Box 130, <gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss>/PRES
                                Memos (<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>) Situation in Vietnam
                                (Apr 72). Secret; Sensitive. Sent for information. <persName corresp="#p_HAM1">Haig</persName> initialed for <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>. A stamped notation on
                                the memorandum indicates that the President saw it. All brackets are
                                in the original.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1972-04-24T23:59:59-05:00" notBefore="1972-04-23T19:45:00+00:00">undated</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_ACW1">Abrams</persName> Assessment of Current
                                Situation</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The following is a summary of General <persName corresp="#p_ACW1">Abrams</persName>’ personal assessment of the military situation in
                            Southeast Asia (Tab A).<note n="2" xml:id="d93fn2">Tab A, <persName corresp="#p_ACW1">Abrams</persName>’s personal assessment of the
                                situation in Vietnam as of April 24, is not attached but a copy is
                                in the <persName corresp="#p_ACW1">Abrams</persName> Papers,
                                Historical Resources Branch, U.S. Army Center of Military History.
                                On April 23, <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> directed
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ACW1">Abrams</persName> to prepare the
                                paper as soon as possible and an additional one by 0800 EST, April
                                26. <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>’s message is in the
                                National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 218, Records of
                                the Chairman, Records of <persName corresp="#p_MTH1">Thomas
                                    Moorer</persName>, Box 69, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                                Out, Eyes Only Messages (1 Jan–31 July 72). <persName corresp="#p_HAM1">Haig</persName> also sent the President a
                                memorandum on April 24 analyzing <persName corresp="#p_ACW1">Abrams</persName>’ paper. A note on that memorandum indicates
                                that the President saw it. (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Vietnam Subject Files, Box
                                130, <gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss>/PRES Memos (<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>) Situation in Vietnam (Apr
                                72))</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">General Current Situation</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The enemy has not taken the vital areas of Quang Tri Province. He has
                            been unable to open Route 547 and reach <gloss target="#t_Hue1">Hue</gloss>. He has not taken <gloss target="#t_Kontum1">Kontum</gloss> Province although the situation there is serious and
                            unresolved as of this moment. He has not taken An Loc and has suffered
                            heavy casualties in his attempts to do so. His objectives in the Delta
                            are less clear than in other areas and his achievements there to date
                            have not been of decisive proportions. One of the most significant
                            features of the current general situation is the absence of any
                            widespread uprising throughout the Republic by local force
                                guerrillas.<note n="3" xml:id="d93fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined “absence of
                                any widespread uprising throughout the Republic by local force
                                guerrillas.”</note> Overall the South Vietnamese have fought well
                            under extremely difficult circumstances.<note n="4" xml:id="d93fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined “South
                                Vietnamese have fought well under extremely difficult
                                circumstances.”</note> There has been a mixture of effective and
                            ineffective performance, as in any combat situation, but on the whole
                            the effective far outweighs the ineffective. Thus far the South
                            Vietnamese have prevented the enemy from achieving his major
                                objectives.<note n="5" xml:id="d93fn5">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined this
                                sentence.</note> U.S. and <gloss target="#t_VNAF1">VNAF</gloss> air
                            power in combination with determined resistance on the ground have been
                            one of the decisive elements in achieving the relatively favorable
                            situation that now exists.</p>
                        <pb facs="0352" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Military Region 1</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Enemy offensive has been stopped in Quang Tri Province, and <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> forces are slowly expanding their
                            defensive positions westward. Stubborn <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> defense of Fire Support Base Bastogne has prevented
                            the movement of enemy tanks, artillery, anti-aircraft and heavy
                            equipment over Route 547 for attacks on <gloss target="#t_Hue1">Hue</gloss>. Also enemy attempts to move eastward in the Quang Nam
                            and Quang Tin border area have been successfully blocked. Quang Nam
                            Province (in the southern part of <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–1)
                            has experienced harassing and terrorist attacks and pacification has
                            been set back, but no decisive actions have occurred in the province.
                            South Vietnamese leadership in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–1 is
                            outstanding, aggressive and competent.<note n="6" xml:id="d93fn6">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined this
                                sentence.</note> The enemy is still capable of launching a new
                            offensive with reinforcements from the 325th Division (which is still in
                            North Vietnam).</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Military Region 2</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>As of this date (April 24) the enemy has not launched the coordinated
                            all-out offensive in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–2 of which he is
                            capable. An attack which began against the 22nd <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> Division headquarters at Tan Canh this morning may be
                            such an offensive [Tan Canh has subsequently fallen to the enemy]. It is
                            too early to tell. Thus far the enemy has conducted heavy attacks
                            against individual <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> units and
                            positions, but these have been local rather than general. The presence
                            of the enemy on Rocket Ridge (now abandoned by friendly forces)
                            jeopardizes the security of Route 14 which is now interdicted in 3
                            places. The Joint General Staff has ordered <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> forces north of <gloss target="#t_Kontum1">Kontum</gloss> to redeploy to defensive positions immediately north
                            of <gloss target="#t_Kontum1">Kontum</gloss> City. This redeployment
                            will be greatly complicated by present enemy attacks in the area. The
                            situation in Binh Dinh Province continues to be difficult and Route 19,
                            the key line of communication to the Pleiku/<gloss target="#t_Kontum1">Kontum</gloss> area, is still interdicted in the An Khe Pass
                            area.</p>
                        <p>South Vietnamese military leadership in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–2 is neither strong nor aggressive. The 22nd and 23rd
                            Divisions in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–2 both have new
                            commanders. But the performance of the 22nd Division commander has been
                                inadequate.<note n="7" xml:id="d93fn7">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined most of this
                                paragraph.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Military Region 3</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The battle for An Loc has been costly for the enemy but he continues to
                            launch daily attacks. <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> forces in
                            the town have done an outstanding job. Their morale is high and they are
                            determined to hold the city. Enemy ground attacks and attacks by fire
                            against An Loc have <pb facs="0353" n="310" xml:id="pg_310"/> gradually
                            diminished in intensity since April 16. Enemy activity throughout the
                            remainder of <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–3 is low level and of
                            little significance. But the pressure on Dau Tieng has been increasing
                            in the last several days. The leadership in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–3 is steady and dependable but not aggressive.<note n="8" xml:id="d93fn8">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined most of this
                                sentence.</note> The outcome of the battle in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–3 should be in favor of the South Vietnamese.<note n="9" xml:id="d93fn9">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined this
                                sentence.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Military Region 4</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The overall situation in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–4 is more
                            difficult to assess than in the other regions. Enemy attacks have been
                            primarily widespread low level attacks against outposts, national
                            police, small <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> units, and
                            communications routes. The enemy main force effort is expected to
                            continue to concentrate on Chuong Thien Province and he has made
                            significant efforts to take over Kien Tuong Province. While the
                            situation in Kampong Trach (just over the border in Cambodia) continues
                            unchanged and the situation looks unfavorable, major elements of the 1st
                            North Vietnamese Division have been tied down and have taken heavy
                            casualties.</p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–4 has probably the most capable
                            regional commander but he has a large geographical area to control and
                            must reply primarily on RF and <gloss target="#t_PF1">PF</gloss>
                            units.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Laos</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The situation in Laos seems to have changed very little since the
                            beginning of the enemy offensive against South Vietnam.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Cambodia</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In Cambodia the enemy has increased pressure on the Mekong River convoys
                            and has interdicted Route 1.<note n="10" xml:id="d93fn10">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined “Mekong
                                River” and “interdicted Route 1.”</note> The opportunity exists for
                            the conduct of <gloss target="#t_FANK1">FANK</gloss> operations to
                            complicate the enemy situation in Vietnam, but to date no effective
                            action has been take; however, plans are being made for <gloss target="#t_FANK1">FANK</gloss> operations along Route 1.<note n="11" xml:id="d93fn11">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined “exists for
                                the conduct of <gloss target="#t_FANK1">FANK</gloss>” and “to
                                complicate” in this sentence.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Performance and Problems of Friendly Forces</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>South Vietnamese forces (<gloss target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss>) would
                            not have had sufficient mobility without U.S. airlift support. Their
                            logistics system has however functioned effectively in the current
                            situation. <list>
                                <item>—President <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> has
                                    provided sound guidance to the Joint General Staff and has made
                                    prompt decisions and timely visits to combat areas.</item>
                                <pb facs="0354" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"/>
                                <item>—The integration of air, armor, artillery and infantry
                                    elements has been outstanding.<note n="12" xml:id="d93fn12">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined this
                                        sentence.</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>—The Vietnamese Air Force (<gloss target="#t_VNAF1">VNAF</gloss>) has provided outstanding support for ground
                                    forces. <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> artillery is very
                                    good.</item>
                                <item>—There has been a minimum of command bickering and no known
                                    instances of high level commanders refusing to carry out their
                                    orders.</item>
                                <item>—U.S. air, naval, advisory and airlift<note n="13" xml:id="d93fn13">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined this
                                        phrase.</note> support has played a key, if not decisive,
                                    role thus far.</item>
                                <item>—Korean units have concentrated primarily on security
                                    operations in their fixed areas and work relatively
                                    independently of <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss>. They
                                    will have little impact on the outcome of the current situation
                                    because of their inflexibility and reluctance to become deeply
                                    involved in high threat areas.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Enemy Intentions</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The enemy has neither lost his resolve nor changed his aims and will
                            probably continue to initiate new actions through at least mid-May.<note n="14" xml:id="d93fn14">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined “his aims
                                and will probably continue to initiate new actions through at least
                                mid-May” in this sentence.</note> A maximum effort has still not
                            been attempted in the <gloss target="#t_B3Front1">B–3 Front</gloss>
                                (<gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–2).</p>
                        <p>A recent <gloss target="#t_COSVN1">COSVN</gloss> directive (51)
                            reportedly indicates that the enemy’s attack in Quang Tri Province was
                            designed to draw <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> reinforcements to
                            the north whereupon the enemy would then attack in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–3 in order to further reduce <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> reserves and launch <gloss target="#t_Sappers1">sapper</gloss> and rocket attacks against key
                            government installations in Saigon. Once these attacks had widely spread
                            the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> forces and reduced their
                            reserves, the enemy would then demand a ceasefire in place and attempt
                            to install a coalition government. The enemy is apparently attempting to
                            force the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> to accept a piece-meal
                            defeat or to withdraw to concentrated positions thus abandoning a
                            substantial percentage of the rural population and obviating
                            pacification success. (The enemy continues to heavily attack
                            pacification targets in all 4 military regions.)<note n="15" xml:id="d93fn15">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> underlined the last
                                three sentences of this paragraph.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>