<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1896-12-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1896-12-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Olney</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Eustis</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1896-12-10"><hi rend="italic">December 10,
                                    1896</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 795.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Our consul at Tamatave, Madagascar, has
                            transmitted to the Department in his No. 169, of October 19, 1896, a
                            copy of the following communication made to him by the French
                            resident-general in Madagascar, September 15, 1896: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Consul</hi>: Madagascar has become a
                                    French colony. A decree of the 9th of June organizes the
                                    judiciary. Foreign subjects will hereafter be amenable thereto.
                                    The <pb facs="0187" n="153" xml:id="pg_153"/> Government of the
                                    Republic has notified the Government of the United States of
                                    this disposition on the 28th of July.</p>
                                <p>I have therefore the honor to make known to you that, beginning
                                    with the 16th of October, our tribunals will exercise their
                                    functions over all your nationality, and from now on will
                                    entertain, on their part, all suits and actions.</p>
                                <p>Until October 16 the cases already inscribed upon the calendar of
                                    your consular court may be by it wound up, but after that date
                                    the consular courts can no longer take cognizance of new cases,
                                    nor further count on our cooperation to assure their working and
                                    execution of their sentences.</p>
                                <p>I seize this occasion to renew to you, etc.,</p>
                                <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Hippolyte Laroche.</hi></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>On May 4, 1896, the consul was instructed by cable, at the instance of
                            the French ambassador here, to “suspend until further instructed
                            exercise consular judicial functions in all cases where cooperation of
                            an established French court is available for disposition judicial cases
                            affecting American citizens.”</p>
                        <p>It appears from the consul’s reply, dated October 5, 1896, to the above
                            quoted note of the French resident-general, that the consul, acting
                            under the telegraphic instructions of May 4, had ceased temporarily the
                            exercise of his judicial functions, and had informed the French
                            resident-general that he would so suspend the exercise of judicial
                            powers in all districts where the cooperation of an established French
                            court was available for the disposition of judicial cases affecting
                            American citizens. The consul goes on further to say that in pursuance
                            of this instruction he had permitted no new case to be entered upon his
                            court calendar after receipt of that telegram. The Department is not
                            informed and can not draw from the consul’s dispatch a clear inference
                            as to whether he continued to exercise his judicial authority in winding
                            up the pending court business after the receipt of the telegram. In the
                            absence of competent French tribunals he might properly have done
                            so.</p>
                        <p>The establishment of French sovereignty and civil jurisdiction over the
                            Island of Madagascar puts an end to the extraterritorial rights of the
                            United States in that country, and to the judicial powers of our consul
                            dependent thereon. This changed condition is assumed to have gone into
                            effect on the 16th of October, when, according to the statement of the
                            French resident-general, the French courts were to have been opened for
                            business. It does not appear from the communications received from the
                            consul—nor from those received from the French Government—what
                            provision, if any, was made for the disposition of the cases and other
                            pending matters which the consul may have been unable to finally
                            adjudicate and dispose of before his judicial authority became extinct.
                            Did these unfinished matters abate ab initio, or has provision been made
                            for their transfer to the proper French tribunals for complete
                            adjudication?</p>
                        <p>It is hoped that the French Government has taken care that the lawful
                            rights of citizens of the United States shall not be lost or prejudiced
                            in the transition from extraterritorial to French jurisdiction. I am,
                            etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Olney.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>