<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1897-07-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1897-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="275" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d275">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Sherman</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Tower</persName></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department op State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1897-07-02"><hi rend="italic">July 2,
                                1897</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 719.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Further referring to Sir Julian
                            Pauncefote’s note of June 13 last, in which the information is contained
                            that the sloop <hi rend="italic">Wild Swan</hi> and the gunboat <hi rend="italic">Pheasant</hi> will be employed in Bering Sea on patrol
                            duties this season, I am constrained to express the deep regret of the
                            President at the obvious inadequacy of the proposed fleet. Five vessels
                            have been designated by the President for this purpose, and in view of
                            the area to be patrolled and of the number of sealing vessels which have
                            already engaged in and are preparing to fit out for sealing operations
                            this season, the President hopes that Her Majesty’s Government will
                            decide for the present season to add to the fleet of three vessels
                            employed last season rather than to reduce its numbers. The President
                            believes it to be impossible properly to execute the laws enacted to
                            enforce the Paris award unless a larger fleet be designated by Her
                            Majesty’s Government.</p>
                        <p>An early reply to this note will be appreciated, as the President fears
                            that the designation of two vessels only by Her Majesty’s Government
                            would be accepted by the sealers as evidence of an abandonment of the
                            patrol, which would render it necessary for him to detail a much larger
                            fleet of United States vessels for this season.</p>
                        <p>It is unnecessary in this connection to repeat what I have already stated
                            in my instruction to Mr. Hay, dated May 10, 1897, as to the inadequacy
                            of the British patrolling fleet during the past three years in which the
                            Paris award has been in operation.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John Sherman.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>