<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1897-12-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1897-12-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="46" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d46">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adee</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Conger</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1897-12-03"><hi rend="italic">December 3,
                                1897</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 82.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose copy of a dispatch from our
                            minister to the Argentine Republic, reporting that the Brazilian
                            consul-general at Buenos Aires declined to furnish the captain of the U.
                            S. bark <hi rend="italic">Antioch</hi> with a bill of health to enable
                            him to clear his vessel for Rio de Janeiro, unless he presented the
                            original of the ship’s articles to him for certification, and to be by
                            him affixed to the manifest.</p>
                        <p>As the ship’s articles were, in accordance with the laws and consular
                            regulations of the United States, deposited in the hands of our consular
                            officer at Buenos Aires, and could not be lawfully restored by him to
                            the captain until the latter had presented his manifests, bill of
                            health, duly certified by the Brazilian consular officer, and clearance
                            papers from the Argentine authorities, the captain offered to furnish
                            the Brazilian official with a certified copy of them. This he declined
                            to receive. To prevent detention of the ship, our minister advised the
                            captain and the vice-consul of the United States to present the original
                            to the consul-general, who attached the document, together with his
                            certificate as to its “genuineness,” to the ship’s manifest by a
                            card.</p>
                        <p>The ship’s articles or shipping articles are defined as containing all
                            the conditions of the contract with the crew as to service, pay, voyage,
                            and all other things, and, in accordance with paragraph 194 of the
                            United States Consular Regulations, must be produced by the master to
                            any consular officer of the United States, whenever the latter may think
                            it necessary to the discharge of his duty toward any seaman. They are
                            needed by the consular officer in the case of a dispute between the
                            master and seamen, and on many other occasions. The crew list, shipping
                            articles, and register constitute “the ship’s papers,” and are regarded
                            by international custom, sanctioned expressly or impliedly by most
                            modern commercial and consular treaties, as the national papers of the
                            ship, the originals of which should always be in the custody of the
                            master at sea, and in that of the consular officer of the nation in a
                            foreign port.</p>
                        <p>As above stated, the laws of the United States require, under a penalty
                            of $500, every master of a United States vessel which sails from a port
                            of the United States, on his arrival at a foreign port, to deposit his
                            register, his sea letter, and Mediterranean passport, if he has any,
                            with the consular officer of the United States at the port. Paragraph
                            175 of our Consular Regulations adds that— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>It is usual also to deposit with the consular officer the crew
                                    list and shipping articles; and these documents, together with
                                    the register, are generally described as the “ship’s
                                    papers.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Article XXXI of the treaty of 1828 between the United States and Brazil
                            (which was abrogated in 1841) indicates that the Brazilian laws, <pb facs="0077" n="43" xml:id="pg_43"/> like our own, contemplated that
                            the ship’s papers, as national papers of the vessels, must be in the
                            hands of either the master or the consul.</p>
                        <p>It provided that the consuls shall have power to require the assistance
                            of the national authorities for the arrest of deserters, “proving by an
                            exhibition of the registers of the vessel, or ship’s roll, or other
                            public documents that those men were part of said crews.” The ship’s
                            articles form a part of this evidence. In the case under consideration
                            they could not have been presented to the Argentine authorities by our
                            consular officer if they had been in the hands of a Brazilian
                            official.</p>
                        <p>Moreover, the strength of their evidence as “national” papers is impaired
                            when they bear a certification of their “genuineness” from the official
                            of a foreign nation.</p>
                        <p>In this connection it may be well for you to examine the laws of Brazil
                            in regard to ship’s papers. They are probably, as above indicated, very
                            similar to our own.</p>
                        <p>There has been at times an effort on the part of certain of the South
                            American Republics to require the master of a foreign vessel to deposit
                            the ship’s papers with the port authorities, instead of with the consul
                            of his nation. This contention has been uniformly resisted by the United
                            States, as well as by other governments, on the ground of its
                            inconvenience, its inconsistence with the spirit of international law
                            and with the express or implied stipulations of treaties. Colombia and
                            Venezuela both receded from their position. You will find the
                            correspondence with Colombia published in <ref target="frus1879">Foreign
                                Relations, 1879</ref> and <ref target="frus1880">1880</ref>; that
                            with Venezuela in <ref target="frus1882">Foreign Relations, 1882</ref>
                            and <ref target="frus1883">1883</ref>.</p>
                        <p>You will observe from Mr. Buchanan’s dispatch that the Government of
                            France is understood to have protested at Rio de Janeiro against the
                            practice of the Brazilian consul general at Buenos Aires.</p>
                        <p>The Department will be glad to have you present its views on this subject
                            to the Government of Brazil, pointing out the inconvenience, if not
                            impropriety, of the course pursued by its officer, which it trusts will
                            be abandoned.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Alvey A. Adee</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>