<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Barrett to Mr. Sherman.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1897</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d472</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">472</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1897-07-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1897-07-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1897-07-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1897-07-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="472"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d472">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Barrett</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Sherman</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bangkok</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1897-07-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 22, 1897</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 222.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that the Siamese
                    foreign minister and myself, after communication with Sir Nicholas J. Hannen,
                    and the Cheek estate, have postponed the date of arbitration in the Cheek case
                    to February 1, 1898. I trust that this date will be acceptable to the
                    Department, as it is to all others concerned.</p>
                <p>As can be seen by correspondence inclosed in my No. 221, of this date, the
                    postponement was readily arranged. The reasons for this step, founded on
                    conditions explained in my 216, and authorized in Department’s telegram of July
                    13, can be briefly summarized as follows:</p>
                <p>In consequence of the Department’s instructions, Mr. Kellett must remain here
                    until my return from Cheangmai. Supposing I am able to leave within the next ten
                    days, I shall not reach Cheangmai until approximately August 31.</p>
                <p>The work to be done at Cheangmai can hardly be accomplished in less than fifteen
                    days.</p>
                <p>Returning with all speed I may be able to get back by October 1, as one can come
                    down in about one-half the time required to go up.</p>
                <p>Supposing Mr. Kellett leaves for Cheangmai one week after my arrival, he will not
                    reach Cheangmai until about November 10.</p>
                <p>To get the evidence, which is apparently of greatest importance, he will require
                    nearly two months in and out of the forests, and could not leave Cheangmai until
                    well into January and hence not reach Bangkok until the last of January.</p>
                <p>The Siamese foreign minister agreed with me as to the necessity of this delay, as
                    otherwise the administrator (through Mr. Kellett) could not possibly make a
                    definite report on the administration of the Cheek estate during this year in
                    response to the Siamese Government’s demand that the administration of the
                    estate be included in the arbitration.</p>
                <p>We first asked Sir Nicholas J. Hannen to agree to a postponement until February
                    15, 1898, but as February 1 is his latest date we have agreed thereto.</p>
                <p>I would simply add that I should have started for Cheangmai long before this,
                    were it not for the characteristic slowness of the Siamese Government in
                    negotiating the Cheek protocol.</p>
                <p>I have the honor, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John Barrett</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Minister Resident.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
