<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adee to Mr. Dupuy de Lôme.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1897</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d573</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">573</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1897-11-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1897-11-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1897-11-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1897-11-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="573"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d573">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adee</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Dupuy de Lôme</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1897-11-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 1, 1897</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 303.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your note of the 26th ultimo, wherein you say with reference to the alleged
                    filibustering schooners <hi rend="italic">Donna T. Briggs</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Sommers N. Smith</hi>, that the consular officers and lawyers
                    of Spain have been directed to furnish the competent authorities with all the
                    data within their possession and to extend every possible assistance for the
                    prosecution of the violations of the neutrality and other laws of the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>Referring to Mr. Day’s note of October 22, 1897, I may remark that it was
                    intended to ascertain whether your Government actually possessed and could
                    furnish any information upon which judicial proceedings against the <hi
                        rend="italic">Donna T. Briggs</hi> could be based. The instructions to the
                    Spanish consular officers and lawyers employed by the Spanish Government suggest
                    that the holding of the vessel is expected in order <pb facs="0571" n="537"
                        xml:id="pg_537"/> to give those officers time to gather inculpating evidence
                    not now possessed by them upon which to base the prosecution.</p>
                <p>In the regular course, probable cause shown, by evidence which would of itself
                    justify the institution of proceedings, should precede detention of the supposed
                    offender. While under the law the President of the United States has the right
                    to detain a vessel until he is satisfied of the character and of the purpose of
                    its destination, yet it is not to be supposed that this permission gives him
                    arbitrary authority to detain such vessel indefinitely, and it was evidence of
                    this character that Mr. Day’s note of the 22d ultimo sought, in order that the
                    machinery of justice might be duly set in motion and the long detention of the
                    vessel on mere allegation and suspicion be justified. If evidence upon which to
                    institute suit be not forthcoming, the question of liability to her owners may
                    naturally arise.</p>
                <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Alvey A. Adee</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
