<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Under Secretary of State ( (Smith))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1061</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1061</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="1061"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1061">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, <gloss
                        target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 301</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the Under
                        Secretary of State</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SGWB1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Smith</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-16">July 16,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear <persName corresp="#p_SGWB1">General
                            Smith</persName>
                    </hi>: The following basic instructions, which have been approved by the
                    President, will guide you as head <pb facs="0462" n="1844" xml:id="pg_1844"/> of
                    the United States Delegation in your participation in the Indochina phase of the
                    Geneva Conference for which you are leaving today.<note n="1" xml:id="d1061fn1"
                        >Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGWB1">Smith</persName> departed for
                        Geneva on the afternoon of July 16.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>I append hereto as Annex A a Six Point France-United States Position
                        Paper, dated July 14, 1954.<note n="2" xml:id="d1061fn2">For text, see <ref
                                target="#pg_1830">p. 1830</ref>.</note> Attached thereto is a Seven
                        Point Memorandum setting out the terms which the French Government states it
                        believes are obtainable at Geneva by negotiation, and which would be
                        acceptable to France, and France believes, to Vietnam, Laos and
                            Cambodia.<note n="3" xml:id="d1061fn3">For text, see <ref
                                target="#pg_1831">p. 1831</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The United States recognizes that these four nations have a direct and
                        primary interest as belligerents which entitles them to negotiate a
                        settlement without any coercion or pressure from the United States. As
                        stated in the Position Paper, the United States will not seek “to impose its
                        views in any way upon those primarily interested”, i.e., France and Vietnam,
                        Laos and Cambodia.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Therefore, your role at the Conference will be that of the representative
                        of a nation friendly to the non-Communist states primarily interested, which
                        desires to assist, where desired, in arriving at a just settlement. You will
                        not, however, go beyond this role.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>If there is a cease-fire, armistice or political settlement which conforms
                        substantially to the seven points referred to in the annexed Position Paper,
                        and which is agreed to by the states primarily interested, you are
                        authorized to make a declaration of the attitude of the United States in the
                        form of the annexed declaration, marked Annex B. This will be a unilateral
                        declaration, unless certain of the non-Communist states desire to associate
                        themselves with it, in which case this is acceptable. The United States will
                        not, however, become cosignatory with the Communists in any
                        Declaration.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>You will note that the Position Paper states that if the terms of
                        settlement differ materially from those set out in the Seven Points, the
                        United States will not be asked or expected by France to respect those terms
                        and “it may publicly disassociate itself from such differing terms.”</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>In the event that you are in doubt as to whether the settlement conforms
                        substantially to, or differs materially from, the Seven Points referred to
                        in the Position Paper, you will seek instructions before either refusing to
                        make the declaration contemplated by the above paragraph numbered 4 or
                        publicly disassociating the United States as contemplated by the above
                        paragraph numbered 5. Of course, before taking any important action which
                        could have serious repercussions upon our international relations, you will
                        naturally communicate with me.</item>
                    <pb facs="0463" n="1845" xml:id="pg_1845"/>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>You will avoid participation in the negotiations in any way which would
                        imply, or give the Communists a plausible case for contending, that the
                        United States was so responsible for the result that it is in honor bound to
                        guarantee that result to the Communists. We apprehend that the Communists
                        might offer to make certain concessions if the United States would then
                        guarantee the settlement so far as they were concerned. You should, so far
                        as possible, avoid getting yourself into a position which would lend itself
                        to such a Communist maneuver. Accordingly, the non-Communist belligerents,
                        rather than the United States, should be the active negotiators, and such
                        ideas as we have should be put forward to the French or Vietnam, Laos and
                        Cambodia, as may be appropriate, and through them to the Conference if they
                        find it desirable to adopt such ideas as their own.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Also, since the United States is not prepared at the present time to give
                        any commitment that it will intervene in the war if the Geneva Conference
                        fails—the United States position in this respect is set out in President
                            <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s letter of June 16,
                        1954, to President <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Coty</persName>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d1061fn4">For the pertinent portion of the text of the
                            letter, see <ref target="#pg_1720">footnote 1, p. 1720</ref>.</note>—you
                        should avoid as far as possible exerting any pressures or giving advice to
                        the French of such a character that, if there is no cease-fire, the French
                        can plausibly contend that it is because of our advice to, or pressure upon,
                        them, and that therefore we are morally obligated to intervene at once in a
                        military way.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John Foster Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Annex A]</note>
                    <p>[Here follow the France-United States Position Paper of July 14, 1954, and
                        its attachment—the Memorandum of Points Referred to in Paragraph 2 of the
                        France-United States Position Paper.]</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Annex B]</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Draft Declaration by the Government of the United
                            States</hi>
                        <note n="5" xml:id="d1061fn5">The copy of this draft in the <persName
                                corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> papers at the <persName
                                corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library bears the
                            handwritten initials of President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                                >Eisenhower</persName> indicating approval.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-16">July 16,
                                1954</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Government of the United States being resolved to devote its efforts to
                        the strengthening of peace in accordance with principles and purposes of the
                        United Nations</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Takes note</hi> of the Agreements concluded at Geneva on
                        (date) ------ between the ------ military commands</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Declares</hi> with regard to aforesaid Agreement that <list>
                            <label>(i)</label>
                            <item>it will refrain from the threat or the use of force to disturb
                                them, <pb facs="0464" n="1846" xml:id="pg_1846"/> in accordance with
                                Art. 2(4) of the Charter of the United Nations dealing with the
                                obligation of Members to refrain in their international relations
                                from the threat or use of force; and</item>
                            <label>(ii)</label>
                            <item>it will seek that other states which are not members of the United
                                Nations shall similarly refrain from the use of force, in accordance
                                with the Art. 2(6) of the Charter of the United Nations dealing with
                                insuring that states which are not members of the United Nations
                                shall act in accordance with the principles of the Charter so far as
                                may be necessary for the maintenance of international peace and
                                security; and<note n="6" xml:id="d1061fn6">The following marginal
                                    notation appears opposite subparagraph two on the source text:
                                    “Deletion recommended by Secretary. <gloss target="#t_Tosec1"
                                        >Tosec</gloss> 560.” Telegram <gloss target="#t_Tosec1"
                                        >Tosec</gloss> 560 to Geneva, July 17, read as follows: “For
                                    Under Secretary from Secretary. Upon reflection and in view of
                                    reactions here, believe that Subparagraph 2 of US Declaration
                                    Annex B should, if at all possible, be eliminated as subject to
                                    misconstruction. Suggest you inform <persName corresp="#p_PH1"
                                        >Phleger</persName>.” (396.1 GE/7–1754) Regarding the
                                    declaration actually issued by the United States at Geneva on
                                    July 21, see editorial note, <ref target="#pg_1859">p.
                                        1859</ref>.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>(iii)</label>
                            <item>it would view any renewal of the aggression in violation of these
                                agreements with grave concern and as seriously threatening
                                international peace and security.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
