<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador at Saigon ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1074</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1074</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-21T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-21T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-21T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-21T08:00:00-05:00" n="1074"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1074">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/7–2154: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-21T21:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 21, 1954—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>305. Repeated information Paris 114, Hanoi 90. In South Vietnam Geneva
                        agreements,<note n="1" xml:id="d1074fn1">See editorial note, <ref
                            target="#d1073">
                            <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> anticipated with pessimism since inauguration <persName
                        corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes-France</persName>, have not evoked as yet violent
                    or marked reaction. With exception of always vocal intellectuals, reaction is
                    chiefly one of unhappy disapproval tempered by relief that fighting ended. The
                    demonstrations which have taken place in Saigon and elsewhere throughout Annam
                    and South Vietnam have been well-organized but without fervor. Protests against
                    participation in Geneva accords have seemed more for the record than as reaction
                    public opinion. Extent of tragedy to country perhaps not yet fully realized.</p>
                <p>As example, French officers training Vietnamese troops, which almost wholly
                    Cochin-Chinese, report little or no emotional reaction to news from Geneva.
                    Similar lack of reaction noted by members of various American missions in
                    Saigon. <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> Saigon representative returning
                    from Hue reports reaction there largely one of intense relief that line
                    established to the north.</p>
                <p>The announcement by Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>
                    and Chief of Staff Vietnamese Army <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>,
                    although deploring partition, counsel calm and preparation of free Vietnam
                    reunite country. Former, in appeal to Vietnamese people, states “in spite of our
                    pain, in spite of our revulsion, we must remain calm and united to hold out our
                    arms to our refugee brothers … while preparing ourselves without delay for the
                    peaceful and difficult struggle which must finally liberate our country from all
                    foreign direction, no matter what it may be, and from all opposition”. Flags on
                    all Vietnamese official buildings half-masted July 22.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> has informed <persName
                        corresp="#p_ODLGJW1">General O’Daniel</persName> he would abide by
                    agreements reached. His public announcement reflects that decision.</p>
                <p>Many intellectuals continue their same line of argument that unless French
                    honestly willing give up control and leave country to Vietnamese <pb facs="0480"
                        n="1862" xml:id="pg_1862"/> there will be no possibility prevent Communists
                    from taking over control country through elections or force. Many argue that
                    with departure of French, non-Communist Viet Minh leaders would not hesitate to
                    join <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> government.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, although Saigon thus far completely calm, French officials remain
                    apprehensive, demonstrations being carefully controlled and evening curfew being
                    imposed on all French military personnel. French military being advised not to
                    appear in public singly and to avoid crowded places.</p>
                <p>Reaction of skepticism regarding appeal of “free” Vietnam to Tonkinese reflected
                    in apprehension expressed by <persName>Pham Huu Chuong</persName>, Minister
                    Health and Social Action, who informed Acting Director <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                        >USOM</gloss>, Saigon, that he beginning to fear that large number of
                    anticipated refugees (some 700,000 according to Minister’s calculations) will
                    not evacuate in belief they might be leaving north to migrate to area which
                    would not offer greater opportunity and which ultimately destined to fall to
                    Viet Minh control.</p>
                <p>We anticipate situation will steadily rankle in Vietnamese opinion and
                    progressively embitter attitude towards French unless latter accomplish a
                    remarkable diplomatic effort and effective aid program.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
