<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-30T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-30T02:00:00-05:00" n="1098" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1098">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/7–3054: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Heath</hi></persName>)
                            <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-30T15:00:00+08:00">July 30, 1954—3
                            p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6:49 a.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>405. Repeated information Paris 146, Hanoi unnumbered. In further comment
                            (<gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 380 [<hi rend="italic">404</hi>]<note n="1" xml:id="d1098fn1"><ref target="#d1097"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note>) on <persName corresp="#p_LCG1">La Chambre</persName>’s statements reported Paris
                        telegram 366 to Department,<note n="2" xml:id="d1098fn2">Dated July 27, <ref target="#pg_1879">p. 1879</ref>.</note> I would say: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>I thoroughly agree that in our own security interest we should
                                increase substantially our economic assistance to remaining Vietnam,
                                    <pb facs="0511" n="1893" xml:id="pg_1893"/> with view to
                                building up strong government there but not necessarily with idea of
                                winning nation wide elections, which in our view probably will not
                                take place. There should be of course free elections in South
                                Vietnam and I am fairly confident that present government or good
                                successor one could win them, given time and opportunity to prepare
                                proper conditions, and would be willing to have them staged under UN
                                supervision. It is certain that Viet Minh will never allow truly
                                free elections in North Vietnam; in fact armistice provides that
                                they should be supervised by international supervisory commission,
                                one of whose three members is a Communist state, another India,
                                which on record to date has shown no desire to offend Communist
                                China, of which Viet Minh are satellite. Truly free elections in
                                North Vietnam would require not only neutral international
                                supervision of actual voting but absolute freedom of non-Communist
                                parties to campaign for months preceding elections without restraint
                                or surveillance by Communist authorities. Last will never
                                happen.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>It is difficult for me to accept as entirely candid <persName corresp="#p_LCG1">La Chambre</persName>’s statement that French
                                Government entertained some fears that going through with signature
                                and ratification of treaties initialled last spring would give
                                impression of creating permanent division of country. Not to sign
                                treaties would appear to Vietnam Government, and rightly, as due to
                                French fear of offending Viet Minh and preventing some possible
                                arrangement with latter. Failure to sign would likewise confirm
                                Vietnamese fears that French have never intended other than to “hold
                                them on a leash”.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>I am disturbed in <persName corresp="#p_LCG1">La
                                    Chambre</persName>’s intimations that he does not think
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> suitable to continue
                                as Prime Minister, since latter’s support was mainly in north and he
                                did not “get along” with three sects in south. I think that
                                statement reflects hopes and possibly plans of former colonial
                                administrators in Ministry of Associated States who would like to
                                set up a government that would be not only friendly to France but
                                would accept French influence. It is possible that using French
                                influence on “sects” in South Vietnam, on Vietnam national army as
                                long as it is under command of General <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>, and promoting political schemes of <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Tam</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TVH1">Huu</persName>, and other former Prime Ministers, would result
                                in forcing <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> Government
                                out of office and replacing it with a pliant successor regime. But
                                that such a regime could be made solid in relatively little time at
                                its disposal is extremely unlikely. It would not enjoy confidence of
                                masses and although latter might be able to do nothing about it they
                                would be more than ever susceptible to Viet Minh subversion.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HDR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>