<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Acting Special Assistant for Intelligence ( (Howe) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1121</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1121</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rechWxPReovs7qx7u" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Urban</term>
                    <term ref="recHrSmzhfG78SwqX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="1121"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1121">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/8–1054</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Special Assistant for
                        Intelligence</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Howe</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-08-10">August 10,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Intelligence Note: The Present Situation in South Vietnam</item>
                </list>
                <p>The situation in South Vietnam is characterized by widespread disillusionment
                    over the terms of the Geneva agreements, a dangerous vacuum of political
                    leadership, and uncertainty with respect to French and other Western intentions.
                    There is general realization throughout South Vietnam of the preponderant
                    strength, both military and political, of the Viet Minh regime, and of the
                    determination of that regime to achieve control of all Vietnam.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Military Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>For the moment at least, French and Vietnamese forces in South Vietnam now have
                    the capability of maintaining internal security. If French Union forces from the
                    north are evacuated to South Vietnam, this capability would be increased. It
                    should be noted, however, that superiority in forces and fire-power provides no
                    guarantee of security. If, as anticipated, the Viet Minh engages in intensive
                    political warfare in South Vietnam, including the use of irregulars in
                    paramilitary activities, the present Franco–Vietnamese capability to maintain
                    internal security could rapidly disappear.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Political Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The partition, which has awarded 14 of Vietnam’s 25 million people to the
                    Communists, has sapped whatever political vitality South Vietnam may have had.
                    Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s government appears
                    temporarily to retain the passive support of his more important nationalist
                    constituents. However, intrigue and opportunism continue to divide Vietnamese
                    politicians and present indications are that certain Cochin-chinese elements,
                    allegedly with French support, are seeking the overthrow of <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s government. Viet Minh political
                    activities aimed at discrediting the non-Communist nationalists are already
                    openly in <pb facs="0553" n="1935" xml:id="pg_1935"/> evidence in both urban and
                    rural areas in South Vietnam. The sentiment for “unification”, even at the
                    expense of Communist domination, appears to be growing.</p>
                <p>A similar memorandum has been sent to the Under Secretary.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Fisher Howe</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
