<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="1181" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1181">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> files</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Special National Intelligence Estimate</hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi><lb/><gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> 63–6–54</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-15">15 September 1954</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Current Trends in South Vietnam</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d1181fn1"><p>According to a note on the cover sheet, this
                                estimate was “Submitted by the Director of Central Intelligence. The
                                following intelligence organizations participated in the preparation
                                of this estimate: The Central Intelligence Agency and the
                                intelligence organizations of the Departments of State, the Army,
                                the Navy, the Air Force, and The Joint Staff.</p>
                            <p>“Concurred in by the Intelligence Advisory Committee on 15 September
                                1954. Concurring were the Special Assistant, Intelligence,
                                Department of State; the Assistant Chief of Staff, <gloss target="#t_G2">G–2</gloss>, Department of the Army; the Director
                                of Naval Intelligence; the Director of Intelligence, <gloss target="#t_USAF1">USAF</gloss>; the Deputy Director for
                                Intelligence, The Joint Staff. The Atomic Energy Commission
                                Representative to the <gloss target="#t_IAC1">IAC</gloss> and the
                                Assistant to the Director, Federal Bureau of Investigation,
                                abstained, the subject being outside of their jurisdiction.”</p>
                            <p>The source text is accompanied by a memorandum of Sept. 17 from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_AWP1">W. Park Armstrong</persName>,
                                Special Assistant for Intelligence, to the Acting Secretary of
                                State, which read as follows: “The attached special estimate was
                                undertaken following discussion of the subject at the <gloss target="#t_IAC1">IAC</gloss> on September 14. The DCI desired to
                                have a brief, coordinated paper for delivery to the President and
                                other members of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>.”</p></note></p>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Estimate</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Since assuming office Premier <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> has been confronted with the usual problems of
                            inefficiency, disunity, and corruption in Vietnamese <pb facs="0647" n="2029" xml:id="pg_2029"/> politics and with the extraordinary
                            problems of a mass evacuation of the Northern population and the
                            hostility of many French officials. Despite his qualities of honesty and
                            zeal, he has not yet demonstrated the necessary ability to deal with
                            practical problems of politics and administration. Lacking an organized
                            political machine and finding control of the Army in the hands of an
                            uncooperative chief of staff, <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s freedom of action has been severely
                            circumscribed.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The French Government appears to have no definite policy toward South
                            Vietnam. While the French Government has not openly opposed the
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> Government, France has
                            failed to support <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> and there
                            is no evidence that the French are prepared to carry out a policy based
                            on unreserved support for Vietnamese independence and nationalism.
                            Accordingly, close cooperation between the French and Vietnamese
                            governments, essential for the survival of South Vietnam, has been
                            lacking and French motives have become more suspect.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Although little real progress has been made under <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s administration in dealing with
                            pressing political, military, and social problems, he still retains
                            considerable unorganized popular support, particularly among Catholic
                            elements of South Vietnam. He has also made some progress in reaching
                            agreement with the powerful Cochin China sects.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>At the moment the <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>
                            Government is threatened by the insubordination of General <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>, the politically ambitious Chief
                            of Staff whom <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> has
                            discharged. It does not now appear that the present struggle between
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> will degenerate into civil strife.
                            In fact <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> now appears to be
                            making some headway in his efforts to control or exile <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>, either of which would enhance his
                            prestige and remove an obstacle to the strengthening of his
                            government.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> has remained in France
                            and apparently is refraining from direct participation in political
                            affairs in South Vietnam. His prestige among Vietnamese nationalists has
                            been considerably lessened by his apathy toward the fate of his country.
                            We believe that if <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> were
                            now to return to Vietnam, he would almost certainly become a center of
                            political intrigue and would further complicate an already complex and
                            confused situation and weaken rather than strengthen the ability of
                            South Vietnam to achieve political stability.</item>
                        <pb facs="0648" n="2030" xml:id="pg_2030"/>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Trends in South Vietnam since the end of the Geneva Conference have
                            enhanced the prospects of an eventual extension of Communist control
                            over the area by means short of large-scale military attacks. Although
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s government will
                            probably survive the present crisis of <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>’s insubordination, and may achieve greater strength
                            and popular support, it will continue to be threatened by Vietminh
                            activity, and hampered by French indecision. <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> appears to be the only figure now on the political
                            scene behind whom genuine nationalist support can be mobilized. However,
                            his ability to create a government that could reverse the current trend
                            in South Vietnam depends at a minimum on an early and convincing
                            demonstration by the French of their wholehearted support.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>