<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Vietnam ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1246</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1246</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-10-10T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-10-10T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007242"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Defense budget</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-10-10T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-10-10T02:00:00-05:00" n="1246"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1246">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G./10–1054: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Vietnam</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-10-10T15:00:00+08:00"
                            >October 10, 1954—3 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1397. Repeated information Paris 469. Embassy telegram 1387, October 9. General
                        <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> came to see me last evening at
                    my request. He was ill at ease, undoubtedly because his conscience is in same
                    condition. He tried, however, to carry it off with a jaunty manner.</p>
                <p>He took initiative in discussion and asked me what I thought of government and
                    whether <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> was going to reform it. I
                    told him I thought it far from ideal, but since as matter of practical necessity
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> had had to give certain cabinet
                    posts to Cao Daists and Hoa Haos, whose candidates were not impressive, I
                    understood <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> would negotiate with
                        <persName corresp="#p_LVV1">Vien</persName> and General
                        <persName>Xuan</persName> and would offer them posts. I said both the latter
                    would doubtless ask greater representation than <pb facs="0747" n="2129"
                        xml:id="pg_2129"/> they probably were entitled to, but neither could at this
                    time expect to have vital positions in government. <persName>Xuan</persName> had
                    entered government first accepting post and then resigning forthwith, afterwards
                    applying again for vice presidency, all this accompanied by critical public
                    statements against government. <persName corresp="#p_LVV1">Le Vien</persName>
                    had undoubtedly many good qualities but he would have to dissociate himself from
                    gambling monopoly and other unpleasant interests before he could occupy greater
                    position in public life. I added I understood he was willing to get rid of these
                    connections. As for Army’s demands, I told him that <persName corresp="#p_BD1"
                        >Bao Dai</persName> had made unmistakably clear to me that his telegram did
                    not contemplate Army as such participating in civil government and that was very
                    decidedly our view. <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> protested that
                    that was also his view, but with paucity of people in Vietnam, President should
                    use his officers as Secretaries of State in Ministries of Defense and Youth. He
                    had particularly brilliant candidate for Youth Ministry. I said certainly there
                    would be no harm in suggesting to President that he use such officer but I did
                    not believe Army should have Secretary of State in Defense unless it were
                    impossible to find suitable civilian candidate. It was very important to
                    maintain separation of civil and military. I went on to say while government was
                    far from ideal, with <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> and other good
                    men in civil branch and with <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> in
                    military, government could successfully attack tremendous problems facing it. I
                    said General <persName corresp="#p_ODLGJW1">O’Daniel</persName> and myself
                    thought Army should take lead in work of pacification. <persName
                        corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> said he had offered plan of pacification
                    to government but no attention had been paid to it.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> I do not believe he has prepared any detailed
                    plan).</p>
                <p>He said he would be glad to show it to me and I said we would be glad to see it,
                    and insofar as possible, would detail some <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>
                    officers to help him on it if he wished, and if funds were a problem, would
                    consider giving aid.</p>
                <p>I reminded <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>, giving him figures, that
                    bulk of Vietnamese defense budget was defrayed by US. Hitherto this passed
                    through French, but we would probably shortly negotiate new arrangement for
                    direct aid. Very likely amounts previously given would be reduced, but there
                    would still be enough to maintain adequate army. I went on to say that in more
                    than four years here I had never interfered in internal political matters and
                    would not call my activities for past few weeks intervention, but with the deep
                    political divisions and unrest which had increased in last few weeks, it had
                    been necessary for US and France to mediate. This internal strife must come to
                    end now if Vietnam were to survive. I felt he could be sure <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> would treat Army properly and French and
                    US would certainly use their friendly influence to see Army is not hindered in
                    its task. He could be sure of our <pb facs="0748" n="2130" xml:id="pg_2130"/>
                    support if Army did its own job and stayed out of politics. <persName
                        corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> said he had no desire to get into politics
                    and if government got on with work and reorganization, he would be glad to take
                    a vacation in France. I replied there was no question of his taking vacation at
                    this time. He had job to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> then indulged in some criticism of
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> to which I replied that
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> had his faults as everyone had,
                    but it should be very obvious to <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>
                    that there was no capable successor in sight at this moment. <persName
                        corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> did not dispute that. He then criticized
                    General <persName>Phuong</persName> of the Cao Dais and General
                        <persName>Soai</persName> of Hoa Haos as being dishonest, untrustworthy and
                    incapable, and said <persName corresp="#p_LVV1">Le Vien</persName>, in spite of
                    his reputation, was man of his word and of ability. I remarked I would not
                    dispute any of those statements, but could hardly expect <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>, after painfully forming a new government,
                    to throw out the Cao Dais and Hoa Haos at this moment.</p>
                <p>Our talk closed with <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>’s saying he and
                    his friends would observe <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> for
                    another forty-eight hours, but if <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>
                    failed to comply with <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>’s request to
                    enlarge his government, Army would have to act. <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                        >Hinh</persName> said in effect he had supported government because Army had
                    power to turn it out of office. He had resisted great pressure of many interests
                    who were urging the Army to overthrow government, and unless government really
                    got to work, Army could not stand by. I said I had no doubt government would
                    tackle its problems now, but that any <hi rend="italic">coup de force</hi> by
                    Army would be fatal to future of Army of Vietnam. It would be disastrous for
                        <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> personally.</p>
                <p>Foregoing is a fairly complete account of our conversation. I omitted number of
                    wild and I would say childish statements by <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                        >Hinh</persName>. After this talk I am more than ever convinced he must be
                    gotten out of picture. Unfortunately this cannot happen now. I believe talk may
                    have postponed, but not avoided <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>’s
                    revolutionary intentions.<note n="1" xml:id="d1246fn1">
                        <p>In telegram 1401 from Saigon, Oct. 10, <persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                                >Heath</persName> further reported that <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                                >Hinh</persName>’s agents had abducted an officer of <persName
                                corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s palace guard and that Vietnamese
                            Army armored cars had circled the palace grounds, menacing the guard
                            force. <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName> informed General
                                <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> of these developments.
                                <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> urged that the Binh Xuyen
                            be given the Interior Ministry, but <persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                                >Heath</persName> replied that the time had come to stand firm
                            against threats. <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> must be
                            provided with a program for restoring internal security, a program which
                            had to be forced upon all concerned, including <persName
                                corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>. (751G.00/10–1054)</p>
                        <p>The Department replied immediately. Telegram 1485 to Saigon, Oct. 10,
                            read as follows: “Concur lines your approach. Clear that resolution
                            political conflict and prevention any overthrow of <persName
                                corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> by force will depend a lot on
                            ability and intention <persName corresp="#p_LCG1">La Chambre</persName>
                            with <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName>, despite difficulties,
                            take decisive and conclusive measures in line Washington understandings
                            and instructions re supporting broadened <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                                >Diem</persName> government and preventing <persName
                                corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> extend his control over civil
                            government. Coincidence any coup d’état with <persName corresp="#p_LCG1"
                                >La Chambre</persName> visit could hardly escape provoking
                            unfavorable reaction various quarters.” (751G.00/10–1054)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
