<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Vietnam ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1313</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1313</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-11-10T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-11-10T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-10T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-10T06:00:00-05:00" n="1313"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1313">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">120.251G/11–1054: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Vietnam</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d1313fn1">This telegram was transmitted in two parts.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-11-10T19:00:00+08:00"
                            >November 10, 1954—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1794. Repeated information Paris 595. Department pass Defense. From <persName
                        corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>. I had two-hour conversation with
                        <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> yesterday at Dalat. In cordial
                    atmosphere and with what I believe to have been considerable frankness we
                    reviewed major problems facing us here, discussed in general terms provisions of
                    President’s directive to me, and reached preliminary agreement with respect to
                    fairly wide range of issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> did not conceal that his first
                    reaction to my assignment had been adverse. He said that he had feared Viet Minh
                    would seize upon it as pretext for agitation which might build up dangerously.
                    However, there had been no such development, nor had he noted any untoward
                    reaction among population of Free Vietnam. During conversation I took occasion
                    to impress upon him that my mission here is diplomatic and in no sense narrowly
                    military. Summary of principal points I made and <persName corresp="#p_EGP1"
                        >Ely</persName>’s responses follow.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>I said my directive called for development and adoption of measures to
                            foster friendly, non-Communist government in Vietnam, and in particular
                            to support <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>. <persName
                                corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> replied that he had backed
                                <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> and would continue to do
                            so, but that he feared this was a losing game. At present time there is
                            no government in Vietnam. Basic problem to be resolved is <persName
                                corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                                >Diem</persName> feud. <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName>
                            thinks that at this stage <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> is
                            more to blame than <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> for
                            persistence of quarrel. Until some <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>
                            is worked out between the two, government will remain paralyzed.</p>
                        <p>When I asked what alternatives <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName>
                            might envisage, he answered that one possibility was to attempt to build
                            up around strong Interior Minister an internal structure capable of
                            buttressing the weakened state. He hesitated to mention the name he had
                            in mind because the man was so ill-considered by Americans: <persName
                                corresp="#p_NVT1">Nguyen Van Tam</persName>. Without entering into
                            any commitment so far as <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Tam</persName> was
                            concerned, I said that the American policy is to support <persName
                                corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>, we are not bound to any
                            particular Cabinet list and would certainly wish urge <persName
                                corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> to gather about him as competent a
                            group of Ministers as possible. <persName corresp="#p_EGP1"
                                >Ely</persName> expressed gratification at this statement and
                            indicated that he could support <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                                >Diem</persName> with more confidence and enthusiasm if we were
                            prepared to bring pressure to bear in this direction.</p>
                        <p>I suggested both respect to <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                                >Hinh</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> dispute
                            and to improvement of <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>’s
                            Cabinet that I take initiative in suggesting remedial measures to
                            parties concerned. Prime Minister, for example, must of necessity <pb
                                facs="0851" n="2233" xml:id="pg_2233"/> be anti-French to a degree
                            and must resist French pressures, therefore he might be more responsive
                            to suggestions of a newlyarrived American. I would of course keep
                                <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> informed. <persName
                                corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> agreed.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> brought up <persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>’s name later in conversation,
                            saying that <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> had asked him
                            some time ago whether he should return to Vietnam. <persName
                                corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> advised against <persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> returning, saying that Chief of
                            State was most unpopular figure in Vietnam. However, Vietnam is now
                            independent, and what would we do if <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                                Dai</persName> suddenly appeared unannounced? I suggested that this
                            might be one alternative to the <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                                >Diem</persName> government which would be legally admissible if
                                <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> were able to take over
                            active direction of government. I asked whether <persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> would now be more acceptable to
                            the people than at time <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName>
                            advised against his return. <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName>
                            said that state of lassitude among population now is such that <persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> might find acceptance. In reply
                            to my question whether <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> had
                            courage enough to return and ability take over government, <persName
                                corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> answered that <persName
                                corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> had enough physical courage to
                            confront danger, but probably not enough courage to undertake tasks
                            incident to heading government.</p>
                        <p>Under this heading, <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> expressed
                            regret that my directive called so explicitly for support of <persName
                                corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>. He had hoped that we might
                            consider problem together and have greater liberty consider different
                            course of action. I answered that we felt still more could be done to
                            support <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> and that he must be
                            given every possible chance to succeed. If every resource is exhausted
                            and <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> still is unsuccessful,
                            we can take further counsel at that point.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> that we were thinking
                            in terms of support for a national army capable of assuring internal
                            security, but not of meeting large-scale external aggression. We believe
                            protection against such aggression should be afforded by the Manila
                            Pact. In this connection, I said, we felt that an <gloss
                                target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> of 100,000 on January 1, 1956, appeared
                            too large and that Congress would probably be unwilling to furnish
                            substantial support to a force of such size.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> stated that French policy,
                            adopted in consultation and accord with the US, was to maintain <gloss
                                target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> here until national army can protect
                            Free Vietnam against Viet Minh. He said we know that Viet Minh in north
                            are building up military strength and believe that they would be
                            prepared use this force against the south. If Franco-US policy to
                            protect Free Vietnam against this danger is altered, French stand ready
                            to withdraw <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> tomorrow. Plans to build
                            up stable and viable non-Communist state, however, are meaningless
                            unless Viet Minh are prevented by presence of effective military force
                            from taking action against Free Vietnam before it is prepared to defend
                            self. Viet Minh will not be intimidated by threat to invoke terms of
                            Manila Pact. To be effective, any protection afforded Vietnam in this
                            manner would <pb facs="0852" n="2234" xml:id="pg_2234"/> have to be
                            subject of detailed specific treaty arrangement within framework of
                            Manila Pact. I stated it would be difficult to secure any such
                            arrangement. Moreover, <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> added,
                            from French viewpoint, maintenance of sizeable <gloss target="#t_FEC1"
                                >FEC</gloss> is necessary for protection of 60,000 French nationals.
                                <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> insisted that this
                            question of maintaining adequate defenses in free Vietnam is the pivotal
                            point in formulating long-range policy for the area and must be subject
                            of further consultation between us.</p>
                        <p>With reference to Vietnamese National Army, <persName corresp="#p_EGP1"
                                >Ely</persName> said that he strongly opposed its being weakened by
                            existence of independent and often rival armed forces. He agreed that
                            army must be subordinate and loyal to the legal government but not
                            threatened by other forces within its own territory.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> that our policy was, as
                            he knew, to provide aid directly to the three Associated States. While
                            we are anxious to coordinate our efforts with French, we must have full
                            authority and responsibility for distribution of American aid;
                            tripartite bodies could serve for full exchange of information but could
                            not have executive power. As part of this direct aid, we wish to have
                            training responsibility for National Army.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> replied that he had long ago
                            invited <persName corresp="#p_ODLGJW1">General O’Daniel</persName> to
                            bring in as many as 500 or even 800 training personnel “to operate under
                            the Commander in Chief”. Our problem now, he said, is to develop an
                            American training program which will not provoke Viet Minh reaction or
                            charges that it is in violation of the armistice agreement. Such a
                            program, however, must be effective within imposed limitations and “take
                            account of my authority”. I reiterated that while we would be willing to
                            direct training in accord with broad agreed policies, we should have to
                            have full authority to execute program.</p>
                        <p>I mentioned to <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> that I had been
                            informed many staff sections in Vietnamese National Army were headed by
                            French officers. I suggested he give consideration to replacing
                            progressively such French officers by Vietnamese, the French withdrawing
                            to positions as advisors to their Vietnamese counterparts.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> agreed to do this; details to
                            be worked out later.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I told <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> that the fourth major
                        point of my directive was to foster relations between Vietnam and its
                        neighbors in Southeast Asia. I told him briefly of my conversation with
                        President <persName>Magsaysay</persName> in Manila and said that the
                        Philippines stand ready to help in training Vietnamese to meet problems
                        which in many respects are similar to those confronted and overcome by the
                        Filipinos. In resettlement, for example, the Filipinos have had an
                        experience which might usefully be shared with Vietnamese authorities
                        responsible for relocating refugees from Communist rule in the north.
                            <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> appeared receptive to this
                        idea but made no particular comment.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0853" n="2235" xml:id="pg_2235"/>
                <p>Concluding conversations, I said that I had been delegated broad powers and hoped
                    that <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> might have similar authority so
                    that we might make joint decisions promptly and without having to refer every
                    detail to our respective governments. <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName>
                    replied that within the limits of French policy in Indochina, which he helped
                    formulate, he had great latitude and felt that he needed no further delegation
                    of authority.</p>
                <p>As an initial exchange of views I believe conversation with <persName
                        corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> was satisfactory. Of course much remains to
                    be done if we are to work out mutually acceptable formulas for support of
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> Government and for military
                    defense of free Vietnam’s territory.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
