<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-15T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-15T13:00:00-05:00" n="1319" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1319">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/11–1554: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DCD1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dillon</hi></persName>)
                            <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d1319fn1">This telegram was
                            transmitted in two parts.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-11-15T19:00:00+01:00">November 15, 1954—7
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>2080. Repeated information Saigon 298 London Moscow unnumbered. Limited
                        distribution. Probable course French action with respect Vietnam (re <gloss target="#t_Embdesp1">EmbDesp</gloss> 282).<note n="2" xml:id="d1319fn2">Not printed.</note></p>
                    <list>
                        <label>I.</label>
                        <item><p><hi rend="italic">General</hi>. It is becoming increasingly evident
                                that a fundamental divergence between French and U.S. approach to
                                Vietnamese problem exists and may be accentuated in coming months.
                                Franco-American differences over <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> government are more fundamental than simply a
                                divergence over how best to increase effectiveness of Vietnamese
                                government. Complexity and pace with which internal Vietnamese
                                political situation has evolved since Geneva has tended to obscure
                                this fact. We feel it essential, therefore, that what appears to be
                                probable future course of French action with respect to Vietnam be
                                recognized now for what it is—and not as what we might hope it would
                                be—in order that it may be taken into account in determination of
                                future phases of U.S. policy with respect to Vietnam and not,
                                through misunderstanding, become basis for future charges of bad
                                faith and recrimination. Pattern of forces taking shape in France in
                                this regard appears to be similar in its broad outline to pre-Geneva
                                pattern and dilemma confronting U.S. at that time may be posed
                                again.</p>
                            <p>Furthermore, we think French approach to Vietnam problem will
                                increasingly tend to reflect broad lines of French approach to
                                overall problem of East-West relations and degree of success
                                encountered on either plane may be expected to have its impact on,
                                and give impetus to, its approach on other.</p></item>
                        <label>II.</label>
                        <item><p><hi rend="italic">Probable course French action Vietnam</hi>. We
                                believe that <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes</persName>, his
                                entourage, his government are, for most part, favorably disposed to
                                explore and consider a policy looking toward an eventual peaceful
                                North-South <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi> in Vietnam.
                                However, this probable course of French action has a broader base
                                and deeper roots than <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes</persName>
                                and his entourage. At risk of oversimplification, we think French
                                tend to feel there are only two possible realistic solutions to
                                Vietnamese problem: An eventual peaceful North-South <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi> on terms likely to be favorable
                                to Vietminh—since Vietminh as military victor unlikely accept
                                anything less—as opposed to an ultimate military show-down with
                                Vietminh and Communist bloc in an effort to prevent reunification
                                taking place on terms favorable Vietminh in line policy to retain
                                South Vietnam as free world bastion. In light of what we have
                                learned in France in recent past, it would <pb facs="0865" n="2247" xml:id="pg_2247"/> appear unrealistic to expect France to adopt
                                latter course. While much is said regarding necessity of developing
                                sufficient strength in South Vietnam in order to attract a majority
                                of Vietnamese voters in the July 1956 nationwide elections, there
                                appears to be a lack of conviction, particularly on part of those in
                                France most familiar with Vietnamese scene, that this represents
                                anything more than a pious hope. We think that it must be recognized
                                that the present French Government, and we think generally,
                                anticipate and expect nationwide elections to take place in Vietnam
                                in 1956 and that they would consider a policy designed to reject
                                them a violation of spirit of Geneva agreement which they are not
                                prepared to accept. We think as well that French prepared to go
                                along with results of such general elections however academic that
                                exercise may eventually prove to be. French would expect to be
                                supported by India and probably U.K. in this respect.<note n="3" xml:id="d1319fn3"><p>Telegram 2498 from London, Nov. 24,
                                        commenting on Paris telegram 2080, read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                            <p>“Embassy concurs view expressed reference telegram UK
                                                would, under present circumstances at any rate, be
                                                unprepared accept policy designed to reject
                                                nationwide elections in Vietnam in 1956 as violation
                                                of letter and spirit of Geneva Agreement. UK takes
                                                position it entered into agreement in good faith and
                                                in absence compelling reasons to contrary it has no
                                                recourse but to support agreement. To do otherwise
                                                would stultify Western position regarding elections
                                                in Germany and Korea. Even though UKG might be
                                                willing consider contrary course it would be faced
                                                with severe criticism from imposition and tremendous
                                                pressure from India. If, however, there were
                                                flagrant Communist violation of terms of agreement
                                                demonstrable to other signatories, especially India,
                                                UK would doubtless be willing review its position,
                                                and perhaps support move postpone elections
                                                indefinitely.”
                                    (751G.00/11–2454)</p></quote></p></note></p>
                            <p>Such approach is consistent with <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes</persName>’ position as outlined to the Assembly last
                                July to effect that France intends to aid South Vietnam to extent
                                possible to prepare for the elections although responsibility for
                                outcome rests with Vietnamese themselves. As we said at time, we
                                gained impression that <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes</persName>’ attitude was essentially “let best man win”.
                                Although broad lines of such a policy might well be expected to be
                                clearly established within expectant life-span of <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes</persName>’ government, we are inclined
                                to think it likely that pressures that developed in France to force
                                settlement of the <gloss target="#t_IC1">I.C.</gloss> war on the
                                best terms available may be expected to reemerge and force any
                                possible governmental coalition that might be formed in France to
                                adopt an approach to the Vietnam problem looking toward eventual
                                North-South collaboration. Although there may be occasional efforts
                                made within France to deflect such a course of French action, we
                                think these would prove to be temporary diversions only and would
                                emanate essentially from those groups who would wish, as a price of
                                maintaining South Vietnam free of eventual [omission] a continuation
                                of a large measure of French control and influence in the south.
                                Although this might prove preferable to eventual Vietminh control,
                                we believe <pb facs="0866" n="2248" xml:id="pg_2248"/> French
                                themselves discount such an approach in longer term knowing that
                                Vietnamese in south are probably not prepared for the most part to
                                accept it and that many might turn to Vietminh as a consequence.
                                Against such diversionary efforts that may be made to deflect French
                                policy must be balanced wide-spread receptiveness in France to any
                                indication of progress registered, however slight, by <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName> in North Vietnam and
                                frequent reiteration of magnitude and inexorable nature of the
                                Vietminh drive toward an eventual absorption of the south.</p>
                            <p>We think Vietnam presents <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes</persName> with a situation ideally designed to test
                                bases of his fundamental political philosophy which appears to
                                regard “peaceful coexistence” as a possibility to be explored, and
                                we inclined think <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes</persName> may
                                prove to be principal architect and exponent of a policy looking
                                toward the achievement of a peaceful reunification of Vietnam. It
                                would appear that Soviet and Chinese Communist encouragement of such
                                a French approach could easily be given since the eventual result in
                                Vietnam would likely be at a minimum a Communist-oriented or
                                neutralist Vietnam in the <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> pattern. Such encouragement could also pay
                                dividends for Soviets and Chinese <gloss target="#t_Commies1">Commies</gloss> on broader plane in contributing to
                                “normalization” of East-West relations.</p>
                            <p>Thus we think the present French situation permits our drawing the
                                following tentative conclusions: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>That French will insist upon holding of nationwide
                                        elections in Vietnam in 1956 on theory of abiding in spirit
                                        of the Geneva settlement even though outcome of such
                                        elections may have become academic through process of
                                        erosion beforehand;</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>That the French do not really believe that any given South
                                        Vietnamese governmental combination, with all the technical
                                        and economic resources that could be usefully exploited, can
                                        overcome present apparent political and military imbalance
                                        between the North and South in time to win any general
                                        election;</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>That French fear that a threat of overt Vietminh military
                                        aggression will arise if any attempt is made to thwart the
                                        holding of nationwide elections in July 1956;</item>
                                    <label>(4)</label>
                                    <item>That the French are no more willing now, and may be
                                        expected to be increasingly less so as time goes by, to risk
                                        a resumption of hostilities in <gloss target="#t_IC1">I.C.</gloss> and a general Asian war as an alternate to
                                        eventual North-South Vietnamese collaboration;</item>
                                    <label>(5)</label>
                                    <item>That the French do not consider <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> either as framework or instrument that
                                        could properly be used in support of policy designed to
                                        avoid elections and hold 17th parallel against eventual
                                        Vietminh attempt to reunify country by force;</item>
                                    <label>(6)</label>
                                    <item>That the French do not believe that the U.S. is prepared
                                        to intervene militarily on the ground in Vietnam in an
                                        effort to establish South Vietnam as a free world
                                        strongpoint and make the 17th parallel another 38th, nor do
                                        the French think that the South Vietnamese militarily <pb facs="0867" n="2249" xml:id="pg_2249"/> will be in a
                                        position to swing it alone or carry lion’s share of
                                        burden;</item>
                                    <label>(7)</label>
                                    <item>That the French appear to conclude from the foregoing that
                                        it is possible, and in any event that it is worth the risk,
                                        to attempt to bring about a peaceful reunification of North
                                        and South Vietnam and try keep a Communist-oriented
                                        Vietminh-controlled reunified Vietnam outside Communist
                                        orbit, and at least neutral to free world.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>As consequence, we think that the French may more and more speak of
                                the desirability of the U.S. adopting a sympathetic view of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Sainteny</persName>’s efforts to
                                reduce dependence of Ho and his government on <gloss target="#t_Commies1">Commie</gloss> China and bring Vietminh
                                closer to free world. We may expect that this approach will be
                                portrayed as offering the only real chance of avoiding an inevitable
                                military show-down in Asia with which the U.S. approach to Vietnam
                                is becoming increasingly identified in French minds.</p></item>
                        <label>III.</label>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Impact U.S. aid</hi>. Although it appears that an
                            early cutoff or substantial reduction in U.S. aid for the French
                            Expeditionary Corps would only further accelerate French trend toward a
                            policy of collaboration with the Vietminh, we do not believe that
                            continuation of U.S. aid for the Expeditionary Corps at substantial
                            levels through at least 1955 would do more than slow down this trend. We
                            do not think that it would reverse or appreciably modify this
                            trend.</item>
                        <label>IV.</label>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Present lines U.S. approach Vietnam</hi>. Our recent
                            exchange of views with French on <persName>Buu Hoi</persName> tended
                            underline and make clear to French that U.S. not prepared to accept an
                            approach in Vietnam that might eventually involve, or look toward, a
                            policy of possible collaboration with Vietminh. At a minimum we think it
                            can safely be said that the present French position with respect to
                            Vietnam encompasses such a possibility. As a consequence, we are
                            inclined to think that U.S. is currently faced, and may be increasingly
                            faced, with prospect of France moving along a path in Vietnam which we
                            might consider as conflicting with our ultimate objectives there.</item>
                        <label>V.</label>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>. We think it unrealistic to expect
                            France in longer term to follow a course of action in Vietnam which it
                            feels might involve it in an eventual military show-down in the Far
                            East. Psychologically, France might have accepted such a show-down
                            during the final days of Dien Bien Phu. However, that time has passed
                            and the trend that led to the conclusion of the <gloss target="#t_IC1">I.C.</gloss> war on terms by which the Vietminh could one day
                            peacefully take over all of Vietnam, has only gained momentum with the
                            passage of time. Hence it would appear that when reference is made
                            hereafter to harmonization of Franco-American policy with respect to
                            Vietnam it will become increasingly necessary to examine our respective
                            objectives in Vietnam and how we intend to achieve them if we are to
                            avoid serious misunderstandings arising in months to come. To speculate,
                            it would also <pb facs="0868" n="2250" xml:id="pg_2250"/> appear that if
                            South Vietnam is to be retained as a free world bastion in Southeast
                            Asia, the burden, i.e., military, may tend fall principally upon U.S.
                            aided by such military force as can be developed in South Vietnam
                            beforehand, and that the implementation of such a policy inevitably will
                            encounter resistance from French and neutralist elements on overall
                            plane as well as an anticipated step-up in the overall Communist
                            coexistence campaign.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DCD1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dillon</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>