<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Vietnam ( (Heath) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-11-12T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-11-12T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-12T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-12T09:00:00-05:00" n="1316"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1316">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">120.251G/11–1254: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Vietnam</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HDR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d1316fn1">This telegram was transmitted in two parts.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-11-12T22:00:00+08:00"
                            >November 12, 1954—10 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1807. Repeated information Paris 598. From <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1"
                        >Collins</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> told us
                    10th that <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> had sent <persName
                        corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> orders to report to him in France by first
                    available plane. Understand <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> received
                    duplicate messages containing orders, one through Defense Ministry and other
                    through imperial cabinet office here. <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                        >Hinh</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> that
                    he could not obey orders for seven or eight days.</p>
                <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> that I had had no conversation
                    with <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> and would receive him for first
                    time 11th. I added however that it seemed to me means should be found to save
                        <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>’s face in departing since
                    although he is an obstructive element at present he may prove useful at some
                    future time.</p>
                <p>Thereafter I discussed problem with <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName>
                    who was present at same social function. We agreed that we would both advise
                        <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> to obey <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>’s summons promptly. On taking leave of
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> I told him of this agreement. He
                    expressed gratification and said he had already talked over matter with
                        <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName>.</p>
                <p>Reference Paris 1984 to Department, repeated Saigon 276.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d1316fn2">According to telegram 1984 from Paris, Nov. 9, not
                        printed, <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> had reportedly cabled
                        Generals <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> and
                            <persName>Xuan</persName>, ordering them to return to France, and had
                        instructed Gen. <persName corresp="#p_LVV1">Le Van Vien</persName> to
                        cooperate with <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>.
                        (751G.00/11–954)</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> did not mention any orders <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> may have sent to
                        <persName>Xuan</persName> or Bay Vien.</p>
                <p>At my invitation <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> called 11th. He
                    spoke forthrightly concerning impasse between him and <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>. He recounted in detail background of
                    difficulty with <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> and declared latter
                    incapable of providing proper leadership.</p>
                <p>He stated that primary current problem is to establish some effective system for
                    resisting the infiltration of communism. He felt that during war governmental
                    propaganda and indoctrination program had been inadequate with result that Viet
                    Minh still have many adherents in free Vietnam, particularly outside large towns
                    and cities. He believes that army is only vehicle with discipline, organization
                    and means to reorient people toward national government.</p>
                <p>Despite lack of government support, he has marshalled army forces in certain
                    provinces to help people and to win their support. He believes <pb facs="0857"
                        n="2239" xml:id="pg_2239"/> that such utilization of army in a peacetime
                    role will assist government materially. <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                        >Hinh</persName> reported that where he has implemented system results have
                    been most encouraging (and I have reports from my observers which tend to
                    confirm this).</p>
                <p>He referred to civilian companies of unpaid volunteers. He said that in these
                    groups called companies of psychological action 100,000 civilians (pedicab
                    drivers and manual laborers) are organized under general supervision of
                    psychological warfare section of his staff. <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                        >Hinh</persName> declares that it is the activity of this group which
                    government views with concern and fears might lead to revolution.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> declared that if he had wanted to
                    start a revolution, he would have done so before now and that he could start one
                    today if he wished. He stated that he would take no action except for benefit of
                    Vietnam despite government’s opposition to him and army.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> stated that situation which had
                    existed past few months must end shortly otherwise south Vietnam will be lost
                    within one or two months. He said he has taken advantage of opportunity created
                    by dispute between him and <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> to
                    demonstrate to world latter’s incompetence and inability to lead. However, he
                    said it was not up to him to determine if <persName corresp="#p_NDD1"
                        >Diem</persName> should remain as Prime Minister.</p>
                <p>He added however that there are two ways to get rid of <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>: (1) <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao
                        Dai</persName> could dismiss <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> or
                    (2) <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> could execute a <hi
                        rend="italic">coup d’état</hi>. However, external considerations had
                    prevented Chief of State and <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> from
                    getting rid of <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>. Hence latter
                    remains, but if he continues in office he must cooperate with all elements of
                    society, especially with army.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> further stated that decision must be
                    made shortly, either by <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>, army, Chief
                    of State or US to resolve current political crisis. He said that those who
                    intervened to keep <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> in power are
                    responsible for future of Vietnam. He said he realized Vietnam needs American
                    aid but if that aid, employed under incompetent leadership, leads to certain
                    defeat, Vietnam would do better without it.</p>
                <p>I thanked <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> for his frankness.</p>
                <p>I told him that I had heard that he had instructions from <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> to report to latter in France and urged
                    him to comply promptly. I assured him that in his absence any steps that I took
                    would be in support of freedom of Vietnam. I also assured him I would do nothing
                    while he was absent which would in any way lower his or army’s prestige. I said
                    however that I had just arrived and was not yet in position to make firm
                    recommendations to my government as to action it should take and I agreed with
                    him that system which he urged (utilization of army described above) made a lot
                    of sense to me. I told him flatly however that if he was to defy <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> he would have to stand alone.</p>
                <pb facs="0858" n="2240" xml:id="pg_2240"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> admitted that he had instructions to
                    report to <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> but stated that he had
                    not yet made up his mind whether to obey. If he decided not to go to France he
                    would execute a <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi>. He said that question was
                    whether Vietnam was better off with <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>
                    and US aid or without <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> and our help.
                    He said he realized that if he executed a coup he would have to forego US aid. I
                    assured him that if he revolted US aid would definitely be withdrawn.</p>
                <p>I asked <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> if Cabinet changes suggested
                    by General <persName>Alessandri</persName> (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1"
                        >Embtel</gloss> 1796 repeated Paris 596)<note n="3" xml:id="d1316fn3"
                        >General <persName>Alessandri</persName>, military adviser to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>, visited Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName> on Nov. 10.
                            <persName>Alessandri</persName>, having returned to Saigon to assess the
                        political situation for the Chief of State, presented a proposal for a
                        durable government under <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> and a
                        list of specific candidates for the various cabinet posts. Among his
                        suggestions were that <persName>Phan Huy Quat</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BLP1">Buu Loc</persName> serve as Vice Presidents, that the
                        Interior Ministry go to Le Kieu of the Binh Xuyen or to <persName
                            corresp="#p_NVT1">Nguyen Van Tam</persName>, and that <persName>Ho Thong
                            Minh</persName> be named Minister of Defense. <persName
                            corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName> reported this conversation in
                        telegram 1796 from Saigon, Nov. 11, not printed. (751G.00/11–1154)</note>
                    appeared sound to him and he replied that he was completely indifferent to
                    proposals. I suggested that when he returned from France he do so as Inspector
                    General or in capacity other than Chief of Staff. I asked then if he would
                    support nomination of General <persName>Vy</persName> as his successor. He said
                    he would.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> then asked whether I would ask
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> to effect changes if I should
                    determine that his government was incompetent. I replied frankly that I was not
                    committed to support any particular Cabinet but was committed to support
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName>.</p>
                <p>I then asked him when he expected to leave to report to <persName
                        corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                        >Hinh</persName> replied he had not decided whether he would leave Vietnam
                    or start a revolution. He said if he decided to go, he would probably leave
                    fifteenth. He said that he was not motivated by any desire to protect his
                    position and, in fact, he would very much like rest of several months; but that
                    he had a responsibility toward country and though he held no hatred for
                        <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> he was convinced that Prime
                    Minister was leading Vietnam to destruction. I again urgently advised him not to
                    attempt a revolution but to obey <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName>
                    promptly. <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> replied he would consult
                    with his friends and determine whether Chief of State was above country or the
                    country above Chief of State.</p>
                <p>At the conclusion of our discussion I outlined to <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                        >Hinh</persName> some of my thinking for support of Vietnamese forces. I
                    told him of my conversation with <persName corresp="#p_EGP1">Ely</persName> and
                    latter’s agreement that US take over training of Vietnamese armed forces. I
                    pointed out that it was planned gradually to replace French officers on
                    Vietnamese staff by Vietnamese officers. I told him of my conversation with
                    President <persName>Magsaysay</persName> and latter’s enthusiastic response to
                    my suggestion that Philippines assist free Vietnam in training and providing
                    guidance in various fields of endeavor.</p>
                <pb facs="0859" n="2241" xml:id="pg_2241"/>
                <p>I assured <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName> that I would urge <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> at every opportunity to broaden framework
                    of government and repeated that in his absence I personally would make no
                    recommendations which would derogate from the prestige of the army or his
                    position. <persName corresp="#p_NVH1">Hinh</persName>’s parting words were that
                    he would decide within 48 hours whether to go to France or start a revolution
                    and he said that if he did not leave there would be trouble.</p>
                <p>Despite a certain amount of bravado in <persName corresp="#p_NVH1"
                        >Hinh</persName>’s statements I was quite impressed with his personality and
                    ability. He spoke forcefully and with great clarity and gave me at least the
                    first impression of a sincere desire to save his country in the face of what he
                    regards as an utterly inadequate government. He is still somewhat immature and,
                    despite his protestations to the contrary, is personally ambitious. However, he
                    has qualities of drive and imagination which should be preserved and if possible
                    used to the maximum in a constructive way.</p>
                <p>I do not take seriously his threat of a <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> but as
                    I do not know the man and know little of his actual hold on the army I cannot
                    guarantee this judgment.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
