<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Laos ( (Yost) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1414</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1414</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-12-28T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-12-28T01:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-28T01:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-12-28T01:00:00-05:00" n="1414"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1414">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/12–2854: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Laos</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_YCW1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Yost</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vientiane</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-12-28T13:00:00+07:00"
                            >December 28, 1954—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>204. Repeated information Saigon, Phnom Penh, Bangkok unnumbered. Joint
                        Legation/<gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> message. Reference Department
                    telegram 133, repeated Saigon 2295, Bangkok 1456, Phnom Penh 181.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d1414fn1">Dated Dec. 7, <ref target="#pg_2349">p. 2349</ref>.</note>
                    Suggest following objectives and projects at this time: <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>Training of Lao officers and noncommissioned officers by Thai Army.
                            Since Geneva accords do not permit <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>
                            establishment in Laos and in view French limitations in this field,
                            training by Thai Army would seem best alternative. Similarity of
                            language and proximity Thailand should permit easy implementation such
                            project.</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>Improvement transportation connections Laos–Cambodia–Thailand. This
                            objective basic to any development Laos as hinterland with no access to
                            sea. Its success will govern importance of objectives suggested
                            paragraphs C and D below. Loss of Hanoi and North Vietnam to Communists
                            has further cut off Laos from outside world. Present sea outlets limited
                            [garble] Tourane (both almost inaccessible), Saigon in South Vietnam,
                            and Bangkok. Road network almost entirely oriented to Vietnam and
                            Cambodia. Although shipment commodities to southern Laos as far as
                            Savannakhet via Saigon economically acceptable, similar shipments to
                            northern Laos prohibitive in cost and slowness. One of first objectives
                                <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss>/Laos will therefore be to
                            continue improving means of transportation between northern Laos and
                            Thailand. Projects for additional ferries, barges and landing ramps on
                            Mekong River will receive favorable consideration, as will project for
                            improving Luang Prabang and Vientiane air fields (where traffic has
                            doubled every year since 1952) and road construction projects leading to
                            landing ramps on Mekong (such as Vientiane-Thadeua road, leading to
                            future landing ramp opposite Thai railhead at Udorn).</item>
                        <label>C.</label>
                        <item>Agreement Thailand–Laos for free transit of commodities shipped to
                            Laos via Thailand. Preliminary discussions have taken place Bangkok this
                            subject but little apparent progress to date. <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                                >USOM</gloss> keenly interested this matter in anticipation that
                            goods formerly shipped via Saigon will increasingly be shipped through
                            Bangkok, particularly for north Laos.</item>
                        <label>D.</label>
                        <item>Trade development Thailand–Laos–Cambodia. Feel that important
                            percentage trade Laos–Thailand is on clandestine basis across unguarded
                            Mekong River, that French policy and Indo-Chinese war have reduced
                            potential trade these two countries. Also informed that present Lao
                            exports far below prewar.</item>
                        <pb facs="1050" n="2432" xml:id="pg_2432"/>
                        <label>E.</label>
                        <item>Educational, technical and public administration training of Lao
                            personnel in Thai and Cambodian institutions. Lao officials have
                            ambitious plans for creation Lao university and various technical
                            institutions. Although such plans should not be discouraged, feel they
                            are beyond realm immediate realization and much time could be saved by
                            taking advantage existing institutions Cambodia and particularly
                            Thailand. Since effectiveness Lao administration determining factor
                            instability and development this country, as well as in success of
                                <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> program, our first emphasis
                            should be in training public administrators who are sadly lacking in
                            Laos today. Remaining French officials have been stripped most their
                            authority, many Vietnamese expelled, while Laotians do not appear aware
                            of fact that independent status now emerging implies responsibilities
                            and numerous administrative functions. Example of Thailand as relatively
                            well-administered neighbor with long tradition independence should
                            provide badly needed stimulus to Lao officials [garble] Bangkok comment
                            this project.</item>
                        <label>F.</label>
                        <item>Will also investigate as soon as practicable feasibility of
                            hydroelectric dams in Mekong River, as possible source of power for
                            adjacent areas Laos and northern Thailand.</item>
                        <label>G.</label>
                        <item>This subject is matter of continuing concern to Legation and <gloss
                                target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> and furthermore detailed proposals
                            will be submitted as soon as time permits.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_YCW1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Yost</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
