<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé at Saigon ( (McClintock) ) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v13p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d864</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">864</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-05-10T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-05-10T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-10T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-10T05:00:00-05:00" n="864"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d864">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.00/5–1054: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé at Saigon</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MR2"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McClintock</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Saigon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-10T18:00:00+08:00"
                            >May 10, 1954—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 11—5:08 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2311. Repeated information Geneva 76, Paris 803, Hanoi unnumbered. I had a
                    general conversation with <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> this
                    morning on situation we now confront following fall of Dien Bien Phu and in
                    light of current conference at Geneva.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> showed me his lengthy telegram of
                    May 3 to <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> outlining in geographic
                    terms minimal conditions for a military armistice. I suggest that <gloss
                        target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> Geneva can secure these recommendations
                    from French delegation and post them on a map of Vietnam. If not I shall
                    telegram summary of text with <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName>’s
                    permission. In essence his proposals are that most of Tonkin delta remain in
                    French-Vietnamese hands but with a corridor which would link area north and west
                    of delta to Viet Minh-held territory in Central Annam. Thai country would go to
                    Viet Minh. Most of central plateau region in vicinity of Kontum and Banmethuot
                    would be in Vietnamese-French hands and all of Cochin China. However, <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> recognized extreme difficulty of
                    separating sheep from goats in areas heavily infiltrated by Viet Minh such as
                    Transbassac and southern tip of Cochin Chinese peninsula.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> showed me <persName
                        corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>’s draft of terms for an armistice dated
                    April 30 and revised as of May 3, which are more complicated and on <pb
                        facs="0149" n="1531" xml:id="pg_1531"/> whole less satisfactory than those
                    set out <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 143 amended as indicated <gloss
                        target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 152.<note n="1" xml:id="d864fn1">For text
                        of telegram <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 143 from Geneva, May 8,
                        see <ref target="frus1952-54v16#pg_730">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xvi</hi>,
                            p. 730</ref>. Regarding telegram <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss>
                        152, see footnote 1 to <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 143.</note>
                    Particularly dangerous in these drafts is <persName corresp="#p_BG1"
                        >Bidault</persName>’s suggestion that political fate of Vietnam be left to
                    negotiation between Vietnamese and Viet Minh. This would simply result in
                    absorption of former by latter. <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> is
                    aware of this danger and is cautioning <persName corresp="#p_BG1"
                        >Bidault</persName> against any such provision.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> will recommend that military terms
                    of armistice agreed upon, be entrusted to a mixed commission made up of former
                    belligerents. He fears that an international commission could only be formed
                    after months of haggling and that British would insist on incorporating
                    “undesirable elements” such as Burmese or Indians.</p>
                <p>I said that if Geneva powers decided on a mixed commission Communist side might
                    demand a seat for Red China. In that case I thought it would be useful if there
                    were a US representative on armistice commission.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> said that mixed commission should
                    devote its attention only to enforcing strictly military provisions of an
                    armistice. Political aspects of armistice might well be entrusted to an
                    international commission appointed by UN Security Council.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> then discussed more basic
                    problems. He said, “There are three issues: First, should there be an armistice
                    at all? Second, if there is no armistice, how to continue war successfully?
                    Third, if there is an armistice, what powers will provide effective guarantees
                    for compliance with armistice agreement?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> said he felt time had come for
                    very frank talking between US and French Governments. He said loss of Dien Bien
                    Phu by no means signified loss of war. There were still some very powerful trump
                    cards which would be played and which if played correctly could result in
                    victory. French still have a powerful military force in Indochina and are able
                    to use that force to contain Viet Minh. However, as was instanced in tragic
                    miscalculation of <persName corresp="#p_NGH1">Navarre</persName> at Dien Bien
                    Phu, character of war had now changed and overt participation by China in form
                    of sending modern artillery and other weapons would no doubt be stepped up if
                    hostilities continued. Under such a postulate it would not be possible for
                    French and Vietnamese forces alone to meet such a strengthened adversary.
                    However, if US Government were willing to contemplate use of overwhelming air
                    strength against Communist China, situation might be radically altered.</p>
                <p>Some overall considerations apply to readiness of US to undertake a military
                    guarantee of an armistice agreement. <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De
                        Jean</persName> did not think British could be brought into such an
                    arrangement and said that French alone could not provide an effective
                    guarantee.</p>
                <pb facs="0150" n="1532" xml:id="pg_1532"/>
                <p>These considerations made it necessary that there be a frank stocktaking of our
                    joint assets and a candid reappraisal of where we stood. If for constitutional
                    reasons or climate of feeling in Congress or fact of elections this year, it was
                    not possible for US to come in either in guaranteeing an armistice or in
                    backstopping renewed hostilities with something more than end-item support, at
                    least we should face the facts calmly and draw necessary conclusions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM1">De Jean</persName> asked if I had no other than
                    Secretary’s latest statement which reached us in <gloss target="#t_USIA1"
                        >USIA</gloss> Wireless File so badly garbled that I was not yet sure what
                    Secretary had actually said. It seemed from such fragments as had reached us
                    that Secretary was advocating speedy negotiation of some form of collective
                    security pact but I had had no other word on this subject.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d864fn2">Reference is presumably to the Secretary’s speech of May 7;
                        see <ref target="#pg_1496">footnote 5, p. 1496</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MR2">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">McClintock</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
