<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-10-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="169" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d169">
                    <head>169. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Human
                        Rights and Humanitarian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_DPM_1">Derian</persName>) to the Deputy Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d169fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, P780176–0654.
                            Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BMM_1">Bova</persName> on
                            October 25; concurred in by <persName corresp="#p_ZM_1">Zak</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_JW_1">Jennette</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SLG_1">Shurtleff</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BJF_1">Buncher</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LG_1">Lister</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CPM_1">Cleveland</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Graham</persName>, and <gloss target="#t_EBOFP_1">EB/OFP</gloss>.
                            Schneider initialed for <persName corresp="#p_DPM_1">Derian</persName>.
                            An unknown hand initialed for the clearing officials.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-10-30">October 30, 1978</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>1979 <gloss target="#t_PL_1">PL</gloss> 480 I Agreements—Human Rights
                            Language Requirement</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Issue for Decision</p>
                    <p>Which <gloss target="#t_PL_1">PL</gloss> 480 I agreements should contain a
                        human rights clause ensuring that the commodities provided or the proceeds
                        derived from their sale will directly benefit needy people?</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Essential Factors</p>
                    <p>Title I of the Agricultural Trade Development and Assistance Act of 1954 was
                        amended by Public Law 95–88 of August 3, 1977 by adding Section 112 which
                        states:</p>
                    <p>No agreement may be entered into under this title to finance the sale of
                        agricultural commodities to the government of any country which engages in a
                        consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human
                        rights, including torture or cruel, inhuman, or degrading treatment or
                        punishment, prolonged detention without charges, or other flagrant denial of
                        the right to life, liberty, and the security of person, unless such
                        agreement will directly benefit the needy people in such country. An
                        agreement will not directly benefit the needy people in the country for
                        purposes of the preceding sentence unless either the commodities themselves
                        or the proceeds from their sale will be used for specific projects or
                        programs which the President determines would directly benefit the needy
                        people of that country. The agreement shall require a report to the
                        President on such use <pb facs="0600" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/> within six
                        months after the commodities are delivered to the recipient country.<note n="2" xml:id="d169fn2">See <ref target="#d58fn6">footnote 6, Document
                                58</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In response to this requirement, the Department, in consultation with <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>, made a determination that for Fiscal Year
                        1978, language in accordance with the above requirement would be placed in
                        agreements with countries where serious human rights problems exist or are
                        widely perceived to exist by the public or Members of Congress. This liberal
                        application of the statute would ensure compliance while avoiding the
                        creation of a public “hit-list” which could follow from a narrower
                        interpretation. It would also, on the other hand, minimize the accounting
                        workload placed on our <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> Missions and
                        Title I recipient governments. Accordingly, language was placed in one third
                        of the Fiscal Year 1979 Title I Agreements and specifically in agreements
                        with the following countries: Bangladesh, Guinea, Haiti, Indonesia,
                        Philippines, Sierra Leone, Somalia, Zaire, and Korea.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_PL_1">PL</gloss> 480 I list for Fiscal Year 1979 has
                        recently been submitted to the Congress. It contains twenty-nine countries.
                        Consensus has been reached within the Department to maintain language in the
                        agreements with the following countries on that list: Guinea, Haiti, Sierra
                        Leone, Philippines and Zaire. There is also a consensus to maintain the
                        language through the side-letter arrangement with Indonesia and Korea as
                        long as it is not necessary to negotiate new agreements. There is also a
                        consensus, in view of changing circumstances, to drop the language from the
                        agreement with Somalia. <gloss target="#t_HA_1">HA</gloss> proposes
                        maintaining language in the Title I Agreement with Bangladesh and adding
                        language to the Title I agreements with Pakistan, Syria and Tunisia. All
                        four were Title I recipients last year. The <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss> Bureau is opposed to re-inserting language in the
                        Bangladesh agreement and to adding language in the other three.</p>
                    <p>New agreements under <gloss target="#t_PL_1">PL</gloss> 480 Title III will be
                        negotiated with Indonesia and Bangladesh later in the year. With <gloss target="#t_HA_1">HA</gloss> consensus, language was not included in the
                        1978 Title III agreement with Bangladesh. Title III by its nature ensures
                        that the assistance provided is used to directly benefit the needy and,
                        accordingly, it is questionable whether separate human rights related
                        language is required. <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>’s General Counsel
                        has been asked to provide guidance on this point. If needed, a separate memo
                        on this issue will be provided subsequent to the receipt of this legal
                        guidance.</p>
                    <p>[Omitted here is information concerning specific Bureau positions with regard
                        to the Title I agreements anticipated for Bangladesh, Pakistan, Syria, and
                        Tunisia.]</p>
                    <pb facs="0601" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Options</p>
                    <p>1. Add the language to the <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1979 Title I
                        agreements with Pakistan, Syria and Tunisia and maintain the language in the
                        Title I agreement with Bangladesh. Papers describing the human rights
                        situation are attached.<note n="3" xml:id="d169fn3">The human rights papers
                            on Syria, Pakistan, Bangladesh, and Tunisia are not attached.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>—This approach will ensure continued compliance with the legislative
                        requirement.</p>
                    <p>—The language reinforces the Administration’s efforts to make Title I more
                        directly benefit the poor.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>—Addition of the human rights clause could cause friction with recipient
                        governments and lead to delays in negotiating Title I agreements.</p>
                    <p>2. Do not include language in the <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1979
                        Title I agreements with Bangladesh, Pakistan, Syria and Tunisia.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>—This approach would not jeopardize our bilateral relations programs as
                        indicated above, nor would it delay the negotiation of the agreements.</p>
                    <p>—The Department would be in compliance with the letter and spirit of the
                        legislation by excluding countries which do not engage in “a consistent
                        pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights.”</p>
                    <p>—We would avoid confusing the leadership for countries where there has been
                        progress in human rights observance.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>—Non-inclusion of language in all but the most serious cases might give the
                        impression that a “hit-list” has been created.</p>
                    <p>—The accounting workload of our <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> missions
                        would not be minimized although, with the exception of the mission in Dacca,
                        neither would it increase.</p>
                    <pb facs="0602" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation</p>
                    <p>That you authorize inclusion of the human rights language in Title I
                        agreements with all or some of the four countries discussed.</p>
                    <p>Bangladesh<note n="4" xml:id="d169fn4">
                            <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> indicated his
                            approval and added his initials and the date “11/6.” According to an
                            additional stamped notation, <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> approved this option on November 16.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Pakistan</p>
                    <p>Syria</p>
                    <p>Tunisia<note n="5" xml:id="d169fn5">
                            <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> indicated his
                            disapproval on Pakistan, Syria, and Tunisia on November 16.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Somalia<note n="6" xml:id="d169fn6">
                            <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> added Somalia to the
                            list by hand and indicated his approval on November 16.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>