<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>172. Memorandum From the Special Assistant to the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (Inderfurth) to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs () to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-12-01T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="human-rights" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379" lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="credit" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856" lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="compound-subject" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">U.S. foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" subject="emigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907" lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations" subject="u-s-soviet-union-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recfABRQvTqVuIjoA" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="antisemitism" subject="antisemitism" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750" lcsh-match="exact">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="near-east" subject="near-east" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085196" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="east-asia-and-pacific" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="east-asia-and-pacific" subject="east-asia">East Asia</term>
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="south-and-central-asia" subject="south-asia">South Asia</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-operations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military coup</term>
                    <term ref="recHKBrLbO74DsZpb" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="human-rights-violations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136190" lcsh-match="exact">Torture</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="amnesty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558" lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-12-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                <head>172. Memorandum From the Special Assistant to the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_IKF_1">Inderfurth</persName>)
                    to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d172fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> Material, <persName corresp="#p_IKF_1">Inderfurth</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GRM_1">Gates</persName> Chron File, Box 3, <persName corresp="#p_IKF_1">Inderfurth</persName> Chron: 11–12/78. No
                        classification marking. Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_SJ_2">Schecter</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TMJ_1">Tuchman
                            Mathews</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                        wrote the following handwritten notation in the top right-hand corner of the
                        memorandum: “<gloss target="#t_RI_1">RI</gloss>, good, put in folder for the
                        meeting. <gloss target="#t_ZB_1">ZB</gloss>.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-12-01">December 1, 1978</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Human Rights Performance</item>
                </list>
                <p>For background purposes I have prepared the attached unclassified paper on “Human
                    Rights Performance: January 1977–December 1978.” It is based on <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>’s “confidential” study which the Agency (Bob
                    Bowie) refused to declassify.<note n="2" xml:id="d172fn2">Presumable reference
                        to a <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> study of the same name prepared by
                        the National Foreign Assessment Center in September 1978, which <persName corresp="#p_IKF_1">Inderfurth</persName> forwarded to <persName corresp="#p_OK_1">Oksenberg</persName> under an October 27 memorandum.
                        (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> Material, <persName corresp="#p_IKF_1">Inderfurth</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GRM_1">Gates</persName>
                        Chron File, Box 3, <persName corresp="#p_IKF_1">Inderfurth</persName> Chron:
                        10/78)</note> I suggest that you—and others—use this information to
                    background the press on human rights improvements during the <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> Administration. We do not want to
                    appear to take credit for all such improvements, but the fact remains that the
                    President’s human rights policy has made the world a better place to live in and
                    he should get some of the credit for this.</p>
                <p>In addition to discussing worldwide improvements (and regressions) in human
                    rights, you might also use the following, which is based on an earlier memo from
                        Jessica.<note n="3" xml:id="d172fn3">See <ref target="#d168">Document
                            168</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> Administration has <hi rend="italic">three human rights objectives</hi>:<note n="4" xml:id="d172fn4">An unknown hand drew an arrow from the margin to this
                        sentence.</note>
                </p>
                <p>—To <hi rend="italic">raise global awareness</hi> of human rights so that the
                    issue is a regular concern of all governments and an expected component of
                    relations both with other countries and with the international community.</p>
                <p>We have <hi rend="italic">met</hi> this objective.</p>
                <p>—To organize U.S. foreign policy making so that human rights concerns are taken
                    into account in all relevant <hi rend="italic">decisions</hi> including foreign
                    assistance, political actions and economic benefits.</p>
                <p>We have <hi rend="italic">partially met</hi> this objective. Excessive delays and
                    inconsistent decisions still persist.</p>
                <pb facs="0608" n="547" xml:id="pg_547"/>
                <p>—To begin the lengthy process of <hi rend="italic">strengthening</hi> the <hi rend="italic">international institutions</hi> (including the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> and its commissions, the <gloss target="#t_IFIs_1">IFIs</gloss> and the regional human rights organizations)
                    so that ultimately they can become the primary focus of international human
                    rights activity.</p>
                <p>We have <hi rend="italic">partially met</hi> this objective. The <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>
                    commissions are vastly improved and some progress has been made in gaining
                    support in the <gloss target="#t_IFIs_1">IFIs</gloss>. There is still a long way
                    to go.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation:</p>
                <p>That you use the attached paper to background the press at the time of the
                    December 6 White House human rights event.<note n="5" xml:id="d172fn5">See <ref target="#d176">Document 176</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared in the National Security Council</hi>
                        <note n="6" xml:id="d172fn6">No classification marking.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" when="1978-12-01">undated</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">Human Rights Performance: January 1977–December 1978</p>
                    <p>Over the past two years the human rights situation worldwide has <hi rend="italic">improved</hi> but in several countries deteriorated.
                        Worldwide trends indicate significant patterns of change. Since January 1977
                        there have been human rights <hi rend="italic">improvements in 41
                            countries</hi> where 2½ billion people live. Most of these countries,
                        however, still have less than good human rights records. In at least <hi rend="italic">10 countries</hi>, the standards of human rights have <hi rend="italic">declined</hi>, affecting almost half a billion people. On
                        a regional basis, these changes have been noted:</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Yugoslavia’s</hi> human rights record is by far the best
                        in <hi rend="italic">Eastern Europe</hi> and it has improved in the last
                        year. <hi rend="italic">Hungary</hi> has improved on such issues as
                        emigration, family reunification and travel. Human rights abuses have
                        increased in <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Soviet Union’s</hi> record has deteriorated, although the regime has
                        apparently liberalized its Jewish emigration policy.</p>
                    <p>—There have been a few changes in human rights practices in the <hi rend="italic">Middle East</hi> over the past two years, although some
                        improvements have been noted in <hi rend="italic">Morocco</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Sudan</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Syria.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>—Although many of the nations of <hi rend="italic">East Asia and the
                            Pacific</hi> region have found themselves at odds, to varying degrees,
                        with U.S. human rights policy, improvements have been evident in <hi rend="italic">South Korea</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Phil<pb facs="0609" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/>ippines</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Indonesia</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Republic of China</hi> (ROC), and
                            <hi rend="italic">Thailand.</hi> In addition, there have been
                        indications of improvement in the <hi rend="italic">People’s Republic of
                            China</hi> (PRC). Conditions have deteriorated in <hi rend="italic">Vietnam</hi> and continue to be deplorable in <hi rend="italic">Cambodia</hi>, where Western influence generally has made no
                        impact.</p>
                    <p>—In <hi rend="italic">South Asia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">India’s</hi> return
                        to constitutional practices dramatically improved its human rights record.
                        Conditions have also bettered in <hi rend="italic">Iran</hi> due to the
                        Shah’s program of liberalization. <hi rend="italic">Bangladesh</hi> has seen
                        some improvement. The human rights situation in <hi rend="italic">Afghanistan</hi> has deteriorated since the April 1978 military
                        coup.</p>
                    <p>—Over the past year human rights practices in some <hi rend="italic">African</hi> countries have improved, including <hi rend="italic">Benin, Djibouti, Ghana, Guinea</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Ivory
                            Coast.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Nigeria</hi> has welcomed the U.S. emphasis on human
                        rights and has proposed a regional <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> human
                        rights commission for Africa. There have been some improvements in <hi rend="italic">Rhodesia</hi> but no real change in <hi rend="italic">South Africa</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Uganda</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Equatorial Guinea</hi> remain two of the worst violators in the world
                        today.</p>
                    <p>—Of the 26 countries in <hi rend="italic">Latin America</hi>, human rights
                        progress has been made in 12. There has been a marked decrease in the worst
                        kinds of abuses, such as officially condoned killings, torture and prolonged
                        and illegal detention. International and regional human rights organizations
                        have taken a more active role in the region and have been receiving
                        cooperation from many governments. <hi rend="italic">Peru</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Ecuador</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Brazil</hi> have all
                        taken steps toward more constitutional procedures. Improvements have been
                        noted in <hi rend="italic">Chile</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Uruguay</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Honduras</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Guatemala.</hi>
                        Recently there has been a deterioration in <hi rend="italic">Nicaragua.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>—In <hi rend="italic">Western Europe</hi> there have been two positive
                        developments. <hi rend="italic">Spain’s</hi> overall human rights rating has
                        clearly improved. A new constitution, soon to be submitted for ratification,
                        contains comprehensive guarantees of democratic freedom. In <hi rend="italic">Cyprus</hi>, the human rights situation has improved
                        markedly during the past 18 months.</p>
                    <p>The causes of the changes cited above are complex. Increased U.S. attention
                        to human rights practices have contributed to a global climate of greater
                        sensitivity to the issue and to the heightened concern of a large number of
                        countries. In a number of cases, U.S. bilateral representations have been an
                        important factor in the improvements noted. In other cases, governments that
                        have rebuffed direct U.S. initiatives as interference in their internal
                        affairs have, as a compensating action, permitted Amnesty International or
                        some regional human rights organization to conduct its own
                        investigation.</p>
                    <p>In many cases, however, especially where substantial and far-reaching
                        improvements have taken place (for example, India and Spain), these changes
                        have reflected dramatic internal political developments. Similarly, the
                        several instances of retrogression can be ex<pb facs="0610" n="549" xml:id="pg_549"/>plained largely by internal dynamics, though at times
                        fear or traditional resentment of international pressures have played a
                        part.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
