<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>332. Memorandum From the Director of the Policy Planning Staff (Lake) to the
                    Special Representative for Economic Summits () to the Special Representative for
                    Economic Summits (Owen))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d332</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">332</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-02-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="recQ2U5eNbEz7Znwk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006006835"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Donor</term>
                    <term ref="recPwjhmSWu0ZTtDD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104910"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Population growth</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rechWxPReovs7qx7u" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Urban</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="european-economic-community" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="european-economic-community">EEC</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006001993"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Interagency</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="332"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d332">
                <head>332. Memorandum From the Director of the Policy Planning Staff (<persName
                        corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>) to the Special Representative for
                    Economic Summits (<persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d332fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Policy and Planning Staff????Office of
                        the Director, Records of <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Anthony
                            Lake</persName>, 1977–1981, Lot 82D298, Box 6, <gloss target="#t_TL_1"
                            >TL</gloss> 2/1–15/80. No classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-02-09">February 9, 1980</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Summit Proposal for <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Water
                        Decade—Background and Options</item>
                </list>
                <p>The 1977 <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Water Conference resolved that by
                    1990 everyone in the world should have reasonable access to adequate water and
                    sanitary facilities. The <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss> subsequently
                    declared 1981–90 the International Drinking Water and Sanitation Decade.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> strongly supports the goals of the Decade.
                    Provision of reasonably pure and conveniently located water supplies, and of
                    adequate sanitary facilities, can make a tangible and meaningful contribution to
                    human well-being. It is a prerequisite of good health and is essential to the
                    betterment of the lot of the Third World’s rural women, millions of whom must
                    walk miles each day with heavy loads of water. Provision of potable water is
                    consistent with our broader North-South strategy emphasizing direct efforts to
                    meet basic needs.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> has urged the world community to take the
                    Decade seriously and was instrumental in arranging for a special one-day session
                    of the General Assembly on November 15, 1980, to launch the Decade. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BP_2">Peter Bourne</persName> is coordinating Water Decade
                    activities within the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> system. He is arranging
                    for the <gloss target="#t_DAC_1">DAC</gloss> to hold a meeting of the donor
                    community late in the summer in Geneva in order to determine (and encourage)
                    donor commitments.</p>
                <p>The goal of meeting the potable water needs of all by 1990 may be impractical—the
                    capital cost of providing basic services to the 2.7 billion people who will need
                    them (taking into account interim population growth) would be $200–$600 billion
                    (1979 dollars), according to the World Bank. However, with strong support from
                    donors and LDCs, it will be feasible to make a major dent in the problem. The
                        <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> calculates that one billion rural people
                    can be provided with safe water for $44 billion (1977 prices), two-thirds of
                    which would be provided by LDCs themselves.</p>
                <pb facs="1175" n="1114" xml:id="pg_1114"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">The U.S. Position</p>
                <p>In late 1978, negotiations among State, <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> and
                    other interested agencies produced an agreement that <gloss target="#t_AID_1"
                        >AID</gloss> should provide a total of $2.5 billion over the decade in
                    bilateral aid for rural water supplies and sanitation, with the annual
                    disbursements rising toward the end of the decade. This figure was contingent on
                    commensurate support from LDCs and other donors and on future absolute increases
                    in the <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> budget. <gloss target="#t_AID_1"
                        >AID</gloss> direct spending on water and sanitation in recent years has
                    been in the range of $150–$180 million; if this level is maintained,
                    expenditures over the decade will total $1.5–$1.8 billion. More than two-thirds
                    of the current annual total is accounted for by a few large <gloss
                        target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss> projects, mainly urban, in the Middle East.
                    Urban projects had not been counted against the original target of $2.5 billion,
                    but, given current funding prospects, will have to be included in any future
                    announcement of a target.</p>
                <p>In view of the uncertain funding outlook, <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>
                    now opposes announcing any spending target for the decade. <gloss
                        target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> is committed to doing more on water, which has
                    second priority in their health sector to the broader primary health care
                    program (which includes water and sanitation in an integrated approach).
                        <persName corresp="#p_BDJJ_1">Doug Bennet</persName> agrees that the
                    proportion going to water should increase as the total <gloss target="#t_DA_1"
                        >DA</gloss> health budget increases. However, <gloss target="#t_AID_1"
                        >AID</gloss> is unwilling to vitiate the primary health care program to meet
                    a high water spending target. Whether or not the high level of <gloss
                        target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss> going into water and sanitation can be
                    maintained will depend on funding levels, the future mix of <gloss
                        target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss> recipients, and recipients’ desires and needs
                    for major water and sanitation investments.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> is currently unable to project its water
                    and sanitation expenditures for the coming decade. Over the next two months they
                    will conduct a water policy review and will clarify their own priorities.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Other Donors</p>
                <p>Some multilateral agencies, especially the World Bank, are gearing up for major
                    efforts. The World Bank already spends close to $1 billion a year on water and
                    sanitation. Its staff has drawn up and submitted to <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1"
                        >McNamara</persName> plans that would push expenditures for the 1980s up to
                    nearly $20 billion, and increase the share going to rural areas. (Assuming
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRS_1">McNamara</persName> approves the new water
                    policy, we should make sure the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> director
                    endorses it.)</p>
                <p>European donor interest, according to <persName corresp="#p_BP_2">Peter
                        Bourne</persName>, is high, but the willingness to commit resources varies.
                    The West Germans and Swedes have been leaders in this area, between them helping
                    37 LDCs develop national plans for the decade. The British are interested but
                    are working with a shrinking aid budget. The French are, as usual, inter<pb
                        facs="1176" n="1115" xml:id="pg_1115"/>ested mainly in former colonies and
                    in linking aid to domestic commercial interests.</p>
                <p>The Japanese have provided aid for a number of water-related projects but have
                    not yet expressed a particular commitment to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1"
                        >UN</gloss> Decade. In Canada, interest was high in the previous government,
                    dropped off with the election of <persName corresp="#p_CRC_1">Clark</persName>,
                    and will probably recover should Trudeau be reelected.</p>
                <p>The EEC is enthusiastic about the decade and has promised to give it high
                    priority, subject to the degree to which recipient countries request such aid.
                    The EEC will try to promote the decade among member countries and will probably
                    hold a two-day meeting in Brussels next fall to encourage and coordinate
                    European donor interest.</p>
                <p>All the main donors seem to accept the idea of the Water Decade as good as in
                    principle. However, given the uncertain and unformed nature of many other summit
                    countries’ commitments, the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> would have to
                    exert early leadership and pressure to achieve a significant result at the
                    summit.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Options for the Summit</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Announce <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> commitment of
                        $2.5 billion for the Decade, encourage others to announce comparable
                        targets</hi>
                </p>
                <p>A summit initiative would have maximum impact if the countries could announce
                    high targets. Public announcement of a <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> target
                    would also be a useful lever for encouraging other donors to set such goals.
                    However, this option faces two major obstacles: 1) it will be difficult, given
                    the fiscal climate, to gain <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> acceptance of
                    the requisite additional funding and advance commitment of funds; and 2) it will
                    probably be quite difficult to persuade all the summit countries to make similar
                    announcements.</p>
                <p>In order to make a public commitment of $2.5 billion in bilateral aid for
                    domestic water and sanitary projects (urban and rural) for the decade, the
                    President and <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> would have to:</p>
                <p>—agree to an absolute increase in <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>’s budget
                    specifically for this purpose. The exact amount of the needed increase has not
                    been determined but may approach $1 billion spread over the decade.</p>
                <p>—agree to an advance commitment of $2.5 billion for <gloss target="#t_AID_1"
                        >AID</gloss> spending on water supplies and sanitation over the decade.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Option 2. Announce U.S. commitment of $2.0 billion for the
                        decade; encourage others to announce comparable targets</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss>
                    may be more willing to make this smaller commitment, though even this level
                    probably exceeds current <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> spending
                    expectations. Announcing a specific target, even if it is lower than that <pb
                        facs="1177" n="1116" xml:id="pg_1116"/> agreed upon internally in 1978,
                    provides us with greater leverage over other donors and more credibility with
                    LDCs. A figure lower than $2.0 billion, however, might not have the same
                    advantages, since it would represent little increase over the status quo.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Option 3. Express strong support for the Decade without
                        announcing funding targets</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and other summit countries could declare
                    their strong support for the goals of the decade, and pledge to provide
                    increased aid for water and sanitation without specifying funding levels. Some
                    countries might be willing to say they will increase the share of their aid
                    funds that will be devoted to these subjects.</p>
                <p>This option would be easily achievable and would be better than nothing in terms
                    of the decade. However, it would be a weak statement for a summit.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Conclusion</p>
                <p>Because of the tangible human benefits that could result from a successful Water
                    Decade, I feel we should do all we can to make it meaningful. I propose that we
                    actively consider Option 1 for the Summit, while recognizing that there will be
                    strong pressures pushing us toward Option 3.</p>
                <p>An interagency High Level Group on the Water Decade was previously established by
                        <persName corresp="#p_BJW_1">Lucy Benson</persName> and would now be chaired
                    by <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Matt Nimetz</persName>. If you wish to pursue an
                    initiative on potable water for the Summit, I’d be glad to suggest to Matt that
                    he call a meeting of the <gloss target="#t_HLG_1">HLG</gloss>. It would be
                    useful if you could attend such a meeting, but, in any case, the meeting would
                    help to clarify the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> position on the Water
                        Decade.<note n="2" xml:id="d332fn2">The <gloss target="#t_G7_1">G–7</gloss>
                        Economic Summit took place in Venice June 22–23. The Declaration issued at
                        the end of the Summit on June 23 did not specifically mention water
                        resources. For the full text of the Declaration, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName>,
                            1980–81,</hi> Book II, pp. 1186–1191. Documentation on the Summit is in
                            <ref target="frus1977-80v03">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1977–1980, volume III, Foreign
                            Economic Policy</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
