<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>47. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski) to President ) to President Carter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d47</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">47</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="human-rights" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379" lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="protocol" subject="protocol" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="transportation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812" lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-05-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="47" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d47">
                <head>47. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>) to President <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d47fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                        Security Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                        Material, <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> Office File,
                        Subject Chron File, Box 94, Human Rights: 1977. Confidential. Sent for
                        action. Sent to <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> by
                            <persName corresp="#p_PRA_1">Pastor</persName> under cover of a May 23
                        memorandum. (Ibid.) The <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> sent a copy to
                            <persName corresp="#p_TP_1">Tarnoff</persName> under a May 24 covering
                        memorandum requesting that the Department of State determine whether or not
                        the signing ceremony could take place at the White House rather than at
                            <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> headquarters. (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-05-23">May 23, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Signing of the American Convention on Human Rights</item>
                </list>
                <p>In your Pan American Day speech,<note n="2" xml:id="d47fn2">See <ref target="#d38fn8">footnote 8, Document 38</ref>.</note> you made two
                    specific commitments—to sign and seek the ratification of Protocol I of the
                    Treaty of <pb facs="0202" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/> Tlatelolco<note n="3" xml:id="d47fn3">The 1967 Treaty of Tlatelolco (Treaty for the Prohibition of
                        Nuclear Weapons in Latin America and the Caribbean), which prohibited and
                        prevented the development, testing, use, or manufacture of nuclear weapons,
                        contained two protocols. Protocol I committed countries outside of the
                        Treaty zone to undertake obligations of the Treaty with respect to their
                        territories within the zone. Protocol II, which Vice President <persName corresp="#p_HHHJ_1">Humphrey</persName> signed on behalf of the United
                        States on April 1, 1968, called upon states possessing nuclear weapons that
                        agree to respect the obligations in the Treaty to not use nuclear weapons
                        against the parties to the Treaty. For additional information, see <ref target="frus1964-68v11#d226">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, volume XI, Arms
                            Control and Disarmament, Document 226</ref>.</note> and of the American
                    Convention on Human Rights.<note n="4" xml:id="d47fn4">The <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> adopted the American Convention on Human
                        Rights at San José, Costa Rica, on November 22, 1969. In a May 31, 1977,
                        briefing memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_HHJ_1">Hansell</persName> indicated that the
                        Convention “treats in detail a wide range of civil and political rights, and
                        establishes both a Commission and a Court to consider complaints of
                        violations of human rights protected by the Convention. The great majority
                        of the provisions of the Convention are entirely consistent with the letter
                        and the spirit of the U.S. Constitution and laws.” (National Archives,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        P770103–1218)</note> The most prevalent reaction to your speech by Latin
                    Americans was whether you would follow up on your promises, and this will
                    undoubtedly be a question Mrs. Carter will hear on her trip.<note n="5" xml:id="d47fn5">Reference is to First Lady <persName corresp="#p_CR_1">Rosalynn Carter</persName>’s goodwill trip to Jamaica, Costa Rica,
                        Ecuador, Peru, Colombia, and Venezuela May 30–June 8.</note> Therefore, I
                    would recommend that you try to sign both treaties before or during her
                    trip.</p>
                <p>The Mexicans will be bringing Protocol I with them for their Cabinet meeting in
                    Washington on Thursday, May 26,<note n="6" xml:id="d47fn6">Minutes of the
                        meeting are scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1977-80v26">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, volume XXVI, Arms
                            Control</ref>.</note> and it would be appropriate to sign it with Mrs.
                    Carter present, before your flight to St. Simons Island.<note n="7" xml:id="d47fn7">The Carter family planned to depart for Musgrove Plantation,
                        on Saint Simons Island, the afternoon of May 26 in order to spend Memorial
                        Day weekend in Georgia. Mrs. Carter left for Jamaica on May 30; the
                        President and Amy Carter returned to Washington on May 31. (<persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName>, <hi rend="italic">White House
                            Diary</hi>, pp. 57–60)</note>
                </p>
                <p>As far as the American Convention, it would seem particularly appropriate if you
                    could sign that on May 31, when Mrs. Carter arrives in Costa Rica, where much of
                    the discussion will probably be focused on human rights issues.</p>
                <p>The State Department Legal Adviser and <persName corresp="#p_LRJ_1">Bob
                        Lipshutz</persName> believe that we can have all the necessary documents
                    ready by late this week. Since the Convention is deposited at the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>, you would have to sign it there. I believe
                    the event would give added meaning to Mrs. Carter’s visit in Costa Rica.</p>
                <pb facs="0203" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation</p>
                <p>That you sign Protocol I of the Treaty of Tlatelolco on May 26 in Washington,
                    before flying to St. Simons Island, and that you sign the American Convention on
                    Human Rights at the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> on May 31.<note n="8" xml:id="d47fn8">
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> placed a check mark on the
                        approval line and added a handwritten note: “Can’t it be brought to me?” The
                        President signed Protocol I of the Treaty of Tlatelolco at the White House
                        on May 26 and the American Convention on Human Rights at <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> headquarters on June 1. For his remarks at
                        each signing ceremony, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName>, 1977</hi>, Book I, pp. 1027
                        and 1050–1051.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
