<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="206" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">810.154/1234</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Costa Rica</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hornibrook</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 26</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-16">November 16, 1937</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Copies of your despatch no. 45 dated
                            October 20, 1937,<note n="29" xml:id="d206fn29">Not printed.</note>
                            stating that the Costa Rican Congress had “approved the bill providing
                            for American participation in the Cartago–San Marcos highway” have been
                            forwarded to the Bureau of Public Roads for its information. Copies of
                            your despatch no. 19 of September 21,<note n="29" xml:id="d206fn30">Not
                                printed.</note> and no. 22 of September 23, 1937, were also referred
                            to the Bureau of Public Roads.</p>
                        <p>It is noted that you were informed by the Minister of Foreign Affairs of
                            Costa Rica that his Government accepts without reservation the proposals
                            for participation in the construction of the section of the
                            Inter-American Highway contemplated in your note no. 6 of September 16,
                            that the proposal would immediately be sent to Congress, and that he
                            would inform you of the disposition of the constitutional Congress of
                            the Republic toward the bill as soon as it should be expressed.</p>
                        <p>No subsequent despatch which has reached the Department has stated that
                            this promised formal communication on the subject had been received by
                            you. The note which the Chargé d’Affaires was directed, in the
                            Department’s instruction no. 387 of February 19, 1937, to address to the
                            Costa Rican Government, stated in conclusion that “as soon as my
                            Government shall be informed that the Costa Rican Government has
                            definitively announced that it desires to proceed with the proposed road
                            construction along the lines indicated, my Government will be ready to
                            begin at once its part of the work.”</p>
                        <p>If on receipt of this instruction you shall not already have received and
                            forwarded to the Department the formal communication on the subject,
                            promised by the Minister of Foreign Affairs, you are requested to inform
                            the Department by telegraph whether the statements contained in your
                            despatches referred to above should be accepted by this Government as
                            the definitive announcement of the Costa Rican Government “that it
                            desires to proceed with the proposed road construction along the lines
                            indicated,” the receipt of which announcement was to be the occasion for
                            this Government “to begin at once its part of the work.”</p>
                        <p>It is the understanding of the Department of State that the Bureau of
                            Public Roads is in fact ready to begin this Government’s cooperation in
                            the proposed construction work; but your definite assurance is desired
                            whether any further pertinent communication from the <pb facs="0205" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/> Costa Rican Government should be awaited
                            before the cooperation actually begins.</p>
                        <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner
                                    Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>