<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-09-24T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-09-24T17:00:00-05:00" n="215" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d215">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3531/514: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                        Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-09-24T18:00:00-04:00">September 24, 1937—6
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 7:12 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>182. My 167, September 7, 5 [<hi rend="italic">6</hi>] p.m. The pertinent
                            portions of the Department’s telegram No. 83, September 3, 1 p.m. having
                            been communicated to the Ministry of Finance and the Exchange Control
                            Board, I wish to report as follows. There is still a tendency among
                            officials here to consider existing discriminatory exchange regulations
                            as a bargaining point. This was implied by the Under Secretary in a
                            subsequent conversation with a member of the Embassy when he indicated
                            that while Argentina may be willing to make the exchange offer a firm
                            one he fears that even if announcement should be made of the trade
                            treaty negotiations, bases for a satisfactory treaty might be lacking.
                            Under Secretary also pointed out that any concessions which either or
                            both sides may request would have to be made in substitution of those
                            formulated several years ago. He went so far as to suggest the
                            advisability of our sending a mission here to study Argentina’s requests
                            to which he was told that the concessions Argentina desired had, we
                            imagined, in the past been sent to the Argentine Embassy in
                            Washington.</p>
                        <p>Head of the Exchange Control Office told Ravndal<note n="5" xml:id="d215fn5">Christian M. Ravndal, American Consul at Buenos
                                Aires.</note> yesterday that he had advised Central Bank and Under
                            Secretary of Finance that now would be an opportune time to grant full
                            official exchange for imports from the United States provided we gave
                            satisfactory—though informal and not binding—assurances that trade
                            agreement negotiations will lead up to suitable concessions to
                            Argentina. Louro stated, however, that it was not his intention to use
                            exchange as a lever.</p>
                        <p>I hope to see the Minister of Finance early next week.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Weddell</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>