<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-10T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-10T15:00:00-05:00" n="333" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d333">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">832.00/1077: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de
                                        Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-10T17:00:00-03:00">November 10, 1937—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6:07 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>147. My 146, November 10, 3 p.m.<note n="1" xml:id="d333fn1">Not
                                printed.</note> The Minister for Foreign Affairs told me this
                            afternoon that he desired to explain to me, before any other Ambassador,
                            the political situation leading up to the events of today. He said that
                            the Government had found itself faced with an electoral campaign which
                            would have inevitably ended in a revolution. For this reason the
                            President had endeavored to find a compromise third candidate. With this
                            in mind he sent an emissary to the governors of the various states but
                            was unable to obtain the consent of the governors of Pernambuco and
                            Bahia.</p>
                        <p>This Minister added that the constitution of 1934 did not give the
                            Executive strong enough powers to govern the country properly. After
                            carefully sounding out public opinion in the different states, he has
                            put forth by decree a new constitution which will be submitted at an
                            early date to a plebiscite. This constitution will preserve the
                            democratic institutions but will give additional powers to the President
                            and will provide for his continuing in office for 6 years more. The
                            constitution makes special provision for the welfare of the laboring
                            classes.</p>
                        <p>The Minister added that it is not the intention of the Government to
                            persecute individuals and only a few politicians have been placed under
                            detention in their own homes. Furthermore, all of the members of the
                            Cabinet with the exception of the Minister of Agriculture are now in
                            agreement with the President. The Minister of Agriculture alone has
                            resigned and will shortly be replaced.</p>
                        <p>The Minister added that the Government intends to continue its present
                            foreign policy, and especially its cordial relations with the United
                            States, and has no imperialistic aims or designs. The Minister said that
                            the Government fully realized the need of foreign capital <pb facs="0323" n="313" xml:id="pg_313"/> and assistance in developing
                            the nation and he explained that the Government intends to pursue a very
                            liberal policy with respect to foreign capital and foreigners who have
                            legitimate interests in Brazil.</p>
                        <p>The Minister asserted emphatically that integralism had no part
                            whatsoever in the present change. He characterized the Integralistas as
                            “clowns in the political circus” and nothing more. In fact, he said that
                            one of the primary reasons for the coup of today came from the
                            President’s realization that decisive action was necessary to “put the
                            brakes” on the growing Integralista movement.</p>
                        <p>The Minister earnestly hopes that the United States will adopt an
                            attitude of sympathy and understanding toward the present changes.</p>
                        <p>In my opinion the coup of today is the climax of a carefully prepared
                            plan. I believe that it was the President’s intention, however, to put
                            it into effect next week and that the action of today was precipitated
                            by Deputy Machado’s reading of the manifesto yesterday.</p>
                        <p>I might add that I am a little skeptical about the effective
                            “preservation of democratic institutions” under the new
                            constitution.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>