<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-06-16T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-06-16T11:00:00-05:00" n="354" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3231/1176: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Scotten</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de
                                        Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-06-16T13:00:00-03:00">June 16, 1937—1
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 1:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>67. For the Under Secretary. In a conversation with the Minister for
                            Foreign Affairs<note n="29" xml:id="d354fn29">Mario de Pimentel Brandão,
                                Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note> last night the latter
                            informed me of the receipt by the President of a letter from Aranha
                            reporting a conversation with Mr. Welles and stating that the latter had
                            taken a firm stand and had called Aranha’s attention to the preferential
                            treatment given by Argentina to the British, although Great Britain did
                            not accord to Argentina the same favorable treatment which the United
                            States extended to Brazil and that Mr. Welles felt that on account of
                            the political relations between the United States and Brazil the latter
                            should be willing to extend better treatment to the United States than
                            is accorded at present. The letter mentioned above is probably the one
                            referred to in the Department’s 36.</p>
                        <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs added that he considered Mr. Welles to
                            be “absolutely right” in his stand and that just before the Minister of
                            Finance departed he, the Minister for Foreign Affairs, had again
                            endeavored to impress upon him that because of the political relations
                            between the two countries he should be willing to waive the immediate
                            material benefits which Brazil derived from the present arrangement with
                            Germany. He added that Souza Costa had replied that the political side
                            of the question did not interest him and that he was only interested in
                            the material side. He then added that he was convinced that the attitude
                            of the Minister of Finance in the forthcoming negotiations in Washington
                            would depend largely upon the degree of firmness with which he was
                            treated by the State Department. He said that he was convinced Souza
                            Costa would endeavor in every way to secure our consent to a renewal of
                            the agreement with Germany with possibly some slight concessions to us.
                            He felt that if our stand was firm, however, Brazil would do away with
                            this agreement.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Scotten</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>