<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on International Economic Affairs
                    ( (Feis))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d389</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">389</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="389"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d389">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.51/1244</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Adviser on International
                        Economic Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Feis</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-22">November 22,
                            1937</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Aranha<note n="46" xml:id="d389fn46">Oswaldo Aranlia, Brazilian Ambassador in
                        the United States.</note> called upon Mr. Welles further to discuss the
                    Brazilian debt problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Welles informed him of the observations that had been made by Mr. White<note
                        n="47" xml:id="d389fn47">Francis White, Executive Vice President and
                        Secretary of the Foreign Bondholders Protective Council, Inc.</note>
                    regarding the inauguration of discussions. The Ambassador said that he could not
                    go to New York tomorrow (and Mr. White could not come to Washington because of a
                    previous engagement with the mission from the City of Danzig); it was therefore
                    agreed that the beginning of discussion should be postponed until Mr.
                        Clark,<note n="48" xml:id="d389fn48">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., President of the
                        Foreign Bondholders Protective Council, Inc.</note> who is now in Utah,
                    could come to Washington, which according to Mr. Clark’s present schedule would
                    have been some time next week. After discussion it was decided that I should
                    inform Mr. White that the protraction of delay was greatly to be regretted
                    because the Ambassador would have to leave shortly for Brazil, and that Sunday
                    would be a good day for the Ambassador, and that therefore I should ask Mr.
                    White to inquire of Mr. Clark whether he could hasten his return and meet with
                    the Ambassador on Sunday. (This I did subsequently.)</p>
                <p>A general discussion regarding the possible bases of discussion with the Council
                    ensued. The Ambassador stated that he thought Souza Costa, the Minister of
                    Finance, was making a special effort to resume some payment on the American
                    debt. But he also was strongly of the opinion that the only form of settlement
                    that would interest the Brazilian authorities would be a permanent settlement
                    which would result in one new type of Brazilian security to be exchanged for all
                    types of dollar securities. The Ambassador argued that this would be to American
                    advantage since the American holdings of Brazilian state and city loans were so
                    much greater proportionately than the American holdings of Federal loans. He
                    brought out the fact that Argentina had sustained full payment on its Federal
                    loans while the provinces had gone into default.</p>
                <p>I merely stated that I could not talk for the Council, that I assumed the Council
                    would be willing to discuss a permanent settlement if the Brazilian authorities
                    were prepared to make an offer which it could recommend as satisfactory to the
                    bondholders as a permanent offer. <pb facs="0368" n="358" xml:id="pg_358"/> I
                    remarked that I had to point out that the Council was naturally apprehensive
                    lest the Brazilian authorities would confront it with a permanent offer
                    calculated on a greatly reduced capacity for payment corresponding to the coffee
                    price lower than at any time in the recent past.</p>
                <p>I am frankly afraid that this question of permanent versus temporary settlement
                    is going to be a great source of difficulty. I rather gather from the
                    Ambassador’s incidental remarks that he was of the opinion that the whole spirit
                    in Brazil was against the payment of foreign debt. I received the distinct
                    impression that the Ambassador had not been consulted regarding the method of
                    handling foreign debts, and felt that the situation was being exploited in
                    Brazil with the hope of getting rid of the Brazilian foreign debt (or at least
                    to reduce the service tremendously), and that he further felt the Brazilian
                    authorities did not fear the consequences of action of this type. In that
                    connection I took occasion to emphasize to him the great number of American
                    holders of Brazilian securities and to remark that cessation of payment by
                    Brazil would be regarded as an injurious action by these bondholders.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador did not manifest his usual spirit of assurance.</p>
                <p>He incidentally gave as his opinion the prophecy that Brazil would not pay
                    anything, at any rate in the immediate future, on its European debt.</p>
                <p>I telephoned immediately thereafter to Mr. White and gave him the substance of
                    the preceding. He said he would telephone Mr. Clark tomorrow morning and after
                    talking with Mr. Clark would telephone us and possibly also the Ambassador.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
