<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-11-09T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-11-09T12:00:00-05:00" n="435" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d435">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.2531/212: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Chargé in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Frost</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-11-09T12:00:00-05:00">November 9,
                                1937—noon</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>48. Your 65 and 69 of October 29 and November 2, 1937.</p>
                        <p>(1) The Chilean substitute text for paragraph 3 is not acceptable for
                            inclusion in the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> because it would
                            appear to constitute recognition by this Government of inequitable
                            treatment of American trade. You are therefore requested to continue
                            negotiations with a view to reaching the best agreement possible in
                            respect of exchange which does not embody a recognition of
                            discriminatory treatment.</p>
                        <p>The Chilean Government has repeatedly given assurances orally and in
                            writing that it intends to abolish exchange restrictions on trade with
                            the United States as soon as conditions permit. It would appear
                            incidentally that it would have a good effect on public opinion in the
                            United States, particularly among the financial and export <pb facs="0423" n="413" xml:id="pg_413"/> communities, were the Chilean
                            Government to make in the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> a clear
                            declaration of its intention to abolish exchange restrictions on trade
                            as soon as may be possible. If you believe that a better exchange
                            provision cannot be agreed upon, you are requested to seek as paragraph
                            3 of the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> the following, which is
                            merely a repetition of previous assurances: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Government of Chile undertakes to abolish as soon as
                                    possible all forms of exchange control affecting the transfer of
                                    payment for articles the growth, produce or manufacture of the
                                    United States.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>It should be clearly understood that the foregoing proposed provision
                            does not cover the question of the exchange treatment which this
                            Government expects from Chile pending the abolition of exchange
                            control.</p>
                        <p>(2) Considering that the provisions of the proposed <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> are particularly limited in their scope, this
                            Government does not believe that it would be advisable to make provision
                            for a joint committee similar to the committees established by Chile and
                            Peru and Chile and Ecuador. This Government would be glad, however, to
                            give appropriate consideration to any definite proposals in this respect
                            which the Chilean Government might later wish to communicate.</p>
                        <p>(3) In regard to the recommendation of the Treaty Commission of the
                            Foreign Office that the treatment accorded three frontier countries be
                            excepted from most-favored-nation treatment granted other countries in
                            future agreements, this Government considers that to accept this
                            proposal would establish a precedent for new exceptions to the
                            most-favored-nation principle such as to undermine its entire liberal
                            trade policy including its trade agreements program. The existing <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> does not provide for such
                            exceptions. Señor Pereira, First Secretary of the Chilean Embassy, in a
                            conversation with officers of the Department on October 21 indicated
                            that his Government would be disposed to omit in the <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> exceptions on the part of Chile. If, however,
                            the Foreign Office should be insistent in the matter, you may offer the
                            following counter proposal: Strike out the period after the word
                            “Agreement” in numbered paragraph 4, and insert in lieu thereof a
                            semicolon and the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="flushleft">“and this Agreement shall not apply in respect
                                    of advantages now accorded or which may hereafter be accorded by
                                    the United States of America or the Republic of Chile to
                                    adjacent countries in order to facilitate short frontier
                                    traffic.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Please communicate orally to the Foreign Minister the Department’s
                            position concerning the points mentioned above and keep the Department
                            informed of further developments by telegraph.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>