<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Ecuador ( (Gonzalez) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d522</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">522</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectaC46Ncpjf3NEb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011129"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Trade balance</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="522"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d522">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.2231/207</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Ecuador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gonzalez</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 919</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Quito</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-10-09">October 9,
                            1937</date>.<lb/>[Received October 18.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Department’s telegram No.
                    42 of October 6th, 7 p.m., 1937, and in confirmation of my telegram No. 57 of
                    October 8th, 4 p.m., 1937, I have the honor to report that I interviewed the
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs yesterday morning during which we discussed the
                    situation which has arisen because of his insistence upon the inclusion of the
                    Ecuadorean trade balance clause in the proposed trade agreement. I anticipated
                    no success in persuading him to recede sufficiently from the position taken in
                    view of his previous categorical statements on the subject and his assertion
                    that the President and the Minister of Finance share the same views.
                    Notwithstanding, I thought it desirable to go over the whole question again in
                    the hope that he might reconsider his position.</p>
                <p>I told the Foreign Minister that my Government had learned with keen regret of
                    the incident which had developed in the negotiations, and that it was not
                    disposed to take the step of considering the suspension of the negotiations
                    pending a frank and thorough <pb facs="0524" n="514" xml:id="pg_514"/>
                    discussion of the conflict which had developed. I then permitted him to read a
                    memorandum in which I had incorporated the three points made in the Department’s
                    telegram under reference.</p>
                <p>The Minister immediately replied that the situation has not changed and that he
                    must state categorically that his Government is not in a position to abandon the
                    conditional trade balance clause. He then proceeded to cite arguments previously
                    presented and he emphasized, in particular, that the abandonment of this clause
                    would imply the abrogation of the several Commercial Treaties recently or about
                    to be concluded by Ecuador with foreign countries. He stated that the primary
                    purpose of the clause and the policy based thereon, is to stimulate foreign
                    markets for Ecuadorean products, and that the policy has had signal success in
                    support of which he referred to the increase in exports to Germany, France and
                    Japan. He also stated that the policy has been a means of increasing the price
                    of many Ecuadorean products, especially vegetable ivory which is now being
                    purchased in large quantities by Japan. He said that in previous years the price
                    had been so low that Ecuadoreans were little disposed to collect the nut, but
                    now with the increased demand and the easy placing of this product in foreign
                    markets, the price has improved and there has been a consequent increase in
                    exportation. The Minister also stated that the abandonment of the trade balance
                    clause would involve a complete disregard of the pertinent law. I ventured to
                    point out that it is my understanding that the clause is not the subject of a
                    law but of an Executive Decree, in view of which an amendment or change would
                    seem to require action only by the Executive Department.</p>
                <p>At this point I called to his attention the statistics on export trade for the
                    first seven months of this year (see my despatch No. 916, October 4, 1937<note
                        n="53" xml:id="d522fn53">Not printed.</note>), and explained that exports to
                    Japan, France and Germany appear to have increased about 21,000,000 sucres, but
                    that this increase has been made at the expense of exports to the United States
                    inasmuch as a corresponding decrease seems to have occurred in their value.
                    Under these circumstances the consequences of the policy seem to be a direct
                    dislocation of the exports from their natural channels. The Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs immediately replied that this dislocation of trade is due to the policy
                    but also to the fact that the price paid for the articles is higher in those
                    countries than in the American market which accounts for their being diverted to
                    those markets. I would add parenthetically that I learned this morning that this
                    question was bitterly debated in Quito a few days ago at a bankers conference on
                    the internal credit situation. One banker pointed out forcibly that the Central
                    Bank of Ecuador now has in its <pb facs="0525" n="515" xml:id="pg_515"/>
                    portfolio credits of 14,000,000 sucres of askimarks, and he charged the Board of
                    the Central Bank as being directly responsible for the present stringent credit
                    situation. He added that the higher prices paid by Germany is a myth since they
                    are entirely dependent on the quotation of the askimark in sucres which he
                    considers excessively high. He further said that the present accumulation of
                    credits in Germany might be better described as the poor country of Ecuador’s
                    having made a loan to Germany in that amount.</p>
                <p>The Minister then proceeded to state that Ecuador is a small country and that it
                    cannot afford to make any innovations in the restrictive systems practiced by
                    the larger countries. I immediately pointed out that we had already concluded
                    trade agreements on the unconditional principle with Costa Rica,<note n="54"
                        xml:id="d522fn54">Signed November 28, 1936, Department of State Executive
                        Agreement Series No. 102, or 50 Stat. 1582; see also <ref
                            target="frus1936v05#pg_373">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1936, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 373</ref> ff.</note> Honduras<note
                        n="55" xml:id="d522fn55">Signed December 18, 1935, Executive Agreement
                        Series No. 86, or 49 Stat. 3851; see also <ref target="frus1935v04#pg_729">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 729</ref> ff.</note> and
                        Nicaragua,<note n="56" xml:id="d522fn56">Signed March 11, 1936, Executive
                        Agreement Series No. 95, or 50 Stat. 1413; see also <ref
                            target="frus1936v05#pg_782">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1936, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 782</ref> ff.</note> and that the
                    position of those countries appeared to be in a great number of respects
                    analogous to that of Ecuador. The Minister immediately changed his tactics and
                    replied that Ecuador could not afford to make any sacrifices.</p>
                <p>The Minister then referred to financial conditions within the country and stated
                    that his Government could not afford to reduce substantially its customs
                    revenues. I stated that while my Government is seeking to stabilize customs
                    charges and to reduce excessive rates, it would be disposed to view the
                    situation sympathetically and not demand more than Ecuador is in a position to
                    grant.</p>
                <p>I then asked the Foreign Minister whether he would be disposed to reconsider his
                    position in the light of the points made in the Department’s telegram under
                    reference. I added that it would seem desirable in doing so to determine whether
                    the consequence of a change in the principles of Ecuadorean commercial policy
                    would be as detrimental economically to the country as he seemed to think. In
                    this connection I ventured to express the opinion that Ecuador’s adoption of the
                    unconditional most-favored-nation principle would be an important contribution
                    to the improvement of world trade which, according to my knowledge of local
                    economic conditions, could be made without any sacrifice to national economy. I
                    also reminded him that the Constituent Assembly has designated a special
                    committee to formulate a complete plan for the financial and economic
                    reorganization of the country and that he might desire to obtain their views.
                    The Chairman of this Committee has broad views and I intend to discuss with him
                    the principles and reasons of our trade policy which <pb facs="0526" n="516"
                        xml:id="pg_516"/> may be helpful. The Foreign Minister agreed to reexamine
                    the whole matter and to consult again with the President of Ecuador and the
                    Minister of Finance. Inasmuch as today through the 12th are local holidays I do
                    not believe that a decision in the matter will be taken before the end of next
                    week at the earliest.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Antonio C. Gonzalez</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
