<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-03-20T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-03-20T11:00:00-05:00" n="534" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d534">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">838.51/3291: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-03-20T11:00:00-05:00">March 20, 1937—11
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 4:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>8. I have just presented orally to the Foreign Minister our Government’s
                            views as set forth in the Department’s instruction No. 458 of March 15.
                            In the ensuing conversation which lasted an hour the Foreign Minister
                            made the following statements:</p>
                        <p>The Haitian Government has no intention of granting customs control in
                            return for a refunding loan. If necessary, the Haitian Government would
                            be prepared to set up something in the bank in the nature <pb facs="0542" n="532" xml:id="pg_532"/> of an attenuated “bank plan”
                            to guarantee the service of the loan; so far, however, nothing of the
                            kind has been suggested and the Foreign Minister’s proposal to Schroder
                            has only dealt with this point by stating that the bank would remain the
                            exclusive agency for receiving Government moneys upon which there would
                            be a first lien for the service of the loan.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Minister has made the following proposal to the potential
                            lenders: the Haitian Government to sell them a two-thirds interest in
                            the bank for $1,000,000 in cash—all profits made by the bank to be
                            distributed prior to the sale—the capital to be increased by $500,000,
                            to be taken by the Haitian Government which would thus retain a
                            one-third interest in the bank with proportionate representation on the
                            Board of Directors; concessions under which the bank operates to be made
                            conterminous with the life of the loan.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Minister declared that he intended immediately to write
                            Schroder to clear up the discrepancy arising from statements being made
                            in the United States that the Haitian Government is willing to grant
                            customs control.</p>
                        <p>The Haitian Government has no special interest in buying German
                            construction material; if a reasonable refunding loan proposition were
                            presented to the Haitian Government which included the purchase of
                            American building material the Haitian Government would be better
                            pleased. However, if the only feasible refunding loan proposition made
                            to the Haitian Government comprises the purchase of German building
                            material the Foreign Minister was willing to buy with blocked marks just
                            as much of such material as he needed and no more; his position in this
                            respect remains as he had stated it to the fiscal representative for
                            communication to Schroder (see enclosure No. 2 to my despatch No. 426 of
                            February 25<note n="18" xml:id="d534fn18">Not printed.</note>).</p>
                        <p>I spent some time stressing the considerations set forth in section II of
                            the Department’s instruction under reference. The Foreign Minister said
                            he understood these points and that he was prepared to take all
                            necessary precautions. I told him that, speaking personally, I had had
                            considerable opportunity to observe at first hand a [apparent omission]
                            to unload blocked marks as well as to unfreeze exchange credits of other
                            denominations and after pressing this point upon him in some detail he
                            did seem to be somewhat impressed.</p>
                        <p>As regards the point of granting customs control to bankers with whom
                            might be associated foreign bankers and through them foreign
                            governments, the Foreign Minister said that he knew nothing of any
                            foreign bankers being connected with the Schroder proposition. When I
                            asked him about Brown Bouverie and reminded him that when the Debachy
                                loan<note n="19" xml:id="d534fn19">See <ref target="frus1935v04#pg_667"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp.
                                    667</ref> ff.</note> was being peddled about this firm had been
                                <pb facs="0543" n="533" xml:id="pg_533"/> represented as having both
                            a contracting and a financing interest, he said that as far as he knew
                            they were only in it as contractors and he was unaware of their having
                            any interest in the financing of the scheme; he had thought that through
                            the London house of Schroder some English money might be participating
                            in the loan but he knew nothing definite even as to this and was unaware
                            of any other foreign money being involved. It was evident that the
                            Foreign Minister felt that he had made considerable progress in the
                            Schroder negotiations and was quite sanguine of the loan going through.
                            One interesting piece of information was that White, Weld and Co. had
                            recently sent a representative to see him. The Foreign Minister said he
                            told this representative that he had authorized Schroder to proceed with
                            the formulation of a loan proposition and the formation of an
                            underwritings group and had suggested that White, Weld might desire to
                            participate in the Schroder group. I take it that a permissible
                            inference therefrom is that White, Weld had nothing more attractive to
                            offer than Schroder. The Foreign Minister agreed that if in spite of his
                            expectations the loan were to break down on the question of customs
                            control it was better to know it at once than to proceed further under a
                            misapprehension, and it was desirable to clear this up and bring the
                            matter to a head as soon as possible; he also admitted that if the loan
                            were to break down it was high time to proceed actively with the
                            negotiations for a protocol terminating our financial control.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gordon</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>