<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-04-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-04-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="608" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d608">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.52/2164</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of
                                State</hi><note n="9" xml:id="d608fn9">This memorandum, together
                                with one on the Pan American Highway (not printed), was sent to the
                                Ambassador in Mexico under cover of a personal letter dated April
                                25, 1937 (not printed). “With respect to the agrarian claims”,
                                Secretary Hull wrote, “you will understand that our conversation was
                                informal. Bach case arising will, of course, require careful
                                consideration of all the pertinent facts.”</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-04-20">April 20, 1937</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>During the call of Mexico’s Secretary of the Treasury<note n="10" xml:id="d608fn10">Eduardo Suarez.</note> and the Ambassador,<note n="11" xml:id="d608fn11">Dr. Francisco Castillo Nájera.</note> I
                            brought up the land seizure question and, after expressing lasting
                            friendship and interest, said that we were in entire sympathy with any
                            program to distribute lands among the peasants; that as friends and
                            neighbors we were encouraging the same thing in Cuba; and that we had no
                            sympathy with people from other countries going into Mexico and fleecing
                            the Mexican people by any sort of method. I said that any foreigner
                            going there and purchasing properties <pb facs="0616" n="606" xml:id="pg_606"/> for a trifle and later expecting the Mexican
                            Government to pay large amounts therefor, comparatively speaking, was
                            without any sympathy so far as I was aware or concerned; that the only
                            real question arising was whether it was possible for the Mexican
                            Government—when some citizen from this country, in good faith and in a
                            spirit of good will towards Mexico, had gone there and in a perfectly
                            honest manner purchased lands or other properties with no plan or
                            purpose to make undue or unreasonable profits or, as stated, to fleece
                            the Mexicans, but solely with a view to fair play and fair dealing—to
                            determine what would be reasonable and just in the way of compensation
                            when properties were thus taken; if so, that it would be much
                            appreciated by this Government and would enable us to be much more
                            helpful to the Mexican Government and the Mexican people than we
                            otherwise would be able in the future.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary of the Treasury promptly replied that he understood and
                            appreciated this viewpoint and that they were undertaking to work to
                            this end. He repeated it with emphasis.</p>
                        <closer><signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ull</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>