<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>115. Telegram From the Delegation at the SEATO Ministerial Council Meeting to
                    the to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d115</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">115</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-04-15T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-04-15T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-04-15T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-04-15T06:00:00-05:00" n="115"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                <head>115. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation at the SEATO Ministerial
                        Council Meeting</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d115fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> 3 PHIL (MA). Secret;
                        Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Repeated to Saigon,
                        Paris, London, and Vientiane. Passed to the White House on receipt in the
                        Department of State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Manila</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-04-15T19:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 15, 1964—7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Secto 49. For Acting Secretary from Secretary.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>As expected, communiqué presented main issue. Text key paragraphs
                        concerning Viet-Nam and Laos being transmitted septel.<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d115fn2">For full text of the communiqué, see <hi rend="italic"
                                >American Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1964</hi>, pp.
                            835–839.</note> As you will see, all members except French finally
                        supported strong paragraphs on Viet-Nam, with French submitting separate
                        paragraph expressing their sympathy for Viet-Nam effort but saying they did
                        not think it wise to join in declaration made by others.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Believe this result best we could have achieved in circumstances and at
                        least heartening evidence of solidarity other <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                            >SEATO</gloss> members. <persName corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve</persName> had
                        resisted stoutly all efforts produce more forthcoming French statement of
                        support during restricted session yesterday,<note n="3" xml:id="d115fn3">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s assessment of this
                            restricted session was transmitted in Secto 26 from Manila, April 14.
                            (Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                            27 VIET S)</note> and had simply gone on repeating that since French
                        believed effort in Viet-Nam doomed to failure they considered political
                        solution must be explored. Incidentally, in discussing escalation
                        possibility in restricted session, <persName corresp="#p_CMM1"
                            >Couve</persName> said that if French were consulted they would probably
                        be “rather against” extending the war to the North, which in his view would
                        have to include hostilities with China. This seems to clarify French
                        thinking this point and to negate <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                            >Alphand</persName>’s contrary interpretation. At same time, <persName
                            corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve</persName> said there certainly was no assurance
                        Chinese Communists in fact would accept a neutral Viet-Nam (even with US
                        forces withdrawn, which he had made clear in private conversation was what
                        French envisaged). Comment on this position seems superfluous, but at least
                        we are a shade clearer where French stand and they are at least willing to
                        express their sympathy for Vietnamese effort.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>As to impact on French-Vietnamese relations, <persName corresp="#p_PHQ1"
                            >Quat</persName> seemed both satisfied with strength of declarations by
                        other members and even somewhat pleased that French had finally ended up
                        with some affirmative [statement?] however mild. <persName corresp="#p_CMM1"
                            >Couve</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PHQ1">Quat</persName> have
                        also had two conversations here,<note n="4" xml:id="d115fn4">An account of
                                <persName corresp="#p_PHQ1">Quat</persName>’s discussions with
                                <persName corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve de Murville</persName> as
                            recounted to <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName> by
                                <persName corresp="#p_PHQ1">Quat</persName> is in Secto 68 from
                            Saigon, April 19. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> FR–VIET
                            S)</note> of which second was reported by <persName corresp="#p_PHQ1"
                            >Quat</persName> to be cordial and <persName corresp="#p_PHQ1"
                            >Quat</persName> considers door now open for French to initiate
                        discussions <pb facs="0268" n="240" xml:id="pg_240"/> that could include
                        economic issues as well as restoration of Ambassadors. I will want to
                        discuss this more fully in Saigon to assess what our next move and position
                        with <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> should be.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>As communique shows, all others remained solid throughout although
                        Pakistanis said little and Lopez<note n="5" xml:id="d115fn5">Salvador P.
                            Lopez, Secretary of Foreign Affairs of the Philippines.</note> made
                        abortive effort find common ground between our strong position and that of
                        French. Thanat, as expected, particularly firm. Essentially French were
                        isolated in restricted session but were not publicly pilloried except by
                        Thanat in opening public session, which <persName corresp="#p_CMM1"
                            >Couve</persName> did resent. Otherwise, he probably content with result
                        and had no latitude to go further. In this morning’s session on communique
                        he quickly suggested solution along lines ultimately reached.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>What French future in <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> is or should
                        be is a matter we should consider on my return, but there no indication here
                        French plan withdrawal. On contrary, given probable rigidity <persName
                            corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s instructions, <persName
                            corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve</persName> seemed to be going to some length to
                        avoid confrontation.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>As to greater individual contributions to Viet-Nam, I have obtained no
                        specific promises of material significance but believe communique and
                        atmosphere here have prepared way for us to keep pressure on.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>In Laos discussion, French proposed text that would have blamed “factions”
                        impartially but yielded to final text which refers “particularly” to
                        Communist violations.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Other communiqué issues revolved around Pakistani effort to invoke <gloss
                            target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> support as between member states and
                        non-member states, meaning of course India, and brief British effort express
                        concern on Malaysia. We stayed out of Pakistani fight, partly in order to
                        avoid disturbing Pakistanis and possibly upsetting their support for
                        Vietnamese paragraphs. Believe result innocuous.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>In sum, meeting closed on fairly high note, considering adamant French
                        position.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
