<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>227. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d227</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">227</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-07-01T18:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-07-01T18:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recDV1FNGQhoilizZ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90000897"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconstitution</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rectswnul2C5uzE9Y" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092233"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Non-alignment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-07-01T18:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-07-01T18:15:00-05:00" n="227"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d227">
                <head>227. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d227fn1">Source: Department of State, Secretary’s
                        Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 65 D 330. Secret. Drafted by Imhof and
                        approved by <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>. Copies were sent to
                        William and <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1964-07-01T19:15:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 1, 1964, 7:15 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Southeast Asia: The Polish Proposals; Discussion of the French Position;
                        Cambodia</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Johannes V. Imhof</persName>, French Desk, WE</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>, French
                        Embassy</item>
                    <item>M. Roger Duzer, Counselor, French Embassy</item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>, at his request, called
                    on the Secretary at 7:15 p.m. on July 1. One of the subjects discussed was
                    Southeast Asia.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of Laos.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion of the French Position</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary said he wished to discuss frankly the French position on Southeast
                    Asia and the points which troubled us. As we saw it, the French position was
                    based on the following points: 1) there should be no Communist takeover in
                    Southeast Asia; 2) the problem cannot be resolved by military means; 3) there
                    was no solid political structure in South Vietnam and it was unlikely that it
                    would be possible to create such a solid structure; 4) there should be a
                    political solution and France should reserve herself for an initiative in this
                    direction; 5) a political solution required strong U.S. military presence in the
                    area. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> did not dispute
                    any of these points.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that we had three problems with regard to this position.
                    One was fundamental, the two others were of a psychological nature. The
                    fundamental problem was that we did not understand what was meant by a
                    “political solution.” We realized, of course, that the war could not be won by
                    military means alone, but, in our opinion, a political solution for the area had
                    been reached through the 1954 and 1962 accords. We could not see any new
                    solution which would not be much worse for the interests of the West.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> agreed that the 1962
                    agreement on Laos was an acceptable political solution. All that was required
                    were the reconstitution of the three political tendencies and perhaps stronger
                    controls. As to Vietnam, the only new element to be added to the 1954 accords
                    was the concept of neutrality. The Secretary asked whether neutrality would
                    apply to both North and South Vietnam. Ambassador <pb facs="0562" n="534"
                        xml:id="pg_534"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said that it should, but suggested
                    that it should be applied to South Vietnam first and that it should be gradually
                    extended to the North.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that if the other side would leave South Vietnam alone, U.S.
                    forces would be withdrawn. The only reason for U.S. military presence was the
                    continued interference by Hanoi in South Vietnam. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> agreed that U.S. military presence in
                    South Vietnam was a result of the military activities of the other side. On the
                    other hand, the U.S. had exerted a dominant political influence in South Vietnam
                    immediately after the French withdrawal in 1954. The French had warned against
                    this because they had been concerned about the reactions of the other side. The
                    Secretary repeated that we had no desire to control South Vietnam and that our
                    presence there would end as soon as the other side stopped its interference.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said that the U.S. and
                    France had a different evaluation of the situation in Communist China. The
                    French felt that the Chinese were beset by their domestic problems. The Chinese
                    were also in difficulties with the Soviets. The only sure way to solve the
                    problem in Southeast Asia was a settlement guaranteed by the United States and
                    China. The Secretary said that we had such an agreement with regard to Laos; it
                    had not worked. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said
                    that Laos had only been a partial settlement which had not worked because of the
                    continued war in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he wanted to mention the two other points in the French
                    position which gave us difficulties. He noted French skepticism about the
                    possibility of creating a viable political structure in South Vietnam. Yet, the
                    French could be of great help in creating such a viable structure by using their
                    influence. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> asked what
                    France could do. Should it give advice to the Vietnamese politicians? The
                    Secretary said that France should state openly that it is opposed to a Communist
                    takeover of the area and that it was prepared to cooperate with South Vietnam to
                    this end. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> felt that
                    France had already made it clear that she was opposed to a Communist
                    takeover.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that the other point concerned U.S. military presence in the
                    area, the need for which France appeared to recognize. On this, we could use
                    some moral support. Standing aside and equating U.S. with Communist presence was
                    definitely not helpful. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>
                    said that he recognized the difficulties. He alluded to France’s own experience
                    in Indochina until 1954. He recognized that France had received material support
                    from the United States. Nevertheless, the war had cost France $8.5 billion and
                    she had to fight the war alone. The Secretary said that it had always been his
                    view that the West had made mistakes with regard to Indochina in the 1953–54
                    period.</p>
                <pb facs="0563" n="535" xml:id="pg_535"/>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said that it was his
                    personal opinion that a choice would have to be made sooner or later with.
                    regard to the Vietnamese problem. The Secretary reiterated that if Peking and
                    Hanoi would leave Southeast Asia alone, there would be no need for U.S. presence
                    in the area. As long as this was not the case, the U.S. would remain. He said
                    that if the French were to tell this to the Chinese, this would be an accurate
                    statement of U.S. policy. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> said that it was necessary to talk to the Chinese. The
                    Secretary said that we have indeed talked to the Chinese. Perhaps we have talked
                    more seriously with the Chinese than any other Western nation that has
                    diplomatic relations with Communist China. The absence of such relations between
                    the U.S. and China was no obstacle to serious talks. We have not ignored China
                    but we haven’t liked what we have heard in these talks. We want a decision from
                    the Chinese that they, as well as North Vietnam, will cease their interference
                    in South Vietnam and Laos.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that there were indications that an important meeting is
                    currently going on in Hanoi. He could also tell Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> in confidence that we had closely
                    watched the situation on the southern border of China and that there had been no
                    Chinese troop movements to the South. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> suggested that perhaps a political solution with regard
                    to Laos was in the offing. The Secretary said that we wanted to return to the
                    1962 accords.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he wanted to be brutally frank. It appeared to him that
                    there were people in Paris—he did not know who they were—who seemed to interpret
                    U.S. actions on the world scene as an attempt to replace and to diminish French
                    influence. Nothing could be further from the truth. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> interjected that he could assure the
                    Secretary that neither he, nor Couve, nor, he thought, General <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> held this view. The Secretary said
                    that, on the contrary, we would be delighted to see an extension of French
                    influence in Southeast Asia, in Africa and in other parts of the world. There
                    have been reports that the French wish to extend their influence in the Congo.
                    Nothing would please us more. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> said that since the last war the U.S., as the dominant
                    power, had been thrust into a position where it had to exert its influence. He
                    said this had been a good thing and had helped to ensure peace. On the other
                    hand, it had led to a deep involvement of the United States in certain areas,
                    such as Southeast Asia. He referred to our initial support of Diem and alluded
                    to <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> activities in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that seen from Europe, Southeast Asia seemed very far away.
                    We, on the other hand, were an Atlantic as well as a Pacific power and the
                    security of Asia was as important to us as the security of Europe. To us, the
                    defense of South Vietnam has the same significance as the defense of Berlin.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> disputed <pb
                        facs="0564" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/> this. He felt the situations were not
                    comparable. The stakes in Europe were enormous. The loss of Berlin would shake
                    the foundations of Western security. On the other hand, if we were to lose South
                    Vietnam we would not be losing much.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that if we were to pull out of South Vietnam our guarantees
                    with regard to Berlin would lose their credibility. It was all part of the same
                    struggle, to prevent an extension of Communist influence. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said that an agreement on Vietnam with
                    guarantees would not have the effect of lessening Western confidence in U.S.
                    guarantees. The Secretary pointed out that we already have such an agreement on
                    South Vietnam. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said
                    that we had not signed the agreement. The Secretary said that we had
                    nevertheless accepted it.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that the reason why we have allies is that we believe in the
                    right of nations to independence. We have 42 allies. Nevertheless, we are not
                    troubled by the concept of non-alignment and neutralism as long as it is
                    genuine.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> wondered what could be
                    done in practical terms. He said that with regard to Southeast Asia, we appear
                    to have a difference of opinion and we were going along different paths. The
                    Secretary asked precisely what was the difference of opinion. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> said France believed there
                    should be a negotiated agreement. The Secretary said that we already have the
                    1954 and 1962 agreements. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> suggested that perhaps all that was needed was the 1954
                    agreement with new guarantees and new controls. The Secretary asked why France
                    did not say so publicly and offer her cooperation to South Vietnam. He said that
                    Saigon did not know what France meant by a “political solution”. Did it mean the
                    inclusion of the Vietcong in the government? Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> admitted that he did not know. He
                    reviewed General <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s approach to
                    the Algerian problem: <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> had a
                    policy—a negotiated settlement. The details, the means to get there, varied
                    depending on day-to-day developments.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that it was distressing that France used the term
                    “neutralization” without giving it any concrete contents. Used in this manner,
                    the concept becomes negative and creates the impression that France does not
                    really care about the security of the area. The terms “neutralization” and
                    “political solution” without concrete contents are merely words, not a policy.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> felt that these words
                    nevertheless expressed a policy, a direction. He felt that a choice would have
                    to be made, and although he did not wish to exaggerate the importance of the
                    coming elections, he felt that the choice would be reached more easily once the
                    elections are over. The Secretary assured Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> that the elections played no role in this. The President
                    had made this quite clear. He had heard the <pb facs="0565" n="537"
                        xml:id="pg_537"/> President say “I don’t have to be re-elected President,
                    but I have to be President while I am President”. Moreover, no U.S. President,
                    before or after the elections, would pull out of Southeast Asia as long as the
                    other side interferes. On the other hand, we would pull out tomorrow if the
                    other side would leave Southeast Asia alone. The Secretary said that his brief
                    trip to Vietnam had convinced him that the country, if it were left in peace,
                    would not only be viable but could be an example to this entire part of the
                    world, thanks to a large extent to what the French had done there in the past.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> agreed. He observed
                    that the French, while in the area, had always found it necessary to have an
                    agreement with the Chinese.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said the question was how to get Chinese assent to a solution. He
                    said Soviet assent in Europe had been accomplished through our defensive
                    arrangements. Only when the Soviets became convinced that they would face a
                    major risk in stirring up trouble in Europe did they assent to actual
                    conditions. Obviously, this lesson must be applied in Asia with regard to the
                    Chinese. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> agreed that
                    Moscow had come to know the risks involved. He was not sure that this applied to
                    China. He did not think the Chinese realized that local actions in Southeast
                    Asia—infiltrations in South Vietnam and Laos—could eventually create the risk of
                    a destruction of China. The Secretary said that the French should make the
                    Chinese aware of the risks. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> said he thought that this had already been done; on the
                    other hand, the U.S. had not as yet made a statement to this effect.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that the appearance of a division of the West with regard to
                    Southeast Asia had a definite bearing on the problem and made a solution more
                    difficult. He said the French should tell the North Vietnamese that they must
                    leave South Vietnam alone and that France will oppose them if they continued
                    their interference. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>
                    asked precisely what the Secretary would wish the French to convey to the
                    Chinese. The Secretary said France should tell the Chinese (1) that if the
                    Chinese and North Vietnamese leave Southeast Asia alone, France will use its
                    influence to see to it that these countries will not present any threat to
                    China; and (2) that if the Chinese do not leave Southeast Asia alone, France
                    will oppose them. The Secretary asked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1"
                        >Alphand</persName> to put these two points to the French Foreign Minister.
                    He said that it seemed to him that a genuinely non-aligned Southeast Asia was
                    also in the interest of France. A non-aligned Southeast Asia would in all
                    likelihood turn toward Paris.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of Cambodia.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
