<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-08-25T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-08-25T07:00:00-05:00" n="325" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d325">
                        <head>325. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d325fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15–1 VIET S. Secret;
                                Flash; <gloss target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>. Also sent to
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, the Department of Defense,
                                and the White House and repeated to CINCPAC. Received at 9:18
                                a.m.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-08-25T20:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">August 25,
                                        1964—8 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>555. CINCPAC for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>. Following the
                            meeting of the <gloss target="#t_MRC1">MRC</gloss> on 25 August, the
                            following proclamation was made: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The <gloss target="#t_MRC1">MRC</gloss> meeting on the morning
                                    of 25 August 1964 at the office of the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> Commander in Chief has resolved the
                                    following:</p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>To revoke constitution of 16 August 1964.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>To call an urgent meeting of the <gloss target="#t_MRC1">MRC</gloss> to elect a new Chief of State.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Following the election of a new Chief of State, the <gloss target="#t_MRC1">MRC</gloss> will be dissolved and will
                                        return the powers of leadership to the armed forces of the
                                        Republic of Vietnam in order to oppose Communism,
                                        neutralism, colonialism and every form of treacherous
                                        dictatorship.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The new Chief of State will be entrusted with the
                                        responsibility of calling a national assembly in order to
                                        develop the national structure in going along with the
                                        aspirations of all the people in a position <pb facs="0732" n="704" xml:id="pg_704"/> which will oppose Communism,
                                        neutralism, colonialism and each form of treacherous
                                        dictatorship and reconstruct the nation in democratic
                                        freedom.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>In the meantime, the work of managing the nation will be
                                        carried out by the present government.</item>
                                </list>
                                <p>Saigon, 25 August 1964</p>
                                <p>Steering Committee of the <gloss target="#t_MRC1">MRC</gloss>”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>I called on <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> at 4:00 pm to
                            obtain his interpretation of recent events to include the meaning of the
                            very general language of the foregoing proclamation. He gave me the
                            following information.</p>
                        <p>The new Chief of State will be elected by the <gloss target="#t_MRC1">MRC</gloss> at a meeting in Saigon, 10:00 am, 26 August. All
                            Generals, including the four Dalat Generals, have been invited to
                            attend. <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> asked me if I
                            would pass the word to <persName corresp="#p_Minh1">Minh</persName> that
                            his presence would be appreciated in the interest of national unity. I
                            agreed to do so.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> explained that with the
                            dissolution of the <gloss target="#t_MRC1">MRC</gloss> there will be no
                            political body above the president who will appoint the members of the
                            executive, the key figures of the judiciary and the members of the
                            national assembly. Although the exact composition of the assembly is
                            still under study, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> is
                            thinking in terms of 300 members representing the various political and
                            religious groupings. He feels that it will take at least a couple of
                            weeks to get the assembly going whereas he expects to round out the
                            executive by the end of this week.</p>
                        <p>With regard to the executive, he intends to have a civilian vice
                            president and Vu Van Mau is still the front running candidate. The heads
                            of executive departments will be largely civilian; in fact, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> (who seems to have no doubt
                            that he will be elected president a second time) intends to have only
                            the Department of Defense headed by a military incumbent.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> stressed that all of this
                            arrangement was provisional and that, within a year, he hopes to have
                            drawn up a permanent constitution and be in a position to hold general
                            elections for a permanent assembly. For the next few days, the
                            government will continue to function as at present.</p>
                        <p>We then discussed some of the factors which have been in the background
                            of recent developments.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> says that he had no
                            particular trouble getting the Generals of the <gloss target="#t_MRC1">MRC</gloss> to agree with this sweeping concession to Buddhist
                            demand which results in the dissolution of the Council. (This easy
                            acquiescence is hard to believe.) He anticipates some trouble with the
                            Dai Viets but feels it will be manageable. He is particularly incensed
                            against Deputy Premier <persName corresp="#p_Hoan1">Hoan</persName> who,
                            in the midst of yesterday’s events, published a letter critical of
                                <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName>.</p>
                        <pb facs="0733" n="705" xml:id="pg_705"/>
                        <p>The master mind behind these incidents has been Buddhist leader,
                                <persName corresp="#p_TQ1">Tri Quang</persName>. His control of the
                            student rioters was proved by the quickness with which order was
                            restored in Saigon today after <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> agreed to his demands. <persName corresp="#p_TQ1">Tri Quang</persName> and his Buddhist colleagues have promised to
                            endorse <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName>’s actions and to
                            come out publicly for the first time against Communism.</p>
                        <p>Now the question is whether the Buddhists will keep their word and
                                <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> is clearly anxious.
                                <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> asked if I or other
                            Embassy representatives could see <persName corresp="#p_TQ1">Tri
                                Quang</persName> and urge upon him the essentiality of living up to
                            his part of the bargain. He described <persName corresp="#p_TQ1">Tri
                                Quang</persName> as a “type special”, more of a politician than a
                            bonze for whose power he, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName>
                            was obvious respect.</p>
                        <p>I pressed <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> hard on the
                            question of whether this was going to be a Buddhist government or a
                            national government, whether he would be Buddhist president or a
                            national president. He fought back hard on both points insisting that he
                            knew the importance of a national government and the impossibility of
                            winning the war without broad national support.</p>
                        <p>I asked him whether he feared a Catholic reaction at this time and I
                            received a negative reply. He would like to discuss his plans with the
                            Catholic leaders but unfortunately Archbishop Binh is out of town and
                            the new Papal Delegate, Palmas, has not yet presented his credentials. I
                            expressed the view that in spite of these circumstances he should
                            explain his position to the Catholics at an early date.</p>
                        <p>In closing, I asked <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> how I
                            should interpret these events to Washington where they were being
                            watched with deep concern. He replied that today’s decision marked the
                            withdrawal of the army from politics. Any other alternative would have
                            resulted in the use of armed force against fellow citizens, a solution
                            which he, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> found was
                            intolerable. If the Buddhists make good on their word, the
                            counterinsurgency program can proceed apace. If they do not, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> sees no military solution to
                            bring the war against the Viet Cong to a successful conclusion.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_TGMD1"><hi rend="strong">Taylor</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>