<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-02-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="33" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d33">
                        <head>33. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_FMV1" type="from">Michael V.
                                Forrestal</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d33fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Vietnam Country
                                File, Vol. 11, Memos and Misc. Secret and Personal. Published in
                                part in <hi rend="italic">Declassified Documents, 1975,</hi>
                                175B.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-02-04"><hi rend="italic">February 4,
                                1964</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>South Vietnam</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Herewith my overnight thoughts for your lunch today:<note n="2" xml:id="d33fn2">Reference is to a luncheon meeting at the White
                                House at 1:04 p.m. among the President, Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>. The meeting ended
                                at 2:45 p.m. Johnson Library, President’s Daily Diary) No record of
                                the meeting has been found, but see <ref target="#d34">Document
                                    34</ref> and <ref target="#d35">Document 35</ref>.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>If <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> must remain, the
                                military commander must be changed. The President might publicly
                                load <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> with full
                                responsibility for the whole U.S. effort in South Vietnam, giving
                                him as deputy the ablest, most modern-minded 3-star general we can
                                find. General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>
                                might fill the bill. He doesn’t have to have an extra star, if he is
                                acting as <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>’s
                                deputy.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Here in Washington we should get a Manager for South Vietnam. He
                                should be in the Department of Defense at a level which would permit
                                him to deal with the Under Secretaries and the Assistant Secretaries
                                of State and the Aid Agency Administrator. He should be <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s man. He should concern
                                himself with operations in South Vietnam and on policy matters he
                                should report to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>. I have in mind someone
                                like Vance, your brother <persName corresp="#p_MBD1">Bill</persName>, or possibly <persName corresp="#p_SP1">Solbert</persName>.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>We should set up immediately a group of about 10 people who would
                                meet together for approximately two weeks, completely free from all
                                other responsibilities, preferably not in Washington but possibly in
                                Honolulu or some reasonably secluded place, to think of specific
                                things which we should do to improve our effort inside South
                                Vietnam. Since we really do not have all of the best people for this
                                job in Washington, we should draw from the following sources: one or
                                two of the best people from <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>;
                                one or two from <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> in Saigon; one
                                or two from the Embassy in Saigon and/or State; one from the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>; one each from <persName corresp="#p_KMGVH1">Krulak</persName>’s shop and <gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss>; and possibly one from the academic
                                world like Fishel or Lucian Pye.<note n="3" xml:id="d33fn3">Wesley
                                    R. Fishel, Professor of Political Science at Michigan State
                                    University, and <persName corresp="#p_PL1">Lucian W.
                                        Pye</persName>, Professor of Political Science at
                                    Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</note>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SP1">Solbert</persName> could be the <pb facs="0088" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/> Chairman of such a group;
                                and we should be ruthless in providing him the time and resources of
                                the best people, regardless of their duties or rank.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>There should be another group assembled entirely from Washington
                                which should be working at the same time on diplomatic and military
                                plans for U.S. initiatives in the <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> area as a whole, principally outside South Vietnam.
                                Believe it or not, I would not be averse to having <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName> handling this one,
                                provided he had tough representation from all the schools of
                                thought.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_FMV1"><hi rend="strong">Michael V.
                                        Forrestal</hi></persName><note n="4" xml:id="d33fn4">Printed
                                    from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>