<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-11-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="423" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d423">
                        <head>423. Memorandum From the Chairman of the National Security Council
                            Working Group (<persName>Bundy</persName>) to the Secretary of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d423fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Bundy Files, Working Papers, Nov 1964, Vol. 1. Top Secret.
                                Also sent to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>. Also printed in <hi rend="italic">Pentagon Papers: Gravel Edition</hi>, vol. III,
                                pp. 646–650. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>’s
                                copy of this memorandum bears his handwritten notes reflecting the
                                discussion of these issues at the meeting at 5 p.m. on November 24.
                                (Johnson Library, National Security File, Vietnam Country File,
                                Courses of Action in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>) For a
                                record of the meeting, see <ref target="#d424">Document
                                424</ref>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-11-24"><hi rend="italic">November 24,
                                    1964</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Issues Raised by Papers on Southeast Asia</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Although the official comments are not all in at this writing, I think it
                            will be useful for your meeting this afternoon to have a list of the
                            issues that appear to one mind to warrant priority discussion. Some are
                            explicitly disagreed, others have been lurking and should be surfaced in
                            my judgment.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">1. Basic Issues as Between the
                                Options</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item><p>Is it true that the South Vietnam situation would deteriorate
                                    further under Option A even with reprisals, but stands a
                                    significant chance of improving under Option B or Option C?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Advocates of A maximize the
                                    chances of decay even under B and C, advocates of B and C think
                                    the lift from greater action could really take hold and move us
                                    forward in South Vietnam, whereas A is doomed. All concede there
                                    is some chance that the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                                    would come apart under any Option.</p></item>
                            <pb facs="0967" n="939" xml:id="pg_939"/>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item><p>Is the negotiating outcome under Option A (with or without US
                                    negotiating participation) likely to be clearly worse than under
                                    Option C?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Advocates of A doubt that it
                                    would be.</p></item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>What are the best estimates of the risks of major conflict under
                                Option B and Option C? If, as the intelligence paper states,<note n="2" xml:id="d423fn2">A copy of this paper, “Probable Communist
                                    Reactions to US Options B and C” (TS# 185782-a), November 19, is
                                    in Department of State, Bundy Files, Working Papers, Nov 1964,
                                    Vol. 1.</note> they are about the same as between Option B and
                                Option C at its highest, is there enough chance that C would succeed
                                before it reached this point to make a real difference on the risk
                                factor?</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>Is it true, as the draft paper states,<note n="3" xml:id="d423fn3"><ref target="#d418">Document 418</ref>.</note> that Option
                                B has the best chance of attaining our full objectives?</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item><p>As to our stakes in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>, is the
                                    paper valid as written, or should it be revised in the direction
                                    of the Joint Staff comments<note n="4" xml:id="d423fn4"><ref target="#d420">Document 420</ref>.</note> that loss of
                                        <gloss target="#t_SVN2">SVN</gloss> would be necessarily
                                    catastrophic? Is the analysis of the attitudes of non-Asian key
                                    allies right, and what weight should we give to this?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> The point of the Joint Staff
                                    comments really is that greater risks of major conflict are
                                    worth accepting in view of their view of the stakes. The Joint
                                    Staff view would also implicitly assign less weight to key
                                    non-Asian allies, and still less to the non-aligned
                                    countries.</p></item>
                            <label>F.</label>
                            <item><p>Can Option C be carried out in practice under the klieg lights
                                    of a democracy, in view of its requirement that we maintain a
                                    credible threat of major action while at the same time seeking
                                    to negotiate, even if quietly?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> this is a key point raised by
                                    advocates of A. The parallel to Korea in 1951–53 is forbidding.
                                    Even advocates of C concede the difficulties.</p></item>
                            <label>G.</label>
                            <item><p>Are we safe in assuming that <gloss target="#t_SVN2">SVN</gloss> can only come apart for morale reasons, and not
                                    in a military sense as well?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> The intelligence estimate is not
                                    confident on <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> “burst
                                    capabilities.” The President’s repeated concern on protecting
                                    the south has not really been met in these papers, but we have
                                    all felt that the purely military aspects of the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> could be contained. This is a
                                    first question to ask of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>.</p></item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0968" n="940" xml:id="pg_940"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">II. Issues Relating to the Immediate
                                Courses of Action (Section VII)</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item><p>Is our reprisal planning in proper shape to produce varied
                                    options on demand? Does it provide adequately for <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> participation?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> CINCPAC Frag Order No. 3 is the
                                    current basis of planning. It provides for optional clusters of
                                    targets, but no one option calls for less than about 175
                                    strikes, under very high damage criteria. Such a high order of
                                    action could throw off all calculations based on the theory of
                                    “squeeze” under Option C and even under Option B. As to <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> participation, the latest plans
                                    do crank this in, at some sacrifice of
                                destructiveness.</p></item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item><p>What do we mean to take as a basis for reprisal?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> We all agree that another Bien
                                    Hoa would call for reprisal, but it would help to refine our
                                    thinking somewhat further. Incidents not solely directed at the
                                    US would be desirable for political reasons. What kind might
                                    these be?</p></item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item><p>What sort of high-level statement is needed if we adopt the
                                    immediate program?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Should it be generalized, with
                                    the infiltration evidence speaking for itself separately, or
                                    should it make express use of the infiltration evidence? Is the
                                    latter wholly ready for surfacing? Is the new Jorden
                                        Report?<note n="5" xml:id="d423fn5">The first Jorden Report
                                        was released on December 8, 1961; see <ref target="frus1961-63v01"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                                Relations</hi>, 1961–1963, vol. I</ref>, pp.
                                        725–726. In the fall of 1964, a new report on infiltration
                                        was being considered. Sometimes called the new Jorden
                                        Report, it was published on February 27, 1965, under the
                                        title <hi rend="italic">Aggression From the North</hi>
                                        (Department of State Publication 7839).</note></p></item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">III. Issues Concerning the Execution
                                of Option A</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item><p>Can this Option really be extended to include continued
                                    (non-reprisal) actions against the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> even at a low scale?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> The longer draft<note n="6" xml:id="d423fn6">Presumably Bundy is referring to the
                                        100-page draft paper.</note> had so extended it. Most of us
                                    think this is a mistake in definition, in that any continued
                                    actions against the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> create
                                    international and other pressures and are an effect the early
                                    stages of Option C.</p></item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item><p>Could or should ground forces be put into northern <gloss target="#t_SVN2">SVN</gloss> even under this Option?</p>
                                <pb facs="0969" n="941" xml:id="pg_941"/>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Advocates of A urge this as a
                                    bargaining counter. Most of us think that, apart from lacking
                                    any military necessity in the absence of attacks on the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>, it would appear as a bluff and
                                    not help any negotiation.</p></item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item><p>Assuming the situation does deteriorate under this Option,
                                    should we let Vietnamese negotiations develop, or ourselves seek
                                    a forum?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> This is a less urgent issue, and
                                    perhaps cannot be answered now.</p></item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">IV. Issues Concerning the Execution of
                                Option B</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item><p>Should we hit major targets, especially airfields, at once, or
                                    only after and if the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> has
                                    hurt us from them?</p>
                                <p>Comment: Even under this Option, many of us feel the actions
                                    should be progressive, with the prospect of more to come at
                                    least as important psychologically as present damage. We all
                                    accept the will of the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> as
                                    the real target.</p></item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item><p>Is ground invasion of the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>
                                    (at Vinh per present plans) a military necessity or advantage
                                    that outweighs the increased risks the Chicoms would then come
                                    in force? (This applies to C as well as B.)</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> The intelligence estimate (p. 9
                                    of “Probable Communist Reactions,” dated 19 November) highlights
                                    this as significantly raising the odds. It would also tend to
                                    change our objectives in the eyes of the world. Is it worth
                                    it?</p></item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item><p>At what stage, if ever, might nuclear weapons be required, and
                                    on what scale? What would be the implications of such use?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> This is clearly a sensitive
                                    issue. The President may want a more precise answer than appears
                                    in the papers.</p></item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">V. Issues Concerning the Execution of
                                Option C</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item><p>Should ground forces be introduced into northern <gloss target="#t_SVN2">SVN</gloss> at the early stages?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> The pros and cons of this are
                                    argued in Section VII of the long draft.</p></item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item><p>Is our early targeting properly thought through?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> This is partly the question of
                                    whether to hit Phuc Yen early. But also some individual comment
                                    has highlighted the possible utility of focusing at length on
                                    low-key targets, not so much for the sake of damage as to show
                                    how helpless the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> is, cause
                                    it to strain <pb facs="0970" n="942" xml:id="pg_942"/> its
                                    security apparatus, and ask for help from the Chicoms in ways
                                    the Chicoms may not be able to give effectively. Also to keep
                                    our losses low. Such an undramatic “water drip” technique would,
                                    in the opinion of many Chicom experts, both hit <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> will harder than more dramatic
                                    attacks and strain the key <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>-Chicom relationships more. Put differently, this
                                    school of thought argues that dramatic acts, with probably
                                    higher US losses, would tend to knit the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> people and the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> and Chicoms; US losses are also a key factor in
                                        <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> morale, as their
                                    propaganda has shown for months. If we were acting with
                                    impunity, this would have a major effect, and the falseness of
                                    their propaganda would become a major weakness in their hold
                                    over their people.</p></item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item><p>How do we handle any early negotiations?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> This is the least satisfactory
                                    part of the present script. To keep up our show of determination
                                    and at the same time listen for nibbles is a tough job in any
                                    case. We need to consider use of third countries at the outset
                                    perhaps more.</p></item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item><p>Do we even listen to nibbles till we have established a clear
                                    “common law” pattern of attacks?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> The point is not made as clear as
                                    it should be. I think not.</p></item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">VI. Action Issues Applicable to any
                                Decisions</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>White House statement.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>High-level speech.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Congressional consultation, including whether Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> should testify if
                                Committees ask.</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>Key Allies—<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, Australia, New
                                Zealand, Thailand, Philippines. Individually or would we now form a
                                group as in Korea? (I am inclined against a formal group, with or
                                without publicity—the interests are too diverse.) <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>?</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item>US Government machinery. Do we not need a designated ExCom now,
                                with a subordinate working group?</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BWP1"><hi rend="strong">William P.
                                        Bundy</hi></persName><note n="7" xml:id="d423fn7">Printed
                                    from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>