<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-02-20T12:17:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-02-20T12:17:00-05:00" n="54" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d54">
                        <head>54. Memorandum for the Record of a Meeting, White House<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d54fn1"><p>Source: Johnson Library, National
                                    Security File, Vietnam Country File, Vol. IV, Memos and Misc.
                                    Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_FMV1">Forrestal</persName>. Copies of this memorandum were sent
                                    to <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName>.</p>
                                <p>Prepared for this meeting, which lasted 1 hour, was an agenda,
                                    annotated by <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                                        Bundy</persName>, which reads as follows:</p>
                                <p>“1. Situation Briefing (5 minutes); 2. Intelligence and
                                    Reporting, (A) Cooper Activities, (B) French Activities; 3.
                                    Operations, (A) Response to <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> Message, (B) Policy on Dependents [Bundy
                                    wrote at this point “P[resident] prefers”], (C) Other Matters;
                                    4. Diplomatic Problems, (A) Cambodia, (B) Laos, (C) Others; 5.
                                    North Viet-Nam, (A) Intelligence [Bundy wrote “increase
                                    efforts”], (B) Propaganda [Bundy wrote “increase”], (C)
                                    Operations; 6. Planning, (A) <persName>Johnson</persName>
                                    Subcommittee [Bundy wrote “Speed up”], (B) Question of Time
                                    Phase.” (Ibid.)</p></note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-02-20T12:17:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">February 20,
                                        1964, 12:17 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>South Vietnam</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The President met today with the Secretaries of State and Defense, the
                            Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, Director <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>, and the members of Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">William Sullivan</persName>’s committee
                            on policy and operations in South Vietnam.</p>
                        <p>After an intelligence briefing on the current situation and a full
                            discussion of the work of the committee, the President directed the
                            following actions:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Any requests for assistance or other Washington action from
                                Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> should be
                                given prompt and sympathetic response. Such staff work as may be
                                required to back up such requests in Washington should be given the
                                highest priority, so that decisions can be reached quickly.</item>
                            <pb facs="0122" n="94" xml:id="pg_94"/>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Contingency planning for pressures against North Vietnam should be
                                speeded up. Particular attention should be given to shaping such
                                pressures so as to produce the maximum credible deterrent effect on
                                Hanoi.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>For the time being, American dependents in Vietnam should be
                                encouraged to accept voluntary repatriation. Early next month, the
                                Secretary of Defense will consult with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> on whether dependents should
                                be evacuated and will make appropriate recommendations to the
                                President and the Secretary of State upon his return.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The Department of State will explore in a positive manner the
                                possibilities opened up by the recent proposals of Prince <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> for a conference in Phnom
                                Penh on the problem of Cambodian neutrality.<note n="2" xml:id="d54fn2">See <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy:
                                        Current Documents, 1964</hi>, p. 847, footnote
                                7.</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_FMV1"><hi rend="strong">M V
                                        Forrestal</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>