<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>69. Memorandum From the Secretary of State to the to the President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d69</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">69</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="69"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                <head>69. Memorandum From the <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d69fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        President’s Reading File: Lot 74 D 164. Secret; No Distribution.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-03-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 4, 1964</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">SUGGESTED ITEMS FOR EVENING READING</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">French Policy in Viet-Nam</hi>—Chip <persName
                        corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> met today with Couve in Paris and was
                    told that France has had no military or operational policy in Viet-Nam for the
                    past 9 years and, therefore, is not working against U.S. interests.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d69fn2">As reported in telegrams 4165 and 4173 from Paris, both
                        March 4. (Ibid., Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET
                        S)</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve</persName> made a personal suggestion, that a
                    “political objective”, such as ultimate mutual withdrawal of U.S. and Viet Cong
                    forces, would promote our military aims.<note n="3" xml:id="d69fn3">When the
                        Embassy in Saigon learned of this suggestion by <persName corresp="#p_CMM1"
                            >Couve de Murville</persName>, it cabled the Department of State that
                        such a proposal revealed a “very fundamental French misunderstanding of the
                        true nature of the Viet Cong.” In telegram 1713, March 9, the Embassy
                        explained that the Viet Cong were “indigenous communists” many of whom
                        derived from the Viet <persName corresp="#p_Minh1">Minh</persName> cadres
                        who remained in the south after 1954. They had to be eliminated or won over;
                        they could not be induced to withdraw in 1964 any more effectively than they
                        had been in 1954. The Embassy asked that this fact be stressed to the French
                        Government and added that, should South Vietnam learn that the United States
                        was “toying with such an idea,” the effect in Vietnam would be
                        “unfortunate.” (Ibid.) The White House copy is published in <hi
                            rend="italic">Declassified Documents, 1976</hi>, 211E.</note> He was not
                    suggesting a conference, although admitting that we might have to deal with the
                    Chinese Communists. <persName corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve</persName> did not respond
                    to <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName>’s mention of a French statement
                    on Viet-Nam but agreed that French official silence would be desirable.</p>
                <p>[Here follow items 2–7 which were unrelated to Vietnam.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Dean Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d69fn4">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
