<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Technical Advisers ( (Nufer, , Donnelly, and Turkel) ) to the
                    Ambassador in Cuba ( (Caffery))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-05-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-05-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="120"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d120">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3731/620</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The American Technical Advisers</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Nufer</hi>
                    </persName>, <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName>Donnelly</persName>, and <persName>Turkel</persName>
                    </hi>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="36" xml:id="d120fn36">Copy transmitted to the Department by
                        the Ambassador in Cuba in his despatch No. 399, May 4, 1934; received May
                        68.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-05-02">May 2,
                            1934</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Form of the Revised Reciprocity Treaty.</p>
                <p>When Mr. Nufer was in Washington the question arose as to the form of the revised
                    reciprocity treaty with Cuba. It was suggested that it might be preferable to
                    limit the treaty primarily to changes in duty preferences and to the binding of
                    maximum rates on specified articles, and for the Cuban Government to put into
                    effect, prior to the date of the treaty, a decree-law which would make all the
                    agreed-upon changes in duty rates, classifications and nomenclature.</p>
                <p>This decree-law would represent a revision of the present Cuban Customs Tariff,
                    and the tariff as thus revised would be the one on which the treaty would be
                    based. Obviously, this decree-law, or tariff revision, would provide no changes
                    in the present duty preferentials, which would be covered by the revised
                    treaty.</p>
                <p>The alternative to this would be to embody in the treaty itself all the changes
                    in duty rates, nomenclature and classification agreed upon in the course of our
                    discussions with the Cuban delegates.</p>
                <p>During the discussion in Washington it was suggested to Mr. Nufer that we
                    approach the Cuban delegates informally in this matter in order to ascertain
                    what would be their attitude toward these two methods. The Cuban delegates,
                    speaking informally and unofficially at <pb facs="0203" n="137" xml:id="pg_137"
                    /> a conference held on April 30, were unanimously in favor of what may be
                    termed the “Decree-Law” form.</p>
                <p>If it is agreed to adopt this form, the treaty would include, as already
                    mentioned, the percentages of duty preference to be accorded to each item, and a
                    list of items on which the rate of duty specified is to be the maximum rate of
                    duty during the life of the treaty.</p>
                <p>In our conference with the Cuban delegates we also brought up the subject of
                    binding certain classifications, especially in those instances where changes had
                    been made (which changes would, of course, be incorporated in the Decree-Law) in
                    order to eliminate or prevent future misclassifications. After discussing this
                    at length it was informally and tentatively agreed that the treaty might include
                    a provision to the effect that while the high contracting parties retain
                    complete liberty to alter classifications in the future, no percentage of
                    preferential may be decreased, and, in cases where the rate of duty is specified
                    as a maximum, such rates may not be increased as a result of any future
                    re-classification.</p>
                <p>The merits of the Decree-Law form are as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Simplicity of appearance, and saving of time in preparing the
                            treaty.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The changes in Cuba’s tariff structure will appear more as an
                            autonomous act.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>In the exceptional cases where increases in general duty are made,
                            they would be only indirectly attributable to the United States.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
