<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-01-17T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-01-17T11:00:00-05:00" n="219" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d219">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">816.01/366: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Chargé in El Salvador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">McCafferty</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-01-17T11:00:00-05:00">January 17, 1934—11
                                a.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1. President Sacasa has undertaken as of his own initiative to suggest
                            that he and the Presidents of Honduras, Guatemala and Costa Rica and the
                                <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> President of El Salvador reached an
                            agreement substantially as follows:</p>
                        <p>[Here follows text of draft agreement quoted in telegram No. 8, January
                            13, 1 p.m., from the Minister in Nicaragua, <ref target="#pg_226">page
                                226</ref>.]</p>
                        <p>President Sacasa has sent his cousin, Crisanto Sacasa, as his
                            representative to present the foregoing suggestion to the other
                            Presidents of Central America. His plan is understood to be to visit
                            Guatemala, Tegucigalpa, San Salvador and San José in the order named.
                            The American Minister in Managua has authorized President Sacasa to
                            permit his representative to advise the other interested governments
                            orally and confidentially that his proposal meets with the approval of
                            this Government and that the United States is prepared to recognize the
                            present government of El Salvador as soon as recognition is accorded by
                            Guatemala, Honduras and Nicaragua. You may confirm this understanding if
                            you are approached by the <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> President or
                            Minister of Foreign Affairs in the matter during or subsequent to the
                            visit of Dr. Sacasa’s representative to San Salvador.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Phillips</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>