<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Guatemala ( (Lawton) ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-01-18T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-01-18T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-01-18T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-01-18T13:00:00-05:00" n="223"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">816.01/380: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Guatemala</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lawton</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-01-18T12:00:00-06:00"
                            >January 18, 1934—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 4:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3. Telegram from Minister at Managua January 17, 10 p.m.<note n="17"
                        xml:id="d223fn17">See penultimate paragraph of telegram No. 15, <hi
                            rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> I inquired of Foreign Office this
                    morning as to whether President Ubico objected to first part of Sacasa plan,
                    namely, that immediately prior to recognition the three Presidents should
                    announce their agreement on continued validity of Treaty as between themselves
                    and on <pb facs="0304" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/> calling a conference of the
                    five countries. I pointed out that, although I had as yet received no
                    instructions as to how the Department would view recognition if this first step
                    were omitted, the Department had expressed its sympathy with the plan as
                    originally proposed by President Sacasa and not with recognition alone. Acting
                    Minister frankly admitted his Government was none too enthusiastic about the
                    proposal but said President Ubico had agreed to recognition because he did not
                    desire to stand out alone against the other Central American States and the
                    United States. Once recognition was agreed upon Ubico had little interest in the
                    other features of plan although he is willing to participate in Central American
                    conference. He feels the spirit and principle of treaty are necessarily lost by
                    recognition and that it is useless to try to justify it by an explanation
                    beforehand. Although agreeing the treaty remains in force between Guatemala,
                    Nicaragua and Honduras, since none of them have denounced it, he feels it is
                    useless to pretend that recognition of Martínez is not a violation of its terms.
                    Finally, although willing enough to participate in a conference, it is evident
                    that Guatemalan Government would not take a new or modified treaty very
                    seriously. Notwithstanding these views Acting Foreign Minister promised to point
                    out to the President the fact that a preliminary announcement in the sense
                    indicated above was an essential feature of the Sacasa plan and to see if he
                    would approve it. Decision on this point may not be reached until late this
                    evening or tomorrow.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Managua.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lawton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
