<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-07-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-07-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">810.5151 Williams Mission/18</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sevier</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 52</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-07-05">July 5, 1934</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has given much thought to
                            the exchange negotiations with the Chilean Government, which are now
                            pending. It has come to the conclusion that in connection therewith, as
                            well as to study the exchange situation in Brazil<note n="14" xml:id="d28fn14">See <ref target="frus1934v04#pg_578">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 578</ref> ff.</note> and
                                Argentina,<note n="15" xml:id="d28fn15">See <ref target="frus1934v04#pg_511"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp.
                                    511</ref> ff.</note> it would be well to have an expert in
                            international exchange matters visit the three countries concerned in
                            order to discuss the problems with our missions and the Governments in
                            those countries.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, as you have already been informed telegraphically,<note n="16" xml:id="d28fn16">Telegram No. 50, July 3, 7 p.m., not
                                printed.</note> Mr. John H. Williams, Economist of the Federal
                            Reserve Bank of New York, has been released by arrangement with the
                            Federal Reserve authorities, and in company with Mr. Donald R. Heath of
                            the Division of Latin American Affairs of the Department, departed on
                            June 30, last, for Rio de Janeiro on the <hi rend="italic">Western
                                Prince</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The present tentative schedule of Messrs. Williams and Heath, subject to
                            possible change through substituting flying for steamship or rail, is as
                            follows: <list>
                                <item>Leave New York June 30, <hi rend="italic">Western
                                    Prince</hi>.</item>
                                <item>Arrive Rio de Janeiro July 13.</item>
                                <item>Depart from Rio de Janeiro July 28.</item>
                                <item>Arrive Buenos Aires July 31.</item>
                                <item>Depart from Buenos Aires August 5.</item>
                                <item>Arrive Santiago August 5 or 6.</item>
                                <item>Depart from Valparaiso August 10, on the <hi rend="italic">Santa Maria</hi> of the Grace Line.</item>
                                <item>Arrive New York August 28.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The pertinent portions of Mr. Williams’ instructions are as follows:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In each of these (designated) countries the American diplomatic
                                    and commercial missions will be instructed to assist you in
                                    obtaining <pb facs="0098" n="32" xml:id="pg_32"/> the fullest
                                    possible understanding of all aspects of the exchange control
                                    situation, and to put you in touch with the local government
                                    authorities who are concerned in this matter. You in turn are
                                    instructed upon your arrival in each of these countries to put
                                    yourself at the disposition of the head of the mission for the
                                    purpose of assisting him in the consideration of the exchange
                                    control situations with which he has been dealing and for the
                                    purpose also of working out with him the major lines of policy
                                    immediately to be pursued by this Government. You will find that
                                    these missions have given very considerable thought to the
                                    subject and have kept themselves closely advised.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Messrs. Williams and Heath are fully informed of the course of
                            developments in Chile in connection with the negotiations relative to
                            the exchange problem in that country. The Department trusts that the
                            despatch of this mission will indicate to the Chilean authorities the
                            importance which this Government attaches to the exchange problem, which
                            is an important factor in the trade relationship between it and Chile.
                            The Department will await with interest the receipt of your and Mr.
                            Williams’ reports and recommendations in connection with this
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wilbur
                                    J. Carr</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>