<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-12-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="591" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d591">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.1928/312</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Panama</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gonzalez</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretafry of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 543</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Panama</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-12-27">December 27, 1934</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                January 7, 1935.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that at an
                            informal interview had today with the Secretary of Foreign Relations he
                            voluntarily spoke regarding the progress of the treaty.</p>
                        <p>He stated that conversations were continuing on more or less minor
                            matters in Washington, but that the objection made by the Panamanian
                            Government as to the provisions of Article II of the Treaty of 1903
                            being inserted into the new treaty seemed to be meeting with obstacles.
                            He said that Panama felt it had already complied with that provision of
                            the treaty and that it was no longer necessary to incorporate it in any
                            new treaty and that that was holding up further progress. That the same
                            question had been raised by Mr. Louis Anderson, an international lawyer
                            of Costa Rica, in connection with the boundary matter upon the ground
                            that since the United States could take over any land which it might
                            require in defense of the Canal, that under those conditions Costa Rica
                            could not accept any land from the Republic of Panama in the settlement
                            of its boundary dispute as it was not free to dispose of any land, which
                            was at all times subject to be requisitioned by the United States
                            Government. For this reason, the boundary conversations with Costa Rica
                            had come to a sudden termination instead of, as expected, being adjusted
                            and settled. Under the circumstances the Foreign Secretary stated that
                            unless the United States was willing, particularly in time of peace, to
                                <pb facs="0676" n="610" xml:id="pg_610"/> refrain from taking over
                            any further land of the Republic of Panama that that in itself would
                            prevent the negotiation of a new treaty.</p>
                        <p>Further, that as a condition for the construction of the transisthmian
                            road, the United States had suggested that it be permitted to erect
                            along said road any and all fortifications and gun emplacements which it
                            deemed necessary and that, regardless of the fact that Panama was
                            anxious to build this road, it could not be considered if it was to be a
                            military area, particularly that portion of the road located within the
                            territory of Panama. Furthermore, the Secretary stated, that the
                            conditions as to construction of this road were so severe in character
                            that it would necessitate a $3,000,000. investment on the part of Panama
                            which it could not afford and, in conclusion, since the main benefit of
                            this road would enure to the United States and not to the Panamanian
                            people, that if such provisions were to be insisted upon, Panama would
                            abandon the idea of constructing the trans-isthmian road.</p>
                        <p>He further stated in conclusion that if the United States insisted on its
                            right to take over further property of Panama that he presumed that the
                            ultimate conclusion would be to withdraw the commission and continue
                            under the old treaty until such time as other arrangements might be
                            made. He informed me further that regarding the Madden Dam road, that it
                            has been tentatively agreed that the Republic of Panama would turn over
                            to the United States the jurisdiction thereof in exchange for permission
                            to build the trans-isthmian road but that the conditions above mentioned
                            made that impossible.</p>
                        <p>He further stated that in connection with the matter of radio, that
                            regardless of the fact of whether the United States made a radio
                            agreement or not the Panamanian Government intended to proceed with
                            radio broadcasting under its recent laws, and the Madrid Convention<note n="25" xml:id="d591fn25">Signed December 9, 1932, <ref target="frus1932v01#pg_873"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1932, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                                    873</ref>.</note> which it had signed, as well as the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>It is quite apparent, insofar as the Panamanian Government is concerned,
                            that they do not seem to be willing to grant any rights to the United
                            States, whether they relate to the maintenance, operation and/or defense
                            of the Canal or not, and that their sole theory is based upon the fact
                            that it has already turned over to the United States all the land and
                            waters which the United States required for the defense of the
                            Canal.</p>
                        <p>I inquired from him as to what was the objection of Panama for the United
                            States having whatever land was necessary for the proper defense of the
                            Canal, and his reply was that without any limitation being made the
                            people of Panama were of the opinion that under an unlimited provision
                            as to further acquisition of land the United <pb facs="0677" n="611" xml:id="pg_611"/> States might be able some day to extend its
                            jurisdiction even to the Costa Rican border.</p>
                        <p>This afternoon I interviewed the President for the purpose of inquiring
                            from him whether or not in his opinion he believed that a treaty which
                            might be agreed upon in Washington and presented to the National
                            Assembly could be passed. He stated that in his selection of Dr. López
                            and Dr. Garay he had two views in mind, one, to obtain a representative
                            of the Chiarista Party by the appointment of Dr. López and, secondly,
                            from the Panamanian Society of International Action in the person of Dr.
                            Garay, and that if they agreed in Washington to terms for a new treaty
                            that he was positive that the Assembly would ratify it. On the other
                            hand, he stated that there had been some delay caused in the
                            conversations in Washington, first, owing to the fact that Dr. Garay had
                            been ill and then Mr. Edwin Wilson having become ill, as well as the
                            Christmas holidays, all of which had slowed up conversations.</p>
                        <p>However, the question of incorporating in the new treaty the provisions
                            contained in Article II of the Treaty of 1903 was objectionable, and
                            that unless the Government of the United States would be willing to
                            eliminate that provision, Panama would be unable to continue
                            conversations as to any new treaty; that as yet his Government had not
                            received definite advice on this question from the State Department. His
                            commissioners in Washington had written for further instructions as to
                            whether or not they should remain any longer in Washington, and he had
                            advised them that they should remain until the end of January before
                            returning.</p>
                        <p>This information seems to be in accord with what is heretofore reported
                            as to the conversation with the Secretary of Foreign Relations.</p>
                        <p>The President then stated that in addition to the objection on the part
                            of his Government, to the subject matter of Article II of the treaty of
                            1903, that Louis Anderson, international lawyer in Costa Rica, was
                            making much to do over the question of whether or not Panama was able to
                            cede any land to Costa Rica in the boundary dispute, because the United
                            States, under Article II, would be able to follow the land and claim it,
                            which the President stated was of course an exaggerated view but,
                            however, had been made authentic enough in Costa Rica to bring about the
                            secession [<hi rend="italic">cessation?</hi>] of all further
                            conversation regarding the determination of the boundary.</p>
                        <p>I inquired of the President as to his opinion concerning the pending
                            banking bill. He stated that it was his understanding that when the
                            original bill was presented to Mr. Manuel José Diez, of the Chase
                            National Bank, that he made no objection to it, but that he, the
                            President, understood that the amendments which had since been made by
                                <pb facs="0678" n="612" xml:id="pg_612"/> the Assembly had changed
                            the complexion of the bill; that the bill was coming up today for second
                            debate in the National Assembly and for further amendments and that he
                            as yet was not familiar with the context of the bill.</p>
                        <p>In speaking of the free port bill, the President stated that he intended
                            to circularize the advantages of that bill among the exporters of the
                            United States through the medium of his consuls, since he believed that
                            sufficient advantages would be found for exporters under it and he
                            wanted to have them fully advised through the medium of his consuls, who
                            would be supplied with copies of the bill.</p>
                        <p>He also stated, in referring to the Blandin rubber contract, that he
                            believed that contract would not only be beneficial to his people, since
                            it would give rise to employment and to a product of exportation, but
                            also to the Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company who, in time of war, would
                            have a plantation accessible to the United States for its needs and that
                            he was ready to re-execute the contract as amended just as soon as a
                            representative of the Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company would come to
                            Panama.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully submitted,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Antonio C.
                            Gonzalez</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>