<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Uruguay ( (Dominian) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d629</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">629</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="629"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d629">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.5151 Williams Mission/32</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dominian</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 673</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-07-16">July 16,
                            1934</date>.<lb/>[Received July 30.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    the Department’s instruction No. 258 of July 5,<note n="14" xml:id="d629fn14"
                        >Not printed.</note> in which referring to the Department’s telegram No. 30
                    of July 3, relative to arrangements made with the Federal Reserve authorities
                    for the visit of Mr. John H. Williams, economist of the Federal Reserve Bank of
                    New York, the Legation is informed that Mr. Williams, accompanied by Mr. Donald
                    R. Heath of the Division of Latin American Affairs of the Department, <pb
                        facs="0720" n="654" xml:id="pg_654"/> will arrive in Rio de Janeiro on July
                    13 and will thence proceed to Buenos Aires prior to returning to the United
                    States by way of the West Coast.</p>
                <p>It is gratifying to find that the Department considers it desirable that Mr.
                    Williams should visit Montevideo and be of assistance in the problems arising in
                    Uruguay as a result of exchange control in the country. It is noted also that
                    Mr. Williams himself is anxious to include Montevideo in his itinerary, subject
                    to the limitations in time of leave granted him by the Federal Reserve
                    authorities.</p>
                <p>A review of the exchange situation at the present moment leads me to conclude
                    that Mr. Williams’ presence at Montevideo, for part of a day, at least, while on
                    his way to Buenos Aires would be of positive importance. I am enclosing herewith
                    copies of a telegram and a letter addressed to him<note n="15" xml:id="d629fn15"
                        >Neither printed.</note> which are self-explanatory regarding the value of
                    not omitting Montevideo from his itinerary. His visit, should he decide to make
                    it, will be all the more useful in view of the conversations on problems of
                    exchange which have taken place between Minister Wright and the Ministry of
                    Foreign Affairs, and which I am carrying on since Mr. Wright’s departure. As
                    steamers proceeding to Buenos Aires by way of Montevideo usually stop over
                    during a great part of the day in this city, it is believed that the enforced
                    stay in the capital will provide Mr. Williams with sufficient time to meet the
                    leading officials and business men here who are dealing with the exchange
                    problems of Uruguay. Care will be taken to provide him with the necessary
                    contacts within the duration of his stay, and the Department will be kept
                    informed of developments as they arise.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Leon Dominian</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
