<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Argentina ( (Weddell) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-06-24T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-06-24T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-06-24T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-06-24T20:00:00-05:00" n="132"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">724.34119/1422: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-06-24T21:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 24, 1938—9 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received June 25—2 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>164. From Braden. Paraguayan counter-proposal offers line D’Orbigny Capirenda,
                    Carandaity, Matico, Ravelo to point on Otuquis at latitude of San Juan down that
                    river to its mouth on Paraguay River leaving forts Galpon and Patria for
                    Paraguay.</p>
                <p>Memorandum accompanying proposal reiterates irreductibility regarding cession of
                    river south of mouth of Otuquis; argues interior line must be based on
                    intermediary line with qualitative territorial compensations for any withdrawal
                    made therefrom; preserves Paraguayan rights to entire Chaco in event this
                    proposal is rejected; claims above line is only one affording security to
                    Paraguay but concludes <pb facs="0155" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/> with statement
                    Paraguay will consider new proposal the Conference may desire to make.</p>
                <p>Argentine Minister for Foreign Affairs reported junior Paraguayan delegate had
                    told him counter-proposal was made to give an opening to negotiations; that
                    civilians in Asunción were disposed to accept Conference proposal in the
                    interior but that military insisted a fight should be made for a better line
                    before accepting; Paraguay would grant Bolivia a free port wherever desired and
                    counter-proposal was made precisely to bring about another one from the
                    Conference.</p>
                <p>Argentine Minister for Foreign Affairs also quoted Bolivian Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs as being willing in the last extremity to accept line D’Orbigny; 27
                    November; a point approximately 20 [<hi rend="italic">19</hi>] degrees 45 south
                    61 degrees 10 west; a point midway between Ravelo and intermediary line; to
                    approximately 19 degrees 15 south 59 degrees 9 west passing close to Galpon and
                    Patria; to mouth of Otuquis. Bolivian Minister for Foreign Affairs previously
                    had agreed with me that he would accept Conference line but ending at mouth of
                    Otuquis and with minor alterations to west and north.</p>
                <p>At the suggestion of Argentine Minister for Foreign Affairs the Conference
                    decided: (1) to advise Paraguayans in session tomorrow their proposal is totally
                    unacceptable and we will not even submit it to Bolivians but we will endeavor to
                    induce the latter to cede river and to improve conference line in the west and
                    north; (2) we will spend 2 or 8 days negotiating maximum concessions from
                    Bolivia; (3) if successful with Bolivia Conference will then present final offer
                    making clear to Paraguayans no further negotiations are possible and if it is
                    rejected direct negotiations will be declared terminated.</p>
                <p>I expressed fear that the peculiar Paraguayan psychology was never to believe us
                    when we claimed to have said our last word; when we offered five they always
                    asked for six hence to get five we should offer four or less. I urged day and
                    night negotiations with Paraguayans trading on the basis of our May 27 proposal.
                    However, procedure decided upon by the Conference at least has the advantage of
                    quickly reaching a conclusion.</p>
                <p>Aside from Paraguayan intransigence principal handicap is timidity of the
                    Argentine Minister for Foreign Affairs vis-à-vis Paraguayans, the fact that he
                    is poor negotiator and his main concern to get rid of the Chaco.</p>
                <p>Bolivian Minister for Foreign Affairs tells me he advised Argentine Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs that if no progress has been made early next week he will
                    withdraw acceptance of Conference proposal and leave Buenos Aires Wednesday.</p>
                <p>Chilean delegate reports unusually large arms shipments through Arica to Bolivia
                    during April. [Braden.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Weddell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
