<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-06-30T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-06-30T13:00:00-05:00" n="139" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">724.34119/1432: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-06-30T14:00:00-04:00">June 30, 1938—2
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>86. For Braden from the Under Secretary. Your 172, June 29, 9 p.m. The
                            Department is delighted that there now is an encouraging prospect of a
                            definitive settlement of the Chaco dispute, and appreciates to the full
                            the perseverance, initiative and ability you have exercised in bringing
                            the negotiations to their present stage. The Department believes,
                            however, that the proposal should come from the Conference rather than
                            from President Roosevelt. You may inform the other mediatory delegates
                            that your Government has instructed you to strongly support the
                            presentation and adoption of such a Conference plan. If this procedure
                            meets with the approval of your colleagues, please make the proposal
                            outlined in your telegram, as modified in the following paragraphs which
                            refer to the corresponding lettered paragraphs of that telegram, to a
                            plenary session of the Conference including ex-belligerent
                            delegations.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The preamble, in addition to emphasizing the importance and need
                                of peace to all of the nations of this hemisphere might also
                                emphasize that the assurance of peace would be of the greatest
                                possible advantage to the people and Governments of Bolivia and
                                Paraguay.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>No changes.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>No changes.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Reference should be made to “arbitrators” instead of
                                “arbitrator”.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                            <item>No changes.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The Conference proposes that the Presidents of the six mediatory
                                countries, acting on behalf of their Governments and in
                                collaboration with the Conference, serve as arbitrators in
                                accordance with the plan outlined in paragraph (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) and that Paraguay and Bolivia sign immediately an
                                arbitral <hi rend="italic">compromis</hi> to this effect committing
                                themselves to acceptance of the award; this <hi rend="italic">compromis</hi> to be ratified within 20 days by the
                                Constitutional Convention in Bolivia and by a plebiscite, possibly
                                including women, in Paraguay, the arbitral award to be given 10 days
                                thereafter.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Department is of the opinion that the modifications suggested in the
                            plan as outlined in your telegram are necessary and desirable in <pb facs="0165" n="156" xml:id="pg_156"/> order to preserve the
                            solidarity of the six mediatory nations, to secure the added weight of
                            the Governments and peoples of those six countries in support of the
                            proposal, and as an effective step in strengthening the general system
                            of inter-American peace machinery. The Department would approve of a
                            motion by you that as host to the Conference the President of the
                            Argentine Republic be requested by the Conference to communicate with
                            the other five presidents regarding their role as arbitrators or to act
                            as Chairman of the arbitrators.</p>
                        <p>The Department assumes that there will be a clear understanding
                            concerning the award as set forth in the final paragraph of your
                            telegram.</p>
                        <p>If it is possible to follow the procedure outlined in this telegram,
                            please so advise the Department immediately. A statement then will be
                            given to the press to the effect that you have been given instructions
                            regarding a possible definitive settlement of the Chaco dispute, and
                            that the instructions themselves will be made public at the hour of the
                            Conference meeting.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>