<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-27T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-27T13:00:00-05:00" n="269" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d269">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3531/586: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                        Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-27T15:00:00-03:00">January 27, 1938—3
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 4:43 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>6. From Ravndal. “Have just been informed unofficially and in the
                            strictest of confidence by Louro<note n="6" xml:id="d269fn6">Alfredo
                                Louro, Chief of the Argentine Exchange Control Board.</note> that
                            President-elect Ortiz and <pb facs="0284" n="275" xml:id="pg_275"/>
                            Minister of Finance Acevedo have accepted the proposal with regard to
                            elimination of discrimination against the United States in exchange
                            matters prepared by Louro with the assistance of Prebisch.<note n="7" xml:id="d269fn7">Raul Prebisch, General Manager, Central Bank of
                                Argentina.</note> Ortiz is now consulting Carcano<note n="8" xml:id="d269fn8">Miguel Angel Carcano, Minister of
                                Agriculture.</note> with respect to agricultural concessions to be
                            arranged probably by trade agreement negotiations and Carcano is being
                            assisted in this matter by Louro. It is expected by the Argentine
                            Inter-Ministerial Committee that the exchange proposal will very shortly
                            be made to the Department and that the Department will make the
                            preliminary announcement within a few days. Irigoyen expects to leave
                            for Washington Saturday and Louro within 10 or 15 days.</p>
                        <p>It is understood that the exchange proposal accepted by Ortiz is along
                            the lines discussed in my strictly confidential report entitled
                            ‘Bilateralism in Argentina’s Exchange Proposals’, sent air mail January
                                25.<note n="9" xml:id="d269fn9">Not printed.</note> [Ravndal.]”</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Weddell</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>