<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-02-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="271" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d271">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3531/579</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Argentine Embassy</gloss></hi></head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The Government of the United States is gratified to receive the
                                assurance contained in the Argentine Government’s reply of December
                                30, 1937,<note n="10" xml:id="d271fn10"><ref target="frus1937v05#pg_231"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1937, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>,
                                        p. 231</ref>.</note> to the Memorandum of the Department of
                                State dated November 22, 1937,<note n="11" xml:id="d271fn11"><ref target="frus1937v05#pg_225"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p.
                                        225</ref>.</note> and in the Argentine Government’s
                                communication of January 28, 1938,<note n="12" xml:id="d271fn12">See
                                    memorandum by the Chief of the Division of the American
                                    Republics, <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi></note> sent in reply to
                                a telegram sent by the Argentine Ambassador to his Government after
                                consultation with officials of the Department of State on January 4,
                                1938, that the Argentine Government from the date of the formal
                                public notice of intention to negotiate a trade agreement, will not
                                apply any charge or surtax on purchases of exchange for the payment
                                of products imported into Argentina from the United States.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The Government of the United States, in the second paragraph of
                                its Memorandum of November 22, 1937, requested assurances regarding
                                the allotment of official exchange on an unconditional
                                most-favored-nation basis. It is noted, however, that the Argentine
                                Government in its replies under reference gives no assurances in
                                this regard. Nevertheless, in view of its earnest desire to proceed
                                with the negotiations at the earliest possible date, the Government
                                of the United States will not at this time insist for the period up
                                to the conclusion of the trade agreement upon full acceptance of its
                                request on this point.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The Government of the United States is prepared to issue its
                                preliminary public notice of contemplated trade agreement
                                negotiations on the basis of the assurances referred to in paragraph
                                1 above and on the understanding that pending the conclusion of a
                                trade agreement the treatment of American commerce, in respect of
                                the allotment of official exchange, will be no less favorable than
                                that which is now enjoyed, subject, of course, to the understanding,
                                as stipulated in the third paragraph of the Memorandum of November
                                22, 1937, “that the Argentine Government is prepared to negotiate
                                the contemplated <pb facs="0286" n="277" xml:id="pg_277"/> agreement
                                upon the basis of the unconditional most-favored-nation principle
                                applied to all forms of trade and payments control”.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The guarantee of full unconditional most-favored-nation treatment
                                with respect to all form of trade and payments control is a basic
                                principle of American commercial policy. It is, therefore, essential
                                that any trade agreement concluded by the United States contain
                                suitable provisions embodying this guarantee. It is of prime
                                importance that there be no misunderstanding in regard to it such as
                                would result in a failure of the negotiations after public
                                announcement has been made.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The paragraph above quoted means with reference to exchange
                                control that if either Government establishes or maintains directly
                                or indirectly any form of control of the means of international
                                payment, it shall not use such control in any manner, direct or
                                indirect, to regulate or in any manner to influence the source of
                                its importations to the detriment of the trade of the other country.
                                It means further that enjoyment of the complete freedom from
                                discrimination thus envisaged shall not be subject to any condition
                                or qualification whatsoever, such, for example, as the requirement
                                by either country that the treatment accorded shall in any way
                                depend upon the amount of its exports to the other country or upon
                                the relation between exports and imports in its trade with that
                                country. Under the system and methods of exchange control at present
                                existing in the Argentine, a practical application of this principle
                                would mean that when the trade agreement goes into effect, so long
                                as exchange at the official rate is provided for all merchandise
                                imports from any third country, exchange would be made available at
                                the official rate for all merchandise imports from the United
                                States. As stated in this Government’s Memorandum of November 22,
                                1937, it would be impossible for this Government to conclude any
                                trade agreement with the Argentine Government unless it contained
                                guarantees fully effectuating the purposes above set forth.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-02-01">February
                                    1, 1938</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Suggested Form of Reply by the Argentine Embassy
                                    to the Memorandum of the Department of State of February 1,
                                    1938</hi><note n="13" xml:id="d271fn13">In a note of February 3,
                                    the Argentine Embassy acknowledged the receipt of the
                                    Department’s Memorandum of February 1, in the form suggested in
                                    this enclosure (611.3531/590½).</note></head>
                            <p>The Argentine Ambassador has the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                                the Memorandum of the Department of State dated February 1, 1938,
                                which reads as follows:</p>
                            <p>(Insert text of memorandum)</p>
                            <pb facs="0287" n="278" xml:id="pg_278"/>
                            <p>The Argentine Ambassador has the honor to state that his Government
                                clearly understands the position of the United States as set forth
                                in its Memoranda of November 22, 1937, and February 1, 1938, and
                                declares its readiness to go forward with the proposed
                                negotiations.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>