<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Argentina ( (Weddell))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-06-25T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-06-25T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-06-25T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-06-25T12:00:00-05:00" n="284"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d284">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3531/644a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-06-25T13:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 25, 1938—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>81. For your confidential information, a memorandum was handed the Argentine
                    Ambassador on June 13, 1938, embodying the following:</p>
                <p>In the event agreement is reached in regard to exchange treatment under a trade
                    agreement (on the basis of the proportional formula, outlined in this
                    Government’s memorandum of March 24, 1938,<note n="23" xml:id="d284fn23">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_287">p. 287</ref>.</note>
                    enclosed with the Department’s instruction number 726 of April 5, 1938,<note
                        n="24" xml:id="d284fn24">Not printed.</note> using the period 1932–1934,
                    giving percentage of 12.86, as the base period for the purpose of the formula),
                    and substantial agreement is reached on the substance of the other general
                    provisions and on the concessions to be granted by both countries before July 7,
                    this Government will issue not later than that date announcement to negotiate a
                    trade agreement with Argentina; if the agreement should not be completed and
                    published by early September, it would be necessary publicly to announce the
                    unsuccessful termination of negotiations. Lists specifying the proposed
                    concessions to be granted to the United States by Argentina, and the proposed
                    concessions to be granted to Argentina (the latter tentative pending hearings in
                    this country as required by law) were attached to the memorandum of June 13. The
                    Department is informed by the Argentine Embassy that this memorandum has just
                    reached the Argentine Government by airmail. You should, <pb facs="0306" n="297"
                        xml:id="pg_297"/> at the earliest opportunity, call upon the President of
                    Argentina and express the earnest hope of this Government that Argentina will
                    find it possible to utilize this opportunity to consummate a trade agreement.
                    You may state that our initiative in this matter has been personally considered
                    and approved by President Roosevelt.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
