<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Argentina ( (Weddell) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d292</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">292</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-08-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-08-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-08-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-08-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="292"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d292">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3531/664</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2155</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-08-17">August 17,
                            1938</date>.<lb/>[Received August 26.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose as of possible
                    interest to the Department a memorandum prepared by the Consul General relating
                    to the proposed United States-Argentine Commercial Agreement and which is based
                    on conversations with Dr. Alfredo Louro and others in the recent past.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexander W. Weddell</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0315" n="306" xml:id="pg_306"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Extracts]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Buenos Aires</hi> (<persName
                            type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in Argentina</hi>
                            (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-08-16">August 16,
                                1938</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to submit herewith for your
                        consideration certain observations on the subject of a United
                        States-Argentine trade agreement, based on conversations with Dr. Alfredo
                        Louro and others during the past week. It is believed that they should be of
                        interest in the light of the speeches made on August the twelfth and their
                        reception in the local press. Attention is drawn in this connection to the
                        August fourteenth issue of <hi rend="italic">La Nación</hi> which contains
                        an editorial on the subject of Dr. Groppo’s speech entitled “La politica
                        comercial”.</p>
                    <p>The frank statements of the Minister of Finance at the Chamber of Commerce
                        banquet on Friday brought into the open views which have been expressed
                        unofficially on innumerable occasions by Argentine officials, bankers and
                        economists. They indicate that the issue is really clear-cut and that
                        Argentina will retain its artificial exchange restrictions against United
                        States commerce as long as the United States keeps its artificial sanitary
                        restrictions against Argentine meat. There seems to be real fear among
                        Argentines that the British market for meat is a declining one and that
                        desperate measures are warranted for the saving of the country’s principal
                        industry. Attention continues to be focused on this industry and there is
                        little or no interest in the problematical benefits that would accrue to
                        Argentina from the lowering of United States tariffs on items other than
                        meat.</p>
                    <p>Argentina, while it has an academic interest in the attempts of the United
                        States through its Trade Agreements program to promote freedom of trading,
                        is seemingly not interested in a pooling of efforts towards this end. Dr.
                        Louro when questioned on this point in unofficial conversation stated that
                        American efforts (1) had failed to induce Britain, France, Germany and Italy
                        to eliminate their quotas and clearings, and (2) had not brought about the
                        reduction of European tariff barriers on products in which Argentina was
                        interested. He seemed not to believe that Argentina could accomplish
                        anything by insisting on free and equal treatment from its principal
                        customers as the United States had done. He thought that United States
                        acquiescence in the French quotas illustrated the hopelessness of the task
                        for Argentina, and therefore felt that Argentina should play safe and get
                        what it could by bargaining in preferences.</p>
                    <p>The general feeling seems current among Argentines that formal adherence to
                        the principle of multilateral balancing would not materially assist it
                        unless restrictions and duties against Argentine products <pb facs="0316"
                            n="307" xml:id="pg_307"/> elsewhere were to be reduced or eliminated. In
                        other words, it is the “other fellow” that must make the first move. The men
                        at the helm in Argentina feel that in the present state of world uncertainty
                        they would prefer not to risk the temporary partial loss of markets which
                        might be incidental to the period of readjusting the country’s exports to a
                        new trade agreement policy.</p>
                    <p>The Roca-Runciman type of trade agreement,<note n="25" xml:id="d292fn25">See
                                <ref target="frus1933v04#pg_722">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1933, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 722</ref> ff</note> which is
                        supposedly Argentina’s standing offer to all comers (except apparently
                        Japan), has set a strong precedent. Dr. Louro is inclined to think perhaps
                        this treaty was a mistake since it unnecessarily limits Argentina’s freedom
                        of action. However, he insists that it is a definite factor to be reckoned
                        with and Argentina would not dare to make an arrangement which was at
                        variance with its principles; that is, reserving exchange created by exports
                        for each contracting country’s uses on the bilateral principle.</p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                    <p>In the meantime it is proposed to make the United States feel the full weight
                        of Argentina’s ability to restrict imports through exchange control.
                        Argentina wishes to make it clear that it will not buy unless it can sell.
                        This same principle has been applied to Italy for some months past and if
                        necessary will be applied to other countries also, in accordance with the
                        provisions of Argentina’s exchange agreements which call for the automatic
                        adaptation of official exchange allocation to the extent of each country’s
                        purchases here. (See Consul Ravndal’s letter to the Ambassador of May 20).
                        Thus there is not exclusive discrimination against the United States, but
                        rather discrimination against those countries which have persistently
                        favorable balances in their trade with Argentina.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Monnett B. Davis</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
