<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Chile ( (Frost))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d443</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">443</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-01-29T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-01-29T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-29T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-29T13:00:00-05:00" n="443"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d443">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.2531/250: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Frost</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-29T13:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 29, 1938—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>12. Your despatch 830, January 15, final paragraph. The Department did not intend
                    that you should discuss the text of the general provisions even informally with
                    Chilean officials at this time. As special conditions in Chile might necessitate
                    changes in the “standard” provisions in a trade agreement with that country, it
                    was the Department’s desire, by its instruction 296 of January 5, to have your
                    own comments as to the applicability and adequacy of the provisions,
                    particularly regarding possible obstacles of a legal or policy nature which
                    might make it difficult for Chile to accept certain of the principles or
                    commitments embodied in the standard provisions. It was the Department’s thought
                    that it would be possible for you to ascertain whether any such obstacles do
                    exist without discussing the exact text of the provisions with Chilean
                    officials. Experience has shown that the presentation of a draft text, even
                    informally, before a mutually satisfactory agreement has been reached in regard
                    to the broad principles upon which negotiations will be based, tends to
                    complicate and delay rather than facilitate the progress of the exploratory
                    conversations. In this connection, should you find that you would be assisted by
                    having further information regarding the reasons for the inclusion of any
                    particular article in the general provisions, the Department will be glad to
                    supply you with such information.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
