<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-03-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="454" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d454">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.2531/279</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Frost</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 927</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-03-22">March 22, 1938</date>.<lb/>[Received March
                                29.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my telegram
                            No. 34 of March 21, 7 p.m., 1938 with regard to the exchange clause
                            suggested by the Chilean Foreign Office in connection with the proposed
                            Chilean-American Trade Agreement.</p>
                        <p>The Chilean position is based upon the necessity of maintaining Chile’s
                            compensation agreements in order to keep open European markets, and upon
                            the necessity of maintaining an exchange control system in order to
                            stabilize the peso against extreme and harmful fluctuations or
                            depreciations. The British Government is understood to have recognized
                            these two necessities; and both myself and the Commercial Attaché, as
                            the Department is aware, are rather disposed likewise to feel that they
                            might well receive a degree of recognition.</p>
                        <p>The proposed clause guarantees most favored nation treatment and a supply
                            and demand exchange rate. It merely specifies that the depreciation in
                            the exchange value here of the blocked currencies, which is due to a
                            supply of those currencies created intentionally by Germany and other
                            powers, does not constitute a discrimination on Chile’s part; and this,
                            from some standpoints, may be taken to be the actual fact.</p>
                        <p>The British Embassy has for the past month made the exchange clause the
                            crucial point of its negotiations, an attitude entirely different from
                            that which it maintained up until the middle of February. This was due
                            to conversations resulting from the Department’s Instruction No. 312, of
                            January 31, 1938. The British took the exchange clause in our <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> as a starting point and was then
                            instructed, as the result of the attitude of the British Board of Trade,
                            to insist also upon an absolute guaranty of most favored nation
                            treatment. The Chileans were willing to concede a most favored nation
                            pledge with the British on condition that the latter in turn should
                            admit that the low value of the blocked currencies here does not
                            constitute discrimination. This point had been carefully discussed
                            between myself and the British Embassy and the conclusion had been
                            reached that the quotations on the blocked mark here are in reality
                            fixed by demand and supply and could not be altered by Chile even if an
                            attempt were made to legislate against <hi rend="italic">aski</hi>
                            currency. The compensation agreements <pb facs="0452" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/> have had no success in promoting imports into
                            Chile, except possibly in the case of Germany. Accordingly the British
                            Embassy accepted the Chilean stipulations.</p>
                        <p>The negotiations were hastened to a conclusion by the fact that don
                            Agustin Edwards, Chilean Ambassador to England, who has been on leave in
                            Chile with the express purpose of activating the general treaty
                            settlement which has been under discussion since early last autumn, was
                            about to depart for his post. It so happened that the British Commercial
                            Secretary was leaving by the same boat (S.S. <hi rend="italic">Orduña</hi>, sailing on yesterday’s date); and this furnished an
                            added incentive. The British clause was completed on the 19th instant,
                            and its substance telegraphed to London. On the 18th Señor García had
                            submitted a draft of it to me, and on the 21st he suggested that I work
                            it over with him. This was done yesterday afternoon and I telegraphed
                            the result to the Department last evening. There are enclosed herewith
                            the copies both of our proposed clause<note n="32" xml:id="d454fn32">Quoted in telegram No. 34, March 21, 7 p.m., from the Chargé in
                                Chile, <ref target="#pg_440">p. 440</ref>.</note> and of the British
                                clause,<note n="33" xml:id="d454fn33">Not printed.</note> in Spanish
                            and English.</p>
                        <p>As the Department would assume, I earnestly hope that the Chilean offer
                            can receive serious and favorable consideration. I do not believe that
                            Chile can afford to cancel her compensation agreements; as this step
                            would cause very important trade losses, despite the fact that the
                            Germans could and probably would continue to do a good deal of business
                            here on a compensation basis (just as they are doing in New York to some
                            extent with <hi rend="italic">aski</hi> marks.) Señor Gazitúa has made
                            estimates indicating that Chile would lose from 40 to 60 percent of her
                            trade with Germany.</p>
                        <p>Referring to the Department’s telegram No. 24, of March 19, 12 noon,
                                1938,<note n="33" xml:id="d454fn34">Not printed.</note> I may say
                            that it will probably be highly desirable, or even necessary, to arrange
                            for the existence of a Mixed Chilean-American Commission similar to the
                            recent Brazilian-American Mixed Commission, in order to make a full
                            success of our trade agreement negotiations. On this condition, and if
                            the Chilean exchange clause offer is found acceptable, it will probably
                            be possible within a very few weeks to reach an understanding with Chile
                            on the basis of which a trade agreement could be negotiated. Several
                            points remain to be cleared up, but the difficulties are minor. On the
                            other hand if the exchange solution now suggested is not in its broad
                            lines acceptable there might be some question as to the value of
                            pursuing discussions on other phases of the proposed accord.</p>
                        <p>Not devoid of relevance in this connection is the fact that the British
                            are now to negotiate with Chile on the various matters which in our case
                            will be dealt with in a general treaty of amity and commerce. <pb facs="0453" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/> They are endeavoring to secure
                            national treatment in Chile for their commercial and banking firms,
                            national treatment in Chilean waters for their steamships, etc. If the
                            Department should find the proposed exchange clause to be substantially
                            acceptable, and if in consequence the stage of announcing the intention
                            to negotiate a trade agreement should shortly be reached, this Embassy
                            could then turn to the negotiation of a general treaty and have the
                            advantage of working synchronously with the British on the questions
                            indicated above. To my mind this would on the whole be advantageous, as
                            the United States and England would be more likely to induce a liberal
                            attitude on Chile’s part which would contribute to the propagation of
                            the Hull policies in Latin America.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wesley Frost</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>