<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Haiti ( (Finley) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d642</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">642</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-08-02T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-08-02T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-08-02T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-08-02T14:00:00-05:00" n="642"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d642">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">838.20/22: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Finley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-08-02T14:00:00-05:00"
                            >August 2, 1938—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 4:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>99. In announcing to the Garde his decision to request an American military
                    mission, President Vincent stated he was requesting two—not three—American
                    officers. Leger today in handing me a note which likewise contained a request
                    for two instead of three officers intimated that the President at the last
                    moment had felt that it was more advisable <pb facs="0658" n="649"
                        xml:id="pg_649"/> politically at this moment to request two than three. The
                    President had nevertheless asked him to explain to me that the Haitian
                    Government would ask for the third officer within two or three months since they
                    were sure that three were needed. The first two were wanted as soon as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>The note containing the request (a copy of which will be transmitted the next air
                    mail) states that the Haitian Government has decided to reopen the military
                    school. The two officers requested would be asked to direct this school and at
                    the same time to give the general staff technical advice “in all that concerns
                    the betterment and the progress of the present organization of the Garde”.</p>
                <p>The note also inquires under what terms these officers will be furnished.</p>
                <p>The President specifically stated in his speech to the Garde that he had
                    requested American regular Army officers.</p>
                <p>I would appreciate instructions as to what reply should be made.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Finley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
