<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d670</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">670</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="670"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d670">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.52/3354</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-09-26">September 26,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Mexican Ambassador came in at my request. He had agreed when he last called
                    to communicate with President Cárdenas on two points and report back to me. One
                    point related to whether his Government could give more substantial information
                    and assurances in regard to time and amount of payments for lands seized during
                    the past ten years, and the other point related to the sending of a brief note I
                    had acquainted him with and thereafter the discontinuance of note writing, with
                    oral conversations substituted. The Ambassador gave no encouragement about the
                    note phase but suggested that his Government be disposed to consider making a
                    reply. He said that his Government was seriously desirous of making payment for
                    the lands seized during the past ten years; that they would be disposed to have
                    a commission proceed very soon with the task of valuing the lands and agreeing
                    as to time and amount of payment; that they would agree that the valuation work
                    should be completed within six months; and that his Government would put in its
                    budget each year, beginning with next year, not less than $500,000, to be
                    applied on the land payments as and when they were valued by the commission. <pb
                        facs="0719" n="710" xml:id="pg_710"/> I replied that this would require a
                    great many years. The Ambassador then remarked that he did not think these lands
                    would be valued at more than two or three million dollars, and, therefore, it
                    would not take so much time for payment. He said that his Government would be
                    willing to adopt a percentage basis which would determine the amount of payment
                    each year. The inference was that this might make payments certain within a very
                    few years. The Ambassador said that his Government could not agree to cease
                    further seizures of lands, although he had said to me on his last visit that it
                    could thus agree orally except as to three small tracts and one large tract
                    which were then in process of being taken over; that it would be agreeable with
                    his Government, however, to have such lands valued promptly and the amount due
                    to be placed in the first budget along with amounts due for lands seized during
                    the past ten years. I said that the only trouble with the proposition was that
                    his Government could and might easily seize properties more rapidly than they
                    would pay off the amounts due for seizures during the past ten years, with the
                    result that the Mexican Government would be getting deeper in debt as it
                    expanded its seizures. The Ambassador had no particular comment on this phase.
                    He did not suggest any way of guarding against this sort of possible development
                    either as to ceasing seizures or making more certain payment for seizures
                    heretofore made. I said that his reply was somewhat discouraging and
                    disappointing; that I would confer with my associates and if we should see any
                    basis for progress in dealing with the matters of difference between the two
                    governments I would advise him.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
