<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d694</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">694</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="694"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d694">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.12/1367</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-04-02">April 2,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Mexican Ambassador called at my request. After brief preliminaries we
                    proceeded to exchange some impressions and ideas with respect to the Mexican
                    expropriation question. I at first said with emphasis to the Ambassador that his
                    Government and his people must know from five years of observation and of
                    experience in its relations with the United States that, in the first place, we
                    have the profoundest interest in the good neighbor policy and its preservation
                    and advancement. I said that, in the second place, this country has consecrated
                    itself in almost every possible way to cooperation with Mexico and other
                    countries to advance the good neighbor policy, and at the same time had bestowed
                    upon Mexico many valuable kindnesses and courtesies over and above the normal
                    processes governing the relations between the two countries. I added that this
                    record of relations between our two countries must confirm the Government and
                    the people of Mexico in the view that our interests and our friendship have been
                    of the most whole-hearted and constant nature.</p>
                <p>I then said that the loss to American land owners, oil owners and other American
                    property owners, whose properties have been taken over by authority of the
                    Mexican Government, while not intended here to be minimized, is the least of a
                    number of much larger and broader considerations which neither of our countries
                    can afford to overlook. These considerations I summarized as follows: (1) When a
                    great country like Mexico establishes a policy of taking over property without
                    any serious plan or purpose to make reasonable payment, it would at once become
                    known to all nations and would have the inevitable effect of destroying the good
                    neighbor policy, especially in this hemisphere. This would work most serious
                    effects upon Mexico in many unexpected ways. (2) To adopt a policy of thus
                    seizing oil and land and a few other properties would inevitably result in the
                    early seizure of all foreign owned properties. In other words, if this country
                    should acquiesce in the seizure of oil or any similar properties on account of
                    the unpopularity of the owners, both in Mexico and in this country, those who
                    seize it would unquestionably suspend all further law for the purpose of seizing
                    other and all foreign owned <pb facs="0751" n="742" xml:id="pg_742"/>
                    properties. Other nations would quickly follow suit. (3) From any other than the
                    immediate shortsighted viewpoint the policy of seizing properties without
                    payment would soon work far-reaching injury to Mexico herself. No longer would
                    the most needed capital for development come to that country from anywhere.
                    Commercial and financial conditions, both internal and international, would
                    steadily deteriorate until revolution or some similar upheaval would occur.</p>
                <p>I said to the Ambassador that his Government must therefore see the impossible
                    position in which these proposed or threatened steps by the Mexican Government
                    are placing this Government and this country. We are expected to acquiesce in
                    these acts that are contrary to law, equity, fair play and fair dealing and they
                    would be so viewed by all civilized nations. Furthermore, they would occur just
                    at the time when the world is on fire; when lawlessness is steadily expanding in
                    many regions and when this Government is preaching to all nations the
                    preservation of all the principles of law and order in every part of the world;
                    that it would be an anomalous situation to announce in these preachments that we
                    are making an exception in the case of Mexico. I said finally the Ambassador
                    realized from his reading of the history of nations that in eight cases out of
                    ten, the nation that undertook to pursue a policy of seizing the property of
                    others without any concern about payment has always become a decadent nation
                    soon thereafter and in its most vital processes of progress and civilization has
                    steadily moved backward and downward. Finally, I said that this country and this
                    Government spend much time every week in the year preaching its friendly
                    feelings to each of the other countries, especially in this hemisphere, and
                    particularly Mexico, and assures our people that similar friendly feelings are
                    entertained in return. I then added that, in the light of certain news from
                    Mexico, I wondered whether his statesmen preached this same state of opinion and
                    attitude on the part of the Mexican people toward the people of the United
                    States, and added that I hoped they would not overlook this phase in view of its
                    importance to both countries alike.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador listened attentively and apparently with the disposition to agree.
                    He said that he had talked with President Cárdenas last evening over the
                    telephone and that he was giving him still further assurances of a determined
                    purpose to solve this situation. He stated that he appreciated what I had said
                    and was in accord; that he would write fully to President Cárdenas today
                    reciting our conversation and our state of mind in this country and earnestly
                    urging that the matter be worked out without any more delay than possible. He
                    admitted that President Cárdenas had not thus far intimated to him the time or
                    means of making payment. The Ambassador added, however, that in his own opinion
                    the matter could be handled. He withheld all details. He would be more than glad
                    to exert himself in <pb facs="0752" n="743" xml:id="pg_743"/> every possible way
                    to stimulate and encourage his Government to work this matter out without fail.
                    I said to him that his Government and his people should realize and must know
                    that whatever is said or done here is done with the feeling of the most sincere
                    friendship, and if it at times is in any sense disagreeable it is because the
                    Mexican Government has driven us to the very edge of the precipice, so that in
                    the interest of international law and order, and as one of its constant
                    upholders, this Government finds itself obliged to speak or act. I said there is
                    no possible way we can abandon basic principles such as those relating to
                    payment when property is expropriated.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
