<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d696</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">696</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="696"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d696">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.6363/3367</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-04-04">April 4,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Mexican Ambassador called this afternoon at my request. I told the Ambassador
                    that I had asked him to come to see me in order that I might tell him of the
                    instructions that had been sent to Mr. Daniels and I repeated to the Ambassador
                    the points that Mr. Daniels had been requested to make in the interview which he
                    was instructed by cable this morning to obtain with General Hay.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador told me that he had again talked with President Cárdenas on the
                    long distance telephone on Saturday night and that he himself on that occasion
                    had said to President Cárdenas, first, that as specific a reply as was possible
                    should be made to the precise inquiries this Government had formulated with
                    regard to the method of the compensation payment and the time thereof; second,
                    that he knew from his conversations with me that this Government would be
                    prepared at any time after this step had been taken to undertake informal
                    conversations between responsible officials of the two Governments with regard
                    to the issues involved; and third, that he also knew that this Government felt
                    it would be preferable for various practical reasons to have these conversations
                    held here in Washington. The Ambassador told me that President Cárdenas had told
                    him that he would immediately summon Dr. Suarez, Mr. Buenrostro,<note n="96"
                        xml:id="d696fn96">Efrain Buenrostro, Mexican Minister for National
                        Economy.</note> and Mr. Villalobos<note n="97" xml:id="d696fn97">Antonio
                        Villalobos, Mexican Secretary of Labor.</note> in order to formulate certain
                    plans which would be responsive to our request, and for the first time, the
                    Ambassador said, specifically authorized him to say that the Mexican Government
                    would be prepared to send to Washington at any time we desired the necessary
                    responsible officials of the Mexican Government to talk over informally a
                    solution of the problem.</p>
                <p>I asked the Ambassador if he had any word from President Cárdenas as to the
                    nature of the plans which he had in mind. He said he did not.</p>
                <p>I then said to the Ambassador that of course many suggestions were being made to
                    us and that it might be desirable for the Mexican Government to know of some of
                    these suggestions but without, of course, this Government assuming any
                    responsibility for fathering them, so that the Mexican Government would not work
                    out one sole alternative and then feel obliged to stick to it. The Ambassador
                    said that from his conversations with President Cárdenas he believed that some
                    immediate conclusions would be arrived at and all that President <pb facs="0754"
                        n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> Cárdenas intended to do in his reply to this
                    Government was to indicate certain ideas to be advanced as a basis for
                    discussion. He said that it seemed to him that the time to consider these
                    various suggestions was as soon as conversations in Washington commenced.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador further told me that President Cárdenas had said to him that the
                    Mexican Government had refused to enter into any discussion even of an agreement
                    with Mr. Rickett<note n="98" xml:id="d696fn98">Francis W. Rickett, a British oil
                        speculator, associated with Bernard Smith, a Wall Street operator, in
                        negotiations for the purchase of oil from Mexico.</note> and that it had no
                    intention of doing so. The President had said that some two hundred proposals
                    had already been received by him and that of these only three or four were even
                    worth thinking about. He said, however, that the Mexican Government had no
                    intention of entering into any arrangements at this time with regard to outside
                    interests in connection with new concessions.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that he had seen the texts of the appeals taken by the oil
                    companies to the courts against the upholding of the expropriation decree of the
                    President of Mexico. He said these documents appeared to him to be ill founded
                    and badly drafted. I made the remark that I had not yet read them.</p>
                <p>In conclusion I said to the Ambassador that I had seen that some purported
                    officials of the Mexican Government now in the United States had been giving out
                    statements to the press and I wondered if the Ambassador did not feel as I did
                    that publicity of this character was unfortunate at the present time. I said
                    that it had now been made evident that both our Governments were on the most
                    friendly possible terms and had decided to exert their best efforts to finding a
                    friendly solution of the problem which confronted them. Under these conditions I
                    thought that the less publicity the better, and in particular, the less
                    recrimination the better. The Ambassador said that of course I knew that he
                    himself was entirely in accord with this point of view and that he had already
                    requested his Government to keep the people I referred to quiet.…</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
