<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Uruguay ( (Dawson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d843</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">843</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-08-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-08-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-08-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-08-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="843"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d843">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3331/206</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 318</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-08-11">August 11,
                            1938</date>.<lb/>[Received August 22.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: This morning’s press contains a summary of what
                    appears to be a very important statement regarding trade policy made yesterday
                    at a Cabinet meeting by the Uruguayan Minister of Finance, Dr. César
                    Charlone.</p>
                <p>From this statement, which is reported to have been unanimously approved by the
                    Cabinet, it would appear that Dr. Charlone and the Government are committed not
                    only to the maintenance but also to the further extension and reinforcement of
                    the bilateral policy and system of trade and exchange control which have had
                    such unfortunate repercussions as respects American trade with Uruguay.</p>
                <p>The press reports that Dr. Charlone’s statement will be published officially and
                    as soon as the official text is available it will be forwarded to the
                    Department. In the meantime, there is furnished the following summary, based on
                    today’s press reports, which has been prepared by Mr. Reed:</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that the Economic Readjustment Law of November 9, 1934,<note
                        n="37" xml:id="d843fn37">Uruguay, <hi rend="italic">Reyistro Naeional de
                            Leyes, Decretos y Otros Documentos</hi>, 1934 (Montevideo, 1943), p.
                        1479.</note> (which established the import quota system) has made it
                    possible for Uruguay to obtain an equilibrium in its balance of payments without
                    resorting to foreign loans. The treaties of commerce and agreements regarding
                    payments already signed cover at present more than 75% of Uruguay’s foreign
                    commercial activities. He declared that this figure demonstrates that, far from
                    its being possible to abandon the system of compensation in order to return to
                    the previous standard of a free economy, Uruguay must persevere in the policy
                    followed and reach total compensation, if possible. He added that the system in
                    question is susceptible of progressive perfecting, with which the Government is
                    now occupied and which recently resulted in the unification and coordination of
                    the controls of importation and exportation. In the same manner that the
                    Government, before beginning each fiscal year, adjusts its receipts and
                    expenditures <pb facs="0929" n="920" xml:id="pg_920"/> in the budget, there must
                    be obtained in interchange (commercial) an adjustment of obligations in foreign
                    money to the normal receipts which are produced for the country by its exports
                    and other items in the balance of payments. This method has already begun to be
                    applied for the year 1938, the probable production of foreign exchange and the
                    form in which it can be used to meet the financial services of the Government,
                    the Municipality of Montevideo, private enterprises and the payment of imports
                    having been estimated in advance. It is calculated that the foreign exchange
                    originated by the sale of products subject to control will amount to pesos
                    78,238,080, to which should be added 15,200,000 pesos from free exchange, in
                    which are liquidated some balances of exportation, tourists funds, etc. In all,
                    the probable revenues (foreign exchange available) should amount for 1938 to
                    93,500,000 pesos, according to very conservative calculations, which allow for
                    the sale of most of the coming wool clip in 1939 instead of this year. With
                    these revenues the Minister proposes to meet the financial services above
                    referred to, which he estimates at 14,668,000 pesos, there remaining available
                    77,307,200 pesos, or somewhat more than £10,000,000.</p>
                <p>With reference to imports covered by free exchange, the Minister reported that
                    70% of the amount mentioned above (15,200,000 pesos) is for imports authorized
                    and paid for prior to June 30 last, and that free exchange will only be
                    authorized during the remainder of the year for merchandise materially
                    impossible to compensate by export business.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Maintenance of Present Exchange Policy.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Of great importance for American business is the statement then made by the
                    Minister that the same policy will be followed for the year 1939 and
                    subsequently, that is, the advance determination each fiscal year of the
                    probable receipts and requirements in foreign exchange. Simultaneously with the
                    Budget, the appropriate offices will work out a preliminary balance of the
                    receipts and payments of interchange (commercial).</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Stabilization Fund.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Minister emphasized the importance of the Exchange Fund (stabilization fund)
                    which advances foreign exchange in moments of scarcity and recovers them in the
                    opposite phase of the annual cycle. The action of this mechanism and the prior
                    determination of the annual figure of importation can afford, in a policy of
                    directed economy, the stability to which import business has a right. He
                    mentioned that this fund amounted to 23,294,638.40 pesos in gold and foreign
                    currencies, excluding foreign debt bonds in the possession of the bank. These
                    reserves are to be defended and increased, especially to recover <pb facs="0930"
                        n="921" xml:id="pg_921"/> advances, amounting to 14,688,000 pesos, granted
                    to countries which had debit balances with Uruguay as a result of difficulties
                    last year in placing the wool clip, the equivalent of which is represented by
                    the still unsold balance of wool, hides, wheat, etc.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusions of the Minister of Finance.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The conclusions of the Minister of Finance were as follows (translation): <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The country should arrange to subject the amount of its importations
                            to the normal production of foreign exchange after the deduction of the
                            public and private financial services.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The reserves of gold and exchange of the Exchange Fund (stabilization
                            fund) must be protected and increased to the greatest possible extent,
                            for which purpose arrangements should be made to compensate with the
                            greatest amplitude the purchases abroad and other debit items of the
                            balance of payments, with sales of our products.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>There can and must be sought a more rational application of the
                            exchange available, by establishing import quotas for those articles or
                            merchandise, the nature or present volume of which may not be in
                            accordance with the real needs of consumption. The same line of conduct
                            should be observed with regard to imported articles similar to those
                            whose domestic production is now developing, even to prohibiting their
                            importation when the progress acquired by our industry permits it to
                            cover the total needs of domestic consumption.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>In order to give interchange transactions (commercial) the desirable
                            stability, it is advisable to prepare annual plans prior to the
                            beginning of each fiscal year. And for that purpose it is necessary that
                            there be a close contact of the Bank of the Republic with the Executive
                            Power, since, although by virtue of the laws in force, the application
                            of those principles belongs to the State Bank, nobody doubts that this
                            institution exercises such powers by delegation, as originally they form
                            part of economic policy, the general objectives of which must be
                            outlined by the Government of the Nation as the representative of
                            collective interests.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William Dawson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
