<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-04-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="886" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d886">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.3131/179</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Venezuela</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Nicholson</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 258</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-04-05">April 5, 1938</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Reference is made to your telegram No. 22,
                            March 23, 5 p.m., in regard to a possible <hi rend="italic">modus
                                vivendi</hi> between the United States and Venezuela. You should
                            inform the Venezuelan Foreign Minister that while the Department will,
                            of course, be happy to consider any suggestion he may wish to make
                            regarding a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> assuring unconditional
                            most-favored-nation treatment between the two countries pending
                            conclusion of the trade-agreement negotiations, it believes that it is
                            preferable to bend all efforts to the most expeditious conclusion of the
                            trade agreement. To that end, as stated in the Department’s telegram No.
                            13 of March 9, 1938, the Department is prepared to set a date at once
                            for the issuance of this Government’s second public announcement, if the
                            Venezuelan Government acquiesces in the publication, in connection with
                            that announcement, of the products comprising group 1 in the memorandum
                            accompanying the Department’s instruction No. 250 sent you on March 7.
                            Furthermore, the Department is prepared to proceed as rapidly as
                            possible thereafter with the negotiation of the trade agreement, and
                            hopes that the agreement may be concluded at an early date after the
                            completion of public hearings in this country which would be about five
                            weeks after the second public announcement. During the period between
                            the issuance of the <pb facs="0980" n="971" xml:id="pg_971"/> second
                            announcement and the conclusion of public hearings in this country,
                            discussions could proceed between the two Governments with respect to
                            the general provisions of the trade agreement, and, with respect to
                            products, keeping in mind, however, that this Government’s position in
                            regard to the latter because of legal requirements must be subject to
                            information and data received from domestic interests as a result of the
                            second public announcement and hearings.</p>
                        <p>You should also inform the Foreign Minister that this Government had
                            assumed that in practice the Venezuelan Government has extended
                            most-favored-nation treatment to products imported into Venezuela from
                            the United States; and that this Government hopes that, pending the
                            conclusion of the trade agreement, the Venezuelan Government will find
                            it possible to extend such treatment in practice to such American
                            products as may be imported into Venezuela.</p>
                        <p>In this connection, you should again point out to the Foreign Minister
                            that this country generalizes to Venezuela all concessions granted in
                            trade agreements negotiated under the authority of the Trade Agreements
                            Act, with the single exception of those granted to Cuba which are not
                            generalized to any third country.</p>
                        <p>For your information, the Department does not consider it advisable to
                            conclude a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> with Venezuela as it is
                            believed that such action might complicate the trade agreement
                            conversations and would possibly delay the conclusion of a trade
                            agreement.</p>
                        <p>Please report fully to the Department in what respects Venezuela is not
                            now granting most-favored-nation treatment to the United States.</p>
                        <p>Also please report fully to the Department any conversations you may have
                            with Venezuelan officials in regard to the foregoing and in regard to
                            the trade-agreement conversations generally, including any comments the
                            Legation may think pertinent.</p>
                        <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Francis
                                    B. Sayre</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>