<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-11-26T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-11-26T02:45:00-05:00" n="94" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d94">
                        <head>94. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d94fn1">Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Reports on
                                    <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, China, and Middle East
                                Discussions, Box 2, China Memcons and Reports, November 25–29, 1974,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s Trip. Top
                                secret; Sensitive. The meeting took place in the Great Hall of the
                                People. All brackets are in the original.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Beijing</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1974-11-26T15:45:00+08:00" to="1974-11-26T17:00:00+08:00">November 26, 1974, 3:45–5:00 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng Hsiao-p’ing</persName>, Vice Premier
                                of the State Council, People’s Republic of China</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Ch’iao Kuan-hua</persName>, Minister of
                                Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>Wang Hai-jung, <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> Vice Foreign
                                Minister</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HZ1">Huang Chen</persName>, Chief
                                of the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> Liaison Office,
                                Washington</item>
                            <item>Lin P’ing, Director, Department of American and Oceanic Affairs,
                                Ministry of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>T’ang Wen-sheng, Deputy Director, Department of American and
                                Oceanic Affairs, Ministry of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>Tsien Ta-yung, Counselor, <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>
                                Liaison Office, Washington</item>
                            <item>Ting Yuan-hung, Director, United States Office, Department of
                                American and Oceanic Affairs, Ministry of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>Chao Chi-hua, Deputy Director, United States Office, Department of
                                American and Oceanic Affairs, Ministry of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName>Chang Han-chih</persName>, Translator</item>
                            <item>Notetaker</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, Secretary
                                of State and Assistant to the President for National Security
                                Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Donald Rumsfeld</persName>, Assistant to
                                the President</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BGHW1">George Bush</persName>,
                                Chief of the United States Liaison Office, Peking</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LW1">Winston Lord</persName>, Director, Policy
                                Planning Staff, Department of State</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HPC1">Philip C. Habib</persName>, Assistant
                                Secretary of State for East Asian and Pacific Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RPW1">Peter Rodman</persName>, Staff Member,
                                National Security Council</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SRH1">Richard H. Solomon</persName>, Senior
                                Staff Member, National Security Council</item>
                            <item>Karlene Knieps, Notetaker</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Normalization</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: They
                            outnumber us today.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Some more on our
                            side are coming. I don’t think you will ever outnumber us because we
                            have 800 million.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: My children
                            and my wife very much appreciated the tour of the Forbidden City this
                            morning. It was very nice.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Did they like it
                            at all?</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Very
                            much.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: How is the
                            health of your wife? I hope it is better.</p>
                        <pb facs="0607" n="578" xml:id="pg_578"/>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It is much
                            better.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: If you need any
                            medical help you just let us know.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: You are very
                            nice. She is going to watch acupuncture.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Well that
                            medical technique of China is almost as old as the Great Wall of China.
                            A few hundred years later than the Great Wall. It was created at the
                            time of the Han Dynasty.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: On one trip I
                            brought a doctor along who was very skeptical of it and after he saw it
                            he was very impressed.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: It goes as far
                            back as about two hundred years after Christ. During the time of the
                            three kingdoms. It was during that time people were able to have an
                            operation with acupuncture.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It is
                            interesting to reflect how it could have been invented. Because as I
                            understand it, to this day nobody understands the theory, why it works,
                            just that it works.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: I think mainly
                            it was through practice.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Who got the
                            first idea to stick a needle into somebody?</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: It was combined
                            with the use of herb medicine.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Who would
                            have thought if you stick a needle into somebody it would help him? No
                            other civilization thought about that.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Shall we come
                            back to our subject? We will listen to the Doctor. All right?</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Let me
                            discuss the subject of normalization. I understand that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPC1">Habib</persName> has already had a talk on the
                            bilateral relations.<note n="2" xml:id="d94fn2">A memorandum of
                                conversation of this counterpart discussion, which took place on
                                November 26, 2–3:15 p.m., is ibid.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>I am confident that our side can keep multiplying the complexities as
                            long as your side can. It is something we are very good at.</p>
                        <p>Let me speak about the normalization problem.</p>
                        <p>When we met the first time, in our first two meetings [in 1971] we
                            discussed completing the process during the second term of President
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>.</p>
                        <p>We said that we would reduce our military forces on Taiwan, and we
                            repeated that in the Shanghai Communiqué;. We said we would not support
                            any two Chinas solution, or a one China–one Taiwan solution, or any
                            variation.</p>
                        <pb facs="0608" n="579" xml:id="pg_579"/>
                        <p>And we would not encourage other countries to pursue such a policy.</p>
                        <p>We have substantially maintained these commitments.</p>
                        <p>We have reduced our forces on Taiwan from over 10,000 to about 3,200
                            today. We encouraged the Japanese movement towards the People’s
                            Republic. This is in fact why you can speak of a Japanese solution. We
                            have given no encouragement to a two Chinas or one China–one Taiwan
                            solution; quite the contrary.</p>
                        <p>Now the problem is how we can complete the process. I would like to
                            divide it into a number of parts: <list>
                                <item>—There is the problem of the diplomatic status of Taiwan, and
                                    of course of the diplomatic relations between us.</item>
                                <item>—There is the problem of our military forces on Taiwan.</item>
                                <item>—And there is the problem of our defense commitment to
                                    Taiwan.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Our problem is different from the situation of Japan, or for that matter
                            from the situation of any other country with which you have normalized
                            relations, in two respects:</p>
                        <p>First, there is a formal defense relationship. Secondly, there is a
                            rather substantial group in the United States that historically has been
                            pro-Taiwan.</p>
                        <p>Together with your cooperation we have been able to neutralize the
                            pro-Taiwan element in the United States by moving step-by-step in a very
                            careful manner. But what we have to keep in mind for our common interest
                            is to prevent Sino-American relations from becoming an extremely
                            contentious issue in the United States.</p>
                        <p>It is not in your interest, or in that of the United States, to have
                            emerge a Senator or Senatorial group which does to Sino-American
                            relations what Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName>
                            has attempted to do to United States-Soviet relations.</p>
                        <p>I am speaking very frankly to you so that we understand each other
                            exactly. After I have put my considerations before you, you will of
                            course give me yours. Then we will see if we can solve the problem. I am
                            here to remove obstacles, not to hide behind them.</p>
                        <p>We believe, as I have said, that while cannons have been fired— mostly in
                            one direction—we have also had common fronts.</p>
                        <p>As the Premier said yesterday, they were mostly produced by the “polar
                            bear.”</p>
                        <p>We do not want to jeopardize that possibility [of developing common
                            fronts with the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>] given the dangers
                            that may be ahead, and keeping in mind what Chairman
                                <persName>Mao</persName> said to me last year of the two
                            strands—normalization, and the international environment.</p>
                        <p>Now having said this, let me go back to the specific issues between
                            us.</p>
                        <pb facs="0609" n="580" xml:id="pg_580"/>
                        <p>First, on the issue of the diplomatic status: We are prepared to solve
                            this on substantially the Japan model; and with the one variation that
                            it would be easiest for us if we could maintain a liaison office in
                            Taiwan and an embassy in Peking. Except for that we would follow the
                            Japan model.</p>
                        <p>With respect to the presence of [U.S.] troops on Taiwan, we are prepared
                            to remove all our troops from Taiwan. We would like to agree with you on
                            a schedule, a time-frame within which this will be accomplished—by which
                            we would reduce the forces by half by the summer of 1976, and the
                            remainder to be removed by the end of 1977.</p>
                        <p>Incidentally, what I am discussing is not something to which we want to
                            agree—we can agree to it here, but it should not be announced until the
                            end of 1975, the agreement we make. But we want to come to an
                            understanding about it now, that this is what would happen.</p>
                        <p>Now that leaves the last problem, which is our defense relationship to
                            Taiwan. And this is a problem to which, in all frankness, we have not
                            come up with a good answer.</p>
                        <p>Our problem is this: on the face of it, it is of course absurd to say one
                            has a defense arrangement with a part of a country one recognizes, that
                            is, which belongs to that country.</p>
                        <p>Secondly, we obviously have no interest in maintaining a strategic base
                            on Taiwan after we have established diplomatic relations with Peking and
                            recognized Peking as the legal government of all China.</p>
                        <p>But as I told the Foreign Minister in New York, we need a formula that
                            enables us to say that at least for some period of time there are
                            assurances of peaceful reintegration which can be reviewed after some
                            interval in order to avoid the difficulties which I have described.</p>
                        <p>If we can, this would mean that we would have accepted Peking as the
                            [legal] government [of China]. We would have withdrawn our recognition
                            from Taiwan, we would have broken diplomatic relations with Taiwan. We
                            would have withdrawn our troops from Taiwan. All that would remain is
                            that we would have some relation to peaceful reintegration.</p>
                        <p>Speaking here frankly and realistically, the political and psychological
                            effect of breaking relations is that our defense relationship will be
                            eroded by the act of recognition. But we need a transition period for
                            our public opinion in which this process can be accomplished without an
                            excessive domestic strain.</p>
                        <p>These are our basic considerations. If we agree on the principles, we can
                            then see what formula can then be worked out.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Is that all?</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: This is the
                            essence, yes.</p>
                        <pb facs="0610" n="581" xml:id="pg_581"/>
                        <p>Let me emphasize one point. To us the question of the defense commitment
                            is primarily a question of the way it can be presented politically. It
                            is not a question of maintaining it for an indefinite period of
                            time.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Well, actually
                            this law was formulated by yourselves. Is that so?</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Which
                            law?</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: You are the ones
                            who make the law. That is, the law of that defense commitment you have
                            with Taiwan. That was fixed by yourselves.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Of course.
                            That is absolutely true.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Well, since you
                            can formulate a law, naturally you can also do away with it.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That is also
                            true. Our point is not that it could not be done. Our point is that for
                            reasons I have explained to you, it is not expedient to do—well, the act
                            of recognition in itself will change the nature of that arrangement
                            because you cannot have a defense treaty with part of a country.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: I have noticed
                            the consideration which the Doctor has just mentioned. And I understand
                            that all of these imaginations the Doctor has discussed with the Foreign
                            Minister while he was in New York in October.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That is
                            correct.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: And I believe in
                            principle the Foreign Minister gave you the answers on our side
                            concerning the principal matters. In essence your imaginations—your
                            considerations—cannot be considered as being in accord with the Japan
                            model.</p>
                        <p>And we feel that in essence it is still a variation of one China and one
                            Taiwan.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Why is
                            that?</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Well, this is
                            primarily that you just reverse the position, change the position of the
                            liaison office. The present situation is that we have established a
                            liaison office in Peking—we have established our liaison office in
                            Washington and you have established one in Peking. And you keep an
                            embassy in Taiwan. This in itself indicates there has not been the
                            necessary conditions for the normalization of relations.</p>
                        <p>In other words, if you change this order, that is, to have an embassy in
                            Peking and a liaison office in Taiwan, it is not the way to correct the
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>People will come to the conclusion that it is actually a variation of one
                            China and one Taiwan. Therefore, we find it difficult to accept this
                            formula.</p>
                        <pb facs="0611" n="582" xml:id="pg_582"/>
                        <p>And just now you touched upon the question of the defense treaty. That
                            is, the defense treaty which you have with <persName corresp="#p_CKS1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> on Taiwan. Of course, if we are to
                            achieve the normalization of relations between our two countries and
                            abide by the course set in the Shanghai Communiqué, then the treaty you
                            have with Taiwan must be done away with.</p>
                        <p>The reasons actually have been given by the Doctor yourself just now.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The defense
                            treaty can have no international status after the normalization of
                            relations.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: But still it has
                            a substantial meaning.</p>
                        <p>So it appears that time is not ripe yet to solve this question, because
                            according to your formula, it would not be possible for us to accept
                            this method of normalization. It still looks as if you need Taiwan.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: No, we do not
                            need Taiwan. That is not the issue. I think that it is important to
                            understand. That would be a mistake in understanding the problem.</p>
                        <p>What we would like to achieve is the disassociation from Taiwan in steps,
                            in the manner we have done until now. There is no doubt that the status
                            of Taiwan has been undermined by the process which we have followed. And
                            this process would be rapidly accelerated by the ideas which we have
                            advanced.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: And the other
                            question is the way [method] to solve the Taiwan problem. As for solving
                            the Taiwan question, suppose you have broken diplomatic relations with
                            Taiwan. Then the Taiwan question should be left with us Chinese to solve
                            among ourselves.</p>
                        <p>As to what means we will [use to] solve the Taiwan question, I believe
                            Chairman <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao Tse-tung</persName> made it very
                            clear in his talk</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Chairman
                                <persName>Mao</persName>, if I understood him correctly, made two
                            statements: One was that he believed that the question would ultimately
                            have to be solved by force. But he also stated that China could wait for
                            one hundred years to bring this about, if I understood him
                            correctly.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That was
                            true. He did say that.</p>
                        <p>Of course, the number of “one hundred years” is a symbolic one.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Of course, I
                            understand this. I was going to say that in one hundred years I will not
                            be Secretary of State. I have to say this occasionally to give some hope
                            to my associates. I understood it was symbolic. I understand also that
                            after normalization that any attributes of sovereignty in the
                            relationship between Taiwan and the U.S. have to be eliminated.</p>
                        <pb facs="0612" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: Chairman
                                <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Mao Tse-tung</persName> made it very
                            clear that the solving of the Taiwan problem is an internal affair of
                            China, and should be left to the Chinese to solve.</p>
                        <p>Just now Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> said that
                            on the Taiwan issue you wish to have a peaceful reintegration.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: That is
                            correct.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: And I believe
                            you mentioned something like a wish of the U.S. in having some part in
                            this guarantee relationship.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Let me
                            explain what is our concern. We have not worked out a legal formula. We
                            believe that it is—what I am saying is capable of misinterpretation. Let
                            me explain our position exactly.</p>
                        <p>When I came here in 1971, it was clear that we were starting a process
                            that would lead to the gradual erosion of the position of Taiwan.</p>
                        <p>You would certainly not have been admitted to the United Nations in
                            1971—eventually it would have happened, but not in 1971. It would have
                            taken longer. And the normalization with Japan would not have been
                            accomplished so soon. We fully cooperated in this, and we established
                            principles that sooner or later have been implemented. And we did this
                            in all seriousness.</p>
                        <p>You know we have made no effort with any country to keep them from
                            establishing relations with you and breaking them with Taiwan.</p>
                        <p>The problem we have is the impact internationally of a sudden total
                            reversal of an American position on other friendly countries, and even
                            perhaps on countries that are not friendly to either of us.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: But on the
                            other hand, if we agree to your formula we will also be creating an
                            impact internationally that we have agreed to the formula of one
                            China–one Taiwan.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: No, we will
                            work to make it clear that it is not this type of situation. We will not
                            now accept a solution which we have both rejected.</p>
                        <p>We have, it seems to me, two basic choices. There are two roads we can
                            now follow: We can continue the present process, which is tolerable, and
                            gradually withdraw our forces from Taiwan, which will continue in any
                            event—whatever you decide here. We will increase our relationship with
                            you as we have done in the past three years, and wait for the opportune
                            time to complete the process with one decision.</p>
                        <p>Or, we can do a process in which we complete the political part of our
                            relationship quickly and make it clear that we are solving the issues of
                            sovereignty—of one China and one Taiwan—at once, and find a formula in
                            which the symbolic thought of Chairman <persName>Mao</persName> is
                            expressed. An effort of peaceful reintegration over a reasonable period
                            of time. <pb facs="0613" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/> We do not want a
                            voice in the discussion on peaceful reintegration. That should be left
                            to the Chinese. We do not want to participate in that process.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>Chang Han-chih</persName>: I’m not clear about the first part
                            of your statement.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The Vice
                            Premier said that of course the one hundred years is symbolic. I
                            understood the symbolic nature of Chairman <persName>Mao</persName>’s
                            statement about a hundred years. I understood it to mean that you are
                            willing to give the peaceful process time to work—that while
                            philosophically the resolution will probably come about by force, you
                            are prepared to give the peaceful road a long opportunity.</p>
                        <p>We do not want to participate in the process of reintegration. And we
                            have no difficulty affirming the principle of one China. So our issue is
                            not one China, one Taiwan.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister Ch’iao: If I understand correctly, I see what you mean
                            is that you are for one China, but the one China you want is a one China
                            which is achieved through peaceful means.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Exactly. For
                            at least a reasonable period of time. We want to avoid a situation where
                            the United States signs a document which leads to a military solution
                            shortly after normalization. But we do not want a commitment which
                            maintains the separation. What we have in mind—we may not know the
                            formula, but what we have in mind seems compatible with what Chairman
                                <persName>Mao</persName> says in terms of the process.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: We have just now
                            checked on what Chairman <persName>Mao</persName> exactly said when he
                            talked with Doctor, and we understand what he said is, “I don’t think
                            the normalization of relations between China and the United States will
                            take one hundred years.” So from this we understand that it does not
                            mean that from what Chairman <persName>Mao</persName> says, that we do
                            not wish to complete a process of the normalization as quickly as
                            possible.</p>
                        <p>I think concerning the Taiwan question that at the same time it is also a
                            question of the normalization of relations between China and the United
                            States.</p>
                        <p>There are three principles to which we cannot give other consideration,
                            which we cannot barter away. The first principle is that we insist—that
                            we should insist on the Shanghai Communiqué. That is, we refuse any
                            method which will lead to the solution of “two Chinas,” or “one China,
                            one Taiwan,” or any variation of these two.</p>
                        <p>The idea of setting up an embassy here in Peking and a liaison office in
                            Taiwan is a variation on “one China–one Taiwan,” which we cannot
                            accept.</p>
                        <p>The second principle is that the solution of the Taiwan question is an
                            internal issue of the Chinese people, and it can only be left to the <pb facs="0614" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/> Chinese people themselves to
                            solve. As to what means we will use to finally solve the Taiwan
                            question—whether peaceful methods or non-peaceful methods—it is a
                            matter, an internal affair, which should be left to the Chinese people
                            to decide.</p>
                        <p>The third point, which is also a principle to us, is that we do not admit
                            that there can be another country which will take part in the solution
                            of the Taiwan question, including the United States.</p>
                        <p>So it looks as if there is quite a distance between our two sides
                            concerning this question. As I said just now, it appears that you still
                            need Taiwan. If you still need Taiwan we can wait. We can wait until the
                            time is more ripe for the solution of the question.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Let me
                            comment on the three points. Then let me say one other thing.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: We were checking
                            with the records we have about what Chairman <persName>Mao</persName>
                            said last year and we feel our understanding is correct. What Chairman
                                <persName>Mao</persName> said last year is that we should separate
                            the two things, that is, the relations between the United States and us
                            and the relations between Taiwan and the United States. These two things
                            should be separate.</p>
                        <p>Then the Chairman went on to say that if you break your diplomatic
                            relations with Taiwan, then it will be possible to solve the issue of
                            diplomatic relations. That is to say, like what we did with Japan. We
                            understand that refers to the Japan model.</p>
                        <p>And then the Chairman went on to say that, as for the relation between
                            Taiwan and us, we do not believe in peaceful transition.</p>
                        <p>Then the Chairman said we can do without Taiwan—we can wait for one
                            hundred years to solve the problem. And the Chairman also said, “As for
                            the relation between you and us, I do not think that will take one
                            hundred years to solve.”</p>
                        <p>I think from this conversation the meaning is clear.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I agree. This
                            is exactly my recollection of the conversation. From this I also made
                            certain deductions, produced by my brain which is somewhat slower than
                            that of the Chinese. I have never had a Chinese contradict me on my
                            statement (laughter).</p>
                        <p>I remember once Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CE1">Chou
                                En-lai</persName> made the comment that I was intelligent, and I
                            said by Chinese standards you mean I am of medium intelligence. He did
                            not contradict me either (laughter).</p>
                        <p>But let me say what I deduce from this conversation; because my
                            understanding is exactly the same as what the Vice Premier has said.</p>
                        <p>I deduce from it that the precondition for normalization of relations is
                            breaking diplomatic relations with Taiwan. That we are prepared to do.
                            And I believe we can find a mutually satisfactory formula for this.</p>
                        <pb facs="0615" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/>
                        <p>The second conclusion I draw from the statement of the Chairman was he
                            believes diplomatic relations could be established, and after that there
                            might be a time interval until the real integration [of Taiwan into the
                                <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>] is complete—in his perspective
                            of history.</p>
                        <p>Now of the three principles you have mentioned, Mr. Vice Premier, the
                            first is, in our judgment, no problem. We will work out a solution that
                            leaves no doubt there is no “one China–one Taiwan.” This is a soluble
                            problem—much easier than many other problems we have solved before.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: But it won’t do
                            if you establish a liaison office in Taiwan, or for that matter a
                            consulate.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I still
                            believe this is a problem to which we can find a solution. I see the
                            Ambassador [<persName corresp="#p_HZ1">Huang Chen</persName>] has a very
                            proprietary interest in the concept of a liaison office. He is the head
                            of the only liaison office in the world which is headed by a Chinese
                            Ambassador.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HZ1">Huang Chen</persName>: My understanding about
                            the nature of a liaison office is according to the ideas which Chairman
                                <persName>Mao</persName> gave—the nature of a liaison office.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I repeat, I
                            believe we can find a solution to the first problem. Although we are not
                            now in a detailed consultation. I believe we can find a solution to
                            it.</p>
                        <p>The second question: We do not wish to participate in any way in the
                            process of reintegration, or in the process of realization of
                            reintegration.</p>
                        <p>The third problem is the one I have put to you: How we can avoid the
                            impression that we have simply jettisoned people with whom we have been
                            associated without giving—as in the passage you read to me, how we can
                            have a period of time to give this process a chance to work.</p>
                        <p>Namely, that diplomatic relations can be established before the process
                            of reintegration is completed—how this can be expressed in our
                            agreement. This is the serious question.</p>
                        <p>It seems to me we have two roads we can take, and we are prepared to take
                            either.</p>
                        <p>One road is that we, the United States, proceed unilaterally to reduce
                            its standing on Taiwan, the way we have been doing. We will do this by
                            withdrawing troops. And at the appropriate time before 1976 [reducing]
                            the seniority of our diplomatic representation.</p>
                        <p>The other is that we begin a negotiation on the three points which we
                            have discussed here. I do not believe our differences need be
                            insurmountable.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: I believe we can
                            continue our discussion on this issue. I do not think we have too much
                            time this afternoon for the <pb facs="0616" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/>
                            question. It looks as if probably it is difficult for both sides to
                            reach any agreement on this visit of yours.</p>
                        <p>We have another consideration about the relations between our two
                            countries. That is, as I have said before, some people have been saying
                            the relations between our two countries have been cooling down. The
                            Chinese Government is therefore extending an invitation to you. That is
                            to say, the Chinese Government wishes to extend a formal invitation to
                            the Secretary of Defense of the United States, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName>, to visit China. We think
                            this would be a good answer to all these opinions which are going on in
                            the world.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: It will
                            produce a Politburo meeting in the Kremlin.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: We don’t mind.
                            Well, actually, it is our wish that they have a Politburo meeting there.
                            But we really extend this invitation with all seriousness.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I appreciate
                            this, and let me think about it. Let me say, however, one thing in
                            principle. We believe from our side it is highly desirable to show that
                            our relationship has not chilled and that we should continue to show not
                            only that it has not chilled but that it is continuing to improve. And
                            whatever the decision on this particular invitation, I am certain we can
                            between us find methods of showing a substantial improvement in our
                            relationship.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: We will be
                            waiting for your answer then—from your government.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister Ch’iao: We understand Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGHW1">Bush</persName> is going to give a reception this afternoon.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador Bush: My wife has spent most of her time waiting, so don’t
                            worry about that.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: We suggest 9:00
                            tomorrow morning [for the next meeting].</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I suggest
                            that at the beginning, for perhaps one-half hour, we have a very small
                            group. On your side it is up to you. I will bring only three people,
                            including me. You can have as many as you want.</p>
                        <p>Vice Premier <persName corresp="#p_DX1">Teng</persName>: We shall decide
                            the number of our participants according to the percentage of our whole
                            population (laughter).</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: In relation
                            to ours! So you will have 12. It will not take very long.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>