<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Argentina ( (Weddell) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-06-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectaC46Ncpjf3NEb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011129"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Trade balance</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-06-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="170"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">835.5151/556</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1203</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-06-01">June 1,
                            1936</date>.<lb/>[Received June 12.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honour to recall to the Department
                    that on instructions contained in its telegram No. 37 of April 29, 6 p.m.,
                        1935,<note n="33" xml:id="d170fn33">
                        <ref target="frus1935v04#pg_273">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 273</ref>.</note> the Embassy in
                    protesting against the Argentine decree establishing a surcharge of twenty per
                    cent, on goods entering Argentina without prior permit, took up with the
                    Argentine Foreign Office the question of the reported intention of the Argentine
                    Government to favor countries with which Argentina has a favorable trade balance
                    in the matter of Government contracts. No satisfactory results were obtained.
                    From time to time the Embassy has subsequently heard of various Government
                    contracts being awarded to firms of countries with which <pb facs="0306" n="207"
                        xml:id="pg_207"/> Argentina has a trade agreement even though the American
                    bids were substantially lower.</p>
                <p>In this connection and as illustrative of what I have just said are the facts set
                    forth in a letter (copy enclosed)<note n="34" xml:id="d170fn34">Not
                        printed.</note> the Embassy has received from Mr. C. T. Brady, Jr., American
                    representative of the United States Steel Products Company. In this case it will
                    be seen that while the bids of three American concerns for merchandise desired
                    by the Argentine Ministry of Agriculture were lower than the bid of a British
                    concern, the latter received the contract.</p>
                <p>I have reported in my despatch No. 1130 of April 17, 1936, my recent
                    conversations with the present Minister of Finance, Dr. Roberto M. Ortiz, in
                    which I have urged equality of treatment for American interests in matters of
                    exchange, Government bids, etc. The Minister who on the surface at least takes a
                    different attitude toward this question from that of his predecessor, Dr.
                    Pinedo, assured me that more liberal treatment would be accorded American goods.
                    In my despatch No. 1137 of April 20 I enclosed a copy of a memorandum received
                    from him stating in effect that the general situation in Argentina did not make
                    it possible for the exchange treatment applied to the United States to be
                    exactly the same as that granted to countries which have signed commercial and
                    exchange agreements or treaties on any basis, but that it was the intention of
                    the Argentine Government to endeavor by all means to make it possible for such a
                    treaty to be concluded with the United States.<note n="35" xml:id="d170fn35">See
                        section entitled “Preliminary Discussions Respecting a Trade Agreement
                        Between the United States and Argentina,” <ref target="#pg_174">pp.
                            174</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I enclose for the Department’s information the English text of a communication in
                    Spanish dated May 29<note n="34" xml:id="d170fn36">Not printed.</note> which I
                    sent to Dr. Ortiz on this subject. In my communication I referred specifically
                    to the contract for merchandise for the Ministry of Agriculture mentioned above
                    in this despatch and requested his good offices in working for a change of
                    attitude and policy on the part of the Argentine officials toward American
                    concerns.</p>
                <p>While I shall do everything I can to remove these discriminations against
                    American commerce, I very much fear that the situation will continue precisely
                    as it is today until such time as the United States is in a position to insist
                    on equitable treatment and to make its insistence effective. The Argentines are
                    fully aware of their present advantage and are leaving no stone unturned to
                    persuade us to come to a trade agreement with them. At the moment they are
                    negotiating with the British for a renewal of the Roca-Runciman Agreement and
                    will throw everything they can to the British to facilitate that end. Moreover,
                    the Argentine Government has reaped a small fortune, <pb facs="0307" n="208"
                        xml:id="pg_208"/> variously calculated to be today in the neighborhood of
                    300,000,000 pesos, through exchange manipulation and I can foresee that it will
                    be very loath indeed to give up such a source of easy money.</p>
                <p>I should greatly value the Department’s comments and instructions on the
                    foregoing.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexander W. Weddkll</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
