<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-06-23T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-06-23T14:00:00-05:00" n="206" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">824.00/776: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Bolivia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Muccio</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">La
                                    Paz</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-06-23T15:00:00-04:00">June 23, 1936—3
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>34. My telegram June 22, 10 a.m. Two new members of governing Junta took
                            oath of office June 23, noon. Finot has been appointed as Minister of
                            Foreign Affairs. I should like to point out that Chief of Army Staff
                            manifesto of June 21 states “the army from this date takes possession of
                            the Government.” The note from Acting Minister of Foreign Affairs
                            received this morning states “the army has assumed full responsibility
                            of the Government satisfying the confidence in the military members of
                            the Junta and leaving the President with full liberty to complete it and
                            develop the program which has been planned.” Colonel Toro decree dated
                            June 22 states “that the army has assumed exclusive government of the
                            country, that it is necessary to provide the executive power. The
                            Military Junta of Government is constituted in the following form.”
                            Juridically this indicates an actual change in the Government though
                            President and six members of the Junta did not take new oath this
                            morning and in interview with the press Toro stated all acts,
                            declarations, and public manifestos of former Junta remain in force both
                            in internal and international matters.</p>
                        <pb facs="0336" n="237" xml:id="pg_237"/>
                        <p>In fact, present Junta is continuation of former Junta and direct army
                            intervention was merely to reproach representatives on Junta. I do not
                            consider that question of recognition therefore arises.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Muccio</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>