<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-04-24T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-04-24T15:00:00-05:00" n="216" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">632.6231/44: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gibson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de
                                        Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-04-24T17:00:00-03:00">April 24, 1936—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received April 24—4:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>117. Department’s 62, April 17, 6 p.m. There is now a prospect that a
                            temporary accord delimiting Brazilian trade with Germany may be
                            concluded within the next few weeks under presidential decree of
                            December 30, 1935<note n="5" xml:id="d216fn5">Brazil, Ministerio das
                                Relates Exteriores, <hi rend="italic">Relatorio</hi>. 1935, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 357.</note> transmitted with my
                            despatch 898, January 2, 1936.<note n="6" xml:id="d216fn6">Not
                                printed.</note> Convinced that Germany needs Brazilian cotton
                            immediately, Brazilian officials are holding up exchange permits and
                            expect this to force Germany into making overtures at once. Thereupon
                            Brazil will insist upon quota arrangement in both directions specifying
                            individual commodities and quantities. The German commodities will be
                            those regularly exported from Germany to Brazil prior to compensation
                            mark regime. The Brazilian commodities will be based on average of 1933
                            and 34 exports to Germany, cotton being cut to approximately 40,000 tons
                            as compared with 100,000 in 1935. Consent of Brazilian exporters is said
                            to be forthcoming.</p>
                        <p>Brazil has learned that Germany has been intentionally and needlessly
                            maintaining excess supply of compensation marks here to force additional
                            types of German exports into this market. The aniline dyes and coal
                            which Brazil has been regularly taking could have been shipped against
                            these marks but instead have been sold as from Holland and Switzerland
                            leaving the excess marks as a load on the Bank of Brazil to be cleared
                            only through purchases of new lines of German goods. Discovery that they
                            have thus been exploited has stiffened determination of Brazilian
                            officials to “buy from the Germans what we want from them not what they
                            want to sell us and to sell them what we want them to take not what we
                            could sell elsewhere anyhow.” At present, however, Brazil does not
                            intend to insist on a favorable balance with Germany but is willing to
                            exchange goods on approximately even terms.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gibson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>