<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-11-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-11-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="446" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d446">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">822.5151/310</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Guayaquil</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McDonough</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 328</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Guayaquil</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-11-06">November 6, 1936</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                November 10.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that according
                            to information obtained today from an undoubtedly reliable source, there
                            is to be no important change in the present Ecuadoran system of control
                            over exchange, imports and exports. The Minister of Hacienda is opposed
                            to any change at present, taking the view that the system should be
                            continued in full force or abolished. Minor administrative changes may
                            be made from time to time.</p>
                        <p>During two months of the control system petitions for permission to
                            import goods amounting to $1,000,000., United States currency, have been
                            filed with the control authorities and permits amounting to $400,000.
                            have been granted. As imports before the control system was put into
                            effect were about $1,000,000. monthly, the comparatively small amount of
                            imports asked for would seem to indicate that large stocks of imported
                            goods are still available.</p>
                        <p>Owing to shortage of the Ecuadoran wheat and sugar crops, rather large
                            imports of flour and sugar are being made. Large orders for sugar at low
                            prices have been placed in Peru.</p>
                        <p>The obligations to American and other foreign exporters which are being
                            paid very slowly are those for goods already shipped before July 31,
                            1936. The exchange control regulations place on the importer the burden
                            of applying for exchange to pay for these pending obligations. The
                            importer often is not interested in seeing that payment is made. The
                            collecting banks may not be very active in trying to obtain exchange
                            especially as the effort involved probably costs them more than the
                            amount of their commission. The American exporter should urge his
                            clients, agents and collecting bank to take steps to obtain payment of
                            these pending obligations at once.</p>
                        <p>The right of tourists to spend their foreign money freely in Ecuador has
                            been reaffirmed. Through some misunderstanding, the passengers and
                            sailors of an American passenger ship recently were not permitted to
                            bring any American money ashore with them and there was no place where
                            they could change their funds into sucres. Steps have <pb facs="0626" n="527" xml:id="pg_527"/> been taken by the local officials to
                            prevent a recurrence of such an incident. The officials desire that
                            complete freedom shall be given to tourists to spend money or traveler’s
                            checks so that dollars may be left in Ecuador. A tourist is not
                            permitted to cash a check or draft.</p>
                        <p>The rumors about possible changes in the control system were mentioned on
                            page 3 of report No. 389 of October 23, 1936, entitled “Monthly Economic
                            Report, October, 1936”,<note n="46a" xml:id="d446fn46a">Not found in
                                Department files.</note> and in despatch No. 326 of November 2,
                            1936, on the subject of “Exchange, import and export control”.<note n="47" xml:id="d446fn47">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <p>The best opinion at present seems to be that the control system might
                            eventually be terminated suddenly just as it was adopted suddenly
                            without notice to the public.<note n="48" xml:id="d446fn48">The Consul
                                General at Guayaquil reported in despatch No. 517, August 18, 1937,
                                that the principal features of the import, export, and exchange
                                control decree of July 30, 1936, were revoked by a decree dated July
                                31, 1937 (822.5151/356), See decree No. 322, July 31, 1937, printed
                                in <hi rend="italic">Registro Oficial</hi>, No. 559, August 7, 1937,
                                pp. 1528–1530.</note> The main factor seems [to?] be extent of the
                            need of the Government of Ecuador for foreign currency to meet its
                            obligations.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dayle C.
                            McDonough</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>