<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-02-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="492" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d492">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">816.51C39/440</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in El Salvador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Corrigan</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 590</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">San
                                        Salvador</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-02-15">February 15, 1936</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                February 26.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the
                            Legation’s despatch No. 579 of February 8, 1936, informing the
                            Department that the Salvadoran Government had approved the bases for a
                            new agreement revising the External Loan Contract of 1922, and to
                            enclose a copy of a form <pb facs="0675" n="576" xml:id="pg_576"/> of
                                agreement<note n="26" xml:id="d492fn26">Not printed.</note> which
                            was handed to me on February 13, 1936, by Mr. Douglas Bradford,
                            Secretary of the Bondholders’ Protective Committee and their
                            representative in recent negotiations with the Government of El
                            Salvador. Mr. Bradford believes that the final agreement will in all
                            probability be substantially as given in this draft.</p>
                        <p>The new rates of interest that would be established under this agreement
                            would be as predicted in recent despatches on the subject: 5½% on the
                            “A” bonds, 4% on the “B” bonds, and 3½% on the “C” issue. The total
                            annual payment for interest, amortization, and the partial redemption of
                            the outstanding scrip, would be $849,063.35. The plan which the draft
                            provides for the retirement of the scrip on the “C” bonds (numbered
                            paragraph 9–<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) is that mentioned in the despatch
                            referred to above as favored by Mr. Bradford: the setting aside of a
                            Scrip Fund to total $270,308.50 out of the annual payments, for the
                            purchase of outstanding scrip during the next five years at the lowest
                            possible price at which it can be obtained, not to exceed 25% of its
                            face value (that is, approximately its present market value). The
                            question of the scrip on the “B” bonds (the British series) is covered
                            separately in paragraph 11 of the draft agreement. Payments on the loan
                            will be resumed as of July 1, 1935, and the new agreement would be
                            considered as bearing the date June 30, 1935.</p>
                        <p>In view of the Department’s previous instructions to the Legation, it is
                            believed that the Department will be particularly interested in the
                            draft agreement’s provisions regarding bonds not deposited with the
                            Committee, and in the continuance of the so-called “security” provisions
                            of the original 1922 Loan Contract.</p>
                        <p>Reference is made in the first connection to the Department’s instruction
                            No. 97 of April 5, 1935, and to its enclosure, a letter of the same date
                            addressed by the Department to Mr. F. J. Lisman, Chairman of the
                                Committee.<note n="27" xml:id="d492fn27">Neither printed.</note></p>
                        <p>The question of the scope of the draft agreement and of deposited and
                            non-deposited bonds is covered in numbered paragraphs 12, 13, and 16,
                            which, for convenience, are quoted below: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“12. Any holders of Bonds of Series “A”, “B” and “C”, whom the
                                    Committee or the Council represents and is or shall be acting
                                    for, who desire to avail themselves of the benefits of this
                                    Agreement and assent hereto may do so by presenting their Bonds,
                                    with coupons maturing July 1, 1935, and subsequently attached,
                                    to the Paying Agent, or to such agent as it may designate, for
                                    stamping, and only such Bonds and coupons as are stamped with
                                    legends substantially as hereinafter set forth shall be entitled
                                    to the benefits of this Agreement.”</p>
                                <pb facs="0676" n="577" xml:id="pg_577"/>
                                <p>(Here follows the form of Legend.)</p>
                                <p>“13. Nothing herein contained shall be deemed to give to any
                                    holders of Bonds not deposited with the Committee or the Council
                                    any right to deposit the same with the Committee or the Council
                                    except upon such terms as may hereafter be agreed upon by the
                                    Committee, the Council and the Republic; nor shall the Committee
                                    or the Council be deemed to have any right to represent, or to
                                    have represented, any holders of Bonds not now or subsequently
                                    deposited with the Committee or the Council.”</p>
                                <p>“16. The Republic agrees that it will not make any agreement with
                                    any other Bondholders of the Bonds of Series “A”, “B” or “C”, on
                                    more favorable terms than this Agreement. Nothing contained in
                                    this agreement shall affect the rights and remedies of
                                    Bondholders who do not assent to the provisions hereof.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>As regards the “security” provisions of the 1922 Loan Contract, reference
                            is made to the Department’s instruction No. 80 of February 25,
                                1935,<note n="28" xml:id="d492fn28"><ref target="frus1935v04#pg_569"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 569</ref>.</note> and to the
                            Legation’s despatch No. 210 of April 12, 1935.<note n="29" xml:id="d492fn29">Not printed.</note> The Department’s instruction
                            referred to the possible omission from a revised agreement of any
                            reference involving the Government of the United States or any of its
                            officials. The Legation’s despatch forwarded to the Department, among
                            other documents, a copy and translation of an undated Memorial prepared
                            by the Salvadoran Ministry of Finance and sent to Mr. Fred Lavis, then
                            representing the Committee in San Salvador, on April 2, 1935, in which
                            it was definitely stated that any new agreement must provide for the
                            payment of the expenses of the local Fiscal Office by the bondholders,
                            and also a copy of a letter from the Minister of Finance to Mr. Lavis
                            dated April 8, 1935, in which he referred to the opposition of
                            Salvadoran public opinion to the clauses of the Contract providing for
                            arbitration by the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court in cases of
                            dispute, and held that under the Salvadoran Civil Code these clauses
                            were illegal and void. Led by interviews given out by the Minister of
                            Finance, the local press at that time instituted a violent campaign
                            against the “security” clauses of the Contract, and it seemed for a time
                            that the Government was resolved to make the revision of these clauses a
                                <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> of any new agreement. The press
                            campaign, however, died out during the summer, and has shown no signs of
                            revival since that time, and as far as the Legation knows the Government
                            has not brought them up in recent conversations with Mr. Bradford.</p>
                        <p>The new draft Agreement specifically calls for the Government’s payment
                            of the expenses of the Paying Agent and its representatives in El
                            Salvador; paragraph 15 reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“15. The Republic agrees to pay all the expenses of the Paying
                                    Agent, and its representatives in El Salvador, in accordance
                                    with the <pb facs="0677" n="578" xml:id="pg_578"/> provisions of
                                    the Loan Contract of 1922 regarding the Fiscal Agent and its
                                    representatives, which provisions are made expressly applicable
                                    thereto, and in addition to pay fees of the Paying Agent in
                                    connection with the purchases of Scrip Certificates hereunder at
                                    the rate fixed in the Loan Contract for retirement of Bonds,
                                    plus all reasonable expenses of the Paying Agent incurred in
                                    connection therewith.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Paragraph 17 would definitely make all unmodified provisions of the 1922
                            Contract an integral part of the new Agreement, and moreover provides
                            that, “In the event of default by the Republic in the performance of any
                            of the provisions herein contained this Agreement shall no longer be of
                            any force or effect, and the rights and remedies of the Bondholders
                            shall be those set forth in the said Loan Contract, with the same force
                            and effect as if this Agreement had never been entered into or assented
                            to by any Bondholders.”</p>
                        <p>Mr. Bradford is confident at present that the new Agreement,
                            substantially worded like the enclosed draft, will be signed without the
                            question of the “security” clauses coming up again. Apparently the
                            reference to the United States Government and its officials mentioned in
                            the Department’s instruction No. 80 of February 25, 1935, will remain a
                            part of the Loan unless action is taken to effect their elimination.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Frank P.
                            Corrigan</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>