<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Mexico (
                    (Daniels))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d590</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">590</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-11-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-11-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="590"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d590">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">312.0051/34</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1285</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-11-23">November 23,
                            1936</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The receipt is acknowledged of your despatch No.
                    4074, dated November 7, 1936, and of your telegram No. 200, of November 19,
                        noon,<note n="30" xml:id="d590fn30">Latter not printed.</note> concerning
                    the new law of expropriation which has now been approved by the Mexican Congress
                    and which you state will undoubtedly be immediately promulgated by the
                    President.</p>
                <pb facs="0823" n="724" xml:id="pg_724"/>
                <p>An examination of the law seems to disclose that it is not confined to agrarian
                    matters but would give authority to expropriate all classes of property. I refer
                    in particular to Article 1 from which it appears that it covers a large number
                    of subjects having little or no relationship to an agrarian program. Paragraph
                    VIII of that Article indicates that the extension of the right of expropriation
                    has for its purpose, among other things, a distribution of wealth.</p>
                <p>Article X of the law fixes, as a basis of compensation for the property seized,
                    the amount declared to the tax or cadastral offices as fiscal value. This
                    obviously is not a proper basis for determining compensation, as decisions of
                    the courts of this country, arbitral tribunals, and foreign offices, have
                    repeatedly held when questions have arisen in the past with respect to
                    compensation to be paid by a government for the requisition of property for
                    public purposes. The basis of compensation is, generally speaking, the fair
                    market value of the property and not the value placed thereon by the owner or
                    the taxing authorities for tax purposes. It probably would seldom, if ever,
                    represent more than the price which might be expected if the property were
                    disposed of at a forced sale. In most instances the value fixed for tax purposes
                    represents even a lesser amount than might be obtained at a forced sale.
                    Apparently the only provision made for appraisal of the property by experts or
                    by judicial processes is that contained in Article X, and that provision is
                    limited to questions pertaining to improvements made or depreciation suffered
                    subsequent to the date of the assignment of fiscal value.</p>
                <p>Article XX provides that the authority which carries out the expropriation shall
                    fix the manner and terms in which the compensation must be paid, which shall
                    never exceed a period of ten years. This is very indefinite and would seem to
                    clothe the authority carrying out the expropriation with complete discretion as
                    to the manner and terms in which compensation shall be paid. It might be in
                    bonds, depreciated currency, goods, or other property. Judging from the
                    experiences of persons from whom agrarian property has been expropriated, there
                    is but little reason to hope that the persons affected by this new law would
                    receive just compensation within a reasonable time as no provision is made in
                    the law for the necessary appropriation nor authorizing such an
                    appropriation.</p>
                <p>This almost unlimited extension of the right of expropriation, coming as it does
                    at a time when every effort is being made to strengthen the friendly relations
                    between the two governments, and to adjust claims that have arisen over a period
                    of years, many of which are claims for property taken under existing agrarian
                    laws, is indeed unfortunate. It is assumed that the President of Mexico is not
                    desirous of promoting feelings of distrust or apprehension as to the safety of
                    investments by Americans in Mexico.</p>
                <pb facs="0824" n="725" xml:id="pg_725"/>
                <p>It is therefore desired that you take up the matter informally and confidentially
                    with President Cárdenas as early as practicable in the sense of the foregoing
                    and express the hope that steps will not be taken to apply this new legislation
                    to American nationals, particularly in the absence of an adequate method for
                    determining and paying just compensation at the time property is taken.</p>
                <p>If you perceive objection to taking the action herein suggested, or have in mind
                    some alternative method of procedure, I shall be glad if you will call me by
                    telephone in order that there may be no unnecessary delay in our efforts to
                    protect, as far as possible, legitimate American investments in Mexico and at
                    the same time preserve and promote the good relations between the two countries
                    in consonance with the policy that the Administration is trying to foster.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Walton Moore</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
