<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Mexico ( (Boal) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1936v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d600</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">600</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1936-06-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1936-06-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-06-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-06-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="600"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d600">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">411.12/2334</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Boal</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 3690</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-06-17">June 17,
                            1936</date>.<lb/>[Received June 18.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Department’s
                    telegram number 97 of June 12, 5 p.m., 1936, and to my telegram number 93 of
                    June 16, 4 p.m., and to enclose a strictly confidential memorandum of
                    conversations I had yesterday at the Foreign Office with Ambassador Castillo
                    Nájera, who is here for consultation with his Government; General Hay, Minister
                    for Foreign Affairs; and Licenciado Beteta, Undersecretary for Foreign
                    Affairs.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre de L. Boal</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chargé in Mexico</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Boal</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-06-16">June 16,
                                1936</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>At the Foreign Office this morning I mentioned to the Ambassador to
                        Washington, Mr. Castillo Nájera, the subject of our note 1634 <pb
                            facs="0835" n="736" xml:id="pg_736"/> of June 2, 1936,<note n="44"
                            xml:id="d600fn44">For text, see draft printed on <ref target="#pg_731"
                                >p. 731</ref>.</note> regarding General Claims arbitration. I told
                        him that I understood that a note was in preparation which might possibly
                        make some difficulty, although of course I did not know what was going to be
                        said. I hoped it would be possible to reach a forthright agreement on the
                        method to be followed, along the lines of the note which we had presented,
                        so as to get this complicated matter proceeded with as soon as possible. I
                        feared that counter-proposals, etc., would merely result in further
                        complication instead of simplifying the problem.</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador suggested that I should take it up with Beteta and said he
                        himself would take it up with the President when he saw him, to urge
                        expeditious and favorable action; he said he would put it on the grounds
                        that Mr. Welles<note n="45" xml:id="d600fn45">Sumner Welles, Assistant
                            Secretary of State.</note> had mentioned it to him.</p>
                    <p>After seeing Ambassador Castillo Nájera, I saw General Hay, and, having given
                        him Ambassador Daniels’ acceptance for the Laredo Highway ceremonies, I also
                        reminded him of the General Claims note.</p>
                    <p>The General said that a note was being prepared; that they had hoped to have
                        it yesterday, but it had been delayed. He said he thought it would meet our
                        views excepting one or two things not clear to them, on which they would
                        desire to have clarification.</p>
                    <p>After leaving General Hay, I stopped in to see Mr. Beteta and we had a long
                        talk of a general character, after which I brought up this matter of General
                        Claims and told him that I had just spoken to General Hay about it.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Beteta said he was the one working on the case in his quality as a
                        lawyer. He said that along most lines our note seemed to be quite acceptable
                        in its proposals for procedure. One point, however, was not clear to them
                        from the note, and that was in regard to the unmemorialized claims. He
                        understood from the note that the proposal was merely to bring up these
                        unmemorialized claims in order that in accordance with the Convention they
                        might receive examination, but that it was not intended to do more than
                        proceed with the formalities in this respect, which would really be just the
                        legalization of their rejection. He understood that all these claims were
                        based on insufficient evidence and if decisions were rendered on them they
                        would have to be adverse ones. Accordingly he felt that while it was a very
                        good idea to bring them before the Commission with a view to disposing of
                        them finally through this procedure, the Mexican Government would not be
                        favorable to any action which would result in opening these claims for
                        extensive study on the basis of their being sufficiently valid and proved to
                        warrant awards to the claims. He <pb facs="0836" n="737" xml:id="pg_737"/>
                        said that if his understanding of the note was correct, he felt that his
                        Government and ours would probably be in agreement regarding the procedure
                        and deposit of an omnibus memorial by June 30 by each Agent. He also
                        remarked that his Department had not yet finally approved the reply to our
                        note and therefore he was speaking merely to express his own personal views
                        on the matter.</p>
                    <p>I am under the impression, however, that he and the Minister are already
                        quite agreed on the reply in the sense of the foregoing.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>P[<hi rend="smallcaps">ierre</hi>] <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> L.
                                B[<hi rend="smallcaps">oal</hi>]</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
