<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-03-28T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-03-28T19:00:00-05:00" n="633" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d633">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.404/1862: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-03-28T18:00:00-06:00">March 28, 1936—6
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 8:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>56. Recently, it has been published that by act of State authorities some
                            Catholic churches have been opened in Colima, Campeche, Oaxaca, Nuevo
                            Leon, Sonora, Sinaloa, and Guerrero. See despatch 3410, March 25 [<hi rend="italic">26</hi>].<note n="74" xml:id="d633fn74">Not
                                printed.</note> Consul at Guaymas thinks outlook in Sonora bright
                            for the opening of churches. Today’s papers state that in Queretaro
                            churches were turned over to boards approved by the municipal president
                            to care for them. The report added “there was much rejoicing by the
                            people”. These are evidences of the spirit of moderation which is
                            indicative of the policy of President Cárdenas as I communicated to the
                            President and to the Department in December.<note n="75" xml:id="d633fn75">Telegram of December 9, 1935, 8 a.m., from the
                                Ambassador in Mexico, <ref target="frus1935v04#pg_806"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 806</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>Yesterday in a conference with President Cárdenas, the first I have had
                            since December, I told him that when I was home I told President
                            Roosevelt that he, President Cárdenas, had stated to me that there would
                            be no persecutions and that I had doubtless observed in my trips through
                            the country a moderating tendency. I also told him that this information
                            had been gratifying to the President. He was careful to say that the
                            policy was in keeping with his purpose when he assumed office. He
                            emphasized that there was no new policy only the carrying out of his
                            original plans. He indicated that local situations would determine the
                            action to be taken in each state. He has made no public statement other
                            than his addresses which have been forwarded in despatches and I do not
                            think he will give out any statement regarding recent developments. He
                            emphasized the overwhelming importance of the economic question. My
                            opinion is that his known moderate policy and opposition to persecution
                            is responsible for the action of the states even though he may not have
                            inspired their action. Fuller particulars by air mail.<note n="76" xml:id="d633fn76">Despatch No. 3416, March 28, not
                            printed.</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Daniels</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>