<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-03-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="829" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d829">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">633.113/22</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lay</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 190</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-03-06">March 6, 1936</date>.<lb/>[Received March
                                14.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of the Department’s Instruction No. 54 of February 12, 1936,
                            concerning Uruguayan customs discrimination on certain American
                            products, with which was enclosed a draft of a note for submission to
                            the Foreign Office.</p>
                        <p>It is observed that this note embodies an implied protest against
                            privileges granted by a recent treaty to Brazilian pine lumber over
                            similar American lumber. In informal discussions with the Foreign
                            Office, I have ascertained that local authorities interpret that treaty
                            provision as coming within the category of privileges to limitrophe
                            countries since it specifies “lumber from Brazil entering Uruguay by
                            land or river ports”, specifically excepting imports through maritime
                            ports. They hold that such privileges constitute recognized exceptions
                            to the application of the most-favored-nation principle whether embodied
                            in a treaty or followed as a simple principle of international
                            commercial intercourse.</p>
                        <p>In view of the fact that the United States Government has maintained that
                            limitrophe countries may in certain cases be accorded special treaties
                            with third parties embodying the most-favored-nation clause, I believe
                            that the case of the American Government might be weakened by the
                            inclusion of the question of treatment of Brazilian pine with those
                            others forming the basis of representations in the draft note. I
                            therefore respectfully request that the elimination of that question be
                            considered by the Department and that I be instructed accordingly.</p>
                        <p>With reference to the last paragraph of the Department’s instruction, I
                            have to report that investigations are now being made concerning
                            differences in valuation and market prices of Brazilian and American
                            hardwoods, the results of which will be transmitted to the Department as
                            soon as obtained.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Julius G. Lay</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>