<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-10-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="854" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d854">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">631.003/518</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Venezuela</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Nicholson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 480</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-10-02">October 2, 1936</date>.<lb/>[Received October
                                6.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my telegram
                            No. 67 of October 1, 4 p.m. and to previous correspondence concerning
                            the proposed increases in the Venezuelan customs tariff, and to report
                            more fully concerning my interview with the Minister for Foreign Affairs
                            on October 1.</p>
                        <pb facs="1072" n="973" xml:id="pg_973"/>
                        <p>Dr. Gil Borges was at pains to repeat his assurances that the proposed
                            tariff increases were not directed against the United States, with which
                            it was a policy of his Government to cultivate friendly relations, nor
                            were they intended to serve as bargaining points in any negotiations for
                            a reciprocal trade agreement between the United States and Venezuela. He
                            appeared to be genuinely concerned as to the effect which the new
                            legislation might have on commercial relations between the two countries
                            and explained that he was continuing his discussions with the Minister
                            of Hacienda in an endeavor to arrive at a compromise which would satisfy
                            the proponents of higher customs duties and at the same time eliminate
                            the principal grounds for objection on the part of the United States. He
                            hoped that these discussions would have proceeded far enough to make a
                            definite reply to my representations early next week.</p>
                        <p>The Minister stated that from the Venezuelan viewpoint, not only was the
                            balance of trade of this country with the United States unfavorable, but
                            that almost half of the imports into Venezuela from the United States
                            represented supplies of various kinds brought in by the oil companies,
                            which were exempt from customs duties in accordance with the terms of
                            the oil concessions. He said that automobiles were regarded as luxuries
                            because many Venezuelans, including laborers, were paying out more than
                            they could afford for private cars, tires and accessories, and that the
                            streets of Caracas had already reached the saturation point as far as
                            motor vehicles were concerned. Moreover, he said, the Ministry of
                            Finance was determined to utilize every possible source of revenue to
                            enable the country to proceed on its program of economic rehabilitation,
                            and that higher customs duties were regarded as essential to a balanced
                            budget.</p>
                        <p>It was evident that the Foreign Minister in our conversation was
                            employing arguments supplied in a memorandum left with him by the
                            Minister of Hacienda, a copy of which he promised to send me later for
                            the Legation’s information. Some of his statements in regard to
                            importations by the oil companies appeared of rather doubtful accuracy,
                            and the Commercial Attaché is preparing a digest of data on this subject
                            which he will request Dr. Planchart, Chief of the Commercial Policy
                            Bureau, to deliver to the Foreign Minister. Dr. Planchart is inclined to
                            favor the American position in connection with the imposition of
                            increased customs duties, but the Ministry of Finance and members of his
                            office are not so easy to convince.</p>
                        <p>In replying to Dr. Gil Borges, I endeavored to show, among other things,
                            that the use of automobiles might be considered an important factor in
                            developing the country when the lack of railways was so obvious; that
                            the great part of Venezuelan products entered the United States free of
                            import duty and that the proposed heavy increases in <pb facs="1073" n="974" xml:id="pg_974"/> automobile duties here might be compared
                            to quota or other restrictions on the entry of Venezuelan coffee or
                            cacao in the United States; that the United States appeared to be the
                            only country adversely affected to any extent by the new Venezuelan
                            tariff scale; that the action of Venezuela in raising its customs duties
                            at this time was a disappointing development to those who were working
                            for a reduction of trade barriers in all parts of the world; and that
                            any negotiations which might be undertaken for a Venezuelan-American
                            trade agreement might be rendered very difficult thereby. These and
                            other arguments have also been used by the Commercial Attaché in his
                            conversations with the Minister of Finance and the Chief of the
                            Commercial Policy Bureau of the Foreign Ministry.</p>
                        <p>At this writing it would appear that the Foreign Minister is endeavoring
                            to do everything possible to meet our views and it is possible that the
                            matter may be discussed in a Cabinet meeting. I am not optimistic as to
                            the possibility of obtaining drastic reductions on the proposed duties
                            affecting all American products but I believe there is some chance of
                            having the duties on passenger cars brought down to a more reasonable
                            level. The Legation will of course, lose no suitable opportunity of
                            continuing its representations on the subject and will keep the
                            Department fully informed as to any change in the situation.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Meredith
                            Nicholson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>