<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>145. Report of the President’s General Advisory Committee on Foreign
                    Assistance Programs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d145</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">145</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKkhgppZ5fwGQoV" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Development assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec8PCbWGrkAaOOXZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001000124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developed countries</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Private investment</term>
                    <term ref="european-economic-community" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="european-economic-community">European Economic Community</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="reclcw7PnxNZVJlcH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006006835"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Donor</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="reckNZbvSeWPsh9jH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036133"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Debt rescheduling</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="145"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d145">
                <head>145. Report of the President’s General Advisory Committee on Foreign
                    Assistance Programs<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d145fn1">Source: Johnson
                        Library, National Security File, Subject File, Foreign Assistance
                        Programs—President’s Advisory Committee on (<persName corresp="#p_PJA3"
                            >Perkins</persName>) [1 of 3], Box 17. No classification marking. The
                        source text comprises pages 21–24 of the Committee’s 43-page report. For
                        another extract from the report, see <ref target="#d79">Document 79</ref>.
                        For additional documentation on this Committee, under the chairmanship of
                            <persName corresp="#p_PJA3">James A. Perkins</persName>, see <ref
                            target="#d32">Documents 32 ff</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-10-25">October 25, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE IN THE NEW ADMINISTRATION</p>
                <p>[Here follow <ref target="#pg_1">pages 1</ref>–<ref target="#pg_21">21</ref> of
                    the report.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Expanded multilateral assistance</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Committee recommends that the United Sates enlarge the share of its
                    development assistance provided through multilateral agencies as rapidly as
                    larger flows can be managed effectively and as other industrialized countries
                    will participate.</p>
                <p>The role of multilateral agencies in the development assistance process has grown
                    in recent years. Cost-sharing among advanced countries through those agencies
                    has been promoted by the United States, and the contributions of the other
                    countries have increased. As shown in Table 3, net multilateral flows are now
                    about $1.3 billion, approximately a sixth of the combined total of multilateral
                    and official bilateral assistance. Only about two-thirds of the multilateral
                    total comes from current official contributions, however, the remainder being
                    provided from private borrowings and drawing down past contributions.</p>
                <p rend="center">Table 3</p>
                <p rend="center">MULTILATERAL DEVELOPMENT ASSISTANCE FLOWS TO LESS DEVELOPED
                    COUNTRIES</p>
                <p>(Disbursements, net of repayments, in $ millions)</p>
                <table cols="4" rows="18">
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="3">
                            <hi rend="italic">Calendar year</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">1963</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">1965</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">1967</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Official contriutions<note n="1" target="d145fn1">Net of principal
                                repayments only; excludes contributions from non-D.A.C.
                                members.</note>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="num">364</cell>
                        <cell role="num">450</cell>
                        <cell role="num">770</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Private purchases of multilateral securities</cell>
                        <cell role="num">-31</cell>
                        <cell role="num">247</cell>
                        <cell role="num">280</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Other multilateral outflow<note n="2" xml:id="d145fn2">Difference
                                between disbursements and receipts of multilateral organizations,
                                largely disbursements out of prior years’ official contirbutions and
                                private investments, but net of contributions, investments and
                                repayments from less developed countries.</note>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="num">469</cell>
                        <cell role="num">349</cell>
                        <cell role="num">238</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Total Multilateral Flows</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="num">802</cell>
                        <cell role="num">1,046</cell>
                        <cell role="num">1,288</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Official bilateral, D.A.C. Countries</cell>
                        <cell role="num">5,707</cell>
                        <cell role="num">5,753</cell>
                        <cell role="num">6,203</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Total Multilateral Plus Official Bilateral</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="num">6,509</cell>
                        <cell role="num">6,799</cell>
                        <cell role="num">7,491</cell>
                    </row>
                    <pb facs="0468" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Private investment<note n="3" xml:id="d145fn3">Includes direct
                                investment, reinvested earnings, net private export credits, and
                                portfolio investment.</note>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="num">2,575</cell>
                        <cell role="num">3,980</cell>
                        <cell role="num">4,110</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Total Development Assistance Flows</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="num">9,084</cell>
                        <cell role="num">10,779</cell>
                        <cell role="num">11,601</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Multilateral Flows By Agency</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>World Bank Family</cell>
                        <cell role="num">431</cell>
                        <cell role="num">569</cell>
                        <cell role="num">694</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Inter-American Development Bank</cell>
                        <cell role="num">75</cell>
                        <cell role="num">109</cell>
                        <cell role="num">146</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Asian Development Bank</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>African Development Bank</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>European Economic Community Institutions</cell>
                        <cell role="num">67</cell>
                        <cell role="num">116</cell>
                        <cell role="num">143</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>United Nations</cell>
                        <cell role="num">229</cell>
                        <cell role="num">252</cell>
                        <cell role="num">305</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">Total</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="num">802</cell>
                        <cell role="num">1,046</cell>
                        <cell role="num">1,288</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The World Bank family provides over half of net multilateral flows, divided more
                    or less evenly between hard-term loans of the Bank itself and easy-term loans of
                    the International Development Association (<gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>).
                    The <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> agencies provide about a quarter, almost
                    all of it for technical assistance. The rest goes through the Inter-American
                    Development Bank, supported largely by the U.S. and limited to the Latin
                    American countries, and the European Economic Community institutions, limited to
                    associated countries in Africa and Europe. The Asian Development Bank and the
                    African Development Bank are just getting into operation.</p>
                <p>There are some significant differences among these agencies. The World Bank
                    family has a very high quality staff, well-established stand-ards of operation,
                    and a clear capacity to expand its operations if additional funds were
                    available, particularly for <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>. The <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> has difficulties in coordinating independent
                    agencies and allocating funds objectively—difficulties that are only gradually
                    being overcome. The regional development banks face in different ways the
                    problem of accommodating sound standards with borrower control, and the Asian
                    and African Banks must still build staff and experience.</p>
                <p>The Committee believes that the United States should increase its contributions
                    to competent international banks, along with other contributors, as rapidly as
                    the banks are prepared to undertake the additional responsibilities. This
                    approach will take advantage of the experience and acceptability of the
                    multilateral agencies, avoid some of the Congressional and diplomatic
                    tribulations of A.I.D., and put pressure <pb facs="0469" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"
                    /> on all advanced countries to share in the development assistance system.</p>
                <p>A particular problem arises because of the size and wealth of the United States.
                    Our share in the <gloss target="#t_GNP1">GNP</gloss> of the D.A.C. countries
                    exceed 50 percent, but if our share in the financing of the multilateral banks
                    increased to more than half, their multilateral character would be weakened. The
                    Committee endorses three possibilities for meeting this problem. First, the
                    United States should offer to raise its share in the next replenishment of
                        <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> from 40 to 45 percent, and to forego
                    special balance of payments protection. Second, the U.S. should be willing to
                    contribute shares at a proportion higher than 45 percent to Special Funds
                    administered by the regional development banks. Third, if the World Bank and
                        <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> will agree to accept Special Funds for
                    particular countries, the U.S. should be prepared to make transfers of bilateral
                    assistance funds in appropriate cases, where the advantages of multilateral
                    administration are strong.</p>
                <p>The Committee recognizes that bilateral assistance has important special
                    strengths which make a combination of multilateral and bilateral programs
                    desirable in the world system. As noted above, A.I.D. has played a leadership
                    role in relation to both the other advanced nations and the multilateral
                    institutions. Other larger donor countries, particularly Germany, France, Japan,
                    and Italy, are committed to bilateral programs, because of distinctive
                    geographical interests and problems of domestic political support. The United
                    States has mutual interests with most of our present large-scale aid recipients
                    that are better developed on a bilateral basis. Our ability to work with them in
                    the future is an important part of the rationale for development assistance.
                    Finally, starting from where the multilateral agencies now are, doubling their
                    rate of disbursements over the next five years would be a considerable
                    management achievement. But as shown in Table 5 below,<note n="2"
                        target="d145fn2">Not printed.</note> even this would still leave a need for
                    bilateral assistance programs larger than at present.</p>
                <p>The Committee emphasizes that an equally important aspect of multilateralism is
                    closer coordination of all assistance to individual countries through various
                    forms of consultative groups of aid-supplying countries. There are now eighteen
                    such groups—in India, Pakistan, Ceylon, Turkey, Greece, Morocco, Tunisia,
                    Nigeria, Ghana, Sudan, East Africa, Colombia, Ecuador, Peru, Malaysia, Thailand,
                    Indonesia, and Korea. They cover close to half of worldwide development
                    assistance. Some are still weak. But where the staffs of multilateral
                    institutions have provided leadership, supported by the U.S., such groups have
                    permitted reasonably objective negotiation of the types and amounts of
                    assistance <pb facs="0470" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/> that are most needed, the
                    terms on which it should be made available, and the economic policy measures
                    that should be adopted.</p>
                <p>The multilateral agencies, however, need to strengthen themselves as development
                    agencies to take full advantage of these opportunities. In particular, the World
                    Bank should play a more energetic role as leader in consultative groups, provide
                    more program loans, and encourage self-help through country programming. It
                    should take the lead in debt rescheduling negotiations, offer more high-level
                    technical assistance to the planning process in host countries, and establish
                    small field staffs in major aid-receiving countries. It would be helpful if it
                    modified its procedures to accept Special Funds for individual countries. Under
                    its new president the Bank is moving along several of these lines. Further steps
                    would strengthen the promising trends in multilateral cooperation already under
                    way.</p>
                <p>[Here follow <ref target="#pg_25">pages 25</ref>–<ref target="#pg_43">43</ref> of
                    the report.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
