<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>163. Airgram From the Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and
                    European Regional Organizations to the to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-01-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-01-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046493"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Export control</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recWYz3Xt2MpsE9Ck" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093072"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nuclear reactor</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-01-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-01-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="163"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                <head>163. Airgram From the <gloss type="from">Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty
                        Organization and European Regional Organizations</gloss> to the <gloss
                        type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d163fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_STR1">STR</gloss> 4. Secret; Priority. Drafted by
                            <persName>Philip M. Lindsay</persName> and <persName>F. D.
                            Hockersmith</persName> (<gloss target="#t_ST1">ST</gloss>) on January 5,
                        and contents approved by <persName>Patten D. Allen</persName> (<gloss
                            target="#t_ST1">ST</gloss>). Repeated to the <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss> capitals except Luxembourg, Ottawa, and Reykjavik, and to
                        Berlin, Algiers, Beirut, Belgrade, Bern, Bucharest, Budapest, Helsinki,
                        Madrid, Prague, Rabat, Sofia, Stockholm, Vienna, Warsaw, Amsterdam, Antwerp,
                        Barcelona, Bilbao, Birmingham, Bremen, Casablanca, Dusseldorf, Frankfurt,
                        Genoa, Goteborg, Hamburg, Liverpool, Munich, Naples, Rotterdam, Stuttgart,
                        Trieste, Zurich, <gloss target="#t_EUCOM1">EUCOM</gloss> J4, <gloss
                            target="#t_USA1">USA</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_COMZEUR1"
                        >COMZEUR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_USAFE1">USAFE</gloss>, and
                        PDD-Frankfurt.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">POLTO A–392</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-01-06"
                            >January 6, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Economic Defense Officers’ Conference in Berlin, December 3 and 4,
                        1964</item>
                </list>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>REF</head>
                    <item>A. <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>-4126, October 15, 1964</item>
                    <item>B. <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>-5171, November 13, 1964<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d163fn2">Neither printed. (Both ibid.)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">Begin Confidential</p>
                <p>Economic Defense Officers (<gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss>s) from most of the
                    addressee posts, and representatives from the military commands listed, attended
                    a conference on export control enforcement problems in Berlin on December 3 and
                    4, 1964 with representatives of the Departments of State, Defense and Commerce,
                        <gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USRO1"
                        >USRO</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ST1">ST</gloss>-Paris. This report follows
                    the order of the agenda listed in ref. B.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. Report on Multilateral Developments.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The US <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_COCOM1"
                        >COCOM</gloss> gave a brief general description of <gloss target="#t_COCOM1"
                        >COCOM</gloss>, stressing its informal nature, and describing the general
                    philosophies of the three leading <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss>
                    countries, the US, <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and France, who follow
                    every discussion in <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> with the closest
                    interest. Noting that Germany in its outlook could almost be considered a fourth
                    member of the <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> hard core, he stated that
                    the remaining 11 participating countries (<gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>s)
                    usually do not take active independent parts in debates unless their direct
                    commercial interests are involved. This description of <gloss target="#t_PC1"
                        >PC</gloss> outlook led to a brief resume of the recently concluded List
                    Review, wherein the US proposed adding several strategic items to the lists in
                    order to have more effective strategic controls, whereas the only proposals made
                    by other <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>s were for deletion or relaxation of
                    controls over items in order to further their commercial interests. The last
                    List Review <pb facs="0511" n="477" xml:id="pg_477"/> ended with several
                    expressions of dissatisfaction. The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and some
                    other <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>s felt that it had lasted too long. The
                    French, who had second thoughts about a particular item they had agreed to,
                    announced unilaterally that in the future they would not be bound by agreements
                    reached on individual items until after the whole package of agreements had been
                    reviewed.</p>
                <p>As a corollary to the List Review and the <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>
                    philosophies pertaining to it, the exceptions procedure was mentioned as a good
                    example where <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>s other than the US take
                    positions which favor their commercial interests, and in an apparent log-rolling
                    operation, generally refrain from critical comments on the exception requests
                    made by other <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>s. The <gloss target="#t_EDO1"
                        >EDO</gloss>s were advised that their representations in their assigned
                    posts could materially contribute to a more active cooperation on <gloss
                        target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> controls.</p>
                <p>The next List Review will commence in November 1965. Suggestions have been made
                    by the Chairman and some <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>s to streamline the
                    procedure by requiring prior submission of thoroughly documented proposals and
                    by making greater use of the existing authority to raise individual items for
                    discussion between List Reviews. In cases where only two <gloss target="#t_PC1"
                        >PC</gloss>s are opposed on an item, much might be resolved by bilateral
                    discussions held in advance of the List Review.</p>
                <p>Questions were raised by <gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss>s concerning the
                    future of <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> and the strategic lists. The
                    US <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> explained that the US offers considerable
                    resistance against unjustified relaxation of controls, but that the list has
                    progressively been pared down, with items of principal civilian and commercial
                    use being progressively decontrolled, especially since 1958.</p>
                <p>In reply to a question concerning the Rumanian request to buy a nuclear reactor
                    in the US and the resulting effect on <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss>,
                    it was explained that some months ago the US press had reported the US
                    willingness to consider the Rumanian proposal and the possibility of growing
                        <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> differentiation among Soviet Bloc
                    countries. These reports provoked the foreign press into predicting a
                    considerable relaxation of all embargo controls. All this raised some doubts
                    among other <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>s, especially because it preceded
                    any <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> discussion of the reactor problem.
                    Both the <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> Chairman and the French <gloss
                        target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> appeared to expect unfavorable effects on
                        <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> cooperation. After a preliminary
                        <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> discussion and a series of bilateral
                    discussions with the most directly affected <gloss target="#t_PC1">PC</gloss>s,
                    however, the initial misunderstandings are believed essentially to have been
                    resolved.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Reports on U.S. Export Control Policy Developments.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Director of the Office of Export Control, Department of Commerce, referred to
                    the changing attitude on the part of US businessmen during the past 18 months to
                    two years toward increasing trade with the Communist Bloc countries in Europe in
                    non-strategic items, i.e., items <pb facs="0512" n="478" xml:id="pg_478"/> not
                    multilaterally embargoed. He stressed that this change was not toward more trade
                    or any trade at all with Communist China, North Korea, North Vietnam or Cuba. He
                    referred to the Businessmen’s Conference at the White House in September of 1963
                    and the recommendations of that group that US policies on East-West trade should
                    be re-examined and re-evaluated.<note n="3" xml:id="d163fn3">Reference is to the
                        White House Conference on Export Expansion September 17–18, 1963. Highlights
                        of the report on the conference are printed in <ref
                            target="frus1961-63v09#pg_616">Foreign Relations, 1961–1963, vol. IX,
                            pp. 616</ref>–<ref target="frus1961-63v09#pg_618">618</ref>.</note>
                    Following this he outlined the development of the statement of policy on
                    East-West Trade through the Committees of the US Chamber of Commerce resulting
                    in a statement of policy, somewhat modified, of the US Chamber in April
                        1964.<note n="4" xml:id="d163fn4">Not further identified.</note> He noted
                    that the statement as finally issued was little different from the terms of the
                    Export Control Act itself.</p>
                <p>He referred next to the statement of the President at Lexington, Virginia
                    relative to the “building of bridges” to Eastern European satellites and
                    indicated that work was underway in Washington relative to this aspect of
                        policy.<note n="5" xml:id="d163fn5">Reference is to President <persName
                            corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s remarks at the dedication of the
                            <persName>George C. Marshall</persName> Library on May 23, 1964. Text in
                            <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                                <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B. Johnson</persName>,
                            1963–64</hi>, Book I, pp. 708–710.</note> He indicated that following
                    the election and the Administration’s desire to examine the whole problem of
                    East-West Trade, a group had been set up in the Commerce Department to examine
                    thoroughly the problem from all angles without being influenced by any
                    preconceived ideas or conclusions. In this connection he referred to the recent
                    study of the Department of State where it had been concluded that US-<gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> trade might possibly reach a half-billion
                    dollars over a 5-year period.<note n="6" xml:id="d163fn6">This study has not
                        been found.</note>
                </p>
                <p>He then referred to the recent visit of 92 US business executives to Moscow under
                    the auspices of Business International, the results of which were not yet
                        known.<note n="7" xml:id="d163fn7">Reference is to a week-long roundtable
                        conference in Moscow ending November 23, 1964. Reports on the conference
                        were transmitted in telegram 1584 from Moscow, November 20, and telegram
                        1609 from Moscow, November 23. (Both in Department of State, Central Files,
                        TP 3 <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> (MO))</note>
                </p>
                <p>As to the future he pointed out that there still remains a great deal of
                    opposition to trade with the Communist Bloc on the part of a substantial portion
                    of the Congress and the voluble public. He concluded by indicating that while
                    some relaxation might occur in the coming months on trade in non-embargoed or
                    non-strategic goods, he personally did not look for any substantial change in
                    the reasonably near future. Reference was also made to the report by the Senate
                    Foreign Relations Committee giving the views of business and university
                    authorities on this subject.</p>
                <pb facs="0513" n="479" xml:id="pg_479"/>
                <p>[Here follow summaries of the Cuban denial program, U.S. Export Licensing
                    procedures, <gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss> questions and suggestions
                    regarding publications, special area problems, U.S. export control investigative
                    and enforcement problems, non-member (<gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss>)
                    country controls, administrative action program, controls on <gloss
                        target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> and foreign excess property, and <gloss
                        target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss> comments and special problems.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">U.S. <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> Comments:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This was the first <gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss> Conference for many of
                    those present. These, as well as their more experienced colleagues, showed a
                    keen interest in the proceedings and made good use of the informal question and
                    answer sessions which followed each presentation. The meeting served not only to
                    acquaint <gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss>s with policies, regulations and
                    practices of Washington export control agencies but with the peculiar and
                    particular problems of their <gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss> colleagues from
                    other countries. Not the least of the benefits derived from this meeting was the
                    insight obtained by the Washington visitors into the varying situations and
                    problems encountered by the <gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss>s in the field.
                    The give and take of the question and answer sessions consequently did not
                    result in a one-way flow of information from Washington to the field but a much
                    more valuable two-way exchange of information and experience.</p>
                <p>It was evident from the attitude and comments of the participants that these
                    annual <gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss> meetings are valuable in stimulating
                    the interest of the <gloss target="#t_EDO1">EDO</gloss>s in their export control
                    activities in clarifying policies and regulations, and in contributing to the
                    general overall effectiveness of the program both in Washington and in the
                    field.</p>
                <p>As in the past it is considered beneficial to have as wide an attendance as
                    possible from all major posts in <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> Member
                    Countries as well as from the important non-member countries and areas where
                    aspects of export control activity are experienced.</p>
                <p>The US <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> is firmly of the opinion that these
                    meetings should be continued on an annual basis as in the past.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Finletter</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
