<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>169. Telegram From the Embassy in the Soviet Union to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d169</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">169</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-03-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="reccAEF3WTG3YVwaX" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85065851"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Industrial development</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="recXoDJKMCaKGDSrd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade relations</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-03-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="169"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d169">
                <head>169. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Soviet Union</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d169fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Committee File, <persName corresp="#p_MJI1">Miller</persName>
                        Committee, Meetings, Box 16. Confidential. Sent via pouch and received on
                        March 22 at 5:27 p.m. Repeated to Paris for <gloss target="#t_USRO1"
                            >USRO</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-03-11"
                            >March 11, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Unnumbered. I welcome establishment Presidential Committee on East-West trade and
                    venture following observations on how our policy on trade with Soviet Union
                    might contribute modestly to President’s Balance of Payments program.</p>
                <p>Dominant Soviet economic purpose in seeking expansion trade with US continues to
                    be procurement technologically advanced equipment and know-how to accelerate
                    industrial development. Their dominant political objective is obtain removal of
                    US discrimination which galls them and which hamstrings attainment their
                    economic objectives.</p>
                <pb facs="0522" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/>
                <p>Our political purpose should also be measure of “normalization” of framework of
                    trade if and as other tensions in our relations with Soviet Union ease. Such
                    “normalization” would have salutary, mainly “atmos-pheric”, political effect by
                    removing one contentious issue and establishing another area of agreement
                    between us. We should not harbor illusions however either as to importance trade
                    questions in overall political relations or extent to which trade will
                    facilitate effective contact with Soviet society. Unlike some countries in
                    Eastern Europe Soviet foreign trade monopoly thus far shows no significant signs
                    of changes, and Western European businessmen and technicians have been fairly
                    effectively isolated from Soviet society even in construction projects in the
                    provinces.</p>
                <p>Our major economic purpose should be to maximize possible payments surplus with
                    Soviet Union and not the overall level of two-way trade.</p>
                <p>I believe a surplus would be the natural tendency of our trade relations with
                    Soviets given our technological superiority over other sources of supply and
                    apparent dearth Soviet products of interest to US and difficulty of Soviet
                    foreign trade monopoly to operate effectively in our market. A policy of
                    “normalization” of framework of trade would serve to foster this tendency and
                    encourage Soviets spend hard currency earned in Western Europe in United States
                    as they did in case of grain crisis.</p>
                <p>Some elements such a policy are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>A licensing strategy, which while adhering to <gloss
                                target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> rules would offer Soviets level of
                            technology above what is available in Europe, at same time reinforcing
                            natural tendency American businessmen not give latest technology. Hornig
                            group’s observation this connection particularly pertinent.<note n="2"
                                xml:id="d169fn2">Donald Hornig, the President’s Science Adviser,
                                headed a delegation of U.S. industrial research leaders that visited
                                factories, laboratories, and engineering design institutes from
                                Moscow to Novosibirsk in Siberia during a 2-week study tour in
                                mid-November 1964.</note> Seen against background continuing US and
                            Western European economic development and prosperity and relatively
                            decelerating growth rates <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, such
                            strategy would (a) not make “significant contribution” to Soviet
                            economic potential; (b) appear be in harmony with current legislation;
                            and (c) constitute prime factor for development export surplus our trade
                            with <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Examination possibilities under our legislation and international
                            obligations for tying licensing of know-how to export of American-built
                            plant. We disturbed by number of sizeable deals involving export
                            American know-how in European plant motivated by availability credits,
                            tax considerations, cheaper labor, and desire avoid publicity.</item>
                        <pb facs="0523" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Strict avoidance implication in possible economic agreement or
                            official statements that our objective is bilateral balance of trade or
                            that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> concerned that Soviets do not
                            have enough of interest to sell us.<note n="3" xml:id="d169fn3">Inserted
                                by hand in the margin next to this sentence are the words,
                                “Important? Not sure.”</note> “Normalization” of trade framework
                            would require granting <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> treatment,
                            when political situation permits to remove basic element of
                            discrimination despite fact no meaning reciprocity possible under Soviet
                            system. But we see little or nothing to be gained by selective <gloss
                                target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> approach or system of tariff quotas to
                            shape volume or composition Soviet exports to US. After giving Soviets
                            equal tariff opportunity in our market, sales should be clearly their
                            responsibility although they should be warned price slashing tactics
                            likely cause invocation legislative provisions to prevent injury either
                            US or friendly suppliers.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Willingness extend maximum guaranteed 5-year credits for equipment
                            sales, after lend-lease settled.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Soviets will probably shape their position on lend-lease settlement in light
                    anticipated volume and length US credits. They may be expected seek assurance
                    latter would be greater than annual L–L payments. However, to extent Soviets
                    believe L–L settlement would involve opportunity acquire unique advanced
                    American technology, our bargaining position with respect to credits likely
                    improve.</p>
                <p>New Soviet leadership shows signs husbanding scarce foreign exchange resources
                    even more carefully than in past and Soviet procurements in West will be even
                    more selective technologically. We cannot estimate with assurance extent to
                    which Soviets likely run deficit with US but believe they might see their
                    interest to develop partial triangular pattern for relatively modest amounts at
                    expense Western Europe provided we offer them unique technology high on their
                    planner’s preference scale.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Kohler</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
