<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-04-09T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-04-09T12:00:00-05:00" n="214" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d214">
                        <head>214. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission in Geneva</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d214fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, INCO–GRAINS <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>. Limited
                                Official Use. Repeated to Bonn, Brussels for <gloss target="#t_USEC1">USEC</gloss>, The Hague, Luxembourg for <gloss target="#t_USEC1">USEC</gloss>, Paris for <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss>, Rome, London, Buenos Aires,
                                Canberra, Ottawa, and Tokyo and passed to the White House for
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> on April
                                10.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-04-09T18:00:00+01:00">April 9, 1964, 6 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_TAGG1">TAGG</gloss> 1936. Pass Agriculture. For
                            Governor <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_BWM2">Blumenthal</persName>. <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> Group on Cereals.</p>
                        <p>Statement by cereals exporting countries, April 7.</p>
                        <p>Discussions in the group in the period 17 March to 3 April have
                            significantly clarified the positions of member governments on each of
                            the “elements” which, it had been agreed earlier, should be taken into
                            account in an international grains arrangement and have revealed certain
                            areas of possible agreement.</p>
                        <p>It is the considered view of the exporting countries, however, that
                            further progress in the negotiation as a whole is dependent upon a
                            narrowing of the basic differences which appear to exist in respect to
                            the ways and means of giving effect to the objective set out in the
                            ministerial resolution of May 1963 “to create acceptable conditions of
                            access to world markets for cereals in furtherance of a significant
                            development <pb facs="0619" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/> and expansion of
                            world trade in cereals.” Fulfillment of the objective will involve a
                            satisfactory outcome to negotiations in all the elements previously
                            agreed upon, all of which are, of course, closely interrelated. But the
                            fundamental issues are those concerning questions of domestic policies
                            and assurances of access opportunities.</p>
                        <p>The position of exporters in respect to these vital questions can be
                            stated clearly and simply: <list>
                                <label>(A)</label>
                                <item>All contracting parties would undertake to so arrange their
                                    domestic cereals policies as to achieve the objectives
                                    established by <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> Ministers.
                                    The agreement itself and the obligations undertaken thereunder
                                    should represent <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>
                                    commitments and have the same validity and continuity as tariff
                                    bindings.</item>
                                <label>(B)</label>
                                <item>Cereals importing countries would so set their prices and
                                    otherwise conduct their domestic cereals policies as to assure
                                    cereals exporting countries as a whole the opportunity to
                                    compete for at least their present share of importers
                                    consumption. This would require cereals importers to maintain
                                    their cereals imports at levels at least equal to those of a
                                    recent representative period and provide exporting countries as
                                    a whole with the opportunity to share proportionately in any
                                    growth in consumption in importing countries.</item>
                                <label>(C)</label>
                                <item>To this end, the levels of producer prices for grain should be
                                    established and bound at levels which will effectively reduce
                                    the incentive for uneconomic production.</item>
                                <label>(D)</label>
                                <item>The mere binding of margins of support as suggested by the
                                        <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> will not achieve the
                                    objectives established by the <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> Ministers. It is essential that the bindings
                                    be at levels which are consistent with these objectives. While
                                    the means used to attain these objectives may take the form in
                                    some countries of reducing and binding domestic prices and
                                    income supports, in other cases, negotiation of reductions and
                                    bindings of tariffs and other border controls may suffice. In
                                    still other cases, the measures that might be employed to carry
                                    out the access objectives may include the limitation of
                                    guaranteed returns to producers to specified quantities.</item>
                                <label>(E)</label>
                                <item>Whatever methods are employed must be effective in achieving
                                    objectives established by <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>
                                    Ministers. To this end, importing countries would therefore not
                                    only undertake to arrange their domestic cereals policies so as
                                    to meet the objectives of the arrangement but would also commit
                                    themselves to take prompt and effective remedial action in the
                                    event the objectives were not realized. The nature of the
                                    remedial action would be at the discretion of the importing
                                    country.</item>
                                <label>(F)</label>
                                <item>The exporters, on their part, are prepared to negotiate
                                    similar limitations on their domestic cereals policies to the
                                    extent required to carry out the broader objectives of the
                                    arrangement including a more economic balance between world
                                    supply and demand. Specifically, they <pb facs="0620" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/> are willing to commit themselves to adjust
                                    as required their production and stocking policies, and to
                                    follow marketing practices that assure importers a regular
                                    supply of cereals at equitable and stable prices. To this end,
                                    exporters are willing to undertake to supply importers
                                    requirements within a specified price range.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>All parties should agree to progressively reduce export subsidies.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="strong">Tubby</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>