<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-11-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="300" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d300">
                        <head>300. Memorandum From the Chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers
                                (<persName corresp="#p_AHG1" type="from">Ackley</persName>) to
                            Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_KNB1" type="to">Katzenbach</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d300fn1">Source: Johnson Library, Confidential File, Oversize Attachments
                                12/65, Box 161. No classification marking.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-11-13">November 13, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Copper</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The present situation in the market for copper and the outlook for the
                            near future pose serious risks to the stability of the U.S. economy and
                            to the common defense. These risks can only be avoided if the President
                            is able, as necessary, to release into the market some portion of the
                            copper contained in our national stockpile.</p>
                        <p>The United States depends for a significant fraction of its copper supply
                            on imports from abroad. Both in the United States and in the free world,
                            copper consumption has been expanding in the past several years more
                            rapidly than copper production. Existing and threatened interferences
                            with the supply of copper may intensify this disparity. As a result,
                            shortages and inflationary price rises have appeared, and threaten to
                            become more widespread. These have tended to interfere with the normal
                            channels of supply of copper to industry and may do so increasingly <pb facs="0778" n="744" xml:id="pg_744"/> in the future. Such
                            interferences can impair the ability of defense contractors and
                            suppliers of essential civilian goods and services to produce for the
                            common defense and for the maintenance of a healthy economy.</p>
                        <p>The world supply of copper has been repeatedly interrupted during the
                            past several years through strikes and political disturbances in several
                            major producing countries. Since most copper producers are operating at
                            capacity, interruptions of supply cannot be easily made up. At the
                            present time, the Chilean copper industry, which produces 15% of the
                            free-world supply and is the largest single foreign supplier for the
                            United States, is on strike, with a loss already which is estimated at
                            30,000 tons. The supply of copper from Zambia is in serious danger of
                            being cut off by the differences between Rhodesia and her neighbors.
                            Zambian production is even larger than Chile’s, and its interruption
                            would immediately impose serious disruptions on the economies of our
                            allies in Western Europe, with immediate repercussions on our own.</p>
                        <p>The result of the disruptions already suffered and of the speculation
                            promoted by the threat of further disruptions in the future has been the
                            creation of shortages and inflationary increases in the price of copper.
                            The large producers of primary copper in the world, including the
                            principal U.S. producers, have endeavored to maintain the flow of their
                            copper to their regular customers under long-term contracts. However,
                            growing demand and restricted supply have prevented the large producers
                            from supplying the full needs of their customers, many of whom have had
                            to turn elsewhere for a substantial fraction of their requirements. The
                            residual “outside” or “dealers” market, both in the United States and in
                            Europe, is supplied by small producers and by copper refined from scrap.
                            The enlarged demands placed on this market have forced copper prices
                            above 60 cents a pound both in New York and in London, compared with the
                            recent price of the large primary producers of 36 cents.</p>
                        <p>These circumstances not only pose serious inequities on users of copper,
                            who must obtain varying fractions of their supply in the two markets,
                            but threaten as well the further disruption of supply. The wide price
                            differential tends to divert copper supply into the outside market. This
                            may result in the increased outflow of copper and copper scrap from the
                            United States, or from the United States and its allies to other
                            countries. And the threat of even greater shortages and still higher
                            prices tends to induce the hoarding of copper, not only by pure
                            speculators but by normal suppliers and users of copper. Indeed, there
                            is already some evidence of the building-up of speculative inventories
                            of copper both in the United States and abroad.</p>
                        <p>An orderly supply of copper is essential for our economic and military
                            strength. Copper is used in a great variety of products, from electrical
                            machinery to automobiles, from household plumbing to our coinage. <pb facs="0779" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> It is a key material in the
                            war in Vietnam. It is essential in the production of ammunition, planes
                            and helicopters, communications equipment, military vehicles, and many
                            other defense products. Defense uses in 1966 are expected to be more
                            than double those in 1965.</p>
                        <p>In addition to the existing and threatened interferences with defense and
                            essential civilian production, the health of our economy and the
                            strength of our Nation are also directly threatened by the increase of
                            our price level associated with recent and prospective developments in
                            the copper market. Higher prices for copper and copper products have
                            contributed significantly to the rise in the index of wholesale
                            industrial prices in the past year, a rise which follows several years
                            of complete stability. As copper prices continue to rise, the pressure
                            on the Nation’s industrial price level becomes greater. Higher
                            industrial prices affect the cost of living, increase the pressures for
                            wage increases in excess of productivity gains, and threaten to touch
                            off a wage-price spiral. A wage-price spiral would greatly impair our
                            ability to restore equilibrium in our balance of payments. A strong
                            balance of payments is essential to our ability to command resources
                            beyond our borders for defense and other essential national purposes.
                            Development of a wage-price spiral would require policies designed to
                            curb inflation by reducing total production and incomes and thereby the
                            economic welfare of every citizen.</p>
                        <p>The release of copper from the national stockpile will offset the loss of
                            production that has been suffered due to disturbances in the major
                            supplying countries. It will help meet the increased demands caused by
                            the step-up in the war in Vietnam and by expanding civilian needs. It
                            will reduce or eliminate disruptions to the normal channels of copper
                            supply and tendencies for copper to be diverted to export or to useless
                            hoards. By contributing to the stability of copper prices, it will help
                            assure continued stability of our industrial price structure. It will
                            thereby help preserve the cost-price record which has been so
                            fundamental to our economic expansion and to the restoration of
                            equilibrium in our balance of payments.</p>
                        <p>Clearly, the President needs to be able to release copper from the
                            stockpile for the common defense and to protect the health of the U.S.
                            economy.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_AHG1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Gardner Ackley</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>