<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-04-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="6" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d6">
                        <head>6. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG2" type="from">Bundy</persName>) to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d6fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> Memos to the President, Vol.
                                1–4, 11/23/63–5/27/64, Box 1. No classification marking. A
                                handwritten note on the source text by a White House secretary
                                reads: “Rec’d 4/2/64.” The source text also bears the President’s
                                initial.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-04-02">April 2, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The Administration’s Argument on its <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> Presentation</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>After the <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> lunch last week<note n="2" xml:id="d6fn2">President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>,
                                and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> met at 1 p.m.
                                on March 24 at the White House for lunch. (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> Appointment Books, 1964)</note>
                            you asked me to talk with <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Dave
                                Bell</persName> about the <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>
                            presentation and the relation between his argument and <persName>Bob
                                McNamara</persName>’s.<note n="3" xml:id="d6fn3">On March 23 and 24,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName> testified before the
                                House Foreign Affairs Committee on H.R. 10502 to amend further the
                                Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as amended. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> testified the next day.
                                For text of the testimonies, see <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Assistance Act of 1964: Hearings Before the Committee on Foreign
                                    Affairs, House of Representatives, 88th Congress, 2nd Session,
                                    on H.R. 10502, March 23–25, 1964, Part I</hi>, pp. 15–37 and
                                39–97.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName> tells me that his own
                            presentation was in line with your message and his talks with you: that
                            there is no difference in principle between this year’s request for $3.4
                            and last year’s request for $4.5. His main argument is that this year we
                            are asking only for what we <hi rend="italic">know</hi> we will need,
                            while last year our request was tailored to meet the <hi rend="italic">possible</hi> requirements of countries with incompleted plans. The
                            $1.1 billion difference is explained by $400 million in military aid,
                            $150 million in the contingency request, $350 million in tighter
                            estimates of the effective level of commitment, and $200 million by not
                            respecting last year’s request for the addition of this amount to the
                            Social Progress Trust Fund. So on his side <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName> sticks to the notion that this is a lean budget
                            which nevertheless will do what we now know to be necessary. He also
                            sticks to the formula that we will come in for more money if and when we
                            need it (and we well may in Brazil, for example).</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName> also reports that as soon as
                            he learned of <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s
                            proposed testimony, he called Bob to raise the question whether it was
                            consistent with your position. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said he had already made his argument in the
                            Armed Services Committee and would have to repeat it before the Foreign
                            Aid Committee. The <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi> editorial this
                            morning shows the difficulty this puts us in, but <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName> concedes that <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s position may well protect
                            the military side of the <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> budget in
                            political terms.</p>
                        <p>The hazard is, however, that the weight of any budgetary cutting will
                            fall on the economic side, where the budget is lean indeed. <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName> hopes that you will be ready to
                            weigh in at the appropriate moment with the <pb facs="0048" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/> Committee Chairmen on this point. Unless instructed
                            differently, he will continue with his own line of argument, and he
                            leaves it to you whether <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s special argument should be continued or
                            modified.</p>
                        <p>My own view is that Bob has done what he quite often does—made the case
                            his own way without checking with everybody else—but that we should not
                            try to change his position for him right now.</p>
                        <p>The next question is what you should say if you get this one at a press
                            conference. My suggestion is that your answer might be something like
                            this: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> request as a whole is
                                    the bare minimum which is essential in the national interest. We
                                    will ask for more if events compel it.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> has
                                    correctly stated that if we had any hope of getting any more
                                    money now from the Congress for military assistance, it would
                                    serve the national interest to have such additional funds. You
                                    have no reason to quarrel with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s estimate of the
                                    readiness of the Congress to provide such additional
                                    funds.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Neither the military nor the economic portions of the <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> program can safely be cut this
                                    year. You decided to submit an <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> program without padding, and that is what you
                                    have done.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">
                                    <hi rend="strong">McG. B.</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>