<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="1008" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1008">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.9421/51</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1272</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-03">May 3, 1935</date>.<lb/>[Received May
                                18.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of the Department’s instruction No. 677, dated January 28, 1935,
                            and the Department’s telegraphic instruction No. 71, April 27, 2
                                p.m.,<note n="26" xml:id="d1008fn26">Telegram not printed; it
                                reported the conversation of April 25.</note> with regard to a draft
                            of a proposed consular convention with Japan, upon which the Department
                            requests the suggestions of the Embassy and the Consulate General.</p>
                        <p>The draft convention was referred to the Consul General and his memoranda
                            on the subject are enclosed herewith.<note n="27" xml:id="d1008fn27">Memoranda not printed.</note> The proposed convention has also been
                            studied by the officers of the Embassy, whose suggestions in regard to
                            points on which it is believed some improvement might be effected are as
                            follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Article V. While the Embassy agrees with the Consul General
                                    that it would be most desirable that the privilege of entry free
                                    of customs duty be extended to tobacco, if possible, it is
                                    difficult to see how this could be done under the present laws
                                    in Japan, which are so framed that only the Ambassador himself
                                    can legally import tobacco free of duty. If, however, the
                                    privilege of importing tobacco free of duty could be extended to
                                    consul officers, it is certain that the privilege would be
                                    greatly appreciated by the officers.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Article VI. It appears that the reference to “All taxes …<note n="28" xml:id="d1008fn28">Omission indicated in the original
                                        despatch.</note> levied upon their persons or upon their
                                    property” might be more definite. It is almost certain that
                                    cases will arise in the future where consular officers will
                                    endeavor to extend the immunity to taxation to various indirect
                                    taxes, such as consumption taxes, excise taxes, motorcar
                                    licenses, fishing licenses, etc., giving rise to much trouble
                                    and discussion. It is suggested that the phrase “all direct
                                    taxes” might be more definite and tend to avoid
                                    misinterpretation.</item>
                                <pb facs="1166" n="1054" xml:id="pg_1054"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Article VI, Comment. It is suggested in the comment that the
                                    privilege of exemption from payment of customs duties might be
                                    extended to officials of the Governments other than consular
                                    officers. While the Embassy has no doubt that the privilege
                                    would be greatly appreciated by the American officials stationed
                                    in Japan, where the customs duties are high, it appears probable
                                    that the granting of the privelege to too many people (some of
                                    whom have not been trained in the rigid codes which govern our
                                    Foreign Service Officers) might lead to scandals and trouble in
                                    the future. Moreover, it might not be advisable for the United
                                    States, with its strict laws against the importation of various
                                    articles, such as plants and narcotic drugs, to grant the
                                    privilege of free entry to too large a group of people.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Article XVI, page 19. The clause “so far as the laws of the
                                    country permit” in defining the right of a consul to take charge
                                    of the effects of one of his countrymen who dies intestate
                                    within his district, possibly may be necessary in order to
                                    accord with the laws of some of the States of the United States,
                                    but as far as Japan is concerned it appears possible that this
                                    qualifying clause might lead to difficulties. As a matter of
                                    general practice, the Japanese authorities are not only willing
                                    but glad to allow the American consuls to take charge of the
                                    effects of deceased American citizens, as they do not desire the
                                    labor of attempting to administer an estate, however small,
                                    belonging to a foreigner. At least one case is known to the
                                    Embassy, however, where the Japanese authorities, apparently for
                                    some reason of their own, endeavored to obtain possession of the
                                    effects of a highly-placed American who died in Japan. It
                                    therefore appears advisable, to clear up any ambiguity which may
                                    exist, to make it mandatory upon the local authorities to turn
                                    over charge to a consular officer of the effects of a
                                    fellow-countryman who dies intestate within the consular
                                    district.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>