<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="124" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/7067</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Dairen</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grummon</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)<note n="46" xml:id="d124fn46">Copy
                                transmitted to the Department by the Consul without covering
                                despatch; received June 17.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Dairen</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-15">May 15, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that Colonel
                            Takashi Sakai, chief-of-staff of the Japanese garrison in North China
                            arrived yesterday morning at Dairen en route to his post at Tientsin,
                            and made a long press statement regarding present relations between
                            Japan and China. The following extracts therefrom may be of interest to
                            the Embassy in view of the recent report that the Japanese Foreign
                            Office has decided to raise the Legation at Peiping to the rank of an
                            Embassy as well as of reports that the military is opposed to such a
                            change: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The present North China situation should cause neither
                                    jubilation nor any anxiety. It is gradually improving from the
                                    Japanese viewpoint, but no rapid and drastic change in the
                                    pending Sino-Japanese relations could be confidently expected
                                    until all the vicious anti-Japanese agencies in China are
                                    exterminated, and the Nanking leaders have a thorough cleansing
                                    of their hearts, and cease indulging in the rainbow hope of an
                                    active Occidental coalition against Japan. The situation
                                    requires patience and vigilance on our part; the time and the
                                    logic of events are in our favor.</p>
                                <pb facs="0280" n="168" xml:id="pg_168"/>
                                <p>“I went to Tokyo primarily to attend the annual conference of the
                                    chiefs-of-staff of the entire Japanese army,” explained Col.
                                    Sakai, “But I also met while there number of eminent military
                                    and civilian dignitaries of the Imperial government. It was
                                    rather strange to hear some responsible officials there
                                    accepting almost at face value the recent pro-Japanese
                                    statements of the Nanking emissaries. Some Japanese
                                    industrialists and traders, interested in Chinese trade, who
                                    should know better, were also inclined to dance to the Nanking
                                    music of feigned friendship.</p>
                                <p>“The general public in Manchuria and abroad should keep in mind
                                    the fact that occasional disorders, kidnappings, and murders of
                                    traders, editors and officials are normal events in China, and
                                    should not place undue importance to such affairs. China has
                                    been a disorderly land for ages; the present era is really no
                                    worse than many previous epochs in that country.</p>
                                <p>“The recent murders of two Chinese editors in Tientsin were given
                                    undue importance in newspapers. The murdered men were persons of
                                    no importance, and China has plenty of assassins for hire.</p>
                                <p>“I can assure you that there is no conflict of views between the
                                    war and foreign ministries in Tokyo. There may have been minor
                                    differences of opinions between certain officials of the two
                                    ministries. But the cardinal policies of the war and foreign
                                    ministries are cooperative and harmonious, specially in regard
                                    to China.</p>
                                <p>“The Tokyo official circles are well aware that the present
                                    Nanking government is honeycombed with anti-Japanese influences
                                    and agencies. From Chiang Kai-shek down there are many
                                    anti-Japanese politicians, generals and agitators holding
                                    prominent posts in the Nanking government. Probably, nothing
                                    short of the inexorable course of events will change their
                                    minds. That takes some years.</p>
                                <p>“Viewed from a larger prospect of history the Manchuria Incident
                                    and its aftermath, meaning the present Sino-Japanese relations,
                                    are simply a natural and belated result of the Russo-Japanese
                                    war. That has complicated the position of Japan in Manchuria and
                                    China. The complicated situation was allowed to drift for nearly
                                    30 years, until the events of September, 1931, brought it to a
                                    climax. We are now witnessing the gradual and natural settlement
                                    of that explosive climax.</p>
                                <p>“So there is nothing to warrant anxiety nor fear on the part of
                                    the Japanese people. They should face the Chinese situation with
                                    confidence and calm. We have the power to tide over the crisis,
                                    started four years ago and now settling favorably.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Manchuria Daily News</hi> of last night carried an
                            editorial regarding the projected change in status of the Legation at
                            Peiping stating “that Great Britain, United States and France which have
                            considerable interests and rights in China have not yet deemed it fit to
                            raise their respective legations in China to the status of embassies.
                            Only Italy has raised the Italian legation in China to an embassy, but
                            in reality the result is nothing to boast about.”</p>
                        <p>[Here follows further quotation of the editorial.]</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart E.
                            Grummon</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>