<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recozOKDL3hzRM0mM" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="150"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">761.94/834</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1331</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-31">May 31,
                            1935</date>.<lb/>[Received June 15.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to despatch No. 500 of
                    March 25, 1935, from the Embassy in Moscow<note n="63" xml:id="d150fn63">Not
                        printed.</note> on the subject of Soviet-Japanese Relations in which the
                    belief of Mr. Demaree Bess<note n="64" xml:id="d150fn64">Moscow correspondent of
                        the <hi rend="italic">Christian Science Monitor</hi>.</note> and Mr. Walter
                        Duranty<note n="65" xml:id="d150fn65">Special correspondent of the <hi
                            rend="italic">New York Times</hi>.</note> that “considerable progress is
                    being made between the Soviet Union and Japan in respect of a <hi rend="italic"
                        >détente</hi> and a mutual understanding with regard to their respective
                    interests” was reported to the Department. Despite recent improvement the
                    Soviet-Japanese situation does not appear fundamentally to be entirely
                    satisfactory to Japanese military leaders, especially in the Kwantung Army. As
                    this Embassy has reported before, the Japanese Government does not think or act
                    as a unit and, even in the special field of the Foreign Office, the attitude of
                    the military limits the freedom of action of Mr. Hirota and his colleagues. At
                    the present time it is perhaps pertinent to discuss the attitude of the military
                    towards the USSR in so far as it has been revealed.</p>
                <p>Although the Japanese Army is genuinely motivated by idealistic sentiments which
                    envisage an exalted role for the Empire, the army’s interest in Soviet-Japanese
                    relations falls into two general categories. One of these is the conventional
                    role of an army, the problem of defending the national territories and
                    dependencies. The other derives from the circumstance that through its
                    constitutional prerogative of direct appeal to the Throne the army occupies a
                    position of such weight and independence that it may have and, in certain
                    instances, may carry into effect (as it did in 1931) policies quite separate
                    from those conceived in the Foreign Office. From this fact arises a second,
                    extraordinary role, largely political in nature, which devolves from the army’s
                    efforts to preserve its preeminent position in the national life.</p>
                <p>In so far as the conventional role of the army is concerned, the defense of
                    “Manchukuo” against the USSR is a technical and strategic problem. The army is
                    now responsible for the defense of the whole area of Manchuria as well as the
                    Japanese Empire and this situation presents certain new aspects. For the first
                    time there is no buffer region militarily speaking, between Russia and Japan;
                    for the first time there is a long continental frontier. Before leaving Tokyo on
                    his present trip to Manchuria the War Minister, General Hayashi, is <pb
                        facs="0306" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/> reliably reported to have stated that
                    one of the objectives of his trip was to study the problem of the defense,
                    delimitation, and demilitarization of this frontier. Incidentally he told one of
                    the local correspondents of the American press that he favored the reduction of
                    Soviet troops along the border to the strength of the Japanese forces on the
                    Manchurian side. Accordingly, were the Japanese Army content to limit its
                    activity to the military exigencies of the Soviet-Japanese-“Manchukuo”
                    situation, a <hi rend="italic">détente</hi> or pact such as Messrs. Bess and
                    Duranty seem to envisage would not be faced with extraordinary difficulties. In
                    fact it would tend to facilitate the discharge of the army’s duty of ensuring
                    the defense of “Manchukuo”. However, the maintenance of the army’s traditional
                    position within Japan as well as its present predominance within the Government
                    complicates the situation.</p>
                <p>Turning then to the extraordinary role of the army in Japan, there are three
                    general factors of perennial importance which render unlikely the acceptance by
                    the army of any pact or mutual understanding with Soviet Russia. They tend to
                    align the army against the Foreign Office; they made it impossible for the
                    Foreign Office to accept Russia’s offer of a non-aggression pact in 1931; and
                    they greatly influenced Mr. Hirota in his choice of a policy of settling
                    specific Soviet-Japanese problems one by one. The three factors are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The annual compilation of the budget is at hand and it is said that
                            the army intends to seek an even larger appropriation for 1936–1937 and
                            thereby to improve the present military machine.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The perpetuation of the predominant position of the army in Japanese
                            national life depends in some measure upon the existence of a potential
                            enemy or menace, and Russia is the traditional and logical country to
                            fulfill this role.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The army does not intend to bind itself by restrictions which might
                            limit any course of action deemed advisable in future; it remains
                            suspicious of the USSR.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>To justify its position in accordance with the foregoing three factors one would
                    expect the appearance of anti-Soviet propaganda. The following items are
                    pertinent in this connection:</p>
                <p>On April 23 the <hi rend="italic">Chugai Shogyo</hi> asserted that the army had
                    sounded a warning against excessive optimism for the future of Soviet-Japanese
                    relations merely because of the transfer of the Chinese Eastern Railway. The
                    article pointed out that the Soviets were not withdrawing troops from the Far
                    East to Europe despite the settlement of the railway question, remarked on the
                    increased capacity of the transportation system of the USSR in the Far East
                    through double tracking, discussed the progress of Russian heavy industry
                    producing war material, and charged the Soviets with seizing the delta between
                    the Amur and Ussuri Rivers and erecting strong <pb facs="0307" n="195"
                        xml:id="pg_195"/> fortifications there. On the same day Major General
                    Itagaki, Vice Chief of Staff of the Kwantung Army, told newspaper men that the
                    Soviet menace had not yet passed. On April 25 a rumor was given wide publicity
                    that the Soviet authorities are shortly to commence construction work on a new
                    railway linking Chita and Urga, a move which the army is said to interpret as
                    indicative of a more aggressive policy in Outer Mongolia. On April 28 another
                    article was circulated by Rengo and Nippon Dempo in which certain views
                    allegedly held by the military were set forth. According to this article it was
                    stated that a new proposal for a non-aggression pact on the part of the USSR
                    would meet with no more favorable reception than did the original proposal of
                    December 1931. It was further claimed that the military had discovered that the
                    Soviets were spending some of the proceeds of the sale of the CER for the
                    expansion of their influence in Sinkiang, that many communists formerly in North
                    Manchuria had now been ordered to North China to foment trouble, and that the
                    military preparations of the USSR were more intensive than ever and pointed to
                    the danger of aggression against “Manchukuo”. On May 8 a Rengo despatch was
                    circulated which claimed that the defense of Vladivostok had been greatly
                    improved, that the Soviets were concentrating their efforts on construction of
                    submarines for the Far Eastern fleet, and that the number of Russian army planes
                    in active service in the Far East now exceeds 800. On May 17 a despatch from
                    Hsinking reported that information current in “certain circles” (i. e. the
                    Kwantung Army) indicated that the Soviet authorities had appropriated proceeds
                    of the sale of the CER for construction of a new network of railways linking
                    Siberia with Sinkiang and Outer Mongolia.</p>
                <p>More important evidence of the attitude of the Japanese military is the recent
                    report concerning a new pamphlet which, according to a Rengo article of May 13,
                    has been in course of preparation by the War Office to deal with the existence
                    of the Soviet menace. According to the report 100,000 copies of this pamphlet
                    are to be distributed throughout the country. It is said that the pamphlet is
                    divided into a historical analysis of the Russian invasion of the Far East, a
                    presentation of the extent of the Soviet military preparations in this region,
                    and an argument proving that a state of crisis still exists in Soviet-Japanese
                    relations.</p>
                <p>The foregoing propaganda is fairly clear indication that, in certain respects at
                    least, the Japanese Army is displeased with the striking improvement in
                    Soviet-Japanese relations; that really cordial relations would not be welcomed
                    by the military; and that the negotiation of a general pact with the USSR
                    remains unlikely. In this connection the tenet held by so many military men in
                    Japan that <pb facs="0308" n="196" xml:id="pg_196"/> Russia must some day be
                    pushed back to Baikal should be remembered. In view of the attitude of the
                    Japanese military therefore it may be stated that Mr. Hirota’s policy of
                    settling individual problems with the Soviet Union one by one is the only one
                    open to him. Moreover it may be stated that no reason is yet seen to modify the
                    belief previously expressed<note n="*" xml:id="d150fn1">Embassy’s despatch No.
                        1236, April 5, 1935. [Footnote in the original; despatch printed on <ref
                            target="#pg_106">p. 106</ref>.]</note> that Soviet-Japanese relations
                    are entering a phase less acute because less vital to Japan. The force of
                    Japanese activities appears to be, for the time being at least, directed
                    elsewhere.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
