<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d234</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">234</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-06-24T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-06-24T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-06-24T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-06-24T03:00:00-05:00" n="234"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d234">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/7111: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-06-24T16:00:00+08:00"
                            >June 24, 1935—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received June 24—2:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>309. Negotiations over the Chahar situation began here last night between Chin
                    Teh-chun together with Cheng Keh, former student in Japan friendly to the Anfu
                    clique, and Doihara and Matsui. Chin telegraphed to Nanking yesterday requesting
                    that he be relieved from the post of acting chairman of Chahar.</p>
                <p>American news correspondent who returned from Kalgan yesterday states that
                    opinion in Kalgan is that all of Sung Che-yuan’s troops will be moved from
                    Chahar when a suitable place is found that these troops being well disciplined
                    will not cause trouble but that some 7,000 irregulars are regarded with
                    apprehension. He states that the Japanese have built an airfield at Kalgan and
                    are behaving toward Chinese officials with effrontery.</p>
                <p>Wang Keh-min arrived at Peiping afternoon June 23 to assume the position of
                    acting chairman of the Peiping Political Affairs Readjustment Committee and met
                    Doihara this morning. According to Chinese newspapermen the National Government
                    has placed a ban on publication of a report that Han Fu-chu submitted his
                    resignation June 22. As it is understood that Han is uncertain about what the
                    Japanese want of him and uncertain with regard to his standing with the National
                    Government submission of resignation might be the result either of Japanese
                    pressure or of his desire for the National Government to clarify its attitude
                    towards him.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
