<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-11-25T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-11-25T04:00:00-05:00" n="395" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d395">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/7429: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Neville</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-11-25T18:00:00+09:00">November 25, 1935—6
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received November 25—2:55 p.m.<note n="50" xml:id="d395fn50">Telegram in two sections.</note>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>216. In conversation with the Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs today he
                            made the following oral statement.</p>
                        <p>1. The present negotiations with Nanking are the result of conversations
                            which the Minister for Foreign Affairs had with the Chinese Ambassador
                            before the latter returned to China to attend the meeting of the
                            Kuomintang. The Ambassador wished to improve relations between Japan and
                            China, a project with which the Minister for Foreign Affairs is in
                            hearty approval. The Ambassador then returned to Nanking and discussed
                            the matter with the officials of the Chinese Government with the result
                            that there were discussions between Japanese and Chinese officials in
                            Nanking and finally Ariyoshi began his conversations with Chiang
                            Kai-shek. The basis of the discussions is three sided. First, the
                            suppression of anti-Japanese propaganda which stirs up the populace to
                            no good purpose; second, the acceptance of the fact of “Manchukuo” which
                            may not necessarily mean diplomatic relations; and finally, means of
                            controlling Communist or Red propaganda which is becoming a serious
                            question both in China and in Manchuria. These Sino-Japanese discussions
                            were interfered with by the attempted assassination of Wang Ching-wei,
                            the murder of a Japanese sailor and the wrecking of a Japanese shop in
                            Shanghai all of which the Japanese have reason to believe are connected.
                            Their reasons are that they know that the Comintern meeting in Moscow,
                            to whose activities both the Japanese and American Governments took
                            exception, considered the question of the Red armies in China and
                            decided to support in every way possible the anti-Japanese movements in
                            China in addition to furthering communistic movements there because they
                            consider the Japanese the greatest menace to Red action in the Far East.
                            However, the Japanese were determined to treat the Shanghai affairs as
                            purely local matters and the conversations continued. They were again
                            disturbed by the Chinese announcement of the nationalization of
                            silver.</p>
                        <p>This had a most unfortunate effect because it put the North China leaders
                            in a panic and some of them went to the Japanese military for advice. It
                            put new life into the autonomy movement which has long existed in a
                            dormant condition.</p>
                        <p>The North China autonomy movement is a matter with which the Japanese
                            Government does not wish to be concerned but it has placed <pb facs="0553" n="441" xml:id="pg_441"/> the Japanese in an
                            embarrassing position because the Chinese leaders in the North have
                            represented to Nanking that the Japanese are urging them to declare
                            autonomy while at the same time these same leaders assure the Japanese
                            that they would declare autonomy over night if it were not for the
                            negotiations that the Japanese are carrying on at Nanking with Chiang
                            Kai-shek which give added strength to the objection of the Central
                            Government. Still the Japanese Government will continue to negotiate
                            with Chiang and will not allow local issues to obscure their object
                            which is to come to a settlement with the Chinese Government along the
                            lines indicated above. At the same time he remarked parenthetically the
                            Japanese feel that any domestic settlement which Chiang may come to in
                            the matter of North China autonomy must take account of (1) the general
                            sentiment in that region which is decidedly opposed to direct Nanking
                            Government, (2) the propinquity of “Manchukuo” and its border problems,
                            (3) the large Japanese interests in the North China area although the
                            latter is a contributing rather than a deciding factor in the situation.
                            He believed that a China centrally governed like Japan or France was an
                            impossibility. The Vice Minister said that he felt hopeful rather than
                            discouraged because he felt that the Chinese now realize the need for an
                            understanding with Japan, an attitude they have not taken hitherto. He
                            said that at no time in the recent discussion has the Japanese
                            Government contemplated the use of armed force although they might be
                            compelled to do so if the Chinese troops moved north. The wild speeches
                            attributed to military officers were largely fictitious he said although
                            he would have to admit that there are some officers with very little
                            discretion. More than that, there is a large element of troublesome
                            Japanese who stir up issues that have no legitimate place in the
                            purposes of the Japanese Government. He said that Chiang was the
                            strongest man in China and that they would continue to work with him.
                            Still he has many enemies and is frequently driven to rather
                            questionable expedients like every man in high political office except
                            that conditions in China are worse than in other countries.</p>
                        <p>2. The foregoing is the first statement I have been able to obtain from a
                            Japanese official. The Vice Minister had obviously thought the matter
                            over carefully and gave every evidence of speaking frankly. The
                            Department will note that there is no sign of easing the Japanese
                            demands but on the other hand the general attitude is not as
                            uncompromising and threatening as was indicated by the reported
                            statements of Japanese Army officers in China.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to Peiping.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Neville</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>