<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d47</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">47</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="47"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d47">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.001 (M) Pu Yi/7</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 686</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-02-05">February 5,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The receipt is acknowledged of your despatch No.
                    1106, dated December 28, 1934,<note n="43" xml:id="d47fn43">Not printed.</note>
                    in which it is requested that the Department give you provisional instructions
                    in regard to the attitude which you should take in the event that invitations
                    are extended to you to attend functions given by the so-called Emperor of
                    “Manchukuo” or given in his honor on the occasion of his projected visit to
                    Tokyo.</p>
                <p>The Department confidently relies upon your judgment and discretion to take such
                    action in regard to the problems envisaged in your despatch under reference as
                    may be best calculated to preserve the dignity and interests of the United
                    States without gratuitously or unnecessarily injuring the susceptibilities of
                    the Japanese people and Government. It believes, therefore, that it would be
                    more helpful to you to have latitude in dealing with these matters than to be
                    restricted by specific and detailed instructions even of a provisional
                    character. The Department would appreciate, however, careful consideration being
                    given to its views and desires as expressed in the following paragraphs.</p>
                <p>The Department expects that you will consult with your British and French
                    colleagues with a view to concerting the action and attitude of the
                    representatives of the principal powers in regard to any <pb facs="0154" n="42"
                        xml:id="pg_42"/> problem that may develop out of the presence in Tokyo of
                    “Emperor Kangte”.</p>
                <p>It is noted that a high official of the Imperial Household has intimated that no
                    invitation to meet “Emperor Kangte” during his sojourn in Tokyo will be
                    addressed to members of the diplomatic corps. It is to be hoped that such will
                    be the case. If, however, invitations are extended to you in the name of the
                    Emperor of Japan to attend social functions to be held by the Imperial Household
                    at which “Emperor Kangte” may be expected to be present as one of the guests,
                    they may in your discretion be accepted, as such acceptance could not, as you
                    are aware, in any way imply recognition of “Manchukuo”.</p>
                <p>The Department is reluctant to believe that the Imperial Household would, in view
                    of the declarations of attitude of the powers vis-à-vis the entity known as
                    “Manchukuo”, address to you and other members of the diplomatic corps
                    invitations in the name of “Emperor Kangte”, or so worded as to indicate that
                    there is intention to do honor to “Emperor Kangte”, but if such invitations are
                    extended to you the Department would expect that you would abstain from
                    accepting them.</p>
                <p>It is assumed that you would not, of course, attend any function which would be
                    made the occasion of political action affecting “Manchukuo”.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William Phillips</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
