<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="553" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d553">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.48/941</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 757</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-06">May 6, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: There are enclosed copies of letters<note n="91" xml:id="d553fn91">None printed.</note> exchanged between the
                            American Cotton Cooperative Association and the Department in regard to
                            102,000 bales of American raw cotton, stated to be in Shanghai, which
                            had previously been purchased in the United States by the Chinese
                            Government under the terms of the wheat and cotton credit extended on
                            May 29, 1933, to the Chinese Government by the Reconstruction Finance
                            Corporation, and which had been purchased by the Association from the
                            Chinese Government. The Association affirms that Chinese cotton mills
                            controlled by Japanese capital “were instructed to boycott the cotton
                            financed by the Reconstruction Finance Corporation and purchased by the
                            Chinese Government”, and that the refusal of such mills to purchase the
                            cotton under reference is detrimental to the consumption in China of
                            American cotton. The Association is inclined to believe that the
                            Japanese-controlled mills in China “would like to see the boycott
                            lifted”, and it suggests that if such assumption is correct a friendly
                            approach to the Japanese Government might at this time meet with a
                            cordial response.</p>
                        <p>In view of the character of the references by officials of the Japanese
                            Government and by the Japanese press to the wheat and cotton credit
                            above mentioned, the Department doubts whether an approach by officers
                            of this Government to the Japanese Government would result in removal of
                            any interdiction which may have been laid down in regard to purchase by
                            Japanese interests of such cotton. However, there have been noted press
                            despatches from Shanghai to the effect that the Commercial Attaché of
                            the Japanese Legation in China entertains the view that Japanese
                            spinning interests should be permitted to purchase the cotton under
                            reference.</p>
                        <p>Any information in regard to the present attitude of the Japanese
                            Government which you may be able to obtain without making inquiry in
                            Japanese official quarters, and your comment in regard to this matter,
                            would be of interest to the Department.</p>
                        <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                        <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William
                                    Phillips</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>