<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-02-20T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-02-20T23:00:00-05:00" n="60" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/6880: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-02-21T12:00:00+08:00">February 21,
                                1935—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 1:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>84. Reference Legation’s telegram 60, February 3, 3 p.m. and paragraph 6
                            of telegram 66, February 7, 2 p.m. According to <pb facs="0173" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/> Chinese News Agency Wang Ching-wei spoke February
                            20, on Sino-Japanese relations before Central Political Council.
                            Referring to speech of January 21 of Japanese Minister of Foreign
                            Affairs, Wang stated that China chooses, under the principles of
                            equality and mutual assistance, to maintain and promote friendly and
                            peaceful relations with any country, “not to mention a neighbor like
                            Japan whose geographical, historical, cultural, and racial relationship
                            with this country is so closely bound.” Wang recalled with emphasis that
                            Sun Yat-sen had said at Kobe in 1924 that Japan and China should work
                            hand in hand. Wang said that this was the basis of Sun’s Sino-Japanese
                            policy throughout his life. Wang recalled the sympathy of Japanese for
                            China down to the revolution, mentioned the unfortunate complications
                            which have developed during the past 20 years, and stated that he
                            believes these complications can be solved by mutual sincerity. Again
                            referring to Hirota’s speech, Wang said that “now that China and Japan
                            have expressed their common desires, it is a matter of great rejoicing
                            for us that by dint of mutual efforts Sino-Japanese relations will
                            henceforth have an opportunity to improve as well as to be restored into
                            regular channels.” He further expressed the wish to solve all
                            complications sincerely and pacifically so that all mutual suspicions
                            and all speeches and actions, repulsive and detrimental, might gradually
                            be eradicated and so that the hope of close friendship as emulated by
                            Sun Yat-sen might be realized.</p>
                        <p>This speech appears to be yet another cautious move in the regimentation
                            of public opinion toward acceptance of Sino-Japanese “cooperation”. With
                            regard to Chinese feeling not much outspoken expression in the press can
                            be anticipated because of government control. Comment which has appeared
                            so far has been critical of and unsympathetic toward Japan. The
                            intelligent Chinese of Peiping show acquiescence in or resignation to
                            the inevitableness of Japanese domination over China for the next
                            generation or two. It is believed that recent developments have caused
                            apprehension among western educated Chinese with reference to their
                            future influence and position in the Government and their participation
                            in the development of China. The Legation will continue to watch Chinese
                            reaction.</p>
                        <p>Sino-Japanese conversations apparently are continuing at Shanghai and
                            Nanking, the latest Japanese participant being the well-known Major
                            General Doihara who already conferred with Wang Ching-wei.</p>
                        <closer>For the Minister:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>