<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-12-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-12-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="635" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d635">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.48/1026</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Raymond C. Mackay of the Division
                                of Far Eastern Affairs</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-12-14">December 14, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Chinese Ambassador at Washington, by letter under date November 18,
                                1935,<note n="57" xml:id="d635fn57">See footnote 54, <ref target="#pg_647">p. 647</ref>.</note> requested of the Farm
                            Credit Administration a material revision of the schedule of payments
                            covering the obligations of the Chinese Government incurred in
                            connection with its purchase in 1931 of certain quantities of wheat and
                            flour. A similar request, also under date November 18, 1935,<note n="57" xml:id="d635fn1">See footnote 54, <ref target="#pg_647">p.
                                647</ref>.</note> was made by the Chinese Ambassador of the
                            Reconstruction Finance Corporation in connection with the obligations of
                            the Chinese Government incurred in connection with its purchase in 1933
                            of certain quantities of cotton and wheat.</p>
                        <p>The Department has now received for transmission to the Chinese
                            Ambassador letters from the Reconstruction Finance Corporation and the
                            Farm Credit Administration<note n="58" xml:id="d635fn58">Neither
                                printed.</note> in reply to the aforementioned communications from
                            the Chinese Ambassador.</p>
                        <p>In the case of the R. F. C. cotton and wheat credit of 1933, the
                            Corporation has indicated that it is prepared to grant to the Chinese
                            Government, in addition to the period provided for in the covering
                            agreement, a further period of two years in which the account may be
                            liquidated. This concession was envisaged but not guaranteed by the R.
                            F. C. in its agreement with the Chinese Government under date May 29,
                            1933.</p>
                        <p>In the case of the wheat credit of 1931, payments in regard to which,
                            under the existing agreement, should be completed on December 31, 1936,
                            the F. C. A. has offered to make a very material concession by extending
                            the period within which the account may be liquidated to September 30,
                            1939. It has also agreed to a sliding scale of payments which, for
                            example, would call for a payment on December 31, 1935, of only $250,000
                            as compared with $3,070,942.18 called for under existing
                            arrangements.</p>
                        <p>Before informing the Chinese Ambassador of the concessions which the R.
                            F. C. and the F. C. A. are prepared to make to the Chinese Government,
                            it would seem highly desirable that further thought be given to the
                            question of those certain obligations of the Chinese Government to
                            American creditors which, notwithstanding repeated protestations on the
                            part of the American Government, have remained in default—with little or
                            no indication by the Chinese Government of concern—over a period of many
                            years. In some cases, notably in connection with indebtedness incurred
                            on large purchases of American <pb facs="0764" n="652" xml:id="pg_652"/>
                            railway materials by agencies of the Chinese Government, new agreements,
                            greatly in the favor of the Chinese Government, have been accepted by
                            American creditors in order that they might obtain at least some payment
                            for goods thus supplied. However, in one case, that of the so-called
                            “Chicago Bank Loan of 1919”,<note n="59" xml:id="d635fn59">In reference
                                to loan negotiations, see <ref target="frus1919v01#pg_505"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 505</ref> ff.</note> the
                            Chinese Government has, since the date of the loan’s maturity in 1921,
                            failed to effect any payments whatsoever, either by way of principal or
                            of interest.</p>
                        <p>The “Chicago Bank Loan” was made to the Chinese Government by the
                            Continental and Commercial Trust and Savings Bank of Chicago, Illinois,
                            under the provisions of a loan agreement and a supplemental agreement
                            bearing the date October 11, 1919. It was issued in amount of $5,500,000
                            U. S. currency and was evidenced by “Republic of China Six Per Cent
                            Two-Year Secured Gold Loan Treasury Notes of 1919”. It was secured by
                            the Chinese Government in respect both to principal and interest “by a
                            direct charge on the Revenues of the Tobacco and Wine Public Sales Tax
                            of the Chinese Government”; by a direct charge on the “Goods tax
                            receipts from the provinces of Honan, Anhwei, Fukien and Shensi, whether
                            receipts be in the nature of likin taxes, transportation taxes or other
                            taxes or imports of like nature”; and, in the event of a deficiency of
                            funds derived from the Tobacco and Wine Tax, by agreement on the part of
                            the Chinese Government to “make good such deficit from other sources of
                            its revenue”. The Chinese Government has not only failed to effect
                            liquidation of this loan but, in disregard of the loan agreement, it has
                            not obtained the bank’s assent to the extinction of the likin taxes
                            pledged. Furthermore, upon its effecting of such extinction, it failed
                            to provide other and satisfactory security.</p>
                        <p>It would appear that the Department bears a special responsibility toward
                            the holders of the Chinese Treasury Notes which were issued to the
                            American public in connection with the loan under discussion. This
                            responsibility arises from the fact that the Department on October 21,
                            1919, complied with a request of the Continental and Commercial Bank for
                            a statement which was so phrased as in effect to attract the investing
                            public to the Chinese loan issue to which it referred and which
                            statement was in fact made a part of the prospectus issued by the bank.
                            That the Department’s statement contributed toward inducing the
                            investing public to purchase the Chinese Treasury Notes offered by the
                            bank is evidenced by testimony in the Department’s files of which a
                            typical example appears in a letter addressed to the Department on
                            November 19, 1935, by one of the note holders who refers to himself as a
                            purchaser who was “induced in large measure to buy these notes on
                            account of a letter furnished by <pb facs="0765" n="653" xml:id="pg_653"/> your department to the Chicago bank when it sold us the loan”.</p>
                        <p>Parenthetically it may be stated that, insofar as the Department is
                            aware, the Chinese Government has never denied its responsibility in
                            connection with, or the validity of, the Chicago Bank Loan—an attitude
                            in sharp contrast to that which, until recently, has characterized the
                            viewpoint of the Chinese Government in regard to the notorious Nishihara
                                Loans<note n="60" xml:id="d635fn60">See <ref target="frus1918#pg_122"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1918, pp. 122</ref>–<ref target="frus1918#pg_123">123</ref>, <ref target="frus1918#pg_130">130</ref>–<ref target="frus1918#pg_133">133</ref>, <ref target="frus1918#pg_147">147</ref>–<ref target="frus1918#pg_148">148</ref>, <ref target="frus1918#pg_155">155</ref>–<ref target="frus1918#pg_159">159</ref>.</note> which were of Japanese origin.
                            Notwithstanding this fact, the American loan remains completely
                            neglected whereas, according to a despatch under date November 13, 1935,
                            from the American Embassy at Peiping,<note n="61" xml:id="d635fn61">Not
                                printed.</note> the Chinese Government is reported to have decided
                            upon payment of 4,500,000 yen in settlement of one of the Japanese loans
                            under reference.</p>
                        <p>Under these circumstances and in view of the foregoing, it is believed
                            that the Department should, by the use of all appropriate and
                            practicable means, continue in its endeavors—and make special effort—to
                            cause the Chinese Government to proceed toward fulfillment of its
                            admitted obligations in connection with the Chicago Bank Loan. To this
                            end, it is suggested that the Chinese Ambassador at Washington be
                            informed orally to the effect that, whereas the American Government, in
                            conformity with its constant desire to afford, whenever appropriately
                            possible, assistance to the Chinese Government, would wish to comply,
                            insofar as the circumstances may permit, with the Chinese Government’s
                            request for a postponement of payments due on the wheat credit of 1931
                            and the cotton and wheat credit of 1933, it seems desirable, before
                            final consideration is given to the matter, to ascertain whether the
                            Chinese Government would be prepared to give positive assurance that it
                            will proceed toward liquidation of the Chicago Bank Loan. It is
                            suggested that the Chinese Ambassador be further informed that, in view
                            of the disturbed political and financial situation in China, it is not
                            expected that the Chinese Government will, at this time, effect payment
                            in full of the loan under reference; that it is expected, however, that
                            the Chinese Government will provide adequate security to replace that
                            which was withdrawn in contravention of the terms of the loan agreement:
                            that, although the Department observes with gratification the apparent
                            improvement in the financial position of the Chinese Government which
                            has rendered possible the reported settlement, among other outstanding
                            obligations, of at least one of the Nishihara loans, there exists in
                            sharp contrast to such developments the fact that American holders of
                            the Chinese note issue under reference have, over a period of many
                            years, been shown by the Chinese Government no consideration; that the
                            Department bears a special responsibility toward the holders of the
                            Chinese Treasury Notes which were issued to the American public in
                            connection <pb facs="0766" n="654" xml:id="pg_654"/> with the loan under
                            discussion; and that, although the American Government should not be
                            expected to provide special inducements to cause the Chinese Government
                            to meet its just obligations to American creditors, the material
                            concessions which the American Government may, under the conditions
                            named, be in position to grant in connection with the postponement of
                            payments due on the wheat credit of 1931 and the cotton and wheat credit
                            of 1933 would in effect free for other uses substantial sums of money
                            which should, in the opinion of the Department, be utilized at least in
                            part to effect a prompt initial payment and to make provision for later
                            payments at periodic intervals on the Chicago Bank Loan.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>