<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Secretary of Commerce ( (Roper))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d735</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">735</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="reclDWPzWLFcH99Zg" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="735"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d735">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.113 Airplanes/101</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Secretary of Commerce</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Roper</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-14">May 14,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: The receipt is acknowledged of
                    Mr. Mitchell’s<note n="65" xml:id="d735fn65">E. Y. Mitchell, Assistant Secretary
                        of Commerce.</note> letter of April 22, 1935, enclosing a copy of a letter
                    of <pb facs="0838" n="726" xml:id="pg_726"/> March 18, addressed by Mr. A. L.
                    Patterson, representative in China of the Bureau of Air Commerce, to the
                    Assistant Director of Air Commerce,<note n="66" xml:id="d735fn66">Neither letter
                        printed.</note> in regard to the restrictions now in effect on the
                    exportation of aircraft and aircraft parts and accessories to China.</p>
                <p>In reply, I have to inform you that the situation which Mr. Patterson discusses
                    in his letter has received the attentive consideration of the Department during
                    the past three or four years. The principal arms exporting countries of the
                    world have placed restrictions upon the exportation of arms and implements of
                    war destined to China, with a view to preventing their use for the fomenting of
                    civil disturbance in that country. We have made efforts to secure such practical
                    uniformity of procedure among all the governments concerned, that these measures
                    of supervision and control may not result in giving advantages to the
                    manufacturers and exporters of one country which are not enjoyed by the
                    manufacturers and exporters of other countries. In most respects, this practical
                    uniformity has now been secured, except as concerns the regulations of the
                    Belgian and Swiss Governments. Efforts are now being made to persuade these two
                    Governments to modify their regulations so as to bring them into line with those
                    of the other exporting governments. In one important respect, this practical
                    uniformity has not as yet been secured. I refer to the definition in the
                    regulations now in effect of civil and military aircraft. This definition and
                    the distinction between the two types of aircraft which should be applied in
                    respect to shipments destined to China has recently been the subject of
                    discussion between this Government and the British Government. In its
                    application to the international traffic in arms in general, it has recently
                    been the subject of discussion in Committees of the General Disarmament
                    Conference in Geneva. No international agreement has, however, as yet been
                    reached on this point. In the meantime, this Department, although it is not at
                    present prepared to modify the procedure now in force, is continuing to give
                    this matter its careful consideration in the light of two principal objectives:
                        (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) that the export of arms and munitions of war from
                    the United States to China shall not promote in China conditions of domestic
                    violence and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) that American manufacturers and
                    exporters be not placed at an unjustifiable disadvantage as compared with their
                    principal foreign competitors.</p>
                <p>I enclose, for your information, a copy of the Revised Regulations in regard to
                    the Export to China of Arms and Munitions of War, of May 28, 1934.<note n="66a"
                        xml:id="d735fn66a">
                        <ref target="frus1934v03#pg_497">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1934, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 497</ref>.</note> You will note that
                    export licenses are required for <pb facs="0839" n="727" xml:id="pg_727"/>
                    military aircraft and for spare parts and equipment therefor. Licenses are not
                    required for aircraft, other than those of specified types, unless the
                    Department has reason to believe in any particular case that the shipment is to
                    be used for military purposes, nor are export licenses required for airplane
                    motors or airplane parts and accessories, unless the Department has reason to
                    believe in any particular case that the shipment is to be used for military
                    purposes.</p>
                <p>I should be pleased to receive any further information in regard to the situation
                    in South China, in respect to export of American aircraft, engines, parts and
                    accessories, which may be brought to your attention.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William Phillips</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Under Secretary</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
