<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="737" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d737">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">846G.113/237</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Division of
                                Far Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-21">May 21, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. Green of WE<note n="68" xml:id="d737fn68">Division of Western
                                European Affairs.</note> and Mr. Mackay and Mr. Hamilton of FE<note n="69" xml:id="d737fn69">Division of Far Eastern Affairs.</note>
                            discussed in detail the situation relating to the export from the United
                            States of small arms and ammunition to Hong Kong, particular reference
                            being had to Hong Kong’s confidential telegram of May 17, 1 p.m. [<hi rend="italic">May 15, 3 p.m.</hi>]. As a result of this discussion
                            it was agreed that the important factors in the situation as it now
                            exists are as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The American exporters have endeavored without success to
                                    obtain from the Hong Kong importers the information desired by
                                    the Department to enable the Department to determine the
                                    ultimate purchaser;</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The American Consul General at Hong Kong has been unable to
                                    obtain this information or information which would afford the
                                    Department a basis for prescribing what particular amount of
                                    arms or ammunition might be construed as for the retail
                                    trade;</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Any attempt by the Department to fix a definite limit as to
                                    the amount of arms or ammunition which might be exported to Hong
                                    Kong during a particular period would operate to bring about
                                    discrimination as between one American exporter and another
                                    American exporter;</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The Department has under discussion with the British
                                    Government a method of handling the situation at Hong Kong,
                                    which, if accepted by the British Government, offers a
                                    reasonable prospect of working satisfactorily;</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Should the Department now devide to permit practically no
                                    exports of small arms and ammunition to Hong Kong, such decision
                                    would result in diverting the present orders now obtained by
                                    American exporters to exporters from other countries, without
                                    effecting a reduction in the amounts imported into China through
                                    Hong Kong.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In view of the foregoing factors, Messrs. Green, Mackay and Hamilton came
                            to the conclusion that, pending the receipt of a reply from the British
                            Government to the last communication from the Department in regard to
                            the situation at Hong Kong, the Department should approve applications
                            for license to export to Hong Kong shipments of small arms and
                            ammunition except when particular circumstances seem to warrant the
                            withholding of a license for any particular shipment.<note n="70" xml:id="d737fn70">The following note was appended to this memorandum
                                by the Under Secretary of State: “Assuming that this is a temporary
                                arrangement I approve your recommendation. We should clear the
                                matter up with the British as soon as possible. W[illiam]
                                P[hillips].”</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>