<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-06-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="823" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d823">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.917 Time/3</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the Division of
                                Far Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-06-06">June 6, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Chinese Minister called and stated that he had received instructions
                            from his Government stating that the Chinese Government found
                            objectionable the terms applied to Chinese Government leaders in the
                            March 18, 1935, issue of the magazine <hi rend="italic">Time;</hi> that
                            other issues of this magazine contained similar statements derogatory to
                            Chinese leaders; that the radio broadcasts entitled “The March of Time”
                            also referred to the Chinese in objectionable terms; that the Chinese
                            Government desired that these objectionable references to the Chinese
                            cease; that the Chinese Government suggested that this end might be
                            attained either by the American Government issuing instructions that
                            such references should be discontinued or by a friendly approach to the
                            editors of <hi rend="italic">Time;</hi> that the Chinese Government
                            understood that the American Congress was considering the enactment of
                            libel legislation applicable to radio broadcasting and suggested
                            therefore that such legislation might make it illegal to broadcast items
                            of the nature <pb facs="0930" n="818" xml:id="pg_818"/> which the
                            Chinese Government found objectionable; and that if the magazine <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> did not cease these objectionable references
                            to Chinese, the Chinese Government would be forced to forbid the entry
                            of this magazine into China.</p>
                        <p>The Chinese Minister stated that he had asked Dr. Willoughby<note n="57" xml:id="d823fn57">Dr. Westel Woodbury Willoughby, former professor
                                of political science at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore,
                                Md.</note> to examine the article on China in the March 18 issue of
                                <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> and that Dr. Willoughby had stated,
                            after examination, that he did not believe that the remarks in regard to
                            Wang Ching-wei<note n="58" xml:id="d823fn58">President of the Chinese
                                Executive Yuan and Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note> and
                            other Chinese would be construed as libel under American statutes.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Hamilton stated that the Department had no legal authority to compel
                            the magazine <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> to refrain from publishing
                            comments of the nature which the Chinese Government found objectionable,
                            and that he doubted whether any informal approach by the Department to
                            the editors of <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> would be advisable, for the
                            reason that the editors might take the stand that the Department was
                            endeavoring to interfere with freedom of the press and might publicize
                            the action of the Department and thereby attract greater attention to
                            the comments made in regard to China.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Hamilton commented that, as the Minister knew, the American people
                            and the American Government believed in freedom of speech and freedom of
                            the press; that because of this belief American statutes relating to
                            libel permitted considerable latitude to the American press and
                            magazines in the publishing of comments; that, although he had not
                            examined recently the article in the March 18 issue of <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> which the Chinese Government found objectionable, it was
                            his recollection that the statements in the article used no more
                            uncomplimentary terms in regard to China and Chinese leaders than
                            statements appearing in other articles of the same magazine and other
                            magazines referring to Americans and American leaders and to various
                            foreign peoples and their leaders; that while we personally regretted
                            the use at any time by the American press and by American magazines of
                            any terms which foreign governments found objectionable, there was very
                            little, if anything, that the American Government could do in the
                            matter; that, in view of Dr. Willoughby’s statement, it was doubted that
                            the statements in the March 18 issue of <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>
                            constituted libel and that, even if they did, Mr. Hamilton seriously
                            questioned the advisability, from point of view of the best interests of
                            the Chinese Government, of the Chinese Government instituting legal
                            measures against <hi rend="italic">Time;</hi> that it seemed to Mr.
                            Hamilton that the best way to handle the matter would <pb facs="0931" n="819" xml:id="pg_819"/> be for the Chinese Government to take no
                            action, for in Mr. Hamilton’s opinion, articles such as this made no
                            particular impression upon the American people whereas the filing of a
                            libel suit based on these comments would bring them forcibly to the
                            attention of the American people; that at times it was possible under
                            American statutes for the Postmaster General to bar from the American
                            mail certain types of publications but that Mr. Hamilton frankly thought
                            that comments made by <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> were not such as to
                            permit the Postmaster General to bar the magazine from the American
                            mails. Mr. Hamilton added that in his personal opinion the Chinese
                            Government would be ill-advised to bar the magazine <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> from entry into China, as such action would probably
                            result in there being created in the minds of many people who were
                            otherwise very friendly disposed toward China the impression that the
                            Chinese Government was disposed to suppress freedom of speech and
                            freedom of the press.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Hamilton stated that, although he personally thought that the
                            attitude of the Department would be along the lines indicated by him as
                            his personal opinion, he would be glad to refer the matter to the Legal
                            Adviser’s office for an expression of opinion.</p>
                        <closer><signed>M[<hi rend="smallcaps">axwell</hi>] M. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">amilton</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>