<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-10-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-10-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="984" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d984">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611B.9417/89</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Sayre</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Appointed High Commissioner in the
                                Philippines</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi></persName>)<note n="89" xml:id="d984fn89">Draft of
                                radiogram transmitted by the Assistant Secretary of State in his
                                letter of October 30 to the Acting Chief of the Bureau of Insular
                                Affairs, War Department.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-10-30">October 30, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>For Messrs. Dorfman and Waring. Your 526, October 29.<note n="90" xml:id="d984fn90">Same as undated telegram received October 28, <ref target="#pg_1012">p. 1012</ref>.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>We are very glad to receive this informative and very helpful
                                telegram.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>It is agreed with the Japanese that transshipments at Hong Kong of
                                cotton piece goods originating in Japan would be included within the
                                annual quota. The Japanese also undertook to regulate as far as
                                practicable shipments to Philippine Islands of cotton piece goods
                                originating in Japanese mills in China. In concluding the
                                arrangement, <pb facs="1129" n="1017" xml:id="pg_1017"/> however, it
                                was agreed that we would not give publicity to the understanding
                                reached in regard to transshipped goods and goods originating in
                                Japanese mills in China.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Your suggestion that the Department issue a press release
                                clarifying the understanding reached with the Japanese in regard to
                                the two points above mentioned was taken up today (October 29) with
                                the Counselor of the Japanese Embassy. We informed him in general of
                                the contents of your telegram and suggested that it seemed important
                                to clear up the misapprehensions which seemed to exist in regard to
                                transshipped goods. The Counselor stated that the Embassy had
                                received a telegram from the Japanese Consul General at Manila
                                containing information substantially along the lines of your
                                telegram under reference. The Counselor, without prompting on our
                                part, pointed out in effect that as the Philippine statistics
                                classified as imports from Japan all imports of Japanese goods
                                whether coming directly or indirectly from Japan, it would
                                necessarily follow that transshipped goods would be included in the
                                quota. He thought that there might be issued a statement making
                                public such fact. We suggested that it would seem preferable if that
                                fact were brought to the attention of the public by the Japanese
                                rather than by ourselves, and he agreed.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The Counselor undertook to communicate with his Government in
                                regard to this matter. It was apparently his thought that some
                                statement along the lines above indicated might be made by the
                                Japanese Consul General at Manila. The Counselor stated that he felt
                                certain that, if the Japanese Government did not desire the issuance
                                of a Japanese statement, it would have no objection to the issuance
                                of an American statement.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>