<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-11-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-11-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="1" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1">
                    <head>1. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                        Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_DRP1" type="from">Davies</persName>) to the Under Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_KNB1" type="to">Katzenbach</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d1fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                            Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Files: Lot 72 D 39, Jordan. Secret.
                            Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HRB1">Robert B. Houghton</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-11-25">November 25, 1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Arms for Jordan</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>There is attached a telegraphic memorandum from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SHM1">Symmes</persName> [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line
                            of source text not declassified</hi>].<note n="2" xml:id="d1fn2">Dated
                            November 24 and addressed to Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Battle</persName>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SHM1">Symmes</persName> is concerned that
                        one of the first matters of business which the King will take up with him
                        when he returns to Amman November 26 is to ask what further response the
                            <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> may have made to his request for
                        arms. The Ambassador is certain that <persName>Hussein</persName> feels that
                        the passage of the U.K. resolution<note n="3" xml:id="d1fn3">Reference is to
                            Resolution 242, adopted by the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            Security Council on November 22. (<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> doc.
                                S/<gloss target="#t_Res1">RES</gloss>/242 (1967)) For documentation
                            relating to the adoption of this resolution, which outlined the basis
                            for a settlement of the Arab-Israeli dispute, see <ref target="frus1964-68v19">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, volume
                                XIX</ref>.</note> was facilitated by his own diplomatic efforts. In
                        addition, the Ambassador points out that it will be indispensable to
                            <persName>Hussein</persName> in continuing to work for a political
                        settlement to have his Army solidly behind him. The Army, according to
                        reports reaching our Embassy, has been generating pressure on the Government
                        to resupply equipment lost during the June war. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SHM1">Symmes</persName> believes that the November 21
                        incidents, with the bombardment of the Karama refugee camp and the Israeli
                        air attack, will heighten this pressure. The Ambassador fears that if the
                        King becomes suspicious that we will not be able to help him out, he could
                        quickly become so frustrated that he might decide to go to the Soviets for
                        arms.</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador reports that the Embassy expects within the next day or so a
                        list of those items whose delivery the Jordanian military command considers
                        absolutely essential.</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador concludes his message by stating that our willingness to lift
                        our embargo on arms for Jordan and to exert efforts to <pb facs="0030" n="2" xml:id="pg_2"/> help Jordan obtain arms from other suppliers may soon
                        become critical to our relationship.<note n="4" xml:id="d1fn4">In telegram
                            74860 to Amman, November 25, the Department responded that the question
                            of arms for Jordan was under intensive review, but in view of the
                            complexity of the problem it was impossible to predict an outcome.
                            (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, DEF 12-5 JORDAN) On November
                            27 the Embassy reiterated the pressing need for a positive response to
                            the Jordanian Government’s request for a recommencement of arms supplies
                            to Jordan. (Telegram 2395 from Amman; ibid.)</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>We subscribe to the Ambassador’s analysis of the pressures which are working
                        on the King to procure arms to re-equip his Army and the likely consequences
                        if we are not in a position to help him. As soon as we have received the
                        list of items which the Jordan Army considers absolutely essential, we will
                        recommend to you a course of action with regard to the shipment of arms to
                        Jordan. In the meantime, we intend, as an interim measure, to query the King
                        as to the status of his efforts to obtain some of his requirements from
                        European sources in the event that we might be able to facilitate his
                        efforts. The Ambassador would make clear that in so querying the King we
                        were trying to be helpful and in no way indicating that we had decided not
                        to supply arms to Jordan.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>