<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>190. Message From Foreign Secretary Stewart to Secretary of State to
                    Secretary of State Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d190</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">190</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recXuFW8WO1tqBrVK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="190"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d190">
                <head>190. Message From Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SM1" type="from"
                        >Stewart</persName> to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1"
                        type="to">Rusk</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d190fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                        POL 27 ARAB-ISR/<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. Confidential. Transmitted
                        to the Department by British Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DSP1">Patrick
                            Dean</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>London</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-06-10"
                            >June 10, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I have asked Pat <persName corresp="#p_DSP1">Dean</persName> to deliver this
                    message about the Arab/Israel situation because I am much concerned about the
                    way events may move during the next few weeks both on the ground in the Middle
                    East and also in New York. The very sharp exchange of fire on 4 June across the
                    Jordan and the subsequent call for a Security Council meeting have underlined
                    the ominous dangers which confront us all. I have in mind also that although the
                    21 May Security Council Resolution on Jerusalem<note n="2" xml:id="d190fn2">On
                        May 21 the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Security Council considered a
                        letter from the Jordanian Permanent Representative protesting actions by
                        Israel to change the status of Jerusalem in contravention of <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> resolutions. Pakistan and Senegal introduced
                        a resolution deploring Israel’s failure to abide by the resolutions relating
                        to Jerusalem, and declaring that all legislative and administrative measures
                        taken by Israel to change the legal status of Jerusalem were invalid. The
                        resolution was adopted by a vote of 13–0, with the United States and Canada
                        abstaining. (<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> doc. S/PV. 1426)</note> did
                    not set a deadline for the Secretary-General to report back to the Council on
                    its implementation, events could easily cause Arab pressure to build up, perhaps
                    very suddenly, for a return to the Council on this issue, particularly as we can
                    presumably rule out any hope of the Israelis doing anything which could even
                    remotely be represented as compliance with the Resolution. All too soon,
                    therefore, we may be confronted with a call for sanctions against Israel, which
                    would involve difficult and dangerous decisions for both our countries. In the
                    circumstances, I attach the greatest importance to our exchanging views with
                    each other and to our trying as far as possible to keep our ideas on how to
                    proceed closely in line. There is the further point that we can expect an
                    approach from Mr. <persName>Malik</persName> to Lord Caradon following up my
                    agreement to Mr. <persName>Gromyko</persName>’s suggestion that the Russians and
                    we should keep in touch on the Middle East. To avoid any possibility of these
                    talks being exploited by the Russians adversely to our common interest, it seems
                    highly desirable that we should make sure that we are working broadly on the
                    same lines with you before matters of substance come up in any Anglo-Soviet
                    meetings in New York. Another reason for our getting together soon is that Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName> indicated to Lord Caradon in a
                    recent talk that he is now thinking in terms of consultation with the permanent
                    members of the Security Council.</p>
                <p>In these circumstances, it seems to me that it would be timely for us to exchange
                    views on the Arab/Israel situation at an early opportunity. <pb facs="0401"
                        n="373" xml:id="pg_373"/> Our presence together in Reykjavik on 23 June for
                    the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting might, if you would agree,
                    provide a suitable opportunity for us to do this. If you agree that this would
                    be helpful, I think it would be desirable if senior officials on both sides
                    could go over the ground first, so that the main problems likely to arise during
                    the next phase can be identified and possible ways of handling them can be
                    reviewed as a basis for our own discussion. I should propose to ask Sir Denis
                    Allen to go to Washington to discuss these problems with your people in the
                    State Department and with representatives of our two U.N. Delegations during the
                    latter part of the week beginning 17 June.</p>
                <p>I should be grateful if you would let me know what you think about this.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d190fn3">A note attached to this message by Executive
                        Secretary Benjamin Read indicates that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1"
                            >Rusk</persName> told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DSP1"
                            >Dean</persName> that he agreed to the proposal for U.S.-British talks
                        on the Middle East.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
