<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>266. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d266</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">266</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-09-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recd7021a58b486ded" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="suez-canal" subject="suez-canal">Suez Canal</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-09-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="266"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d266">
                <head>266. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d266fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, POL 27-14
                        ARAB-ISR. Secret; Exdis. Drafted by Battle on September 30 and approved in U
                        on October 9.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1968-09-29">September 29,
                            1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Views of the United States Government Regarding the Communication
                        Presented by the Government of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Under Secretary</item>
                    <item>His Excellency <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Anatoliy Dobrynin</persName>,
                        Ambassador of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Lucius D. Battle</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The Soviet Ambassador called on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1"
                        >Katzenbach</persName>, at the latter’s request, at his residence on Sunday,
                    September 29, at approximately 8:15 p.m.</p>
                <pb facs="0551" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> handed to the Soviet
                    Ambassador the attached paper which the Under Secretary described as the views
                    of the United States with respect to the recent communication presented by the
                    Government of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to the United
                        States.<note n="2" xml:id="d266fn2">The attached paper was summarized in
                        telegram 254018 to Tel Aviv, October 11. (Ibid., POL 27 ARAB-ISR)</note> Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> emphasized that the paper
                    contained the views of the United States and did not represent the views of the
                    Government of Israel or any other country in the area. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> pointed out that Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName> has worked long and hard and
                    that he has a chance in the weeks ahead with the Foreign Ministers present to
                    make progress under the resolution of November 22, 1967. The United States
                    expects to exercise all influence possible on the situation and hopes to get
                    substantive discussions underway in what will be an important period. It is
                    particularly important, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName>
                    emphasized, for all pressure possible to be placed upon the countries concerned
                    and in particular the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, Jordan, and Israel.
                    The longer there is no move toward peace, the greater the difficulty, and the
                    United States hopes very much that progress will be possible during the New York
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Ambassador asked what the main point was of the communication. Is it
                    merely to assist Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName>?</p>
                <p>The Under Secretary replied that this was the main point and that the United
                    States was making every effort to support him in his efforts.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador asked what was new in the paper. The <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> considers that there must be concrete proposals if there is to
                    be progress.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> replied that we considered
                    proposals for a solution should be advanced by <persName corresp="#p_JG1"
                        >Jarring</persName> in an effort to promote agreement of the parties. One of
                    the most difficult points would be to arrive at a definition, for example, of
                    agreed and secure boundaries.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that the Soviet
                    Union agrees that adjustments in these lines are the business of the parties and
                    not the business of the Soviet Union. However, he felt that it was necessary to
                    make concrete proposals and that the Soviet Union, while wishing to help
                    Jarring, considered that its more detailed suggestions had been a move in that
                    direction. The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> did not wish to press its
                    paper. If the United States does not like the Russian proposal, the Russians
                    would welcome steps by the United States to offer its own plan. France has a
                    practical approach, and other countries must be equally practical.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> replied that the question
                    of timing was an important element. We consider it important to get the parties
                    down to discussion of issues and substance. We believe that we have a common
                    purpose with the Soviet Union of getting a settlement and ending a <pb
                        facs="0552" n="524" xml:id="pg_524"/> dangerous situation. We are reluctant,
                    however, to tell Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName> what
                    to do. He must make that decision.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> replied that Jordan was, he
                    understood, depressed and may give up. What can be done that is practical and
                    will help? The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> is not trying to impose a
                    settlement because of the Czech situation. It, too, wished to help Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName>.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> said that he had not
                    brought up the Czech matter, that the Ambassador had mentioned it first.</p>
                <p>There was general talk of the problems of the area with Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> emphasizing that the Arabs primarily
                    wanted withdrawal while the Israelis primarily want peace arrangements based on
                    recognition of their existence and a permanent arrangement. The United States,
                    of course, is aware that a peace treaty would be difficult, but there were other
                    forms of settlement that could accomplish the same goal.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador agreed to present to the Government of the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> the views contained in the memorandum.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Attachment</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-09-29">September 29, 1968</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The United States Government has noted the views of the Soviet
                            Government concerning a Middle East settlement presented by Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> to Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> on September 4,
                                1968.<note n="3" xml:id="d266fn3">See <ref target="#d245">Document
                                    245</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The United States takes the view that peace in the Middle East is not
                            the concern only of the countries of the region and that the persistence
                            of tension in that area, and the absence of peace, threatens the general
                            peace.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>While sharing Soviet concern over the situation in the Middle East,
                            the United States cannot accept the description contained in the Soviet
                            document of the causes of that situation and the positions and actions
                            taken by the parties since the cessation of hostilities. Moreover, it
                            must reject as totally unfounded the allegation that the United States
                            Government has supported a negative and deliberately obstructionist
                            policy on the part of the Government of Israel. This statement is
                            unwarranted and untrue. On the contrary, it is the view of the United
                            States Government that the level of the flow of arms from the Soviet <pb
                                facs="0553" n="525" xml:id="pg_525"/> Union into the area has been a
                            major factor in obstructing meaningful peace negotiations between the
                            parties.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The views of the United States have been set forth by the President
                            and other senior U.S. Government representatives on a number of
                            occasions and are well known to the Government of the Soviet Union. The
                            five principles enunciated by the President in his address of June 19,
                            1967, as reiterated by him on September 10, 1968, remain the basis for
                            United States policy concerning a Middle East settlement.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Since the adoption of the Security Council resolution, the United
                            States has given its full support to the efforts of Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_JG1">Gunnar V. Jarring</persName> to fulfill his mandate
                            “to promote agreement and assist efforts to achieve a peaceful and
                            accepted settlement in accordance with the provisions and principles” in
                            the Council resolution. The United States Government believes that its
                            primary effort, along with that of the Soviet Union and other
                            governments, should be directed at supporting Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName> and in doing nothing that would
                            in any way detract from or interfere in his activities. This attitude is
                            reflected in the Security Council’s resolution of September 18,
                                1968,<note n="4" xml:id="d266fn4">On September 18 the Security
                                Council adopted a resolution reaffirming the principles of
                                Resolution 242, urging the fullest cooperation with the <persName
                                    corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName> Mission, and stipulating
                                that the cease-fire ordered by the Security Council in several
                                resolutions be respected. (<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> doc.
                                    S/<gloss target="#t_Res1">RES</gloss>/258 (1968))</note> to
                            which both the United States and the Soviet Union gave their
                            support.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>The United States, on its part, will make a renewed effort to
                            encourage the parties to engage in the fullest and freest exchange of
                            substantive proposals under his auspices and to accept such procedures
                            as he may suggest to promote agreement as required by the resolution. It
                            is hoped the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> will do likewise.
                            Just as we have felt that insistence upon direct negotiations as a
                            pre-condition to serious substantive exchanges is unrealistic, so we
                            believe the view that no joint talks can take place under <persName
                                corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName>’s auspices is equally
                            unrealistic. We hope the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> will give
                            this critical point the serious attention it deserves; for it is most
                            difficult for us to conceive that stable peace can be achieved in this
                            area without negotiations involving the parties at some stage, given the
                            complexity of the issues.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>The Soviet document requests the views of the United States Government
                            concerning steps which in its view must be taken for a prompt settlement
                            of the Middle East problem. In response to that request, the United
                            States Government would like to seek certain clarifications and present
                            the following observations, which inter alia could be explored in future
                            consultations: <list>
                                <label>(a)</label>
                                <item>The Soviet document refers in paragraph (a) to the readiness
                                    of the parties to implement the Security Council resolution of
                                    November <pb facs="0554" n="526" xml:id="pg_526"/> 22, 1967. The
                                    United States wishes to point out that an essential part of the
                                    obligation to implement the resolution is the obligation to
                                    cooperate fully with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JG1"
                                        >Jarring</persName> in the carrying out of his mandate as
                                    set forth in paragraph three of the resolution to promote
                                    agreement among the states concerned. It does not regard the
                                    Security Council resolution as self-implementing. It believes,
                                    on the contrary, that under the resolution the parties must take
                                    responsibility for an agreed settlement and that a settlement
                                    cannot be imposed upon the parties by others. The United States
                                    would welcome further clarification of the Soviet views on this
                                    point.</item>
                                <label>(b)</label>
                                <item>The United States notes with interest that the Soviet document
                                    refers in paragraph (a) to the possibility of consultations
                                    “through <persName corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName> or in
                                    some other form.” The United States believes that consultations
                                    involving the parties will be essential to the development of
                                    agreement on a peaceful settlement envisaged by the November 22,
                                    1967 Security Council resolution. Does the Soviet Union share
                                    this view?</item>
                                <label>(c)</label>
                                <item>The United States agrees that it may be desirable for United
                                    Nations forces to be employed to assist in the carrying out of
                                    the terms of a settlement agreed by the parties and notes in
                                    this connection that the Soviet document makes a number of
                                    suggestions in this regard. While not being able to accept some
                                    of the concepts reflected in these suggestions, the United
                                    States would be prepared to discuss with the Soviet Government
                                    the idea of use of United Nations forces in connection with an
                                    agreed settlement.</item>
                                <label>(d)</label>
                                <item>The United States further notes that paragraph (b) 5 of the
                                    Soviet document provides that the declarations of the Arab
                                    countries and Israel on the cessation of the state of war and
                                    the establishment of peace would become effective “either
                                    through the instrumentality of the Security Council or through
                                    the signing of a multilateral document.” The United States
                                    believes that the peace must be based upon arrangements which
                                    directly bind the parties. Is this what is intended by the
                                    reference to a “multilateral document”? The United States
                                    believes that a document signed jointly by the parties is the
                                    most desirable, if not the only, means of obligating the parties
                                    to carry out the agreement worked out in accordance with the
                                    resolution of November 22, 1967. It believes, also, that
                                    Security Council endorsement of the terms of a settlement agreed
                                    by the parties could serve a useful purpose. The United States
                                    is not clear what a Four Power guarantee would add to such a
                                    Security Council endorsement of the agreement of the parties,
                                    but it is willing to examine the possibility at the appropriate
                                    time.</item>
                                <label>(e)</label>
                                <item>Concerning the above point on the cessation of the state of
                                    war, does the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> share the
                                    view of the United States that a termination of the state of
                                    belligerency would mean that there would be complete <pb
                                        facs="0555" n="527" xml:id="pg_527"/> freedom of passage
                                    through international waterways, including the Suez Canal, for
                                    all vessels?</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>The Soviet document comments at some length on the desirability of a
                            plan or timetable for implementation of the Security Council resolution.
                            The United States has no objection to the concept of a plan under which
                            the steps required for carrying out the peace settlement agreed to by
                            the parties, and the timing of those steps, would be spelled out. It may
                            be that the parties would find such a detailed plan necessary since, as
                            the Soviet document also notes, the actions to be taken by the parties
                            in carrying out their agreed settlement would inevitably be interrelated
                            and in some degree interdependent. It is in light of this
                            interrelationship that the United States firmly adheres to the view that
                            all elements of a settlement must be dealt with in arriving at the terms
                            of a settlement. It is the understanding of the United States, moreover,
                            that the parties, including the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, all
                            recognize that the Security Council resolution requires a “package”
                            which would settle all the problems left open for negotiations by the
                            resolution, whatever the chronology for implementation on which they
                            might agree. In our view this position represents a proper
                            interpretation of the resolution.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>There is one specific aspect of the program outlined in the Soviet
                            document which in particular merits comment: the idea of Israeli
                            withdrawal to the pre-June 5 line. The essence of the United States
                            policy since June 5, 1967, has been and remains that the state of
                            armistice among the parties must be replaced, as the resolution of
                            November 22, 1967, states, by a condition of peace. The armistice
                            agreements of 1949 called for a transition to peace and specifically
                            contemplated the possibility of agreed changes in the armistice lines of
                            1949 as part of that transition. The Security Council resolution calls
                            for withdrawal of Israeli armed forces to secure and recognized
                            boundaries, free from threats or acts of force, but does not specify
                            that those boundaries should be precisely the lines held prior to June
                            5, 1967, or on any other date. In view of the complexity of this
                            question, the United States believes that this is a matter which
                            requires the priority attention of both the parties and Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName>.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>The United States believes it important that the Soviet and United
                            States Government continue to consult on all possibilities for a
                            settlement of the Middle East situation. It expects to be in contact
                            with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JG1">Jarring</persName> in the
                            days immediately ahead and, of course, there will be further opportunity
                            for the two governments to exchange views during Minister Gromyko’s
                            forthcoming visit to New York during the General Assembly
                            session.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
