<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>352. Action Memorandum From Harold Saunders of the National Security Council
                    Staff to President of the National Security Council Staff to President
                    Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">352</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recgNB1TfjBBo9Fg4" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041888"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Electric power plant</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recQI8RFLxCFovNr2" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092985"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nuclear fuel</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recpqcSvEFyuxPc7E" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-12-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="352"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d352">
                <head>352. Action Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SHH1" type="from">Harold
                        Saunders</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to President
                        <persName type="to">Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d352fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Subject File, Desalting Projects, Vol. II. Confidential;
                        Exdis. <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Saunders</persName> sent this memorandum
                        to the President under a December 18 covering memorandum in which he
                        indicated that <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName> had asked
                        him to forward it to the President in his absence. (Ibid.) The President
                        wrote the following instruction to <persName corresp="#p_JJR1">Jim
                            Jones</persName> on the covering memorandum: “Hold until I’m back &amp;
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt</persName> returns.” On December 23
                            <persName corresp="#p_JJR1">Jones</persName> sent the memorandum to
                            <persName>Rostow</persName> with the suggestion that
                            <persName>Rostow</persName> take it up with the President after luncheon
                        on December 24. (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-12-18">December 18, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>George <persName corresp="#p_WG1">Woods</persName>’ Proposal on Israeli
                        Desalting</item>
                </list>
                <p>In short, George proposes (Tab A)<note n="2" xml:id="d352fn2">
                        <ref target="#d319">Document 319</ref>.</note> that we stop thinking for the
                    moment in terms of a large 100–150 million-gallon-per-day (MGD) desalter and
                    concentrate on a 40 MGD plant. He fully shares your goal of becoming able over
                    the next 10–15 years to desalt seawater on a large scale, and he believes we
                    should push ahead with this plant “as a matter of priority.” He has two main
                    reasons for recommending a smaller plant than we initially considered: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>He believes that the next logical step in developing the technology of
                            large-scale desalting would be to build a 40 MGD plant. This would be
                            enough larger (more than 5 times) than present plants to provide an
                            important test of new technology at reasonable cost (about $58 million).
                            We would gain almost as much in technological knowledge as we would from
                            the $100 million plus that would be needed at a minimum from us to help
                            build the $250 million larger plant.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Taking this smaller bite, he feels, is the only way to cut through the
                            highly emotional argument we’ve had for several years between the
                            crusaders and those who don’t believe the time is ripe yet for a
                            $100–250 million leap of faith. Everyone—except possibly <gloss
                                target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>—believes this has been George’s main
                            contribution.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0722" n="694" xml:id="pg_694"/>
                <p>To simplify our financial problem, George believes we should concentrate on
                    desalting and get away from the idea of financing an Israeli electric power
                    plant as part of a dual purpose water and power plant. The Israelis will be
                    building new power plants right along to meet increasing demand for electricity.
                    He doesn’t see why they shouldn’t provide the steam from one of these power
                    plants as part of their contribution while we concentrate on the desalter to
                    turn that steam into water.</p>
                <p>Therefore, George proposes we take the necessary steps to get Congressional
                    authorization for Interior to spend up to $40 million on this plant. In addition
                    to the steam from the power plant, Israel would provide $18 million using a loan
                    from the World Bank or some other such loan agency. While the cost of water
                    would still be very high, George believes the total Israeli contribution would
                    not exceed the actual value of the water to Israel. Since the power plant would
                    cost around $20 million, this would add up roughly to a 50–50 split between
                    us.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt</persName> asked Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> to pull together the views of State,<gloss
                        target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>, Interior and <gloss target="#t_AEC1"
                        >AEC</gloss> on George’s proposal (Tab B).<note n="3" xml:id="d352fn3">The
                        reactions of the Departments of State and Interior,<gloss target="#t_AID1"
                            >AID</gloss>, and the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> were
                        summarized by Benjamin Read in a November 29 memorandum to <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>, attached at Tab B.</note> With
                    some variations, I think it is fair to say that each of them but <gloss
                        target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> would go along with George’s general proposal
                    that we try to move ahead with a smaller plant and that you put it in your
                    legislative program.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> has no objection to going as far as George
                    proposes but objects (especially <persName corresp="#p_JJR1">Jim
                        Ramey</persName>) strenuously to: <list>
                        <item>—George’s strong words about “abandoning” or “holding in abeyance” the
                            plan for a big dual purpose plant. They believe it is important to
                            preserve the idea that this is just the first step toward a later
                            expansion into a larger plant. Secretary Udall goes along with
                            presenting this to the Congress as Phase I of a larger project, but he
                            would say that Israel must fund later expansion by itself. George says
                            he didn’t mean to close any doors—just to re-focus for a moment.</item>
                        <item>—George’s unwillingness to insist that the plant use nuclear fuel. His
                            investigations persuade him that there’s no economic advantage to
                            nuclear over fossil fuel and that, if we ask the Israelis to provide the
                            steam-producing plant, the choice of fuel ought to be theirs. <gloss
                                target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> believes we have a strong interest in
                            nuclear desalting. <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> further feels we
                            should keep our strings on that Israeli decision to be sure they buy US
                            nuclear equipment with safeguards. <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>
                            believes it could justify a contribution of $10–15 million to the power
                            (not desalting) plant if it were nuclear, and if our own California
                            plant doesn’t go ahead. Secretary Udall believes we should leave the
                            choice of fuel open. (The Israelis, <pb facs="0723" n="695"
                                xml:id="pg_695"/> like the rest of us, would like to leave the
                            choice of fuel open until they can decide what is most
                            economical.)</item>
                        <item>—George’s judgment that it’s “not possible at this time to obtain
                            financing in the amount [$244 million]<note n="4" xml:id="d352fn4"
                                >Brackets in the source text.</note> on the terms which would be
                            necessary.” <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> feels there would be
                            “extensive Congressional support” for a big nuclear desalting plant
                            because of the sympathetic attitude of the Joint Committee on Atomic
                            Energy which would review the proposal along with the two Interior
                            Committees. George’s proposal for an Interior contribution would only go
                            before the two Interior Committees which would be less cordial.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>On this last point, Secretary Udall thinks the Senate Interior Committee would be
                    receptive but is less sure about the House. However, he points out that the
                        <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1970 expenditure would be only $5 million
                    and remaining costs would be spread over five years. Only about $1 million of
                    the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1970 figure would be needed for Israeli
                    planning. The rest would go for testing some promising new technology which
                    should go into the Israeli plant. Interior should proceed with this testing in
                    any case, and that would cost about $4 million. <gloss target="#t_AID1"
                        >AID</gloss> feels Congress might see even $40 million as “just another aid
                    spigot” and thinks Israel should foot even more of the bill than George
                    recommends. State recommends that we pick up about $30 million of the $40
                    million, leaving the rest to Israel.</p>
                <p>In searching for a reasonable compromise, I would stand with George in saying
                    that the fuel is an Israeli decision, but I would be a little less emphatic in
                    “abandoning” the goal of a larger plant. I don’t believe we are ready to commit
                    ourselves yet, but I don’t see why we shouldn’t be quite honest in saying we’re
                    neither opening nor closing that door at this stage.</p>
                <p>We asked both Don Hornig and Charlie Zwick to look at this package: <list>
                        <item>—Don feels that desalting technology has reached a stage where it’s
                            time to test a prototype of a large plant. He believes the 40 MGD size
                            George proposes is reasonable. Given the apparently indefinite delay in
                            building the large plant in California, he thinks it’s sensible to try
                            the experiment in Israel. He accepts George’s recommendation that we
                            concentrate on the desalter and let Israel provide the power plant to
                            produce the necessary steam. He does not believe we should commit
                            ourselves to future expansion of the Israeli project.</item>
                        <item>—Charlie suggests that you let this decision ride. He questions the
                            need to spend tight resources on a large experimental plant where the
                            economic benefits are uncertain, especially when we are straining to
                            keep your budget down. If a large desalting demonstration is to be
                            undertaken, he would prefer that it be done in the US where
                            technological <pb facs="0724" n="696" xml:id="pg_696"/> access to the
                            plant is assured over time. He specifically questions the Israeli site
                            in view of the risk of building and operating the plant in a war zone.
                            He feels that <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> funds should not be
                            used to put <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> in the “foreign aid”
                            business on the scale contemplated by <gloss target="#t_AEC1"
                                >AEC</gloss>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>For these reasons, Charlie feels that if we go ahead with the Israeli project the
                    contribution be limited to $30 million, and like foreign aid, we should require
                    that procurement, construction, and operation contracts be limited to US
                    sources. Charlie agrees with Don that we should not commit ourselves to future
                    expansion of the Israeli project. Charlie also agrees with <persName
                        corresp="#p_WG1">Woods</persName> that we would get as much technology out
                    of the 40 MGD plant as out of the big dual-purpose-plant-and at substantially
                    less cost.</p>
                <p>Yesterday, I had a visit from Yaacov Herzog—<persName corresp="#p_EL1"
                        >Eshkol</persName>’s chief assistant whom you met at the Ranch—and General
                    Ben Artzi—George <persName corresp="#p_WG1">Woods</persName>’ Israeli
                    counterpart. George has shared his thinking with them informally to see whether
                    he was being realistic. Yesterday, Herzog gave me the following message for you
                    in <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Eshkol</persName>’s name: <persName
                        corresp="#p_EL1">Eshkol</persName> deeply appreciates your continued
                    attention to this project, even in the closing days of your Administration. He
                    thinks <persName corresp="#p_WG1">Woods</persName>’ proposal is quite
                    reasonable, and he would be prepared to discuss details of how to proceed.
                    Herzog felt it would be helpful if you were to include this in your legislative
                    program.</p>
                <p>The issues are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Whether you wish to put George’s proposal in your legislative
                                program. The advantage in doing so would be to put yourself on
                                record with a proposal for a feasible next step (a) in desalting and
                                (b) in a program which you launched with Israel in 1964. The
                                disadvantage is that the Congress may well disregard this proposal,
                                leaving it in worse shape than if it had been left to a riper time.
                                I personally feel that, after four years of pushing this, we should
                                have a concrete proposal from President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                                    >Johnson</persName> on the record.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Put it in the program<note n="5" xml:id="d352fn5"
                                    >The first option under each of the three issues is checked. A
                                    marginal note in Rostow’s hand reads: “approved by the President
                                    24 Dec. 1968” On December 30 <persName>Rostow</persName> sent a
                                    memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>
                                    summarizing the President’s decisions and asking <persName
                                        corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> to provide a recommendation
                                    on the organization best suited to coordinate and manage the
                                    project. (Johnson Library, National Security File, Subject File,
                                    Desalting Projects, Vol. II)</note>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">No</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Call me</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Whether, if you put it in your program, you would seek authorization
                                for a US contribution of the full $40 million George suggests or
                                press the Israelis to pay even part of the desalting research <pb
                                    facs="0725" n="697" xml:id="pg_697"/> costs and go for only $30
                                million. In either case, only about $5 million would need to be
                                appropriated in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1970. The argument
                                for the full $40 million is that Israel would build the entire power
                                plant (roughly $20 million plus more than $1.5 million yearly for
                                fuel) and assume the $18 million loan in addition as its fair
                                contribution. This would be about a 50–50 split between us. The
                                argument for $30 million is that Israel too will profit in future
                                plants from the results of the research and should contribute to the
                                desalter too.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">$40 million</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">$30 million</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Call me</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>Whether, if you go ahead, you make clear that nuclear fuel must be
                                used. The only people pushing for this are the <gloss
                                    target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>. George and the rest of us think it
                                makes sense just to leave the door open. Ben Artzi yesterday said
                                he’d like the door left open until they can make studies to
                                determine the most economical approach.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Leave door open on fuel</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Nuclear</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Call me</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>My own feeling is that, uncertain as our judgments are, we should go ahead with a
                    plant like this soon. However, I recognize that there are still political
                    questions to be considered and that we would probably not wish to begin
                    construction if another war seemed likely. But these are questions for the next
                    Administration. The main issue is whether you wish to propose this first step
                    now or leave the issue entirely to the next team.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName>Hal</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
