<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>9. Telegram From the Embassy in Jordan to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-12-06T08:50:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-12-06T08:50:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-12-06T08:50:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-12-06T08:50:00-05:00" n="9"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                <head>9. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Jordan</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d9fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                        DEF 12-5 JORDAN. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Repeated
                        to <gloss target="#t_CINCSTRIKE1">CINCSTRIKE</gloss>, Moscow, London, and
                        Tel Aviv.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Amman</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-12-06T13:50:00+00:00">December 6, 1967,
                        1350Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2530. Subject: Arms for Jordan. Ref: State 79171.<note n="2" xml:id="d9fn2"
                        >Telegram 79171 to Amman, December 5, informed the Embassy that the question
                        of resuming the supply of arms to Jordan was under active high-level
                        discussion. The question would have to be explored with Congressional
                        leaders, however, so a decision was not imminent. The Department instructed
                        the Embassy to try to persuade the Jordanian Government to be patient.
                        (Ibid.)</note> Amman 2519<note n="3" xml:id="d9fn3">Not found.</note> and
                        2528.<note n="4" xml:id="d9fn4">In telegram 2528 from Amman, December 6, the
                        Embassy reported that King <persName>Hussein</persName> was being pressed by
                        the Soviet Union to continue a military dialogue begun during the King’s
                        recent visit to Moscow. The Soviet Union planned to send a military
                        delegation to Amman to explore Jordan’s military requirements, and the
                        Soviet Ambassador in Amman had told the King that his government was
                        prepared to supply Jordan’s arms need at bargain prices and under favorable
                        terms. (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, DEF 12-5 JORDAN)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>By prior agreement I stayed on with King <persName>Hussein</persName>
                        following Senator Ribicoff’s audience for a brief discussion of arms
                        situation. <pb facs="0047" n="19" xml:id="pg_19"/> Arms question had already
                        come up in general way during meeting with Senator.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I said I was pleased His Majesty had had opportunity mention Jordan arms
                        requirements to the Senator, who had seemed quite sympathetic to Jordan’s
                        needs as described by the King. I had been concerned, however, to learn
                        through <gloss target="#t_EmbOff1">EmbOff</gloss> on 4th (Amman 2528) that
                        Soviet economic survey mission scheduled to come to Jordan later this month
                        would, at Soviet request, include three Soviet military officials. I could
                        appreciate sense of frustration felt by His Majesty. I felt obliged
                        nevertheless to say I personally believed presence in Jordan of Soviet
                        military, if it became known, would tend prejudice our efforts gain approval
                        for resumption of U.S. arms shipments to Jordan as well as for our general
                        efforts in support of Jordan. I had noted Jordan press article that morning
                        stating that Soviet survey mission would not arrive until after first of
                        year. I hoped this was true because it would allow time for <gloss
                            target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> to arrive at what I believed would
                        ultimately be favorable decision on resuming some arms shipments to
                        Jordan.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>His Majesty responded that he was not sure when Soviet mission would
                        arrive. It might be before end of year. Soviet Ambassador in informing him
                        only a few days ago of mission’s coming had stated mission would include
                        three senior military officials but that latter would not be identified as
                        such in order to avoid embarrassing Jordanian Govt. King said he had been
                        taking line with Soviets that he still intended obtain his arms from usual
                        sources. Nevertheless, he had not felt he could tell Soviet <gloss
                            target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> to delete three military from survey
                        mission. For one thing, Soviets had been taking very moderate line recently.
                        They were supporting U.N. resolution in talks with Jordan and had stressed
                        Israel’s right to existence. Soviet <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss> had
                        also spoken of Soviet efforts to dampen Syrian extremism. He considered
                        Soviets, despite some outward appearances, had been playing a generally
                        constructive role with regard to Arab-Israeli problem. This factor also led
                        him to feel he could not tell Soviets not to send mission at this time or
                        not to bring military personnel if they did. On other hand, it was his
                        intention to see that Soviet military only looked around in general way and
                        that they did not get into any specific discussion of Jordan’s requirements.
                        This was understood, he emphasized.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I commented that His Majesty was, of course, best judge of <gloss
                            target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> interests in this respect. Some of us,
                        however, still have suspicions about Soviet motives in the Near East. Only
                        in last few days Soviets had been making noises of willingness to discuss
                        some form of arms limitation in area; yet with Jordan they were pursuing
                        what could only be considered a significantly new arms supply role in Near
                        East. Although Soviets more cautious and seem to recognize danger of
                        escalation of Arab-Israeli incidents, some of us still believe they will
                        pursue their <pb facs="0048" n="20" xml:id="pg_20"/> spoiling operations in
                        Near East wherever possible. I personally was suspicious enough of their
                        motives to wonder if they could be counted on to keep presence in Jordan of
                        three military personnel quiet.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Conversation concluded with my telling His Majesty I had new word from
                        Washington indicating high level <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>
                        officials fully appreciate urgency <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss>
                        requirements and actively reviewing matter. I was therefore hopeful of a
                        favorable decision on Jordan arms shortly after Congressional action is
                        completed on foreign aid appropriation bill. I thought this could be before
                        Christmas. King seemed to appreciate these assurances. He said earlier in
                        morning he had spoken to assembled senior <gloss target="#t_JAA1"
                            >JAA</gloss> officers to tell them he expects soon to be able to provide
                        them with specifics regarding military equipment supplies.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Symmes</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
