<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-11-09T19:26:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-11-09T19:26:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">315.3/11–653: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d143fn1">Repeated to London as telegram
                                    2523.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-11-09T19:26:00-05:00">November 9, 1953—7:26 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1779. <gloss target="#t_urtel1">Urtel</gloss> 1791, <gloss target="#t_Depcirtel1">Depcirtel</gloss> 186 Nov 7, fol is
                                summary of memorandum of law for use of French in their review of
                                technical position.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi></p>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> has legal right and responsibility
                                review and refuse give effect to decisions of Administrative
                                Tribunal.</p>
                            <pb facs="0395" n="367" xml:id="pg_367"/>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Background of international administrative tribunals and
                                    relevant international law support above conclusion. <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>International administrative tribunals are relatively
                                            new institutions. They are <hi rend="italic">sui
                                                generis</hi>. Their relationship to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> is not controlled by
                                            analogy to institutions of similar name or functions in
                                            municipal law.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>International administrative tribunals operate on
                                            basis of underlying agreement between states which makes
                                            relevant to them principles of international law. One
                                            such well settled principle, developed in connection
                                            with arbitral tribunals, is that an award is null or
                                            voidable if it involves excess of tribunal’s power or
                                            terms of reference.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Under Charter of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> power and
                                    responsibility for personnel and functioning of Secretariat are
                                    vested in <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. Source of Assembly’s power in
                                    establishing Tribunal is found Art 22 of Charter, which permits
                                        <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> to establish subsidiary
                                    organs to assist in discharge of its responsibilities. Neither
                                    legislative history nor intent evidenced by other Charter
                                    provisions gives basis for conclusion that <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> cld or shld be bound by decisions
                                    of such a subsidiary body.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Precedent of League of Nations Administrative Tribunal,
                                    Statute of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Administrative
                                    Tribunal, and its legislative history combine to show that
                                    neither intent nor effect of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>’s
                                    action was to place judgments of Tribunal beyond its power of
                                    review. <list>
                                        <label>(a)</label>
                                        <item>When initially used in Statute of League of Nations
                                            Tribunal phrase “final and without appeal” meant that
                                            processes established by Statute ended and that no right
                                            of appeal was provided.</item>
                                        <label>(b)</label>
                                        <item>That power to review and refuse to give effect to
                                            decisions of Tribunal was reserved to Assembly was
                                            established beyond any possible doubt by 1946 League
                                            precedent where this power was exercised respecting 13
                                            judgments.</item>
                                        <label>(c)</label>
                                        <item>Legislative history of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Tribunal’s statute shows that from
                                            outset League Statute was its model. Nothing occurred to
                                            cast even a shadow on clearly established meaning of
                                            “final and without appeal” as carried into new
                                            Statute.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                            <p>Tribunal has gone substantially beyond its proper powers and has made
                                number of important errors in applying regs as well as errors of law
                                and fact in fixing amounts of awards.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Administrative Tribunal misinterpreted functions assigned to
                                    it by <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> in disciplinary cases.
                                    It treated cases as though it possessed power to hear <hi rend="italic">de novo,</hi> and substituted its judgment for
                                        <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>’s in application of
                                    standards to staff conduct, all in disregard of need to have
                                    conclusion of arbitrariness or bad faith based on substantial
                                    evidence compelling such conclusion.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Tribunal committed serious errors of law in its application of
                                    Staff regs. <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Actions of staff members involved cld properly be
                                            viewed as “serious misconduct”.</item>
                                        <pb facs="0396" n="368" xml:id="pg_368"/>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>These actions were clearly unsatisfactory conduct and
                                            Tribunal shld have sustained them on this ground.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>As to temporary indefinite employee (Crawford case),
                                            Tribunal acted contrary to intent of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> as recently clarified for
                                            its benefit in reg 9.1(c).</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>In setting amounts of awards Tribunal failed to base its
                                    findings on reasons capable of justifying varying amounts upon
                                    which it fixed, and it accepted as controlling unverified and
                                    erroneous representations of fact.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi></persName>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>