<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic Missions</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-12-11T13:28:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-12-11T13:28:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-11T13:28:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-12-11T13:28:00-05:00" n="170"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">315.3/12–1154: Circular telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to Certain
                            <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Missions</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">limited official use</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-12-11T13:28:00-05:00"
                            >December 11, 1954—1:28 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>301. 1. U.S. most anxious ensure passage <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                    resolution containing provision accept in principle establishment procedure for
                    judicial review judgements made by <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    Administrative Tribunal. If principle accepted now <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                        >GA</gloss> expected during Tenth Session take action safeguard its powers
                    and those <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> and prevent future ill advised
                    opinions such as Tribunal gave when awarding $180,000 damages eleven <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> employees U.S. nationality dismissed by <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> for invoking Fifth Amendment and refusing
                    answer questions re subversive activities.</p>
                <p>2. <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss> in advisory opinion last July held that
                    under Tribunal’s Statute <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> has no right refuse
                    payment awards. Payment inevitable but U.S. able negotiate least objectionable
                    method financing award from <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> resources. Owing
                    our traditional respect judicial opinions, <pb facs="0438" n="410"
                        xml:id="pg_410"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> has stated U.S. will abide by Court’s
                    finding despite our sharp disagreement.</p>
                <p>3. U.S. aims on above issues were contained single resolution co-sponsored U.S.,
                    Argentina, Canada, Chile, Cuba, Turkey and considered Dec. 9 in Fifth Committee.
                    Belgium, with Brazil, Egypt, India, Norway and Pakistan proposed an amendment
                    eliminating the acceptance in principle of judicial review feature stated in
                    paragraph one above and substituting language which <hi rend="italic">inter
                        alia</hi> requests Member States to communicate to the <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> before 1 July 1955 their views on possible
                    establishment appeal procedure against judgments of Tribunal. Following
                    delegations voted in favor Belgian amendment: Belgium, Brazil, Burma, Costa
                    Rica, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, Ecuador, Egypt, El Salvador, France, Iceland,
                    India, Indonesia, Luxembourg, Mexico, Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway,
                    Pakistan, Peru, Poland, Saudi Arabia, Sweden, Syria, Ukraine, <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, Yemen, Yugoslavia, U.S., South Africa,
                    Turkey, Thailand, Philippines, Paraguay, Panama, Nicaragua, Liberia, Lebanon,
                    Iraq, Iran, Honduras, Guatemala, Greece, Dominican Republic, Cuba, China, Chile,
                    Canada, Byelorussia, Bolivia, Australia, Argentina. Abstentions <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, Israel, Venezuela and Colombia, latter two
                    indicating privately they favored Belgian amendment but did not wish vote
                    against us. Haiti and Uruguay were absent and did not vote although both had
                    pledged their support. Total vote 28 for amendment, 24 against and 4
                    abstentions. Resolution as whole approved vote 28 for, three against (U.S.,
                    China, Turkey) and 27 abstentions: Argentina, Bolivia, Byelorussia, Canada,
                    Chile, Colombia, Cuba, Czechoslovakia, Dominican Republic, Greece, Guatemala,
                    Honduras, Iran, Israel, Lebanon, Liberia, Nicaragua, Panama, Paraguay,
                    Philippines, Poland, Thailand, South Africa, Ukraine, <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss>, Yemen.</p>
                <p>4. Subject to be considered at <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Plenary Session
                    probably Dec. 15 when US plans re-introduce acceptance in principle judicial
                    review as substitute for Belgian amendment. U.S. proposal which <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> will co-sponsor with previous co-sponsors
                    expected have more appeal than defeated version, since omits provision
                    suspending payments future awards until review procedure operative. Doubt U.S.
                    proposed amendment will carry however without special appeal at seat certain
                    Governments not fully determined support Belgian view.</p>
                <p>5. As situation stands, failure obtain approval acceptance in principle item
                    means awards will be paid leaving U.S. with no assurance Tribunal Statute will
                    be amended. Department seriously concerned consequences such failure. One basic
                    consideration is passage last fall House–Senate Resolution 262 expressing sense
                    of Congress that all possible steps be taken by U.S. delegation to prevent
                    payment awards. <gloss target="#t_Amb1">Amb</gloss>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName>, Sens.
                        <persName>Fulbright</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SMITHWB1"
                        >Smith</persName> convinced outcome this question has important bearing U.S.
                    support <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</p>
                <pb facs="0439" n="411" xml:id="pg_411"/>
                <p>6. Unless you perceive significant objections you requested approach <gloss
                        target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> seek support proposed U.S. resolution
                    through urgent instructions their <gloss target="#t_GADel1">GA Del</gloss>. Vote
                    by Dec. 15 likely. If vote for resolution clearly not possible seek abstention
                    since two thirds vote required to carry.</p>
                <p>7. In justification U.S. position and record on whole subject you may wish
                    mention following concessions: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Acceptance Court’s opinion</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Agreement to pay past awards and method of financing</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Withdrawal position that <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> act now on
                            amendment Tribunal Statute</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Withdrawal position that review should be by <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                                >GA</gloss>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Dropping suspension of payments feature noted para 4 above</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Willingness approach with open mind question how judicial review
                            procedure would be developed. (Our proposed resolution provides for 15
                            member committee to develop procedure report Tenth <gloss
                                target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>You may wish also mention many <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss>s have spoken
                    favorably moderate and reasonable attitude US has maintained on subject.</p>
                <p>8. Report urgently your approach.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
