<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                    United Nations Affairs ( (Sandifer))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d216</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">216</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="216"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">315/4–3053</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy Assistant Secretary
                        of State for United Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SANDIFERDV1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sandifer</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-30">April 30,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject:</item>
                    <item>Election of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1"
                            >Hammarskjold</persName> as Secretary General.</item>
                </list>
                <p>While Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LIETH1">Lie</persName> was waiting in my office
                    today to go with Mr. <persName>Simmons</persName>, Chief of Protocol, to the
                    White House, he referred to the election of Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1">Hammarskjold</persName> as Secretary General. He
                    asked how we had discovered Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1"
                        >Hammarskjold</persName>. I expressed surprise and said that the first time
                    we had had any inkling of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1"
                        >Hammarskjold</persName> as a possible candidate was the time his name was
                    suggested by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HOPPENOTH1">Hoppenot</persName> in the
                    course of the Security Council conversations. I said that so far as I knew, the
                    suggestion came as a complete surprise to everyone here and we started
                    scrambling around to find out who Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1"
                        >Hammarskjold</persName> was and what his qualifications were. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LIETH1">Lie</persName> said that he had the impression that
                    Ambassador <persName>Boheman</persName> or Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_BONNETH1">Bonnet</persName> had originated the idea and he
                    repeated the story we have heard elsewhere that the suggestion to them had
                    originated with Mrs. <persName>Betty Jacob</persName>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d216fn1">Presumably Mrs. <persName>Philip E.
                            Jacob</persName>, Deputy to the Director of the United Nations
                        International Children’s Emergency Fund.</note> who claimed that Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1">Hammarskjold</persName> had the
                    support of the Administration. I told him this sounded like one of the usual
                    “figments” of Mrs. <persName>Jacob</persName>’s imagination and that while I
                    could not profess to know anything about Mrs. <persName>Jacob</persName>’s
                    activities in this particular case I felt confident myself that there was no
                    foundation for any impression she may have tried to give that she had access to
                    special or secret consideration of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1"
                        >Hammarskjold</persName> among responsible officials in Washington. I could
                    only repeat that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1"
                        >Hammarskjold</persName>’s nomination came as a complete surprise to us and
                    all of our information and ideas concerning him were developed after his name
                    was brought forward in the Security Council.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LIETH1">Lie</persName> spoke in high terms of Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1">Hammarskjold</persName>’s
                    qualifications and work but remarked that he might let the political functions
                    of the Secretary General wither. He said that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HAMMARSKJOLDD1">Hammarskjold</persName> was a Conservative in
                    Swedish politics and if he were in the United States he would belong to the
                    conservative wing of the Republican Party.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
