<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Acting Assistant Secretary of State for United Nations
                    Affairs ( (Sandifer) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-07-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="233"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d233">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">320/7–953</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                        United Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SANDIFERDV1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sandifer</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d233fn1">
                        <p>Drafted by the Officer in Charge of General Assembly Affairs
                                (<persName>Taylor</persName>) and the Deputy Assistant Secretary of
                            State for <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Affairs (<persName
                                corresp="#p_SANDIFERDV1">Sandifer</persName>) (who was in an
                            “Acting” capacity at this time); and cleared by the geographic bureaus
                                (<gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>—<persName>Woodward</persName>,
                                <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>—<persName>Bonbright</persName>,
                                <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>—<persName>Jernegan</persName>,
                            and <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_JOHNSONUA1"
                                >Johnson</persName>). This memorandum was approved by Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName> on July 22.</p>
                        <p>The recommendations herein presumably resulted from a meeting held on
                            July 16 by the Assistant Secretaries of the bureaus or their
                            representatives with the Deputy Under Secretary of State, <persName
                                corresp="#p_MATTHEWSHF1">H. Freeman Matthews</persName>. No record
                            has been found of this meeting, which was called by <persName
                                corresp="#p_SANDIFERDV1">Sandifer</persName> in a circular
                            memorandum of July 15 to which was attached a memorandum entitled
                            “Eighth Regular Session of the General Assembly Major Slates Problems”,
                            neither printed (<gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> files, lot 59 D
                            237, “Slates”).</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-07-18">July 18,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject:</item>
                    <item>Eighth General Assembly: Election of President and Three Non-Permanent
                        Members of the Security Council</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName> has suggested to you
                    that we support Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_PANDITMVL1">Pandit</persName> for the
                    General Assembly presidency (<hi rend="italic">Tab A</hi>, Correspondence). This
                    question and the related Security Council elections were considered at <pb
                        facs="0505" n="477" xml:id="pg_477"/> a meeting of the Assistant Secretaries
                    of the Geographic Bureaus with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MATTHEWSHF1"
                        >Matthews</persName>, and the recommendations given below were approved.</p>
                <p>The Indian Embassy has indicated to the Department that Prime Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_NEHRURK1">Nehru</persName> is considering putting forward Mrs.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PANDITMVL1">Pandit</persName> for the General Assembly
                    Presidency and as asked for our reaction (Tab B). Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_MALIKC1">Malik</persName> (Lebanon) has informally sounded us
                    out here and in New York on his possible candidacy. The Thai Government, in a
                    note of June 30, 1953,<note n="2" xml:id="d233fn2">Not printed.</note> formally
                    requested United States support for <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince
                        Wan</persName>. We have been on notice of <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1"
                        >Prince Wan</persName>’s prospective candidacy over a period of two
                    years.</p>
                <p>As to the Presidency of the General Assembly, the problem is principally one of
                    weighing the superior competence of <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince
                        Wan</persName> as compared with Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_PANDITMVL1"
                        >Pandit</persName>. There is general agreement here that on her record Mrs.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PANDITMVL1">Pandit</persName> would be unstable,
                    unreliable and inadequate as President. The resentment in this country over the
                    Indian position on Korea and the Chinese Communists would probably make our
                    support of her candidacy, or of India for the Security Council, quite unpopular.
                        <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName>, on the other hand,
                    has demonstrated sobriety and political wisdom and can be counted on in crucial
                    East-West issues. As pointed out by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1"
                        >Lodge</persName>, there would be some political advantage in supporting
                    Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_PANDITMVL1">Pandit</persName>. It might make it
                    easier to oppose India for the Security Council. However, with Commonwealth
                    opposition this candidacy may not prosper. The consensus here is strongly that
                    the possible political advantage does not balance the clear liabilities involved
                    in Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_PANDITMVL1">Pandit</persName> as President.</p>
                <p>Elections will be held for three Security Council seats being vacated by
                    Pakistan, Chile and Greece. For the first—regarded as the Commonwealth seat—all
                    Commonwealth Members, except India, favor New Zealand. However, India has just
                    indicated its desire to run for this seat, urging the need for more Asian
                    representation in the Council. The United Kingdom has informed us that it has
                    advised India of its opposition to India for any Security Council seat.
                    Particularly because of India’s position on Chinese representation, we oppose
                    its candidacy.</p>
                <p>Brazil and Peru are candidates for the second seat. Either would be satisfactory
                    to us. The Latin American caucus has not yet reached a decision between
                    them.</p>
                <p>The greatest difficulty arises over the seat vacated by Greece. Under a 1945
                    arrangement, this seat was allocated to the Soviet bloc for the first election.
                    In 1949 Yugoslavia was elected to it with our strong support; in 1951 strong
                    American efforts succeeded after 19 ballots in electing Greece. As a gesture to
                    the Soviets a good many countries will probably be inclined to favor a return of
                    the seat to a satellite. There <pb facs="0506" n="478" xml:id="pg_478"/> are as
                    yet no candidates for this seat. The existing political situation, national and
                    international, makes it unwise and undesirable to support for this post a
                    satellite or any state which supports the seating of the Chinese Communists.
                    Although Asia is under-represented in the Council, there are no suitable
                    candidates from that area since the Philippines would be extremely difficult to
                    elect and the risk of a defeat makes it unwise for us to encourage a Thai
                    candidacy. We could not support India, Burma or Indonesia because of their
                    Chinese representation policy. Latin American devotion to the geographic
                    representation principle suggests that Turkey might be the most effective
                    candidate, since it adjoins the Eastern European area.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>That we inform Thailand and other friendly governments, particularly India
                        and Lebanon, that we will support <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince
                            Wan</persName> if there is reasonable prospect of his election.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>That we support New Zealand for the Commonwealth seat if, as we
                        understand, it has the support of all Commonwealth Members except India, and
                        that we so inform other friendly countries.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>That we take steps to develop a Turkish candidacy for the Greek seat,
                        approaching the Turks first, and if they agree, other key governments. We
                        should encourage the Turks to take the lead in developing their candidacy.
                        While giving firm support to Turkey, we should not stake United States
                        prestige on her election or for the election of our candidates to other
                        General Assembly posts. We should not in any event accept or support a
                        satellite for this seat, or any state which could be expected to support the
                        seating of the Chinese Communists. If the Turkish candidacy does not prosper
                        our preferred alternative candidates would be the Philippines and
                        Ethiopia.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>That we support a Latin American country to replace Chile but defer the
                        decision until we know the views of the Latin American countries.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>That we support the election of India to the Trusteeship Council for which
                        it is also a candidate. (This is an adequate counter-balance for our
                        declining to support Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_PANDITMVL1"
                            >Pandit</persName> and India for the Security Council. India is now a
                        member of the Economic and Social Council.)</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
