<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="326" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d326">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">
                            <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> files, lot 59 D 237, “Slates”</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Under Secretary of State</hi>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_MURPHYRD1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d326fn1">Drafted by Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KEYDMK1">Key</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-30">June 30, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>Subject:</item>
                            <item>Presidency of Ninth General Assembly</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Pursuant to your request, a meeting was held in my office yesterday for
                            the purpose of a further discussion of <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName>’s possible candidacy for the Presidency of
                            the Ninth General Assembly. The meeting was attended by Assistant
                            Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_KEYDMK1">Key</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_ROBERTSONWS1">Robertson</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BARBOURW1">Barbour</persName> vice Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName>, and Mr.
                                <persName>Kennedy</persName> vice Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BYROADEHA1">Byroade</persName>. The following
                            conclusions and recommendations were reached unanimously: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>We recommend that <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince
                                        Wan</persName> should be sounded out as to whether he is a
                                    candidate for the Presidency and that, if he is, we should give
                                    him our full support. The principal reasons are: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item><persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName>
                                            is a staunch friend of ours and a very able
                                            parliamentarian. Thailand’s continued support is of key
                                            significance to us in the development of our Southeast
                                            Asian policy. Since Asian problems will be the center of
                                            attention at the Ninth General Assembly, it would be
                                            very desirable to have a friendly individual from that
                                            area of the world elected President.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item><persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName>
                                            was a candidate for the Presidency last year, but we
                                            supported <persName corresp="#p_PANDITMVL1">Madame
                                                Pandit</persName> instead, and she was elected. This
                                            was a matter of great disappointment to <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName>. We
                                            have heard through the British and French that <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName> is a
                                            candidate again this year.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>We recommend that the decision to support <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName> be reached as
                                    quickly as possible since <persName corresp="#p_KLEFFENSEN1">Van
                                        Kleffens</persName> has been actively campaigning for some
                                    time past, and the opening of the Ninth General Assembly is only
                                    a little over two and a half months away. This amount of time
                                    would be required to conduct an effective campaign for <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName>.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>We believe that if his candidacy is put forward in the near
                                    future, and vigorously pushed, the prospects for his election
                                    are quite favorable. He would probably be able to count on a
                                    fairly solid group of votes from the so-called Asian-African
                                    bloc as well as from most of the Latin American group. In
                                    addition, he would perhaps get votes from Turkey, Greece, and
                                    Yugoslavia, although most of the European countries would vote
                                    for <persName corresp="#p_KLEFFENSEN1">Van Kleffens</persName>.
                                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName>
                                    feels that <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince
                                        Wan</persName> would have a good fighting chance of being
                                    elected if he and we conduct an active campaign.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>For the above reasons we recommend that you give your approval
                                    to sounding out <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince
                                        Wan</persName> as to his candidacy and, if he is a
                                    candidate, <pb facs="0580" n="552" xml:id="pg_552"/> to assuring
                                    him of our support. We suggest that you raise the matter with
                                        <persName corresp="#p_WWPWWKNB1">Prince Wan</persName> when
                                    he meets with you on Thursday, July 1, at 2 p.m. However, if you
                                    would prefer, arrangements could be made for Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName>, Mr.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KEYDMK1">Key</persName>, or me to do
                                    this.</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>