<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>United States Delegation Memorandum of the Restricted Session of the Fourth
                    Tripartite Heads of Government Meeting, Bermuda Mid-Ocean Club, December 7,
                    1953, 11 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d476</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">476</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-12-07T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-12-07T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec2qYX3T6ktEaSsg" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85087216"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Moratorium</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-07T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-07T10:00:00-05:00" n="476"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d476">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 185</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Delegation Memorandum of the Restricted Session
                        of the Fourth Tripartite Heads of Government Meeting, Bermuda Mid-Ocean
                        Club, December 7, 1953, 11 a.m.</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d476fn1">For documentation on the Bermuda Conference of the
                        Heads of Government of the United States, United Kingdom, and France,
                        December 4–8, 1953, see <ref target="frus1952-54v05p1">volume <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">strictly limited distribution</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1953-12-07T11:00:00-04:00">December 7, 1953, 11 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Participants:</item>
                    <item>United States—President <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ROBERTSONWS1"
                            >Robertson</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Lt. Colonel <persName>Walters</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>United Kingdom—Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWSSWA1"
                            >Churchill</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>J. Colville</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>France—M. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>M. <persName>Bougenot</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>M. <persName>Roux</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>M. <persName>Andronikov</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The President opened the meeting by saying that he understood that it was desired
                    to have additional members of delegations present when the questions of security
                    guarantees and Indo-China were discussed, but that the meeting should be
                    restricted for the discussion of Far Eastern and Middle Eastern problems.
                        <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWSSWA1">Sir Winston Churchill</persName> then
                    said he would like to discuss what was to be done if the truce were to break
                    down.</p>
                <p>The President then said that he would ask Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName> to express our position on this. He
                    understood that the French would want additional members of the delegation in
                    for the discussion on Indo-China. They could discuss the Far East in the first
                    place, then the Middle East and finally follow with a discussion on Indo-China.
                        <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWSSWA1">Sir Winston</persName> then stated
                    that he hoped the meeting would be held particularly secret. He said he wished
                    to bring up the question of the Suez Canal in which the French also had a
                    historic interest as well as a financial interest. The President then said that
                    they might begin discussion by having Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1"
                        >Dulles</persName> make a statement on the Far East.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName> said that the Far
                    Eastern situation was a very confusing one for our policies were at variance
                    with each other. This was not surprising. The Soviets were also somewhat
                    confused and, as M. <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> had
                    mentioned, they had had three ambassadors to China in eighteen months. The
                    Secretary felt the Chinese Communist rule was pretty solidly established, though
                    less so in the South and North. There did not appear to exist in an open form
                    resistance forces seriously <pb facs="0739" n="711" xml:id="pg_711"/>
                    threatening the Communist rule over the mainland. In the question of relations
                    between Communist China and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, it was
                    difficult to come to a clear conclusion but he thought we were justified in
                    believing that there was strain. This would seem logical. <persName>Mao
                        Tse-tung</persName> was himself an outstanding Communist leader in his own
                    right. His prestige, while less than that of <persName>Stalin</persName>’s was
                    greater than <persName>Malenkov</persName>’s. It was natural, therefore, that
                    there should be a certain unwillingness on the part of <persName>Mao</persName>
                    to be dictated to by Moscow as had been possible with
                        <persName>Stalin</persName> because of the latter’s enormous prestige
                    resulting from his internal and external victories.
                    <persName>Stalin</persName>’s presige had been such that
                        <persName>Mao</persName> could be second to him. This was not the case with
                        <persName>Malenkov</persName>. The very fact that the Soviet Communist
                    leaders went to such extremes to eulogize <persName>Mao</persName> and push him
                    forward as a major figure in the international scene was partly because of
                    self-interest and partly because of the necessity of treating
                        <persName>Mao</persName> as an equal partner on the world scene. The fact
                    that this relationship exists is important and may eventually give us an
                    opportunity for promoting division between the Soviet Union and Communist China
                    in our own common interest.</p>
                <p>There were major differences between the three powers in their approach to this
                    problem, especially as between the United Kingdom and the United States. It was
                    the view of the United States that the best hope for intensifying the strain and
                    difficulties between Communist China and Russia would be to keep the Chinese
                    under maximum pressure rather than by relieving such pressure. There were two
                    theories for dealing with this problem. One was that by being nice to the
                    Communist Chinese we could wean them away from the Soviets, and the other was
                    that pressure and strain would compel them to make more demands on the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> which the latter would be unable to meet and
                    the strain would consequently increase.</p>
                <p>The United States adhered to the latter view that pressure should be maintained
                    on Communist China both politically and economically and to the extent possible
                    without war, military pressure should likewise be maintained. In the view of the
                    United States this was the course to be followed rather than to seek to divide
                    the Chinese and the Soviets by a sort of competition with Russia as to who would
                    treat China best. This would put China in the best of worlds. The Secretary felt
                    that if contradictory policies were applied to China, none of them could make
                    progress toward success and each would cancel out the other’s efforts. He felt a
                    very serious effort should be made to try to bring policies on China into closer
                    harmony than was the case at present. We recognize the fact that the United
                    Kingdom had given political recognition to the Communist regime in China. The
                    Secretary had understood from what the Prime Minister had said the other day
                    that this did not carry moral approbation. The British had said that one must
                    recognize even one’s enemies. This was true, but the fact that <pb facs="0740"
                        n="712" xml:id="pg_712"/> they were recognized did not mean that you had to
                    give them aid of a political, moral or economic nature. The conduct of Communist
                    China as a proclaimed aggressor in Korea, promoting aggression in Indo-China and
                    generally attempting to arouse all Asia against the Western Powers created a
                    situation which brought up the question as to whether they should be given <hi
                        rend="italic">de facto</hi> recognition. The Secretary did not feel that we
                    should give them aid and comfort as was the case when some seemed to promote the
                    admission of Communist China to the United Nations despite the standard of
                    conduct required of members of the United Nations, i.e., to be peace-loving
                    countries willing to undertake the obligations of the Charter. That seemed to be
                    carrying recognition far beyond the conditions of the recognition of a <hi
                        rend="italic">de facto</hi> government. The Secretary felt that if we could
                    align policies in the United Nations, taking the position that Communist China
                    was an aggressor in Korea, as well as a promoter of aggression in Indo-China,
                    and she had not proved her willingness to be peace loving and faithful to the
                    obligations of the United Nations Charter, this would be helpful in establishing
                    a common policy with some chance of success. As things stood now, some opposed
                    the admission of Communist China to the United Nations while others were
                    supporting it, despite its derelictions. This cleavage could be exploited by our
                    enemies so that the policies of neither of us would be effective.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he was mentioning the point at this time because the
                    moratorium agreement at present in effect on preventing this issue from coming
                    up in prolonged debate would expire at the end of December, and the whole
                    question of future policy on this subject would force itself on our attention.
                    It was probable that the United Nations would recess until January or February.
                    The first thing we could expect after this recess would be the resumption of the
                    move by <persName corresp="#p_VYSHINSKYAY1">Vishinsky</persName> for acceptance
                    of the credentials of the Communist regime in China and we must have agreement
                    on that point.</p>
                <p>[Here follows extended discussion of other aspects of the Far Eastern situation:
                    commercial relations with Communist China, Korea, and Formosa.]</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName> then said that they had
                    listened with the greatest interest to every word in the masterly survey of Far
                    Eastern problems by the Secretary of State. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1"
                        >Eden</persName> said that it was a puzzling question to know how far we can
                    by our actions help to foster a division of opinion between the Chinese
                    Communists and the Russians. It probably to some extent exists and will grow.
                    History was on our side, for these two had never worked harmoniously together
                    for long, but it might be long for in China things take centuries which require
                    but years elsewhere. They were trying to divide the three of us, just as we were
                    trying to divide them, and that in itself was in a measure an excuse for
                    argument for not thinking it wise to break off all contacts, however <pb
                        facs="0741" n="713" xml:id="pg_713"/> unsatisfactory our relationship with
                    the Chinese Communists might be at present. The Foreign Secretary said that he
                    would not go into the question of recognition at that time, all were familiar
                    with the reasons for which it had been done and how it had been done. We should
                    freely admit that we had a problem to face at the United Nations in February and
                    we should immediately start talks. We would, of course, like to consult the
                    Commonwealth Governments so that we might work out a common line to be used in
                    February. It would be very bad if we found ourselves in disarray.</p>
                <p>[Here follow other remarks by <persName corresp="#p_EDENA1">Eden</persName>.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1">Bidault</persName> followed, and concluding
                    remarks were made by President <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>. Neither <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName> nor <persName corresp="#p_BIDAULTG1"
                        >Bidault</persName> referred to the Chinese representation question.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d476fn2">
                        <p>For <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s brief
                            reference in his memoir to the Chinese representation question at the
                            Bermuda Conference, see <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1">Dwight D.
                                Eisenhower</persName>, <hi rend="italic">The White House Years:
                                Mandate for change, 1953–1956</hi> (New York, Doubleday and Co.,
                            1963), pp. 248 and 249. A Policy Planning Staff briefing paper of Dec.
                            2, 1953 (Conference Document BM Special 3c) contains this entry: <quote
                                rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“C. Communist China</p>
                                <p>Until the regime stops promoting aggression in Korea and
                                    Indochina and shows its willingness to conform to principles of
                                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter, the U.S. will not
                                    consider recognizing the Communist regime in China, will oppose
                                    its admission to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss>, and
                                    will maintain a trade embargo.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>In a private meeting with <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWSSWA1"
                                >Churchill</persName> (presumably a luncheon) at the Bermuda Club on
                            Dec. 4, 1953, <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWERGADD1"
                                >Eisenhower</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWSSWA1"
                                >Churchill</persName> had a brief exchange of views about Communist
                            China, in which “the President urged a closer alignment of <gloss
                                target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> policy with the U.S.” (Conference files,
                            lot 60 D 627, CF 185)</p>
                    </note>]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
