<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Charles Runyon, Attorney Adviser, Office of the Assistant Legal
                    Adviser for United Nations Affairs, to the Director of the Office of Security
                    and Consular Affairs ( (Boykin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recwiCYrBEGX9Z5wr" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recGaMyuvucEAg8hm" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85098258"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Parole</term>
                    <term ref="recRIwGRq2ONxRdH9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022007585"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigrant</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="51"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_LUNA1">L/UNA</gloss> files, “Privileges &amp; Immunities;
                    Entry, Transit, Travel—1946.–”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by <persName type="from">Charles Runyon</persName>,
                        Attorney Adviser, Office of the Assistant Legal Adviser for United Nations
                        Affairs, to the Director of the Office of Security and Consular Affairs</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Boykin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-03-06">March 6,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Attached for clearance is the revised text of a letter to Justice,<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d51fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> signed for the Secretary by the Acting
                    Legal Adviser, which sets out the construction of the passport regulations under
                    which consuls have in fact approved visas in cases of <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> officers and employees lacking valid national passports, and
                    which construction, as a matter of law and correct reading of the current
                    regulations, is a correct construction.</p>
                <p>You will recall that at a meeting in your office on Friday, February 29, you and
                    Mr. <persName>L’Heureux</persName>, Chief of the Visa Division, agreed that the
                    Department should transmit such a construction of its regulations for the
                    guidance of the Immigration and Naturalization Service should the Department of
                    Justice and the Service raise no legal objection and should they agree to act in
                    accordance with the construction and to eliminate the practice of “detention and
                    parole”. It was agreed at the meeting in your office that the correctness of the
                    practice and construction involved would be confirmed to our Consular
                    officials.</p>
                <p>The present wording has been discussed with the Chief Counsel of the Immigration
                    and Naturalization Service<note n="2" xml:id="d51fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_WININGSLP1">L. Paul Winings</persName>.</note> and
                    with Mr. <persName>Herzel Plaine</persName> of Justice and will be satisfactory
                    to them. Justice has further <pb facs="0236" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/> reached
                    agreement with us that in the cases referred to there is no bar to admission
                    deriving solely from lack of evidence of future ability to gain admission to a
                    foreign country, and this conclusion of law is specifically recited in the
                    attached letter.</p>
                <p>I realize that the Visa Division holds strong views to the effect that in most,
                    if not all, cases of persons falling in categories (1)–(7) of the exceptions to
                    “immigrant” status set out in 22 <gloss target="#t_USC1">USC</gloss> § 203 there
                    should, as a matter of policy, be a showing of probable ability to gain
                    admission to a foreign country. The present letter would make a specific
                    qualification to such a policy only in relation to the officers and employees
                    referred to in the second part of § 203 (7).</p>
                <p>I trust that on the basis of the express limitations set out in this memorandum
                    and embodied in the present letter itself, you will initial and approve the
                    present letter so that we may formally confirm to Justice and Immigration the
                    understanding reached with them and secure the elimination of the harmful and
                    futile practice of “detention and parole” which in fact does <hi rend="italic"
                        >not</hi> assure admissibility of aliens to other countries but does place
                    it in the power of the Soviet Union and its satellites unjustly to penalize
                    their nationals who work for the United Nations when those nationals lose favor
                    with the Communist political machine.</p>
                <p>The need for an immediate and effective solution of this problem, which was first
                    formally presented to Justice in January of 1951, seems obvious, and is
                    emphasized by the expected return to the United States of Assistant Secretary
                    General <persName corresp="#p_KERNOIS1">Kerno</persName> of the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> on March 9. I understand that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KERNOIS1">Kerno</persName> has not been granted a renewal of his
                    passport by the Communist Government of Czechoslovakia.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
