<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-06-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-06-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="574" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d574">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">330/6–2452</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Far
                            Eastern Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Allison</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant
                            Secretary of State for United Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HICKERSONJD1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d574fn1">Drafted by the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Adviser (<persName corresp="#p_BACONRE1">Bacon</persName>).</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-06-24">June 24, 1952</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <item>Subject:</item>
                        <item>Membership Proposals in the Security Council</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>I recommend that we take the following action (or some procedurally
                        appropriate variant) on the membership question in the Security Council: (1)
                        propose the addition of Japan to the list of candidates now included in the
                        Soviet list and then vote or abstain on the entire proposal; or (2) if the
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> itself adds Japan to its list,
                        vote for or abstain on the amended proposal; and (3) in either case, if
                        procedurally possible without prejudicing the success of the project,
                        propose the addition of other present candidates (Korea, Vietnam and
                        Cambodia) to receive anticipated Soviet vetoes before we accept the residual
                        list.</p>
                    <p>This procedure, if successful, would open the way for the admission of the
                        following states: Austria, Ceylon, Finland, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Jordan,
                        Libya, Nepal and Portugal; and Albania, Bulgaria, Hungary, Rumania and Outer
                        Mongolia.</p>
                    <p>In connection with these steps we would make a statement stressing our
                        continued opposition to the policies and practices of the satellites, our
                        continued support for the candidacies of Korea and Vietnam, our
                        disappointment that the intransigent attitude of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> had for so long prevented the admission
                        of many worthy candidates and our decision, in view of the obstructive
                        Soviet attitude and of the necessity in the interests of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> as a whole of breaking the stalemate, to vote
                        for (or abstain on) the proposal.</p>
                    <p>It is my understanding that the Department now has under consideration the
                        possibility of accepting a package proposal in connection <pb facs="0844" n="816" xml:id="pg_816"/> with the 7th <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. I realize that strong arguments exist against as well as for
                        acceptance of such an arrangement. I realize also that there are reasons
                        against as well as for taking such a step at the present moment. A statement
                        of the various arguments on each side of these questions is attached.<note n="2" xml:id="d574fn2">Not attached to source text.</note></p>
                    <p>On balance, I believe that the arguments in favor of immediate acceptance of
                        a package proposal, if it includes all candidates having any realistic
                        expectancy of admission under present circumstances, outweigh the arguments
                        for either postponing or rejecting the proposal. I accordingly recommend
                        that action be taken along the lines indicated in the first paragraph above
                        on an urgent basis in view of the probable <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                        timetable.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>