<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Japanese Minister of Embassy ( (Kamimura) ) to the Director of the Office
                    of Northeast Asian Affairs ( (Young))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d611</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">611</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-11-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-11-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="611"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d611">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">310.2/11–452</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Japanese Minister of Embassy</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_KAMIMURAS1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kamimura</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Office of Northeast Asian
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_YOUNGKT1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Young</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-11-04">November 4,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. <persName corresp="#p_YOUNGKT1"
                            >Young</persName>
                    </hi>: With reference to my letter of October 23, we have received from the
                    Ministry of Foreign Affairs the attached draft formula for the so-called <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Associate Membership.</p>
                <p>This formula is the result of technical study of the problem in question by the
                    Ministry, and is submitted in the hope that it will constitute a basis for
                    further mutual study of the problem. It is an informal, tentative draft without
                    commitment, and it should not by any means prejudice the future decision of the
                    Government of Japan on this problem.</p>
                <p>Again, even when an informal mutual agreement is reached along the line of this
                    formula as to the status of “Associate Membership”, the Government of Japan
                    wishes to be free to decide its course on this problem one way or the other, by
                    taking into consideration the then prevailing situations abroad and at home, the
                    number of other countries willing to become Associate Members, etc.</p>
                <p>The submittal of this technical paper, therefore, should not be construed as
                    reflecting the decision of the Government of Japan to apply for “Associate
                    Membership”.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KAMIMURAS1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shinichi Kamimura</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The following is a technical study of the status of the so-called <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Associate membership, and should not be
                        construed as reflecting the decision of the Government of Japan to apply for
                        “Associate membership” at this time.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The formal designation of the so-called “Associate Member” shall be
                            Non-Voting Participant.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Any nation which, in response to the invitation extended through a
                            resolution of the General Assembly, sends a representative to the
                            General Assembly, shall become a Non-Voting Participant.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The nations which will be thus invited by the General Assembly shall
                            be those for whom no recommendation for admission has been made by the
                            Security Council in spite of the fact that its application for admission
                            has received more than seven (7) favorable votes in the Security
                            Council.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The rights and obligations of a Non-Voting Participant shall be
                            defined in the General Assembly resolution mentioned in Paragraph 1. At
                            the same time, necessary revisions shall be made to the rules of
                            procedure of the General Assembly. <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                                </label>
                                <item>Rights <list>
                                        <label>(i)</label>
                                        <item>Right to send a delegation similar to that of a full
                                            member to all the meetings of the General
                                            Assembly.</item>
                                        <pb facs="0898" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/>
                                        <label>(ii)</label>
                                        <item>Right to participate without vote in the discussions
                                            of the Plenary sessions of the General Assembly, of its
                                            major committees and other committees of the whole. This
                                            right shall include all the rights to participate in
                                            discussion but the voting right, such as the right to
                                            speak, to submit a draft resolution, an amendment, and
                                            to submit and withdraw a motion.</item>
                                        <label>(iii)</label>
                                        <item>Right to receive from the Secretary-General all
                                            communications and documents pertaining to the General
                                            Assembly.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                                </label>
                                <item>Obligations <list>
                                        <label>(i)</label>
                                        <item>Obligation to present credentials.</item>
                                        <label>(ii)</label>
                                        <item>Obligation to comply with the rules of procedure of
                                            the General Assembly.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
