<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-03-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-03-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="78" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d78">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_LUNA1">L/UNA</gloss> files, “Headquarters
                                Agreement—Section 6”</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Legal Adviser for
                                    United Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MEEKERLC1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Meeker</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Legal Adviser</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PHLEGERH1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Phleger</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-03-26">March 26,
                                    1953</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <item>Subject:</item>
                                <item>Headquarters Agreement with the United Nations</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>In the Headquarters Agreement with the United Nations, the United
                                States has engaged to permit certain classes of individuals to come
                                into the United States in order to go to the United Nations in New
                                York. Section 11 of the Agreement defines these classes. The
                                President was authorized to bring the Headquarters Agreement into
                                effect by Public Law 357 of the 80th Congress. Section 6 of that
                                public law provides, in part: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Nothing in the Agreement shall be construed as in any way
                                        diminishing, abridging, or weakening the right of the United
                                        States to safeguard its own security and completely to
                                        control the entrance of aliens into any territory of the
                                        United States other than the headquarters district and its
                                        immediate vicinity, …”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Section 212(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of the
                                Immigration and Nationality Act sets forth 31 categories of
                                inadmissible aliens. Three of these categories are based on security
                                criteria: Section 212(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (27), 212(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (28), and 212(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                                (29). Section 212(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) (3) of the Immigration
                                and Nationality Act authorizes the Attorney General to waive the
                                grounds of inadmissibility for nonimmigrant aliens other than the
                                grounds set forth in subparagraphs (27) and (29).</p>
                            <p>In the past, a number of aliens entitled to enter the United States
                                under Section 11 of the Headquarters Agreement have been
                                inadmissible under Section 212(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (28) of the
                                Immigration and Nationality Act. In these cases, the Department of
                                State has recommended that the Attorney General waive the
                                inadmissibility, on the ground that such waiver in the particular
                                case was in the national interest. Although at times there have been
                                delays in securing a decision, the waivers have, in the end, been
                                granted.</p>
                            <p>Two very recent cases, however, have been handled differently,
                                raising problems. A Canadian national, Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_LUCKOCKMR1">M. R. Luckock</persName>, sought to
                                enter the United States to attend a meeting of the United Nations
                                Commission on the Status of Women, under Section 11(4) of the
                                Headquarters Agreement. She sought to come as a representative of
                                the Women’s International Democratic Federation, a
                                Communist-dominated organization. She appeared to be inadmissible
                                under Section 212 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (28) of the Immigration
                                and Nationality Act. This Department requested the Department of
                                Justice to waive her inadmissibility. The Department of Justice, for
                                the first time, denied the request, stating that the information
                                forwarded to Washington by the consul <pb facs="0281" n="253" xml:id="pg_253"/> showed that Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_LUCKOCKMR1">Luckock</persName> fell within Section
                                212 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (29) of the Immigration and
                                Nationality Act. The information forwarded by the consul had covered
                                two points: (1) Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_LUCKOCKMR1">Luckock</persName> held hostile views toward the United States
                                Government, and (2) at a public meeting in Canada, she sponsored a
                                resolution criticizing the course of the
                                    <persName>Rosenberg</persName> spy case. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HICKERSONJD1">Hickerson</persName> and Mrs.
                                    <persName>Hahn</persName> (our representative on the Status of
                                Women Commission) talked by telephone with Mr.
                                    <persName>Rogers</persName>, the Deputy Attorney General, about
                                the <persName corresp="#p_LUCKOCKMR1">Luckock</persName> case, but
                                apparently did not discuss the legal aspects under the Immigration
                                and Nationality Act and the Headquarters Agreement.</p>
                            <p>A French national, <persName corresp="#p_VAILLANTCOUTURIER1">Madame
                                    M.–C. Vaillant-Couturier</persName>, is now seeking to come to
                                the United States for the April meeting of the United Nations’
                                Economic and Social Council, again under Section 11 (4) of the
                                Headquarters Agreement. Like Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_LUCKOCKMR1">Luckock</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VAILLANTCOUTURIER1">Madame Vaillant-Couturier</persName> would be a representative
                                of the <gloss target="#t_WIDF1">W.I.D.F.</gloss> The Department’s
                                visa office has informed <gloss target="#t_UNA1">UNA</gloss> of its
                                determination that <persName corresp="#p_VAILLANTCOUTURIER1">Madame
                                    Vaillant-Couturier</persName> falls within Section 212(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (29) of the Immigration and Nationality
                                Act, and of its decision not to request a waiver of inadmissibility
                                by the Department of Justice. From the facts available to this
                                Office, it is not clear whether the view of the visa office is based
                                on <persName corresp="#p_VAILLANTCOUTURIER1">Madame
                                    Vaillant-Couturier</persName>’s status with the <gloss target="#t_WIDF1">W.I.D.F.</gloss>, or on additional facts.
                                Unless a recommendation is made to the Department of Justice, the
                                applicant will not receive a visa and will not be admitted to the
                                United States.</p>
                            <p>As you know, this type of problem under the Headquarters Agreement
                                has given concern to Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_WADSWORTHJJ1">Wadsworth</persName> in New York. Attached to this memorandum
                                is a telegram of yesterday from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName>.<note n="1" xml:id="d78fn1">Not attached; presumably telegram 578, Mar. 25,
                                        <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.<persName corresp="#p_MEEKERLC1">Meeker</persName> also enclosed
                                    copies of the Headquarters Agreement and the Immigration and
                                    Nationality Act.</note> There are difficult legal problems
                                involved in individual cases, both under the Headquarters Agreement
                                with the United Nations and under the Immigration and Nationality
                                Act. These problems need to be carefully considered in each case, in
                                order that the United States make a disposition which would leave us
                                in a strong position if the case were later to be taken to
                                arbitration by the United Nations under Section 21 of the
                                Headquarters Agreement.</p>
                            <p>I suggest that careful consideration needs to be given to this type
                                of case at two stages: (1) when this Department is considering
                                whether to recommend to the Attorney General that inadmissibility
                                under Section 212(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) (28) be waived, and (2)
                                in discussing the matter with the Department of Justice after the
                                State Department has recommended a waiver of inadmissibility. In the
                                first stage, it is not satisfactory for the visa office alone to
                                make a determination; there needs to be consultation among the
                                Departmental offices concerned, including the Office of the Legal
                                Adviser. In the second stage, the Department of Justice <pb facs="0282" n="254" xml:id="pg_254"/> should not be put in the
                                position of having to make a decision on waiver without the benefit
                                of discussion with officers of this Department, including officers
                                in <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>. If you agree, we should suggest
                                to the visa office and to <gloss target="#t_UNA1">UNA</gloss> the
                                holding of appropriate consultations at both stages. In this way, I
                                believe, the best application of the Immigration and Nationality Act
                                would be secured, and we would minimize the possibilities of future
                                arbitral difficulty under the Headquarters Agreement.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MEEKERLC1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Leonard C.
                                            Meeker</hi></persName>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>