<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Curtis C. Strong of the Office of Dependent Area Affairs to the
                    Working Group on Colonial Problems</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d796</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">796</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recebl4V1INuqlVGh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="796"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d796">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Committee files, lot 54 D 5,
                    “Working Group on Colonial Problems”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by <persName type="from">Curtis C.
                            Strong</persName> of the Office of Dependent Area Affairs to the <gloss
                            type="to">Working Group on Colonial Problems</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d796fn1">Circulated to the Working Group under cover of Doc.
                        CP D–11, Aug. 26, 1952 (the second of five attachments).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-08-26">August 26,
                            1952</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Dilemmas for the United States Presented by Somaliland
                        Under Italian Administration</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d796fn2">For documentation on this subject, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v11p1">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">xi</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">the problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The problem is to ascertain the dilemmas for the United States involved in the
                    question of Somaliland under Italian administration.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The disposition of the former Italian colony of Somaliland after World War II is
                    a question in the colonial field which has found certain United States foreign
                    policy interests in conflict with certain other United States interests. The
                    conflicts that have arisen in this case may be summarized briefly as
                    follows.</p>
                <p>On the one hand, it is in the interests of the United States that the former
                    Italian colony of Somaliland be given a stable administration by a friendly
                    power capable of insuring its security. In view of the lack of interest in
                    administering Somaliland among other friendly powers which would meet these
                    qualifications, the above-mentioned United States interests were factors leading
                    the United States to support the return of Italy to Somaliland. Furthermore,
                    with a critical struggle being waged over the allegiance of Italy, as between
                    the free world and the Soviet world, it was in our interests to strengthen the
                    prestige of an Italian government favorable to the free world. This was another
                    consideration which inclined the United States to support the return of Italy to
                    Somaliland.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, it is in the interest of the United States to retain the
                    sympathy and support of the many “anti-colonial” nations in Asia, Latin America
                    and Africa. These nations tended to support the Somali leaders and the
                    neighboring African state of Ethiopia in their opposition to Italy’s return to
                    Somaliland. There were strong reasons therefore for the United States to
                    sympathize with their views.</p>
                <p>It is also in the interest of the United States that there be a strong and
                    effective United Nations. To the extent that the United Nations fails to deal
                    with colonial questions, such as the disposition of Somaliland, in a way favored
                    by the majority of its members, the latter will <pb facs="1173" n="1145"
                        xml:id="pg_1145"/> tend to lose faith in the United Nations. It is therefore
                    in the interests of the United States to see that the United Nations deals
                    effectively with such problems in a way that will obtain majority support.</p>
                <p>It was in part as a result of these conflicting interests that the United States
                    supported the return of Italy to Somaliland for a period of ten years only and
                    under the terms of the trusteeship agreement which provided also for a United
                    Nations Advisory Council. The same conflict of interests affect United States
                    positions in United Nations bodies on Italy’s administration of the Trust
                    Territory of Somaliland.</p>
                <p>Further dilemmas confront the United States in the case of Somaliland in view of
                    the fact that the territory must be made independent in less than eight years.
                    The United States, therefore, tends to support recommendations in the United
                    Nations urging the Italian administration to take more active steps in the
                    direction of setting up responsible local government ready to take over
                    increasing responsibilities in the near future. However, such proposals tend to
                    encourage the more extreme dissident elements in Somaliland, such as the Somali
                    Youth League, which not only makes difficulties for the Italian administration
                    but increase their complaints to the United Nations in regard to Italian
                    administration. On the other hand, blanket support of the Italian administration
                    arouses the suspicions of the “anti-colonial” powers in the United Nations and
                    makes us liable to the charge of encouraging the Italians to take undue
                    advantage of their position to maintain a large corps of Italian officials in
                    the territory, to squeeze the economic life of the territory in the interest of
                    Italians, and otherwise to favor and perpetuate Italian interests in
                    Somaliland.</p>
                <p>A further dilemma confronts the United States in that proposals for improving the
                    economic, social and educational status of the territory would require resources
                    which go far beyond that which the territory could maintain and may need to
                    maintain when it stands on its own feet. Thus the United States is torn between
                    its desire to support needed developments in Somaliland, generally favored by a
                    majority of United Nations members, and its recognition of the need for realism,
                    a course favored by Italy and other administering powers but much less popular
                    in the United Nations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
