<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Text of United Nations ( (ECOSOC) ) Doc. E/2397, April 10, 1953</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-04-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-04-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recZPVvCSdB8G01JR" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recKYrSKAcKpKC6kD" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86007360"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Nongovernmental organization</term>
                    <term ref="recFzikmNCJDCCGBL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade unions</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="82"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_LUNA1">L/UNA</gloss> files, “Privileges &amp; Immunities,
                    General, 1944–1954”</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Text of United Nations</hi> (<gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">
                        <hi rend="italic">ECOSOC</hi>
                    </gloss>) <hi rend="italic">Doc. E/2397, April 10, 1953</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1953-04-10">April 10, 1953</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admission of Representatives of Non-Governmental
                        Organizations Enjoying Consultative Status</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">memorandum by the legal department</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. This memorandum is transmitted in compliance with the request, made on 9 April
                    1953 at the 679th plenary meeting of the Economic and Social Council, for a
                    legal opinion on the extent to which the denial by the United States of the
                    applications by two representatives of non-governmental organizations for
                    transit to the Headquarters District is consistent with the terms of the
                    Agreement between the United Nations and the United States of America regarding
                    the Headquarters of the United Nations.</p>
                <pb facs="0286" n="258" xml:id="pg_258"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">A. <hi rend="italic">Summary of Facts</hi>
                </p>
                <p>2. In accordance with resolution 288 (X) concerning consultative arrangements
                    with non-governmental organizations, adopted by the Economic and Social Council
                    under the authority of Article 71 of the Charter, the Women’s International
                    Democratic Federation, a nongovernmental organization in consultative
                    relationship with the Council in Category B, designated Mrs. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LUCKOCKMR1">Margarette Rae Luckock</persName> as its
                    representative to attend the seventh session of the Commission on the Status of
                    Women, which adjourned on 3 April 1953, and thereafter to attend the current
                    session of the Economic and Social Council. The World Federation of Trade
                    Unions, a non-governmental organization in consultative relationship with the
                    Council in Category A, designated Mr. <persName>Jan Dessau</persName> as it
                    representative to attend the current session of the Council. Both
                    representatives made application for a visa at appropriate United States
                    Consulates and the Secretariat of the Economic and Social Council made
                    notification to the United States Mission to the United Nations of these
                    applications, in accordance with established procedures.</p>
                <p>3. The representative of the United States reported to the Economic and Social
                    Council at its 679th plenary meeting on 9 April 1953 that his Government had
                    found it impossible to grant these applications. He explained the position of
                    his Government as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In denying these applications, my Government has found it necessary to
                            invoke the right to safeguard its security which it reserved to itself
                            in Section 6 of the Joint Resolution (Public Law 357) of the 80th
                            Congress, which authorized the United States to enter into the
                            Headquarters Agreement, and in the note of its Representative, dated
                            November 21, 1947, bringing the Headquarters Agreement into effect.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">Provisions of the Headquarters
                        Agreement</hi>
                </p>
                <p>4. Section 11(4) of the Headquarters Agreement provides: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The federal, state or local authorities of the United States shall not
                            impose any impediments to transit to or from the headquarters district
                            of … (4) representatives of non-governmental organizations recognized by
                            the United Nations for the purpose of consultation under Article 71 of
                            the Charter…”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>5. Section 13 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of the Headquarters Agreement reads as
                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Laws and regulations in force in the United
                            States regarding the entry of aliens shall not be applied in such manner
                            as to interfere with the privileges referred to in Section 11. When
                            visas are required for persons referred to in that Section, they shall
                            be granted without charge and as promptly as possible.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>6. These are the only provisions in the Headquarters Agreement bearing upon the
                    right of transit to the Headquarters District on the part of properly designated
                    representatives of non-governmental organizations. Nothing in the text of the
                    Headquarters Agreement reserves <pb facs="0287" n="259" xml:id="pg_259"/> to the
                    United States the authority to deny a visa to any of the classes of persons
                    specified in Section 11. Indeed, Section 13(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) specifies
                    that, except as provided above, “…the United States retains full control and
                    authority over the entry of persons or property into the territory of the United
                    States…”.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">C. <hi rend="italic">Joint Resolution of the 80th Congress</hi>
                </p>
                <p>7. By Joint Resolution (Public Law 357–80th Congress) the Senate and House of
                    Representatives of the United States Congress authorized the President of the
                    United States to bring the Headquarters Agreement into effect on the part of the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>8. Section 6 of the Joint Resolution stated that nothing in the Agreement should
                    be construed as in any way diminishing, abridging or weakening the right of the
                    United States to safeguard its own security and completely to control the entry
                    of aliens into any territory of the United States other than the Headquarters
                    District and its immediate vicinity, and such areas as it was reasonably
                    necessary to traverse in transit between the same and foreign countries.<note
                        n="*" xml:id="d82fn1">“See. 6. Nothing in the agreement shall be construed
                        as in any way diminishing, abridging, or weakening the right of the United
                        States to safeguard its own security and completely to control the entrance
                        of aliens into any territory of the United States other than the
                        headquarters district and its immediate vicinity, as to be defined and fixed
                        in a supplementary agreement between the Government of the United States and
                        the United Nations in pursuance of section 13(3) (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)
                        of the agreement, and such areas as it is reasonably necessary to traverse
                        in transit between the same and foreign countries. Moreover, nothing in
                        section 14 of the agreement with respect to facilitating entrance into the
                        United States by persons who wish to visit the headquarters district and do
                        not enjoy the right of entry provided in section 11 of the agreement shall
                        be construed to amend or suspend in any way the immigration laws of the
                        United States or to commit the United States in any way to effect any
                        amendment or suspension of such laws.” [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                </p>
                <p>9. The Secretary-General of the United Nations was authorized to bring the
                    Headquarters Agreement into force by the General Assembly, which approved the
                    text of the Agreement in its resolution 169(II). But in the event that the
                    provision in section 6 of the Joint Resolution had been intended by the United
                    States to constitute a reservation, it was never made known to the General
                    Assembly as such, and it was never considered by the General Assembly nor
                    accepted by it.</p>
                <p>10. It is an established principle of international law that a reservation to a
                    bilateral treaty or agreement is in effect a proposal to amend the text of the
                    agreement and must therefore be accepted by the other party if it is to have any
                    effect. <persName>David Hunter Miller</persName>, for example, in his well-known
                    work on “Reservations to Treaties”, after reviewing the history of qualifying
                    declarations in United States treaty practice, states (p. 76), “One conclusion
                    supported by <hi rend="italic">all</hi> of the foregoing precedents is that the
                    declaration, whether in the nature of an explanation, an understanding, an
                    interpretation, or reservation of any kind, <hi rend="italic">must be agreed to
                        by the other Party to the treaty</hi> … <pb facs="0288" n="260"
                        xml:id="pg_260"/> Accordingly, in a treaty between two Powers only, the
                    difference between a reservation of any nature and an amendment, is purely one
                    of form.” (Author’s emphasis.)</p>
                <p>11. Pursuant to its section 28, the Headquarters Agreement was brought into force
                    by an exchange of notes between the Secretary-General and the representative of
                    the United States. The United States note, dated 21 November 1947, added: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Pursuant to instruction from my Government, I have the honor to inform
                            you that the Government of the United States of America is prepared to
                            apply the above-mentioned Headquarters Agreement subject to the
                            provisions of Public Law 357.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>This observation is in general terms and did not make reference to any
                    reservation. It was made subsequent to the final adoption of the Agreement by
                    the General Assembly. For these reasons, and because it appeared in a formal
                    note of entry into force, it did not give notice to the Secretary-General that
                    the United States might claim the authority to restrict transit to and from the
                    Headquarters District.</p>
                <p>12. Finally, even if the United States had intended to formulate a reservation,
                    it would not appear from a reading of section 6 of the Joint Resolution that it
                    could have application to the present cases. It refers to control by the United
                    States of the entrance of aliens into any territory of the United States <hi
                        rend="italic">other than</hi> the Headquarters District, its immediate
                    vicinity, and the necessary area of transit.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">D. <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>13. It appears from the foregoing that persons falling within the classes
                    referred to in section 11 of the Headquarters Agreement are entitled to transit
                    to and from the Headquarters District, and that this right of transit has not
                    been made the subject of any reservation.</p>
                <p>14. Should the United States adhere to its position, it is clear that there would
                    then exist a dispute between the United Nations and the United States concerning
                    the interpretation or application of the Headquarters Agreement. The Council
                    will note that section 21 of the Headquarters Agreement establishes the
                    procedures for handling any such dispute. If the dispute is not settled by
                    negotiation or other agreed mode of settlement, it “shall be referred for final
                    decision to a tribunal of three arbitrators, one to be named by the
                    Secretary-General, one to be named by the Secretary of State of the United
                    States, and the third to be chosen by the two, or, if they should fail to agree
                    upon a third, then by the President of the International Court of Justice.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
