<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Position Paper Prepared in the Department of State for the United States
                    Delegation to the General Assembly Ad Hoc Committee on Factors</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d823</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">823</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-09-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-09-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec3xWCKc8tJ1gyWw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="rec9yKWGNvCFmqmdD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">International organizations</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                    <term ref="recTdbwPhSPuOaeNu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-09-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-09-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="823"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d823">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> files, SD/A/AC.58/1</note>
                <note n="1" xml:id="d823fn1">This was one of three papers in a Position Book
                    entitled “General Assembly <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on Factors”
                    and dated Sept. 4, 1952. Copies of this and Position Books for other Committee
                    sessions are also in the <gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss> files, lot 62 D
                    182.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Position Paper Prepared in the <gloss type="from">Department
                            of State for the United States Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">General Assembly Ad Hoc Committee on Factors</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d823fn2">Regarding the membership and function of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on Factors, see the text of General
                        Assembly Resolution 567 (VI) in Annex E of this paper, <ref
                            target="#pg_1227">p. 1227</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-09-02">September 2,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Assembly Ad Hoc Committee</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(“to carry out a further study of the factors which should be
                    taken into account in deciding whether a territory is or is not a territory
                    whose people have not yet attained a full measure of self-government”)</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">the problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The problem is to determine the position of the United States Delegation to the
                    General Assembly’s <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on Factors.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> Recommendations on the specific questions of (<hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>) Cessation of Submission of Information on the
                    Netherlands Antilles and Surinam and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Future Cessation
                    of Submission on Puerto Rico, are contained in separate position papers which
                    should be utilized in conjunction with this paper.]<note n="3" xml:id="d823fn3"
                        >Brackets throughout this document are in the source text. The position
                        paper on the Netherlands Antilles and Surinam is not printed; for the paper
                        on Puerto Rico, see <ref target="#pg_1427">p. 1427</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>In view of the complexity and emphasized importance of the problem to date
                        in the United Nations, the United States Representative should favor full
                        discussions in the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee as the United
                        States has previously done in the Special Committee and Committee IV.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The United States Representative should bear in mind that the most
                        desirable outcome of the discussions, in view of the exhaustive treatment
                        the factors question has received in the last four years, would be a report
                        by the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee which would sum up previous
                        considerations and set forth the conclusion that any definition or list of
                        factors which finally might be formulated can only be useful as a guide in
                        determining when a territory ceases to become non-self-governing.<note n="*"
                            xml:id="d823fn4">If the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee decides
                            to take up the question of competence, see the previous position paper
                            (Annex F). [Footnote in the source text.]</note> In this connection the
                        United States Representative should <pb facs="1242" n="1214"
                            xml:id="pg_1214"/> be guided by the position taken repeatedly by the
                        United States that neither a definition nor a list of factors could be
                        flexible enough to take account of the complexities of constitutional forms
                        and usages in the wide variety of territories and at the same time specific
                        enough to be definitive. In discussions on this point the United States
                        Representative may take occasion to point out that the careful and
                        exhaustive consideration which the factors question has received to date in
                        the United Nations and the divergencies which have characterized the
                        consideration of this question by various Members have amply demonstrated
                        the soundness of the United States position.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Should the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee desire, in response to
                        General Assembly Resolution 567 (VI), to submit to the Assembly a list of
                        “factors which should be taken into account” elaborating the list contained
                        in the Annex to the resolution, the United States may agree to such a list,
                        provided that no one factor or combination of factors is presented as
                        determining in any given case the status of a territory in relation to
                        Chapter XI. In this connection, the factors emphasized previously by the
                        United States are contained in Annex A.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The United States Representative should support the principle that the
                        General Assembly may examine information submitted to it regarding the
                        cessation of information but should oppose any proposed resolution or
                        language which implies that it is the prerogative of the General Assembly
                        ultimately to decide when a territory ceases to become non-self-governing or
                        even the General Assembly and the Administering Authority to decide. We
                        might, however, express the hope that any actions leading to the cessation
                        of reporting under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) would be such as to
                        meet with the general satisfaction of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                        Members.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In formal or informal consultations with representatives of other powers
                        in the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> or Fourth Committee, the United States
                        Representative should <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Express appreciation for the substantive contributions they have
                                made to the discussions of the “factors question” and the wisdom of
                                their efforts to maintain a cooperative atmosphere in this
                                regard;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Urge the administering powers to exercise the utmost patience in
                                order to maintain a friendly and cooperative atmosphere and, despite
                                whatever the majority conclusions of the <hi rend="italic">Ad
                                    Hoc</hi> Committee and Committee IV may be, not to exacerbate
                                the situation by any suggestions of non-participation in activities
                                under Chapter XI or disregard for recommendations in the field of
                                non-self-governing territories. We should invite them to interpret
                                in the broadest practicable sense their obligation to transmit
                                information under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the
                                Charter on economic, social, and educational conditions in
                                non-self-governing territories.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Share fully and frankly with them [as well as the
                                non-administering Members] the United States position on substantive
                                questions.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="1243" n="1215" xml:id="pg_1215"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Should a point of order be raised in regard to views of the Belgain
                        Government which stress the fact that many Members have not reported on the
                        aboriginal peoples living within their jurisdictions, the United States
                        Representatives should take the position that such views may legitimately be
                        placed before the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee and the General
                        Assembly since neither are bound by the terms of reference of the Committee
                        on Information from Non-Self-Governing Territories which do not entitle it
                        to apply its conclusions to any specific territory. The United States
                        Representative should not initiate discussions on this matter, but in the
                        course of their development, should take the following position: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Express appreciation to the Belgian delegation for the important
                                and impressive data which they have presented for the information of
                                the Committee and the General Assembly;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Indicate that concern for the welfare and development of all
                                aboriginal peoples ought, on the one hand, to enhance appreciation
                                with the United Nations of the general problem of promoting
                                self-government and, on the other, by virtue of their participation
                                in the work of the United Nations to increase the awareness of
                                Member Governments who administer such peoples of their
                                responsibilities in regard to them;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Point out, however, that the absence of territorial identity
                                outside the territorial limits of the Member Governments who
                                administer such peoples would seem to preclude them from the
                                reporting provisions of Chapter XI of the Charter;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Present the view that the matter of reporting on aboriginal
                                peoples within the boundaries of Member States would depend upon the
                                present provisions of the Charter being reviewed and, therefore,
                                extended consideration of this question could only lead the
                                Committee into difficult discussions in the political field which
                                would be beyond the competence of the General Assembly to decide
                                under its present terms.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>In discussing the Belgian views, care should be exercised to avoid any
                        statement which might be prejudicial to the position of the United Kingdom
                        with respect to the South African protectorates of Bechuanaland, Basutoland,
                        and Swaziland, the administration of which is desired by the Union of South
                        Africa.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>If it seems appropriate at the early stages of the <hi rend="italic">Ad
                            Hoc</hi> Committee’s deliberations, the United States Representative
                        should make a general statement along lines of the attached draft (Annex
                            B).<note n="4" xml:id="d823fn5">Not printed.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">background</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Under Chapter XI of the United Nations Charter “Members of the United Nations
                    which have or assume responsibilities for the administration of territories
                    whose peoples have not yet attained a full measure of self-government,”
                    undertake certain responsibilities in <pb facs="1244" n="1216" xml:id="pg_1216"
                    /> regard to these territories. The Charter does not, however, undertake to
                    define the term “a non-self-governing territory.”</p>
                <p>At the First Session of the General Assembly, after some discussion of the
                    problem, the Assembly merely “noted” the list of 74 territories on which eight
                    members had transmitted, or declared their intention of transmitting
                    information.</p>
                <p>By 1948 the General Assembly had before it information on only 62 of the 74
                    territories listed in the 1946 resolution. The Assembly then adopted a
                    resolution proposed by India (and considerably modified) which affirmed the
                    principle that the United Nations should be informed of such changes in the
                    constitutional position and status of certain territories as had led the
                    responsible Government to discontinue transmission of information, and requested
                    the Members concerned to furnish the Secretary General with the relevant
                    documents relating to the new status of the territory and its constitutional
                    relationship to the metropole. (<gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Res. 222
                    (III), Annex C).<hi rend="superscript">6</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At the Fourth Session of the General Assembly a resolution on “Territories to
                    which Chapter XI of the Charter Applies” was adopted. In this resolution the
                    General Assembly considered that it was within its responsibility “to express
                    its opinion on the principles which have guided or may in the future guide the
                    Members concerned in enumerating the territories for which the obligation exists
                    to transmit information under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the
                    Charter.” The Assembly further invited the Special Committee “to examine the
                    factors which should be taken into account in deciding whether any territory is
                    or is not a territory whose people have not yet attained a full measure of
                    self-government.” (See <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Res. 334 (IV), Annex
                        D).<note n="5" xml:id="d823fn7">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In 1951 the Special Committee undertook an examination of the factors. The
                    Committee’s report on this problem noted that there are numerous elements which
                    should be taken into consideration in determining if a territory is or is not
                    self-governing and that it did not consider that “any single factor or any
                    particular combination of factors can be regarded as prominent or decisive in
                    every case, except that the will of the people of the territory concerned
                    properly and freely expressed, would in all cases be the paramount factor in
                    deciding whether a relationship between the administering authority and a
                    non-self-governing territory has evolved to a stage where that territory could
                    be said to have attained a full measure of self-government.” The report listed a
                    number of factors of a geographical, political, economic and cultural nature
                    which in the opinion of the Committee should be taken into account in
                    determining if a territory has achieved a status of full self-government,
                    stressing that the list is not to be considered as being exhaustive. In “a
                    spirit of seeking understanding rather than <pb facs="1245" n="1217"
                        xml:id="pg_1217"/> marking [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] controversies” the
                    Special Committee did not enter into the question of competence, that is, who
                    should determine when a territory is no longer non-self-governing.</p>
                <p>After receiving the report of the Special Committee, the Fourth Committee of the
                    Sixth General Assembly appointed a sub-committee to study the basic and general
                    factors to be taken into account in deciding whether a territory is or is not a
                    territory whose people have not yet attained a full measure of self-government
                    and to consider the advisability of establishing procedures for the further
                    study of the problem.</p>
                <p>This sub-committee drew up a list of factors as well as a draft resolution which
                    the Fourth Committee submitted to the General Assembly, The Assembly adopted the
                    sub-committee’s resolution (see <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Res. 567 (VI),
                    Annex B) and thereby: decided to take as a basis for the future study of the
                    factors the list drawn up by the sub-committee; invited the Members of the
                    United Nations to transmit to the Secretary General by May 1, 1952, a statement
                    of their views on the factors; appointed an <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi>
                    Committee of ten members (Australia, Belgium, Burma, Cuba, Denmark, France,
                    Guatemala, Iraq, the United States, and Venezuela) to carry out a further study
                    of the factors and to report to the Seventh General Assembly; and invited the
                    Secretary General to convene the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee in
                    order that it might complete its work one week before the opening of the 1952
                    session of the Committee on Information from Non-Self-Governing Territories. The
                    Committee is to convene in New York September 4.</p>
                <p>To date seventeen Member Governments have provided statements of their views on
                    the factors question in accordance with the request contained in para. 2 of
                        <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Res. 567 (VI)—Belgium, Burma, Byelorussian
                    Soviet Socialist Republic, Denmark, Egypt, El Salvador–Guatemala (joint reply),
                    France, Greece, Indonesia, Iraq, the Netherlands, Pakistan, Philippines, <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, the United Kingdom and Yugoslavia.<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d823fn8">
                        <p>These replies are printed in <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> Doc.
                            A/AC.58/1 and additions 1–6, dated variously from May 22, 1952 to Aug.
                            20, 1952, and entitled “<hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on
                            Factors (Non-Self-Governing Territories) Replies of Governments
                            indicating their views on the factors to be taken into account in
                            deciding whether a territory is or is not a territory whose people have
                            not yet attained a full measure of self-government”. These documents are
                            filed (item 10) in the Position Book for the U.S. Delegation to the 1953
                            Session of the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on Factors
                                (<gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> files and <gloss target="#t_ODA1"
                                >ODA</gloss> files, lot 62 D 182). (This item also includes replies
                            filed by Chile and New Zealand subsequent to Aug. 20, 1952.)</p>
                        <p>Relevant documentation relating to “the factors question” is also in the
                                <gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss> files, lot 60 D 257, “<gloss
                                target="#t_NSGT1">NSGT</gloss>: Factors, etc.”</p>
                    </note> The United States response to this request was as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The United States assumes that the General Assembly Resolution of
                            January 18, 1952, inviting Members to submit their views on this
                            question by May 1, 1952, is primarily intended for those Members who
                            have not participated in the General Assembly’s Committees dealing with
                            this question. The United States has already made known its <pb
                                facs="1246" n="1218" xml:id="pg_1218"/> views through active
                            participation in these Committees and has nothing to add to these views
                            at this time. Any further comments which the United States may wish to
                            present will be made in the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee of
                            the General Assembly…”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The Committee is to take into account all the information available, including
                    that transmitted to the Secretary General on the reasons which have led certain
                    Administering Members to cease to transmit information on certain of their
                    territories.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Past United States Position</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In a note of August 19, 1946 transmitting copies of the latest annual reports of
                    the Governors of Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands and Panama
                    Canal Zone, Guam and Samoa, the Department of State suggested that Chapter II of
                    the Charter “would appear to apply to any territories administered by a Member
                    of the United Nations who do not enjoy the same measure of self-government as
                    the metropolitan area of that member.” The Department of State added that for
                    1946 the United States had used a purely pragmatic approach in selecting the
                    territories on which it should transmit information on the hope that the
                    experience of the various Members would perhaps reveal more clearly the kind of
                    criteria, if any, which could eventually be agreed upon in making the selection.
                    The United States ceased transmitting information on the Panama Canal Zone after
                    1946, having received a protest from the Republic of Panama, and indicated
                    subsequently that this was a matter for consultations between the United States
                    and the Republic of Panama. The United States voted for <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                        >GA</gloss> Res. 222(III) and stated that even had this resolution not been
                    adopted the United States would expect to inform the Secretary General if for
                    any reason it ceased to transmit information on one of its territories. The
                    United States recorded its understanding, however, that the transmission of the
                    information requested in the resolution did not alter the right of each
                    administering state to determine the constitutional position and status of any
                    particular territory under its sovereignty. The United States restated this
                    understanding when the Special Committee was entrusted with the task of studying
                    the factors. The United States position at that time was that the General
                    Assembly had the right to compile a list of factors for the guidance of Members
                    but that no definition or list of factors could be flexible enough to take
                    account of the complexities of constitutional forms and usages in the wide
                    variety of territories involved and at the same time specific enough to be
                    definitive.</p>
                <p>At the Sixth General Assembly during the discussions in Committee IV on the
                    Report of the Committee on Information from Non-Self-Governing Territories, the
                    Alternate United States Representative, <pb facs="1247" n="1219"
                        xml:id="pg_1219"/> Dr. <persName>Channing Tobias</persName>, included in his
                    statement on November 21, 1951 the following comments on the factors question:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“…A special section of the Report contains a carefully studied analysis
                            of the factors which should be taken into account in determining whether
                            or not a territory has become self-governing within the meaning of the
                            Charter. This report results from an Assembly resolution of two years
                            ago and it reflects, in the view of my Delegation, a great deal of
                            wisdom and intelligence. Undoubtedly some Delegations here may think
                            that they could add other factors to this list and some may think that
                            certain factors appearing there should be eliminated. My Delegation has
                            always taken the position that the circumstances of the various
                            non-self-governing territories are so different that no single factor or
                            combination of factors would necessarily apply in all cases. We have
                            studied this document most carefully and we believe that the Fourth
                            Committee should accept it as a guide to be seriously taken into account
                            in determining when a people have reached the point when it has become
                            self-governing or when it has attained a status whereby it need no
                            longer be reported upon under Chapter XI.</p>
                        <p>“The United States Delegation believes that territories should be
                            encouraged and assisted to become self-governing as rapidly as possible
                            and we would not wish such a development delayed as a result of laying
                            down so many complex factors to be met that the people might become
                            discouraged in their onward progress toward self-government. We believe
                            it is the duty of this Committee not unnecessarily to complicate the
                            progress or to place too many difficult hurdles in the way. As I look
                            over this list of factors, I could not help but think that a number of
                            so-called independent countries might find it difficult to qualify on
                            all the points mentioned in this list.</p>
                        <p>“Mr. Chairman, my delegation believes that what we must always strive for
                            is that non-self-governing peoples may be placed in a position where
                            they can freely choose their destiny. It is this element of freedom of
                            choice which in our view is the keystone of the whole question.
                            Non-self-governing peoples should not be coerced against their will to
                            assume a status which they do not desire. Such a relationship is almost
                            certainly bound to make trouble and will usually create deep-seated
                            resentments. And when I say that these peoples should be free-to choose,
                            I mean that they should be able freely to decide the nature of the
                            relationship which they wish to maintain with any other country. History
                            has shown that this relationship has sometimes taken the form of
                            independence. In other cases it has taken the form of some degree of
                            association with the mother country and other countries, and in still
                            other cases, it has taken the form of complete assimilation or
                            integration with another State. All these are possibilities, and it
                            would be a wise man indeed who would undertake to forecast which is the
                            most desirable form of self-government for peoples who are now not fully
                            self-governing.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Application to Territories Administered by the United
                        States</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) the United States reports on Alaska,
                    Hawaii, Puerto Rico, Virgin Islands of the United States, Guam and American
                    Samoa. It also reports to the Trusteeship Council on its administration <pb
                        facs="1248" n="1220" xml:id="pg_1220"/> of the Trust Territory of the
                    Pacific Islands. These seven territories are at widely varying stages of
                    political, as well as economic, social and educational development. On the one
                    hand, Hawaii and Alaska are on the threshold of statehood in the Union while
                    Puerto Rico has as of July 25, 1952 achieved the status of an autonomous
                    Commonwealth under a constitution drafted by the people of Puerto Rico and
                    approved by the United States Congress. At the other extreme is the Trust
                    Territory of the Pacific Islands composed of 96 distinct island units composed
                    of 2,141 individual islands scattered over an ocean area of approximately three
                    million square miles and with a combined land area of only 687 square miles. The
                    United States has placed on record in the Security Council the statement that
                    despite the fact that no people are more consecrated to the principle of
                    independence than the people of the United States, such status for the Trust
                    Territory could not be achieved within any foreseeable future. The territories
                    of the Virgin Islands, Guam and American Samoa enjoy varying intermediate stages
                    in the development of local self-government and no one can foretell what their
                    ultimate political status will be.</p>
                <p>It is obvious, however, that in taking positions in the United Nations on the
                    factors question, the United States must bear in mind that all territories under
                    its jurisdiction are not likely to achieve statehood as an ultimate status and
                    that our present new relationship with Puerto Rico calls for a broader
                    interpretation of “self-government” than simply membership in the Federal
                    Union.</p>
                <p>It is assumed that, in view of the changed status of Puerto Rico as a result of
                    the promulgation of its new Constitution on July 25, 1952, it will no longer be
                    appropriate or advisable for the United States to submit information on Puerto
                    Rico in accordance with Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the
                        Charter.<note n="7" xml:id="d823fn9">See documentation on Puerto Rico, <ref
                            target="#pg_1427">pp. 1427</ref> ff.</note> Such action on the part of
                    the United States will depend upon a definition by this Government as to the new
                    relationship between it and the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico. However, since
                    information remains to be transmitted for the period July 1, 1951 to June 30,
                    1952, it is assumed that the cessation of submission of information would not
                    become effective until a year hence.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Administering Authorities Which Have Ceased to Transmit
                        Information</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">France:</hi> The French Government in 1949 maintained that the
                    territories on which no information was transmitted (Martinique, Guadeloupe,
                    Reunion, French Guiana, St. Pierre and Miquelon, French Oceania, New Caledonia
                    and Dependencies, French Establishments in India and the Associated States of
                    Indo-China) were no longer non-self-governing by virtue of having become
                    departments of France <pb facs="1249" n="1221" xml:id="pg_1221"/> “with a regime
                    which is largely identical with that of the Departments of Metropolitan France,”
                    or overseas territories “with a regime which on the whole closely resembles that
                    of the Overseas Departments of Metropolitan France as regards the status of the
                    inhabitants and their method of political representation” or associated states
                    with “freedom of self-government to the extent of independence within the
                    framework of the French Union.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">United Kingdom:</hi> The British position with respect to
                    Malta in 1947 as stated by the United Kingdom Representative, was that Malta on
                    September 5, 1947 “had attained full responsibility for local self-governments”
                    and while not yet in full control of its external affairs was nevertheless fully
                    responsible for the conduct of its internal affairs. In 1949, the United Kingdom
                    Representative invoked “constitutional consideration” from the phrase “subject
                    to such limitation as security and constitutional considerations may require” in
                    Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) as a reason for the United Kingdom’s
                    ceasing to transmit information on Malta. The United Kingdom Representative
                    stated that “since under the 1947 constitution Malta was responsible for its own
                    internal administration, including the matters mentioned in Article 73(<hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi>) the United Kingdom Government was not concerned with
                    these matters for constitutional reasons and could not, therefore, supply any
                    information regarding them”.<note n="8" xml:id="d823fn10">Marginal notation
                        beside this paragraph: “would resume reporting, with approval of Malta, if
                        anyone should raise question.” (Source text for this notation is from the
                        paper filed in the Position Book in the <gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss>
                        files, lot 62 D 182.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Netherlands:</hi> On June 29, 1950 the Government of the
                    Netherlands informed the Secretary General of the United Nations that the
                    Netherlands Government would from the current year on no longer present a report
                    on Indonesia since the sovereignty over these territories, with the exception of
                    Netherlands New Guinea, was formally transferred to the Republic of the United
                    States of Indonesia on December 27, 1949. The note of the Government of the
                    Netherlands continued as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>… “in all probability no further report on the Netherlands West Indies
                            and Surinam will be submitted after 1950 since both these territories
                            will then have acquired an autonomous status and a full measure of
                            self-government placing them outside the scope of Chapter XI of the
                            Charter. It is, however, the intention of my Government in that case to
                            present to your Excellency a report pursuant to paragraph 2 of
                            Resolution 222 (III) of the General Assembly.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>On August 31, 1951 the Netherlands Government advised the Secretary General that
                    in the opinion of that Government, the Netherlands Antilles and Surinam have now
                    ceased to be Non-Self-Governing Territories within the meaning of Article 73(<hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Charter and that consequently the Netherlands
                    Government had decided to terminate <pb facs="1250" n="1222" xml:id="pg_1222"/>
                    the transmission concerning these territories. The Special Committee considered
                    the communication from the Netherlands Government and adopted a resolution which
                    noted the information made available by the Netherlands Government relating to
                    Surinam and the Netherlands Antilles and the fact that a conference among
                    representatives of the two territories and the Netherlands on an equal footing
                    was to be held in March 1952 to decide upon a system of cooperation for the
                    common affairs of the three countries and the establishment of a new
                    constitutional order to replace the present interim arrangement. The concluding
                    paragraph of the resolution “Takes note of the communication of the Government
                    of the Netherlands with reference to the cessation of the transmission of
                    information on these territories, and transmits this information, together with
                    its Special Committee report on General Assembly Resolution 334 (IV) and the
                    summary records relating to these questions, to the General Assembly, for any
                    necessary action.” The General Assembly decided (Resolution 568 (VI)) that in
                    1952 it should examine the communication of the Netherlands Government in the
                    light of any report prepared by the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee and
                    take into account whatever new arrangements as to common affairs may be
                    developed by the 1952 conference of representatives of the Netherlands and of
                    the Netherlands Antilles and Surinam. The resolution concludes with the decision
                    “to include in the agenda of the next regular session of the General Assembly
                    the question of the cessation of the transmission of information under Article
                        73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Charter as regards the Netherlands
                    Antilles and Surinam.”</p>
                <p>[See separate paper covering U.S. position on the question of Cessation of
                    Information on the Netherlands Antilles and Surinam]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Views of the Non-Administering Members</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The records of debates show that many non-administering members hold that the
                    General Assembly has final authority to decide, or that this authority is to be
                    exercised jointly by the General Assembly and the respective administering
                    authorities. The replies of the non-administering members who have given views
                    on the factors question are difficult to summarize. It is apparent that a
                    sincere attempt has been made on the part of these members to give careful and
                    objective consideration to the factors question. Their replies, as might well be
                    expected, reflect that they take their own particular political situations and
                    outlooks as the principal point of departure. One recurring theme of the replies
                    has been the question of the competence of the General Assembly to apply any one
                    list of factors to specific territories with the corollary that the cessation of
                    the transmission of information under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of
                    the Charter should depend on a separate investigation of each particular case.
                    Another recurring theme calls for the <pb facs="1251" n="1223" xml:id="pg_1223"
                    /> application of the principle of self-determination. It is significant that of
                    all the non-administering members which have submitted their views only Burma,
                    while agreeing that it would be advantageous to have a list of factors laid
                    down, believe strongly that the list should merely serve as a guide and not be
                    applied rigidly.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Views of the Administering Members</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The attitude of the administering authorities likewise reflects their individual
                    political situations as well as their colonial responsibilities. They all hold
                    the general view that, in the final analysis, the decision as to when a
                    territory ceases to be non-self-governing rests with the metropolitan
                    government, and that Chapter XI of the Charter does not provide the basis for
                    maintaining that the General Assembly has the power to decide the question of
                    the cessation of the application of Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) to a
                    particular territory. Some of them have even threatened to cease to participate
                    in the work of the Committee on Information from Non-Self-Governing Territories
                    and Fourth Committee work as it pertains to Chapter XI of the Charter. While
                    maintaining that the list of factors can only be of value as a guide to Members
                    responsible for transmitting information under Article 73(<hi rend="italic"
                        >e</hi>), they have participated in the discussion of this question and five
                    Members (Belgium, Denmark, France, the Netherlands, and the United Kingdom) have
                    presented detailed and constructive sets of comments for consideration by the
                        <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Special Views of Belgium:</hi>
                    <note n="9" xml:id="d823fn11">The Belgian position is set forth at length in the
                        Belgian reply to the Secretary-General, which is incorporated into <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Doc. A/AC.58/1, May 22, 1952, pp. 3–14. See
                        footnote 7, <ref target="#pg_1217">p. 1217</ref>.</note> The Belgium views
                    contain the theme upon which the Belgians have spoken for some time, namely,
                    that there exists in the Americas and Asia peoples with a lower degree of
                    civilization for whom no information has yet been transmitted. There are many
                    examples of the formal establishment through laws and decrees of a special
                    system taking into account their particular status or giving to the State some
                    form of trusteeship over such peoples. The areas in which they live may be
                    regarded as vast reservations in which they are more or less completely outside
                    the laws in force for the rest of the State. In elaborating upon this theme, the
                    Belgian Government lists, from <gloss target="#t_ILO1">ILO</gloss> publications,
                    27 Members of the United Nations who administer sizeable groups of indigenous
                    peoples concerning whom information has not been transmitted in accordance with
                    Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>). The important point is not that the
                    Belgians have now provided elaborate documentation of their theme that reporting
                    on non-self-governing peoples is incomplete. It is to be noted that previous
                    efforts on their part to expand upon this theme have been ruled out of order in
                    the Special Committee and Committee IV on the ground that such information was
                    not before the Committees for consideration. The <pb facs="1252" n="1224"
                        xml:id="pg_1224"/> important question which now arises is whether or not the
                    views submitted by Belgium are properly before the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi>
                    Committee. These are legitimate views and if the Belgians are not ruled out of
                    order, (and they have informed us that they will walk out if ruled out of order)
                    a new factor of broad significance may have to be considered by the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee and possibly the General Assembly. In
                    this connection it should be pointed out that the terms of reference of the
                    Committee on Information from Non-Self-Governing Territories which do not
                    entitle the Committee to apply a definition or list of factors to any specific
                    territory for the purpose of determining its status are not binding upon the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee.</p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Annex A</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">U.S. Position on the Factors Question for the</hi> 1950
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi> 51 <hi rend="smallcaps">Sessions of the
                            Special Committee on Information from Non-Self–Governing
                            Territories</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">[Extracted from <gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss>–630 August
                        9, 1950, S/<gloss target="#t_NSGT1">NSGT</gloss> D–37/50 revised as of
                        October 1951]<note n="10" xml:id="d823fn12">Entitled “Position Paper on
                            Resolution 334 (IV): Examination of Factors To Be Taken Into Account in
                            Deciding Whether a Territory Is or Is not a Territory Whose Peoples Have
                            not Yet Attained a Full Measure of Self-Government”; not printed. This
                            was a document of the Department of State Committee on Problems of
                            Dependent Areas; it was also serialized in a second documents series,
                            that of the Interdepartmental Committee on Non-Self-Governing
                            Territories (Department of State files, lot 54 D 5, Colonial Policy
                            Committees). Regarding the Committee on Problems of Dependent Areas, see
                                <ref target="#pg_1427">pp. 1427</ref> ff.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>In view of the complexity and importance of the problem the United
                            States Representative should favor full discussion in the plenary
                            sessions of the Committee, but may support the appointment of a
                            subcommittee once the subject has been thoroughly explored.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The United States Representative should be guided by the consideration
                            that the most desirable outcome of the discussions in the Special
                            Committee (and later in the Fourth Committee) would be a recognition of
                            the difficulty or even the impossibility of formulating either a
                            definition or a list of factors which would be presented as determining
                            in every case whether a territory is or is not “a territory whose people
                            have not yet attained a full measure of self-government”. Neither a
                            definition nor a list of factors presumably could be flexible enough to
                            take account of the complexities of constitutional forms and usages in
                            the wide variety of territories involved and at the same time specific
                            enough to be definitive.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>In the event that the Committee reaches a conclusion along the lines
                            of Recommendation 2 above the United States Representative should
                            consider seeking the co-sponsorship of a non-administering <pb
                                facs="1253" n="1225" xml:id="pg_1225"/> Member for a resolution
                            which would recommend to the General Assembly that it take note of the
                            difficulties encountered by the Special Committee, express the view that
                            it is not possible to formulate a definition or a list of factors which
                            would be determining in all cases, and invite administering Members to
                            interpret in the broadest practicable sense their obligation to transmit
                            information under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Charter on
                            economic, social, and educational conditions in non-self-governing
                            territories.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>If, however, the Committee should desire, in response to General
                            Assembly Resolution 334 (IV) to submit to the Assembly a list of“factors
                            which should be taken into account” the United States Representative may
                            agree to a list along the lines of Recommendation 5(<hi rend="italic"
                                >a</hi>) below provided the list is not presented as a definition
                            and no one factor or combination of factors is presented as determining
                            in every case the status of a territory in relation to Chapter
                            XI.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>In any discussion of the “factors which should be taken into account”
                            the United States Representative: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                                </label>
                                <item>May, as appropriate during the discussion, advance some or all
                                    of the following as factors which might be taken into account,
                                    pointing out, however, their varying degrees of significance and
                                    the difficulty of using them individually or in combination as a
                                    test: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>Whether the inhabitants of the territory are
                                            represented in the metropolitan parliament on the same
                                            basis as the inhabitants of the metropole.</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>Whether incorporation in the metropolitan area assures
                                            to the inhabitants of the territory rights and
                                            privileges equal to those enjoyed by the people of other
                                            component units of the metropole.</item>
                                        <label>(3)</label>
                                        <item>Whether the territorial legislature is locally
                                            elected.</item>
                                        <label>(4)</label>
                                        <item>The respective powers of the territorial legislature
                                            and the metropolitan legislature in relation to the
                                            territory.</item>
                                        <label>(5)</label>
                                        <item>Whether the Governor is appointed by the metropole or
                                            elected by the inhabitants of the territory.</item>
                                        <label>(6)</label>
                                        <item>Whether the ministers or heads of departments are
                                            inhabitants of the territories, and whether they are
                                            appointed by the metropole, chosen by the Governor,
                                            chosen by the majority party in the territorial
                                            legislature, or elected by the people.</item>
                                        <label>(7)</label>
                                        <item>The extent of the Governor’s veto, reserve, or decree
                                            powers.</item>
                                        <label>(8)</label>
                                        <item>Whether universal adult suffrage exists in the
                                            territory.</item>
                                        <label>(9)</label>
                                        <item>Whether the inhabitants possess metropolitan
                                            citizenship.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                                </label>
                                <item>Should oppose, as factors determining the status of
                                    territories in relation to Chapter XI, control of external
                                    affairs or eligibility for membership in the United
                                    Nations.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>If the question arises, the United States Representative should recall
                            the terms of reference of the Special Committee, which do not entitle
                            the Special Committee to apply a definition or list of factors <pb
                                facs="1254" n="1226" xml:id="pg_1226"/> to any specific territory
                            for the purpose of determining the status of that territory in relation
                            to Chapter XI of the Charter.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>If, through consultation, it appears that the United Kingdom maintains
                            its intention to seek Special Committee agreement that an administering
                            Member may invoke the phrase “subject to such limitation as security and
                            constitutional considerations may require” to cease reporting on a
                            territory which, although admittedly not fully self-governing in the
                            sense of controlling its external relations, is fully responsible for
                            its internal affairs including the economic, social, and educational
                            matters specified in Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>), the United
                            States Representative should seek informally to dissuade the United
                            Kingdom Representative from raising this point in the Special Committee
                            except insofar as he might consider it necessary to make a reservation
                            on the point on behalf of his Government.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">Extract from the discussion section of the paper dealing with
                        the distinction between self-government and independence.</p>
                    <p>There is a distinction drawn between self-government and independence in
                        Article 76 of the Charter. Since control of its external relations is
                        generally accepted as an attribute of a state, the framers of the Charter
                        meant to imply, in making the distinction between self-government and
                        independence, that a territory might be fully self-governing short of having
                        obtained control of its affairs in this sphere. Moreover, Article 76 speaks
                        of development toward self-government or independence “as may be appropriate
                        to the particular circumstances of each territory and its peoples and the
                        freely expressed wishes of the peoples concerned”, and, in Article 73(<hi
                            rend="italic">b</hi>) administering Members undertake “to take due
                        account of the political aspirations of the peoples”. Finally, the inclusion
                        of this factor as a determining factor would cast doubt on the right of a
                        territory to be considered self-governing for the purposes of Article 73(<hi
                            rend="italic">e</hi>) even if the people of the territory should choose
                        incorporation into a larger unit or a special form of relationship with the
                        metropole whereby, by mutual agreement, the metropole conducted the external
                        relations of the territory.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">See also Department of State Legal Adviser’s “Interpretation
                        of Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the United Nations Charter”
                        annexed to CDA–630.<note n="11" xml:id="d823fn13">
                            <p>Annex A of Doc. CDA–630, Aug. 9, 1950 was a 10-page document which
                                included a summary at the beginning as follows: <quote
                                    rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The question has been raised as to the meaning of the phrase
                                        “subject to such limitations as security and constitutional
                                        considerations may require” which appears in Article 73(<hi
                                            rend="italic">e</hi>) of the United Nations Charter. In
                                        particular, it has been suggested that this phrase may be so
                                        construed as to permit a Member of the United Nations to
                                        cease reporting with respect to a territory, on the ground
                                        that Changes in the territory’s status make it
                                        constitutionally inappropriate for the metropolitan state to
                                        transmit information to the United Nations under Article
                                            73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>), and, further, that the
                                        General Assembly would not be competent to review this
                                        action and pronounce upon whether such action is
                                        justifiable.</p>
                                    <p>“Examination of the pertinent provisions of the Charter, the
                                        proceedings of the San Francisco Conference, and applicable
                                        rules of international law, leads to the following
                                        conclusions: <list>
                                            <item>“1) The meaning of the phrase in question is not
                                                clear and precise, nor can the exact intent of the
                                                negotiators be ascertained. Nevertheless the San
                                                Francisco records indicate that many delegates would
                                                not have agreed to the insertion of this language in
                                                the Charter had they considered that this language
                                                could be construed so as to permit a metropolitan
                                                state to relieve itself arbitrarily and unilaterally
                                                of its reporting obligation under Article 73(<hi
                                                  rend="italic">e</hi>).</item>
                                            <item>“2) Under general rules of international law
                                                governing interpretation of treaties, it is believed
                                                that the reasonable and natural interpretation of
                                                the language in question, in the light of the
                                                general objective of Article 73, is as follows:
                                                  <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“‘the Members of the United Nations which are
                                                  administering non-self-governing territories
                                                  undertake by Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)
                                                  to report to the United Nations with respect to
                                                  economic, social and educational conditions in
                                                  such territories. This undertaking is subject to
                                                  “limitation” (in legal parlance, the term
                                                  “limitation” is used in the sense of
                                                  “qualification” or “restriction”), i.e., a Member
                                                  may qualify or limit the information transmitted
                                                  where security or constitutional considerations so
                                                  require. To <hi rend="italic">qualify</hi> or <hi
                                                  rend="italic">limit</hi> information transmitted
                                                  obviously is not substantively the same as to
                                                  withhold information absolutely. Only under the
                                                  most exceptional circumstances, such a threat to
                                                  or breach of international peace which directly
                                                  endangers the security of the territory or of the
                                                  metropolitan power, could withholding of all
                                                  information conceivably be justifiable.’</p>
                                                </quote>
                                            </item>
                                            <item>“3) It is clear that the administering Member
                                                could and would determine in the <hi rend="italic"
                                                  >first</hi> instance what security and
                                                constitutional considerations may require in
                                                connection with its reporting obligations.</item>
                                            <item>“4) In a case where an administering Member has
                                                been reporting with respect to a territory, pursuant
                                                to Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>), and ceases
                                                to report on the ground of changes in the
                                                constitutional status of such territory, the General
                                                Assembly would, and is competent to, review this
                                                action, at least to the extent of determining for
                                                itself that the territory in question is no longer a
                                                “non-self-governing” territory within the meaning of
                                                Article 73 and that consequently the administering
                                                Member has not violated its obligations under
                                                Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>). The General
                                                Assembly’s competence to do so is based upon its
                                                broad powers to discuss and recommend contained in
                                                Article 10, in conjunction with the particular
                                                provisions of Article 73.</item>
                                            <item>“5) If the General Assembly were to refer these
                                                questions to the International Court of Justice for
                                                an advisory opinion, it is believed that that
                                                tribunal would consider itself fully competent to
                                                pass upon them, since that tribunal has
                                                jurisdiction, by its Statute to “give an advisory
                                                opinion on any legal question at the request of” an
                                                authorized United Nations organ. Obviously a
                                                question involving an interpretation of a treaty, as
                                                with Chapter XI of the Charter, falls within the
                                                Court’s advisory jurisdiction under Article 65 of
                                                its Statute.” (Department of State Committee files,
                                                lot 54 D 5, “Committee Documents”)</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="1255" n="1227" xml:id="pg_1227"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Annex E</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">567 (VI). <hi rend="smallcaps">Future Procedure for the
                            Continuation of the Study of Factors Which Should be Taken Into Account
                            in Deciding Whether a Territory is or is Not a Territory Whose People
                            Have Not Yet Attained a Full Measure of Self-Government</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">The General Assembly</hi>,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Recalling</hi> that, in resolution 334 (IV) adopted on 2
                        December 1949, the General Assembly invited any special committee which
                        might be appointed on information transmitted under Article 73(<hi
                            rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Charter to examine the factors which should
                        be taken into account in <pb facs="1256" n="1228" xml:id="pg_1228"/>
                        deciding whether any territory is or is not a territory whose people have
                        not yet attained a full measure of self-government,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Having examined</hi> the report on the matter prepared by
                        the Special Committee on Information transmitted under Article 73(<hi
                            rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Charter,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Having undertaken</hi> a revision of the above-mentioned
                        factors,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Considering</hi> that the production of a more definitive
                        list of factors involves protracted and complex studies on the basis of more
                        complete information than was available in 1951, <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Decides</hi> to take as a basis the list of
                                factors drawn up at the sixth session of the General Assembly, which
                                list is annexed to the present resolution;</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Invites</hi> the Members of the United Nations to
                                transmit in writing to the Secretary-General, by 1 May 1952, a
                                statement of the views of their governments on the factors which
                                should be taken into account in deciding whether a territory is or
                                is not a territory whose people have not yet attained a full measure
                                of self-government;</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Appoints</hi> an <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi>
                                Committee of ten members comprising Australia, Belgium, Burma, Cuba,
                                Denmark, France, Guatemala, Iraq, the United States of America and
                                Venezuela, in order to carry out a further study of the factors
                                which should be taken into account in deciding whether a territory
                                is or is not a territory whose people have not attained a full
                                measure of self-government;</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Invites</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi>
                                Committee to take into account all information available, including
                                that transmitted to the Secretary-General on the reasons which have
                                led certain Administering Members to cease to transmit information
                                on certain of these territories, and to submit a report to the
                                General Assembly at its seventh regular session;</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Invites</hi> the Secretary-General to convene the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee in order that it may
                                begin its work one week before the opening of the 1952 session of
                                the Committee on Information from Non-Self-Governing
                                Territories.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>361st plenary meeting,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">18 January 1952.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex to Resolution</hi> 567 (VI) <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Factors Which Should be Taken Into Account in Deciding Whether a
                            Territory is or is Not a Territory Whose People Have Not Yet Attained a
                            Full Measure of Self-Government</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">introduction</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The territories which are covered by Chapter XI of the Charter are
                            these territories whose people have not yet attained a full measure of
                            self-government. It may be noted that the expression “self-government”
                            is qualified in the Charter by the words “full measure” in the English
                            text, <hi rend="italic">“completement”</hi> in the French text, and <hi
                                rend="italic">“plenitud”</hi> in the Spanish text.</item>
                        <pb facs="1257" n="1229" xml:id="pg_1229"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The task of the General Assembly, at present, is to indicate the
                            factors which should be taken into account in determining whether the
                            result of the advancement of the people of any given territory is such
                            that that territory has reached a stage of self-government where it
                            falls outside the scope of Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the
                            Charter.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The condition under which the provisions of Chapter XI of the Charter
                            cease to apply will be that the inhabitants of the territory have
                            attained, through political advancement, a full measure of
                            self-government. The fulfillment of this condition may be achieved by
                            various means, involving in all cases the expression of the free will of
                            the people. The two principal means are (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the
                            attainment of independence and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the union of
                            the territory on a footing of equal status with other component parts of
                            the metropolitan or other country or its association on the same
                            conditions with the metropolitan or other country or countries. The
                            extent to which the provisions of Article 73e continue to apply in the
                            case of territories which have become neither independent nor fully
                            integrated within another State but which have already attained a full
                            measure of self-government in their internal affairs is a question which
                            merits further study.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The two principal forms of political advancement mentioned in the
                            above paragraph, call for the consideration of different factors in
                            determining whether a territory has or has not reached a stage of
                            self-government where it falls outside the scope of Article 73(<hi
                                rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Charter.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Accordingly, the General Assembly lists under two separate headings
                            below the factors to be taken into account, stressing that the list
                            cannot be regarded as exhaustive or definitive, and that a single factor
                            or particular combination of factors cannot be regarded as decisive in
                            every case. Whether the peoples of a territory should be regarded as
                            having reached a stage of self-government where there is no longer any
                            obligation to transmit information should be solved in the light of the
                            conditions enumerated under either of the two headings, taking into
                            account the circumstances of each particular case, which will need to be
                            studied separately.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Nevertheless, the General Assembly considers that the essential
                            factors to be taken into account in deciding whether a
                            Non-Self-Governing Territory has attained a full measure of
                            self-government are the following: <list>
                                <label>(i)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Political advancement:</hi> Political
                                    advancement of the population sufficient to enable them to
                                    decide upon the future destiny of the territory with due
                                    knowledge;</item>
                                <label>(ii)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Opinion of the population:</hi> The opinion of
                                    the population of the Territory, freely expressed by informed
                                    and democratic processes as to the status or change in status
                                    which they desire.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="1258" n="1230" xml:id="pg_1230"/>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>These factors apply both to Non-Self-Governing Territories which have
                            achieved independence and to Non-Self-Governing Territories which have
                            freely United or associated themselves on a footing of equal status with
                            other component parts of the metropolitan or other country or countries.
                            In the latter case, however, the following factors are also essential
                            and should be taken into account: <list>
                                <label>(i)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Legislative representation:</hi>
                                    Representation without discrimination in the central legislative
                                    organs on the same basis as other inhabitants and
                                    regions;</item>
                                <label>(ii)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Citizenship:</hi> Citizenship without
                                    discrimination on the same basis as other inhabitants.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">i. factors indicative of the attainment of independence
                            or other seperate system of self-government</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">A. <hi rend="italic">General</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Political advancement:</hi> Political advancement of
                            the population sufficient to enable them to decide upon the future
                            destiny of the territory with due knowledge.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Opinion of the population:</hi> The opinion of the
                            population of the territory, freely expressed by informed and democratic
                            processes, as to the status or change in status which they
                            desire.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">International Status</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Independence:</hi> The attainment of independence by
                            the territory, or complete control over its external relations and
                            internal affairs.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Eligibility for membership in international
                                organizations:</hi> Eligibility for membership in the United Nations
                            or for membership or associate membership in other international
                            organizations; representation by delegates selected by the territorial
                            government.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">General international relations:</hi> Power to enter
                            into direct relations of every kind with other governments and with
                            international institutions, and to negotiate, sign and ratify
                            international conventions.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Voluntary limitation of sovereignty:</hi> Degree to
                            which the sovereignty of the territory is limited by its own free will
                            when that territory has attained independence or other separate system
                            of self-government.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">C. <hi rend="italic">Internal Self-Government</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Territorial government:</hi> Freedom from control or
                            interference by the government of another State in respect of the
                            internal government (legislature, executive, judiciary) and
                            administration of the territory.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Participation of the population:</hi> Effective
                            participation of the population in the government of the territory by
                            means of an adequate electoral and representative system.</item>
                        <pb facs="1259" n="1231" xml:id="pg_1231"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Economic and social jurisdiction:</hi> Complete
                            autonomy in respect of economic and social affairs.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">ii. factors indicative of the free association (whether
                            in a federal or unitary relationship) of a territory on equal status
                            with other component parts of the metropolitan or other country</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">A. <hi rend="italic">General</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Political advancement:</hi> Political advancement of
                            the population sufficient to enable them to decide upon the future
                            destiny of the territory with due knowledge.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Opinion of the population:</hi> The opinion of the
                            population of the territory, freely expressed by informed and democratic
                            processes, as to the status or change in status which they
                            desire.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Geographical considerations:</hi> Extent to which the
                            relations of the territory with the capital of the central government
                            may be affected by circumstances arising out of their respective
                            geographical positions, such as separation by land, sea or other natural
                            obstacles.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Ethnic and cultural considerations:</hi> Extent to
                            which the population are of different race, language or religion or have
                            a distinct cultural heritage, interests or aspirations, distinguishing
                            them from the peoples of the country with which they freely associate
                            themselves.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constitutional considerations:</hi> Association (<hi
                                rend="italic">a</hi>) by virtue of the constitution of the
                            metropolitan country or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) by virtue of a treaty
                            or bilateral agreement affecting the status of the territory taking into
                            account (i) whether the constitutional guarantees extend equally to the
                            associated territory, (ii) whether there are constitutional fields
                            reserved to the territory, and (iii) whether there is provision for the
                            participation of the territory on a basis of equality in any changes in
                            the constitutional system of the State.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">Status</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Legislative representation:</hi> Representation
                            without discrimination in the central legislative organs on the same
                            basis as other inhabitants and regions.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Citizenship:</hi> Citizenship without discrimination
                            on the same basis as other inhabitants.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Government officials:</hi> Appointment or election of
                            officials from the territory on the same basis as those from other parts
                            of the country.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">C. <hi rend="italic">Internal Constitutional Conditions</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Suffrage:</hi> Universal and equal suffrage, free
                            periodic elections by secret ballot, freedom of choice of electoral
                            candidates.</item>
                        <pb facs="1260" n="1232" xml:id="pg_1232"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Local rights and status:</hi> Equal rights and status
                            for the inhabitants and local bodies of the territory as enjoyed by
                            inhabitants and local bodies of other parts of the country.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Local officials:</hi> Appointment or election of
                            officials in the territory on the same basis as those in other parts of
                            the country.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Internal legislation:</hi> Complete legislative
                            automony of the territory, by means of electoral and representative
                            systems, in all matters which in accordance with the normal terms of
                            association are, in the case of non-unitary systems, not reserved to the
                            central government.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Annex F</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Extract from Position Paper Cleared for Item III,
                            A</hi>, 3 <hi rend="smallcaps">of the Agenda for the Colonial Policy
                            Discussions in</hi> 1950 <hi rend="smallcaps">Entitled “Problems in
                            Connection With the Definition of the Concept of
                            ‘Non-Self-Governing’”</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The following extract (p. 3 of the paper) deals with the question of
                        competence: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“1. The United States agrees that each administering Member has the
                                right to determine the constitutional position and status of any
                                particular territory under its sovereignty. The United States also
                                considers that the decision with a respect to specific territories
                                rests with the administering Members concerned. It is assumed that
                                administering Members and all other Members of the United Nations
                                would wish to respect any opinion or judgment handed down by the
                                International Court of Justice with respect to Chapter XI of the
                                Charter. The United States does not consider, however, that the
                                interpretation of the expressions “non-self-governing territories”
                                and “territories whose peoples have not yet attained a full measure
                                of self-government”, since they appear in the Charter, is a matter
                                for unilateral determination by individual administering Members.
                                The United States considers, therefore, that in view of Article 10,
                                the General Assembly would not be exceeding its authority in
                                discussing and attempting to define these expressions, in
                                recommending to administering Members generally the consideration of
                                any definition the Assembly might be able to arrive at, or even in
                                expressing its opinion in general terms, on the principles which
                                have guided or may guide Members in determining on which of its
                                territories it will transmit information. The United States believes
                                that the General Assembly would be unwise to recommend to individual
                                administering Members that they should transmit information on a
                                specific territory or territories.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
