<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-10-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-10-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="835" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d835">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">S/A files, lot 53 D 65, “<gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> 1952—4th Committee”</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Legal Adviser</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_TATEJB1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Tate</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Deputy Director of
                                the Office of Dependent Area Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_CARGOWI1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Cargo</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d835fn1">Sent to New York
                                for the Assistant Legal Adviser for <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MEEKERLC1">Meeker</persName>), an adviser–member of the U.S. Delegation
                                staff, who in turn transmitted it to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JESSUPPC1">Jessup</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-10-23">October 23, 1952</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>Subject:</item>
                            <item>Revision of Position Paper: “Transmission and Discussion of
                                Political Information under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)”</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>This is to confirm the conversations which members of the Legal Adviser’s
                            Office have had with you concerning the revision of the General Assembly
                            position paper, “Transmission and Discussion of Political Information
                            under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)”, (SD/A/C.4/99, October 6,
                            1952). As this paper itself indicates, it has not received final
                            clearance in the Department; and this office cannot give its clearance
                            until some modification is made in Recommendation 2 which reads: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“2. The Delegation should be guided by the view of the United
                                    States that the General Assembly is competent, under Article 10
                                    of the Charter, to discuss and make recommendations on
                                    conditions in non-self-governing territories generally,
                                    including political questions arising out of Articles 10, 14,
                                    and 73.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>This office objects to the present phrasing of this recommendation
                            because it may reasonably be implied that the United States does not
                            consider that the General Assembly has competence under Article 10 <pb facs="1311" n="1283" xml:id="pg_1283"/> to discuss and make
                            recommendations on political conditions in particular non-self-governing
                            territories. Such an implication is inconsistent with the Comment on
                            Recommendation 2 which appears upon page 5 of this position paper, and
                            is most certainly inconsistent with the United States position on the
                            items of Tunisia and Morocco which have been assigned to Committee 1.
                            Regarding the Tunisian and Moroccan questions, the United States
                            position is that the General Assembly is competent to discuss and make
                            recommendations relating to these items; and that this competence is not
                            restricted to recommendations generally, but extends to whatever type
                            recommendation the General Assembly may decide upon.</p>
                        <p>This office therefore proposes that Recommendation 2 of this paper be
                            clarified so as to reflect accurately the United States position on the
                            competence of the General Assembly, as follows: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Delete the word “generally” from the recommendation; or</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Add new language, so the text will read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“2. The Delegation should be guided by the view of the
                                            United States that the General Assembly is competent,
                                            under Article 10 of the Charter, to discuss and make
                                            recommendations on conditions in non-self-governing
                                            territories, including political questions arising out
                                            of Articles 10, 14, and 73, both generally and also with
                                            respect to particular non-self-governing
                                                territories.”<note n="2" xml:id="d835fn2">
                                                <p>The Department telegraphed the following
                                                  instruction to the Delegation on Oct. 29: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“Re: Comite 4 Political Discussions.</p>
                                                  <p>“<gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> has
                                                  decided not to complete clearance draft position
                                                  paper on transmission and discussion of polit info
                                                  under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) sent to
                                                  <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> as
                                                  SD/A/C.4/99. Question of competence <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> consider polit
                                                  questions in colonial field may not arise Comite 4
                                                  in form requiring statement US views. Question of
                                                  transmission polit info under Article 73(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) is dealt with in position
                                                  paper SD/A/277.</p>
                                                  <p>“If competence issue raised <gloss target="#t_Del1">Del</gloss> shld seek to
                                                  discourage discussion in order avert repetition of
                                                  situation precipitated Sixth <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> by Iraq draft res. If
                                                  situation arises requiring US take position on
                                                  substance of issue either in gen or specific form,
                                                  <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> shld be
                                                  consulted.” (Telegram <gloss target="#t_GADel1">Gadel</gloss> 26, Oct. 29, 1952, 4:08 p.m.,
                                                  320/10–2952)</p>
                                                  </quote>
                                                </p></note></p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>