<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-11-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-11-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="841" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d841">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Press Release No. <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>/T/244 Issued by the Secretariat of the United Nations,
                                New York, November 18, 1952.</hi><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d841fn2">Source: <gloss target="#t_ODA1">ODA</gloss> files,
                                lot 60 D 257, “<gloss target="#t_NSGT1">NSGT</gloss>: Factors,
                                etc.”</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1952-11-18">November 18, 1952</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Fourth Committee Adopts Nine-Point Resolution on
                                Factors; Recommends That</hi> 10–<hi rend="smallcaps">Member Special
                                Committee Make Further Study</hi></p>
                        <p>The Fourth (Trusteeship) Committee today recommended that a 10-member
                            special committee be set up to carry further the study on factors which
                            determine whether a territory is fully self-governing.</p>
                        <p>The recommendation of the Committee formed part of a nine-point
                            resolution which will come before the General Assembly in plenary
                            session.</p>
                        <p>The resolution represented a proposal introduced originally by Burma,
                            Cuba, Egypt, Guatemala, Iraq and Venezuela (Doc. A/C.4/L.231), to which
                            an amendment by the Dominican Republic and Peru (Doc. A/C.4/L.234) was
                            introduced. In its final form, the text incorporated amendments by
                            Argentina, Ecuador, the Netherlands, Poland and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The resolution was adopted at the close of a three-and-a-half-hour
                            session involving a 90-minute discussion of procedure and 24 separate
                            votes. The resolution was finally adopted as a whole by 34 to 12, with 8
                            abstentions. Six of the 60-member Committee were absent when the ballot
                            was taken.</p>
                        <p>The resolution asks the Assembly to: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Approve provisionally “as a guide” the factors listed in the
                                    report of the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee on Factors
                                    (Doc. A/2178).</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Consider individual cases individually, taking into account
                                    the right of self-determination of peoples.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Declare that the list of factors should in no way be
                                    interpreted to hinder the attainment of self-government.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Declare that “for a territory to be deemed self-governing in
                                    economic, social or educational affairs, it is essential that
                                    its people shall have attained a full measure of self-government
                                    as referred to in Chapter XI of the Charter.”</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Recommend that the list of factors be taken into account
                                    provisionally in cases examined by the General Assembly
                                    concerning cessation of transmission of information on
                                    territories or the obligation to transmit information.</item>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>Decide to set up a new <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> committee
                                    of 10 members with instructions to continue and carry out a more
                                    thorough study of the factors.</item>
                                <label>(7)</label>
                                <item>Invite the new committee to take into account also earlier
                                    statements by governments as well as the following “additional
                                    elements,” in relation to Chapter XI of the Charter: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>the possibility of defining the concept of
                                            self-government;</item>
                                        <pb facs="1319" n="1291" xml:id="pg_1291"/>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>the features guaranteeing the principle of the
                                            self-determination of the peoples;</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>the manifestation of the freely expressed will of the
                                            peoples.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>(8)</label>
                                <item>Invite members to transmit by 1 May 1953 a statement of their
                                    views on “the subjects contained in the terms of reference of
                                    the committee.”</item>
                                <label>(9)</label>
                                <item>Convene the committee four weeks before the opening of the
                                    next General Assembly.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The 12 members voting against the resolution as a whole were: Australia,
                            Belgium, Colombia, Denmark, France, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, New
                            Zealand, Sweden, Union of South Africa, the United Kingdom and the
                            United States.</p>
                        <p>The eight abstaining were: Canada, Dominican Republic, Greece, Israel,
                            Nicaragua, Norway, Peru and Uruguay.</p>
                        <p>The six absent when the ballot was cast were: Costa Rica, Honduras,
                            Iceland, Panama, Paraguay and Turkey.</p>
                        <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_MUOZR1">Rodolfo Munoz</persName>
                            (Argentina) announced at the close of today’s vote that the choice of
                            members to form the special committee would be made after the resolution
                            had been considered by the General Assembly.</p>
                        <p>The Committee decided, after a lengthy debate this morning, that it would
                            vote first on an amendment by Argentina (Doc. A/C.4/L.237) which
                            proposed, among other things, that provisions of an amendment by the
                            Dominican Republic and Peru (Doc. A/C.4/L.234) should be added to—and
                            not substituted for—the provisions of the six-power draft resolution. By
                            this decision, the six-power draft resolution was made the basis of the
                            Committee’s voting.</p>
                        <p>In a series of votes, the Committee then incorporated the amendments by
                            the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> (Doc. A/C.4/L.233), Poland
                            (Doc. A/C.4/L.235), Ecuador (Doc. A/C.4/L.239) and the Netherlands (Doc.
                            A/C.4/L.236), as well as amendments by Argentina and joint amendments by
                            the Dominican Republic and Peru.</p>
                        <p>During the voting, the representatives of the Dominican Republic and Peru
                            withdrew a provision of their amendment which would have the Assembly
                            take note of the report of the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee
                            on Factors.</p>
                        <p>In explanation of vote, <persName corresp="#p_GERIGOB1">Benjamin
                                Gerig</persName> (United States) stated that two theories underlying
                            the resolution had led the United States to vote against its adoption as
                            a whole. The first of these was the concept of the indivisibility of
                            autonomy, which was embodied in the resolution. The second, he said, was
                            the idea that the General Assembly was the authority which was competent
                            to decide when a territory was fully self-governing.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName>Brita Skottsberg-Ahman</persName> (Sweden) gave similar
                            reasons for her delegation’s negative vote.</p>
                        <pb facs="1320" n="1292" xml:id="pg_1292"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName>Carlos Peon del Valle</persName> (Mexico) reserved the
                            position of his delegation.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName>Enrique de Marchena</persName> (Dominican Republic) and Dr.
                                <persName>Carlos Salazar</persName> (Peru) said that their
                            delegations had abstained in the vote on the resolution as a whole
                            because of the inclusion of two paragraphs which dealt with autonomy and
                            which they could not accept.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName>Emile Najar</persName> (Israel) said he believed that the
                            Committee had not been successful in reconciling diverging views.</p>
                        <p>The Committee adjourned until tomorrow at 10: 30 a.m., when it is
                            expected to begin consideration of the Report of the Trusteeship Council
                            (Doc. A/2150).</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>