<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-08-17T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-08-17T10:00:00-05:00" n="853" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d853">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">320/8–1753: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Belgium</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Alger</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d853fn1">Repeated by Brussels for information to London,
                                Paris, The Hague, Copenhagen, Canberra, and Wellington; passed by
                                the Department of State to the Mission at the United Nations at 5
                                p.m., Aug. 17; read by <persName corresp="#p_CARGOWI1">Cargo</persName> at 6 p.m.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                <lb/><gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                                </gloss></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Brussels</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-08-17T16:00:00+01:00">August 17,
                                    1953—4 p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>127. Department telegram <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss> 161,
                            August 14. In absence Foreign Minister and Secretary General sent urgent
                            note August 15 to Foreign Office along lines reference telegram. This
                            morning I discussed note fully with Poswick, who is in charge Foreign
                            Office. He said Belgian intention to withdraw had been clearly stated in
                                <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> last December 10 and on several
                            other occasions during last two years; that Belgian <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> delegate had several days ago been
                            instructed to give formal notification which undoubtedly is being done
                            today if not sooner; that final decision on this matter was taken by
                            Foreign Minister and Minister Colonies since at any review, decision
                            could only be undertaken by two ministers concerned; and that Foreign
                            Minister will not return from vacation abroad until near end of month.
                            Poswick said Belgian representative <pb facs="1346" n="1318" xml:id="pg_1318"/> will not participate in meeting of committee
                            tomorrow, unless he attends merely to withdraw immediately.</p>
                        <p>When pressed for immediate action, Poswick said Foreign Office unable to
                            postpone implementation its decision, although it fully appreciates US
                            Government views on subject. Poswick is <hi rend="italic">Chef de
                                Cabinet</hi> to <persName corresp="#p_ZEELANDP1">Van
                                Zeeland</persName> and undoubtedly is accurate in his statement of
                            Belgian position. He admitted that after return Foreign Minister,
                            Foreign Minister and Minister Colonies may review decision, but said
                            alteration decision rather remote.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Alger</hi>
                                </persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>