<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="901" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d901">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711C.03/6–3052</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State for Congressional
                                    Relations</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McFall</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director,
                                    Bureau of the Budget</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Lawton</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d901fn1">Drafted
                                    by the Acting Officer in Charge, Caribbean Affairs
                                        (<persName>Wellman</persName>) and cleared by the Deputy
                                    Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs
                                        (<persName>Mann</persName>).</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-03">July 3,
                                    1952</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. <persName>Lawton</persName></hi>:
                                The Department of State has received your request for its views and
                                comments with respect to House Joint Resolution 430 approving the
                                Constitution of the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico which was adopted by
                                the people of Puerto Rico on March 3, 1952. The Department
                                recommends that the President approve this Joint Resolution.</p>
                            <p>The Department has supported the successive steps which have been
                                taken by the Congress and by the President, with the objective of
                                giving to the people of Puerto Rico the opportunity to organize a
                                constitutional <pb facs="1456" n="1428" xml:id="pg_1428"/>
                                Government in accordance with their own freely expressed wishes. The
                                Department took the following position before the Senate Committee
                                on Interior and Insular Affairs on May 17, 1950 with respect to S.
                                3336, “a Bill to provide for the organization of constitutional
                                government by the people of Puerto Rico”, which was enacted into law
                                on July 3, 1950: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Department of State believes it to be of the greatest
                                        importance that the Puerto Rican people be authorized to
                                        frame their own constitution as provided for in S. 3336, in
                                        order that formal consent of the Puerto Ricans may be given
                                        to their present relationship to the United States. It is
                                        believed that, with their own constitution, the high degree
                                        of internal self-government which the Puerto Ricans today
                                        enjoy in their voluntary association with the United States,
                                        will assume for them an added significance. Moreover, such
                                        action by our Government would be in keeping with the
                                        democratic principles of the United States and with our
                                        obligations under Chapter XI of the Charter of the United
                                        Nations to take due account of the political aspirations of
                                        the people in our territories and to develop self-government
                                        in them. The Department of State feels that the enactment of
                                        S. 3336 into law would have great value as a symbol of the
                                        basic freedom enjoyed by Puerto Rico, within the larger
                                        framework of the United States of America.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>On April 22, 1952 the President transmitted to the Congress for its
                                approval the Constitution which had been drafted by a constitutional
                                convention elected by Puerto Ricans and which had been approved by
                                the people of Puerto Rico by a vote of 374,649 to 82,923. The
                                President declared that the Constitution conformed fully with the
                                applicable provisions of the act of July 3, 1950 and of the
                                Constitution of the United States, that it contained a bill of
                                rights and that it provided for a republican form of Government.</p>
                            <p>The Department informed the Chairman of the Senate Committee on
                                Interior and Insular Affairs by letter dated May 13, 1952 that it
                                recommended the adoption of <gloss target="#t_SJRes1">S. J.
                                    Res.</gloss> 151 approving the Constitution of the Commonwealth
                                of Puerto Rico which was adopted by the people of Puerto Rico on
                                March 3, 1952. House Joint Resolution 430 is identical with Senate
                                Joint Resolution 151 with the addition of one exception and three
                                provisos all of which it is understood are acceptable to the Insular
                                Government of Puerto Rico.</p>
                            <p>Other governments and peoples, particularly of countries having the
                                same cultural and linguistic background as those of Puerto Rico,
                                have taken a keen interest in the relations between the United
                                States and Puerto Rico. The United States has given, in the
                                enactments which have provided an ever-increasing self-government in
                                Puerto Rico, evidence of the sincerity of its devotion to the
                                principles of self-government for dependent peoples, government by
                                the consent of the governed, democracy and freedom. The Constitution
                                of the Commonwealth <pb facs="1457" n="1429" xml:id="pg_1429"/> of
                                Puerto Rico gives Puerto Rico a status chosen and carefully worked
                                out by Puerto Ricans themselves in accordance with their own
                                conception of the needs of Puerto Rico and its relationship with the
                                United States.</p>
                            <p>The achievement of self-government by Puerto Rico will be a matter of
                                great interest to Members of the United Nations in their discussions
                                of the political progress of non-self-governing territories. It will
                                be a convincing answer to attacks by those who have charged the
                                United States Government with imperialism and colonial exploitation,
                                and it should be warmly welcomed by Members who have a sincere
                                interest in the political advancement of dependent peoples. The new
                                relationship which would be established by the approval of House
                                Joint Resolution 430 would give Puerto Rico the full measure of
                                self-government contemplated in Chapter XI of the Charter of the
                                United Nations. The people of Puerto Rico themselves have stated, in
                                a resolution adopted by their constitutional convention on February
                                4, 1952, that this compact entered into by mutual consent would mark
                                Puerto Rico’s attainment of “complete self-government”.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName><hi rend="smallcaps">Jack K. McFall</hi></persName>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>