<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chairman of the United States Atomic Energy Commission ( (Strauss) ) to
                    the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d967</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">967</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-12-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-12-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="recvFrDY7vSGKPYDH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Joint task force</term>
                    <term ref="reckO9szxNydLBID0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85003956"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Aluminum</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recOzoeUb5OaUz29X" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Laboratory</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recHACUlxTgQEpllD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture">Food production</term>
                    <term ref="rec9d4JhL8LoZOBAk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002599"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Ecological</term>
                    <term ref="recNBOveCHYDHbAqL" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="food" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-12-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="967"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d967">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.5611/12–254</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the United States Atomic Energy
                        Commission</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Strauss</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-12-02">December 2,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: In my letter dated September 30 to
                    Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SMITHWB1">Walter Bedell
                        Smith</persName>,<note n="1" xml:id="d967fn1">Not found in Department of
                        State files.</note> I noted the Commission’s interest in an expeditious
                    settlement of the problems arising from the use of certain locations in the
                    Marshall Islands for the conduct of nuclear experiments. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SMITHWB1">Smith</persName>, in his letter of September 11,
                    forwarding copies of letters received from Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_LODGEHCJ1">Lodge</persName> and Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SEARSM1">Mason Sears</persName>, had requested that the
                    Commission inform the Department of State of the steps being taken to carry out
                    the commitments made by the U.S. Government to the Marshall Islanders affected
                    by the Pacific tests. In my interim letter to Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SMITHWB1">Smith</persName> I stated that the Commission would
                    prepare a detailed reply on this subject.</p>
                <p>In the recent meetings of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Trusteeship
                    Council the United States gave assurances that it would take every precaution to
                    prevent the recurrence of casualties as a result of fallout such as occurred
                    following the March 1 experiment. As you know, immediately following that test,
                    which was the first of the Castle series, the warning area around the test site
                    was greatly enlarged. A warning area of similar scope will certainly be
                    established in any future experiments conducted in the Pacific Proving Grounds.
                    You may be assured that the Commission is determined that no repetition of such
                    an accident shall occur.</p>
                <p>As Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SEARSM1">Mason Sears</persName> has recorded in his
                    letter to you of July 23, a copy of which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SMITHWB1"
                        >Smith</persName> forwarded to the Commission with his letter of September
                    11, there are two outstanding problems which relate to compensation to the
                    Marshall Islanders as the result of Pacific test activities. The first of these
                    concerns compensation due the inhabitants of Bikini, who were displaced in 1946.
                    In respect to this aspect of the problem a Memorandum of Understanding is now
                    being negotiated between the Departments of Navy and Interior under the terms of
                    which use and occupancy agreements will be negotiated between the Department of
                    the Navy and the Government of the Trust Territory for the use of Bikini and
                    Eniwetok atolls by the Atomic Energy Commission. The Commission has authorized
                    the Department of Navy to represent the Commission in these negotiations. As
                    presently visualized the agreements for the use of Bikini and Eniwetok, when
                    completed, will provide for lump sum payments to the Government of Trust
                    Territory from funds appropriated by the Congress to the Department of the Navy.
                    These payments will enable the Government of Trust Territory to compensate the
                    Bikinians. The Commission has <pb facs="1561" n="1533" xml:id="pg_1533"/> been
                    advised that the Department of the Navy is continuing the negotiations with the
                    Department of Interior, and it is our hope that this aspect of the compensation
                    matter can be finally discharged in the near future.</p>
                <p>The second aspect of this problem refers to the promises made to compensate the
                    Rongelap and Uterik people for damages resulting from the March 1 fallout. The
                    Department of Defense, under authority derived from the Foreign Claims Act, has
                    agreed to consider and settle these claims. It should be noted, however, that
                    such claims must be presented within one year after the occurrence of the
                    incident out of which the claim arises. The Commission is not aware that any
                    claims from the people of Rongelap and Uterik have yet been received.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d967fn2">Marginal notation by <persName>C. Dudley Withers</persName>
                        of the Office of Dependent Area Affairs states: “Interior
                            (<persName>Yeomans</persName>) says deadline has been brought to
                        attention of those affected. CDW 12/16/54”. <persName>William
                            Yeomans</persName> was an officer in the Interior Department’s Office of
                        Territories.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Immediately after the March 1 fallout, it was deemed necessary, as you know to
                    remove the natives of Rongelap and Uterik to Kwajalein for medical observation
                    and care. The natives received the finest medical attention available. It soon
                    became apparent that the natives of Uterik had not been exposed to dangerous
                    amounts of radioactive fallout and they were returned to their native homes,
                    under living conditions equivalent to or better than those existing before their
                    evacuation. Continued medical attention was given, however, to the natives of
                    Rongelap who had received significant amounts of radioactive contamination.
                    Because of residual radioactivity on Rongelap, it was deemed wise to resettle
                    the Rongelapians on another atoll until the activity had decayed to a safe
                    level. These people have therefore been temporarily housed on the island of Ejit
                    in Majuro Atoll. Housing was constructed for them under supervision of an <gloss
                        target="#t_AEC1">A.E.C.</gloss> contractor, using funds supplied by Joint
                    Task Force 7. These houses, of plywood with aluminum roofs, have been so
                    constructed as to make it possible to remove them to the natives’ original home
                    when it is safe for them to return.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile the Atomic Energy Commission has accepted the responsibility for
                    continued medical examinations of the natives of Rongelap as a routine
                    precautionary measure. The first medical recheck has just recently been
                    completed and was conducted for the Commission by medical teams from the Naval
                    Medical Research Institute and the Navy Radiological Defense Laboratory. The
                    preliminary report of these medical teams has been reviewed in the Commission
                    and reveals that no permanent impairment of the natives’ health is to be
                    expected. A further medical recheck will take place probably around February
                    1955 and further checks will be made thereafter.</p>
                <pb facs="1562" n="1534" xml:id="pg_1534"/>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_AEC1">A.E.C.</gloss> has also accepted the responsibility
                    for such periodic resurveys of Rongelap and the collection of biological
                    specimens and soil samples as may be necessary to determine the earliest
                    possible time when the natives may be safely returned to their homes. The first
                    such resurvey is presently being planned and it is expected that it will be made
                    within the next two months. It is still the Commission’s view that the residual
                    level of radioactivity will decay to insignificance and the natives will be
                    returned to their homes by May 1955.</p>
                <p>You will be interested in two further programs which the Commission is
                    considering in order to improve the living conditions of the Marshall
                    Islanders.</p>
                <p>Acting on a suggestion made originally by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MIDKIFFFE1"
                        >Midkiff</persName>, then High Commissioner of the Trust Territory of the
                    Pacific Islands, the Commission has agreed to bear the cost of constructing an
                    island communication system between Kili and Jaluit and the construction of
                    family housing units on Jaluit which will enable the Bikinians on Kili to fish
                    in the lagoon at Jaluit. It is planned that the actual construction will be
                    supervised by <gloss target="#t_AEC1">A.E.C.</gloss> contractor personnel and
                    paid for from <gloss target="#t_AEC1">A.E.C.</gloss> funds.</p>
                <p>The Commission’s Division of Biology and Medicine, in cooperation with the Trust
                    Territory and the University of Hawaii, is investigating the possibility of
                    undertaking certain agricultural programs to increase food production for the
                    people on Kili and Majuro and for the Marshall Islands generally. The objective
                    is to provide the islanders displaced from their homes by the Pacific
                    experiments with a satisfactory ecological environment. This project, in which
                    the Commission is deeply interested, would have an importance to the Marshallese
                    far beyond the alleviation of distress arising from the conduct of nuclear
                    experiments.</p>
                <p>I hope that the information which is set forth in this letter will place the
                    Department in the position to deal effectively with any charges which may be
                    made in the United Nations discussions or elsewhere concerning our test
                    activities in the Trust Territory.</p>
                <p>Inasmuch as the responsibility for carrying out the commitments made to the
                    Marshall Islanders are shared with the Commission by the Department of Defense
                    and the Department of Interior, I have taken the liberty of sending copies of
                    this letter to Secretary <persName>Wilson</persName> and Secretary
                        <persName>McKay</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d967fn3">In a letter of Dec.
                        29, 1954, Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KEYDMK1">Key</persName>,
                        writing in the name of the Secretary of State, informed Admiral
                            <persName>Strauss</persName> saying that the information which the
                        Commission had furnished would enable the Department to deal effectively
                        with any charges which might be made in the Trusteeship Council or
                        elsewhere, (letter, <persName corresp="#p_KEYDMK1">Key</persName> to
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEARSM1">Sears</persName>, Dec. 30, 1954,
                        711.5611/12–3054) Non-Self-Governing Territories.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lewis Strauss</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
