<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 466.Mr. Beardsley to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d160</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">160</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1872-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-12-12T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-12-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1872-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="160" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d160">
                <head>No. 466.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RB1" type="from">Beardsley</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Agency and
                                        Consulate-General of the United States in
                                        Egypt</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1872-12-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 12, 1872</date>. (Received January 27,
                                1873.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 46.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Recurring to my last dispatch, No. 45,
                            detailing an interview with His Highness the Khedive, I have the honor
                            to report in continuation of the same interview the substance of His
                            Highness’s remarks concerning the future railway development of
                            Egypt.</p>
                <p>His Highness considers that the railway system of Lower Egypt is
                            sufficiently extended for the present, and that sound policy dictates
                            that the resources of the country should now be devoted to the work of
                            extending the railway into Upper Egypt and Nubia.</p>
                <p>It is desirable that Port Saïd, Damietta, and Rosetta should be connected
                            with Alexandria by a coast line; but that is a project of secondary
                            importance. With Suez, Ismailia, Zagazig, and Mansoorah brought into
                            close connection with Cairo and Alexandria, the Delta of Egypt is
                            sufficiently supplied with commercial arteries to meet the demands of
                            the hour. Egypt’s mission, His Highness thinks, is to civilize Africa by
                            pushing up through the valley of the Nile, and overflowing Nubia and the
                            Soudan. To do this the railway system of Upper Egypt must be completed,
                            and communication established with those countries.</p>
                <p>The railway is now finished to Roda, 180 miles south of Cairo. It is
                            proposed to complete the line to Assouan at the first cataract, and
                            thus, with a few side branches to the several oases, make the railway
                            system of Egypt proper complete.</p>
                <p>From Assonan to the second cataract it is estimated that, owing to
                            engineering difficulties, the expense of a railway would be £4,000,000
                            sterling. This sum His Highness considers to be more than the resources
                            of Egypt will at present bear, and it is proposed to establish
                            water-communication between those two points by transporting the Nile
                            steamers over the first cataract by means of a marine railway, the
                            expense of which will be insignificant compared with either the expense
                            of the railway to the second cataract or with locks at the first
                            cataract. This work His Highness thinks will be completed in four years
                            from this date.</p>
                <p>From the second cataract the railway will again commence and run to
                            Khartoum, from whence it will eventually be carried on one branch to
                            Dongola, and the other to Massowah on the Red Sea.</p>
                <p>To reach Massowah by rail the territory of Bogos must be crossed: It thus
                            appears that the occupation of Bogos by the Egyptian government looked
                            toward the completion of the railway system of Egypt <pb facs="0494" n="1124" xml:id="pg_1124"/> rather than to the invasion of
                            Abyssinia, and was a preliminary step toward bringing all the territory
                            tributary to the Upper Nile within the pale of Egyptain authority, as
                            indicated in my dispatch No. 19 of October 16.</p>
                <p>To accomplish this it is not necessary that Abyssinia should be
                            disturbed, and His Highness disavows all wish or intention of molesting
                            her; conscious that in developing the resources of his own territory he
                            has a difficult and arduous work to perform, which will sufficiently
                            task all his energies, without the political embarassments which an
                            invasion of Abyssinia would entail.</p>
                <p>On this as well as former occasions His Highness emphatically asserted
                            that Bogos has been Egyptian territory since the time of Mehemet Ali,
                            and that in taking possession of it he was only asserting rights which
                            had lain dormant since the time of Saïd Pasha, during whose reign the
                            Egyptian forces were withdrawn owing to causes brought about by French
                            influence exerted in favor of certain Catholic missionaries, to protect
                            whom the government of Saïd Pasha was not disposed to wage an internal
                            warfare. The history of Bogos for the last forty years appears not to be
                            well known here, but I see no reason to doubt the statements of His
                            Highness; and I believe Prince Kassa, of Abyssinia, has no good reason
                            for apprehending an invasion of his territory.</p>
                <p>If I have devoted more time and space to this subject than its merits
                            would seem to warrant, it is because it has been a subject of
                            considerable discussion here, as well as in Europe, where the idea seems
                            to prevail that the Khedive is bent upon the annexation of
                            Abyssinia.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RB1">R. BEARDSLEY</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
