<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-09-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="234" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d234">
                                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JCBD1" type="from">Davis</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KvS1" type="to">Schlözer</persName></hi>.</head>
                                        <opener>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-09-18"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 18,
                                                1873</date>.</dateline>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your note of the 15th
                                            instant, relative to the case of Leopold Ungar, has been
                                            received. It seemed so obvious that the main purpose of
                                            your previous note, of the 8th instant, was to obtain
                                            possession of <pb facs="0685" n="1315" xml:id="pg_1315"/> the valuables in the possession of one Twiney, the
                                            English lawyer, that the Department deemed itself
                                            justified in assuming that you wished the consul-general
                                            of the United States at Alexandria to be instructed, to
                                            cause the valuables to be surrendered, especially as
                                            Twiney was said to hold them subject to his order. It
                                            seems, however, that your principal object was to induce
                                            this Department to decide that Ungar is not a citizen of
                                            the United States. In reply, I again have to express my
                                            regret that it is not deemed either expedient or
                                            competent to make any such decision in such case. This,
                                            however, does not arise from any disposition to deprive
                                            German subjects of their rights to the valuables
                                            adverted to. The consul-general of the United States at
                                            Alexandria will consequently be directed not to allow
                                            any control which he may have over those articles as the
                                            property of a countryman to interfere with the just
                                            claims of others thereto. Accept, sir, a renewed
                                            assurance of my very high consideration.</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_JCBD1">J. C. B.
                                                  DAVIS</persName>.</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                    </body></text></TEI>