<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-01-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="26" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                    <head>No. 332.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Schuyler</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the
                                    United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">St.
                                Petersburg</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-01-08"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 8, 1873</date>.
                            (Received February 7.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 50.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am now in a position to inform you more
                        exactly of the details of the negotiations between England and Russia, of
                        which I spoke in my dispatch No. 43.</p>
                    <p>It appears that Mr. <persName>Forsyth</persName> was sent here in 1869, by
                        the British government, to endeavor to come to some arrangement with the
                        Russian government with regard to the extent of their conquests in Central
                        Asia and their ultimate limit. After some negotiation it was agreed that so
                        long as Russia respected the boundaries of Afghanistan, or rather the
                        dominion of the Emir of Cabul, Shere Ali Khan, for so long the Indian
                        government would restrain Shere Ali Khan from attacking or interfering with
                        Russia. It was at first proposed that the dominions of Shere Ali Khan should
                        be considered those which he inherited from his father, Dost Mohammed Khan,
                        but an additional condition was made that they should be now in Shere Ali’s
                        actual possession.</p>
                    <p>This result was come to without much difficulty; but when the question arose,
                        What are the provinces which the Shere Ali received from Dost Mohammed, and
                        of which he has actual possession? there were divergencies of opinion, and
                        especially with reference to Badakhshan and Vakhan. It was finally decided
                        to refer this question to General Kaufmann, the Russian governor-general of
                        Turkestan, who, being near the spot, could have access to more accurate
                        sources of knowledge. General Kaufmann having made no report, and a note
                        addressed by Sir Andrew Buchanan, the British embassador here, to Prince
                        Gortchacow in November, 1871, remaining without a satisfactory answer, Earl
                        Granville, in a dispatch dated October 17, 1872, informed Lord Augustus
                        Loftus, the present British embassador, of this state of facts, and stated
                        further that, having heard nothing more from the Russian cabinet, the
                        British government had used its own methods of investigation, and had come
                        to the conclusion that Badakhshan and Vakhan were part of the dominions of
                        Shere Ali left to Mm by Dost Mohammed, and that the northern boundary of
                        Afghanistan begins at Lake Sari-kul, the source of the river Payja, the main
                        branch of the Amu-Darya or Oxus, runs thence along the river Payja to its
                        confluence with the Koktchas, and thence along the Oxus or Amu-Darya to
                        Khodja-Sala, and thence southwesterly to a point at or near Puli-Hatun, on
                        the well-known Persian boundary, including Meimana and two or three other
                        disputed provinces. Earl Granville further said that the Indian government
                        had communicated this conclusion to the Emir of Cabul, and had informed him
                        that he might consider himself at liberty to defend himself in case the
                        territories south of this line should be invaded by Russia. Lord Augustus
                        Loftus was instructed to communicate this dispatch to the Russian
                        government.</p>
                    <p>The reply of the Russian government consists of a dispatch from Prince
                        Gortchacow to Count Brunnow, the Russian embassador at London, dated
                        December 7–19, 1872, inclosing a report by General Kaufmann and another by
                        Colonel Struve, who had been delegated by him to study the question.</p>
                    <p>Prince Gortchacow, after referring to a previous dispatch on the same subject
                        of the preceding year, speaks of a desire of the imperial government to have
                        nothing but the most frank and cordial relations and explanations with the
                        British cabinet, and of the advantage it will be to <pb facs="0139" n="769" xml:id="pg_769"/> both powers that their relations in Central Asia be
                        placed on the firm footing of a mutual good understanding. He then excuses
                        General Kaufmann for not reporting sooner, on the ground of the disturbed
                        relations of the countries in Central Asia, and the fact that it is
                        impossible to obtain accurate information except from persons who are on the
                        spot 5 and that lie has not wished to send agents to Badakhshan, even on a
                        scientific mission, for fear that his action might be misinterpreted by the
                        British cabinet as well as by the native government. The Prince then refers
                        to the reports by General Kaufmann and Colonel Struve for such information
                        as they have been able to gather on the facts of the case. As to the
                        provinces on the northwest frontier of Afghanistan, as they are separated
                        from Russia by large desepts and wastes, he will waive any question and will
                        accept the English assertion that they belong to Afghanistan, but he denies
                        that Badakhshan and Vakhan are now in the actual possession of Shere Ali
                        Khan, or were inherited by him from Dost Mohammed Khan.</p>
                    <p>It is true, the Prince says, that Dost Mohammed on one occasion interfered
                        iii the affairs of Badakhshan in consequence of an intrigue in the family of
                        the reigning Emir, and for a money consideration supported one claimant
                        against the other and maintained him on the throne 5 but the Prince soon
                        refused to pay the money, and Dost Mohammed was unable to enforce its
                        collection. He never occupied Badakhshan by his troops, nor maintained
                        officers there. In the same way, in 1867, Shere Ali was called in by Mahmud
                        Shah, the nephew of Jahandar Shah, the reigning Emir. Jahandar Shah was
                        deposed and Mahmud Shah put in his place, who promised to pay a yearly sum
                        of money to the Afghans. This payment he has now refused to make, and the
                        Afghans, though much stronger in the point of actual force, have been unable
                        to collect, and exercise no authority of any kind in Badakhshan. Jahandar
                        Shah, who had taken refuge in Shagnan, is now intriguing with the Afghans to
                        be reinstated, and promises, in his turn, a tribute in recompense. This
                        information was obtained from a former minister of the Emir of Balkh, an
                        Afghan feudatory. There is nothing to show that Vakhan is a feudatory of
                        Badakhshan, as it neither pays tribute nor supports officials, and it is
                        certainly not an Afghan dependency.</p>
                    <p>Since this dispatch of Prince Gortchacow, which, with the inclosures was
                        communicated to Earl Granville, there has been no new exchange of notes
                        between the two governments, but Count Schouvaloff, the director of the
                        secret police, has gone to London on a mission connected with this
                        question.</p>
                    <p>I can only add that the geography and political condition of Badakhshan and
                        Vakhan are inshrouded in the deepest darkness, and hardly two geographers
                        agree on the subject.</p>
                    <p>As I stated in my previous dispatch, the question of Khiva is officially
                        ignored by the British cabinet. In the mean time the Russians are pushing
                        their preparations for an active campaign, partly in consequence of the
                        disagreeable intelligence that 15,000 Khivans are roving over the steppes
                        between the Caspian and Aral Seas, plundering the friendly Kirghiz and
                        exciting them to rebellion, and threatening the forts on the Emba, and even
                        Orenburg itself, and the post-road to Tashkent. General Kaufmann, who will
                        have chief command of the expedition, is still here, and will not leave
                        before the 20th January. He is waiting to consult with the Grand
                            <persName>Duke Michael</persName>, who is expected shortly. The
                        expedition will consist in all of about 9,000 men and 40 guns, and will be
                        divided into three columns: one starting from Kramovodsk, on the Caspian,
                        will go direct to Khiva by the nearest route across the steppe; one will <pb facs="0140" n="770" xml:id="pg_770"/> go along the old caravan-road from
                        Orenburg, and the third, under General Kaufmann in person, will proceed from
                        fort No. 1, on the Syr Darya through the country east of the Aral Sea. Each
                        will carry its provisions, forage, &amp;c. They will probably start about
                        the middle of March. The Grand Duke Nicholas, son of Constantine, will take
                        part in the expedition.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName>EUGENE SCHUYLER</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>