<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>B.—Extracts from the analytical index to the treaties of the United States
                    with other powers, showing what privileges are conferred upon aliens in the
                    United States by treaties..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d301</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">301</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="301"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                <head>B.—<hi rend="italic">Extracts from the analytical index to the treaties of the
                        United States with other powers, showing what privileges are conferred upon
                        aliens in the United States by treaties</hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-volume-rules" calendar="gregorian"
                            notAfter="1873-12-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                            notBefore="1873-11-05T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>* * * * * * *</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Asylum</hi>:</p>
                <p>vessels and citizens seeking asylum by reason of stress of weather to be treated
                    with humanity, and shall be allowed to repair and depart—Bolivia, Brazil,
                    Columbia, (New Grenada,) Ecuador, France, (obsolete,) Guatemala, Hayti, Mexico,
                    Morocco, (as to United States vessels,) Netherlands, (obsolete,) Nicaragua,
                    Portugal, Prussia, San Salvador, Sardinia, Spain, Sweden, (see Sweden and
                    Norway.)</p>
                <p>to be exempt from the payment of duties on vessel or cargo unless entered for
                    consumption—Hawaiian Islands, Morocco, (as to American vessels,) Sardinia.</p>
                <p>to be subject to no duties or charges except pilotage, unless remaining longer
                    than forty-eight hours in port—Columbia, (New Grenada.)</p>
                <p>unloading and reloading not to be considered an act of commerce—Sardinia, Two
                    Sicilies.</p>
                <p>vessels seeking asylum to be treated as national vessels—Sardinia, Two
                    Sicilies.</p>
                <p>shelter shall not be given in ports of one power to enemies of the other power
                    who have captured prizes from the other at sea—France, Great Britain.</p>
                <p>consulates not to be used as asylum—Germany, Italy.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aubaine, Droit de</hi>: [See <hi rend="italic">“Personal
                        property,” “Real estate.”</hi>] abolished by treaty with Bavaria, France,
                    (obsolete,) Hesse, Nassau, Saxony, Würtemberg.</p>
                <p>* * * * * * *</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Détraction, Droit de</hi>:</p>
                <p>abolished by treaty with Bavaria, France, (obselete,) Hanover, Hanseatic
                    Republics, Hesse, Nassau, Saxony, Spain, Würtemberg, Sweden.</p>
                <p>* * * * * * *</p>
                <pb facs="0786" n="1416" xml:id="pg_1416"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Personal Property</hi>:</p>
                <p>citizens of each, in the country of the other, may own personal property, and may
                    dispose of it by gift, will, or in any other way, and may take such property by
                    gift, purchase, will, or sueeesssion, paying only such dues as the inhabitants
                    of the country would pay in such case—Austria, Bavaria, Bolivia, Brazil,
                    Brunswick, and Luneburg, Columbia, (New Grenada,) Costa Rica, Dominican
                    Republic, Ecuador, France, Guatemala, Hanover, Netherlands, (obsolete,)
                    Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Mexico, Oldenburg, Hanseatic Republics, Hawaiian Islands,
                    Hayti, Hesse-Cassel, Honduras, Italy, Nassau, Nicaragua, Orange Free State,
                    Paraguay, Portugal, Prussia, Russia, San Salvador, Sardinia, Saxony, Spain,
                    Swiss Confederation, Two Sicilies, Würtemberg.</p>
                <p>citizens of each in the country of the other may own and succeed as above, and on
                    removal of the property it shall be exempted from all duty called “Droit de
                    détraction”—France, (obsolete,) Sweden. [See “<hi rend="italic">Sweden and
                        Norway</hi>].”</p>
                <p>in case of the absence of persons who would be entitled to personal property so
                    situated on the death of the owner, the property shall receive the same care
                    which would be bestowed upon the property of a native—Austria, Bavaria,
                    Brunswick, and Luneburg, Dominican Republic, Hanover, Hawaiian Islands, Hayti,
                    Hesse-Cassel, Honduras, Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Nassau, Orange Free State,
                    Prussia, Russia.</p>
                <p>in case of the absence of persons who would be entitled to personal property so
                    situated on the death of the owner, the property shall receive the same care
                    which would be bestowed upon the property of a native—Continued. Sardinia,
                    Saxony, Spain, Swiss Confederation, Two Sicilies, Würtemberg.</p>
                <p>disputes as to the inheritance of such property shall be decided by the courts of
                    the country where the property is situated—Austria, Brunswick and Luneburg,
                    Dominican Republic, Hanover, Hawaiian Islands, Hayti, Hesse-Cassel, Honduras,
                    Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Nassau, Orange Free State, Prussia, Russia, Sardinia,
                    Saxony, Spain, Swiss Confederation, Two Sicilies, Würtemberg.</p>
                <p>* * * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Real estate</hi>:</p>
                <p>citizens and subjects of each nation are to be on the footing of the most
                    favored</p>
                <p>nation in the territories of the other—Italy.</p>
                <p>citizens of each country may dispose of real estate in the territories of the
                    other by will, donation, or otherwise—France, (obsolete,) Bavaria, Colombia,
                    (New Granada,) San Salvador, Two Sicilies.</p>
                <p>their heirs, legatees, and donees, being citizensvor subjects of the other
                    contracting party, may succeed to their real estate—Bavaria, Colombia, (New
                    Granada,) France,</p>
                <p>(obsolete,) San Salvador, Two Sicilies.</p>
                <p>citizens of each country may dispose of real estate in the territories of the
                    other, where the laws of the state in which it is situated permit it to be
                    done—Nicaragua,</p>
                <p>Swiss Confederation.</p>
                <p>citizens of each country may possess real estate in the territories of the other,
                    and dispose of it in the same manner as citizens can—France, San Salvador.</p>
                <p>the United States are to recommend states where this is not permitted, to pass
                    laws to allow it; and France reserves the right of establishing reciprocity.</p>
                <p>where, on the death of the owner, real estate in the territories of the one power
                    descends upon a citizen of the other, who is disqualified by alienage from
                    taking, he shall be allowed two years to sell the land and withdraw the
                    proceeds—Austria, Bavaria, Hesse, Nassau, Saxony, Würtemberg.</p>
                <p>he shall be allowed three years—Brazil, Ecuador, Guatemala, Hanseatic Republics,
                    Swiss Confederation.</p>
                <p>he shall have the longest period allowed by law—Bolivia, Dominican Republic.</p>
                <p>he shall be allowed the time allowed by the law of the state or country—Brunswick
                    and Luneburg, Nicaragua, Orange Free State, Portugal, Russia, Swiss
                    Confederation.</p>
                <p>he shall be allowed a reasonable time—Hanover, Hawaiian Islands, Portugal,
                    Prussia, Russia, Sardinia, Spain, Mecklenburg-Schwerin.</p>
                <p>the time allowed may be prolonged by the government in whose territories the land
                    is situated—Austria, Hesse, Nassau, Saxony, Würtemberg.</p>
                <p>the tax or dues charged on the succession or withdrawal is to be the same as that
                    imposed upon natives—Austria, Bavaria, Bolivia, Brazil, Brunswick, and Luneburg,
                    Colombia, (New Granada,) Dominican Republic, Ecuador, France, Nicaragua, Orange
                    Free State, Portugal, Russia, San Salvador, Sardinia, Swiss Confederation, Two
                    Sicilies.</p>
                <p>such tax or dues to be the same as imposed upon the most favored nation—Hawaiian
                    Islands.</p>
                <p>there shall be no duties of detraction—Bavaria, France, Guatemala, Hanover,
                    Hanseatic Republics, Hawaiian Islands, Saxony, Spain, Prussia.</p>
                <pb facs="0787" n="1417" xml:id="pg_1417"/>
                <p>the property of absent heirs is to receive the same care as if it were the
                    property of</p>
                <p>citizens—Austria, Bavaria, Hesse, Nassau, Saxony, Two Sicilies, Würtemberg.</p>
                <p>all disputes relating to such real estate must be settled before the courts of
                    the</p>
                <p>country—Bavaria, Hesse, Nassau, Orange Free State, Saxony, Swiss
                    Confederation,</p>
                <p>Two Sicilies, Würtemberg.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Reciprocal privileges of citizens of each nation within the
                        territories of the other</hi>:</p>
                <p>the citizens of each may reside in the territories of the other, remaining
                    subject to the laws—Argentine Confederation, Austria, Bolivia, Brazil, Colombia,
                    (New Granada,) Costa Rica, Denmark, Dominican Republic, Ecuador, Great Britain,
                    (obsolete,) Greece, Guatemala, Hanover, Hawaiian Islands, Hayti, Honduras,
                    Italy, Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Oldenburg, Mexico, Nicaragua, Portugal, Prussia,
                    Russia. San Salvador, Sardinia, Sweden and Norway, Swiss Confederation, Two
                    Sicilies, Liberia.</p>
                <p>the citizens of each may reside in the territories of the other—Borneo.</p>
                <p>vessels and effects of citizens of each in the territories of the other are to be
                    protected and defended—Sweden, (see Sweden and Norway,) Tunis.</p>
                <p>citizens of each being within the territories of the other shall be exempt from
                    forced military service—Argentine Confederation, Costa Rica, Dominican Republic,
                    France, (obsolete,) Hawaiian Islands, Hayti, Honduras, Italy, Mexico, Nicaragua,
                    Orange Free State, Paraguay, Switzerland, Two Sicilies.</p>
                <p>from billeting of soldiers—Two Sicilies.</p>
                <p>from contribution in kind or money for compensation for personal military
                    services —Italy, Two Sicilies, [they shall <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be exempt
                    from such contribution—Orange Free State, Swiss Confederation.]</p>
                <p>from forced loans—Argentine Confederation, Bolivia, Costa Rica, Dominican
                    Republic, Hawaiian Islands, Honduras, Nicaragua, Paraguay, Two Sicilies.</p>
                <p>from military exactions—Argentine Confederation, Costa Rica, Dominican Republic,
                    Hayti, Honduras, Nicaragua, Paraguay.</p>
                <p>from contributions—Bolivia, Nicaragua.</p>
                <p>from contributions in time of war, in which case property is not to be taken
                    without compensation paid in advance—Nicaragua; without compensation on the same
                    footing as natives—Orange Free State.</p>
                <p>from extraordinary contributions not general and established by law—Hawaiian
                    Islands, Two Sicilies.</p>
                <p>from contributions higher than those paid by natives—Costa Rica, Dominican
                    Republic, Hayti, Honduras, Mexico, Orange Free State, Paraguay.</p>
                <p>from judicial or municipal office—Italy.</p>
                <p>the citizens of each shall not be liable to the embargo or detention of their
                    vessels, cargoes, merchandise, or effects—Bolivia, Brazil, Colombia, (New
                    Granada,) Ecuador, Guatemala, Italy, Mexico, Netherlands, (obsolete,) San
                    Salvador, Spain, Swe-” den, Tunis; without compensation—Bolivia, Brazil,
                    Colombia, Ecuador, Guatemala, Italy, Mexico, San Salvador; to be paid in
                    advance—Bolivia; when it can be agreed upon—Italy.</p>
                <p>their vessels are to be subjected to such embargo only in cases of urgent
                    necessity, and an equitable indemnity shall be paid—Prussia.</p>
                <p>their books and papers are not to be subjected to inspection without the order of
                    a competent legal tribunal—Bolivia, Hawaiian Islands, Hayti, Two Sicilies.</p>
                <p>the citizens of each country are to have a right to travel in the possessions of
                    the other—Bolivia, Hawaiian Islands, Italy, Nicaragua, Two Sicilies.</p>
                <p>citizens of each residing in the territories of the other may intermarry with
                    natives</p>
                <p>—Nicaragua.</p>
                <p>may enjoy freedom of religious belief, respecting at the same time the laws and
                    usages of the country—Brazil, Bolivia, China, Ecuador, Guatemala, Hawaiian
                    Islands, Hayti, Netherlands, (obsolete,) Colombia, (New Granada,) Paraguay,
                    Argentine Confederation.</p>
                <p>and also of religious worship, on conditions as named in the respective
                    treaties—(as to consuls and agents,) Algiers, (obsolete,) Argentine
                    Confederation, Colombia, (New Granada,) Costa Rica, Dominican Republic,
                    Honduras, Mexico, Nicaragua, Paraguay, San Salvador, Sweden, (see Sweden and
                    Norway.)</p>
                <p>they are to have the liberty of burial—Argentine Confederation, Brazil, Bolivia,
                    Colombia, (New Granada,) Costa Rica, Dominican Republic, Ecuador, Guatemala,
                    Hayti, Honduras, Netherlands, (obsolete,) Nicaragua, Mexico, Poraguay, San
                    Salvador, Sweden, (see Sweden and Norway.)</p>
                <p>on the breaking out of a war between the two countries, the citizens of each in
                    the country of the other may remain and continue to trade so long as they behave
                    peaceably—Argentine Confederation, Paraguay, Great Britain, (obsolete.)</p>
                <p>all may remain whose occupations are for the common benefit of mankind—Italy,
                    Prussia.</p>
                <pb facs="0788" n="1418" xml:id="pg_1418"/>
                <p>six months are granted to merchants and citizens to arrange their busines and
                    with. draw their effects—France, (obsolete,) Dominican Republic, Hayti, Two
                    Sicilies</p>
                <p>* * * * * * *</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Succession</hi>:</p>
                <p>the dues are to be the same as those paid by natives—Denmark, German Empire</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
