<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-03-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="94" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d94">
                    <head>No. 400.<lb/><hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_DES1" type="from">Sickles</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps"> United States
                                    Legation in Spain</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-03-30"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 30, 1873</date>.
                            (Received April 23.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 566.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On Tuesday last, pursuant to appointment, I
                        had a conference with the minister of state and his colleague of the
                        colonial office respecting several pending questions.</p>
                    <p>In reply to a reference made by myself at the outset to the case of Santa
                        Rosa, Mr. <persName>Castelar</persName> informed me that he was released,
                        and he had received an expression of your thanks, through Admiral
                            <persName>Polo</persName>, for the action of the Spanish government in
                        the matter. Mr. <persName>Sorni</persName> added, that the release of this
                        person was his first official act after entering the colonial department.
                        Mr. <persName>Castelar</persName> said the omission to acquaint me with the
                        action of the government, in reply to my note of the 2d ultimo, must be
                        attributed solely to his pre-occupation in the assembly and in the cabinet
                        council.</p>
                    <p>Passing to the subject of embargoed estates in Cuba, Mr.
                            <persName>Castelar</persName> stated, in reply to a preliminary inquiry,
                        that he had not received from his predecessor any explanation of the
                        question. Having recapitulated the origin and bases of our reclamations and
                        the course of the negotiations which had taken place, I presented two
                        propositions for the consideration and action of the Spanish government, as
                        follows: <list>
                            <item>First. That the embargoes, so far as they affected the property of
                                citizens of the United States, were violations of the seventh
                                article of the treaty of 1795, which expressly forbids all
                                embargoes, and also because the property was seized by the arbitrary
                                act of the executive authorities, thus depriving the owners of the
                                right to a judicial hearing and judgment expressly guaranteed by
                                treaty.</item>
                            <item>Second. That the reference of these reclamations to the mixed
                                commission sitting in Washington was a dilatory and inadequate
                                remedy, and that in all cases in which evidence had been presented
                                showing that the claimants were citizens of the United States the
                                right to the immediate restitution of their estates was clear and
                                unquestionable.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Having explained the arrangement made with Mr. <persName>Martos</persName>
                        before his resignation, by which the pending cases were referred for
                        immediate action to the Spanish minister at Washington and the
                        captain-general of <pb facs="0330" n="960" xml:id="pg_960"/> Cuba, I stated
                        that your reasonable expectation of a satisfactory result from this
                        disposition of the matter had been disappointed, since no action had been
                        taken, and no reason had been assigned for the continued delay; and I added
                        that some of these cases had been pending more than two years, that the
                        embargoes in certain instances had been so improvidently ordered that the
                        property of one party had been seized for the alleged offense of another,
                        arid that in another case the promised restitution was impeded by the
                        refusal of one branch of the administration in Cuba to furnish evidence
                        demanded by the bureau having the matter of these embargoed estates in
                        charge. Under these circumstances, and in view of the vexatious character of
                        these proceedings, I urged the prompt action of the government of the
                        republic in releasing all property of American citizens now held by the
                        Cuban authorities in violation of the treaty of 1795 and of the law of
                        nations.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Castelar</persName> took notes of the essential points of my
                        statement, and promised to inform himself of the purport of my several
                        communications addressed to his predecessor with reference to this class of
                        reclamations; and he added that I might assure you of his desire and purpose
                        to remove at once any just ground of complaint on this subject.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Sorni</persName>, on his part, repeated the same assurance, and
                        remarked that he would acquaint himself with the state of the question so
                        far as his department was concerned, and see that no unnecessary delay
                        should happen in the disposition of the pending cases.</p>
                    <p>I then suggested for the consideration of ministers that great abuses had
                        been committed in the matter of embargoes; that, as a war measure, they had
                        done more harm than good to the government; that the practice of seizing
                        large properties by executive order on mere rumor, and often on the
                        suggestion of persons inimical to the owners, had swelled the ranks and
                        increased the resources of the insurgents, and that the proceeds of these
                        estates had been so manipulated as to demoralize and enfeeble the
                        administration of affairs in Cuba. In view of these, and other like
                        reflections, I pointed out the expediency of a general measure restoring all
                        estates confiscated by arbitrary decrees, and confining any future
                        sequestrations that might be deemed necessary to the regular and authorized
                        action of the established judicial tribunals.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Sorni</persName>, who is a lawyer of distinction, replied that
                        both in a legal and administrative aspect there were serious grounds to
                        question the justice and utility of these proceedings, and it was his
                        intention to make this matter the subject of a special instruction to the
                        captain-general of Cuba.</p>
                    <p>Referring to the correspondence that had taken place respecting the
                        complaints of our shipmasters and merchants on account of the unreasonable
                        tines and exactions imposed on American vessels in Cuba, I begged the
                        attention of the colonial minister to this subject.</p>
                    <p>His excellency kindly promised that it should not escape his notice.</p>
                    <p>I then remarked that with a radical change in the administration of Cuba and
                        Porto Rico it would not be difficult to avoid, for the future, a repetition
                        of the numerous questions that had arisen during the past four years between
                        the United States and Spain; that now, more than ever, the Government and
                        people of the United States would be disposed to cultivate the most friendly
                        relations with this country; that it rested with the government of the
                        republic, by means of simple justice to its American possessions, to deprive
                        the insurrection of its hold upon public sympathy; that with the abolition
                        of slavery, the reform of the administration in Cuba and Porto Rico, and the
                        concession to the people of a proper share in the management of their local
                        affairs, the motives which <pb facs="0331" n="961" xml:id="pg_961"/> had
                        incited the war of independence would disappear; that the commerce and
                        intercourse between the United States and those islands created legitimate
                        interests in their welfare to which no government could be indifferent, and
                        these were the surest guarantees of the sincerity and disinterestedness of
                        our counsels; that if we desired to acquire those possessions we would not
                        be heard appealing to the sense of justice of the mother country for a
                        milder and more conciliatory rule in Cuba and Porto Rico, since it would be
                        for our advantage if Spain continued to provoke them to hatred and sedition;
                        that if it were true that whatever contributed to alienate the affections of
                        the Creole population from Spain must facilitate and hasten a separation,
                        nothing could better serve the supposed desire of the United States to
                        possess these islands than the past policy of Spain in holding a large
                        portion of the people in absolute servitude and the remainder in a qualified
                        condition of caste which could not increase their desire for a change of
                        allegiance; that the large emigration which annually leaves Galicia and the
                        Asturias for South America would naturally flow towards Cuba and Porto Rico,
                        thus increasing their wealth and strengthening their loyalty, if emigration
                        were not repelled from the Spanish possessions by slavery and its kindred
                        contempt for the laboring classes; that heretofore the irreconcilable
                        antagonism between American institutions and the system of Spanish rule in
                        their colonies in the Gulf, had been a constant source of perturbation in
                        the otherwise congenial relations between the two countries; that now this
                        conflict between self-government and despotism ought to cease with the
                        extension of free institutions to all in the Spanish Empire; that the
                        establishment of a republican form of government seemed to afford the best,
                        and perhaps the last, opportunity of regaining the attachment of the Cubans;
                        that any considerable delay in putting in force the milder policy of
                        republican rule in those parts of the island, at least where the peaceful
                        condition of the population invited conciliatory measures, might confirm the
                        belief of the people that all parties in Spain were disposed to treat them
                        as an inferior race not entitled to the rights belonging to Spaniards; that
                        nothing had contributed more to increase the sympathy felt in America for
                        the Cuban insurgents than the fact that the Spanish revolution of 1868
                        brought no alleviation of the wrongs of Porto Rico nor of the eastern and
                        western departments of Cuba, whose loyalty remained unshaken; that so soon
                        as Cuba and Porto Rico were treated on an equal footing as an integral part
                        of the republic, enjoying the same liberties and laws and free institutions
                        established in the peninsula, the insurgents would no longer find
                        encouragement in American opinion, and any attempt on the part of European
                        powers to deprive the Spanish possessions in the Gulf of Mexico of a
                        republican form of government might justly be regarded as an inadmissible
                        interference with rights entitled to our consideration and respect; and that
                        for these reasons, justice, patriotism, and self-defense commended the
                        inauguration of a republican policy in the Spanish Antilles.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Castelar</persName> replied that the executive duties incident
                        to the late change of government had so engrossed the attention of ministers
                        since the formation of the present cabinet that it had been impossible to
                        give due consideration to the important questions to which I referred; that
                        I would nevertheless find in the well-known views of himself and his
                        colleagues ample guarantees of their disposition to do ample justice to Cuba
                        and Porto Rico. A great step had been taken in the unanimity and good
                        feeling with which the emancipation act for the latter island had been
                        enacted; in the execution of the act of 1870, the government that very day
                        had ordered the liberation of more than ten thousand slaves (<hi rend="italic">emanciados</hi>) <pb facs="0332" n="962" xml:id="pg_962"/>
                        in Cuba, a measure which he trusted would be regarded by the United States
                        as a proof of the sincere purposes of this government; that the superior
                        offices in Cuba and Porto Rico would be at once confided to eminent and able
                        men, distinguished for their liberal opinions and enjoying the confidence of
                        the republic; that the Cortes Constituyentes, clothed with plenary authority
                        and animated by the most advanced ideas of the epoch, could not fail to
                        sweep away the remains of the traditional policy of the old monarchy; that
                        with the abolition of slavery, the existence of which could not be
                        prolonged, the governments of Cuba and Porto Rico must be essentially
                        modified, since the system of servile labor had been unhappily the
                        unavoidable basis of arbitrary rule; that meanwhile the government would do
                        all in its power to prepare the way for the inauguration of republican
                        institutions in the Antilles; and with respect to their intercourse with the
                        United States, with whom, as a sister republic and a loyal ally, Spain
                        desired relations of intimate confidence and friendship, I could not doubt
                        his sincerity when he assured me that nothing would be wanting on his part
                        to promote the most cordial and satisfactory understanding between Spain and
                        America.</p>
                    <p>With reference to the intimation given me by his excellency of an immediate
                        change of governors in Cuba and Porto Rico, I suggested that the matters I
                        had brought to his notice might conveniently be made the subject of fresh
                        instructions to the personages now to be appointed; and I expressed the hope
                        that in addition to the particulars already pointed out these instructions
                        would include the cases of American citizens when arrested and confined in
                        prison, in order that they might be allowed to communicate freely with the
                        nearest United States consul, and obtain the advice and assistance proper to
                        their situation. And in conclusion I remarked that it might be well to
                        furnish the captain-general of Cuba with a copy of the seventh article of
                        the treaty of 1795 as his guide in the questions of embargoes and in the
                        treatment of citizens of the United States who might have occasion to claim
                        the protection of the ordinary judicial tribunals for their persons and
                        property.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Sorni</persName>, the minister of the colonies, replied that in
                        preparing the instructions to be given to General
                            <persName>Pieltain</persName> and <persName>Primo de Rivera</persName>,
                        my suggestions would not be forgotten.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName corresp="#p_DES1">D. E. SICKLES</persName>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>