<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 401.General Sickles to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1873p1v2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1873-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1873-03-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85105939"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Poverty</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1873-03-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1873-03-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="95"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d95">
                <head>No. 401.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_DES1" type="from"
                            >Sickles</persName> to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF1" type="to"
                            >Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation in Spain</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-03-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 30, 1873</date>. (Received April
                        23.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 567.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to forward herewith, for your
                    perusal, a translation of an appeal to the nation, published by the executive
                    under date of the 25th instant. The Carlists have lately given a character to
                    their hostilities, which is not too strongly denounced by the government.
                    Repeated instances of cruelty to captives, barbarous acts of violence to
                    non-combatants, from which even women and children are not always exempt, firing
                    on railway trains with their passengers, burning depots, stations, dwellings,
                    and even churches, are among the authenticated reports of outrages committed by
                    the partisans of the pretender. Some <pb facs="0333" n="963" xml:id="pg_963"/>
                    of these guerrilla bands are led, and most of them are attended by priests, who
                    incite their adherents to all sorts of crimes by appeals to the religious
                    fanaticism common to the population of the Pyrenees. It seems inevitable, in
                    view of these occurrences, that Spain is again to suffer the scourge of a war of
                    extermination, like that which disgraced modern civilization in the dispute
                    between the eldest daughter of Ferdinand VII and his nephew for the succession
                    to the throne.</p>
                <p>It is said that, in deference to repeated remonstrances made by this government,
                    the French authorities have promised to exercise more vigilance on the frontier
                    in preventing the use hitherto made of their territory as a base of operations
                    for the Carlists forces. The headquarters of the Prince have been for some time
                    established in the French Pyrenees. It is supposed that he has about ten
                    thousand men under arms in Spain, and if more equipments are obtained, as is
                    probable from the proceeds of subscriptions made in Paris and London, the
                    strength of the insurgents may be considerably increased.</p>
                <p>I am. &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DES1">D. E. SICKLES</persName>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Appendix.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Address of the Executive Power of the Spanish Republic to
                            the Nation.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the executive power to the nation</hi>.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Spaniards</hi>: The government elected by the vote of
                        the Cortes, whose choice has received the assent of the nation, would deem
                        itself unworthy of its high charge and unfit for the responsibility it
                        assumes if it disguised the truth, however hitter the truth may he, with
                        palliatives only fit to deceive communities worn with debility or sunk in
                        hopeless impotence.</p>
                    <p>And this truth, this fact, is that the partisans of absolutism, who took
                        arms, as their proclamations averred, to overthrow a foreign king, have
                        still persisted in their stubborn rebellion even after the nation, by the
                        proclamation of the republic, has entered upon the full exercise of its own
                        rights and has thereby asserted its sovereignty, to which all parties are
                        bound to yield.</p>
                    <p>In vain is the fullest liberty accorded to ideas of every stamp; in vain is
                        the ballot-box open to the free vote of every citizen; in vain does the
                        approaching electoral verdict of the people secure the government of the
                        nation to a majority of its citizens. The royalists, well knowing that the
                        younger generations, nurtured and brought up in the ideas of the age, will
                        never voluntarily accept their rule through the channels of freedom and of
                        law, now seek to subjugate them forcibly by fire and steel.</p>
                    <p>To do this they are destroying the means of communication, cutting the
                        telegraphs, laying waste the fields, imposing forced tribute upon the
                        villages, burning the town archives, committing highway robbery, immolating
                        helpless and defenseless creatures, shooting those who surrender after
                        heroically resisting their bands, and amidst the smoke of their burnings
                        they respond to the birth of a republic of reconciliation and peace with the
                        awful spectacle of a restoration of the eras of war and vengeance.</p>
                    <p>The time has come for the Spanish nation to realize with ripe judgment the
                        vast extent of the evil, and to apply, with its traditional heroism, a
                        prompt and powerful remedy. The holy war of liberty should respond to the
                        barbarous war of tyranny. The government, though weighed down by the gravity
                        of passing events, will not cease in its efforts to ward off the dangers
                        that menace public order, to restore discipline in the army, and to arm the
                        volunteers of the republic. The soldiers of Catalonia are already in the
                        field attacking the enemies of freedom. The brave and well-disciplined army
                        of the north has sealed with its blood, on heroic fields of battle, its
                        loyalty to the republic. The troops in Valencia know no repose. The roving
                        bands in Andalusia are disheartened and are surrendering under the
                        formidable attacks that meet them on every side. And wherever the rebellion
                        has sought to effect a rising in the remaining provinces, it has been
                        combated and annihilated by the people and the troops in happy unison.</p>
                    <p>Fully appreciating this gallant conduct, the government is untiring in its
                        efforts to unite all possible means and forces. The resources voted by the
                        Cortes for the nationa armament are being made effective as rapidly as the
                        laws will allow. The advantage <pb facs="0334" n="964" xml:id="pg_964"/>
                        inuring to the army by the recent reforms are being realized with all the
                        zeal and dispatch permitted by the poverty of the treasury. The free corps
                        now being formed will be put in the field as rapidly as circumstances will
                        permit. The military and civil authorities of the province most severely
                        ravaged, fully realize the gravity of the situation, and are resolved to
                        meet open warfare with open warfare, without truce and without quarter.</p>
                    <p>But republican governments need the co-operation of all their citizens,
                        without exception, if the social structure is to be in reality
                        self-governing. Each citizen should be brought to know that in defending the
                        republic lie defends his own moral dignity and his own inalienable rights.
                        The liberal parties should remember that their highly-prized liberty—that
                        liberty for which they have made so many sacrifices—is indissolubly united
                        to the forms of republicanism. Let no means of warfare be spared, even as
                        none were spared in our civil war. Let the citizen militia be put on a war
                        footing; let the free corps be armed; let our citizens arm to maintain
                        public order and protect their hearths and homes, in order that our soldiers
                        may be free to fall with force and vigor upon the rebellion bands. Thus
                        alone can we show our title to the liberty held in store for the nations who
                        redeem and save themselves by their own strength. Thus only, and by most
                        heroic efforts, can we save the republic, and, with the republic, our
                        liberties and our country.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1873-03-25">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 25, 1873</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>ESTANISLAUS FIGUERAS</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">President of the Government of the
                                        Republic</hi>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>EMILIO CASTELAR</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister of State</hi>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>NICOLAS SALMERON</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister of Grace and Justice</hi>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>JUAN ACOSTA</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister of War</hi>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>FRANCISCO PI <hi rend="smallcaps">y</hi>
                                        MARGALL</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister of Interior.</hi>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>JUAN TUTAN</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister of the Treasury</hi>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>JACOBO OREYRO</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister of Marine</hi>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>EDUARDO CHAO</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister of Public Works</hi>.</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>JOSÉ CRISTOBAL SORNI</persName>,<lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister of the Colonies.</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
