<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-08-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-08-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="176" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                        <head>176. Intelligence Note Prepared in the Bureau of Intelligence and
                                Research<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d176fna">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1970-1973, SOC 11-5 <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss>.
                                Confidential. Drafted by John J. Donovan (<gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/SGR).</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d176fn2">Intelligence note on the
                                problem of drug abuse to be considered at a special <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> meeting in Geneva.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-08-04">August 4, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                        <pb facs="d176-01" n="1" xml:id="d176-01"/>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>: PROBLEM OF DRUG ABUSE TO BE
                            CONSIDERED AT SPECIAL MEETING IN GENEVA</p>
                        <p>Due largely to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> initiative, a special
                            session of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>’s Commission on
                            Narcotic Drugs (<gloss target="#t_CND1">CND</gloss>) will begin in
                            Geneva on September 28, 1970. This session, which was unanimously
                            approved by the Economic and Social Council (<gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss>) on July 24, is to consider short- and long-term
                            policy recommendations for international action against drug abuse and
                            to prepare a report to the 25th General Assembly, which meets this fall.
                            In addition to focusing international attention on the drug problem, now
                            reaching epidemic proportions, the <gloss target="#t_CND1">CND</gloss>
                            meeting may also take some of the heat out of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> discussions with Turkey over opium production in that
                            country. The Turkish Government has recently been accused by its
                            domestic critics of “selling-out” to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                “pressure.”<note n="1" xml:id="d176fn1">* See RNAN-21 “Turkey: Opium
                                Poppies-Reaping and Weeping Ahead,” July 17, 1970</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Takes Initiative</hi>. Feeling
                            that the alarming increase in drug abuse is becoming a danger to all
                            nations, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> took the initiative in
                            the current <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> session to assure
                            that the problem would be discussed <pb facs="d176-02" n="2" xml:id="d176-02"/> at the 25th General Assembly. A <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> resolution approved in <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> calls for international action in
                            three principal areas: (a) illicit traffic (establishing effective
                            national and international enforcement machinery); (b) illegal
                            production (stopping narcotic raw materials by all means); and (c)
                            demand (reducing the illicit demand for drugs by means of treatment,
                            rehabilitation, and education programs). Both the Turks and the Indians
                            at first opposed the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> proposal.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Indian Objections Pro-forma</hi>. India, which is
                            the largest opium-producing country but also has the most stringent
                            controls over illegal channels, appeared to be concerned that the <gloss target="#t_CND1">CND</gloss> meeting would be used as a forum to
                            advocate the complete elimination of opium production. Actually,
                            however, Indian reservations were based on India’s opinion that the
                            industrialized countries have managed to impose strict controls in the
                            poppy-producing countries while refusing to accept equally strong
                            controls on synthetic substances, which could be an even greater menace
                            to the developing world. India agreed to go along after minor changes in
                            the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> draft.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Turks are Sensitive</hi>. The Turkish observer
                            suggested amendments reflecting the Turkish Governments concern that the
                                <gloss target="#t_CND1">CND</gloss> would focus on illicit opium
                            production in Turkey. The Turks were assured that the term “drug abuse”
                            was not restricted to narcotic drugs, and Turkish objections were
                            satisfied by additions to the resolutions preamble.</p>
                        <p>During the discussions, however, the Turkish observer made quite clear to
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> officials his governments “serious
                            concern” over the manner <pb facs="d176-03" n="3" xml:id="d176-03"/> in
                            which the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Government was handling the
                            opium-production problem in Turkey, stating that <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> was treating the Turkish Government “like a small
                            African country”. Ankara’s sensitivity to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> “pressure” stems from Turkish domestic criticism on the
                            opium issue, which followed Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Demirel</persName>’s decree of June 38 announcing that areas in
                            which poppies may legally be cultivated will be reduced from nine to
                            seven provinces in 1971 and to four provinces by the 1972 spring
                            harvest. The decree is a set-back to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                            efforts, which were aiming for a complete ban on opium cultivation by
                            1971. The subsequent reporting in the Turkish press of speeches and
                            alleged comments by <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> officials critical
                            of Turkey’s handling of the opium issue has had an adverse impact upon
                            Ankara’s dealing with Washington.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Prospects</hi>. The <gloss target="#t_CND1">CND</gloss> discussions may serve to help Turkish Prime Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Demirel</persName> domestically by
                            demonstrating to his critics that illicit opium-production is of serious
                            concern not only to the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> but to the
                            world. International consideration of the problem may have some effect
                            also in conveying to many Turks that their country’s role in world
                            affairs will be measured in part by the cooperation Turkey gives to
                            international efforts to curb the opium traffic.</p>
                        <p>While it is doubtful that the special meeting will produce any dramatic
                            results, it will serve to focus world attention on the seriousness of
                            the problem. For the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> the meeting
                            represents a welcome alternative <pb facs="d176-04" n="4" xml:id="d176-04"/> means of action because of the disappointing
                            results of the bilateral discussions with Turkey, which is the source of
                            an estimated 80 per cent of the heroin entering the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> annually(Mexico accounts for 15 per
                            cent). The meeting may also give the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                            an opportunity to announce its proposal that the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> undertake pilot project on narcotics control, for which
                            the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> would make a special financial
                            contribution.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>