<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>257. Memorandum From Robert M. Behr of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d257</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">257</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec5leqjXNtlx0kjy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space">Space cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="257"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d257">
                <head>257. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_BCRM1" type="from">Robert M.
                        Behr</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to"
                        >Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d257fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 393, Subject
                        Files, Space Programs, 1971. Limited Official Use. Sent for action.
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote the following
                        note on the first page: “OK-Put on agenda with <persName corresp="#p_DEEJ1"
                            >David</persName>. Should see him soon.” The note was dated March 18.
                        Attached at Tab A but not published was a copy of telegram 774 from
                        Brussels, March 6.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d257fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BCRM1">Behr</persName> pointed out to Kissinger the
                        difficulties of carrying on political negotiations on European participation
                        in a post-Apollo program of space cooperation when that program had been
                        neither defined nor fully approved within the U.S. Government.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-03-16"
                        >March 16, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>Post-Apollo Space Cooperation</item>
                </list>
                <p>Minister <persName corresp="#p_LT1">Lefevre</persName> has sent <persName
                        corresp="#p_JUA1">Alex Johnson</persName> a letter (Tab A) requesting <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> views on a number of areas relating to
                    post-Apollo space cooperation. These areas include (1) technical opportunities
                    open to European space industry, (2) management and financial arrangements, (3)
                    access to technical data, and (4) the availability of US launch services for
                    European payloads.</p>
                <p>Once the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> views are made known, the governments
                    of the member countries of the European Space Conference will, according to
                        <persName corresp="#p_LT1">Lefevre</persName>, take a decision on the
                    question of collective European participation in the post-Apollo program. This
                    should occur “during the next few weeks”.</p>
                <p>We have gotten ourselves into a peculiar position where we are negotiating
                    formally (and stiffly) at a political level over a specific program (the Space
                    Transportation System) which has within our own government neither been fully
                    defined nor fully approved. Not only is the venue awkward but the pace seems to
                    have been set by the “Red Queen”—faster and faster with scant hope for true
                    progress. We are, in fact, facing the danger that in our negotiations what now
                    may be noted as misunderstandings could soon turn into deep seated and
                    destructive bitterness.</p>
                <p>We should shift gears and look at the whole program more reflectively.</p>
                <p>To do this there is a first requirement to somehow accommodate the legitimate
                    short-term objective of Europeans with regard to a regional telecommunications
                    satellite. If we are satisfied that the system they propose will not function to
                    the detriment of <gloss target="#t_INTELSAT1">INTELSAT</gloss>, we should
                    develop a formulation which will assure them that the satellite will be launched
                    without their having to go to the expense of developing a European launch
                    vehicle. We could then address the longer term aspects of post-Apollo
                    cooperation at a pace that is not driven by immediate tactical needs.</p>
                <p>State is prepared to take this approach. Before answering <persName
                        corresp="#p_LT1">Lefevre</persName> Secretary <persName corresp="#p_IJNII1"
                        >Irwin</persName> will send over for consideration a paper originating with
                    the Ad Hoc Group formed by the Under Secretaries Committee in response to <pb
                        facs="d257-02" n="2" xml:id="d257-02"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 72 (Space Cooperation). The regular
                    membership of the Group will be expanded to include those agencies such as OTP
                    and <gloss target="#t_FCC1">FCC</gloss> whose views must be obtained to insure
                    balance. The paper will not seek to lock us in to program decisions, but instead
                    to suggest an approach whereby a program of beneficial cooperation with the
                    Europeans can evolve.</p>
                <p>I expect you will want to issue an <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> in
                    response to the recommendations of the Under Secretaries Committee. In
                    anticipation of that action, I believe you should consider an approach to
                    post-Apollo cooperation that is somewhat skewed from what has been our course to
                    date.</p>
                <p>A strong argument can be made that we ought to broaden our perspective and to
                    think in terms that encompass more than the space shuttle. Accepting the premise
                    that cooperation with the Europeans should be, to the extent possible, mutually
                    beneficial, several points need to be mentioned regarding a program that is
                    oriented along a single vector—the space shuttle.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>-- European cooperation should not ride or fall on their decision with
                        respect to the shuttle. The program currently lacks the definition necessary
                        to provide a sound basis for decision, and other programs could have
                        considerable promise for both partners.</item>
                    <item>-- Europe may not be prepared to operate effectively as an integrated team
                        member in the shuttle development. As a consequence there could be program
                        delays and unanticipated <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> costs.</item>
                    <item>-- The shuttle is really nothing more than a truck. The payoffs in
                        technological advancement and scientific knowledge lie in the space station
                        and its experiment modules. These modules could be developed incrementally
                        in accordance with an agreed European priority, or individually as each
                        nation evaluates its own requirements.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In summary, while not discouraging the Europeans from participating in the
                    shuttle development, we could conceivably evolve a more satisfactory pattern of
                    cooperation by suggesting that they focus more on payload and less on the launch
                    vehicle.</p>
                <p>A. way to test the water would be to explore the concept with <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> Science Minister <persName corresp="#p_LH6"
                        >Leussink</persName> when he comes here in April. He is very interested in
                    the post-Apollo program. You may wish to discuss this idea with Ed <persName
                        corresp="#p_DEEJ1">David</persName> when you meet on 18 March.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">RECOMMENDATION</hi>:</p>
                <p>That you discuss with Dr. <persName corresp="#p_DEEJ1">David</persName> the
                    possibility of broadening European interests in post-Apollo cooperation by
                    suggesting other attractive avenues as alternatives to the space shuttle.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
