<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-04-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="279" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d279">
                        <head>279. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1" type="from">Rogers</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d279fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970-73, SP 10
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Limited Official Use. Drafted
                                by Pollard and <persName>Packard</persName>.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d279fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> called President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s attention to the
                                negative attitudes developing within the U.S. Government toward
                                European participation in the post-Apollo program, and the need for
                                prompt U.S. decisions.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-04-29">April 29, 1972</date>.</dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Post-Apollo Relationships with the Europeans</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I wish to bring to your attention my increasing concern about developing
                            U.S. attitudes toward European participation in the development of the
                            post-Apollo Space Transportation System and the need for prompt U.S.
                            decisions in this matter, if we are to control the play of events.</p>
                        <p>Your name has been closely identified with U.S. efforts over the past
                            several years to encourage European participation in the development of
                            that System—the Shuttle, the Tug and associated research applications
                            modules (<gloss target="#t_RAM1">RAM</gloss>s) Tom Paine, alluding
                            repeatedly to what he described as your views, visited each major
                            European capital to invite such participation. In October of 1970 and
                            again in February 1971 <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Alex
                                Johnson</persName> and a sub-cabinet team met with the European
                            space and science Ministers. These and other activities of responsible
                            U.S. officials, including our Ambassadors, have provided the Europeans
                            every reason to believe that the U.S. was seriously interested in having
                            them participate in the development of certain parts of the Shuttle, in
                            one or more, of the <gloss target="#t_RAM1">RAM</gloss>s, and especially
                            in the Tug. As an indication of their interest the European governments
                            have already spent or committed a total of $11.5 million on preliminary
                            technical studies.</p>
                        <p>The European space and science Ministers are scheduled to meet in three
                            weeks (May 19th) to formulate their views with respect to participation,
                            and again in early July to take a final position. We can expect a visit
                            of a high-level European delegation shortly after the May meeting.</p>
                        <p>Within the last several months U.S. views that we should minimize
                            European participation have begun to harden. These views hold that we
                            should not permit European participation in development of the Shuttle
                            because of domestic economic considerations and the difficulties of
                            sharing such a task with foreign governments and subcontractors. With
                            respect to the Tug they hold that the development task will be too <pb facs="d279-02" n="2" xml:id="d279-02"/> difficult technically to
                            rely on European performance. European participation would thus be
                            limited to development of one or more of the <gloss target="#t_RAM1">RAM</gloss>s.</p>
                        <p>Were the European share of Shuttle development to be truly substantial,
                            these economic and management considerations might well be overriding.
                            However, the extent of their possible participation is now limited to a
                            few specific projects totaling about $100 million out of the total
                            Shuttle program costing $5.15 billion. The advantages of denying their
                            participation at this level do not justify the loss of U.S. integrity
                            abroad.</p>
                        <p>There is no need to reverse our position now on European development of
                            the Tug, since it is a very advanced project which will require several
                            more years of design study. The Europeans areas yet not convinced that
                            they should undertake it.</p>
                        <p>My basic worry is that we <hi rend="italic">will</hi> buy more trouble
                            with the Europeans than can be justified by the ephemeral domestic
                            advantages that we <hi rend="italic">may</hi> gain by denying their
                            participation. To limit them now to development of only a <gloss target="#t_RAM1">RAM</gloss> would be judged by them as a clear
                            reversal of our previous policy. Your reputation as a consistent
                            advocate of international cooperation in space and specifically with
                            Europe on the post-Apollo program would inevitably suffer. Furthermore,
                            we ought not to ignore altogether the very real political values that
                            would result from European participation with us in the development as
                            well as the use of the Space Transportation System.</p>
                        <p>Balancing all these considerations, I suggest: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>That we accept, but not encourage, European participation in
                                    the tasks in the development of the Shuttle already identified
                                    by <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> conditioned on a prior
                                    commitment by the European Space Conference (<gloss target="#t_ESC1">ESC</gloss>) that it will undertake the
                                    subsequent development of one or more <gloss target="#t_RAM1">RAM</gloss>s.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>That we bring the Europeans to agree that consideration of
                                    their undertaking the development of the Tug will be deferred
                                    pending further mutual study.</item>
                                <pb facs="d279-03" n="3" xml:id="d279-03"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>That we conduct negotiations on these matters so as to avoid
                                    indicating a major change in our policy toward European
                                    participation (i.e. in the proposals which we have already made
                                    to the <gloss target="#t_ESC1">ESC</gloss>.)</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>I urge that you approve this course of action in principle and instruct
                            me to reach agreement with the Europeans along these lines.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">William P. Rogers</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>