<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-07-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="345" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d345">
                        <head>345. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d345fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967-69, POL 33-5. Limited
                                Official Use. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Pollack</persName> and approved in <gloss target="#t_J1">J</gloss>. The conversation was held in <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName>’s office. For the seabed
                                principles proposed by the United States at the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Ad Hoc Committee to Study the
                                Peaceful Uses of the Sea-Bed and the Ocean Floor Beyond the Limits
                                of National Jurisdiction, see <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                                Document A/AC.135/25 (June 28, 1968).</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d345fn2">Executive Branch
                                representatives discussed with Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Henry</persName> “Scoop” Jackson differences and concerns about
                                Law of the Sea issues. All agreed on the need for a moratorium on
                                seabed boundary claims. The Interior department reserved its
                                position regarding the U.S. negotiating stance on seabed boundary
                                issues in upcoming negotiations at the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1969-07-07">July 7,
                                1969</date>.</dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item>Seabed Principles</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS:</head>
                            <item>Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Henry M.
                                Jackson</persName>;</item>
                            <item>Jerry T. Verkler, Staff Director Senate Committee on Interior and
                                Insular Affairs;</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_NGW1">Warren Nutter</persName>, Assistant
                                Secretary of Defense;</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Russell E. Train</persName>, Under
                                Secretary of Interior;</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GB2">Boyd Gibbons</persName>, Special
                                Assistant to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName>;</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis Johnson</persName>, Under
                                Secretary for Political Affairs;</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Herman Pollack</persName>, Director,
                                International Scientific and Technological Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Approximately three weeks ago Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> requested a meeting with Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> following the oral insistence
                            of Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> that the
                            Department of Interior would have to reserve its entire position on
                            seabed principles pending consultation with the Senator. The meeting
                            took place this morning in Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName>’s office.</p>
                        <p>Almost at the outset of the conversation Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> asserted that under the Geneva
                            Convention, there is no definition of a boundary and concurred in Under
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>’s statement
                            that there is a need to draw a line. Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> observed that until the character
                            of the regime beyond the line was clearer, we need to go slow on the
                            location of the boundary. Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> at that point repeated an earlier statement
                            about the very great complexity of the problem. He went on to say that
                            the process of coming up with answers would be a long one and initiated
                            the suggestion that an international moratorium was needed on boundary
                            claims. All of the Executive Agency participants agreed on the necessity
                            for a moratorium.</p>
                        <p>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> said that
                            one of the pending questions within the Executive Branch was whether to
                            seek a definition of a boundary by international agreement or by
                            unilateral actions and <pb facs="d345-02" n="2" xml:id="d345-02"/>
                            stated the general preference of the State Department for the
                            international agreement. Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> said that he looked forward to seeing the
                            definition in the form of a treaty which would come before the
                            Senate.</p>
                        <p>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> said that
                            the oil industry wanted us to move slowly, maintain the present status
                            quo, and avoid commitment to a boundary line at this time. Senator
                                <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> stated that he had
                            not yet consulted the economic interests involved but had asked Charlie
                            Jackson to provide him with some information on the industry points of
                            view. (He described Charlie Jackson as a former Senate staff member.)
                            Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> went on to
                            suggest that he establish a subcommittee which might hold executive
                            session hearings to obtain the view points of the interested executive
                            agencies and of industry. In response to his question as to the urgency
                            of the subject, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NGW1">Nutter</persName> spoke
                            about the current discussions with the Soviets on territorial seas and
                            straits, the pending discussions with the Peruvians, and the <gloss target="#t_ENDC1">ENDC</gloss> seabed discussions in Geneva. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Pollack</persName> described the
                            increasing difficulty of our position at the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> where the Seabeds Committee was currently conducting
                            “informal” discussions on seabed principles. He made clear that there
                            was on the table for discussion the U.S. June 28, 1968 Principles, Rio
                            sets A and B, and 3 or 4 other sets of principles introduced by
                            participants in the informal discussions.</p>
                        <p>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> stated that
                            there was no disagreement on the need for principles, but that the
                            Interior Department wanted to be very sure that the words used in
                            formulating the principles would not give away anything we might later
                            wish to retain. He cited as an example the proposed change in the word
                            “arrangement” to “regime.” Regime connoted institutions, whereas
                            arrangements was a broader and looser term. He also referred to the
                            question as to whether the boundary should be “agreed” or
                            “accepted.”</p>
                        <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> alluded again to
                            the proposal to establish a subcommittee to hear the views of the
                            several Executive Departments. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Pollack</persName> stated that he thought it would be unfortunate
                            if the subcommittee’s time was taken up with hearing <pb facs="d345-03" n="3" xml:id="d345-03"/> explanations with the differences between
                            “arrangements” and “regime.” Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> suggested that State, Defense, Interior and
                            other Executive Departments continue to work on the principles and
                            moratorium language. Once that had been worked out, a meeting with the
                            subcommittee would be most useful. He went on to suggest that it would
                            be helpful if the several interested committees—Interior, Commerce,
                            Armed Services, and Foreign Relations—could agree to combined
                            consultations or hearings. Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> said that he would look into that
                            possibility.</p>
                        <p>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> said that
                            the Interior Department was preparing a memorandum to be sent to State
                            listing the words which were troubling them and seeking clarification as
                            to their precise meaning. He hoped to show this memorandum on Thursday
                            to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HW3">Hickel</persName> who would be
                            returning to his office on that day, but hoped to be able to make it
                            available to the State Department even before that time. Under Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> made it clear that he
                            could not commit Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HW3">Hickel</persName>’s position on the principles. Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> said that he thought that the
                            Departments ought to proceed with their efforts to get together on the
                            language of the principles. Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> asked if Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHM1">Jackson</persName> was saying that the State Department should not
                            go forward with the discussions in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            and its guidance to the U.S. delegation. The Senator responded that he
                            was sure that the State Department would have to do what was
                            necessary.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Pollack</persName> said that it would be
                            necessary for the U.S. delegation to proceed in the “informal”
                            discussion on the basis of the June 28 Principles. Under Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> wanted to know if it
                            would be necessary to do this this week. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Pollack</persName> said that he would want to talk to those who
                            were following the discussions more closely in New York, but that from
                            his knowledge of that, it would appear to be necessary to do this by the
                            end of this week or the first of next. Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TRE1">Train</persName> asked what our position would be
                            if Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HW3">Hickel</persName> were to
                            conclude later this week that the present administration of the Interior
                            Department could not concur in the language of the June 28 Principles.
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Pollack</persName> then proposed that the
                            delegation be instructed <pb facs="d345-04" n="4" xml:id="d345-04"/> to
                            state that the United States had under consideration clarifying changes
                            in the language of the principles and that it be authorized to discuss
                            the substance of the principles without continuing commitment to the
                            exact language of the June 28 Principles. The Interior Department was
                            assured that it would have an opportunity to clear this instruction.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>