<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>38. Action Memorandum From Deputy Under Secretary of State for Administration
                    (Macomber) to Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs () to Under
                    Secretary of State for Political Affairs (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d38</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">38</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006005376"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Extremist</term>
                    <term ref="recdZke2uFUGdGg1d" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="rec8uqG4zFwFzxdlO" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104422"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recHKBrLbO74DsZpb" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136190"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Torture</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="38"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d38">
                <head>38. Action Memorandum From Deputy Under Secretary of State for Administration
                        (<persName corresp="#p_MWBJ1" type="from">Macomber</persName>) to Under
                    Secretary of State for Political Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_JUA1" type="to"
                        >Johnson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d38fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                        1970-73, POL 17 <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Secret. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_HRA3">Hurwitch</persName> and Frederic L. Chapin
                            (<gloss target="#t_ARALA1">ARA/LA</gloss>/MGT), cleared in draft in
                            <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>,
                        and <gloss target="#t_OSY1">O/SY</gloss>, and approved in <gloss
                            target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_MWBJ1"
                            >Macomber</persName> did not initial the memorandum, and there is no
                        indication that <persName>Johnson</persName> approved or disapproved of the
                        recommendations.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d38fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MWBJ1">Macomber</persName> discussed policy options
                        available to reduce politically motivated kidnapping of U.S. officials
                        abroad.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-04-02"
                        >April 2, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>U.S. Policy Toward Politically Motivated Kidnapping of U.S. Officials
                        Abroad-ACTION MEMORANDUM</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="underline">DISCUSSION</hi>:</p>
                <p>This paper addresses the question of policy options open to the U.S. with respect
                    to politically motivated kidnapping of U.S. officials abroad, the category in
                    which all of the recent kidnappings involving U.S. citizens fall. The isolated
                    non-politically motivated kidnapping by criminals is not considered, for it is
                    virtually impossible to guard against such an event. This paper does not address
                    incidents involving private U.S. citizens, who would continue to receive normal
                    consular protection. The questions of improved security for our personnel abroad
                    and of political measures we could undertake to inhibit kidnapping are addressed
                    in other papers.</p>
                <p>With the exception of the abortive kidnapping attempt of Soviet officials in
                    Argentina, all of the kidnappings involving foreign officials (including U.S.)
                    have been carried out by left extremist dissident groups. They appear in all
                    instances to have been motivated by the three-fold desires to (1) obtain the
                    release of political prisoners (often their comrades); (2) publicize and gain
                    sympathy for their cause; and (3) embarrass their government.
                    Politically-motivated kidnapping of U.S. officials could occur in virtually any
                    Latin American <pb facs="d38-02" n="2" xml:id="d38-02"/> country where there are
                    extremist groups with the above-described political motives. Conditions are
                    propitious under the following circumstances: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>in countries where kidnappings have recently taken place: Argentina,
                            Brazil, Colombia, the Dominican Republic, Guatemala and Uruguay.</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>in other countries that hold political prisoners and in which there
                            are organized extremist groups: Bolivia, Chile, Ecuador, El Salvador,
                            Mexico, Nicaragua, Panama and Venezuela.</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>Additionally, kidnappings may be expected in some of the
                            above-mentioned countries as the result of political violence in
                            connection with elections this year: Chile, Colombia, the Dominican
                            Republic, Ecuador, and Mexico.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Given the probable triple motivations of these dissident groups, the categories
                    their prospective victims might come from may perhaps be roughly delimited. In
                    Latin America, politics is a man’s game. A successful daring act against a
                    political opponent, actual or symbolic, is an accepted, if not applauded,
                    manifestation of virility. The more prominent the individual the more attractive
                    the target, provided that that individual were not a popular figure, whose
                    kidnapping would arouse sympathy for him and commensurate opprobrium for the
                    kidnappers and their cause. The following inferences from the dissidents’
                    political motivations may therefore be drawn: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>Women and children will probably not be their targets.</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>Tourists will probably not be their targets.</item>
                        <pb facs="d38-03" n="3" xml:id="d38-03"/>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>Low-level businessmen will probably not be their target.</item>
                        <label>(d)</label>
                        <item>Prominent businessmen will probably be somewhat vulnerable, for they
                            would be regarded by these dissidents as allied with the “oppressive”
                            host government.</item>
                        <label>(e)</label>
                        <item>Officials will probably be a main target, with the more prominent the
                            more vulnerable.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The capabilities of the dissident groups vary considerably from country to
                    country as do the political situations of each of the host governments at any
                    given time. It is therefore extremely difficult to predict how the host
                    government might react to the conditions set by the kidnappers for freeing a
                    U.S. official captured, and it is equally difficult to predict how insistent the
                    kidnappers would be in the face of resistance by the host government to
                    accepting the terms of freedom. Much would also depend upon the nature of the
                    terms themselves.</p>
                <p>With prominent officials the most likely target, and the reactions of host
                    governments to kidnappers’ demands unpredictable, the generally accepted
                    principles of international law and practice concerning the inviolability of the
                    person of a diplomatic agent and his dependents become particularly significant.
                    The most recent authoritative statement of these principles is found in the
                    Vienna Convention of 1961, which the U.S. has signed but not ratified. Article
                    29 of the Convention states: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The person of a diplomatic agent shall be inviolable. He shall not be
                            liable to any form of arrest or detention. The receiving State shall
                            treat him with due respect and shall take all appropriate steps to
                            prevent any attack on the person, freedom or dignity.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="d38-04" n="4" xml:id="d38-04"/>
                <p>In those countries where the risk of kidnapping is considerable, we should
                    express unequivocally to the host government our expectation that the sense of
                    Article 29 will be met in full measure.</p>
                <p>Any specific U.S. reaction to a future kidnapping should be preceded by general
                    statements at appropriate levels of the U.S. Government deploring kidnapping of
                    public officials or private citizens as a crime and decrying the use of such
                    methods as a political weapon. The possibility of <gloss target="#t_OAS1"
                        >OAS</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> resolutions condemning
                    kidnapping of officials for political purposes as near term objectives and of
                        <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    conventions establishing such kidnappings as crimes under international law as
                    longer term objectives are discussed in a separate paper. The public
                    announcement of the initiation of international consultations or negotiations
                    toward these ends or even the announcement of the U.S. intention to pursue these
                    objectives would help build a general climate of opinion which would diminish
                    the advantages kidnappers would expect to derive.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="underline">Options for U.S. Policy and Action</hi>
                </p>
                <p>If a U.S. diplomat or a dependent were kidnapped (our improved system of alert
                    and control with respect to our personnel overseas, our campaign to inhibit
                    kidnapping by decreasing its potential political benefits, and the host
                    government’s efforts to prevent it notwithstanding), the U.S. would be faced
                    with essentially three options for action: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>apply pressure to the extent necessary to persuade the host government
                            to comply fully with the kidnapper’s terms;</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>express our expectation that the host government will do everything
                            reasonable to obtain the freedom of the kidnapped official, <pb
                                facs="d38-05" n="5" xml:id="d38-05"/> recognizing, however, that the
                            determination of what is reasonable would be made by the host
                            government; and</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>urge the host government to refuse publicly the kidnappers’
                            demands.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="underline">Apply Pressure to the Extent Necessary to Persuade the Host
                        Government to Comply Fully with the Kidnappers Terms.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This option has the advantage of maximizing the chances of recovering a U.S.
                    official or his dependent whose life is in immediate danger.</p>
                <p>A disadvantage of this course of action is that the kidnappers would have gained
                    their ends. Also, they or others would become encouraged to repeat the
                    performance. A further disadvantage would be that we could be making compliance
                    with the kidnappers’ terms a major issue in our relations with the host country.
                    Finally, the “open endedness” of this course could encounter considerable public
                    and Congressional concern as to where and when the line would finally be
                    drawn.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="underline">Express in most categorical terms our expectation that</hi>
                    host governments will take all reasonable and practicable action in advance to
                    protect our personnel in their country in order to deter kidnap attempts. Note,
                    however, that when the host government has, in the opinion of the U.S.
                    Government, taken all appropriate preventive action and a kidnapping still takes
                    place the U.S. Government will expect the host government to do everything
                    reasonable and practicable to obtain the freedom of kidnapped officials or their
                    dependents. It will leave to the host government the ultimate decisions as to
                    what measures are reasonable and practicable and the host government’s decision
                    in this regard will not lead to recriminations by the U.S. Government.</p>
                <pb facs="d38-06" n="6" xml:id="d38-06"/>
                <p>The advantages to this course would be: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>We would have acknowledged the importance of the life at stake and
                            avoided the possibility of the problem becoming a major issue in our
                            relations.</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>Since each case might be decided differently by the host government,
                            the resultant uncertainty as to the outcome of their demands could deter
                            some potential kidnappers.</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>Since it is possible that the U.S. might be faced with the reverse
                            situation, this course of action would create a reciprocal basis for the
                            U.S. President to decide in a given case that may occur in the
                            U.S.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The main disadvantage would be that failure on our part to insist upon full
                    compliance with the kidnappers’ terms would quite probably result in the
                    eventual torture and/or death of a U.S. official or dependent. Another
                    disadvantage would be Congressional and public criticism from some quarters.</p>
                <p>A subsidiary disadvantage would be that hazardous pay may have to be paid to U.S.
                    personnel serving in areas where substantial danger of kidnapping existed.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="underline">Urge the Host Government to Refuse Publicly the Kidnappers’
                        Demands.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>If we were to adopt this course, we should probably announce it immediately and
                    publicly for its deterrent potential-its main advantage.</p>
                <p>Its disadvantage lies in the near certainty that one or more U.S. officials or
                    their dependents would suffer torture and/or death as the kidnappers tested our
                    will.</p>
                <p>Based upon its experience to date, <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> would be
                    least uncomfortable operating within the second option.</p>
                <pb facs="d38-07" n="7" xml:id="d38-07"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="underline">RECOMMENDATIONS</hi>:</p>
                <p>A. Since kidnapping as a political weapon could occur in any area of the world
                    and could involve the officials of any overseas U.S. agency, I recommend that
                    the Under Secretaries Committee be tasked with reaching a government-wide
                    recommendation, based upon the foregoing analysis, for the President’s decision
                    as to U.S. policy toward politically-motivated kidnapping of U.S. officials or
                    their dependents abroad.</p>
                <p rend="right">Approve_________</p>
                <p rend="right">Disapprove__________</p>
                <p>B. I recommend that the second option above be followed as U.S. policy in the
                    event a kidnapping should take place before the ultimate policy decision is
                    reached by the President.</p>
                <p rend="right">Approve________</p>
                <p rend="right">Disapprove_________</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
