<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-31T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-31T18:00:00-05:00" n="100" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">320/10–3150: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Spain</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority   <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-31T18:00:00-05:00">October 31, 1950—6 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>236. <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Polit Comite approved this
                                afternoon resol on Spain by vote Yes–37, No–10, Abstention–12, one
                                    absent.<note n="1" xml:id="d100fn1">Documentation on the policy
                                    of the United States regarding the Spanish question at the
                                    United Nations and within the framework of bilateral relations
                                    between the United States and Spain is scheduled for publication
                                    in volume <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>. The matter as a United
                                    Nations issue had been inscribed on the agenda of the General
                                    Assembly as item No. 62, “Relations of States Members [of the
                                    United Nations] and specialized agencies with Spain,” upon the
                                    initiation of two separate resolutions by the Dominican Republic
                                    and Peru which called for normalization of relations with Spain.
                                    The General Assembly had assigned the matter to its <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Political Committee, which after
                                    consideration of the item in five meetings from October 25–31
                                    accepted a joint resolution cosponsored by eight states revoking
                                    recommendations in the General Assembly resolution of December
                                    12, 1946, for the withdrawal of Ambassadors and Ministers from
                                    Madrid and intended to debar Spain from international agencies
                                    associated with the United Nations. The United States favored
                                    such modifications of the 1946 resolution and spoke in favor of
                                    the joint draft resolution on October 31. For relevant public
                                    documentation on this matter, see fascicule 62 in United
                                    Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Records of the General
                                        Assembly, Fifth Session, Annexes</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>. For the United States statement in
                                    the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Political Committee on October
                                    31, see United Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Records of
                                        the General Assembly, Fifth Session, Ad Hoc Political
                                        Committee</hi>, pp. 184 and 185. The General Assembly
                                    adopted the resolution on November 4; for the plenary
                                    proceedings, see United Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official
                                        Records of the General Assembly, Fifth Session, Plenary
                                        Meetings</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 371 ff.
                                    (hereafter cited as <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (V), <hi rend="italic">Plenary</hi>).</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>