<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d147</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">147</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-07-29T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-07-29T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-29T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-29T19:00:00-05:00" n="147"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d147">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">330/7–2950: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d147fn1">
                        <p>Repeated “for action” to Cairo (93) and Oslo (72); repeated “for
                            information” to London (542), Taipei (90), and <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                                >USUN</gloss> (79).</p>
                        <p>In telegram 540, July 30, 8 p. m., the Ambassador reported “I discussed
                            this question with Parodi tonight. Instructions have been sent to
                            Chauvel favorable to our attitude.” (330/7–3050)</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-29T20:00:00-04:00"
                            >July 29, 1950—8 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>534. <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> has been negotiating with other <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> Dels re situation which might arise in <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> if returning Soviet rep, who sits as Pres at all
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meetings during month of Aug, seeks use
                    his presidential prerogatives to unseat Chi Natl Rep and replace him with Chi
                    Commie.</p>
                <p>While it is impossible predict exactly how Sov Rep might bring up this issue, and
                    exactly what course procedural debate might take, essential elements of problem
                    will clearly be as follows. <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> Pres may abuse his
                    power to make procedural ruling to exclude Chi Natl Rep, in hope that challenge
                    of his ruling will not receive necessary seven <hi rend="italic">votes</hi> in
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> to become effective. Thus his ruling wld
                    stand and, by this procedural device, Chi representation question in <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> wld be settled.</p>
                <p>Opposition to Pres will undoubtedly take form of disputing his power to make
                    ruling on a representation question. Basis opposition will undoubtedly be rule
                    17 <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> rules procedure which states: “Any rep on
                    the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, to whose credentials objection has been
                    made within the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, shall continue to sit with
                    the same rights as other reps until the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> has
                    decided the matter”. Reasoning wld probably be that <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss> Pres, like any other member <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>,
                    must raise objection to credentials in normal way and that this objection must
                    be supported by seven <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> members if it is to
                    result in an <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> decision.</p>
                <p>Pls stress to <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> fact that we wld consider
                    it most unwise to debate Chi rep question at this crucial moment in <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> operation against aggression. Moreover, we have
                    always considered that Chi rep question shd be dealt with on its merits and not
                    by procedural dodges and that proper constitutional majority shd decide for each
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> organ. We have also stated that veto does
                    not apply to this subject in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. We consider it
                    inadmissible that <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> Pres shd precipitate
                    decision by procedural <pb facs="0267" n="251" xml:id="pg_251"/> trick. You may
                    state that US will be prepared to challenge in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    any presidential ruling of this nature. In line with our feeling that this not
                    the time for consideration this question, we hope that govt to which you are
                    accredited will not at this time support any motion which if adopted wld have
                    effect of changing Chi representation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
