<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of the First Meeting of the United States Delegation to the General
                    Assembly, New York, September 18, 1950, 11:00 a. m..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d167</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">167</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-09-18T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-09-18T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-18T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-18T10:00:00-05:00" n="167"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d167">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">IO Flies: US/<gloss target="#t_A1">A</gloss>/M
                    (Chr)/136</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the First Meeting of the United States Delegation
                        to the General Assembly, New York, September 18, 1950, 11:00 a.
                    m</hi>.</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1950-09-18T11:00:00-04:00">September 18, 1950, 11:00 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows list of persons present (39).]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Chinese Representation</hi> (SD/<gloss
                        target="#t_A1">A</gloss>/225/Rev. 1 and SD/<gloss target="#t_A1"
                    >A</gloss>/234)</p>
                <p>Mr. Bancroft explained that this subject had been discussed by the Foreign
                    Ministers who had reached agreement on procedures to be followed, but not on
                    substance. Our position was summarized in the papers before the Delegation. It
                    was expected that the issue would be raised either by a Soviet or Indian motion.
                    Our position was to vote for the continued seating of the Nationalists; we
                    believed this issue should be discussed with a minimum of debate and quickly
                    voted upon. We would indicate our belief that the matter should be decided only
                    after deepest thought and consideration which was not possible at the outset of
                    the session in view of the urgent business before the Assembly. We would,
                    however, agree to further study in connection with the Cuban proposal on
                    representation which would presumably provide a basis for deciding between rival
                    claimants for United Nations representation. In the meantime, we could observe
                    the attitude of the Chinese Communists toward the United Nations. Obviously, as
                    the Secretary had observed during the Foreign Ministers meetings, we did not,
                    desire to slam the door forever on the possibility that the Chinese Communists
                    might be admitted to the United Nations, but at the same time we wished to make
                    clear to them that their conduct was under close scrutiny.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bancroft stated that Bevin had indicated the position of his Government would
                    continue to favor seating the Communists both before and after the Cuban study,
                    and the Secretary, on the other hand, had made it clear that no commitment was
                    intended as to the way in which the United States would vote after the study was
                    concluded.</p>
                <pb facs="0308" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/>
                <p>Mr. Bevin had argued that our position was isolating China from the Western
                    World, forcing it into the arms of the Soviet Union and driving a wedge between
                    India and China. Mr. Schuman had taken the position that recognition and
                    representation in the United Nations were two different problems, and while his
                    Government had no thought of recognizing the Chinese Communists so long as they
                    maintained their present position toward Indo-China, it would wish to face the
                    fact that the Chinese Communists controlled all of China and the Nationalist
                    representatives represented nobody. Nevertheless, France would vote against
                    ousting the Nationalists and against seating the Communists.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bancroft called attention to another aspect of our position namely, that we
                    were prepared to accept Chinese Communist participation if requested in the
                    Committee 1 debate on Korea and Formosa, and perhaps in the Committee
                    considering the Cuban item. In no way would we suggest that this was a first
                    step toward admission of the Communists, but there were sound political
                    advantages in giving this group a chance to expound its position. Such a device
                    would, among other things, forestall any attempt by India to become the advocate
                    for Red China. However, Mr. Bancroft emphasized that this aspect of the problem
                    would not come up in the immediate future and was not for discussion.</p>
                <p>Mr. Hickerson explained that Sir B. N. Rau had visited the Secretary yesterday
                    and talked to him at considerable length on Chinese representation. Rau had said
                    that he saw a great deal of merit in having a commission set up to look into
                    this question and make specific recommendations to the Assembly on the Chinese
                    situation. Possibly the Cuban proposal could be pin-pointed to this particular
                    problem by looking at such matters as actual control of the territory,
                    opposition to the Government, foreign policy of the Government etc. Mr.
                    Hickerson went on to say that fifteen minutes after he had left the Secretary,
                    Rau was telephoning for another appointment since he had received new
                    instructions. This time he had talked to Messrs. Ross and Hickerson and had
                    explained that he was now instructed to give immediate notice of the
                    introduction of a resolution at the beginning of the session which would provide
                    for seating the Chinese Communists, and would attempt to be recognized for this
                    purpose at the very start of the session. Mr. Hickerson read the text of the Rau
                    proposal to the Delegation. Noting that this draft would involve consideration
                    of the question on its merits, Mr. Hickerson reported that he had informed Rau
                    that the United States preferred his previous idea of a Commission, and that we
                    felt quite strongly that it was impossible to get impartial, objective
                    consideration of the question on its merits at the <pb facs="0309" n="293"
                        xml:id="pg_293"/> present time because of Korea. Moreover, it was important
                    to get on with the Assembly’s business,</p>
                <p>Mr. Rau had inquired what position the United States would take on the Indian
                    resolution, and Mr. Hickerson had replied that we would oppose it. Then Rau had
                    asked whether we would use our influence against the resolution, and the answer
                    had been that we would use all our influence to get the proposal voted down
                    because we thought the procedure which we had in mind was a better way of
                    dealing with the problem.</p>
                <p>Mr. Ross observed that Rau did not wish it known that he was in any way the
                    author of the commission idea or that there was any difference between himself
                    and his government.</p>
                <p>Senator Lodge inquired as to the significance of the phrase on Page 3 of the
                    position paper, “the attitude the Chinese Communists would adopt in the
                        Assembly.”<note n="1" xml:id="d167fn1">See Doc. SD/<gloss target="#t_A1"
                            >A</gloss>/225/Rev. 1, <ref target="#pg_287">p. 287</ref>.</note> It was
                    explained that it meant if they were members; in any case here the assumption
                    was simply that the Chinese Communists would be heard as witnesses, and would be
                    permitted to take a limited part in the debate by making statements and
                    answering questions. Senator Lodge asked whether this had been done previously;
                    hearings for Albania and Bulgaria in connection with the Greek case and for
                    Italy in the disposition of the former Italian colonies were mentioned as
                    previous illustrations of this practice, and it was noted that in each case the
                    Committee had set the terms for participation of such witnesses.</p>
                <p>Senator Lodge asked whether such action would look as if the Chinese Communists
                    were being accorded some kind of recognition. The reply was in the negative. Mr.
                    Hickerson referred to the fact that a number of friendly delegations, such as
                    the Canadians, felt it would be a great mistake not to hear the Communists.
                    Moreover, if no hearing was granted, the Indian Delegation would feel called
                    upon to be their spokesman, an obviously undesirable development. If the
                    Communists did appear, there was a chance that they might make fools of
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cohen still believed, in view of our general objectives, that it would be
                    more effective to hold the present Chinese seat vacant, rather than keep the
                    Nationalists in the seat. That position would facilitate the watching of
                    developments and would not give the impression that we were maintaining the
                    Nationalists in the United Nations without due cause. Mrs. Roosevelt asked
                    whether our real objective was not to keep the Nationalists in because of their
                    representation on the Security Council.</p>
                <pb facs="0310" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/>
                <p>Ambassador Austin referred to the language of the position paper in this regard,
                    which indicated the importance of the Chinese Nationalist vote in the Council.
                    He observed that we were operating on a thin margin in the Council, and that
                    actually we could not have maintained our position without the Chinese vote. Mr.
                    Dulles referred to the requirement of Article 28 which indicated that China must
                    be represented on the Council, and thought, that if the seat were left vacant,
                    it would throw a cloud over the legality of Security Council action.</p>
                <p>Referring to possible Chinese Communist participation in Committee 1, Ambassador
                    Gross wondered whether we might not also say we favored inviting other
                    interested parties to be heard, as for instance the Japanese. Possibly the paper
                    was incomplete on this point. Mr. Bancroft explained that while the position
                    paper singled out the Chinese Communists, it was not meant to exclude the
                    participation of others.</p>
                <p>Mr. Tate asked what the word “perhaps” meant in connection with the possibility
                    of hearing the Chinese Communists on the Cuban item. He saw no reason for their
                    participation on this item. Mr. Bancroft indicated that was the basis for the
                    use of the word “perhaps”.</p>
                <p>Senator Lodge asked whether it would be inconsistent with the international
                    status of the Japanese for them to be heard. Mr. Dulles agreed it might
                    constitute a problem, since <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> was the
                    representative of the Japanese in matters of this sort; he also wondered whether
                    representatives of Formosa might not be heard, although Senator Lodge doubted
                    there were any which would not be under the control of Chiang Kai-Shek.</p>
                <p>Speaking to the recommendation that the Assembly should act on the matter of
                    Chinese representation by a simple majority vote, Mr. Cohen thought we should be
                    a little careful of what the Secretary’s statement said, particularly since the
                    paper referred to this subject as a serious and important question. He believed
                    we might be subject to possible embarrassment on this point. He did not recall
                    that our interpretation of Article 18 excluded its application to other
                    questions.</p>
                <p>Senator Sparkman asked what the basis for difference in position in the Assembly
                    was, as contrasted with our position taken in the Security Council last week.
                    Ambassador Austin explained that in the Council the real issue was whether the
                    Chinese Communists should be allowed to represent China. The only formal request
                    from the Peiping regime before the Council expressly asked that its
                    representatives be seated in the Council. This intention of the Chinese
                    Communists had been exposed in the Council, and they had failed to get in.
                    Unfortunately, the public had not understood clearly the basis of the position
                    taken by the United States. In addition, Ambassador Austin <pb facs="0311"
                        n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/> pointed out that the United States had been
                    prepared to support a Commission on the alleged Manchurian bombings,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d167fn2">For documentation on this matter, see <ref
                            target="frus1950v06">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> which would have conducted actual hearings on the spot, and
                    after it reported back, we had indicated we would be willing to reconsider the
                    question whether the Chinese Communists should be heard in the Council. Senator
                    Sparkman observed that the press had not made this situation very clear. Mr.
                    Popper pointed out that the hearings recommended in the position paper did not
                    relate to the representation question.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bancroft turned to the question whether either regime should be seated. He
                    believed that, as a matter of policy, it would be unwise at this stage to give
                    the Communists any prize. Obviously a second prize would be to exclude
                    representatives of both governments. He suggested also we should see whether any
                    other delegations raise this possibility.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Austin stated that the position paper was unanimously adopted as the
                    policy of the Delegation.<note n="3" xml:id="d167fn3">That is, Doc. SD/<gloss
                            target="#t_A1">A</gloss>/225/Rev. 1.</note>
                </p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of other subjects.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
