<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="464" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d464">
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>On July 22, 1950, disorders occasioned by anti-Government
                                demonstrations began in Guatemala and continued until the 26th, when
                                the Government declared a state of siege and temporarily gave police
                                powers to the Army.</p>
                            <p>In the course of the disorders, university students and the Chamber
                                of Commerce, both largely in opposition, declared a general strike.
                                Most businesses closed. The Government on July 25 ordered them to
                                reopen and stated the licenses of noncomplying foreign businesses
                                would be canceled. Later the Government instead imposed fines on
                                those which did not open, and, in the Embassy’s opinion, on some of
                                those which did.</p>
                            <p>During the crisis the Embassy advised all United States citizens to
                                do “everything possible and consistent personal safety comply law
                                and abstain actions which might be interpreted as political.”
                                (Telegram 48 from Guatemala City, July 24, 714.00/7–2450)</p>
                            <p>Officers of the Embassy believed that “in view of the suspension of
                                [constitutional] guarantees [on July 23], business houses were
                                justified in failing to open to avoid threats of violence by student
                                groups.” (Memorandum by Ernest V. Siracusa, Assistant Officer in
                                Charge of Central America and Panama Affairs, to Mr. Miller, July
                                31, 714.00/7–3150)</p>
                            <p>Mr. Miller expressed concern over the fines to Ambassador Goubaud on
                                July 31. On instructions from the Department, Mr. Wells discussed
                                the subject informally with the Foreign Office on August 7. He
                                stressed the United States belief that Americans had not engaged <pb facs="0927" n="911" xml:id="pg_911"/> in politics and that those
                                American concerns which had closed had done so only for reasons of
                                safety.</p>
                            <p>On August 10 the Embassy learned that fines would be forgiven when
                                constitutional guarantees were restored. The constitution went back
                                into effect on September 6. (File 714.00 for July–September
                                1950)</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>