<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d514</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">514</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-01-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEWsf4stFSIl3L6" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Press relations</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="514" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d514">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>On December 1, 1950, at 4:30 p. m., Mr. Michael J. McDermott, Special Assistant
                    to the Secretary of State for Press Relations, made this statement orally:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Edward G. Miller, Jr., Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                        Affairs, received the Colombian and Peruvian Ambassadors today to discuss
                        the tensions prevailing between those two countries, arising out of the
                        asylum which has been granted in the Embassy of Colombia at Lima to Victor
                        Raúl Haya de la Torre, leader of the now outlawed <gloss target="#t_ARAP1"
                            >APRA</gloss> party in Peru.</p>
                    <p>“Mr. Miller expressed to both Ambassadors the hope of this Government that
                        the energies of their countries would be united to those of the entire free
                        world in combating Communist aggression and that they would find a means of
                        resolving their difficulties in a manner which would preserve friendly
                        relations between them.</p>
                    <p>“Now as <hi rend="italic">background</hi>, it would be premature at this time
                        to discuss any specific proposal for solving the Haya de la Torre asylum
                        case. Mr. Miller’s conversations were of an exploratory nature with the view
                        to encourage the two countries to seek a mutually satisfactory
                        solution.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Mr. McDermott was asked by a reporter whether the conversations mentioned
                    indicated that Columbia and Peru were using or preparing to use the good offices
                    of the United States. He replied: “We are prepared, of course, to be of any
                    assistance we can in aiding the two partes to come to an agreement and Mr.
                    Miller so informed the two Ambassadors.” Mr. McDermott explained his answer by
                    stating:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">“Off the record</hi>, I go around the barn because this
                        Government doesn’t offer good offices unless they are quite sure that they
                        are going to be accepted. So this is really not exactly a tender of good
                        offices but is [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] prepared for such a tender if it
                        would be acceptable to the other side, and phrased that way so far as
                        possible so that they may accept the good offices, and I am sure that it
                        shows the other countries that we are willing to be of aid and assistance.”
                        (723.00/12–150)</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Both memoranda, not printed, of the separate conversations which Mr. Miller held
                    (at his request) with the Peruvian and Colombian Ambassadors on the morning of
                    December 1 are filed under 723.00/12–150.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
