<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d528</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">528</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-01-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="528" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d528">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Documents in files 731.5622 and 731.5811 for 1950 indicate that on July 7, 1950,
                    the Department, on the recommendation of Ambassador Donnelly, approved the
                    extension by the Department of the Air Force of an official invitation to Lt.
                    Col. Felix Roman Moreno, Chief of Staff of the Venezuelan Armed Forces, to visit
                    the United States. Since the previous February the Defense Department had
                    favored this invitation, partly for reasons of protocol and partly to stimulate
                    the interest of the Venezuelan Government in United States jet aircraft.</p>
                <p>Previously the State Department, while willing to approve the sale of such
                    aircraft to Venezuela under certain circumstances, had wished to separate this
                    issue from that of military visits, or at the least to ensure that Colonel
                    Moreno’s visit be under private instead of public auspices. In a memorandum to
                    Mr. Miller of May 15, Willard F. Barber, Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Inter-American Affairs, had said in part: “The Department has strong political
                    reasons for not wishing to invite leading Venezuelan military officers to the
                    United States. This is particularly true at the present time when the recent
                    strikes in the oil fields and among other unions in Venezuela have revealed the
                    deep and widespread dislike of the military government in Venezuela on the part
                    of large sectors of the people.” (731.5622/5–1550)</p>
                <p>In recommending reversal of this policy, Ambassador Donnelly stated in part:
                    “Since Air Force invited other chiefs <gloss target="#t_LA1">LA</gloss> air
                    forces to visit US as their guests, I feel similar courtesy should be extended
                    Moreno. I have some doubt he would accept invitation by private <pb facs="1057"
                        n="1041" xml:id="pg_1041"/> interests, but he would be highly honored
                    receive invitation from Air Force. Further he been led believe invitation would
                    be extended by General [Hoyt S.] Vandenberg [Chief of Staff, United States Air
                    Force].” Ambassador Donnelly added in part that Colonel Moreno was “definitely”
                    friendly to the United States and that he would play an important role in plans
                    for protecting the oil fields in the event of serious emergency and in
                    implementing any program for joint action with the United States in case of war.
                    (Telegram 12 from Caracas, July 6, 731.5811/7–650)</p>
                <p>For the Department’s policy regarding sale of jet aircraft to Venezuela, see the
                    memorandum of June 1 from Mr. Miller to John Foster Dulles, Consultant to the
                    Secretary of State, scheduled for publication in volume I.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
