<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-11T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-11T19:00:00-05:00" n="59" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d59">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">320/9–1150: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d59fn1">Repeated for action to the
                                    Embassies in Paris (1250) and Ottawa (60) and to the U.S.
                                    Mission, New York (238).</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-09-11T20:00:00-04:00">September 11, 1950—8 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1322. Pls review urgently with <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> fol ideas with respect composition <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Genl Comite and report soonest
                                reactions and suggestions you obtain.</p>
                            <pb facs="0138" n="122" xml:id="pg_122"/>
                            <p>On overall geographic balance <gloss target="#t_GC1">GC</gloss> Dept
                                feels past distribution shld be followed: Big 5, 1 <gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>, 1 Commonwealth, 3 from <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss>
                                and <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> area, 1 <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss> (Sov bloc) and 3 <gloss target="#t_LA1">LA</gloss>
                                States.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">President</hi>. US has not decided between leading
                                candidates Entezam and Zafrullah. US hopes after they canvass voting
                                strength NY one or other will retire from race.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vice Presidents</hi>. In addition five major
                                powers, US intends support Commonwealth candidate (Canada or
                                Australia; US hopes one or other will withdraw) and probably <gloss target="#t_LA1">LA</gloss> state, possibly Venezuela or Mexico,
                                which are candidates.</p>
                            <p>Dept’s tentative preference, assuming president from Middle East, is
                                for <gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss> to chair First Comite. Views
                                as to this idea and possible individuals available very much wanted.
                                From list dels now available, although we do not have Belg list,
                                best possibilities occurring to us are Lange (Norway)<note n="2" xml:id="d59fn2">Halvard M. Lange, Norwegian Minister of Foreign
                                    Affairs and Chairman of the Norwegian Delegation to the General
                                    Assembly.</note> if he would accept, or Van Heuven Goedhart
                                    (Netherlands).<note n="3" xml:id="d59fn3">G. J. van Heuven
                                    Goedhart, Vice Chairman of the Netherlands Delegation to the
                                    General Assembly.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>On <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Political Comite we have considered
                                Padilla Nervo (Mexico) or other suitable <gloss target="#t_LA1">LA</gloss> candidate, such as Urdaneta (Colombia).<note n="4" xml:id="d59fn4">Roberto Urdaneta Arbelaez, Chairman of the
                                    Colombian Delegation to the General Assembly.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>On Comite 2, Santa Cruz (Chile)<note n="5" xml:id="d59fn5">Hernán
                                    Santa Cruz, Chairman of the Chilean Delegation to the General
                                    Assembly.</note> has been mentioned but some feeling exists he
                                has held this position too many times. He has indicated to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> he may recommend Chile not be
                                candidate view Chile’s four years on <gloss target="#t_GC1">GC</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>If <gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss> does not chair First Comite
                                Goedhart could also be considered for Third Comite.</p>
                            <p>On Fourth Comite we have favorably considered Prince Wan
                                    (Thailand).<note n="6" xml:id="d59fn6">Prince Wan Waithayakon,
                                    Permanent Representative of Thailand at the United
                                    Nations.</note> Though UK has suggested McEachen of
                                    Uruguay,<note n="7" xml:id="d59fn7">Roberto E. MacEachen,
                                    Uruguayan Ambassador to Mexico.</note> who wld also be
                                acceptable to us, Dept. has no info he will attend.</p>
                            <p>Dept feels Slav group shld have one seat in addition USSR on Gen
                                Comite, preferably thru Comite Chairmanship, but has not been able
                                to find any suitable Comite Chairmanship. Wld welcome <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> views.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>