<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-02-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="14" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                        <head>14. Memorandum From the Panama Canal Treaty Co-Negotiator (<persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName>) for the Files<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d14fn1">Source: Library of Congress,
                                Manuscript Division, Linowitz Papers, Box 113, Panama Canal
                                Treaties, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Jimmy</persName> and White House Staff 1977,
                                Feb–1978, Jan. Confidential; Personal.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-02-14">February 14, 1977</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>Re: Meeting with President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> on February 11, 1977</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At noon on February 11th, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Ellsworth Bunker</persName> and I arrived at the White House for a
                            meeting with the President, Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> and National Security Advisor
                                <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> in connection
                            with the Panama Canal Treaty negotiations.</p>
                        <p>Soon after we arrived <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                            greeted us and then took us into the Oval Office, where we awaited the
                            President. As we entered <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> encountered the President’s Appointment
                            Secretary, a young man who had served in the Peace Corps in Guatemala
                            before he returned to the University, where he acquired an interest in
                            politics and ultimately became a devoted supporter of <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Jimmy Carter</persName> in 1975.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_PJ_1">Jody Powell</persName>, the President’s
                            Press Secretary, entered for a few moments and then suddenly the
                            President came into the room quietly and as he saw me he called out,
                            “Hello, Sol” and came striding forward. He shook hands with <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Ellsworth Bunker</persName> and told him how
                            pleased he was to see him and then he and I shook hands.</p>
                        <pb facs="0098" n="63" xml:id="pg_63"/>
                        <p>Although it was a warm spring day there was a fire crackling in the
                            fireplace and after a few moments of standing around the President asked
                            us to sit down. His first question to <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Ellsworth Bunker</persName> was, “How do you like working with
                            Sol?” <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> told him how much he
                            liked the idea and said that he was pleased that we were in harness
                            together. I told the President that <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> had been my mentor and that we therefore had an
                            especially personal relationship. <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> endorsed that warmly and the President seemed
                            pleased.</p>
                        <p>The President then asked what were the prospects for a new Treaty and
                                <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> told him about the
                            main problem being the defense-security one. The President made quite
                            clear that if there were not a proper provision for defense and
                            neutrality after the year 2000 the Treaty would not be approved by the
                            Senate even if he himself signed it. He then asked what were the
                            toughest issues and again <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName>
                            talked about defense and security and I added a word about the Zonians
                            and the matter of compensation.</p>
                        <p>The President wanted to know what the effect would be of <persName corresp="#p_BAE_1">Boyd</persName>’s resignation as Foreign Minister
                            and I pointed out that one possible favorable interpretation would be
                            that <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> might smell a new
                            Treaty developing and wanted his own name on it rather than that of
                                <persName corresp="#p_BAE_1">Boyd</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d14fn2">In telegram 1009 from Panama City, February 11, the
                                Embassy analyzed <persName corresp="#p_BAE_1">Boyd</persName>’s
                                resignation: “Differences of both form and substance between him and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> almost
                                certainly played a part in his departure—but it was also a renewed
                                sign that the general is the one who runs things here and that
                                others had better not forget it. We see in <persName corresp="#p_BAE_1">Boyd</persName>’s departure a signal that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> is determined
                                to make a greater share of decisions in the negotiations himself.”
                                (Department of State, Bureau of Inter-American Affairs, Office of
                                the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> Permanent Mission to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>, Einaudi Country Files,
                                1977–1989, Lot 91D371, Box 6, Panama 1977)</note> The President
                            said, “You don’t have to worry about that with me. I would be perfectly
                            willing to have it the <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName>
                            Treaty.”</p>
                        <p>I talked a bit to the President then about payments to the Panamanians
                            and the situation with reference to the tolls which had already been
                            raised twice recently. He asked what the cost was for a ton through the
                            Canal in light of the charge of $1.29 per Panama ton. I pointed out that
                            the cost generally included all the costs of the Zone and he indicated
                            that perhaps this was “unfair”.</p>
                        <p>I then mentioned to the President that it was possible that we might
                            reach an impasse in the negotiations and in that event a letter from him
                            to <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> might be helpful for
                            us to have. I then read to him a proposed letter which I had written out
                            shortly before coming to the meeting. He found it acceptable and
                                <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> asked for it so
                            that he could have it prepared and signed by the President. The
                            President said that in the light of <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName>’ interest in obtaining recognition he might be
                            pleased to have the President suggest that <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> would <pb facs="0099" n="64" xml:id="pg_64"/>
                            be signing the Treaty together and he asked <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> to add that to the letter.<note n="3" xml:id="d14fn3">In telegram 38993, February 19, the Department
                                transmitted the text of Carter’s letter to <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName>, in which <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> expressed his “hope that
                                these negotiations will bear fruit and will result in a treaty which
                                will be fair, reasonable and appropriate in every respect.”
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> assured <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> that the United States
                                intended to “proceed in a cooperative and flexible spirit in the
                                effort to arrive at a treaty which will satisfactorily meet the
                                proper concerns of both Panama and the United States.” If the treaty
                                negotiations were successful, and “as a sign of our friendship and
                                determination to place our relations on a firm basis, it might be
                                fitting for us to meet and sign the treaty jointly,” <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> concluded. (Department of
                                State, American Embassy Panama, Panama Canal Treaty Negotiation
                                Files, 1964–1977, Lot 81F1, Box 127, POL 33.3.2)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>With reference to the new Treaty itself the President made clear several
                            times that he believes that it is vitally important to us and that after
                            signature he would do everything he could to assure that it got
                            ratification by the Senate.</p>
                        <p>He then went on to say that if we thought it were necessary for him to
                            come in at any time to talk to <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> or otherwise, he stood ready to do so and to be
                            of help in any other way he might. Similarly, <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Cy Vance</persName>, who joined us later
                            indicated that he, too, would be available in any way that it might be
                            helpful.</p>
                        <p>At that point the President was briefly interrupted to be told that his
                            mother had been suggested to go to India as his representative with his
                            son, Chip, to attend the funeral of the President of India. He then
                            asked <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> for his reaction and
                                <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> thought it was fine
                            and said he would assure proper protection and inform Mrs. Carter.</p>
                        <p>I then took a moment to say to the President that it seemed to us that a
                            citizens committee for support of the Treaty would be a good and,
                            indeed, a necessary move. I pointed out that we could get someone like
                            Dean Rusk or Admiral Zumwalt<note n="4" xml:id="d14fn4">A reference to
                                Elmo R. “Bud” Zumwalt, Chief of Naval operations, July 1970–June
                                1974.</note> to serve as the head of such a committee and told him
                            that I had talked to Zumwalt. The President responded quite favorably
                            and seemed to react especially to the suggestion that Dean Rusk would
                            take it on.</p>
                        <p>Before leaving I asked him what we might tell the press about the meeting
                            and he suggested that it would be appropriate to say that we talked over
                            the main points of the proposed negotiations and that the prospects for
                            a Treaty were good.</p>
                        <p>I found the President extraordinarily well informed on the Treaty
                            negotiations, confident, informal and in excellent spirit. He seemed,
                            indeed, to look presidential and acted as if he were perfectly
                            comfortable to be occupying the post of President of the United
                            States.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>