<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-07-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-07-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="189" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d189">
                        <head>189. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_ADL_1">Aaron</persName>) to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d189fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                                Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, President’s Correspondence
                                with Foreign Leaders, Box 15, Panama: General <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Omar Torrijos Herrera</persName>, 8/78–12/79.
                                Confidential. Sent for action. <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> initialed and wrote on the top-right corner
                                of the memorandum: “This is more encouraging to <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> than I want. Make it more
                                non-commital. ‘Other factors’—ok. ‘Promise to include
                                Panama’—no.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-07-28">July 28, 1978</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Letter from General <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> on the Inter-American Development
                                Bank</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>General <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> sent you a cable
                            on June 30 (Tab B)<note n="2" xml:id="d189fn2">Tab B is not attached. A
                                June 30 letter from the Panamanian Embassy to <persName corresp="#p_JH_1">Jordan</persName> transmitted the June 30
                                cable from Torrijos. (Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                Brzezinski Material, President’s Correspondence with Foreign
                                Leaders, Box 15, Panama: General <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Omar
                                    Torrijos Herrera</persName>, 8/78–12/79)</note> asking that we
                            support continued eligibility for Panama, Costa Rica, and Jamaica to the
                            soft-loan window (<gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss>) of the
                            Inter-American Development Bank (<gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>).
                            This issue—the criterion for determining access to the <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss>—is an important one in the current
                            negotiations for the next <gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>
                            replenishment.</p>
                        <p>Treasury, State, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>, and <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry Owen</persName> all agree that we should
                            seek a formula that uses several social and economic indicators in
                            addition to per capita income in determining access to the <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss>; under this formula, the major share
                            of <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss> funds would clearly be reserved
                            for the poorest countries of the hemisphere, but Panama, Costa Rica, and
                            Jamaica would also have limited access to the <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss> for projects that assist low-income groups.</p>
                        <p>Resolution of this issue will not alter our position on the level of
                                <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss> replenishment; all we are
                            talking about is how to allocate these funds.</p>
                        <pb facs="0500" n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/>
                        <p>The issue which <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> raised
                            proved to be a difficult one, and it has taken two weeks for the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> Government to decide on a position.
                            The attached draft reply sets forth an approach which Treasury, State,
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry Owen</persName> all support.<note n="3" xml:id="d189fn3">Draft reply is not attached.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">RECOMMENDATION:</p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> does not—<persName corresp="#p_MJT_1">McIntyre</persName>’s comment is attached.<note n="4" xml:id="d189fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_MJT_1">McIntyre</persName>’s comment is not
                                attached. In an August 2 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MJT_1">McIntyre</persName> disagreed with State and <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>’s proposal that <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> respond positively to
                                Torrijos’s request, arguing that proposed response undercut the
                                “general approach of conserving soft loans for the poorest countries
                                and permits ad hoc bilateral considerations to drive overall
                                development assistance policy.” <persName corresp="#p_MJT_1">McIntyre</persName> recommended that <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> send a negative response to
                                Torrijos. (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski
                                Material, President’s Correspondence with Foreign Leaders, Box 15,
                                Panama: General <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Omar Torrijos
                                    Herrera</persName>, 8/78–12/79)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>That you sign the letter to <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> at Tab A.<note n="5" xml:id="d189fn5">There is
                                no indication of approval or disapproval of the recommendation.
                                However, on August 3, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                                sent a letter in response to <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName> stating: “My administration believes a
                                formula can be negotiated that will take account of several
                                important social and economic indicators in determining access to
                                the <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss>.” Whatever the outcome,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> expected that “a
                                large majority of <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss> funds would
                                be reserved for the poorest countries and that any concessional
                                funds for countries other than the poorest would be directed to
                                projects that clearly assist low income groups.” (Carter Library,
                                National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, President’s
                                Correspondence with Foreign Leaders, Box 15, Panama: General
                                    <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Omar Torrijos Herrera</persName>,
                                8/78–12/79)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The text has been approved by Jim Fallows.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>