<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-05-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="41" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d41">
                        <head>41. Memorandum for the Files<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d41fn1">Source: Carter Library, Office of Congressional Liaison, Jeff
                                Neuchterlein Subject Files, Box 237, (Panama Canal Treaty
                                Negotiations), 1/3/77–4/2/77 (CF, O/A 193). No classification
                                marking.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-05-27">May 27, 1977</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>Subj: Meeting with Senators <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CA_2">Cranston</persName>, Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CC_1">Curt
                                    Cutter</persName> on the PANAMA CANAL TREATY Negotiations</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_AMB_1">Ambs</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName> briefed Majority Leader <persName corresp="#p_BRC_2">Byrd</persName> and Senate Whip <persName corresp="#p_CA_2">Cranston</persName> on the Panama Canal Treaty
                            negotiations. They indicated at the beginning of the conversation that
                            agreement on major points of the treaty could well be concluded within
                            two to three weeks, and felt it was important to begin briefing Senators
                            on the key issues <pb facs="0181" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/> of the
                            treaty. <gloss target="#t_AMB_1">Amb</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> described the major points of
                            the agreement to date, including lands and water, and most importantly,
                            the neutrality issue.</p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_AMB_1">Amb</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName> then gave a more in depth description of
                            neutrality which was clearly the issue Senator <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName> was most interested in. After
                            describing the neutrality agreement, Senator <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName> asked a series of questions
                            concerning the defense of the Canal after the year 2000, as well as the
                            involvement of the Defense Dept in the negotiating process. <gloss target="#t_AMB_1">Amb</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName> told him that the Defense Dept was in perfect
                            agreement, and described in brief, the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> program for defending the Canal after the treaty
                            expires. He stated that the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> did not
                            want or need troops in the Canal Zone after the expiration of the
                            treaty.</p>
                        <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName> explained he had
                            been an original signer of the <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName> Resolution,<note n="2" xml:id="d41fn2">See <ref target="#d3fn15">footnote 15, Document 3.</ref>
                            </note> but seemed generally pleased with the description of the
                            neutrality issue, which he agreed was the single most important aspect
                            of the treaty. Senator <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName> then
                            suggested that a meeting be convened the week of June 12 with Senate
                            Armed Services, Foreign Relations and Leadership positions in
                            attendance. He specifically mentioned Senators <persName corresp="#p_HHH_1">Humphrey</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JHM_1">Jackson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SJC_1">Stennis</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BHH_1">Baker</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_SR_1">Stone</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d41fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BRG_1">Beckel</persName> wrote: “<persName corresp="#p_EJ_1">Eastland</persName>” in the right margin.
                                According to telegram 141764 to Panama City, June 18, <persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> met privately with <persName corresp="#p_BHH_1">Baker</persName> on June 15 and <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ACL_1">Alexander</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RBW_1">Rogers</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DWG_1">Dolvin</persName> briefed a group of senators
                                assembled by <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName> on June
                                16. In addition to <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName>, the
                                following senators attended the June 16 meeting: <persName corresp="#p_BHL_1">Bellmon</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CCP_1">Case</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CA_2">Cranston</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CCT_1">Curtis</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_EJ_1">Eastland</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GB_1">Goldwater</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HHH_1">Humphrey</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JHM_1">Jackson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LP_1">Laxalt</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LR_1">Long</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SPS_1">Sarbanes</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sparkman</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_TJ_2">Tower</persName>. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770218–0646)</note> He directed Senator <persName corresp="#p_CA_2">Cranston</persName> to convene the meeting that week. The
                            Ambassadors then described the potential problems with the economic
                            package to be discussed next week, but insisted that the <gloss target="#t_US_2">U.S.</gloss> position would be to avoid asking
                            Congress for additional appropriations. Both Senators <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CA_2">Cranston</persName> agreed that this would be very important to the
                            success of the treaty. The meeting ended on a very positive note.</p>
                        <p>AD:</p>
                        <p>At one point during the discussions Senator <persName corresp="#p_BHF_1">Byrd</persName> indicated that the Senate would never have passed a
                            treaty that did not include a neutrality agreement as strong as the one
                            that Ambs. <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName> had negotiated. I read this
                            to be an important sign of his willingness to continue to listen and
                            remain open on the issue.<note n="4" xml:id="d41fn4">At the end of the
                                memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_BRG_1">Beckel</persName> wrote:
                                “It was also suggested that at the next briefing <gloss target="#t_Gen_1">Gen.</gloss>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BGS_1">Brown</persName> accompany the
                                negotiators.”</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>