<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-08-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="73" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                        <head>73. Memorandum From Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d73fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                Brzezinski Material, Subject File, Box 18, Evening Reports (State),
                                8/77. Secret. <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                                initialed the top of the memorandum and wrote: “[<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>],” next to his initials.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-08-02">August 2, 1977</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>[Omitted here is information unrelated to Panama.]</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Panama</hi>. Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LSM_1">Linowitz</persName> today outlined the economic package to
                            Panamanian Minister for Planning and Development <persName corresp="#p_BNA_1">Barletta</persName>, emphasizing that we consider
                            this package to be as far as we can go. Further talks are planned to
                            explain to <persName corresp="#p_BNA_1">Barletta</persName> certain
                            aspects of the Canal’s financial operations. He clearly feels that more
                            money is available for the annuity than we are prepared to offer.
                            Notably, however, the Panamanians are no longer talking about a $460
                            million lump sum payment and a $150 million annuity.</p>
                        <p>The August 5 meeting of several Latin American Chiefs of State, called
                            for by <persName corresp="#p_THO_1">Torrijos</persName>, is going ahead
                            as planned. We have provided several of our embassies with additional
                            material on the negotiations so that they can brief host governments
                            prior to the meeting. Mexican Foreign Minister Roel, whom we briefed
                            yesterday, has said he will be helpful to us.<note n="2" xml:id="d73fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> wrote: “Let’s do the
                                same with others” in the left margin. On the day of the meeting,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> sent the
                                following message to the six Latin American presidents attending the
                                meeting: “I extend to you my good wishes and my warm appreciation
                                for your help and cooperation in helping us find a mutually
                                agreeable basis for a new Panama Canal treaty in which we can all
                                take pride.” (Telegram 184493 to Bogotá, August 5; National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Official and
                                Personal Files of Ambassador at Large <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Ellsworth Bunker</persName>, Lot 78D300, Box 1, Negotiating
                                Round, 8/7–11/77)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is information unrelated to Panama.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>