<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-05-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-05-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="142" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/4034½</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d142fn1">The source text is endorsed “CH OK
                                    FDR” in Roosevelt’s handwriting. It was returned to Hull from
                                    the White House under cover of the following memorandum, dated
                                    June 11, 1943, from Roosevelt: “Will you bring this up to date?
                                    I have heard nothing from Winston. Churchill who said he would
                                    let me know and has done nothing further. I think it is just as
                                    well to send this as is. If you approve, go ahead. F.D.R.” No
                                    record of any discussion between Roosevelt and Churchill
                                    regarding this paper or any other phase of the refugee problem
                                    has been found. Such a discussion was referred to in the
                                    memorandum of conversation by Assistant Secretary of State Long,
                                    dated June 4, 1943, the memorandum, of conversation by Hull,
                                    dated June 17, 1943, the memorandum of conversation by Welles,
                                    dated June 24, 1943, the memorandum from Long to Hull, dated
                                    June 29, 1943, and the telegram from Churchill to Roosevelt,
                                    dated June 30, 1943, <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_309">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 309</ref>, <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_313">313</ref>, <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_319">319</ref>, and <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_321">321</ref>, respectively. These
                                    references indicate some discrepancy of views as to what
                                    Roosevelt, and Churchill had actually discussed. In this
                                    connection, a memorandum of June 15, 1943, from R. Borden Reams
                                    of the Division of European Affairs to Long, not printed, reads
                                    in part as follows: “Mr. Hayter called today to state that a
                                    reply had been received from Mr. Churchill stating that he had
                                    not discussed the Intergovernmental Committee with the
                                    President. He had talked to the President about a refugee camp
                                    in North Africa.” (840.48 Refugees/4034)</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-05-22">May 22,
                                    1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I recently had
                                occasion to direct your attention to the refugee situation in
                                connection with the recommendations of the Bermuda Conference which
                                proposed a meeting of the Intergovernmental Committee to carry on
                                the work.<note n="2" xml:id="d142fn2">See the letter from Hull to
                                    Roosevelt, May 7, 1943, <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_176">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 176</ref>. For documentation
                                    regarding the Bermuda Conference on Refugees of April 1943, see
                                        <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_134">
                                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 134</ref> ff.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>As my mind approaches the subject matter to be discussed and the
                                questions to be decided by the Committee which it is now proposed to
                                start in London and to continue in Washington, certain doubts assert
                                themselves.</p>
                            <p>A meeting of that character would attract world-wide attention. It
                                could not be allowed to fail. Unless the American and British
                                Governments were determined in advance as to the purposes which they
                                would pursue and as to the extent to which they would commit <pb facs="0439" n="337" xml:id="pg_337"/> themselves on financial
                                accounts, the Conference could not come to any satisfactory
                                conclusions.</p>
                            <p>Attached is a telegram directed to London which was prepared after
                                the receipt of your recent memorandum on this matter.<note n="3" xml:id="d142fn3">Roosevelt’s memorandum of May 14, 1943, to Hull
                                    is printed in <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_179">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 179</ref>; telegram 3128,
                                    May 15, 1943, to London is printed <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_180">
                                        <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 180</ref>.</note> The
                                Department has been in telegraphic correspondence with the British
                                Foreign Office and has discussed the matter on several occasions
                                with Mr. Law, Parliamentary Under Secretary of Foreign Affairs, now
                                in the United States. Before proceeding further with it the thought
                                occurs to me that its extreme importance from the psychological
                                point of view would probably justify consultation by you with Mr.
                                Churchill.</p>
                            <p>1. Expressed concretely, refugees who may need attention and
                                protection are found in the following places in the following
                                approximate number: <table cols="2" rend="width: 75%" rendition="#center-block" rows="8">
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Iran</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">19,000</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Cyprus</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">4,650</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Spain</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">20,000</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Bulgaria</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">4,500</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>France</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">10,000</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Switzerland</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">13,500</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Portugal</cell>
                                        <cell rendition="#underline" role="num"> 1,400</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell>Total</cell>
                                        <cell role="num">73,050</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </p>
                            <p>2. It is impractical to estimate accurately the cost of transfer by
                                vessel and maintenance of the individual on a yearly basis, but
                                considering the short haul to some part of Africa, a figure of
                                $2,000 per capita per annum is considered not unreasonable. The
                                moving of all these 73,000 on that basis would cost $150,000,000.
                                The estimate should include repatriation at the end of the war.</p>
                            <p>3. The determination is to be made whether it would be possible to
                                limit the Intergovernmental Committee’s participation in the plan
                                for the succor and transit of the refugees to a place of temporary
                                refuge where Governor Lehman’s relief organization could take up the
                                relief activities during their temporary residence, provided there
                                is legal authority under existing legislation to permit it and
                                provided further that the British join on equal terms.</p>
                            <p>If you could present this matter to the consideration of Mr.
                                Churchill and arrive at some common decision with him as to what
                                extent our respective Governments could be committed at the
                                suggested Intergovernmental Committee meeting it would seem to be
                                justifiable to proceed with that meeting, with the assurance of
                                achieving some <pb facs="0440" n="338" xml:id="pg_338"/> success.
                                Lacking an understanding of the attitudes of our respective
                                Governments it would seem that the Conference could not accomplish a
                                very useful purpose.</p>
                            <p>Those persons who have escaped from German control or who may escape
                                in the future can be forwarded to places of temporary refuge till
                                the successful ending of the war will assure them the right to
                                return to their homes.</p>
                            <p>I am attaching a telegram which I would propose to send to London in
                                case it is justified by the conclusions you will reach with the
                                Prime Minister.<note n="4" xml:id="d142fn4">The draft telegram has
                                    not been found. For final text see telegram 3879, June 25, 1943,
                                    to London, <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_190">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 190</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Respectfully,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cordell Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>