<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-08-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-08-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="223" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">Roosevelt Papers</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum Prepared in the Operations Division of
                                    the War Department General Staff</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d223fn1">Copies of this memorandum were sent to
                                    Roosevelt and to each United States officer designated to attend
                                    the Quebec Conference. See Matloff, <ref target="#pg_176">p.
                                        176</ref>.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-08-08">8 August
                                    1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Conduct of the War in Europe.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The United Nations have failed during the past
                                        year and a half to concentrate their forces and to hold to
                                        decisions</hi>. The violation of these basic principles has
                                    resulted in the assembly of a much smaller military force
                                    against the European Axis than would otherwise have been
                                    possible. Since April, 1942, the United States and Great Britain
                                        <pb facs="0582" n="468" xml:id="pg_468"/> have maintained
                                    verbal adherence to the decision that the main and decisive
                                    effort would be a cross-channel operation and that forces and
                                    supplies would be built up in the U.K. for that purpose. The
                                    giving bit by bit of resources to the Mediterranean, which has
                                    always been regarded as a secondary theater, has resulted in a
                                    net decrease in the U.S. forces and resources which could have
                                    been brought to bear against the enemy. After deciding firmly to
                                    attack across channel and to build up the necessary forces in
                                    accordance with the <gloss target="#t_Bolero1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bolero</hi>
                                    </gloss> plan, it was decided to do <gloss target="#t_Torch1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Torch</hi></gloss>. There was to be no
                                    change in the U.S.-British main decisive effort. A net result of
                                    the disruptions of personnel and cargo shipping caused by this
                                    shift, originally considered as temporary, and by the day to day
                                    allotment of men and resources for the Mediterranean was that by
                                    1 April 1943 the U.S. had only approximately 452,000 men facing
                                    the European Axis from the U.K. and from the Mediterranean,
                                    instead of the 1,074,000 scheduled for the U.K. by 1 April 1943
                                    in the original <gloss target="#t_Bolero1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bolero</hi>
                                    </gloss> plan—a net loss in U.S. troop movements overseas of
                                    over 600,000 men prior to April 1943. We have every reason to
                                    believe that the figure of approximately 1,000,000 men in the
                                    U.K. by 1 April 1943 could have been attained. It was based on a
                                    careful investigation of possibilities by British as well as by
                                    American authorities. The British who worked on <gloss target="#t_Bolero1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bolero</hi>
                                    </gloss> will doubtless agree that the project could have been
                                    carried out. The loss of 600,000 men can be attributed mainly to
                                    the movement of 150,000 U.S. and 250,000 British troops to North
                                    Africa from [the] U.K.; the delays caused by readjustment of
                                    shipping schedules in preparation for the North Africa move; the
                                    meager port capacities in North Africa which limited the number
                                    of ships that could be handled in each convoy from the U.S. to a
                                    troop list of about 40,000 during the early period of the
                                    occupation; the lack of sufficient naval escorts for convoys to
                                    the U.K. at the same time they were being run to North
                                    Africa.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The above is by no means a complete measure of
                                        the waste which has resulted from reversal of decisions and
                                        from day-to-day variations from programs established and
                                        accepted as the basis for training men, producing equipment
                                        and deploying these resources throughout the world</hi>.
                                    Included in this waste are: the loss in cargo lift due to the
                                    transshipment of hundreds of thousands of tons of supplies
                                    through the U.K. to North Africa rather than directly; the waste
                                    of U.S. manpower resulting from pressing at high speed the
                                    training and equipment of units for an agreed major operation
                                    which is continually postponed, while a series of secondary
                                    operations are undertaken for which they are either not required
                                    or unsuitable; the waste in moving units great distances into
                                    staging areas and then failing to ship them overseas because of
                                    sudden changes in plans; the uneconomic use of <pb facs="0583" n="469" xml:id="pg_469"/> U.S. and British labor and
                                    production facilities in straining every effort to produce
                                    equipment and provide a base in time for a major scheduled
                                    operation which is not carried out according to plan. These
                                    disruptions are relatively much greater in the U.S. than in the
                                    U.K. The bulk of the supplies come from here. The great
                                    distances in the United States between depots, military camps
                                    and ports and the distances between bases serving theaters and
                                    sub-theaters of war must be kept always in mind when any change
                                    in a course of action is suggested. A diversion of any part of
                                    the flow of men and supplies once started towards a particular
                                    sub-theater results in delays and wastes which the United
                                    Nations cannot afford. Unsound practices such as those listed
                                    above, if continued, will certainly postpone victory, and may
                                    result in only a partial defeat of the Axis.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">In showing the cost of the change from the
                                        Channel to Africa there is no intention to belittle the
                                        effects of <gloss target="#t_Torch1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Torch</hi></gloss></hi>. <gloss target="#t_Torch1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Torch</hi></gloss> was successful
                                    and has brought great results. The Mediterranean has been
                                    opened, Italy is trembling in the balance, southern and eastern
                                    Germany have been placed under threat of air attack, the vitally
                                    important Ploeşti oil fields have been attacked. Much has been
                                    gained. <gloss target="#t_Bolero1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bolero</hi>
                                    </gloss> was not carried out and any appraisal of what might
                                    have resulted can be questioned. However, this direct action was
                                    the one chance to end the war in Europe this year. If this had
                                    happened, all that has been gained would be insignificant in
                                    comparison. It is particularly pertinent now to note that if we
                                    can put our air far enough north in Italy to bomb southern
                                    Germany, all the major military gains to be gotten from the
                                    African operation will have been attained. Decisive military
                                    action against Germany cannot come from that area. We recognize
                                    that plans must be flexible. We do not advocate sticking blindly
                                    to a plan regardless of what happens. All military undertakings
                                    are uncertain. We cannot control what the enemy does nor predict
                                    definitely his reaction. Changes should and must be made. Minor
                                    changes can be made. What we are trying to bring out is that
                                    major changes are terribly destructive and wasteful.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Today the United States and Great Britain have
                                        two forces of limited size located in widely separated areas
                                        facing the European Axis</hi>. Neither of these forces nor
                                    their bases are at present adequate to launch an offensive which
                                    will bring victory, quick and complete. Furthermore, it is
                                    doubtful that they are now sufficient to take full advantage of
                                    an opportunity presented by a major weakening of Axis power. The
                                    price of variations and reversals in decisions is now and will
                                    continue to be the failure to economize in our use of resources
                                    and the failure to concentrate such resources in a way to assure
                                    complete victory. A firm decision with determination to stick to
                                    the agreed <pb facs="0584" n="470" xml:id="pg_470"/> decision is
                                    now a “must.” Any variations, no matter how attractive, may
                                    endanger the entire program. Small diversions create grossly
                                    disproportionate disruptions and delays in preparations for the
                                    decisive effort. These may culminate in unforeseen demands for
                                    major portions of U.S.-British resources. The United States and
                                    Great Britain have now reached the crossroads in the war where
                                    perseverance in the practice of dispersing the limited resources
                                    and reversing or amending decisions, involves a grave danger
                                    that the war will become stalemated or that decisive action
                                    leading to complete victory will be indefinitely
                                    postponed.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">In order to clinch at the earliest practicable
                                        moment, the victory now in sight the United States and Great
                                        Britain must decide on a main effort, must stick to that
                                        decision, must concentrate overwhelming air, sea, and land
                                        power for that main effort, must launch the main effort with
                                        skillful and explosive force, and must assign to all other
                                        efforts the task of preparation for and support of the
                                        decisive blow. A failure to adopt this overall policy will
                                        imperil the final victory.</hi>
                                </item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The United States and Great Britian must, at
                                            <gloss target="#t_Quadrant1">
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Quadrant</hi></gloss>, choose
                                        between attempting a decisive effort from the Mediterranean
                                        and reaffirming again the decision taken in London in April
                                        1942 and affirmed at <gloss target="#t_Anfa1">
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Anfa</hi>
                                        </gloss> and <gloss target="#t_Trident1">
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Trident</hi>
                                        </gloss> Conferences</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d223fn2">See
                                            <ref target="frus1941-43#pg_796">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The
                                            Conferences at Washington, 1941–1942, and Casablanca,
                                            1943, p. 796</ref>, and <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>,
                                            <ref target="#pg_365">p. 365</ref>.</note>
                                    <hi rend="italic">to launch a decisive main effort across the
                                        channel</hi>. The choice made must be supported by a strong
                                    resolution to carry out the decision with completely adequate
                                    resources and without variation or delay.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The allocation of additional forces to the
                                        Mediterranean is uneconomical and assists Germany to create
                                        a strategic stalemate in Europe</hi>. The returns which can
                                    be foreseen from such commitments are based upon speculative
                                    political considerations. The terrain and communications systems
                                    prevent [the] United States and Great Britain from effectively
                                    using large forces and enable the Germans to effect a stalemate
                                    in the rugged areas bordering the Mediterranean using
                                    comparatively small forces which may be little more than present
                                    garrisons. The quantity and effectiveness of aid or opposition
                                    to be expected from Turks, Bulgars, Rumanians, Hungarians,
                                    Croats, Slovenes, Serbs and Greeks cannot be assessed. The area
                                    of operations is distant from major United Nations bases,
                                    particularly those suitable for supporting the first and
                                    critical phases of an amphibious assault.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">In short, the Mediterranean does not offer an
                                        opportunity for decisive military action against Germany,
                                        does not present an opportunity to draw continually
                                        increasing forces from Russia, and does not provide the
                                        opportunity to place effectively in combat the ground forces
                                        of the United States and Britain</hi>. Furthermore,
                                    operations in <pb facs="0585" n="471" xml:id="pg_471"/> the
                                    Mediterranean do not contribute to the defeat of the submarine
                                    and do not force Germany to expose her air force to the
                                    destructive losses inherent in a defense against a decisive
                                    U.S.-British air-ground offensive.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">A cross-channel offensive contributes directly
                                        and with ever-increasing impact toward the essentials of
                                        military victory over the Axis</hi>. It can be launched from
                                    the U.K. which is the only U.S.-British base capable of
                                    unleashing a mass explosive air, sea and land attack directly
                                    against the German army. It will destroy or neutralize the most
                                    important German submarine bases. It will bring on an air battle
                                    which will result in the destruction of the German air force. It
                                    will bring our forces to grips with the German army in an area
                                    where all available British and U.S. air and ground forces can
                                    be used effectively and decisively. Germany must then choose
                                    between a retreat which will allow the assault forces to seize
                                    decisive land areas, and the transfer of divisions from the
                                    Russian front and other areas. Such transfers must quickly lead
                                    to the crumbling of her defenses and the attainment by the
                                    United Nations of complete victory.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The choice between Mediterranean operations
                                        and a decisive cross-channel operation is a decision
                                        between:</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Trusting that the Germans and Russians will continue
                                            to weaken and destroy each other while the U.S. and
                                            Great Britain succeed in crumbling the internal support
                                            of the German war machine by raids, limited operations,
                                            propaganda, sabotage, strategic bombardment and
                                            political disintegration <hi rend="italic">and</hi>
                                        </item>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                        <item>Accepting that Germany cannot be defeated without
                                            bringing to bear against the German army the maximum
                                            military power of the U.S., Britain and Russia with the
                                            objective of defeating the German army by coordinated
                                            offensive air-ground action across the channel and from
                                            the Eastern front.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>An expansion of operations in the Mediterranean is consistent
                                    with the first course of action. This area offers only an
                                    opportunity for gambling that victory can be achieved as a
                                    primary result of psychological and political pressure. The
                                    estimates governing the detailed course of action and the
                                    appraisal of the likelihood of success must be based primarily
                                    on political speculations and hopes concerning the weaknesses of
                                    our enemies and strengths of our allies. Military action is not
                                    and will not be the decisive factor. On the other hand a
                                    cross-channel operation is consistent with the second course of
                                    action set forth above. The opposition to be overcome and the
                                    cost in men and resources can be appraised in terms of military
                                    action. Men, guns and planes and not political and psychological
                                    imponderables, determine ultimate success or failure.</item>
                                <pb facs="0586" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/>
                                <label>11.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">It is very doubtful that the Russian Army
                                        supplemented by the effects of strategic bombardment will,
                                        unaided by a major U.S.-British air-ground operation, be
                                        sufficient to destroy the fighting power of Axis ground
                                        forces</hi>. It is certain that dependence upon the Russian
                                    army alone for major ground operations will result in a
                                    protracted European war and may lead to unilateral action
                                    culminating in peace short of complete victory. Such a course of
                                    action is unacceptable.</item>
                                <label>12.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">It is clear that the soundest course of action
                                        is to mass air, sea and land power in the U.K. for a
                                        cross-channel assault. But even more vital to the
                                        achievement of victory than the particular course of action
                                        chosen, is the pressing necessity of deciding what that
                                        course of action shall be and then sticking vigorously and
                                        wholeheartedly to that decision.</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>