<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-08-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="251" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d251">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">Roosevelt Papers</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chief of Staff, United States Army</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Marshall</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d251fn1">Delivered to the White House Map
                                    Room at Washington; forwarded to Roosevelt, who was then at
                                    Birch Island, as telegram No. <gloss target="#t_White1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">White</hi>
                                    </gloss> 22.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-08-02">2 August
                                    1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum for the President</hi>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Following the receipt of information from the State
                                        Department<note n="2" xml:id="d251fn2">Cicognani’s letter to
                                        Welles of August 2, 1943, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, had
                                        been communicated to Marshall, first by telephone and then
                                        in writing, shortly after its receipt (740.0011 European War
                                        1939/31287).</note> that the Italians intended to declare
                                    Rome an open city, the War Department sent to General Eisenhower
                                    in Algiers the following radio: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“The Italian Government through the Vatican has requested
                                            the U.S. Government to prescribe the essential
                                            conditions to recognizing Rome as an open city. This is
                                            for your information only. Pending further instructions
                                            it would appear desirable to refrain from air <pb facs="0643" n="529" xml:id="pg_529"/> activities
                                            against the city of Rome proper. I am taking this up
                                            with the <gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> but
                                            meanwhile pass this view informally on to you. You
                                            certainly should continue to strike at such airfields in
                                            the vicinity of Rome as give evidence of being used by
                                            either the Germans or Italians.”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>A few minutes after this message was dispatched, the following
                                    message was received from General Eisenhower’s headquarters:
                                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“Stand by flash release Rome raid approximately 1300
                                            hours 3rd August same targets same reasons.”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>As a result of this message, the following was then
                                    transmitted to General Eisenhower, and receipt of this and the
                                    first message has been acknowledged by his headquarters: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“About thirty minutes ago I advised you that the Vatican
                                            through our State Department informed us that the new
                                            Italian Government was prepared to declare Rome an open
                                            city and wished to know the essential requirements. In
                                            that message I passed on to you my view informally to
                                            the effect that pending further instructions it would
                                            appear desirable to refrain from air activities against
                                            the city of Rome proper.</p>
                                        <p>“A few moments ago message number 1735 your headquarters
                                            arrived, ‘From Martelli. Stand by flash release. Rome
                                            raid approximately 1300 hours third of August same
                                            targets same reasons’, message to be passed to <gloss target="#t_OWI1">OWI</gloss>”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>At approximately 5:30 Eastern War Time, following concurrence
                                    with the British Chiefs of Staff, the following additional
                                    message was sent to General Eisenhower: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“The Italian Government through the Vatican has requested
                                            the U.S. Government [to prescribe<note n="3" xml:id="d251fn3">These two words were not in
                                                Marshall’s memorandum, but were inserted when the
                                                memorandum was telegraphed to Roosevelt.</note>] the
                                            essential conditions the Allies will impose before
                                            recognizing Rome as an open city. Pending further
                                            instructions the Combined Chiefs of Staff desire that
                                            you refrain from air activities against the city of Rome
                                            proper. You should continue to strike at such airfields
                                            in the vicinity of Rome as give evidence of being used
                                            by either the Germans or the Italians. Please
                                                acknowledge,”<note n="4" xml:id="d251fn4">
                                                <p>A typed notation on the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">J.C.S.</gloss> file copy of telegram No. <gloss target="#t_White1">
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">White</hi>
                                                  </gloss> 22 indicates that the Secretary of the
                                                  Joint Chiefs of Staff (Deane) telephoned the
                                                  following additional paragraph to the White House
                                                  Map Room for inclusion in Marshall’s message to
                                                  Roosevelt: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“Since dispatching the above the Prime Minister
                                                  called me by phone and stated the British Cabinet
                                                  and he personally thinks it may be a good thing at
                                                  this moment to go ahead with the bombing.
                                                  Accordingly and pending your instruction to the
                                                  contrary, I have taken the responsibility of
                                                  authorizing Eisenhower to go ahead if he desires
                                                  to do so. Signed Marshall.”</p>
                                                  </quote>
                                                </p>
                                                <p>For Marshall’s message to Eisenhower, see <hi rend="italic">infra.</hi>
                                                </p>
                                            </note>
                                        </p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>G C <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                                </signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chief of Staff</hi>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>