<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Minister ( (Campbell) ) to the Adviser on Political Relations (
                    (Dunn))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d256</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">256</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="256"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d256">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 <gloss target="#t_EW1"
                    >EW</gloss>/8–343</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The British Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Campbell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Adviser on Political Relations</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dunn</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-08-03">August 3rd,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Jimmy</hi>, I enclose a copy of a telegram from the
                    Foreign Office on the subject of an approach made to our Ambassador at
                        Lisbon.<note n="1" xml:id="d256fn1">Sir Ronald Hugh Campbell.</note>
                    Although the peace feeler described in this telegram has been overtaken by
                    events, the Foreign Office thought that you would be interested to have an
                    account of it.</p>
                <p>I also enclose a copy of a telegram received from the Ambassador in Ankara
                    recording approaches made by the Italian Ambassador there to the Turkish
                    Minister for Foreign Affairs. You may have received a report of this from Ankara
                    through your own channels,<note n="2" xml:id="d256fn2">See <hi rend="italic"
                            >ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_531">p. 531</ref>.</note> but if not you
                    may find it interesting to have this telegram.</p>
                <p>Yours ever,</p>
                <closer>(for <signed>Sir R. Campbell</signed>) <lb/>
                    <signed>W G <hi rend="smallcaps">Hayter</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1—Telegram]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The British Foreign Secretary</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Eden</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the British Ambassador in the United
                            States</hi> (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi>
                        </persName>)<note n="3" xml:id="d256fn3">Received by the British Embassy at
                            Washington on July 31, 1943.</note>
                    </head>
                    <p>Dr. Salazar sent for His Majesty’s Ambassador on July 22nd and said that he
                        washed to speak about the situation in Italy as a result of an approach
                        which had been made to him by certain elements in the country. He did not
                        feel able to reveal the identity of these persons until he knew whether His
                        Majesty’s Government were interested in the approach. The Ambassador
                        surmised that Crown Prince and certain army leaders, perhaps with the
                        complicity of the King were authors of the approach.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Salazar suggested that to insist on “unconditional surrender” would only
                        serve to unite all the Italians. Resistance might then continue <pb
                            facs="0649" n="535" xml:id="pg_535"/> until there was a complete
                        breakdown and chaos followed. In these circumstances, we should be obliged
                        to condemn the whole country for a considerable period and Dr. Salazar
                        wondered whether it would not suit us better to have some entity to deal
                        with (possibly a military government) which with our help could carry on
                        life of the country.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Salazar said that he quite understood that Mussolini and his gang must be
                        eliminated. Of the remaining elements in Italy he thought that only dynasty
                        and the army were capable of effective action and then only if they were
                        given some incentive to do so.</p>
                    <p>Finally, Dr. Salazar said that he had not undertaken to pass on this approach
                        but felt it was his duty to do so. In reply His Majesty’s Ambassador
                        explained our attitude and said that while he would of course pass on Dr.
                        Salazar’s communication, he did not think that His Majesty’s Government
                        would be interested since he did not suppose any grounds would be seen for
                        modifying decision not to negotiate in advance of complete surrender
                        whatever government was responsible for the offer of surrender.</p>
                    <p>A similar approach to the Embassy has been made by M. Pangal, the former
                        Roumanian Minister in Lisbon, representing the views of Signor Prunas and
                        Signor Fransoni, the present and former Italian Ministers to Portugal.</p>
                    <p>M. Pangal reported that both Italian diplomats had shown anxiety about the
                        meaning of an “honourable peace” which was the way in which they had
                        interpreted message from the President and the Prime Minister.<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d256fn4">For the text of the Roosevelt-Churchill joint message
                            to the people of Italy, July 16, 1943, see Department of State <hi
                                rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, July
                            17, 1943, pp. 27–28; Rosenman, pp. 305–306.</note> Their chief anxiety
                        had been to learn whether by capitulation Italy could be prevented from
                        becoming a battlefield between the Allies and Germany and whether Allied
                        military occupation could be limited to a part of the country and that the
                        remainder should be left under an Italian administration.</p>
                    <p>In reply, M. Pangal was told that the keystone to our policy remained
                        “unconditional surrender” and that this could only be negotiated by
                        government other than that of Mussolini. It was also pointed out to him that
                        if Italians did not capitulate nothing could save the whole of the country
                        from becoming a battlefield subject to attacks by both sides.</p>
                    <p>His Majesty’s Ambassador adds that M. Pangal has also been in touch with
                        German Minister<note n="5" xml:id="d256fn5">Oswald, Baron von Hoyningen
                            genannt Huene.</note> and it is therefore probable that the latter knows
                        and probably agrees with approach made by M. Pangal to try to sound his
                        “English friends” about terms which would be <pb facs="0650" n="536"
                            xml:id="pg_536"/> accorded to Germany in the event of her throwing over
                        Hitler and the Nazi party.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2—Telegram]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName
                            type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Knatchbull-Hugessen</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the British Foreign Secretary</hi>
                            (<persName type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Eden</hi>
                        </persName>)<note n="6" xml:id="d256fn6">Repetition received by the British
                            Embassy at Washington on August 2, 1943. On August 4 Campbell informed
                            Dunn, with reference to this message: “Mr. Eden has asked me to let you
                            know that His Majesty’s Government attach no importance to these
                            conversations.” (740.00119 <gloss target="#t_EW1"
                            >EW</gloss>/8–443)</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">most secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Minister for Foreign Affairs sent for me on his return from Istanbul this
                        morning.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>While there he had had two conversations with the Italian
                            Ambassador.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>First on July 21st when the Ambassador had said that Italy was
                            finished. In reply to appeal for tanks the Germans had stated they could
                            supply 15 <hi rend="italic">per mensem</hi> in 1944 but nothing until
                            then. Ambassador asked if the Turkish press could publish unfavourable
                            comments on the bombardment of Rome. Minister for Foreign Affairs said
                            that this would be entirely out of place.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Second conversation was on the morning of July 27th. Ambassador stated
                            that he was not yet in touch with Marshal Badoglio and did not know his
                            views but he was sufficiently acquainted with the situation to be able
                            to talk.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>In Italy there was no Anglo-American problem. It was impossible for
                            Italy to stand up against maritime powers.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Also there was no Fascist problem. Fascisim had collapsed and could
                            not be revived.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>On the other hand there was the German problem. Italian Ambassador
                            asked whether the Minister for Foreign Affairs could not appeal to the
                            United States and to ourselves to adopt an “understanding” policy.
                            Minister for Foreign Affairs asked what he meant by this. Ambassador
                            explained that if we pressed the war in Italy too hard and too rapidly
                            the country would become squeezed between the Allies and the Germans.
                            There were Germans in every Government office, railway station, bank,
                            etc., and they were all armed. Ambassador also spoke of large German
                            concentrations in the south of France. If we landed in Southern Italy,
                            Italy would be powerless to resist and the result would be that Italy
                            would become the battleground between the Allies and the Germans. In
                            such circumstances Italy could do nothing and would unavoidably be
                            destroyed.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>Minister for Foreign Affairs remarked that the Ambassador was using
                            arguments of beaten man. It would serve little purpose <pb facs="0651"
                                n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> to put up such arguments to us. Could he
                            make some more concrete suggestion?</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>In reply the Ambassador muttered something about Sardinia. Minister
                            for Foreign Affairs owing to his deafness had to make the Ambassador
                            repeat it three times. Upshot was that the Italian Ambassador was
                            suggesting that if the Allies followed the policy of carrying the war on
                                <hi rend="italic">slowly</hi> Italy would escape the above fate and
                            avoid the impossible task of turning the Germans out in quick time; she
                            could continue on the surface as an Ally of Germany but would in point
                            of fact help in turning the Germans out gradually and would move towards
                            cooperation with the Allies. He suggested that if the Allies did not
                            attack the Italian mainland but invaded Sardinia there would be no
                            Italian resistance nor would there be opposition to action against the
                            Greek islands in the Southern Mediterranean (Crete, etc.). In this way
                            the Allies could strengthen their general position round Italy against
                            Germany without Italian opposition while Italy did what she could to get
                            the Germans out gradually. Minister for Foreign Affairs in speaking to
                            me summed up the Ambassador’s proposals as a “policy of
                            treachery”.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Italian Ambassador said that after reaching Rome he would establish
                            contact with Osborne who is old friend. He leaves immediately. Germans
                            have refused to supply petrol for his flight.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Minister for Foreign Affairs undertook to pass the above on to me. I
                            said that J would refrain from comment except to remark that the Italian
                            Ambassador would since have seen the Prime Minister’s speech.<note n="7"
                                xml:id="d256fn7">See Churchill’s speech of July 27, 1943, reported
                                in <hi rend="italic">Parliamentary Debates: House of Commons,
                                    Official Report</hi>, 5th series, vol. 391, cols.
                                1397–1402.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
