<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-08-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="518" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d518">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">863.01/8–2043</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <persName type="from">Archduke Otto</persName> of Austria to the
                                        <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Quebec</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-08-20">August 20th,
                                        1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Hull</hi>, Enclosed I am sending to
                                you two short <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoires</hi> on questions
                                which I believe are of a great importance for the cause of the
                                United Nations in Central Europe.</p>
                            <p>I most sincerely hope that it will be possible for you to consider
                                these questions at the present conference and to bring to them an
                                adequate solution.</p>
                            <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Otto</hi>
                                </signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">of Austria</hi>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                                </head>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Austrian Question</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The military and political events of the near past have put
                                    Austria into the forefront of the interest of the United
                                    Nations. As approximatively 84,8% of the German implements of
                                    war for Italy are shipped <pb facs="1226" n="1112" xml:id="pg_1112"/> over the Austrian railroads, much will
                                    depend on the attitude and action of the Austrian people.</p>
                                <p>The trend of the United Nations has been to recognize the heroic
                                    fight of Austria against the Germans by considering that country
                                    as an occupied country, which shall be liberated. But as this
                                    point has not yet been made sufficiently clear, certain agencies
                                    have used this to spread false impressions.</p>
                                <p>News from Russia indicate that the Soviet Government is about to
                                    launch an Austrian Government or National Council under the
                                    presidency of Wilhelm Koplenig (36 Gorkova ulica, Moscow),
                                    former leader of the Austrian Communist Party. Such a move would
                                    very much strengthen the Austrian Communist Party—which hitherto
                                    was negligible—and would disturb the Catholic, agrarian and
                                    patriotic opposition. The fear of Communist dictatorship would
                                    gravely weaken the Austrian resistance against the Axis.</p>
                                <p>Under these circumstances and with due regard to the ever
                                    increasing strategic importance of Austria, the following
                                    program with regard to Austria is submitted: <list>
                                        <label>1.)</label>
                                        <item>A clear declaration at the Quebec Conference, that
                                            Austria is an occupied country and will therefore be
                                            liberated, like the other occupied countries.</item>
                                        <label>2.)</label>
                                        <item>A settlement of the question of Southern Tyrol, along
                                            the lines suggested in the annexed memorandum on that
                                            question.</item>
                                        <label>3.)</label>
                                        <item>The recognition by the United Nations of a provisional
                                            Austrian authority. This authority should be
                                            non-partisan and represent Austria only as long as its
                                            people is silenced. It should not have authority to
                                            commit Austria on constitutional questions. In order to
                                            achieve this aim, a Committee of all former Austrian
                                            diplomats and consuls, who have kept their nationality
                                            and resisted the Nazis, could be formed, linking thus
                                            the legality of the past with the condition of
                                            non-partisan character.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>Such a program would avoid the harm which might be clone by a
                                    Russian unilateral step, without too much antagonizing Russia.
                                    It would strengthen Austria’s resistance against the Axis and
                                    thus help the progress of the war. It is finally in line with
                                    the lofty principles announced by the leaders of the United
                                    Nations.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                                </head>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Question of Southern Tyrol</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">Alto Adige</hi>)</p>
                                <p>In the coming discussions of the United Nations, the question of
                                    establishing just and reasonable borders for Italy and her
                                    neighbours will be of great importance for the foundation of a
                                    lasting peace.</p>
                                <p>In this connection the question of Southern Tyrol, called by the
                                        <pb facs="1227" n="1113" xml:id="pg_1113"/> Italians Alto
                                    Adige, will be of paramount importance. This land was conceded
                                    to Italy in the last peace treaty over the protest of its
                                    Austrian population and of several Allied leaders. Under Italian
                                    occupation the Southern Tyrolese population was severely
                                    persecuted, dispossessed and partly replaced by Italians. Under
                                    an agreement between Mussolini and Hitler<note n="1" xml:id="d518fn1">The reference is to an Italo-German
                                        agreement reached at Berlin on June 23, 1939. See <hi rend="italic">Documents on German Foreign Policy,
                                            1918–1945</hi>, series D, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 778–779.</note> a notable part of the
                                    population was forcibly moved to Germany between 1939 and 1942,
                                    where they still live under very hard and inhuman conditions.
                                    Southern Tyrol has therefore suffered more than many other parts
                                    of Europe from Axis cruelty.</p>
                                <p>Southern Tyrol can be divided roughly into two parts: <list>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>South of the present Austrian border and North of a
                                            line Adamello Mountains–Salurn–Cortina d’Ampezzo, is a
                                            country with 85% Austrian population, deeply attached to
                                            Austria.</item>
                                        <label>
                                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>South of the above mentioned line and North of the
                                            Italian border of 1914 is a country which, contrary to
                                            Italian propaganda, has still 54% Austrian
                                            population.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>It is therefore a matter of justice, well in line with the
                                    principles of the United Nations, that this territory should be
                                    returned to Austria. It would be also a matter of political
                                    wisdom. Neither the Southern Tyrolese, nor the Austrians have
                                    ever accepted the present border. If good relations ought to be
                                    established between Austria and Italy, this can only be done by
                                    solving the Southern Tyrolese question in an Austrian sense.
                                    This would furthermore strengthen Austria materially and morally
                                    against Germany.</p>
                                <p>If the necessity of a plebiscite in the Southern zone of Southern
                                    Tyrol would be felt, care should be taken that only real
                                    Southern Tyrolese could vote. The right to vote restricted to
                                    residents as of 1918 and to their descendants would be the
                                    guarantee that the voters really represent the Southern Tyrolese
                                    people.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>