<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Ambassador in Portugal ( (Campbell) ) to the British Foreign
                    Office</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d540</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">540</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="540"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d540">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 <gloss target="#t_EW1"
                    >EW</gloss>/8–2643: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Campbell</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">British Foreign
                            Office</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d540fn1">Received by the Foreign Office on August 26, 1943.
                        Printed from a copy made available to the Department of State by the British
                        Embassy at Washington.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                        calendar="gregorian" when="1943-08-26">August 26, 1943</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">most secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>General Carton de Wiart has turned up in company with another Italian General.
                    They left Rome by air yesterday morning and arrived at Lisbon this morning.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>General C. de Wiart was released a few days ago from his prisoner camp,
                        taken to Rome, fitted out with civilian clothes and Italian name and
                        diplomatic passport and told that he was to accompany to Lisbon and if
                        possible to London an Italian General who was empowered to parley armistice
                        terms.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Italian General whose name is Zanussi is principal assistant to General
                        Roatta who is Chief of the General Staff in Chief to General Ambennio[<hi
                            rend="italic">Ambrosio</hi>] who is Chief of Army Staff.<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d540fn2">The references are to Mario Roatta, Chief of the Army
                            General Staff, and Vittorio Ambrosio, Chief of the Armed Forces General
                            Staff.</note> General Zanussi knows all about General C.<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d540fn3">Giuseppe Castellano. Concerning Castellano’s mission to
                            Lisbon, see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1070">pp.
                                1070</ref> ff.</note> and General C. de Wiart was told that the dove
                        had been sent out (General C.) but as it had not returned another was being
                        despatched (General Z.) In point of fact General C. must have arrived
                        (barring accidents) a few hours after the departure of General Z.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I have told General C. de Wiart in broad terms of the result of General
                        C.’s visit and that unless instructed by you to do so I see no point in
                        receiving General Z. as this might introduce unnecessary complications.
                        General C. de Wiart will so inform General Z. at late meeting arranged for
                        tonight in the flat of a member of my staff. General Z. will be told to
                        remain here until it is certain that there is no message for him.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
