<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-09-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-09-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="584" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d584">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_JCS1">J.C.S.</gloss> Files</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Note by the Secretaries of the Combined Chiefs of
                                    Staff</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d584fn1">For the action taken on
                                    this paper at the 117th and 118th Meetings of the Combined
                                    Chiefs of Staff, September 3 and 10, 1943, see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_1205">pp. 1205</ref>, <ref target="#pg_1221">1221</ref>.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 331</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-09-01">1 September
                                        1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Netherlands Marine Landing Force</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The enclosure received from the Netherlands Staff Mission is referred
                                to the Combined Chiefs of Staff for consideration.</p>
                            <p>It is suggested that the Secretaries be directed to draft a reply
                                along the following lines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Combined Chiefs of Staff have noted with interest that
                                        the Netherlands Military and Naval authorities are working
                                        on plans for raising an Army to participate in the war
                                        against Japan following the liberation of Holland. They will
                                        be pleased to review these plans upon their completion and
                                        give them such support as is justified in the prosecution of
                                        the war.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">H. Redman</hi>
                                    <lb/> J. <hi rend="smallcaps">R. Deane</hi>
                                </signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Combined Secretariat</hi>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Enclosure</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                        <lb/> No. 917–5/8</seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-08-30">30 August
                                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Netherlands Representatives</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Stoeve and Dijxhoorn</hi>) <hi rend="italic">to the Combined Chiefs of Staff</hi>
                                </p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Emanating from an earnest desire to contribute in the
                                        largest possible degree to the war effort, the Netherlands
                                        Government has <pb facs="1353" n="1239" xml:id="pg_1239"/>
                                        instructed its Naval and Military authorities to work out a
                                        plan for the speedy raising of an Army to participate in the
                                        war against Japan immediately after the liberation of
                                        Holland, as the first step in the re-mobilization of Dutch
                                        manpower. As soon as this plan will have been completed and
                                        approved by the Netherlands Government, it will be submitted
                                        to the Combined Chiefs of Staff in Washington.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Since they will most likely fight under American
                                        operational command, it is highly desirable that their
                                        training, indoctrination and armament be similar to that of
                                        the United States Forces. Consequently, the assistance of
                                        the United States will be essential in the execution of this
                                        plan with regard to the training and the supply of equipment
                                        and weapons.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>As a first step towards the execution of this plan, the
                                        Netherlands Government has decided to form, soonest after
                                        the liberation of Holland, a Marine Landing Force of 5,000
                                        men.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>On behalf of the Netherlands Government the cooperation of
                                        the Combined Chiefs of Staff is requested in order to
                                        secure, even now, the most necessary assistance from the
                                        United States authorities for building up this Force.</item>
                                </list>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>G. W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Stoeve</hi>
                                    </signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Rear Admiral, <gloss target="#t_RNN1">R.N.N.</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed>A. Q. H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dijxhoorn</hi>
                                    </signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Major General, <gloss target="#t_RNA1">R.N.A.</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>