<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-09-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-09-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="593" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d593">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War
                                1939/31526¼</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-09-04">September 4,
                                        1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum of Conversation</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Danish Request for Statement From the
                                President</p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Secretary of State Hull and the
                                        Minister of Denmark, Mr. Henrik de Kauffmann</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>The Minister of Denmark called at his request. He said it meant a
                                great deal to his people to receive encouragement just now and
                                especially such encouragement as would be given by a brief statement
                                that the President and Mr. Churchill might together or individually
                                put out. He handed me a copy of a draft which he said he gave to the
                                President yesterday (copy attached). I showed every interest in the
                                situation and said that he had fully presented the idea to the
                                President, that the matter is perfectly simple and calls for no
                                conference between the President and myself, and that the President
                                himself will decide whether or not to put it out and that if he does
                                not do so, the <pb facs="1367" n="1253" xml:id="pg_1253"/> matter
                                will have to remain in abeyance until later when it could be revived
                                on some suitable occasion.<note n="1" xml:id="d593fn1">Concerning
                                    other conversations on this subject which Kauffmann had with
                                    officers of the Department of State while Churchill was in
                                    Washington, see <ref target="frus1943v02#pg_10">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 10</ref>–<ref target="frus1943v02#pg_11">11</ref>, <ref target="frus1943v02#pg_13">13</ref>. Hull was informed on
                                    September 10, 1943, that at Roosevelt’s suggestion Kauffmann had
                                    also discussed the matter of a statement with Cadogan
                                    (859.00/1068). No indication has been found that Roosevelt
                                    discussed this subject with Churchill, and Hull’s
                                    recommendations were not forwarded to Roosevelt until September
                                    15, 1943, after Churchill had left the United States. See <ref target="frus1943v02#pg_14">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 14</ref>–<ref target="frus1943v02#pg_15">15</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Minister was greatly appreciative of what I had said on this same
                                subject during the past three days.<note n="2" xml:id="d593fn2">The
                                    reference is to Hull’s statement to a press and radio news
                                    conference on September 2, 1943, and to his letter of that date
                                    to Kauffmann, which was released to the press. See Department of
                                    State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, September 4, 1943, pp. 152–153; <ref target="frus1943v02#pg_10">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 10</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ull</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Statement</hi>
                                </head>
                                <p>The Danish people, long subjected to the Nazi yoke, have revolted
                                    against their oppressors in a way that has stirred the
                                    admiration of the Free World. The sympathy of all free men go
                                    forward to the Danish Nation and their gallant King, who, though
                                    made virtually a prisoner in his own country, continue[s] to
                                    fill the hearts of his people with his defiant spirit, which the
                                    tyrants have been unable to break.</p>
                                <p>Since the occupation of Denmark on April 9, 1940, the Danes in
                                    the Free World, through their contributions to the Allied war
                                    effort, have voiced the suppressed feelings of their countrymen
                                    at home. Greenland has taken her place as a bastion in the
                                    Atlantic battle.</p>
                                <p>In December 1941, Mr. Churchill and I invited the Danish Minister
                                    in Washington, Mr. Henrik Kauffmann, to join the United Nations
                                    declaration (of January 1, 1942). In accepting, Mr. Kauffmann
                                    referred to the fact that the Danish Government in occupied
                                    Denmark were under German duress, and thus not free to sign the
                                    Declaration by the United Nations. Mr. Kauffmann proclaimed that
                                    the Danish Nation, “though subjugated, now more than ever,
                                    believes in the principles and purposes of the Atlantic Charter.
                                    Danes in the free world feel pledged to contribute the best of
                                    their efforts in the common struggle for victory over Hitlerism,
                                    adhering to the principles of the Declaration of January 1, 1942
                                    as if the Declaration had been signed by a free Danish
                                    Government.”</p>
                                <pb facs="1368" n="1254" xml:id="pg_1254"/>
                                <p>All remnants of a Danish Government in Copenhagen have now ceased
                                    to exist. As trustees for Danish interests outside Denmark, the
                                    Danish Ministers in Washington and London and Danish official
                                    representatives elsewhere, working for the liberation of Denmark
                                    together with Free Danish organizations all over the world, may
                                    count upon our fullest support.</p>
                                <p>Our thoughts and our good wishes go to the people of Denmark in
                                    their struggle; they have clearly demonstrated to the world that
                                    they fully endorse the declaration of the Danish Minister in
                                    Washington on January 2, 1942. Every Dane, whether in his home
                                    country or abroad, who contributes to our common cause is an
                                    ally in name as well as in fact. We welcome Denmark’s
                                    time-honoured flag, “Dannebrog”, by the side of the banners of
                                    the United Nations.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>