<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>249. Memorandum From Acting Secretary of the Treasury Barr to President to
                    President Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d249</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">249</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="249"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d249">
                <head>249. Memorandum From Acting Secretary of the Treasury <persName type="from"
                        >Barr</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to"
                        >Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d249fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Memos to the President, <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                            Bundy</persName>, Vol. 14. No classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-09-10">September 10, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Last night at about 11 p.m. London time, the Bank of England and the Chancellor
                    of the Exchequer wrapped up a multilateral package to support the pound
                    sterling. The package should total between $900 million and $1 billion with the
                    exact amounts and form of participation of some countries not yet finally
                    settled. The countries participating are Austria, Belgium, Canada, Germany,
                    Holland, Italy, Japan, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United States, plus the Bank
                    for International Settlements. The Bank of France was originally in the package
                    but pulled out of the deal yesterday morning.</p>
                <p>United States participation in the package will total roughly $400 million in
                    line with our agreement. This amount will be divided between the Federal Reserve
                    and the Exchange Stabilization Fund of the Treasury.</p>
                <p>The Federal Reserve Bank in New York began operations this morning in the spot
                    sterling market and very limited operations have brought good results thus far
                    in terms of a higher rate for sterling. The rate has moved from 2.7918 to a
                    recent bid of 2.7940. We are hoping that this improvement in the rate will give
                    the speculators [no?] reason for concern and by accelerating a return of the
                    confidence in sterling will trigger a re—flow of funds to the United
                    Kingdom.</p>
                <pb facs="0542" n="506" xml:id="pg_506"/>
                <p>This negotiation has been much more difficult than that of last November but we
                    are hopeful that the package will carry the pound through the uncertainties of
                    the next few months.</p>
                <p>While this operation has started well, the first real test may come as early as
                    Monday or Tuesday, when the British trade figures will be announced. We have no
                    information as yet of these figures.</p>
                <p>A release issued by the Bank of England is attached plus our own response to
                    press inquiries.<note n="2" xml:id="d249fn2">Not attached.</note> We will not
                    add any comments to these statements and feel that the details of this operation
                    must be held very close-especially the figures.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Joseph W. Barr</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
