<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-12-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-12-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="252" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                        <head>252. Memorandum Prepared by the Executive Secretary of the Department
                            of State (<persName corresp="#p_RBH1">Read</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d252fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1964-66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>. Secret. <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName>’s record of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_WH1">Wilson</persName>’s visit is in Department of
                                State, <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName> Diaries: Lot 64
                                D 327. <persName corresp="#p_BF1">Bator</persName>’s notes on part
                                of President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s
                                December 16 meeting with <persName corresp="#p_WH1">Wilson</persName> are in the Johnson Library, Bator Papers,
                                Europe. A portion of the <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>-<persName>Wilson</persName> private meetings
                                dealing with nuclear sharing is in <ref target="frus1964-68v13#d117">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. XIII,
                                    Document 117</ref>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" from="1965-12-15" to="1965-12-19" type="content-date">undated</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">VISIT OF PRIME MINISTER <persName corresp="#p_WH1">WILSON</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">December 15-19, 1965</p>
                        <p>The following is a list of the meetings in which Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_WH1">Wilson</persName> participated during his visit to
                            Washington: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">December 16</hi>—5:15-7:00 p.m. President and
                                    Prime Minister alone for approximately an hour and thereafter
                                    with officials.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">December 17</hi>—Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName> met with the
                                    Prime Minister at the British Embassy.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">December 17</hi>—1:00-3:30 p.m. Lunch at White
                                    House with conversation continuing thereafter. President and
                                    Prime Minister spoke privately before lunch.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The notes are based on the comments of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName> and Assistant Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> who attended some but
                            not all of the meetings listed. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName> was present at the White House on December 16 and
                            also attended the lunch on December 17. He was not present at the
                            meeting at the British Embassy the morning of December 16 which was
                            largely concerned with the British defense review. Assistant Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> attended only the lunch
                            on December 17 and the discussion which followed.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Rhodesia</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This subject was discussed on both days with the Prime Minister
                            expressing his appreciation for US backing, particularly on the oil
                            sanctions and the airlift for Zambia.<note n="2" xml:id="d252fn2">For
                                text of the statement issued by the Department of State on December
                                17, see <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy</hi>: Current
                                Documents, 1965, pp. 693-694.</note> (In his press briefing on
                            December 17, the Prime Minister said in response to a question that
                            United States planes would be used in the airlift.) The Prime Minister
                            took an optimistic view of the prospects of bringing down the <persName corresp="#p_SBK1">Smith</persName> regime in a short time through
                            economic action. While the Prime Minister did not give a specific time
                            estimate, Oliver Wright subsequently told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName> that the British Government
                            hoped to achieve this result in a matter of weeks.</p>
                        <pb facs="0547" n="511" xml:id="pg_511"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">British Defense Review</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>At the White House meetings attended by officials the Prime Minister did
                            not go into details on the defense review but said he understood the
                            importance we attach to a continuation of British defense commitments
                            and gave assurances that the British world-wide role would be
                            maintained. He said that there would be readjustments in the British
                            defense posture East of Suez but that they would maintain their
                            presence. In the long run, Singapore might become very tricky and the
                                <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> had no real assurance that it
                            could be used in case of need. As a consequence the British Government
                            had been considering the possibility of an alternative base in Northern
                            Australia. The Australians, he said, had shown interest in this
                            possibility. He expressed interest in the possibility of defense talks
                            with Australia and New Zealand and, by implication, with the US on the
                            defense problems of the area. The Prime Minister indicated that he was
                            thinking, in connection with a base in Australia, of the post 1970
                            period. With respect to Aden, the Prime Minister said that this could
                            not be regarded as a long-term base. In the Persian Gulf there continues
                            to be a need to afford some protection to Iran and Kuwait. The Prime
                            Minister thought Bahrein would have some use in this connection but that
                            generally it should be possible to lighten the British presence in the
                            Gulf.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName> noted that the
                            Prime Minister was careful in phrasing his remarks on the defense review
                            to indicate a desire to have our comments while avoiding any commitment
                            that British decisions would conform to our views. In the meeting at the
                            British Embassy on the morning of December 17, it was agreed that
                            Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SM2">Stewart</persName> and
                            Defense Minister <persName corresp="#p_HDW1">Healey</persName> would
                            visit Washington in January for more detailed talks with Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Nuclear Sharing</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This subject was apparently discussed privately by the President and the
                            Prime Minister. In the subsequent discussion with officials on December
                            16, the Prime Minister said that the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                            preferred a consultative arrangement to a “hardware” solution but that
                            if necessary it was prepared to support its 1964 proposal for an <gloss target="#t_ANF1">ANF</gloss>. The Prime Minister indicated that he
                            and the President would have further contact on the nuclear problem in
                            the Alliance as the situation developed and after the President had
                            discussed the matter with Chancellor Erhard.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Vietnam</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In replying to press queries the Prime Minister took a strong line in
                            support of US efforts to pursue peace in Vietnam and said that his
                            Government was quite satisfied with the willingness repeatedly expressed
                            by the United States to go to the conference table. He cited the <pb facs="0548" n="512" xml:id="pg_512"/> efforts made by his Government
                            to bring about negotiations and said these efforts would continue with
                            the full support of the President. These press responses were along the
                            lines earlier indicated by the Prime Minister in talks with the
                            President and US officials. The discussions reflected continued
                            understanding and support for the US position in Southeast Asia and
                            appreciation on our part that notwithstanding domestic political
                            pressures the Wilson Government has been constant in maintaining this
                            attitude. The Prime Minister did, however, indicate that any bombing of
                            Hanoi or Haiphong would create the most serious problems for him and his
                            Government in determining what line they would be obliged to adopt.</p>
                        <p>As a result of the discussions with US officials the British agreed to
                            give further consideration to increasing their contribution to the Asian
                            Development Bank from $10 million to $30 million.</p>
                        <p>The foregoing appear to be the principal subjects covered in the
                            discussions although other matters such as the India-Pakistan dispute
                            were also touched on briefly.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>