<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>315. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-01-22T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-01-22T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-01-22T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-01-22T10:00:00-05:00" n="315"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d315">
                <head>315. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d315fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Conference Files: Lot 66 D 110, CF 3258.
                        Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_TWR1">Tyler</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_AWC1">Armstrong</persName> and approved in U. The
                        memorandum is Part 4 of 14. Part 13 is <ref target="#d316">Document
                            316</ref>; the other memoranda of conversation are ibid. The meeting was
                        held at the White House. Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_PLB1"
                            >Pearson</persName> visited Washington January 21-23. <persName
                            corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName>’s recollections of the meeting are
                        in <hi rend="italic">Mike: The Memoirs of the Right Honorable <persName
                                corresp="#p_PLB1">Lester B. Pearson</persName>
                        </hi>, Vol. 3, pp. 119-123.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1964-01-22T10:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 22, 1964, 10 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Far East and Southeast Asia</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States Side</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">George W. Ball</persName>, Under
                                Secretary of State</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BWW1">W. Walton Butterworth</persName>, United
                                States Ambassador to Canada</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_JGG1">G. Griffith Johnson</persName>,
                                Assistant Secretary, E</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_TWR1">William R. Tyler</persName>, Assistant
                                Secretary, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BWH1">William H. Brubeck</persName>, The White
                                House</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_AWC1">Willis C. Armstrong</persName>,
                                Director, <gloss target="#t_BNA1">BNA</gloss>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Canadian Side</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Lester B. Pearson</persName>, Prime
                                Minister of Canada (part of the time)</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Paul Martin</persName>, Secretary of
                                State for External Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RCSA1">Charles S. A. Ritchie</persName>,
                                Ambassador of Canada</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName>R. Gordon Robertson</persName>, Clerk of the Privy
                                Council</item>
                            <item>Tom Kent, Coordinator of Government Policy</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RAE1">A. E. Ritchie</persName>, Assistant
                                Under Secretary of State for External Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RHB1">H. Basil Robinson</persName>, Minister,
                                Canadian Embassy</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName>O. W. Dier</persName>, Special Assistant to the Prime
                                Minister</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>While President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> and Prime Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName> were talking together in
                    President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s office,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d315fn2">No record of this private talk was found.</note> the Under
                    Secretary proposed to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> that
                    they discuss certain subjects of mutual interest.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> mentioned the intention of
                    President <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> to recognize
                    Communist China.<note n="3" xml:id="d315fn3">France extended diplomatic
                        recognition to the People’s Republic of China on January 27.</note> He said
                    it looked as though this were now inevitable, <pb facs="0708" n="672"
                        xml:id="pg_672"/> and that this could “upset a few apple carts.” He said
                    that according to our information <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                        Gaulle</persName> probably intended to make an announcement, and then go
                    into the matter further in his press conference. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> said that this indeed seemed to be the
                    case. He said he thought that, however disagreeable such a development was bound
                    to be for the United States, he hoped that the United States Government would
                    not unduly dramatize the occasion by reacting too violently. He asked Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> what he thought would be the
                    effect on Southeast Asia and the Far East generally of <persName
                        corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s decision. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> said that it would be considered by Saigon
                    as a clear indication of a trend toward some kind of neutralist solution in
                    Southeast Asia, and that this would gravely affect the morale of the government
                    and people of South Viet Nam and thus hamper current United States efforts to
                    help the Vietnamese to achieve victory over Communism. He said the United States
                    reaction would undoubtedly be very severe. It would also seriously complicate
                    the situation in the United Nations, in the event that African and other
                    countries followed France’s lead. He said that President <persName
                        corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> was concerned by what the position of
                    the Canadian Government would be in the United Nations on the recognition
                    issue.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> said that the Canadian
                    Government felt that there was much to be said for the basic premises underlying
                        <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s views. He said it was not
                    possible to isolate Communist China forever. He said that contacts had already
                    been established between Ottawa and Peiping. As an example he cited the
                    forthcoming exchange between the Canadian Press Agency and the New China News
                    Agency, whereby each would have a representative in the other’s country. He said
                    it was important to watch carefully how things would develop. The Canadian
                    Government was fully aware of the possible implications of the French move for
                    the United States and for the Alliance as a whole. He could not at this time say
                    what the evolving posture and attitude of the Canadian Government would be in
                    the future. He could not honestly say now what the Canadian Government would do
                    eventually in the General Assembly. He hoped that such a situation would not
                    arise until after November. He said that Canada wanted to establish increasing
                    contacts with China because it sincerely felt that it was not a practical or
                    farsighted policy to continue to ignore the Chinese indefinitely. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> went on to say that when he had talked
                    with French Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve de
                        Murville</persName> in Paris,<note n="4" xml:id="d315fn4">They apparently
                        met during the <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> Ministerial meeting
                        December 13-18, 1963.</note> he had not said as much as he had just said to
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>. He did say to <persName
                        corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve</persName> that he hoped that the French Government
                    would carefully weigh the effect on the Alliance <pb facs="0709" n="673"
                        xml:id="pg_673"/> and on the US attitude of its proposed action. However he
                    had not told the French that what they intended to do was wrong. He said the
                    Prime Minister and he had told the French that the Canadian Government at this
                    present time had not changed its policy on the question of recognition of
                    Communist China, or with regard to Communist Chinese admission to the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> said that it was still not clear
                    what Taiwan planned to do if France recognized Peiping.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> said he was pessimistic on
                    the chances of survival of the present government in South Viet Nam. He said
                    that it did not enjoy the confidence of the Vietnamese people.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> refuted this assertion and went
                    on to say that an attempt to find a neutralist solution in that part of the
                    world would be tantamount to facilitating a take-over by the Chinese Communists.
                    He pointed out that the circumstances which had made desirable a solution of
                    neutrality for Laos were peculiar to that country, and did not constitute a
                    precedent for a neutrality formula for South Viet Nam.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> asked Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> for his opinion about the Soviet proposal
                    for a conference on Cambodia in April.<note n="5" xml:id="d315fn5">On January 22
                        the Soviet Union forwarded to its Co-Chairman, the United Kingdom, a request
                        from Cambodia for convening the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>.</note>
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> said that we preferred not to
                    have such a conference, but that we did not want to seem to be in direct
                    opposition to Sihanouk’s suggestion.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> pointed out that there were two
                    points which could together be extremely harmful for the US attitude toward the
                    United Nations: first, financial problems in relation to Article 19 and, second,
                    a vote in the United Nations to admit Communist China.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> asked whether the United
                    States did not think that a Soviet-Chicom confrontation in the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> would be to the advantage of the Free World. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> said he doubted this, since they
                    would probably tend to get together on major issues. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> asked whether the French initiative
                    would swing the balance in the United Nations in favor of the admission of
                    Communist China. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> explained that
                    this would not necessarily be the case. He said the French Government had
                    advised its former colonies in Africa that it would be desirable they should not
                    recognize Communist China when France does so. He said that there would be an
                    obvious reluctance on the part of most of those governments to have a
                    representative of Peiping in their capitals.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> said that Canada was
                    recognizing Outer Mongolia, and that some people in Canada would say that this
                    was a move towards recognizing the Chinese People’s Republic. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> referred to the action of 1955 to
                    admit Outer Mongolia to the United Nations. He said <pb facs="0710" n="674"
                        xml:id="pg_674"/> he recalled that the United States had favored this, and
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> concurred, indicating that it
                    was part of a package transaction.</p>
                <p>(Later, with the Prime Minister present.)</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> said that while the President and
                    the Prime Minister had been having their private conversation the rest of the
                    group had discussed <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> and
                    Peiping. The Prime Minister said that he had also talked about this with the
                    President. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> pointed out that if
                    there should develop a trend in favor of Chinese recognition in the United
                    Nations, at the same time as a discussion of Article 19 of the United Nations
                    Charter, it could generate a wave of public opinion against the United Nations
                    in the United States. The Prime Minister said that the President and he shared
                    the view that nobody can do anything with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de
                        Gaulle</persName> once he has made up his mind, and that the best course in
                    the situation is to minimize the importance of it, as far as public treatment is
                    concerned. The Prime Minister went on to say that he hoped that the recognition
                    of Communist China by France would not have a drastic effect. He said in the
                    long run it might be helpful if the arrangement results in providing a
                    transition toward a two-China situation. He said the President had agreed that
                    it was not desirable to exaggerate the matter.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> spoke of the concern over a
                    possible trend among African states toward recognition and said that we do not
                    want to allow this sort of thing to be built up. We understand that the French
                    Government has suggested the <gloss target="#t_UAM1">UAM</gloss> states not
                    follow the French example. The Prime Minister remarked that the French must lack
                    confidence in their own action. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>
                    said that some <gloss target="#t_UAM1">UAM</gloss> states may resist the
                    temptation to recognize Communist China. He said we certainly hope for a firm
                    line on the Western side, and we are particularly concerned over the reaction in
                    Viet Nam. Certainly the French action would be interpreted in Viet Nam as a
                    further move in the wrong direction.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister wondered whether the greatest embarrassment would be in Tokyo,
                    and the Under Secretary said it was doubtful whether the Japanese could stand
                    against great pressure to do the same thing. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1"
                        >Martin</persName> referred to a speech by the Japanese Prime Minister of
                    the preceding day, reported in January 22nd issue of the New York Times, in
                    which the problem was reviewed. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>
                    said that we have advised Taiwan to sit tight. There may be no actual exchange
                    of ambassadors between Communist China and France for about three months. The
                    situation is hard for Chiang Kai-shek, because the French have never permitted
                    him to have an ambassador in Paris, only a Chargé. If there is to be a Chinese
                    ambassador, and only a Chargé for the Nationalists, this would be very awkward
                    indeed.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister said that it had been reported in the newspapers, particularly
                    in Canada, that he had told the President that Canada <pb facs="0711" n="675"
                        xml:id="pg_675"/> would not recognize Red China without United States
                    consent. This type of newspaper story is exceedingly damaging and he had had to
                    deny it on domestic political grounds. He said he felt the world must some day
                    get out of the difficult situation in which it has painted itself, but that he
                    had no wish whatsoever to add to the difficulties of the United States,
                    especially in an election year. He said that some pressure would develop in
                    Canada but he did not want to do anything now to add to United States
                    difficulties. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> said it might be
                    wise to see what happened as a result of French recognition. After all the
                    British had not gained very much by having diplomatic representation in Peiping.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> said that this was the sort
                    of thing the Japanese Prime Minister had suggested—wait and see what
                    happened.</p>
                <p>At one point during the meeting, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BWH1"
                        >Brubeck</persName>, who had been absent from the room briefly, returned to
                    say that the press was inquiring whether it was true that Canada and the United
                    States were discussing the possible recognition of Red China by Canada. The
                    Prime Minister authorized a statement to the effect that this subject had not
                    been considered in the discussions.<note n="6" xml:id="d315fn6">For text of the
                        joint communiqué, see <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current
                            Documents, 1964</hi>, pp. 432-434.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
