<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>49. Memorandum From Horace Busby of the White House Staff to President of the
                    White House Staff to President Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d49</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">49</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-06-10T12:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-06-10T12:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-06-10T12:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-06-10T12:45:00-05:00" n="49"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                <head>49. Memorandum From <persName type="from">Horace Busby</persName> of the White
                    House Staff to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to"
                        >Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d49fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Memos to the President, <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                            Bundy</persName>, Vol. 11. No classification marking. A handwritten
                        notation reads: “For <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> for
                        comments to me. L” No written comments have been found.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-06-10T13:45:00-04:00">June 10, 1965, 1:45 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Conversation, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I am sure you will be interested in various comments made to me within the past
                    several days on his own initiative by the Ambassador of France, who has just
                    returned from a visit to Paris.</p>
                <pb facs="0134" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> says the “poor relations
                        between France and America are a figment of the journalists in both
                        Washington and Paris.” He says that among the people, outside Government, he
                        finds no anti-American sentiment in France and little other than pro-France
                        sentiment among Americans. “All of this,” he says, “is salon talk among a
                        limited number of people in or on the fringes of our Governments.”</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> says, “Whatever is said in
                        Paris, France will always be with you when we are needed. The average
                        Frenchman knows this, just as the average American knows it. Your President
                        is being misrepresented by his press, so is my President—except that my
                        President has more trouble with cartoonists in both countries than your
                        President has in either country. The journalists want to keep alive the
                        fight that was started before your President became President—and President
                            <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">DeGaulle</persName> knows that President
                            <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> has discouraged the
                        people in your Government from keeping that fight alive.”</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AH1">Alphand</persName> says, “Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> made a speech that has been badly
                        reported in this country.<note n="2" xml:id="d49fn2">In a June 1 address
                                <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">William McChesney Martin</persName>,
                            Chairman of the Federal Reserve, opposed a rise in gold prices, a return
                            to the gold standard, or the delegation of monetary policy to an
                            international agency. A summary of his remarks is in <hi rend="italic"
                                >The New York Times</hi>, June 2, 1965.</note> If you will read it
                        carefully, he is only saying that the Western countries should look at the
                        international monetary situation and its problems and do some things about
                        that which have not been done all through these post-war years. What Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MWMCJ1">Martin</persName> says—if you forget his
                        remarks about 1929—is only the same thing that General <persName
                            corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> and Mr.
                            <persName>Rueff</persName> have been saying too. When General <persName
                            corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> talks about gold standards, he
                        doesn’t have a Council of Economic Advisors guiding him on what he says—he
                        just has Mr. <persName>Rueff</persName>. The General does not know much
                        about gold or international monetary matters. What he has asked for, I
                        believe, is not a return to the Gold Standard as much as he has asked the
                        allies to look for a better standard than what we have now. I think many
                        people in your Government feel the same way, although they would not follow
                        the same way that General <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>
                        suggests. President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> has a
                        fine opportunity to take leadership in this field that has been neglected by
                        too many people in my Capital and your Capital, too.”</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comments:</hi> I am not sufficiently informed to make
                    judgments about this, but some of the Ambassador’s observations, made on and at
                    his own initiative, seem to be in the nature of an overture. Perhaps others
                    could explore this more usefully and more intelligently than I.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Buzz</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
