<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>13. Memorandum for Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v31</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-05-11T15:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-05-11T15:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="recp2SiyR1nvI0JZ2" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123997"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Social reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="tariffs" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132405" lcsh-match="good_close">Tariff</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-05-11T15:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-05-11T15:45:00-05:00" n="13"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d13">
                <head>13. Memorandum for Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d13fn1">Source:
                        Johnson Library, National Security File, Agency File, Alliance for Progress.
                        Secret. No drafting information appears on the memorandum. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> wrote “OK” on it. The meeting was
                        held in the Cabinet Room.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-05-11T16:45:00-04:00">May 11, 1964, 4:45 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Memorandum of Conversation in the Cabinet Room Monday, May 11, 4:45
                        p.m.</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PRESENT WERE</head>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>Ambassadors or Chargé d’Affaires of the Latin American Republics</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Carlos Sanz de Santamaria</persName> (head
                        of <gloss target="#t_CIAP1">CIAP</gloss>)</item>
                    <item>Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">George Ball</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAB1">Duke</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>[Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>]</item>
                </list>
                <p>The President opened the meeting by offering a welcome to the Ambassadors who
                    were seated around the Cabinet table. He said that this group of advisers might
                    well be more effective than his regular Cabinet, and he then read or paraphrased
                    the attached statement.<note n="2" xml:id="d13fn2">Not found. During a telephone
                        conversation <persName>Johnson</persName> had asked <persName
                            corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> to prepare a “page” for the meeting.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> replied: “All right. I think
                        the scenario is that you’re going to open up with a couple of things. We’ve
                        primed two or three of them to set the right tone.” Both men agreed that
                        this might avoid a “gripe session,” which would inevitably leak to the
                        press. (Ibid., Recordings and Transcripts, Recording of telephone
                        conversation between President <persName>Johnson</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_MTC1">Thomas Mann</persName>, May 11, 12:50 p.m., Tape
                        F64.26, Side B, PNO 3)</note> At the close of his statement the President
                    announced that he was proposing the appointment of The Honorable <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt W. Rostow</persName> to replace Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MT1">Teodoro Moscoso</persName> as the American Representative
                    on <gloss target="#t_CIAP1">CIAP</gloss>. The President initially asked that
                    this announcement be kept private, <pb facs="0079" n="34" xml:id="pg_34"/>
                    because he had not had a chance to discuss it with Mr.
                        <persName>Rostow</persName>, who was airborne—but while he was making the
                    announcement, Acting Secretary Ball was called to the telephone and reported
                    that Mr. <persName>Rostow</persName> had accepted the President’s proposal. The
                    announcement was greeted with obvious pleasure by the Ambassadors.</p>
                <p>The first reply to the President’s remarks came from Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz de Santamaria</persName>, who described his recent
                    swing through Central America. He said that he conceived of <gloss
                        target="#t_CIAP1">CIAP</gloss> as a political motor for the promotion of the
                    Alliance. He had found a very affirmative response in every country from Mexico
                    to Panama. All were trying to do their part. He particularly praised the efforts
                    of coordination of the Central American nations. He believed that they had made
                    great progress in integration, and that their effort compared favorably with the
                    achievement of the European nations over a similar period of time.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName> said that he made it a practice
                    to emphasize that the Alliance for Progress was not simply another name for
                        <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>, and that <gloss target="#t_AID1"
                        >AID</gloss> was merely one agency for the work of the Alliance, and that
                    indeed the Alliance must never be conceived of as an effort by the U.S.
                    alone.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName> reported that in some countries
                    he found that the people were not yet interested in the Alliance. The
                    Governments and the larger business interests were actively engaged, but the
                    Alliance had a need for the people as a whole and for political action.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName> reported that he had repeatedly
                    been asked whether he himself believed in the Alliance for Progress and that his
                    standard answer had been a strong “Yes.” He has explained that he had talked to
                    President <persName>Johnson</persName>, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD2"
                        >Rusk</persName>, and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>,
                    and he knew of their own personal commitment to the Alliance, commitments
                    reemphasized again by this meeting.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName> praised the appointment of
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>. He said that this was a
                    very intelligent appointment which would be received with favor in Latin America
                    and he emphasized the importance of this appointment in the light of the very
                    great service which <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Teodoro Moscoso</persName> had
                    rendered to the Alliance.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName> said that it was his practice to
                    discuss needed improvements frankly both with the U.S. officials and with
                    officials in Latin America. He was proud that in Mexico he had been invited to
                    speak as if he were a Mexican. He had done so, and he believed that much could
                    be accomplished in both directions by this kind of candor. He believed that in
                    the case of the U.S. there was a need for the reduction of red tape, and for an
                    ability to make decisions promptly even if the decision was negative.</p>
                <p>The President asked if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> found it
                    difficult to say “No,” and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>
                    promptly defended himself, while agreeing that the criticism offered by Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName> was justified.</p>
                <pb facs="0080" n="35" xml:id="pg_35"/>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName> said in conclusion that he was
                    asked in Latin America why the U.S. insisted on a development program when the
                    U.S. itself had never had such a program. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1"
                        >Sanz</persName> said that his answer was that it was not the United States
                    but the Latin American countries themselves which had requested such programs,
                    and that when resources were limited and choice was necessary, it was entirely
                    natural that a lending or granting agency would need to know how a given
                    proposal fitted into the general program of the country concerned.</p>
                <p>The President said that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName> had made
                    a very constructive statement. We agreed with it, and the President could say
                    that however long he was in the White House, he was going to be at work on the
                    Alliance. There was not a man living that cared more than he did, and no one
                    more competent to work for the Alliance than Tom Mann. The President agreed that
                    there was too much red tape and he believed it could be cut down. We were going
                    to act for the Alliance and we were glad to have the help in this work of such
                    men as Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SSC1">Sanz</persName>.</p>
                <p>The next speaker was Dr. Francisco R. Lima of El Salvador. He spoke briefly and
                    made four points: (1) that at Geneva there was a significant difference between
                    the hopes of the Latin American countries and the position of the United States
                    delegation; his Government hoped that the U.S. could take a more sympathetic
                        position;<note n="3" xml:id="d13fn3">Reference is to the United Nations
                        Conference on Trade and Development (<gloss target="#t_UNCTAD1"
                            >UNCTAD</gloss>), which met in Geneva, March 23–June 16.</note> (2) that
                    the assignment of sugar quotas was a matter of the greatest importance to Latin
                    American countries, and that his Government hoped for part of the Cuban quota.
                    The President interjected that his Government was not alone. (3) That coffee
                    prices should go up, and that the housewife should be brought to accept the need
                    for higher coffee prices. The President interjected that producers always had
                    believed in high prices, but that consumers were not so easily persuaded. (4)
                    That concern with the U.S. balance of payments was interfering with relations
                    between the U.S. and countries of the Hemisphere.</p>
                <p>At the President’s request, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MTC1"
                        >Mann</persName> replied briefly to Ambassador Lima saying that sugar quotas
                    were under careful review, that the U.S. expected to pass legislation supporting
                    the coffee agreement, and that in cases where transactions having a very minor
                    effect on the balance of payments were impeded by restrictions growing out of
                    this problem, it should be possible to make arrangements that would prevent
                    delay or obstruction on this account.</p>
                <pb facs="0081" n="36" xml:id="pg_36"/>
                <p>Ambassador Correa of Ecuador emphasized the concern of his country with the fate
                    of the <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss> legislation.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d13fn4">Reference is to a bill authorizing an increase in the U.S.
                        contribution to the International Development Association, a World Bank
                        affiliate. The House approved the legislation on May 13; the President
                        signed the bill into law on May 26. (78 Stat. 200)</note> The President
                    responded by saying that this was one of the many great problems we have this
                    year, that we were working very hard on it and that we were worried about it
                    too, and that he proposed to discuss it with the Legislative Leadership. The
                    President telephoned on the spot to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_OBLF1">Lawrence
                        O’Brien</persName> and asked for an up-to-date report on the legislative
                    account. A little later in the meeting he received a telephone answer from
                        <persName corresp="#p_OBLF1">O’Brien</persName>’s office and reported to the
                    meeting that the current estimate was that there would be 215 votes in the House
                    for the measure, which would probably be just enough.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador of Uruguay remarked that trade also was very important, that we
                    should work at the increase of trade as a part of the whole program, and that we
                    were not yet working on it as we should.</p>
                <p>Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, in response,
                    emphasized the concern of the U.S. with the expansion of trade and, with a
                    reference back to the earlier comments of Ambassador Lima, he remarked that
                    there was real hope for progress in the <gloss target="#t_UNCTAD1"
                        >UNCTAD</gloss> meeting in Geneva during the last five weeks of hard work.
                    He himself hoped that there would be answers that would not be too disappointing
                    to the assembled group.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> pointed out that we face a real
                    problem in framing our policy on tariff preferences. This was a problem on which
                    we ought to work together. The U.S. has to trade with all the world, and if the
                    U.S. should introduce tariff preferences specifically for Latin America, we
                    would be one step further along on the road toward the creation of a series of
                    closed trading systems, in place of the traditional target of a single
                    world-wide open system.</p>
                <p>The President said that we ought to list some of our common interests and work on
                    them some more. He reemphasized his conviction that the Latin American future
                    was the American future, that “your welfare is our welfare.”</p>
                <p>The Ambassador of Chile remarked that some of the criticism which the Alliance
                    for Progress was now receiving was the result of understandable impatience. In
                    order to launch the Alliance for Progress we had set it at a very high pitch,
                    and the things said at the beginning may have made the overall task seem easier
                    than in fact it is.</p>
                <p>The President entirely agreed with this point and said that in his view we had
                    indeed started off on a very high pitch and that we must now show leadership in
                    getting the real difficulties better understood.</p>
                <pb facs="0082" n="37" xml:id="pg_37"/>
                <p>The Ambassador of Chile continued that we had nevertheless accomplished a good
                    deal, although there was a natural tendency for each of us to suppose that he
                    was doing everything and that the other fellow wasn’t doing enough. The
                    President agreed, remarking that is his experience the other fellow always
                    thought it was the President of the United States who wasn’t doing his part. The
                    Ambassador of Chile replied that in the U.S. press it always appeared that it
                    was the U.S. that was doing the work and no one else was doing enough. The
                    Ambassador recognized that we all had bureaucratic problems. He thought that
                        <gloss target="#t_CIAP1">CIAP</gloss> was a good way of meeting
                    responsibility, but that it had taken too long to get organized. Nevertheless,
                    most of our countries had prepared or were preparing development programs, and
                    programs for tax reform and agrarian reform, and while we should not relax, we
                    need not feel frustrated either. The Latin American countries were doing better.
                    The weakest point was in the private sector. The conditions for a perfectly
                    stable private sector were very complex, and in his judgment only two countries
                    in the world could meet all the desired standards: the U.S. and Switzerland. He
                    did not think Latin American countries could turn Swiss overnight. The
                    Ambassador felt that Latin America faced a heavy requirement for political and
                    social reform, and such programs commit governments and they have to go on
                    forward with them.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador pointed out that annual debate of public funds available for the
                    Alliance put the whole case in suspense and created an element of doubt and
                    concern.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador of Venezuela conveyed the apologies of President Betancourt.<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d13fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> inserted the following phrase
                        by hand: “for his inability to attend the meeting in response to the
                        President’s invitation.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>The President concluded the meeting by emphasizing the need for optimism and
                    enthusiasm in supporting the Alliance. He remarked that if you want to lose an
                    election all you have to do is predict that you will lose it. If you want to
                    lose a baseball game, all you have to do is announce your doubts. The President
                    believed that we had come a long way and we should emphasize our success and do
                    all that we can to create the appearance of success as well, since the
                    appearance would reinforce the reality. The President reemphasized his complete
                    confidence in Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>, who was
                    going to be the one “Jefe” here in Washington for the Alliance. The Ambassadors
                    should think of him as a friend, that if they would work with us we would keep
                    at the improvement of the Alliance. But if we should predict its failure, the
                    Congress would make it a failure. The program was surrounded by outsiders who
                    liked to criticize and editors who looked for diplomats <pb facs="0083" n="38"
                        xml:id="pg_38"/> whom they might quote in a critical vein, and the President
                    believed it of great importance that we should do our best to build up the
                    Alliance, not tear it down.<note n="6" xml:id="d13fn6">After the meeting the
                        President invited the participants to the East Room, where he delivered an
                        address and signed 12 loan agreements under the Alliance for Progress.
                        Earlier that afternoon <persName>Johnson</persName> discussed the address
                        with <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>: “I think we need some
                        facts in there about what we’ve done the last 6 months. We ought to know if
                        we’ve done anything worthwhile, in the achievements, and we ought to point
                        them out, not defensively but rather positively, so that we can show that we
                        haven’t been asleep, and—This damn <persName corresp="#p_SAMJ1"
                            >Schlesinger</persName> is going all over the world denouncing us. I saw
                        a cable yesterday, it had been circularized to everybody, about how our
                        whole policy on Latin America had changed, and how we’d abandoned the
                        Alliance. And so I think we ought to answer him by saying: ‘We’re building
                        this big waterworks here, and we’re doing this road here, and we’re doing
                        this here—all this has been done in the last 90 days.’” (Johnson Library,
                        Recordings and Transcripts, Recording of telephone conversation between
                        President <persName>Johnson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MTC1"
                            >Thomas Mann</persName>, May 11, 12:19 p.m., Tape F64.26, Side B, PNO 2)
                        For text of <persName>Johnson</persName>’s remarks, <hi rend="italic">see
                            Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States: <persName
                                corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B. Johnson</persName>, 1963–64</hi>, Book
                        I, pp. 677–681.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
