<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-07-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="22" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d22">
                        <head>22. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SRM1" type="from">Robert M.
                                Sayre</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG1" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d22fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Country File, Cuba, <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> Resolution, Vol. V (9th <gloss target="#t_MFM1">MFM</gloss>), 7/64–8/64. Confidential.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-07-23">July 23, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>At the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> meeting this morning,
                            Argentina came out strongly against Cuba, but at the same time said that
                            the action taken should <pb facs="0107" n="62" xml:id="pg_62"/> be a
                            matter of conviction with each American Republic. The Foreign Minister
                            said Argentina had already resolved what it would do—it has broken
                            relations, etc., but did not want to vote a resolution that would give
                            other countries troubles. How Argentina will come out is hard to say;
                            its position this morning was not helpful. The military members of the
                            Argentine delegation are most unhappy with their Government’s position.
                            State’s Director Argentine Affairs<note n="2" xml:id="d22fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_HHA1">Henry A. Hoyt</persName>.</note>
                            continues of the view that the Argentine Government will have to get in
                            line or face the prospect of being tossed out by the military as it was
                            in 1962, when it failed to agree at Punta del Este.</p>
                        <p>Haiti said it would vote with the majority on sanctions, but a
                            double-cross is possible. The Haitian Foreign Office put the heat on
                            Ambassador Timmons to get approval of an export license for T–28’s in
                            the same conversation about Haiti’s support on Cuba.</p>
                        <p>Brazil is working with our delegation, and is ready to go down the line
                            with us. Counting Haiti, there are 13 votes lined up with us. Rusk
                            discussed with the President at lunch, a telegram to President Paz to
                            get Paz to instruct his Foreign Minister to vote with us.<note n="3" xml:id="d22fn3">Although no substantive record of this discussion
                                has been found, the President approved the telegram to Paz.
                                (Telegram 49 to La Paz, July 23; National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 23–8 VEN) <persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName> also called Ambassador to
                                Bolivia Douglas Henderson to emphasize the importance of Bolivia’s
                                vote: “Sec asked what time he [<persName corresp="#p_HD1">Henderson</persName>] would see Pres Paz and <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Henderson</persName> said 4:15. Sec asked him
                                to do his very best; this could make quite a lot of difference. Sec
                                said we could get very good result if <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Henderson</persName> was successful. Sec. asked the Amb to
                                phone us after his interview.” (<persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Henderson</persName>, July 24, 2:50 p.m.; ibid., <persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName> Files: Lot 72 D 192, Telephone
                                Calls 7/1/64–8/5/64) No record of a return call from <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Henderson</persName> has been found. The
                                subsequent reply from <persName corresp="#p_PEV1">Paz</persName> was
                                non-committal. (Telegram 121 from La Paz, July 25; ibid., Central
                                Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 23–8 VEN)</note>
                            Peru says it will vote with the majority, but it is also still talking
                            like Argentina.</p>
                        <p>Chile, Mexico and Uruguay are opposed to sanctions, and unlikely to
                            change their minds.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SRM1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">RMS</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>