<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>312. Paper Prepared in the Bureau of Intelligence and Research</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v31</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMtGtOqSFHX53RU" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military coup</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic reform</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="312"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                <head>312. Paper Prepared in the Bureau of Intelligence and Research<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d312fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, <gloss target="#t_ARACV1">ARA/CV</gloss> Files, 1965:
                        Lot 67 D 622, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 2 Sitreps. Secret. Drafted
                        in <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss> by
                        Robert R. Hendon, Thomas C. Colwell, and Mary K. Manzoli. Forwarded to
                            <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> as an attachment to a May 5
                        memorandum from Wolfe who noted that <persName corresp="#p_SRM1"
                            >Sayre</persName> had requested the paper on <persName corresp="#p_MTC1"
                            >Mann</persName>’s behalf earlier in the day, thereby precluding its
                        coordination within either the Department or the intelligence community.
                        (Ibid.) <persName corresp="#p_SRM1">Sayre</persName> forwarded the paper to
                            <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> on May 12. (Memorandum from
                            <persName corresp="#p_SRM1">Sayre</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName>, May 12; Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, Colombia, Vol. I, 12/63–7/65)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-05-05">May 5, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">COLOMBIA: SITUATION AND PROSPECTS</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Basic Judgment</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Political tensions in Colombia have once again built up to crisis point. There
                    is, as on the many other occasions when the National Front government has been
                    torn by deep partisan conflict, a chance that some <pb facs="0726" n="681"
                        xml:id="pg_681"/> fundamental change in the governing authority will be
                    made. That change could come by military coup or through some basic political
                    rearrangement in the form and composition of the government. Colombian
                    politicians of all stripes and the military establishment, however, have a way
                    of coming together for mutual advantage in time of crisis and thereby averting a
                    break up of the National Front and a return to civil strife or military
                    dictatorship. We believe that the danger of a military coup or a breakdown in
                    the Front is greater today than a year ago, or even several months ago, but we
                    are still inclined to feel that the end is not at hand yet.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Current Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The recently announced alliance of the majority Laureanista– Alzatista (L/A’s)
                    faction of the Conservative Party and two smaller opposition parties, the
                    Liberal Revolutionary Movement (<gloss target="#t_MRL1">MRL</gloss>) and the
                    Popular National Alliance (ANP), has created the latest, serious problem for the
                    Front government of Conservative President <persName corresp="#p_VGL1"
                        >Valencia</persName>. The alliance formalizes the L/A’s de facto opposition
                    to the National Front government, which along with absenteeism in the Congress
                    and lack of party discipline, has served to block passage of important
                    legislation since mid-1964. The Liberal Party that shares the responsibility of
                    government with the Conservative Party in the National Front and the Ospinista
                    minority faction of the Conservative Party (still loyal to the National Front)
                    are pressuring <persName corresp="#p_VGL1">Valencia</persName> to remove the
                    L/A’s from the government or to exact a pledge of legislative support from them.
                        <persName corresp="#p_VGL1">Valencia</persName> is extremely reluctant to
                    make any move that would further undermine his already shaky government.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">What May Happen</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_VGL1">Valencia</persName> probably will respond to the
                    present crisis—as he has to other crisis situations in the past—by temporizing,
                    in hopes that it will go away. If the Liberals force the issue and the L/A’s
                    remain intransigent, <persName corresp="#p_VGL1">Valencia</persName> may be
                    forced to remove the latter from their government posts. This measure would
                    probably kill any chance for congressional action on a major fiscal package now
                    under consideration and all but end hopes for any meaningful legislation before
                    elections in March 1966 when a new congress is to be chosen. An outcome to the
                    present crisis of this sort would probably not topple the <persName
                        corresp="#p_VGL1">Valencia</persName> government.</p>
                <p>The National Front’s problems are growing, however, and its political base for
                    dealing with these problems is shrinking. The greatest danger that may emerge
                    from the latest crisis is that it may lead Liberal Party leaders to believe that
                    the National Front cannot survive the electoral test in 1966 when it is their
                    turn to put a member of their party in the presidency. As a result, the Liberals
                    may decide to conspire with <pb facs="0727" n="682" xml:id="pg_682"/> the
                    military with the idea of bringing about an extra-legal change of government
                    through which they would gain the upper hand. The military, faced with a growing
                    problem of subversive violence, may be receptive to the Liberals’ overtures,
                    thinking perhaps that the Liberal leaders might be able to help them establish
                    effective government. At this time there is little indication that the Liberals
                    are seriously considering an extra-legal change or, for that matter, that they
                    have the military support they would need for such a move.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Economic Problems as a Factor</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Colombia’s financial condition is deteriorating and the economic frustrations of
                    the masses contribute to political tensions. Inflationary pressures are not
                    great at the moment but a push against prices is expected in coming months. A
                    Special Session of the Congress, called to consider a package of revenue
                    proposals, may reject some of the measures proposed by the <persName
                        corresp="#p_VGL1">Valencia</persName> government that could at least limit
                    the size of a prospective large 1965 budget deficit. The spread between the
                    official and the free rate of exchange is increasing and the government lacks
                    the international reserves to protect the official rate against speculative
                    raids and the rising demand for imports. <persName corresp="#p_VGL1"
                        >Valencia</persName>’s heavy commitment to avoid devaluation has prevented
                    his administration from taking the remedial measures that are necessary to
                    rectify the monetary and exchange situation.</p>
                <p>The prospect is that Colombia will try during the balance of 1965 to obtain
                    short-term commercial financing to relieve pressures on the exchange rate and
                    impose additional indirect taxes on imports. With government attention devoted
                    primarily to maneuvering its way through the country’s political and financial
                    difficulties, it does not seem likely that Colombia will make much headway on
                    basic long-term social and economic reform in the near future.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d312fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> briefed President
                            <persName>Johnson</persName> on Colombia during a telephone conversation
                        the afternoon of May 5. He told the President “we have a problem in
                        Colombia.” <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> explained that
                        Colombian President <persName corresp="#p_VGL1">Valencia</persName> is very
                        pro-U.S., but “does not know beans from bull about economics” and wants
                        $60–100 million a year to maintain rates of exchange that are unrealistic.
                            <persName corresp="#p_VGL1">Valencia</persName> does not want to devalue
                        or stop inflation because it will cost him popularity, but if he doesn’t do
                        something “it will cost us billions without giving us anything.” <persName
                            corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> told <persName>Johnson</persName> that
                        “we have this type of problem all over the world, but in Colombia it is a
                        matter of leadership. He said if it blows it won’t necessarily go Communist
                        but he did not think this guy would last. He said he has been very
                        anti-Communist and a good friend but does not know anything about running a
                        country.” (Johnson Library, Papers of <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Thomas C.
                            Mann</persName>, Telephone Conversations with <gloss target="#t_LBJ1"
                            >LBJ</gloss>, May 2, 1965–June 2, 1966)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
