<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>331. Telegram From the Embassy in Ecuador to to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v31</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d331</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">331</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-05-13T17:20:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-05-13T17:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recfrz0b94d87k9th" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-engineering" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092968" lcsh-match="exact">Engineering</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-05-13T17:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-05-13T17:20:00-05:00" n="331"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d331">
                <head>331. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Ecuador</gloss> to <gloss
                        type="to">the Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d331fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> ECUADOR–US. Secret; Limdis.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Quito</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-05-13T22:20:00+00:00">May 13, 1967, 2220Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5824. 1. I called yesterday at my initiative on President <persName
                        corresp="#p_AGO1">Arosemena</persName> for review of Ecuadorean–U.S.
                    relations Prior to my departure on home leave (mentioning that this leave
                    coordinated with children’s vacation and had been long planned).</p>
                <p>2. After congratulating him on political gains he had made as result his
                    performance Punta del Este,<note n="2" xml:id="d331fn2">According to an April 20
                            <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> report <persName corresp="#p_AGO1"
                            >Arosemena</persName> received an enthusiastic reception after Punta del
                        Este as “the only Latin American president with the ‘courage to put the US
                        in its place’.” <persName corresp="#p_AGO1">Arosemena</persName>’s
                        performance “fed Ecuador’s pride which—apart from Ecuador’s coming in second
                        in a basketball competition in Scranton, Pennsylvania—has had little
                        sustenance in recent years.” (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_ARAEP1"
                            >ARA/EP</gloss>/E Files: Lot 70 D 247, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 15 <persName corresp="#p_AGO1">Arosemena</persName>
                        Government)</note> I pointed out that these gains had been made largely at
                    expense of <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> program’s reputation. I pointed
                    out that the program’s degree of success depends largely on its political
                    support by the government and political acceptability to the people, both of
                    which had suffered significantly through the attacks which he had been making,
                    especially since his return from Punta del Este. I said I thought his public
                    statements about the aid program were unbalanced, in that they mentioned nothing
                    good about it, and in some cases erroneous, in that they disregarded pertinent
                    facts.</p>
                <pb facs="0759" n="714" xml:id="pg_714"/>
                <p>3. During our discussion <persName corresp="#p_AGO1">Arosemena</persName> stuck
                    to his guns, reasserting his declarations about the aid program and giving
                    ground, by tacitly accepting my point of view, in only two respects. When I told
                    him I had been disappointed that he had publicly declared the U.S. was requiring
                    “inadmissible” conditions on the malaria loan, despite the fact that I
                    previously assured him I would take no position on requests until
                    sub-ministerial negotiations had reached either agreement or clear disagreement,
                    he obviously got the point but avoided comment. When I pointed out that he had
                    urgently requested my assistance in signing the primary education loan and then
                    expressed recognition only by publicly disputing whether his or the <persName
                        corresp="#p_YIC1">Yerovi</persName> government should get the credit for
                    having eliminated from the loan twenty “humiliating” conditions, he laughed in
                    hearty agreement.</p>
                <p>4. He declared he would never accept conditions that we are negotiating in the
                    proposed malaria loan designed to insure that the National Malaria Eradication
                    Service (SNEM) be independent and employ an outside administrator, and he asked
                    why we tried to impose these conditions on him when we had not imposed them on
                    the military junta. He was surprised and interested to learn that these
                    conditions had characterized the successful program that had been started before
                    the military junta assumed power and terminated in 1965.</p>
                <p>5. I assured him and he recognized that we are interested in carrying forward the
                    program on Alliance for Progress criteria and with no thought of any period of
                    coldness or retaliation in reaction to his criticisms. He commented that we had
                    authorized two grant projects since his return from Punta del Este and called my
                    attention to the very favorable publicity he had given to the signing of the
                    public safety project agreement.</p>
                <p>6. He continued to rant about the performance of the TAMS engineering company
                    under the road construction agreement. When I called his attention to my
                    previous suggestion that he meet personally with TAMS representatives in order
                    to get from them information with which to form a balanced picture of the value
                    of their operations, he said he would meet with them only to kick them
                    physically out of his office.</p>
                <p>7. Our conversation being interrupted by his need to meet with his cabinet and
                    chiefs of staff in order to consider the Duran strike situation which had
                    produced some dead and wounded, he suggested that we continue our talk early
                    next week.<note n="3" xml:id="d331fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGO1">Arosemena</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_CWR1">Coerr</persName> held “two strenuous hour-long
                        negotiating <persName corresp="#p_SEO1">sessions</persName>” on May 16 and
                        17, reaching agreement on the wording of the proposed Malaria loan.
                        (Telegram 5909 from Quito, May 17; ibid., Central Files 1967–69, <gloss
                            target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>(US) 8–5 ECUADOR)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWR1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Coerr</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
