<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-03-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="361" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d361">
                        <head>361. Information Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant
                                (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="from">Rostow</persName>) to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d361fn1">Source: Johnson Library,
                                National Security File, Country File, Mexico, Vol. IV, 1/68–10/68.
                                Confidential.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-03-09">March 9, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Mexican Border Restrictions</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0808" n="763" xml:id="pg_763"/>
                        <p>US merchants, particularly in Laredo, felt the pinch and made loud
                            complaints at State, here and on the <persName corresp="#p_HJCJ1">Hill</persName>. On both occasions strong representations to the
                            Mexican Ambassador and the Foreign Office brought relaxation of the
                            enforcement.</p>
                        <p>While we protested the Mexican action, our grounds were not strong
                            because the Mexican Government was simply enforcing customs regulations
                            on the books—even though not always applied. Mexico has a peculiar
                            customs system under which nationals returning by air can bring back a
                            long list of articles duty free, while overland returnees are restricted
                            to just a few items. We understand the severe enforcement measures at
                            Christmas and Washington’s birthday were due to pressure of Monterrey
                            merchants who anticipated heavy purchases in US border cities by
                            Mexicans living in the interior.</p>
                        <p>The issue of eliminating the discrepancy of exemptions between air
                            travellers and overland travellers was raised in the US–Mexico Trade
                            Committee meeting last December. The Embassy has also taken it up with
                            the Foreign Office. In view of the recent difficulty, State instructed
                            Ambassador <persName>Freeman</persName> on March 1 to press for a
                            resolution of the problem.<note n="2" xml:id="d361fn2">In telegram
                                123164 to Mexico City. (National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, FT 23 MEX)</note> He
                            is to point out that purchases along the border by our respective
                            tourists is a two-way street. For years we have waived the Treasury
                            requirement that US tourists must remain at least 48 hours outside the
                            US before taking advantage of the duty-free exemptions for purchases
                            abroad. In the new proposals governing US tourism, Mexico has a
                            privileged position. We expect the Mexicans to reciprocate.</p>
                        <p>Specifically, <persName>Freeman</persName> is to seek: <list>
                                <item>—simplification and clarification of customs
                                    regulations.</item>
                                <item>—elimination of differences between air and overland
                                    travellers, hopefully making the overland treatment conform to
                                    the more liberal air treatment.</item>
                                <item>—assurances of consistent enforcement during holiday and
                                    non-holiday periods.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>I will keep you posted on how these talks progress.<note n="3" xml:id="d361fn3">An initial report on the Embassy’s efforts is in
                                telegram 3868 from Mexico City, March 15. (Ibid.)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Walt</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>