<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-02-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="386" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d386">
                        <head>386. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                            Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MTC1" type="from">Mann</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD2" type="to">Rusk</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d386fn1">Source: National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59,
                                Central Files 1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> PAN–US.
                                Confidential. A handwritten note on the memorandum reads “Secretary
                                saw.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-02-01">February 1, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The Panama Problem</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>It seems to me that the “line” we take from here on out in our talks with
                            Panamanians and with other Latin Americans is very important.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName> decided to put pressure
                            on the United States to force us to agree, in advance of discussions, to
                            negotiate a new treaty to replace, or at least substantially alter,
                            existing treaties. As <persName corresp="#p_MMJJ1">Moreno</persName> has
                            confirmed to Bunker, this means language which can be interpreted as
                            United States pre-commitments to open up the sovereignty and perpetuity
                            issues to re-negotiation.</p>
                        <p>Breaking of relations was part of the tactic of pressure. The demagogic
                            press, television and radio campaigns by Panamanian media, controlled
                            for a time from the Presidencia itself, was part of the tactic. So was
                            the complicity of Panamanian Government officials in the 36 hours of
                            violence. The demagogic appeals to Latin American governments for
                            support, intransigence in the Peace Committee and the invocation of the
                            Rio Treaty on false charges of United States “aggression” were part of
                            the tactic. <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName>’s “painting
                            himself into a corner” by unnecessary public statements was part of the
                            tactic.</p>
                        <p>In launching the campaign, <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName>
                            was gambling that the United States would yield. The gamble turned out
                            to be a bad one. We have already gone as far as we can in making
                            concessions. <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName> has not
                            really moved an inch.</p>
                        <p>All of these facts are, or will be, known to knowledgeable people in
                            Latin America. There are signs that at least some Latin Americans are
                            beginning to realize the dimensions of Panamanian irresponsibility and
                            understand that the validity of their treaties and their interests, as
                            well as ours, are involved.<note n="2" xml:id="d386fn2">On January 30
                                Lansing <persName corresp="#p_CVL1">Collins</persName> provided
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> with an analysis of
                                Latin American official opinion on the Panama situation, which
                                indicated that Latin American officials deplored any attempt by
                                Panama to take the issue to the United Nations and “have expressed
                                understanding of our firm position in Panama.” (Memorandum from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CVL1">Collins</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName>, January 30; ibid.)</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0867" n="822" xml:id="pg_822"/>
                        <p>It is doubtful that <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName> can
                            yield. If the impasse continues, it seems equally doubtful that
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName> can “hang on” until
                            the May elections. He may decide voluntarily to turn the office over to
                            someone else. He may be overthrown. Nevertheless, anti-communist
                            political leaders of the country continue their active or tacit support
                            of <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName> because this is “good
                            politics” as long as there is a chance that the United States will yield
                            to <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName>’s pre-conditions.</p>
                        <p>As long as the anti-communist political leaders continue their support of
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName>’s tactic, only the
                            communists or Arnulfo Arias, perhaps in combination with each other,
                            will have an organization and a plan— in short, the capacity—to fill the
                            vacuum which <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName>’s departure
                            will leave.</p>
                        <p>If this estimate is correct, then it would make good sense to disabuse
                            all Panamanians, and indeed all Latin Americans, of any ideas that, in
                            the end, we are going to save <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName> by agreeing to his preconditions. Only then will
                            anti-communists adjust to reality and begin to organize and plan. When
                            they adjust to reality <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1">Chiari</persName>
                            will lose support. But we gain by giving anti-communist elements the
                            time and the opportunity to organize an alternative to a
                            communist-infiltrated or communist-controlled government.</p>
                        <p>By being candid and decisive we would also minimize the risk that other
                            Latin Americans will miscalculate in the current <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> proceedings.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>