<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-10-15T11:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-10-15T11:30:00-05:00" n="41" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d41">
                        <head>41. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="from">Rostow</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d41fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Memos to the President, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt W. Rostow</persName>, Vol. 14. Secret. A copy was sent to
                                Moyers.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-10-15T12:30:00-04:00">October 15, 1966, 12:30
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Our Program for the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss>
                                Summit</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName> in the attached
                                memorandum<note n="2" xml:id="d41fn2">Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName> to the President, undated;
                                attached but not printed. A copy, dated October 14, is in the
                                National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files
                                1964–66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 IA SUMMIT.</note>
                            requests your approval of general guidelines for our negotiators on
                            Summit preparations.</p>
                        <pb facs="0145" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">The guidelines are based on a Summit program which has
                                substantial inter-agency concurrence except for the budgetary
                                implications</hi>. Because of the difference, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName> is not asking that you make a
                            decision on this aspect until you can review the Summit price tag in the
                            light of the total aid request for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                            1968.</p>
                        <p>These guidelines provide adequate interim direction for the preliminary
                            multilateral preparatory work which will take place during the next 6–8
                            weeks.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Summit Deal</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>We are asking the Latins to: <list>
                                <item>—integrate their economies and sharply reduce tariffs.</item>
                                <item>—revamp their antiquated agricultural and educational
                                    systems.</item>
                                <item>—work with us in promoting private investment.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>It will take courage for the Latin American Presidents to take their
                            countries down this uncharted path.</p>
                        <p>To induce them to step off into the dark and break past the obstacles, a
                            substantial U.S. “carrot” will help. Expanded economic assistance is our
                            part of the deal.</p>
                        <p>The guidelines will enable our negotiators to explore: <list>
                                <item>—how far the Latins are prepared to go.</item>
                                <item>—how much inducement must we offer to make them take the
                                    jump.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Based on their findings, you can decide on the specific proposals.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Our Present Summit Program</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is <hi rend="italic">designed to begin meeting now serious social and
                                political problems we see coming in the decade ahead</hi> from
                            population increase, growing urban unemployment and continued
                            backwardness of agriculture. The main elements are:</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">1. Latin American Economic Integration</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The broadened, more competitive market that can result from more rapid
                            economic integration is the single, most promising move that Latin
                            America can take to accelerate growth and reduce future foreign aid
                            needs.</p>
                        <p>We would expect the Latin Americas to agree to a concrete plan for
                            automatic reduction of intra-zonal tariffs and non-tariff barriers; a
                            commitment to adopt reasonable external tariffs, declining as their
                            economies strengthen; competitive investment and internal trade
                            policies; and reasonable access to the region for foreign
                            investment.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">You, in turn, would announce</hi> at the Summit our
                            readiness to support this effort by <hi rend="italic">expanding our
                                contribution to the Inter-American Bank’s <pb facs="0146" n="101" xml:id="pg_101"/> Fund for Special Operations</hi> (<gloss target="#t_IDB1">IDB</gloss>/FSO). This would involve increasing the
                            U.S. contribution in the three fiscal years 1968–70 from the present
                            level of $250 million per year to $300 million, with an indication that
                            if additional funds are required, we would consider further
                            replenishment of the FSO.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_IDB1">IDB</gloss>
                            <hi rend="italic">would agree to set aside a stated amount of the new
                                resources</hi> to: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">finance sound multinational</hi> projects in
                                    support of economic integration and development of “inner
                                    frontiers” (e.g., roads, flood control, hydroelectric power,
                                    irrigation, communications).</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <hi rend="italic">assist countries with temporary adjustment
                                        problems</hi> resulting from rapid integration (e.g.,
                                    balance of payment difficulties, affected industries and
                                    workers, export financing for intra-Latin American
                                    trade).</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Higher Alliance Targets</hi>: Primarily Agricultural
                            and Education</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Annual per capita growth rates</hi> in Latin America
                            should increase from the 2.5% level realized in 1964 and 1965 to 4–6%.
                            Economic integration will help. But also <hi rend="italic">basic to the
                                objective are more dynamic agricultural sectors and broader access
                                to higher quality education</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The type of across-the-board programs and self-help we have in mind are
                            described in the guidelines paper (Enclosure 1 of the <persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName> memo).<note n="3" xml:id="d41fn3">Attached but not printed.</note> In addition to remedial measures
                            for the more common deficiencies, the programs include some exciting new
                            ideas such as establishing two or three regional centers of excellence
                            in science and engineering in Latin America.</p>
                        <p>At the Summit <hi rend="italic">you would announce an increase</hi> in
                                <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> bilateral assistance in these
                            two fields of up to $200 <hi rend="italic">million per year</hi> for 5
                            years.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">3. Stimulate Private Investment</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>There are two proposals for increasing U.S. investment in Latin America
                            under favorable conditions which State has advanced but on <hi rend="italic">which full inter-agency agreement has not been
                                reached</hi>. They are: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>an imaginative idea for <hi rend="italic">expansion of <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> risk guarantees</hi>
                                    developed by Tony Solomon.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>the negotiation with the Latin Americans of an agreed <hi rend="italic">investment code</hi> to encourage use of
                                    modern technology and provide for coordination of foreign
                                    investment with development plans.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0147" n="102" xml:id="pg_102"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Budgetary Implications of the Package</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_GAL1">Linc Gordon</persName>’s estimates not concurred
                            in by <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_BOB1">BOB</gloss>)</p>
                        <p>For <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1968 the <hi rend="italic">implications</hi> are <table cols="3" rows="5">
                                <row role="label">
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Appropriation</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Expenditure</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell cols="2">(in millions)</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Economic Integration (replenishment of the <gloss target="#t_IDB1">IDB</gloss>/FSO over the planned level
                                        of $250 million)</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">$50</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">$5</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Increased Bilateral Aid for Agriculture and
                                        Education</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">$200</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">$50</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Total</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">$250</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">$55</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">For the four-year period beyond <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1968:</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>—Replenishment of the FSO will continue for 2 years at $50
                                    million per year.</item>
                                <item>—Requirements for bilateral assistance in agriculture and
                                    education will not exceed $200 million per year and may be less,
                                    depending upon allocation of <gloss target="#t_IDA1">IDA</gloss>
                                    funds to Latin America.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Original Package</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_GAL1">Linc Gordon</persName>’s original Summit
                                proposals<note n="4" xml:id="d41fn4">As contained in a draft
                                memorandum to the President, undated; attached but not
                                printed.</note> had three elements which have been deleted or
                            diluted. They added a zest to the program which is now lacking.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">1. Separate Integration Fund</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>As an inducement to the Latin Americans to take the plunge on integration
                            he proposed a <hi rend="italic">separate</hi> Latin American Integration
                            Fund to handle adjustment assistance and a Multinational Projects window
                            at the <gloss target="#t_IDB1">IDB</gloss> to finance such projects. We
                            would contribute up to $300 million to the fund and $500 million to the
                                <gloss target="#t_IDB1">IDB</gloss> for multinational projects, both
                            over a five-year period.</p>
                        <p>Joe Fowler took sharp exception to these proposals and countered with the
                            idea of using the Bank’s FSO and increasing our contemplated annual
                            contribution to the FSO by $50 million for the next three years. Linc
                            reluctantly went along with this.</p>
                        <p>I think the Treasury formula dilutes the “carrot” aspect of the proposals
                            to such a degree that much of its value as an inducement for prompt
                            Latin American action is lost. We need more flexibility in negotiating
                            with the Latins on integration.</p>
                        <pb facs="0148" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">2. Expanded Risk Guarantee Program</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The <persName corresp="#p_SAM1">Solomon</persName> proposal is to: <list>
                                <item>—expand the program in six basic fields: iron and steel,
                                    chemicals, fertilizers, pulp and paper, petro-chemicals,
                                    automobiles.</item>
                                <item>—cover up to the legal maximum of 75% of each investment, and
                                    relax the 100% tieing requirement.</item>
                                <item>—require the U.S. investor to offer for sale up to 51% of the
                                    stock of his company to Latin American purchasers within a fixed
                                    number of years after the start of the project (e.g., 15–20
                                    years) and reinvest a percentage of his profits while he still
                                    held a controlling interest.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The proposal is encountering heavy going in Treasury and Commerce on
                            balance of payments grounds and the advisability of conditioning
                            guarantees to the mandatory offer of stock sales after a fixed period
                            and to required profit reinvestment. I am not convinced by: <list>
                                <item>—the balance of payments argument because Latin America does
                                    not leak to Europe, or</item>
                                <item>—the preoccupation with conditioning of guarantees since the
                                    investor is free to decide whether or not he wants to accept
                                    them.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">3. Limited Untieing of Procurement</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>To accommodate Latin American criticism to “tied” aid, Linc proposed
                            extending procurement eligibility for Alliance financing to include
                            Latin America. It would apply, in effect, to manufactured products,
                            mostly capital goods. This is largely a gesture—but symbolically a
                            meaningful one for the Latin Americans—because they produce few such
                            goods on competitive terms. State estimates that over an initial
                            three-year period the procurement might reach $15 million.</p>
                        <p>The Treasury objection is on balance of payments grounds. Since the
                            proposal is largely cosmetic, Linc dropped it from the package. I think
                            it bears closer examination.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">My Reaction to the Program</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It goes to the heart of what the Latins must do and only Presidents can
                            take the political decisions required. It is, therefore, of Presidential
                            stature.</p>
                        <p>If the Latins are willing to start down the track we propose, the bargain
                            to help them financially is a good one.</p>
                        <p>The portions of Linc’s original package which have not prospered are
                            “carrot” which we may have to use to get the Latins to accept the deal.
                            They should be held in reserve.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That you approve the guidelines proposed by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName>, with the understanding that you
                            wish to review at a later date each of the <pb facs="0149" n="104" xml:id="pg_104"/> three aspects of <persName corresp="#p_GAL1">Linc
                                Gordon</persName>’s original proposals not adequately covered in the
                            Summit program as it now stands.<note n="5" xml:id="d41fn5">Although the
                                memorandum does not record the decision, <persName corresp="#p_SBK1">Bromley Smith</persName> subsequently reported that the
                                President approved this recommendation—“with the understanding that
                                no decisions or commitments are to be made with respect to
                                additional United States assistance without prior referral to him
                                along with a firm indication of what the Latin Americans are
                                prepared to do.” (Memorandum from <persName>Smith</persName> to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RD2">Rusk</persName>, October 19; National
                                Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66,
                                    <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 IA SUMMIT)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Walt</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Approve</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Disapprove</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Speak to me</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>