<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-02-06T11:05:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-02-06T11:05:00-05:00" n="11" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d11">
                    <head>11. Memorandum of Conference With President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d11fn1">Source:
                            Kennedy Library, National Security Files, <persName>Chester V.
                                Clifton</persName> Series, Conferences with the President, Volume I.
                            Top Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CCV1">Clifton</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-02-06T11:05:00-05:00">February 6,
                                1961, 11:05 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>OTHERS PRESENT</head>
                        <item>General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName></item>
                        <item>General <persName corresp="#p_DGH1">Decker</persName></item>
                        <item>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Burke</persName></item>
                        <item>General <persName corresp="#p_WLC1">White</persName></item>
                        <item>General <persName corresp="#p_SGDM1">Shoup</persName></item>
                        <item>General <persName corresp="#p_CCV1">Clifton</persName></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The President asked General <persName corresp="#p_DGH1">Decker</persName> if
                        the magazine which prepared the extensive “sell” on the Nike/Zeus was his
                        magazine. There <pb facs="0060" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/> was some confusion
                        because both <hi rend="italic">Missiles and Rockets and Army Magazine</hi>
                        had come out within the last week.</p>
                    <p>General <persName corresp="#p_DGH1">Decker</persName> explained to the
                        President <hi rend="italic">Army Magazine</hi> and its relation to the
                        Association of the U.S. Army. Then the Chiefs told about the various
                        associations, including the Navy League and the Air Force Association, and
                        the magazines published, both officially and unofficially.</p>
                    <p>General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> briefed the
                        President on his weekend visit with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Gilpatric</persName> and two others to <gloss target="#t_SAC1">SAC</gloss> Headquarters in Omaha and the <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss>. He said the operation plan goes into effect April 1st,
                        although it was approved on December 1st.<note n="2" xml:id="d11fn2">By
                            President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>.</note> He
                        gave the President quite a few details on how targets are covered. The
                        President asked them, “if we hit first and some of our forces are
                        diminished, how do you provide for the second strike?” General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> said individual commanders
                        duplicate strikes. General <persName corresp="#p_WLC1">White</persName>
                        explained to him there were second and third runs laid on all targets, and
                        that if the first run did not take off, the second run would get it. Also,
                        if the first run was successful, there were plans to divert the second run
                        to other targets.</p>
                    <p>The President asked if there were any limitations on the U.S. operating from
                        Japanese bases against the Soviet Union with atomic weapons. The Joint
                        Chiefs answered those questions. The President asked, if we decided to make
                        the first strike, could we eliminate the Soviet strikeback? The Joint Chiefs
                        answered no, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> could strike back and
                        especially in the missile age it is becoming more and more difficult to
                        actually know where the targets are—that is, the Soviet Union
                        capabilities—and we couldn’t possibly get them all. Their estimate was that
                        under any circumstances the Soviet Union could strike back hard.</p>
                    <p>The President asked if the Department of Defense, in analyzing the last
                        budget that was submitted, had discussed with them what, in the opinion of
                        the Chiefs, were the priorities—the first priorities—of items they would
                        want above the budget that was submitted. General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> intercepted this with an
                        explanation of the four task forces in the Department of Defense<note n="3" xml:id="d11fn3">Not further identified.</note> and that on the 10th of
                        February the Chiefs would be examining the results of the task forces
                        analysis of the budget and by the 20th would report to the President which
                        items would be needed in addition to the last budget, or what changes should
                        be made within the limitations of the last budget. (I believe that there was
                        a failure of communication on this point. The President did not get the
                        answer he was seeking, which was what, in the opinion of the Chiefs, should
                        they have had as first priority items above the last budget when it went in,
                        but maybe there was a deliberate lack of communication on this point.) The
                            <pb facs="0061" n="29" xml:id="pg_29"/> President indicated that perhaps
                        the Joint Chiefs might want to give him some ideas about this after they see
                        the February 10th paper and before the final Department of Defense paper
                        comes in.</p>
                    <p>The President mentioned guerrilla activities in Laos, the Congo and Viet-Nam
                        and asked what we are doing in each of the Services on this type of
                        training. He asked especially if the guerrilla activity which we are going
                        to face in the future on an intensified basis by the enemy couldn’t have
                        some effect on our <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> training efforts.
                        There was a long discussion on this point and the President said, “Maybe you
                        would like to give me a short memorandum on Viet-Nam, especially as far as
                        our guerrilla efforts in that area are concerned.”</p>
                    <p>The President then requested a memorandum on what the Services are doing on
                        guerrilla activity and training.<note n="4" xml:id="d11fn4">This request
                            eventuated in an undated memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_DGH1">Decker</persName> to the President, attached to a note from
                                <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_CCV1">Clifton</persName>, February 16. (Kennedy Library,
                            National Security Files, Departments and Agencies Series, Department of
                            Defense, Special Warfare Volume I) In a February 18 memorandum to
                                <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CCV1">Clifton</persName> listed the detailed questions
                            on guerrilla training posed by the President after his reading of
                                <persName corresp="#p_DGH1">Decker</persName>’s memorandum.
                            (Ibid.)</note> He stated that there are 7,000 to 15,000 Communist
                        guerrillas in South Viet-Nam and yet we have no guerrillas in North
                        Viet-Nam. He asked specifically how many Americans are in guerrilla
                        training. General <persName corresp="#p_DGH1">Decker</persName> replied with
                        a discussion of special forces training, and the Joint Chiefs all promised
                        to get him more data on this subject. The President then asked how the
                        special forces in Laos are doing with the tribesmen.</p>
                    <p>The President also asked if we should do more about bringing more Laotians
                        out of Laos, training them and sending them back in. Are we doing enough in
                        this field?</p>
                    <p>The President said there is obviously going to be more guerrilla and
                        counter-guerrilla activity in Africa and Asia in the near future. He then
                        asked what plans they had to step up our own training and plans in those two
                        spheres, and asked if they had learned anything from the other nations on
                        this matter. General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName>
                        responded that we have studied the British experience in Malaya and the
                        French experience in Southeast Asia, and we have been training some <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> people, but, obviously, we are not doing
                        enough.</p>
                    <p>General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> then mentioned the
                        memorandum here on the airlift and sealift readiness posture of Laos and how
                        detailed it is. He said that he would turn it over to me for briefing. The
                        President indicated he wanted to be briefed on this subject and he asked
                        them if the memorandum gave him any information on the relative buildup from
                        North Viet-Nam over the roads that could be accomplished in the same thirty
                        days which he had asked for before. The Chiefs responded that there was
                        nothing like that in this report, and they thought it might not be
                        meaningful <pb facs="0062" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/> because, obviously, they
                        could put a lot more Communists in there than we could get ourselves if they
                        so decided. The President emphasized again that he wanted their best opinion
                        on what the Viet-Namese could do in the same thirty days, and they promised
                        him a reply.</p>
                    <p>The next item was the B-52G, covered in a separate memorandum, attached.<note n="5" xml:id="d11fn5">Not found attached; see <ref target="#d12">Document 12</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>The President asked the Chiefs about the reenlistment rate, especially in
                            <gloss target="#t_SAC1">SAC</gloss>. All three Chiefs gave the President
                        a rundown on the reenlistment rate and emphasized that his “gold widow”
                        decision was going to be a help.</p>
                    <p>There then ensued a discussion of the efforts in the Services to hold down
                        the spending of American dollars by the Service people in lieu of having the
                        dependents refused the opportunity to go overseas. The President directed
                        that the Services take every measure possible to indoctrinate our people on
                        the importance of this matter, even though there was no good way of
                        measuring whether the men and their families were saving money or not.
                        General <persName corresp="#p_DGH1">Decker</persName> mentioned the U.S.
                        Savings Bond program and the Soldiers Deposits program as good steps to cut
                        down the amount of money. None of the Chiefs had any idea of restricting the
                        amount of funds that a man was paid in American currency. The President
                        reiterated that he hoped that they would take open and strong measures to
                        win the voluntary compliance with the spirit of this order so that he would
                        never again have to consider taking the dependents away from them.</p>
                    <p>The President asked Admiral <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Burke</persName>
                        about the water supply in Guantanamo. Admiral <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Burke</persName> told him that we had a three-week water supply
                        available by shipping and that we could keep this up with some strain on the
                        logistics supply line.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, the President directed that they give some attention to
                        guerrilla activities in relation to their future position in the Congo,
                        especially concerning training of intelligence teams and our advisory
                        groups, if and when they were to go in there.</p>
                    <p>After the meeting, General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName>
                        expressed his concern with our having all these papers and the backup
                        material in considerable detail. I assured General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> that after I had briefed the
                        President, I would keep the papers around for two weeks and return them to
                        him, and I would not give them wide distribution around the staff because
                        they held so much rather planning type information.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">CVC</hi></persName></signed><lb/><hi rend="italic">Brig. Gen., U.S. Army<lb/>Military Aide to the
                            President</hi></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>