<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>147. Memorandum From Spurgeon M. Keeny, Jr., to the President’s Special
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (, Jr., to the President’s Special
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (Bundy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d147</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">147</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recNHstTN4mCmPSgR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011305"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Missile defense</term>
                    <term ref="recyvYvKBWCiz1E8g" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026326"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil defense</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="147"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d147">
                <head>147. Memorandum From <persName type="from">Spurgeon M. Keeny</persName>, Jr.,
                    to the President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BMG2" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d147fn0">Source: <persName>Johnson</persName> Library, National
                        Security File, Agency File, Defense Budget 1965 Section 2. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-11-22">November 22, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>22 November Budget Meeting with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName>
                        <note n="1" xml:id="d147fn1">No meeting was held on November 22, the day
                            President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> was
                            assassinated. A meeting was held on November 16 among <persName
                                corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BMG2"
                                >Bundy</persName>, Gordon, <persName corresp="#p_WJB1"
                                >Wiesner</persName>, and others. (Memorandum for the record by
                                <persName>J.S. Hoover</persName>, Deputy Assistant Secretary of
                            Defense (Budget); ibid.)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The briefing paper prepared by the Bureau of the Budget<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d147fn2">Dated November 20. (Ibid.)</note> presents a good summary
                    of the four <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> white papers<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d147fn3">Reference is to semifinal versions of three <gloss
                            target="#t_DPM1">DPM</gloss>s and the final version of one. They are
                        cited in footnotes below.</note> and covers all of the key budget issues to
                    be discussed with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                    today. I have the following general comments on these papers:</p>
                <p>(1) Strategic Retaliatory Forces. While not abandoning the concept of “damage
                    limiting” capabilities, Secretary McNamara in this very interesting paper<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d147fn4">“Recommended <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                            1965-<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1969 Strategic Retaliatory
                        Forces,” dated November 13. (Department of State, Central Files, DEF 1
                        US)</note> continues to shift the focus of his strategic doctrine away from
                    the concept of “damage limiting” counterforces to the concept of “assured
                    destruction” of the Soviet Union. Within this context the central issue is the
                    proper size for the Minuteman force. The analysis presented makes it clear that
                    we have a capability for “assured destruction” of the Soviet Union entirely
                    independent of the <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> force. This is significant
                    since the previous draft of this document<note n="5" xml:id="d147fn5">The August
                        31 version of the strategic <gloss target="#t_DPM1">DPM</gloss> is attached
                        to a September 2 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>.
                        (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                            >RG</gloss> 218, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Records, JMF 7000
                        (31 Aug 61) Sec 1)</note> that I believe you read went through an elaborate
                    and unimpressive argument in an attempt to demonstrate that under certain
                    extremely pessimistic assumptions one could justify the entire force of 1200
                        <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> force under the requirement for an
                    “assured destruction” of the Soviet Union. The rationale for the <gloss
                        target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> force level is tied exclusively to the “damage
                    limiting” concept. However, examination of the table on page 19 of the <gloss
                        target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> paper<note n="6" xml:id="d147fn6">Reference is
                        to the chart entitled “U.S. Fatalities Assuming the Soviets Initiate the
                        Attack” in the strategic <gloss target="#t_DPM1">DPM</gloss>. The chart is
                        unchanged in the final version, <ref target="#d151">Document
                        151</ref>.</note> shows that the “damage limiting” strategy is at best not
                    very effective in a second strike situation and that diminishing returns have
                    set in long before one reaches the proposed <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> force level of 1200. When the Soviets initiate
                        <pb facs="0567" n="535" xml:id="pg_535"/> the attack, a force of 1200 <gloss
                        target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> does not appear to be significantly more
                    effective in reducing fatalities than a force of 950 <gloss target="#t_MM1"
                        >MM</gloss>.<note n="7" xml:id="d147fn7">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName> made a similar argument
                        regarding the August 31 draft of the strategic <gloss target="#t_DPM1"
                            >DPM</gloss>. (Memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_BMG2"
                            >Bundy</persName>, October 25, with 8-page attachment;
                            <persName>Johnson</persName> Library, National Security File, Agency
                        File, Defense Budget 1965 Section 2)</note>
                </p>
                <p>As compared with last year, the new <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> proposals
                    essentially involve a reduction in <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> force
                    levels by 100 <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> from 1300 to 1200, a slippage of
                    one year in achieving these goals (<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 68 to
                        <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 69), and an acceleration in the retrofit
                    program of improved <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_MM1"
                        >MM</gloss> in existing silos. I do not believe that the <gloss
                        target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> paper makes a real case either for the total
                    force level or for the urgency in the improved <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss>
                    program, even in the most pessimistic contingencies. (If one chooses to be
                    pessimistic about future adverse technological developments, I think that it
                    would be wiser to begin to invest strategic funds in advance systems development
                    such as the Polaris B-3 missile rather than build up of the <gloss
                        target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> force beyond 950 since it is conceivable that in
                    the 70’s the <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> may prove more vulnerable than we
                    are now willing to admit.) While I think the improved <gloss target="#t_MM1"
                        >MM</gloss> is a sensible program which overcomes some of the serious
                    limitations of the <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> system, it is being pushed
                    on a very tight concurrency schedule for which there appears to be no military
                        justification.<note n="8" xml:id="d147fn8">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> wrote “agreed” in the margin
                        next to this sentence.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In view of the above, I agree with the <gloss target="#t_BOB1">BOB</gloss>
                    proposals to hold the <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> force level at 950, to
                    slip the schedule of improved <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> program
                    slightly, and to delay the retrofit program of improved <gloss target="#t_MM1"
                        >MM</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss>. Nevertheless, Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> will undoubtedly argue,
                    persuasively, that it is impossible for Congressional and Pentagon political
                    reasons to cut the force objectives below 1200 and that an acceleration of the
                    improved <gloss target="#t_MM1">MM</gloss> program is necessary to sell even
                    this modest objective.<note n="9" xml:id="d147fn9">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> wrote “I doubt this” in the
                        margin next to this paragraph. In a budget discussion held November 27,
                            <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> did not accept the
                        Bureau of the Budget proposals for a reduced Minuteman force level and
                        slippage in improved Minuteman production, and it was agreed that the issues
                        would be submitted to President <persName>Johnson</persName>. (Memorandum
                        from Keeny to <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>, November 30;
                            <persName>Johnson</persName> Library, National Security File, Agency
                        File, Defense Budget 1965 Section 2) In a December 9 memorandum to President
                            <persName>Johnson</persName>, Kermit Gordon recommended holding the
                        Minuteman force level at 950 in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1965, but
                        did not oppose <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s eventual
                        force goal of 1,200. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>I believe that there is an additional issue here as to whether it is really
                    necessary to fire 10 percent of the missile force annually as part of the
                    reliability program. I do not believe that this many firings are necessary to
                    obtain adequate reliability statistics. Such a large number of firings would
                    also appear to be rather provocative as the size of the <gloss target="#t_MM1"
                        >MM</gloss> force grows (e.g. one every four or five days by <gloss
                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 65 and one every three days in <gloss
                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 69).</p>
                <pb facs="0568" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/>
                <p>There is no real reason to continue the B-70 program; however, given the amount
                    of our investment, I believe that it would be politically impossible to cancel
                    the program without any flights. I believe a practical solution to this problem
                    would be the cancellation of the third aircraft which the <gloss
                        target="#t_BOB1">BOB</gloss> estimates would save $80 million.<note n="10"
                        xml:id="d147fn10">At the November 27 meeting, <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName> agreed to cut back one of three programmed B-70s
                        “provided a positive decision was made on handling of the classified project
                        with which you are familiar.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>(2) Continental Air and Missile Defense. This paper<note n="11" xml:id="d147fn11"
                        >Reference is to <ref target="#d145">Document 145</ref>.</note> essentially
                    pushes all significant policy issues into the future. It is an unusual document
                    that appears to have been written by supporters of a very large continental
                    defense program who were directed to support a very small program. Since <gloss
                        target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> is not prepared to face the policy issues
                    involved, it only appears practical at this time to question whether the
                    recommended program is in fact consistent with future decisions to go either to
                    a smaller or much larger continental defense effort. The points raised by the
                        <gloss target="#t_BOB1">BOB</gloss> all appear valid with the exception of
                    the objections to <gloss target="#t_BMEWS1">BMEWS</gloss> improvement. I believe
                    that, unless these can be shown to be technically unsound, they are probably
                    justified given our existing investment in <gloss target="#t_BMEWS1"
                        >BMEWS</gloss> and alert B-52 aircraft.</p>
                <p>The civil defense question is not really covered in the <gloss target="#t_OSD1"
                        >OSD</gloss> paper and the discussion of this subject in the <gloss
                        target="#t_BOB1">BOB</gloss> briefing paper is not very helpful. The basic
                    issue on civil defense is whether we should attempt to get additional shelter
                    spaces through an incentive program as Secretary Pittman<note n="12"
                        xml:id="d147fn12">
                        <persName>Steuart L. Pittman</persName>, Assistant Secretary of Defense
                        (Civil Defense).</note> proposes or whether we should take the steps
                    necessary to make the shelters we have already identified useable as OST
                    proposes. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> has asked
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Gilpatric</persName> and Jerry to discuss this
                    question separately and I assume, therefore, it will not be discussed at the
                    meeting today, other than to establish a fiscal ceiling.</p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss>
                    </hi>. The principal budget issue in the <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss>
                    area is the force level and procurement of <gloss target="#t_SSN1">SSN</gloss>
                    (nuclear attack submarines). Unfortunately, the <gloss target="#t_OSD1"
                        >OSD</gloss> paper<note n="13" xml:id="d147fn13">“Anti-Submarine Warfare
                        Forces <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1965-1969,” November 9. (Department
                        of State, Central Files, DEF 1 US)</note> sheds little real light on this
                    question. The paper does not make a convincing case for the use of large numbers
                    of <gloss target="#t_SSN1">SSN</gloss> submarines and admittedly presents no
                    rationale for the proposed force level other than it will provide a better basis
                    from which to build a force if it is found to be necessary. While the <gloss
                        target="#t_BOB1">BOB</gloss> proposal to entirely eliminate production of
                        <gloss target="#t_SSN1">SSN</gloss> submarines is very appealing, I am
                    afraid that it is a bit too harsh to be acceptable. A good argument can
                    certainly be made that some continuing production capacity should be retained.
                    Therefore, I would propose building three or four <gloss target="#t_SSN1"
                        >SSN</gloss>’s in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 65 rather than the six
                        <pb facs="0569" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> proposed by <gloss
                        target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> or the nine proposed by the Navy.<note n="14"
                        xml:id="d147fn14">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> made a similar recommendation
                        in a December 5 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName>. (<persName>Johnson</persName> Library, National
                        Security File, Agency File, Defense Budget 1965 Section 2)</note> Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> will undoubtedly take the
                    position that he has already cut the Navy as much as he possibly can on this
                    highly emotional item.<note n="16" xml:id="d147fn16">The final version of the
                            <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_DPM1">DPM</gloss>, dated December 11, retains the
                        recommendation that <gloss target="#t_SSN1">SSN</gloss> procurement continue
                        at six boats per year. (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 218, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                        Records, JMF 7000 (3 Jan 64) Sec 1A)</note>
                </p>
                <p>(4) General Purpose Forces. This is an excellent paper<note n="17"
                        xml:id="d147fn17">“Recommended <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1965-<gloss
                            target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1969 Army and Marine Corps General Purpose
                        Forces,” November 15. (Department of State, Central Files, DEF 1 US) The
                        final version of this paper is <ref target="#d153">Document
                        153</ref>.</note> which arrived at important policy conclusions with which I
                    agree. If there are important budget issues in this area, they have been
                    carefully disguised by the <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> and have not been
                    identified by the <gloss target="#t_BOB1">BOB</gloss>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Spurgeon Keeny</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                    <note n="18" xml:id="d147fn18">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                        signature.</note>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
