<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>57. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Kaysen) to President ) to President Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d57</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">57</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoJDbAasG9LhuGg" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Force structure</term>
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007242"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Defense budget</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recvZDidU8pZ1fdw1" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">First
                        strike capability</term>
                    <term ref="recMrVNgNJpQ8DjcR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037301"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deterrence</term>
                    <term ref="rec4lWVXbMNjYBnWz" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Medium-range ballistic missiles</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="reckP3QiieAZd7kwE" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003001255"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Launchers</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="ballistic-missiles" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011308" lcsh-match="exact">Ballistic missiles</term>
                    <term ref="rec_korean_war" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="korean-war" subject="korean-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073119" lcsh-match="exact">Korean conflict</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-11-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="57"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d57">
                <head>57. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KC2" type="from">Kaysen</persName>) to
                    President <persName type="to">Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d57fn0">Source: Kennedy Library, National
                        Security Files, Departments and Agencies Series, <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                            >FY</gloss> 1963 Defense Budget 11/61-12/61. Top Secret. Forwarded to
                        the President with several other documents, including <ref target="#d58"
                            >Document 58</ref>. In a November 22 covering memorandum, Bundy
                        commented that this memorandum “sketches the argument for a much smaller
                        strategic force than <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> is
                        arguing. This is well worth attention because the argument is not developed
                        anywhere else in your papers.” (<persName>Kennedy</persName> Library,
                        National Security Files, Departments and Agencies Series, <gloss
                            target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1963 Defense Budget 11/16-12/61)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-11-22">November 22, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Force Structure and Defense Budget</item>
                </list>
                <p>1. The major issue which was presented by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                        >McNamara</persName>’s memorandum on the Defense budget<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d57fn1">
                        <ref target="#d50">Document 50</ref>.</note> is that of the balance between
                    the long-range strategic striking force and the general purpose (limited war)
                    forces. Speaking broadly, the Secretary’s proposed Planning Guidelines resolved
                    the inevitable doubts and uncertainties on the high side with respect to
                    long-range striking forces, and, on the low side with respect to <pb facs="0242"
                        n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/> the general purpose forces. The purpose of the
                    following is to present a case for a different force structure which would
                    resolve these issues the other way.</p>
                <p>2. The two elements of the strategic striking force which show rapid growth in
                    the Secretary’s memorandum and proposed Guidelines are the hardened and
                    dispersed Minuteman and Polaris missiles. The B-52 force remains constant, and,
                    while the Atlas and Titan both show substantial growth, the new sites involved
                    are now under construction and the missiles have already been bought. The
                    proposed Minuteman and Polaris forces grow as follows:</p>
                <table cols="7" rows="6">
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1962</cell>
                        <cell>1963</cell>
                        <cell>1964</cell>
                        <cell>1965</cell>
                        <cell>1966</cell>
                        <cell>1967</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Polaris</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Submarines</cell>
                        <cell role="num">6</cell>
                        <cell role="num">9</cell>
                        <cell role="num">18</cell>
                        <cell role="num">30</cell>
                        <cell role="num">35</cell>
                        <cell role="num">41</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Missiles</cell>
                        <cell role="num">96</cell>
                        <cell role="num">144</cell>
                        <cell role="num">288</cell>
                        <cell role="num">480</cell>
                        <cell role="num">560</cell>
                        <cell role="num">656</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Minuteman</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Missiles</cell>
                        <cell>—</cell>
                        <cell role="num">150</cell>
                        <cell role="num">600</cell>
                        <cell role="num">700</cell>
                        <cell role="num">800</cell>
                        <cell role="num">900</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>These forces were proposed on the basis of the old estimates of the probable
                    development of Russian missile strength. If we take into account the newer
                    estimates (shown in comparison with the estimates underlying the <gloss
                        target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> calculations in Annex I attached), we find we
                    can accept a significantly smaller force as follows:</p>
                <table cols="6" rows="5">
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1963</cell>
                        <cell>1964</cell>
                        <cell>1965</cell>
                        <cell>1966</cell>
                        <cell>1967</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Minuteman (HD)</cell>
                        <cell role="num">150</cell>
                        <cell role="num">300</cell>
                        <cell role="num">400</cell>
                        <cell role="num">500</cell>
                        <cell role="num">600</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Polaris</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Missiles</cell>
                        <cell role="num">144</cell>
                        <cell role="num">288</cell>
                        <cell role="num">464</cell>
                        <cell role="num">464</cell>
                        <cell role="num">464</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Submarines</cell>
                        <cell role="num">9</cell>
                        <cell role="num">18</cell>
                        <cell role="num">29</cell>
                        <cell role="num">29</cell>
                        <cell role="num">29</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The proposed Polaris force represents the submarines we have already bought,
                    coming into service on the present schedule. The proposed Minuteman deployment
                    involves postponing the achievement of the planned 4th wing from the end of
                        <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1963 to the end of <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                        >FY</gloss> 1967.</p>
                <p>The rationale for these lower forces is two-fold. First, as will be explained in
                    the paragraph immediately following, they can do the job. Second, if they can do
                    the job the risks of having higher forces are considerable. In setting the level
                    of our strategic force, we must always consider the possibility of interaction
                    between the size of our force and the size of the Soviet force. It is dangerous
                    for us to seek to achieve a full first strike capability, because such a goal
                    will almost certainly provoke a Soviet reaction in the same direction. Both
                    sides will spend more of their resources on larger forces and neither will gain
                    in security. The present plan provides for an extremely sharp increase in our
                    strategic striking power between July 1963 and July 1964. Our total long-range
                    missile strength, which is now in the neighborhood of 120, will by July 1963
                    have grown to over 500 and by July 1964 it will have more than doubled again to
                    over 1100. Will not such a sharp increase present the appearance of our <pb
                        facs="0243" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/> seeking a first strike posture, and
                    thus have a high probability of provoking a response in kind by the Soviets?
                    They are perfectly capable of such response. At present, the most sensible
                    interpretation of their own missile deployment is that it rests on the concept
                    of finite deterrence. It is certainly to our advantage to have them continue to
                    hold that concept. The Air Force has in the past equated national security with
                    an ever increasing strategic striking force, and this position has wide popular
                    appeal and support. This view is filled with dangers; to the extent that the
                    best evidence indicates it lacks justification, it is important to move our
                    military planning away from it as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>3. We can safely rely on the proposed smaller force for two reasons: First, the
                    number of missiles we expect the Russians to have is lower than that on which
                    the plans were made. On this basis alone, the task the Memorandum shows as
                    requiring 700 Minutemen in the force (Median assumptions, 1965, column I), could
                    be done by some 550. This involves not only a smaller number of targets for us
                    to strike at, but also a higher survival rate for our forces under the Russian
                    first strike, on the basis of which the calculations are made. Second, the
                    targeting concepts underlying the calculations in the Secretary’s memorandum are
                    unnecessarily conservative. No targets are assigned to the theatre forces. Only
                    Polaris strikes against cities are taken into account in estimating casualties
                    and destruction in built-up areas. At least the medium-range bomber and recovery
                    airfields and the medium-range ballistic missiles could be assigned to the
                    theatre forces. Some of the surviving <gloss target="#t_SAC1">SAC</gloss> B-52’s
                    would be available for strikes on cities. The missiles we program against Soviet
                    military targets would cause considerable casualties all over the Soviet Union,
                    which are not taken into account in the casualty estimates from fallout
                    presented in the memorandum. When all these adjustments are made in the
                    calculations, the proposed smaller forces become adequate for the defined goal:
                    to maintain a survivable second strike capability which can both blunt the
                    further Soviet threat and provide a reserve force capable of threatening attack
                    on Soviet cities on a large scale.</p>
                <p>4. The Secretary’s memorandum offers no explicit rationale for fixing the size of
                    the Army at 14 divisions comparable to the analysis contained in Appendix I on
                    long-range striking forces,<note n="2" xml:id="d57fn2">
                        <ref target="#d46">Document 46</ref>.</note> and the Secretary pointed out
                    in our staff discussions that as yet no such analysis has been made.
                    Nonetheless, the recommendation is similar to that contained in the Secretary’s
                    memorandum to the President of May 10, 1961,<note n="3" xml:id="d57fn3">
                        <ref target="#d27">Document 27</ref>.</note> on the reappraisal of the
                    capabilities of conventional forces. That analysis rested on two doubtful
                    assumptions: First, that we would not be engaged in a conventional war on a
                    scale greater than that of the Korean <pb facs="0244" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/>
                    conflict (250,000-300,000 men); second, that we would not be engaged in more
                    than one such war at any one time. If in fact it is our policy to raise the
                    nuclear threshold in the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> area, as well as
                    in the rest of the world, the first of these assumptions may be inappropriate.
                    The appropriateness of the second one is also open to question, although here a
                    policy question is involved as to the circumstances in which we would be willing
                    to commit U.S. troops in other theatres, that is as yet unsettled.</p>
                <p>5. The planned 14-division army raises the question of whether or not the extra
                    forces provided by calling up the reservists and National Guardsmen in
                    connection with the Berlin crisis should be retained on active duty. The
                    Secretary’s proposal calls for the return of these men to reserve status and a
                    consequent reduction in the active duty strength of the Army to 920,000 men.
                    This reduction raises a number of questions. It may make it more difficult for
                    us to convince our Allies to increase their conventional war capabilities in
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. It may diminish significantly the
                    message conveyed by our other military preparations to the Soviets, who are
                    impressed by ground force strength. Further, there is an important efficiency
                    question involved. If there is any substantial probability that future
                    re-examination of the ultimate size of the Army would lead to a higher
                    requirement than 14 divisions, it would seem wasteful to reduce and then
                    increase its size in the course of the next year or two. This in turn raises the
                    question of the extent to which, in fixing the ultimate size of the Army, it is
                    wise to rely on calling up and then demobilizing reserves as crises arise, if,
                    as seems likely, crises will occur with fair frequency in the future.</p>
                <p>6. With respect to the size of the Army, the proposed alternate program is to
                    recommend that the Berlin augmentation be maintained in <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                        >FY</gloss> 1963 and that otherwise the Secretary’s program for
                    strengthening the logistic support and tactical air complement of the present
                    force be carried out. This would involve not only keeping the Army at the level
                    of 16 divisions with 970,000 men. Further, the proposed Planning Guidelines
                    should not now be issued, and the Department of Defense should be instructed to
                    produce an analysis and proposed Planning Guideline for the period 1964-67 early
                    next year. At that point, the question of phasing down can be examined in the
                    light of a clear conception of what our ultimate goals are.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KC2">
                            <hi rend="strong">Carl Kaysen</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0245" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Annex I<note n="4" xml:id="d57fn4">Top Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">ESTIMATES OF FUTURE SOVIET MISSILE STRENGTH<lb/>Projected
                        Number of Launchers</p>
                    <table cols="6" rows="17">
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> Planning Guide</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss> Estimate (9 November)</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Type of Site</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Launchers per Target</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Median</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Range</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Median</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">Range</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">1965</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Soft</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2</cell>
                            <cell role="num">400</cell>
                            <cell role="num">200-600</cell>
                            <cell role="num">125</cell>
                            <cell role="num">100-150</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Dispersed</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1</cell>
                            <cell>-</cell>
                            <cell>-</cell>
                            <cell role="num">210</cell>
                            <cell role="num">150-275</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hard</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1</cell>
                            <cell role="num">350</cell>
                            <cell role="num">200-500</cell>
                            <cell>a few</cell>
                            <cell>a few</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Total Missiles</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">750</cell>
                            <cell role="num">400-1100</cell>
                            <cell role="num">340</cell>
                            <cell role="num">250-325</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Total Targets</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">550</cell>
                            <cell role="num">300-800</cell>
                            <cell role="num">275</cell>
                            <cell role="num">200-325</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="italic">1967</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Soft</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2</cell>
                            <cell role="num">250</cell>
                            <cell role="num">100-400</cell>
                            <cell role="num">125</cell>
                            <cell role="num">100-150</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Dispersed</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1</cell>
                            <cell>-</cell>
                            <cell>-</cell>
                            <cell role="num">300</cell>
                            <cell role="num">200-400</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hard</cell>
                            <cell role="num">1</cell>
                            <cell role="num">750</cell>
                            <cell role="num">400-1100</cell>
                            <cell role="num">100</cell>
                            <cell role="num">50-100</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Total Missiles</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">1000</cell>
                            <cell role="num">500-1500</cell>
                            <cell role="num">525</cell>
                            <cell role="num">350-650</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Total Targets</cell>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="num">875</cell>
                            <cell role="num">450-1300</cell>
                            <cell role="num">465</cell>
                            <cell role="num">300-575</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
