<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d112</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">112</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-01-27T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-01-27T23:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-27T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-27T23:00:00-05:00" n="112" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/1–2849: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-28T12:00:00+08:00">January 28, 1949—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received January 30—3:06 a.
                        m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>255. On January 27, officer of Embassy and Naval Attaché interviewed Kan
                    Chieh-hou, just returned from Shanghai following series conferences with
                    minority party leaders on behalf Li Tsung-jen. Kan said that, while these
                    leaders not directly representing CCP, they are in sufficiently close touch with
                    Communists that they can accurately report and interpret Communist policy.
                    Leaders told him Communists have three peace requirements. First is no “middle
                    road”; all political groups and factions must adopt same attitude toward CCP as
                    KmtRC and Democratic League. Second is no further American influence in Chinese
                    affairs, no further dealings with Americans including no acceptance American aid
                    by any group. Third is no negotiations with any group on basis its possession
                    military or territorial resources; negotiation only with individuals on basis
                    past political performance and present political record. On basis above, Kan and
                    President both convinced no agreement with Communists possible.</p>
                <p>Despite Communist intransigence, Li intends attempt negotiate. Already has two
                    delegates Peiping who made initial contact with Communists January 26. No report
                    received on result contact. On 27th or 28th, plans send telegram Mao Tse-tung
                    reaffirming sincere desire for peace in denying that he is creature of Americans
                    and pointing out that, while Communists have claimed desire negotiate, their
                    terms have been couched as ultimatum. As follow-up, Li then plans send Shao
                    Li-tze and Chang Chih-chung [to] Peiping with instructions <pb facs="0104" n="94" xml:id="pg_94"/> wait until Communists receive them for purposes
                    negotiation. Purpose of above is to show clearly onus for continuing war lies
                    with Communists, thus gaining popular support for Nationalists. Also hopes
                    pressure public opinion and Communist hope that they can get Government
                    surrender through negotiations may make Communists delay crossing Yangtze. Li
                    convinced no possibility get fair agreement from Communists, but hopes use this
                    technique stall for time.</p>
                <p>Government would like defend Yangtze line but lacks required forces. Tang
                        En-po<note n="82" xml:id="d112fn82">Head of the newly established
                        Nanking–Shanghai–Hangchow garrison command.</note> deploying to defend
                    Nanking-Shanghai Railroad over which he will withdraw when seriously threatened.
                    Liu Ju-ming,<note n="83" xml:id="d112fn83">Deputy Commander in Chief, Rebellion
                        Suppression Forces, Hsuchow area.</note> with very inferior forces, will try
                    prevent crossing between Wuhu and Nanking. Pai Chung-hsi will retreat to Wuchang
                    when threatened. After Communist crossing, Government hopes establish defense
                    line along Chientang River into northern Kiangsi and Hunan with Kiangsi-Hunan
                    sector under Pai Chung-hsi. Government will hold this line longest possible,
                    hoping for American assistance. This aid must include military mission. No
                    question interference with China’s sovereign rights exists. American troops
                    welcomed as would be American participation protection Taiwan.</p>
                <p>We are in general agreement with contention that any agreement Government may
                    reach with Communists will be at price of whatever resources it might have to
                    preserve itself as entity in coalition government. Communists appear determined
                    eradicate once and for all any political grouping which might conceivably form
                    nucleus resistance their political and military control over entire country.</p>
                <p>We think it highly unlikely Li’s maneuvers will delay Communist attempt cross
                    Yangtze. Also, it is doubtful if they will succeed in rousing any considerable
                    degree popular support for Government. However, they will establish clearly
                    total character Communist aims, and should to some extent succeed in firming up
                    resistance sentiment [of] south and southwest China leaders.</p>
                <p>Sent Department, pouched Consulates.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
