<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Stuart) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d131</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">131</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recHrSmzhfG78SwqX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="rec9yKWGNvCFmqmdD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="131"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d131">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/2–549</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 44</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-05">February 5,
                            1949</date>.<lb/>[Received February 18.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to comment on some of the deeper
                    implications of the catastrophic events in China which are happening so rapidly
                    that we have been reporting them zalmost entirely by telegraph.</p>
                <p>What we have been observing since V–J Day, and especially during the latter half
                    of last year, is in a sense the decay of the ancient Chinese system of
                    Government. The original urge of the Kuomintang was chiefly anti-dynastic—as had
                    been true of the earlier Taiping Rebellion—and, although it included democratic
                    ideas and modern reforms, these were weakened or lost in a reversal to
                    traditional practises. In the case of Chiang Kai-shek himself there is no need
                    to question his personal probity nor his patriotic motives, but his concepts and
                    methods were undemocratic. There were also many in the Government of high
                    integrity and liberal views. But the system permitted and even fostered the
                    evils which caused its downfall. It had become so corrupt and inefficient, and
                    had so completely lost all popular support, that there was but little hope of
                    orderly reforms arising from within, and revolutionary outbreaks might have been
                    expected even had there been no Communist Movement.</p>
                <p>This had its genesis in China independent of the Kuomintang and had already
                    attained sizeable proportions before that Party had come into power. It would
                    doubtless have gained adherents, as in other countries, regardless of the
                    failings of the Kuomintang. But these were effectively exploited by the Chinese
                    Communist Party and have been an important element in its success. This is the
                    reason why so many of the more idealistic students have been attracted to it. It
                    will therefore serve as a catalyst in ridding China once and for all of the
                    scholar-official privileged caste. Whether in doing so it will enforce a worse
                    form of totalitarian despotism is now the question.</p>
                <p>American antipathy to the evils apparently inherent in the Communist State has
                    led us to outspoken sympathy with and generous <pb facs="0119" n="109"
                        xml:id="pg_109"/> assistance to the Chiang Government. But to the leader of
                    that Government and his most ardent followers Chinese Communism was at the
                    outset more in the nature of one more rival faction to be subdued by force—like
                    the warlords—than a social upheaval to be neutralized by political and economic
                    reforms. Through all the following years this factional antagonism has been
                    intensified by personal animosities. The American policy has been sorely
                    misunderstood as seeming to be on the side of the present-day equivalent of the
                    rascally and reactionary mandarins of a bygone age instead of with the pioneers
                    of a new and nobler social order. This may seem naive to us or even
                    disingenuous, but an attempt to see it through their eyes will help to explain
                    not only the virulence of Communist anti-American propaganda but the embittered
                    criticism of our policy prevailing among almost all of the younger and perhaps a
                    majority of the older nonpartisan intellectuals.</p>
                <p>There is a poignant irony in all of this. We came into existence as a nation
                    through a revolutionary struggle for freedom and have led the world as the
                    defenders of political democracy and of basic human rights. Nowhere has this
                    been more heartily acclaimed than in China. Nowhere have we given more unstinted
                    moral inspiration and material assistance. Yet now we are being blamed by
                    anti-Communist leaders for not coming more vigorously to their rescue, as we did
                    against the Japanese, and by all others for strengthening a decadent feudalistic
                    regime and by thus meddling in China’s internal affairs lengthening a
                    devastating civil war. Our motives are also impugned as being directed against
                    the Soviet Union rather than for the welfare of the Chinese people.</p>
                <p>None the less we have very great assets for the impending struggle. There is an
                    immense reservoir of good will for us among the Chinese people. We have done
                    much through our cultural activities in China and from what they themselves have
                    learned of our way of life to reinforce the teachings of their revered sages as
                    to human relationships and social justice. This heritage will not fit them for
                    meekly enduring intolerant regimentation. As they come into power the Communists
                    will probably perpetrate their customary excesses and this will tend to alienate
                    those not yet sufficiently indoctrinated. There will for some time be large
                    areas on the periphery of this country where we can continue to exert our
                    influence. The President’s Inaugural Address will have a profound effect as a
                    declaration of the high-principled, dynamic foreign policy of the present
                    Administration.</p>
                <p>Acting President Li is making a brave effort to secure a negotiated peace and is
                    thus far revealing a commendable patience and indifference <pb facs="0120"
                        n="110" xml:id="pg_110"/> to personal consequences. He is keeping the public
                    fully informed and is pressing for an early settlement on behalf of the
                    suffering people. There is a fair probability that he will be successful because
                    of the popular desire for peace and the weakness of the Government. He hopes to
                    make his case unmistakably clear before the Nation and the world as to whether
                    or not Chinese Communism will agree to a reasonable peace and a truly democratic
                    form of government. If not, he and Pai Chung-hsi will return to their native
                    province and rally all those areas not yet subjugated in a new form of
                    resistance depending primarily on popular support.</p>
                <p>In any case we may expect a period of harshly dictatorial and discriminatory
                    treatment of foreigners, especially of Americans. The Embassy is attempting to
                    tabulate a factual record of this nature. Thus far the indications are far from
                    reassuring—in Tsinan, Mukden, Tientsin, with ominous overtones from Peiping.
                    Some allowance must be made of course for confusion and excessive self-assertion
                    at the outset and for the period of nonrecognition. It will be useful to
                    converse with the leaders when that becomes feasible and to ascertain as best we
                    can what are their real intentions.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile I venture to suggest an attitude of quiet and watchful reserve, with
                    preparation for expansion of USIS<note n="12" xml:id="d131fn12">United States
                        Information Service.</note> and emphasis on the spreading of stimulating
                    ideas and practical information rather than on money or military power. These
                    latter may be needed later. Continuation of E. C. A. might well be kept in
                    abeyance until they raise the issue. One possible exception might be the Joint
                    Commission on Rural Reconstruction in provinces not yet “liberated” where it can
                    have immense value, both in directly improving the people’s livelihood and in
                    educating them for democratic citizenship.</p>
                <p>The Acting President has committed himself to long-needed governmental reforms.
                    He should, as he is able, carry these out and make it known. If Communist
                    administration is as oppressive as we have reason to fear it may be, it can be
                    confidently expected that a spirit of revolt will sooner or later find concrete
                    expression and if this is under a leadership which has popular support we can
                    give it our unreserved assistance. Until then we can deal with the new
                    authorities on a basis flexible and friendly but also very firm, in the
                    assurance that our cause is right and will in time be proven so to a people as
                    intelligent and as sympathetic to our history and principles as are the
                    Chinese.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Leighton Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
