<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="198" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/3–749</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Tsingtao</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Strong</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>)<note n="84" xml:id="d198fn84">Copy
                                transmitted to the Department without covering despatch; received
                                April 5.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 3</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tsingtao</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-07">March 7,
                                1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit the monthly
                            political and military summary for the Tsingtao consular district for
                            February 1949. The initial portion of this report is an introductory
                            summary.</p>
                        <pb facs="0175" n="165" xml:id="pg_165"/>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Introductory Summary</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Mid-February saw an almost complete about-face in the political and
                            military prospects for Tsingtao. Instead of withdrawing as planned, the
                            Nationalist troops were ordered to remain. In turn, the American Naval
                            forces which were in the main to move out, leaving only a small
                            rearguard, extended their stay. Thus the timing for a communist takeover
                            of Tsingtao and its environs again has been revised; current prospects
                            lead to the estimate of several months of relative stability before
                            possible assumption of control by the communist regime. The
                            reinvigoration of the Taiyuan airlift from Tsingtao; the apparent
                            intention of the communists not to attack the Yangtze line during peace
                            negotiations, thus freeing Nationalist forces for holding Tsingtao; the
                            probability that the negotiations will continue for some time; and the
                            logical desire of the Nationalist Government to hold as many points as
                            possible in North China for prestige and bargaining purposes, all lead
                            to this conclusion. Thus Tsingtao, which was to have been lopped off the
                            body of Nationalist China as a useless appendage, has been brought into
                            the national scene and its fate is now dependent on the momentous events
                            of the next few months.</p>
                        <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>Only the generous contributions of ECA to Tsingtao in terms of food and
                            coal have kept Tsingtao afloat. The presence of the United States Naval
                            Forces at Tsingtao is viewed as evidence of Nationalist intention to
                            hold the city, and its withdrawal would initially be interpreted as the
                            preliminary to departure of the Nationalist troops. Whereas in the past
                            the U.S. Navy was regarded as the real protective force for Tsingtao, it
                            is now recognized that the communists have no intention of posing a
                            military threat to Tsingtao. Thus Chinese residents tend to gauge the
                            intentions of the Nationalist Government toward Tsingtao by the
                            activities of the U.S. Naval Forces. During the absence of Admiral
                            Badger with his flagship for twelve days [this] had no visible effect on
                            internal stability.</p>
                        <p>Evacuation of foreigners from Tsingtao was to all intents and purposes
                            completed during the month. Somewhat over eight hundred non-Asiatics
                            remain of whom over one-half are Soviet citizens. It is anticipated that
                            the foreign community will hereafter remain stable.</p>
                        <p>The tension which pervaded Tsingtao in January and early February has
                            almost entirely been eliminated. However with trade at low ebb and
                            inflation rampant, Tsingtao’s citizens are anxious to have their fate
                            settled in one way or another in order that a return to more normal
                            business and living conditions may improve their lot. (End of
                            Introductory Summary)</p>
                        <p>[Here follows detailed report.]</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Strong</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>