<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-22T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-22T06:00:00-05:00" n="229" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d229">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/3–2249: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-22T19:00:00+08:00">March 22,
                                    1949—7 p. m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received March 23—3:10 p. m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>628. Following our study of such CCP pronouncements as Mao Tse-tung’s
                            article commemorating October revolution and Liu Shao-chi’s<note n="41" xml:id="d229fn41">Vice Chairman of the Central Committee of the
                                Chinese Communist Party.</note> article on “nationalism and
                            internationalism” last November, we had concluded as reported that time
                            that CCP, at least verbally, had left undone little to subordinate
                            Chinese national interests to those of USSR. However, with North Shensi
                            broadcast March 18 (repeated March 19 for emphasis) CCP advanced its
                            satellite foreign policy still further by announcing “Chinese people
                            cannot but regard <pb facs="0203" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/> leaders of
                            war provocateurs, American imperialist bellicose elements, as their
                            mortal foes and cannot but regard leaders of world anti-imperialist
                            front, great socialist state, Soviet Union, as their comrades in arms,
                            from first to last”.</p>
                        <p>Whole tone of broadcast is that CCP wholeheartedly and optimistically
                            backs Soviet “struggle for peace” but that if worst comes to worst, CCP
                            will enter war alongside USSR. At risk of reading falsely between lines,
                            we do note, however, that (1) CCP commitment to fight could have been
                            more clearly and irrevocably expressed than it was, and (2) it is
                            conditioned upon USSR accepting “strong and independent China as good
                            friend and ally”. We do not derive much cheer from these observations,
                            however, since (1) CCP commitment is no more indirect than statements of
                            Thorez and Togliatti,<note n="42" xml:id="d229fn42">Maurice Thorez and
                                Palmiro Togliatti, leaders of the French and Italian Communist
                                Parties, respectively.</note> serving similar purpose; and (2)
                            Soviets—particularly after their lesson in Yugoslavia—will doubtless
                            display sufficient vision and tolerance in their foreign policy to avoid
                            offending sensibilities of Chinese Communists, at least at present stage
                            of history. Because of this as well as timing of broadcast, our
                            convictions are strengthened that Chinese Communists are wittingly or
                            unwittingly tools of Soviet expansion and as such are constitutionally
                            incapable of objective international attitude toward US.</p>
                        <p>This reaffirmation of loyalty to USSR and world Communism on three
                            important grounds seems far more Communist than Chinese. First, except
                            for one passing reference to “Kmt reactionary government”, principal
                            enemy of CCP, US was sole target of attack. Second, it so debases
                            Chinese national interests as to rationalize Soviet occupation of Dairen
                            and Port Arthur as “severe blows to imperialist aggression in Far East
                            and far-reaching guarantees of interest of Chinese people against
                            aggression”. Third, its timing with North Atlantic treaty,<note n="43" xml:id="d229fn43">Signed at Washington, April 4, 1949; for text, see
                                Department of State Treaties and Other International Acts Series No.
                                1964, or 63 Stat. (pt. 2) 2241.</note> which is certainly not of
                            immediate consequence to China’s struggle, betrays same kind of loyalty
                            to Moscow and disregard of Chinese interest that prompted Mao Tse-tung
                            in 1942 to urge concentration of united nations’ efforts against Germany
                            rather than Japan.</p>
                        <p>We fear this broadcast indicates Chinese Communists may be falling into
                            same web of self-deception that cost Nazis and Fascists so dearly and
                            which is now attracting Communists everywhere, namely that America is
                            weak. Chinese Communists have long inveighed against our principles and
                            good intentions. But now, for first time, they raise question of our
                            power, saying “Chinese people see in American imperialism a paper tiger”
                            and that “if only peace-loving forces unite <pb facs="0204" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/> in struggle and do not commit misjudging, American
                            imperialism is sure to be vanquished”. If CCP-controlled press and
                            theoreticians succeed in cultivating this auto-intoxication, it will
                            prove one more obstacle to CCP objective appraisal of international
                            scene and China’s proper place therein.</p>
                        <p>We consider this broadcast major statement of public policy, albeit
                            described as “New China News Agency editorial”. It is most disturbing in
                            its implications for US and ominous for our continuing efforts to reach
                                <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> with Communists.</p>
                        <p>Sent Department 628; repeated Canton 181; Shanghai 286; Moscow 22.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>