<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d355</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">355</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-05-10T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-10T06:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="oil" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-10T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-10T06:00:00-05:00" n="355" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d355">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.50/5–1049: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-10T19:00:00+08:00">May 10, 1949—7 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received May 11—1:45 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>989. [To Shanghai:] I met with my French and British colleagues, latter’s
                    request, this morning to discuss present, future situation Shanghai and possible
                    courses action by you and your colleagues to mitigate effects all-out defense of
                    city. (Reurtel 1550 to Department May 7, repeated Nanking 865, Canton 418.) We
                    decided to recommend to you and British, French ConGens that you suggest to your
                    respective Chambers of Commerce that they participate in and support any move of
                    non-political nature by local Chinese (presumably Chinese Chamber of Commerce)
                    vis-á-vis military authorities to preserve physical plant of city, principally
                    utilities and industries, from deliberate destruction. It was felt that any
                    approach should be Chinese-led although appropriately supported by local foreign
                    interests.</p>
                <p>We further agreed that should this appeal of Chinese and foreign interests
                    materialize and prove successful, the foreign governments might possibly endorse
                    action taken by local bodies.</p>
                <p>Since French Ambassador experiencing some difficulty communicating with his
                    ConGen Shanghai, please inform your French colleague substance of above in which
                    Meyrier concurs. Your British colleague receiving similar message direct from
                    Stevenson.</p>
                <p>Re first consideration urtel under reference, you will remember question joint
                    foreign intervention in somewhat different terms was considered by Department
                    early December and was discouraged at that time. Second consideration is covered
                    by above recommendations. Re third consideration, I can not believe our best
                    interests would be served by gratuitous stocking of supplies, including oil,
                    preparatory to Communist takeover or extending credit for their subsequent
                    acquisition. We have recommended against any additional aid to Nationalist <pb facs="0313" n="303" xml:id="pg_303"/> defenders of Shanghai (see Embtel 493,
                    May 3, repeated Department 926<note n="94" xml:id="d355fn94">
                        <ref target="frus1949v09#pg_641">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, p.
                            641</ref>.</note> Canton 346) and could scarcely justify, on political
                    grounds at least, similar assistance to their enemies.</p>
                <p>I want to take this opportunity to assure you and American community Shanghai of
                    my lively sympathy your predicament and full appreciation heavy responsibility
                    for protection American lives and interests which rests upon you.</p>
                <p>Sent Shanghai 550, repeated Department, OffEmb Canton 393.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
