<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Shanghai ( (Cabot) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d373</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">373</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-16T00:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recCP2IC3LozXMzXn" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recfgV5j0WMmONcRO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic crisis</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-16T00:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="373"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d373">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/5–1649: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-16T13:00:00+08:00"
                            >May 16, 1949—1 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received May 16—8:15 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1656. That Generalissimo feels no compunction but likely satisfaction in seeking
                    make Shanghai battlefield and shambles regardless all but his own shortsighted
                    interests is conviction most observers based on evidence such as:</p>
                <p>Feverish defense preparations: Ruthless leveling wide belt villages and estates
                    around city perimeter now being followed by fortifying roof tops and sandbagging
                    main buildings and junction spots into very heart city with apparent expectation
                    street fighting.</p>
                <pb facs="0331" n="321" xml:id="pg_321"/>
                <p>Other military signs such as selective retention in city all operable army tanks
                    and air strafing of Communists at very low level rarely risked by Nationalist
                    planes.</p>
                <p>Anti-Communist parade with floats depicting Communist and Yellow Ox atrocities;
                    exhortation of populace by speeches, hand bills to support “supreme military
                    authority” unconquerable stand against “Red bandits”, make Shanghai second
                    Stalingrad, et cetera.</p>
                <p>Desperate efforts bolster collapsing army morale with various rumors American
                    aid, announcements of unprecedented privileges, free meals, entertainments, et
                    cetera, to be given “our soldier heroes” and alleged hasty replacements
                    undependable units with new divisions from Formosa.</p>
                <p>Intense secret service activity directed by Generalissimo through his son
                    Ching-kuo and BIS chiefs: Assignment special troops handle desertions and
                    rebellion; and increasing terroristic suppression student, leftist, civil and
                    business elements suspected as likely promoters peaceful turnover by wholesale
                    arrests, man hunts, deportations and intimidation. Even Mme. Sun Yat-sen<note
                        n="16" xml:id="d373fn16">Widow of the founder of the Kuomintang and of the
                        Chinese Republic; sister of Mesdames Chiang Kai-shek and H. H. Kung and of
                        T. V. Soong.</note> said now in some danger arrest.</p>
                <p>Attempted removal all government organs from city; arbitrary requisitioning of
                    motor cars; heavy exporting of city’s removable equipment and materials; and
                    financial manipulations to syphon off all available wealth.</p>
                <p>Persistently reported plans demolish utilities, dockyards, et cetera, upon final
                    withdrawal Nationalist forces.</p>
                <p>Generalissimo’s apparent strategy making Woosung region his final defense area to
                    permit full completion his stripping, demolition and evacuation programs.</p>
                <p>Aside from vindictive punishment Shanghai leaders and groups whose
                    non-cooperation has earned them his bitter hatred, Generalissimo’s primary
                    motives for apparent planning this senseless fighting and destruction appear to
                    be: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Exploit Shanghai stage for limelighting melodramatic show last ditch
                            defense of “international city” against world Communism in face
                            overwhelming odds unaided by “ungrateful” America.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Crush all possibility of an orderly city turnover under circumstances
                            propitious for development of mutually beneficial <hi rend="italic"
                                >modus vivendi</hi> among Communists Shanghai Chinese and
                            international interests; and force Communists to take city in ruined
                            chaotic state with every possible liability and problem serving to
                            complicate city’s existence, exacerbate Communists relations with
                            foreign interests, and increase tension between Moscow and western
                            democracies.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Protect Generalissimo’s operations “drama” “udder” “dynamite” and
                            “Dunkirk” to last possible moment.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0332" n="322" xml:id="pg_322"/>
                <p>Meanwhile mounting Communist military pressure and close approach city leads many
                    now believe final showdown may come any moment. Seems likely Communists will (1)
                    press attacks at many points perimeter with view force Nationalists spread thin
                    their inferior strength; (2) seek minimize destruction in city by avoiding heavy
                    bombardment and taking city by infantry alone as far as possible; (3) close in
                    on Nationalists’ Woosung bastion with view cutting off of Generalissimo’s
                    evacuation. Generalissimo’s need to retain Woosung area longest and general
                    Communist pressure around city will probably force him attempt early withdrawal
                    from city to Woosung or coast to escape trapping. Observers feel his forces will
                    disintegrate rapidly under Communist attack and that Communists could smash his
                    resistance in week or so if ready for determined effort. Prospects of imminent
                    violence and disorders in city preceding, during and immediately following final
                    battle are increasing in view of following factors: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Progress of secret preparations for establishment of intermediate
                            peace maintenance regime appears delayed as result of Generalissimo’s
                            energetic surveillance of movement’s chief organizers, of his bellicose
                            preparations—which lessen chances for early crumbling or voluntary
                            abandonment of Nationalist resistance and, perhaps, of Communists’
                            waning interest in project owing to its now dubious potentialities for
                            effective action. [W. W.] Yen, following his recent creation of
                            maintenance regime, has been hounded by Generalissimo to point forcing
                            him retire to hospital confinement; and Chinese source who claims
                            regular contact with Communists says Communists themselves disapproved
                            of his relief body as method for formation peace regime. Other leading
                            organizers (Yang Hu, Hu Chow-wen and Hsu Kuo-mou) said in imminent
                            danger arrest.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Generalissimo’s reported intention to force municipal police to leave
                            city with withdrawing troops, if carried out, could materially increase
                            looting and lawless excesses, though known control of part police force
                            by anti-Generalissimo groups and probably refusal of many police to
                            leave posts (especially if adequately paid and fed) would undoubtedly
                            nullify his efforts to some extent. Military has savagely threatened any
                            police who defect.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Events seem heading rapidly toward moment when commencement of
                            attempted Nationalist evacuation of city will set stage for
                            Generalissimo’s reported demolition program; final looting by armed and
                            unsated Nationalist soldiers ideally distributed for effective
                            plundering of entire city; further pillaging by local riffraff.
                            Communist underground and Yang Hu’s police and plain-clothes agents are
                            understood to be ready prevent some destruction but they can hardly hope
                            to stop general looting (unless Yang’s troops have been bought off to
                            much greater extent than Consul General aware) and their very efforts
                            will provoke fighting.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Any further aggravation of food, fuel, currency and labor aspects of
                            economic crisis is likely precipitate rioting with street fighting in
                            which Communist underground may feel compelled to participate.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0333" n="323" xml:id="pg_323"/>
                <p>While these conjectures represent well-informed consensus, events may prove them
                    unduly pessimistic. Possibility of reports being spread for ulterior motives
                    should be always kept in mind. We have fortunately no concrete evidence support
                    observers’ general expectation Generalissimo’s plans demolish utilities and
                    demolitions thus far have all been outside city proper. Also source close to
                    Yang Hu tells us this morning change-over will come soon without serious
                    disorders—though unknown capabilities of Yang’s organization suggest great
                    caution re this assurance. All in all there remains little visible basis for
                    optimism. Best hope is that events, perhaps spurred by massive defections, will
                    move with sufficient rapidity to prevent destructive fighting in city or
                    extensive demolitions. If Communists are welcome even by conservative business
                    interests not to mention populace, it will not be surprising.</p>
                <p>If any approach to Nationalist authorities to urge them abandon senseless
                    fighting and destruction is to be made, need for action is urgent. Delicacy and
                    probable inadvisability of attempting have Shanghai declared open city is
                    realized, but feel we could properly insist to Nationalist military authorities
                    there be no demolitions of essentially civilian installations—possibly taking
                    parallel action with British and French—in view fact utilities are virtually all
                    owned by interests of the three countries. I urge Department authorize
                    representations this sense.</p>
                <p>Sent Nanking 919, repeated Department, OffEmb Canton 461.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cabot</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
