<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Shanghai (
                        Cabot
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d494</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">494</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-07-12T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-07-12T03:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="democracy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647" lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-07-12T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-12T03:00:00-05:00" n="494" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d494">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00B/7–1249: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-07-12T16:00:00+08:00">July 12, 1949—4 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received July 12—10:29 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2717. Persistency and extent Communists’ efforts to woo Mme. Sun Yat-sen reveals
                    importance they attach to winning her active identification <pb facs="0435" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/> with their cause—not only as widow of Dr. Sun
                    (thereby providing symbolic reaffirmation to public of Sun’s “approval” of
                    Communist principles and pro-Soviet orientation) but also as widely popular
                    liberal-humanitarian in her own right, and finally as a Soong sister<note n="96" xml:id="d494fn96">The three Soong sisters were Mesdames H. H. Kung, Sun
                        Yat-sen, and Chiang Kai-shek; their most prominent brother was T. V.
                        Soong.</note> whose very fact of blood connection with Kmt’s four
                        families<note n="97" xml:id="d494fn97">Chiang, Soong, Kung, and Chen.</note>
                    invests her support with enhanced value and with opportunity for impressive
                    display of truth Communists’ contention that their cause commands a loyalty
                    transcending personal and family ties.</p>
                <p>May be recalled that Li Tsung-jen in connection attempts strengthen his peace
                    bargaining position tried vainly win some approving gesture from Mine. Sun.
                    Later as Communist occupation Shanghai drew closer she was reported pressed by
                    various apprehensive quarters for her patronage as protective leftist cover for
                    their enterprises. [Possibility?] of Generalissimo’s including her in group of
                    prominent pro-Communist suspects whom he pressured into removing to Hong Kong
                    from Shanghai before Communist occupation was also rumored. She steadfastly
                    resisted these various pressures and was reliably reported to be determined
                    avoid political involvements and devote herself solely to her humanitarian work
                    Shanghai.</p>
                <p>Immediately following Communist occupation Shanghai, Chen Yi<note n="98" xml:id="d494fn98">Communist mayor of Shanghai.</note> honored Mme. Sun by
                    what understood to be his first official call. This was followed by three
                    telegrams June 6 despatched to her by All-China Women’s Federation leaders,
                    including Mesdames Chou En-lai and Feng Yu-hsiang,<note n="99" xml:id="d494fn99">Madame Feng was the widow of the “Christian General”, Marshal Feng
                        Yu-hsiang.</note> KmtRC Chairman Li Chi-shen<note n="1" xml:id="d494fn1">Leader of the Kuomintang Revolutionary Committee (KmtRC).</note> and
                    Democratic League leaders respectively felicitating her on liberation Shanghai
                    and approaching realization of common “freedom and democracy” goals and
                    indicating high esteem for her and implied hope for renewal personal association
                    with her at Peiping. Mme. Sun’s reply was reportedly to effect that she
                    appreciated felicitations but unable visit North China for present as
                    recuperating from illness in Shanghai.</p>
                <p>On June 25 Teng Ying-chao (Mme. Chou En-lai) arrived Shanghai for visit which was
                    publicly explained as for purpose medical attention but which two reliable
                    sources state was to persuade Mme. Sun proceed Peiping to join pre-PPC meetings.
                    First reports indicated Mme. Sun adamantly sick [<hi rend="italic">opposed?</hi>] to these overtures. Pressure continued, however. On July 1 she
                    attended Communist Party anniversary gathering where she was accorded special
                    honor and contributed a speech hailing Communist Party leadership which in view
                    her “indisposition” was read for her by Mme. Chou. Same procedure repeated <pb facs="0436" n="426" xml:id="pg_426"/> at July 7 Lukouchiao anniversary<note n="2" xml:id="d494fn2">Beginning of undeclared war between Japan and China,
                        1937.</note> gathering where the speech read for her by Mme. Chou warned
                    foreign imperialists to “get out of China”. (See Contel 2713<note n="3" xml:id="d494fn3">July 12, not printed.</note> for texts.)</p>
                <p>Close American friend of Mme. Sun says he suspects that second speech was
                    prepared not by her but by others. He believes that while Communists would never
                    venture to employ rough methods force her comply with their wishes they are
                    applying such steady “friendly” pressure that she is gradually weakening in
                    determination to avoid political involvements and may quite likely go north
                    before long.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 2717; repeated Nanking 1526, Canton operational; Department pass
                    Peiping 202.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cabot</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
