<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-18T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-18T07:00:00-05:00" n="683" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d683">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01/11–1849: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Strong</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-18T19:00:00+07:00">November
                                    18, 1949—7 p. m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received November 19—12:55 a. m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Cantel 1293. It becomes apparent that move of Generalissimo-selected
                            Chinese Government personnel to Taiwan is about to begin and <pb facs="0612" n="602" xml:id="pg_602"/> it is expected that, if
                            Chungking becomes insecure before movement of personnel completed,
                            Chengtu will be used as staging point, despite its greater distance from
                            Taipei, in view fact it can be held longer.</p>
                        <p>Recent refusal of Szechwan “leaders” return Chungking from Chengtu to see
                            Generalissimo would indicate their belief in futility of attempting
                            improve matters now. It may be expected that they will endeavor play
                            ball with Communists in every way.</p>
                        <p>An increasingly independent attitude on part of the various military
                            leaders will doubtless show itself before long, each seeking in best way
                            preserve forces and position. Friction between population and troops in
                            western Szechwan will heighten and before end there may even be clashes
                            between different groups of Nationalist forces.</p>
                        <p>We now believe President Li Tsung-jen will not attempt attract enough men
                            of caliber to form government in Nanning. It seems more likely that,
                            although for face purposes he may return briefly to Chungking, he will
                            regard it as useless to attempt create rump government. Unless he could
                            get numbers of capable men to join him and be sure of outside financial
                            help, he would merely be increasing overhead expenses without achieving
                            object. Provincial Government of Kwangsi is quite adequate for purely
                            local purposes of Li and Pai Chung-hsi.</p>
                        <p>Headlines in leading paper today supporting current rumors that
                            Generalissimo may soon resume presidency seem entitled credence as
                            logical move in view virtual abdication by Li, who is being criticized
                            even by friends for neither returning nor resigning. A brief absence
                            might have increased strength of his position but failure join issue in
                            crisis has decreased his stature.</p>
                        <p>SWMPA now controls all travel and cargo out of Chungking. Tickets sold
                            only by China Travel Service, which must have prior clearance each
                            case.</p>
                        <p>Sent Department; repeated Taipei 225, Hong Kong 70, Shanghai 574.
                            Department pass Taipei, Hong Kong, Shanghai.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Strong</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>