<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="767" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d767">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">124.93/1–2749</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chinese Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Koo</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The Chinese Ambassador presents his compliments to the Secretary of State
                        and, referring to the Ambassador’s memorandum of January 21, 1949, has the
                        honor to inform the Secretary that the Chinese Government has decided to
                        move the Capital from Nanking to Canton, and that effective from February 5,
                        1949, Canton will be the legal seat of the Chinese Government. Every effort
                        will be made by the Ministry of Foreign Affairs to assist the several
                        diplomatic missions in their change of residence. To that end all the
                        missions have been asked to send representatives to the Ministry of Foreign
                        Affairs at their earliest convenience for consultation in regard to such
                        removal and related matters. It is requested that the United States
                        Government will instruct its Ambassador to China to take up his residence in
                        Canton as soon as possible.</p>
                    <p>Pursuant to the determination of the Chinese Government to restore peace, the
                        Executive Yuan has decided to issue cease-fire orders to its troops and
                        designated representatives to undertake peace negotiations. However, after
                        the lapse of six days there is still no response from the Communist Party.
                        Instead, its armies are still exploiting every opportunity to advance. As a
                        measure of precaution the Government has of necessity to move the Capital to
                        the south, though it will continue to persevere in the effort to bring peace
                        to the nation.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-27">January 27,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>