<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Hong Kong (
                        Hopper
                    ) to the Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    )Copy transmitted to the Department
                        without covering despatch; received February 16.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v08</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-01-20T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="77" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00 Yunnan/1–2049</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Hong Kong</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hopper</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="20" xml:id="d77fn20">Copy transmitted to the Department
                        without covering despatch; received February 16.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 3</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hong Kong</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-20">January 20,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose a copy of a
                    memorandum prepared by Vice Consul R. M. Service,<note n="19" xml:id="d77fn19">Not printed.</note> describing an interview on January 19, 1949 with
                    General Lung Yun, former governor of Yunnan. It will be recalled that General
                    Lung arrived at Hong Kong on December 10, 1948 (reference this office’s telegram
                    no. 212, December 11, 3 p. m. to the Embassy, repeated to Canton), after
                    escaping from Nanking by air.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary of Enclosure</hi>. Lung Yun said that he was convinced
                    that the Generalissimo will not quit, although he has lost the respect and
                    support of the people. Lung was encouraged by Washington’s coolness toward the
                    Nanking Government, and hoped that the United States will adhere to a “hand’s
                    off” policy until the present historical crisis is over, when China will welcome
                    American friendship. He was interested in the American attitude toward Formosa,
                    advocating self-rule on the island, and American cooperation to keep Chiang from
                    making of it a final bastion of Kmt survival. He described Li Chi-shen’s
                    activity in north China as of the utmost significance to China’s welfare, and
                    predicted imminent convocation of the PCC. Lung said it was too late for south
                    and west China leaders to form an alliance against Communism, as the
                    Generalissimo had sacrificed too many troops and brought the CCP armies to the
                    north bank of the Yangtze, and the Chinese people are war-weary. He said that Fu
                    Tso-yi and Yen Hsi-shan<note n="21" xml:id="d77fn21">Marshal Yen was Governor of
                        Shansi and Taiyuan Pacification Commissioner.</note> are entitled to make
                    separate peace arrangements with the CCP, as Chiang did not give them promised
                    support. Lung Yun said that he had come to Hong Kong for physical and spiritual
                    relaxation, and that he had not yet formulated plans for the future. He avoided
                    discussion of Yunnan and KmtRC<note n="22" xml:id="d77fn22">Kuomintang
                        Revolutionary Committee with headquarters at Hong Kong.</note> affairs. <hi rend="italic">End of Summary of Enclosure</hi>.</p>
                <pb facs="0075" n="65" xml:id="pg_65"/>
                <p>A source of uncertain reliability, describing a recent interview with Lung’s
                    secretary, said that differences between Lung and Lu Han, present governor of
                    Yunnan, have not yet been resolved. This source said that Lung’s half-brother
                    will be obliged to come to a settlement with Lung, but that representatives of
                    the two have not yet concluded their negotiations. Other sources have also said
                    that delicate problems remain to be settled between the two Lo-los, but all are
                    confident that Lung Yun will return to Yunnan when Central Government
                    disintegration permits.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi> D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hopper</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
