<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to President Wilson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d419</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">419</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="419"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d419">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">841.857 Ar 1/91½a</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to President
                            <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-08-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">26 August, 1915</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: Count Bernstorff at my request
                    called upon me this morning. I informed him that I wished to see him about the
                    proposed wireless code message which he desired us to send for him to his
                        Government.<note n="44" xml:id="d419fn1">
                        <ref target="frus1917Supp01v01#pg_525">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1915, supp., p.
                        525</ref>.</note> I pointed out to him the objectionable feature of making
                    any reference to the <hi rend="italic">Arabic</hi> in connection with
                    negotiations; that the <hi rend="italic">Arabic</hi> could not be considered in
                    the same way as the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> in view of what had passed
                    between the Governments since the latter vessel was sunk; that he must
                    appreciate, that the torpedoing of the <hi rend="italic">Arabic</hi> might
                    interrupt further negotiations, since a condition of their continuance was the
                    cessation of destroying <pb facs="0540" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/> passenger
                    vessels without warning and opportunity to reach a place of safety.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador replied that he realized the situation had changed and that he
                    would take the proposed wireless message and rewrite it. As soon as he sends it
                    to me in revised form I will send it to you.</p>
                <p>I then asked the Ambassador what the statement of his Government, which he had
                    telegraphed to me and had made public,<note n="45" xml:id="d419fn2">
                        <ref target="frus1915Supp#pg_524">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1915, supp., p.
                        524</ref>.</note> meant in regard to instructions to submarine officers,
                    that I would like to know what those instructions are.</p>
                <p>He replied that he had not been told but supposed they referred to warnings and
                    opportunities to leave ships attacked.</p>
                <p>I asked him, if such instructions had been given, how there could be any doubt
                    about their violation in the case of the <hi rend="italic">Arabic?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>He said that the facts seemed uncertain and he hoped to have an explanation from
                    his Government.</p>
                <p>To this I answered that we had received evidence from Americans on board the <hi
                        rend="italic">Arabic</hi> showing the vessel was torpedoed and that a German
                    submarine had shelled the <hi rend="italic">Dunsley</hi> and was seen by the
                    survivors of that vessel after the <hi rend="italic">Arabic</hi> foundered, and
                    that there was practically no doubt at all but that the vessel was intentionally
                    attacked without warning. I said to him that to advance any excuse of mistake by
                    the submarine commander would be absurd and would irritate rather than relieve
                    the situation.</p>
                <p>He asked me if we were willing to await a report of the affair from Berlin,
                    because he felt sure there was some explanation.</p>
                <p>I replied that I could not see how any explanation could be given which would be
                    satisfactory and that our experience in awaiting reports of submarine attacks
                    was not encouraging. I then pointed out the case of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Orduna</hi>, in which we had waited for a report for a month without reply.
                    The Ambassador seemed greatly surprised and said that he could not understand
                    it.</p>
                <p>I said that any considerable delay could not be thought of, that, while the
                    public feeling here was less demonstrative than it had been after the sinking of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi>, I believed it to be far more intense.</p>
                <p>He said that he realized this, but hoped that some time would be given so that
                    his Government might have opportunity to make reparation if its officer was at
                    fault.</p>
                <p>This was the substance of our conversation.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador seemed to be worried over the situation and was, for him, in a
                    very serious mood. He is, however, optimistic that the affair can be amicably
                    arranged. I did not indicate to him that I shared his optimism but rather tried
                    to give him the impression that I considered the situation most critical and
                    that Germany would <pb facs="0541" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> have to act quickly
                    to avoid the consequences of the torpedoing of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Arabic</hi>, even if it were possible to do so.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
