<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to President Wilson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d442</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">442</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-11-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-11-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="442"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d442">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72/2269a</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to President
                            <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-11-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 2, 1915</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I had a talk this morning with
                    Ambassador Bernstorff in regard to the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> matter.
                    He is evidently far less hopeful of a settlement satisfactory to this Government
                    of that case than of the <hi rend="italic">Arabic</hi> case. I think I can
                    understand this attitude in view of the telegrams which we have received from
                    Berlin, and which you have undoubtedly seen, as to the disapproval of his
                    Government of his action in admitting as much as he did. I believe he has been
                    told by his Government that his conduct of that matter was not satisfactory. For
                    that reason I did not feel that I could insist as strongly as I otherwise could
                    that the German Government should admit the wrong and pay indemnity without the
                    intervention of arbitration.</p>
                <p>At the time that the Ambassador delivered to me the note which settled the <hi
                        rend="italic">Arabic</hi> question he also handed me for consideration a
                    draft of a note in regard to the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi>.<note n="67"
                        xml:id="d442fn1">See <ref target="#pg_484">p. 484</ref>.</note> He again
                    produced this draft and said that he felt sure that was as far as his Government
                    could go in the matter. I told him that I would consider the draft further but
                    that in its present form it would be unacceptable to this Government. I will, in
                    a day or two, send you the draft with notes and suggestions as to what, it seems
                    to me, would be satisfactory. The Ambassador said that any suggestions I might
                    have he would have to refer to Berlin as he did not feel he was authorized to
                    accept them without instructions.</p>
                <p>I pointed out to him (the Ambassador) that in view of the fact that they had
                    under their naval instructions ceased to attack passenger vessels I could see no
                    practical reason why they should insist that the attack on the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lusitania</hi> was justifiable; that there might be a sentimental reason
                    for this insistence in view of the natural dislike which a Government had to
                    admit a wrongful act and that I realized the public opinion in Germany might
                    criticise such an admission. I told him further that I was willing to go as far
                    as possible to relieve that situation but that we also had to deal with public
                    opinion <pb facs="0557" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/> in this country and that in
                    the case of the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> it was not a sentimental matter
                    at all but a practical matter and that I thought his Government should admit
                    liability for the loss of life. He said that he was convinced his Government
                    would not make such an admission and that some other method would have to be
                    found to determine liability. I also said to him that I thought the matter
                    should be settled because we had already been extremely patient in the matter.
                    He replied that if we insisted upon an admission of liability he did not believe
                    it could be settled. I said that I regretted very much to have him say that as I
                    felt that the question must be settled and very soon.</p>
                <p>He left me with the understanding that I would go over the draft and communicate
                    with him in a few days.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
