<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to President Wilson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d451</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">451</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-11-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSGyPwUYTaLPhEi" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038182"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Consular service</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-11-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="451"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d451">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72/2322½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to President
                            <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-11-24">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 24, 1915</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: Thank you for letting me see
                    the two letters from Colonel House, which I herewith return.</p>
                <p>I tried to impress upon Bernstorff when I saw him the necessity of a speedy
                    settlement of the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> case. I have heard nothing
                    from him since that conversation and shall write him today urging him to act in
                    the matter. Something must be done before Congress assembles or else I am afraid
                    we will have some embarrassing requests for the correspondence.</p>
                <p>I think the time is very opportune for us to press compliance with our demands,
                    with the success for the Teutonic arms in the Balkans and the wavering
                    neutrality of Roumania and Greece the German Government could ill afford to have
                    any sort of a break with this Government on account of the moral effect it would
                    have.</p>
                <p>In regard to the discussion relative to peace, I think that there is a
                    possibility that it might work out along the lines suggested but there are so
                    many problems connected with it—such as boundaries, colonial possessions and
                    indemnities, that I hardly like to express an opinion until it takes more
                    definite form.</p>
                <p>In regard to the two questions which Colonel House asks in his second letter<note
                        n="73" xml:id="d451fn1">See Charles Seymour, <hi rend="italic">The Intimate
                            Papers of Colonel House</hi>, vol. II, p. 47.</note> relative to the
                    removal of certain persons connected with the Embassies and Consular Service of
                    Germany and Austria-Hungary, I feel that the time is very near when some such
                    step should be taken. As you know, we have been collecting and marshalling, as
                    far as possible, the evidence which we have against the various individuals.
                    While the proofs are not conclusive I think there is sufficient for action but I
                    would prefer to submit to you the memorandum on the subject before any decision
                    is reached.</p>
                <p>In regard to severing diplomatic relations with Austria on account of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ancona</hi>, you know how incomplete our information is. I
                    hope that we may shortly have something definite from Vienna and from Rome
                    also.</p>
                <p>I am attending the Army-Navy football game in New York on Saturday and will
                    remain over Sunday. Colonel House has been <pb facs="0564" n="496"
                        xml:id="pg_496"/> good enough to invite Mrs. Lansing and myself to luncheon
                    Sunday, so I will have an opportunity to discuss these questions with him at
                    length.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>[File copy not signed]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
