<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Germany ( (Gerard))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d492</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">492</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1916-01-26T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1916-01-26T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-01-26T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-01-26T17:00:00-05:00" n="492"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d492">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72/13402b: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gerard</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-01-26T17:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 26, 1916—5 p. m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2645. For the Ambassador and Colonel House:</p>
                <p>On the 22d the German Ambassador submitted two tentative drafts of a memorandum
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> case by which the German Government
                    repeated its regret that Americans were killed by the justifiable retaliatory
                    act of its submarine commander and offered, out of regard for the friendship of
                    the two countries, to pay an indemnity.</p>
                <pb facs="0594" n="526" xml:id="pg_526"/>
                <p>On the 25th I had an interview with Count von Bernstorff and told him that both
                    drafts were unsatisfactory; that the act of the submarine commander, being
                    retaliatory, was admittedly illegal and though it might be justified against an
                    enemy it could not be justified against neutrals. I told him that this
                    Government would be satisfied with nothing less than an admission of the
                    wrongful conduct of the submarine commander and an admission of liability for
                    the lives of American citizens lost by his act. He replied that he was sure his
                    Government could not go as far as that as they had denied liability. He asked me
                    what would be our course in case Germany could not meet our demands. I replied
                    that I saw no other course except to break off diplomatic relations, to which he
                    answered that he thought it would go further than that in case we followed that
                    course. I told him that was probably correct but that I had discussed the matter
                    fully with the President and that we would not hesitate to assume responsibility
                    for the consequences. He stated that he would think the matter over and see me
                    again today.</p>
                <p>At noon today the German Ambassador called and after discussing the matter he
                    submitted the following memorandum which he is sending to his Government for
                    their approval.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The German submarine war against England’s commerce at sea, as announced on
                        February 4, 1915, is conducted in retaliation of England’s inhuman war
                        against Germany’s commercial and industrial life. It is generally recognized
                        as justifiable that retaliation may be employed against acts committed in
                        contravention of the law of nations. Germany is enacting such retaliation
                        because it is England’s endeavor to cut off all imports from Germany by
                        preventing even legal commerce of neutrals with her and thereby subjecting
                        the German population to starvation. In answer to these acts Germany is
                        making efforts to destroy England’s commerce at sea, at least as far as it
                        is carried on by enemy vessels. If Germany has notwithstanding limited her
                        submarine warfare this was done in view of her longstanding friendship with
                        the United States and in view of the fact that the sinking of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> caused the death of citizens of the United
                        States. Thereby the German retaliation affected neutrals, which was not the
                        intention as retaliation becomes an illegal act if applied to other than
                        enemy subjects.</p>
                    <p>The Imperial Government, having, subsequent to the event, issued to its naval
                        officers the new instructions which are now prevailing, expresses profound
                        regret that citizens of the United States suffered by the sinking of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> and, recognizing the illegality of causing
                        their death, and admitting liability therefor, offers to make reparation for
                        the lives of the citizens of the United States who were lost by the payment
                        of a suitable indemnity.</p>
                    <p>In the note of the American Government, July 21,<note n="6" xml:id="d492fn1">
                            <ref target="frus1915Supp#pg_480">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1915, supp., p.
                            480</ref>.</note> concerning the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi>
                        incident, the Government of the United States invited the practical
                        cooperation of the Imperial German Government in contending <pb facs="0595"
                            n="527" xml:id="pg_527"/> for the principle of the freedom of the seas,
                        and added that this great object could, in some way be accomplished before
                        the present war ends. The Imperial Government will at all times gladly
                        cooperate with the Government of the United States for the purpose of
                        accomplishing this common great object.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>If the German Government can agree to the above memorandum I believe that the <hi
                        rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> case will be satisfactorily ended. The
                    memorandum was read to the President and received his approval.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lansing</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
