<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Colonel E. M. House to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d590</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">590</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="590"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d590">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72/3579½</note>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel E. M. House</hi>
                    </persName>
                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: Thank you for your letter of
                    yesterday with its enclosure.</p>
                <p>In regard to the Egan despatch, I think we ought to do everything possible to
                    discredit Zimmermann whose influence seems to be wholly anti American. Suppose
                    we let the matter rest until you come on Saturday when we can talk it over.
                    There are some things I can tell you about the matter that perhaps have not
                    reached you.</p>
                <p>I wrote the President very strongly yesterday along the lines you suggested
                    through Frank Polk. I find that many thoughtful people believe that the
                    President would do better not to call Congress before the sixteenth if he would
                    proceed as rapidly as possible towards preparing the country for war.</p>
                <p>There is so much to be done and so little time in which to do it that it might be
                    prudent not to declare war until we have more nearly gotten ready. Haste in this
                    direction is what I believe is most to be desired. If the President would
                    outline such a policy to you and to <pb facs="0698" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/>
                    the Army and Navy Departments and let it be known what was being done, it would
                    satisfy public opinion and be more effective than if actual war was declared
                    before having taken the necessary precautions.</p>
                <p>I hope nothing will prevent your coming on Saturday for we not only have invited
                    some twenty odd people to meet Mrs. Lansing and you, but I am anxious to have a
                    talk which we can do better here than in Washington.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <dateline rend="flushleft">
                    <placeName>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-03-20">
                        <hi rend="italic">March 20, 1917</hi>.</date>
                    <lb/> [Received March 21.]</dateline>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. M. House</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
