<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>President Wilson to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d595</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">595</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-03-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-03-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-03-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-03-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="595"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d595">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">701.6311/271</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">President <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-03-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">27 March, 1917</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: This is certainly a most
                    delicate and embarrassing situation, but I see only one thing we can do. There
                    is no choice in the circumstances but to say to Count Tarnowski that the
                    explicit acceptance and avowal by his Government of the policy which led to our
                    breach of diplomatic relations with Germany (before the policy had been put into
                    operation) makes it impossible, to our sincere regret, that I should receive
                    him.</p>
                <p>This announcement to him (I think it should not until absolutely necessary be
                    made public) can of course be made in the most friendly <pb facs="0702" n="634"
                        xml:id="pg_634"/> spirit; and he can be told that we will relieve the
                    embarrassment at Vienna by recalling Mr. Penfield so soon as he (Tarnowski) has
                    heard from his Government and received its instructions.</p>
                <p>All of this, I take it for granted, will be at once communicated to Mr. Penfield
                    and he will be told to hold himself in readiness to receive instructions as to
                    himself, pending Vienna’s reply to Tarnowski.</p>
                <p>In any case Penfield should express again to Count Czernin our deep regret that
                    the Austro-Hungarian Government should have felt itself obliged to join Germany
                    in its sub-marine policy and so interrupt relations which we had hoped might
                    remain friendly in form as well as in fact. In short, he ought to make it plain
                    to Count Czernin that we are acting without feeling in this matter, and merely
                    on principle.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>W. W.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
