<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-11-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-11-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="605" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d605">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72/2252½</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Austria-Hungary</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Penfield</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-11-11">
                                        <hi rend="italic">November 11, 1915</hi>.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received November 29.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: In both Austria and
                                Hungary the Third War Loan closed a few days since, and it was
                                successful to a remarkable degree. The aggregate figures as
                                semi-officially announced are 5,500,000,000 crowns, which sum in
                                ordinary times would be more than a billion dollars. The first loan,
                                made when the Russians occupied the most of Galicia and were well
                                through the Carpathians, was not very successful. The second loan,
                                occurring a few weeks after Italy entered the fray, was but
                                moderately successful. But this new loan, to run fifteen years and
                                netting the holder about six and one-quarter per cent, has been a
                                veritable triumph in financing.</p>
                            <p>Great corporations and firms and municipalities subscribed liberally.
                                The Archduke Friedrich appears on the subscribers’ list for
                                12,000,000 crowns, and his brother Archduke Eugen is down for
                                2,000,000 crowns. The Wiener Bank Verein claims to have placed a
                                tenth of the loan with its clients.</p>
                            <p>If one could know the inside facts it might be discovered that the
                                loan’s success is more apparent than real, especially when
                                intelligent Austrians assure one that perhaps half the gross amount
                                has been <pb facs="0711" n="643" xml:id="pg_643"/> arrived at by
                                hypothecating every form of obligation having pecuniary value,
                                including government pensions, public bonds of lower interest, and
                                even certificates of the first and second war loans netting lesser
                                revenue. It is well known that a goodly part of the loan was
                                subscribed on what Americans would recognize as the “margin” plan.
                                But, with all these deductions, the third loan is an unqualified
                                success.</p>
                            <p>Probably two-thirds of the gross sum realized has already been spent,
                                as it must have been by a Government whose direct war cost is stated
                                to be $7,000,000 a day, and whose cash-box was practically empty
                                when the war began.</p>
                            <p>From this time forward the war must be a test of resources quite as
                                much as a trial of military strength, I feel. There are several raw
                                materials of which Austria-Hungary is absolutely destitute, and were
                                it not for Holland, Sweden and Denmark there would be little
                                possibility of getting another pound of such vital requisites as
                                cotton, copper or rubber. Bohemian cotton mills, those not already
                                closed, have for months been running on half time, and were it not
                                for the accommodating neutral neighbors of Germany and Austria all
                                the factories would have closed many months ago. I hear of an
                                enterprising speculator who last week succeeded in getting twenty
                                carloads of crude rubber through from Holland and cleaned up a small
                                fortune therefrom.</p>
                            <p>The Austrian Government has issued an appeal to the public to take
                                all gold and silver jewelry, plate and other articles made of these
                                metals to the mints for conversion into coin or bars. The necessity
                                of strengthening the gold reserve and meeting payments abroad for
                                goods for military purposes is given as the reason for the appeal.
                                Persons who surrender gold or silver will receive full payment in
                                bank notes as well as certificates of honor, it is stated.</p>
                            <p>By way of showing existing conditions at Fiume I extract these
                                pertinent sentences from a letter of Consul Chase to me under date
                                of the 5th instant:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Croatian authorities have placed an embargo on foodstuffs of
                                    every kind being taken out of that province. This affects Fiume
                                    very seriously, as much of the vegetable and garden truck used
                                    was brought from near-by Croatian places. It makes more serious
                                    the question of food supplies for Fiume. One paper advocates
                                    seriously the use of wooden shoes, especially for children,
                                    owing to the shortage of leather. In Fiume the question of the
                                    war seems to be partly forgotten and to have given way to the
                                    one great question of food. It seems the sole live topic of
                                    constant street discussion. This is the result of conditions,
                                    not theories. The city has been unable to procure over one-fifth
                                    of the grain promised long ago by the Government. At a meeting
                                    of the City Council the director of the gas plant reported that
                                    he would soon have to suspend unless arrangements were promptly
                                    made for more coal and other prime necessities. Gas is <pb facs="0712" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/> much used for heating,
                                    cooking and lighting. The director of the civic hospital at the
                                    same meeting demanded that an increase in the sum for the daily
                                    feeding and care of the inmates be provided or the hospital
                                    would have to be closed. Another member of the Council urged the
                                    importance of procuring potatoes before the price became too
                                    high.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>This picture of conditions in a city at the beginning of winter
                                forebodes great misery through scarcity of staples of existence
                                before the cold season is half over. And what Consul Chase writes of
                                Fiume must be true of Trieste and probably of every city and town in
                                the Monarchy.</p>
                            <p>To one possessing adequate means the matter of existing in Vienna has
                                thus far presented no very serious problem. But one has to exist in
                                keeping with the possibilities of this war time, and not as he might
                                prefer to live. There are scores of essential articles that cannot
                                be had at any price, and nearly every obtainable article of food has
                                doubled or even quadrupled in cost. Meats cost generally a dollar a
                                pound, while pork and ham is even more expensive. And on two days in
                                each week it is forbidden to purchase meat. Fish is practically
                                unobtainable. The price of butter and eggs is practically
                                prohibitive. Milk has decreased in purity and doubled in cost. Coal
                                and coke have correspondingly advanced in cost.</p>
                            <p>As I have said, these conditions may be met by persons of means, but
                                the masses can be in no position to purchase articles of food having
                                these inflated values. Great self-denial has to be practiced on all
                                sides by the millions, and the wonder is that poor people can find
                                ways of existing. Yet the proletariat seems to do so, and without
                                complaining. How much longer the people can go on living under these
                                conditions I know not.</p>
                            <p>In this connection I think I may be permitted to tell a little of how
                                my wife and I manage to live in this capital rent by conditions of
                                war. More than a year since, perceiving that the conflict was to be
                                a long and bitter one, we decided to guard against possibilities by
                                having our own milk, butter, fowls and eggs. Being Catholics, we
                                had, before hostilities began, been generous to an order of Sisters
                                having a convent ten or fifteen miles out of Vienna. When it was
                                seen that the war was to be a terrible one, these good souls were
                                glad to lend us the small farm connected with their institution.
                                There we installed a Tyrolean cow and a hundred hens, and the
                                Embassy has had the products of these to a bountiful extent.
                                Recently we have added forty live turkeys to our holdings—and famine
                                can gain no foothold in our modest home. An attendant goes daily
                                back and forth, and Vienna society has enjoyed many a laugh over the
                                Ambassador’s neutral cow and hens. Just now I am getting a thousand
                                litres of gasoline from Roumania by favor of the Roumanian <pb facs="0713" n="645" xml:id="pg_645"/> Minister in Vienna. There
                                are practically no private motors in commission in the capital, and
                                none in the diplomatic service save those of our Embassy. Our wheat
                                flour comes from Bucharest by the slowest imaginable train, through
                                the personal influence of our colleagues in that capital.</p>
                            <p>Naturally members of this Embassy, as well as of the Embassy in
                                Berlin, are living in a beleaguered land shut off by sea power and
                                blockade from a good part of the world. There are many necessary
                                things, perhaps not essential to actually keeping alive, that we
                                want and should have. Certain articles not too bulky we used to get
                                through from London, but that medium seems harshly to have been cut
                                off. If the war runs a few months longer the Department, it seems to
                                me, must consider plans for getting certain supplies if not succor
                                to its diplomatic and consular servants loyally performing a
                                burdensome duty in the Central Empires without complaining.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Frederic C. Penfield</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>