<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Germany ( (Gerard) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914-20v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d652</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">652</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1916-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1916-08-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-08-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="652"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d652">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72/2928½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gerard</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-08-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 30, 1916</hi>.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received September 11.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: The entry of Roumania took
                    every one by surprise. Beldiman the Roumanian Minister here was visiting the
                    reigning Prince of Hohenzollern Sigmaringen, brother of the Roumanian King, and
                    apparently knew nothing of even the danger of a break.</p>
                <p>Today Hindenburg is named Chief of the General Staff, and his chief of Staff,
                    Ludendorff, is made Quartermaster General. Falken-hayn, former Chief of Staff is
                    bounced without even excuse of a diplomatic illness. This is all a great
                    concession to popular opinion. I do not know where Hindenburg stands with
                    reference to America, but have heard that he is a reasonable man. Of course here
                    the Army has as much to say in Foreign affairs as the Foreign Office, if not
                    more. When I was at the Great General Headquarters, Falk-enhayn, although I know
                    him did not call on me, and dodged me, even not appearing at Kaiser’s table when
                    I lunched there. From all this I judge he was against America on the submarine
                    question. I have also heard that at this time when Helfferich was talking before
                    the Kaiser, in favor of peace with America, that Falkenhayn interrupted him, but
                    was told by the Kaiser to “stick to his last” or words to that effect.</p>
                <pb facs="0764" n="696" xml:id="pg_696"/>
                <p>These people here are now nervous and unstrung and actually believe that America
                    will now enter the war against them. You cannot conceive of the general
                    breakdown of nerves among this people.</p>
                <p>I have heard lately of men as old as 47 being taken for the Army.</p>
                <p>In the Foreign Office waiting room the other day I was talking to Count Moltke,
                    the Danish Minister, who is violently pro-German. I noticed that he had with him
                    a sort of report about the action of the Danish Parliament concerning the sale
                    of the islands to America, which he was evidently waiting to give to
                    Zimmermann.</p>
                <p>Zimmermann has now gone on a vacation, his place being temporarily taken by von
                    Treutler, Prussian Minister to Bavaria, who since the commencement of the war
                    has been with the Kaiser. I judge this means the Kaiser is looking personally
                    into matters at the Foreign Office. Von Treutler is, I think, against the
                    resumption of reckless submarine war, he is lunching with me today. . . .</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Yours ever</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. W. G[<hi rend="smallcaps">erard</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
