<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Stevens to
                                    Mr. Blaine..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1894app2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d125</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">125</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1890-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1890-02-07T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664" lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193" lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1890-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1890-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="125" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d125">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Stevens</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Confidential.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 17.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                            States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Honolulu</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-02-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 7,
                                        1890</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I improve the earliest opportunity to
                                inform the Department of State as to the result of the election in
                                the Hawaiian Islands, which took place this week, February 5. It was
                                for the choice of the 48 nobles and representatives which compose
                                the national legislature that is largely to control the country the
                                next two years. It has been looked forward to with the deepest
                                interest by all the native and foreign residents, and the discussion
                                and agitation have been very heated and determined, and on the part
                                of the opponents of the present ministry extremely bitter and
                                unscrupulous. The result is a triumph of the opponents of the
                                present ministry and of the reform constitution. The election was
                                conducted with exceeding fairness by the legal authorities, and the
                                polls were kept open from 8 in the morning until 5 in the afternoon.
                                    <pb facs="0308" n="302" xml:id="pg_302"/> The most complete
                                quiet and good order prevailed in all the voting precincts of
                                Honolulu. An election conducted in the most intelligent and moral of
                                American rural towns could be no more orderly.</p>
                <p>The ministry had taken the most careful precautions for the
                                maintenance of order; the liquor saloons were closed, the ballot was
                                secret, and both parties worked with the utmost determination and
                                precision to get their supporters to the polls. This defeat of the
                                existing Government is deeply to be regretted, for it has been
                                accomplished by a most reckless appeal to race prejudices and to all
                                the elements of corruption and disorder in the Kingdom. It is well
                                known to the Department of State that in July, 1887, the best
                                citizens of these islands, composed of most of the property holders,
                                the men of business, and the professions, chiefly Americans,
                                English, and Germans—largely of the first named—were driven to a
                                revolution, accomplished without bloodshed, resulting in the
                                overthrow of the corrupt Gibson rule and the adoption of the reform
                                constitution, by which the chief power was taken from the King and
                                given to the Legislature and a responsible ministry. It has been
                                under this constitution that the country has been governed the past
                                two and a half years with signal success. Few of our American States
                                in that time have had their affairs more honestly conducted, their
                                laws more faithfully administered.</p>
                <p>Two of the ministers are of the best American stock, the sons of
                                missionaries, and another, the minister of foreign affairs, was born
                                and educated in the State of New York, though he has been many years
                                identified with this country. These three men have done their utmost
                                to govern the Kingdom wisely and honestly. To do this they have been
                                obliged to resist the King and all the worst elements of the
                                islands. Among these are the men who thrived on former
                                maladministration, whose plundering devices had been brought to an
                                end. I am sorry to say that some of the worst men in bringing about
                                the triumph of reaction are Americans, either by birth or adoption.
                                Yet so successful has been the new constitution and the reform
                                administration that the opposition party was obliged to pledge
                                itself in speech and platform not to return to the former state of
                                things, and to promise to carry on the Government according to the
                                terms of the present constitution, which has so deeply intrenched
                                itself in the existing state of things as not to be easily
                                overthrown. Among the successful party there are some large property
                                holders, who will be driven to restrain their political associates,
                                and these, with the determined efforts of the minority reform party,
                                will be likely to keep the country to constitutional rule in a
                                considerable degree.</p>
                <p>It is proper for me to say that among the leaders of the party just
                                successful at the polls are those not friendly to the United States,
                                and that the Department of State and this legation will have to deal
                                with the incoming ministry with great caution and circumspection.
                                The new legislature will meet in May, when a new ministry
                                undoubtedly will be chosen. In a future dispatch I will give the
                                result of my most careful observations as to the status of things
                                here relative to the interests of the United States and her
                                immediate duties and responsibilities as to these islands.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John L.
                                Stevens.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>N. B.—Above I have given the present estimate here of the
                                    election result. It is possible that full returns from the other
                                    islands may not sustain the present hopes of the
                                    reactionists.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
