<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-03-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="218" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d218">
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Stevens</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Gresham</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Confidential]</seg></opener>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 91.]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                            States Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Honolulu</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-03-07"><hi rend="italic">March 7,
                                        1893</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: By the American newspapers it appears,
                                and I have the information from other sources, that a Mr. E. C.
                                Macfarlane is in Washington, professing to be an ardent American,
                                sometimes claiming to be an annexationist, but avows himself hostile
                                to the Hawaiian Provisional Government and to the course of the
                                Hawaiian commissioners:</p>
                            <p>It is proper for me to inform the Department of State that this man
                                is one of the firm of George Macfarlane &amp; Co., referred to by my
                                predecessor here, Minister Merrill, in his dispatch 78, to Secretary
                                Bayard, of September 2, 1886, page 558 of printed volume of
                                diplomatic documents. Again, the minister refers to the same firm in
                                his dispatch 138, of August 2, 1887, page 832, printed volume, by
                                which it is seen that the firm was a party to defrauding the
                                Hawaiian Government of more than $100,000 in negotiating a loan with
                                a London house. For years this firm has been ultra English in its
                                political affiliations and mercantile plans.</p>
                            <p>A few months since this E. C. Macfarlane, by intrigues and
                                associations became one of the recent Queen’s ministers, minister of
                                finance. So unsatisfactory was he to all the best members of the
                                Legislature and to the business men of the Islands, that he remained
                                in the ministry but a few days, being voted out by the Legislature
                                though the English minister, openly and by personal effort, and his
                                wife more conspicuously in the legislative hall, worked to retain
                                him. After Macfarlane was voted out, the English minister used the
                                former as a go-between to the Queen to get her to appoint another
                                pro-English cabinet, but the effort failed. This E. C. Macfarlane is
                                referred to in my 70 and 71. This is the man who sought to get
                                access to President Cleveland, at Lakewood, according to the New
                                York and Washington papers, and is now posing as an American and is
                                said to be asking a <pb facs="0421" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/>
                                hearing at Washington. He and his brother were born here of Scotch
                                parentage, and E. C. lived several years in California. But American
                                interests here have no more unrelenting foe than this
                                liquor-importing house of G. W. Macfarlane &amp; Co.</p>
                            <p>E. C. Macfarlane is a fitting confederate in Washington, as he has
                                been in Honolulu, with Paul Neuman, the deposed Queen’s attorney,
                                whose character is described in my dispatch 81 of January 26.</p>
                            <p>I am, sir, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John L.
                                Stevens.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>