<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-04-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="254" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d254">
                                <head>No. 6.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blount</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Gresham</persName></hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 3.]</seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Honolulu, Hawaiian Islands</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-04-26"><hi rend="italic">April 26, 1893</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 7th instant the <hi rend="italic">Alameda</hi> reached this place. Among its
                                    passengers were Dr. William Shaw Bowen and Mr. Harold M. Sewall
                                    The San Francisco papers announced that they had refused <pb facs="0486" n="480" xml:id="pg_480"/> to say that they were
                                    not joint commissioners with myself to Honolulu, The former
                                    represented himself to me as a correspondent of the New York
                                    World, and said he would be glad to give me any information he
                                    could gather here. Thinking it a mere matter of courtesy, I
                                    thanked him. On Sunday, the 16th instant, I was out walking and
                                    met him on the street, riding in a buggy. He left his buggy in
                                    the hands of his friend, Mr. Sewall, and joined me in a walk of
                                    some length. Before it was concluded he said to me that he and
                                    Paul Neumann were arranging a meeting between President Dole and
                                    the Queen, the object being to pay her a sum of money in
                                    consideration of her formal abdication of the throne and lending
                                    her influence to the Provisional Government with a view to
                                    annexation to the United States. He repeated this statement
                                    frequently, at intervals, to which I made no response.</p>
                                <p>Finally he asked me if I did not think it would simplify the
                                    situation very much here and facilitate annexation. Suspecting
                                    that my answer was designed to be used to induce the Queen to
                                    yield to solicitations to abdicate: I replied “I have nothing to
                                    say on this subject.” Dr. Bowen said: “I did not ask you
                                    officially, but simply in a private way.” I responded: “I am
                                    here as a Commissioner of the United States and must decline to
                                    converse with you on this subject.”</p>
                                <p>The next morning early I had an interview with President Dole. I
                                    told him that I had seen in the San Francisco newspapers
                                    intimations that Dr. Bowen and Mr. Sew all were here as
                                    representatives of the President of the United States; that the
                                    former told me that he had arranged to bring him and the Queen
                                    together on that morning; that I desired to say to him that
                                    neither Dr. Bowen nor Mr. Sewall, nor any other person was
                                    authorized to act for the Government in that or any other matter
                                    relating to the present condition of affairs in the islands save
                                    myself; that I did not know absolutely that these two gentlemen
                                    had claimed to have such authority. He replied that he had been
                                    informed that they were here representing the Government. He did
                                    not give his authority.</p>
                                <p>He said that there had been some approaches from the Queen’s side
                                    with propositions of settlement; that he had responded: “I will
                                    consider any reasonable proposition.”</p>
                                <p>I told him I would not permit the Government of the United States
                                    to be represented as having any wish in the matter of any
                                    negotiations between the Queen and the Provisional Government.
                                    He asked if I would be willing to authorize the statement that I
                                    believed it would simplify the situation. It replied that I was
                                    not willing to do this, that I was not here to interfere with
                                    the opinions of any class of persons.</p>
                                <p>Since this interview with President Dole I have heard that Dr.
                                    Bowen, when asked by newspaper people if he represented the
                                    President of the United States, declined to answer, saying that
                                    all would be revealed hereafter.</p>
                                <p>He is representing himself in various quarters as an intimate
                                    friend of the President. I can but think that these statements
                                    are made to create the impression that he is here authorized to
                                    bring about negotiations for a settlement between the Queen and
                                    the Provisional Government.</p>
                                <p>On the day before yesterday Dr. Bowen came over to my table to
                                    say that a meeting between the Queen and President Dole had
                                    occurred, and terms were agreed upon. I said I did not care for
                                    him to talk with me on that subject.</p>
                                <p>On the 21st instant Mr. Claus Spreckels called to see me. He said
                                        <pb facs="0487" n="481" xml:id="pg_481"/> that he suspected
                                    there was an effort at negotiation between the Queen and the
                                    Provisional Government, and that he had urged the Queen to
                                    withdraw her power of attorney from Paul Neumann. I inclose
                                    herewith a copy of that power of attorney (Inclosure No. 1)
                                    which Mr. Spreckels says was derived through the agency of Mr.
                                    Samuel Parker, the last secretary of foreign affairs. He told me
                                    that Paul Neumann would leave for Washington by the next
                                    steamer, under pretense that he was going to the United States
                                    and from there to Japan. How much or how little Mr. Spreckels
                                    knows about this matter I am unable to say, as I do not know how
                                    to estimate him, never having met him before. He promised to see
                                    me again before the mail leaves for the linked States on next
                                    Wednesday and give me such information as he could acquire in
                                    the meantime.</p>
                                <p>I believe that Dr. Bowen, Mr. Sewall, and Mr. Neumann have
                                    pretended that the two former knew the opinions of Mr. Cleveland
                                    and assured the Queen that annexation would take place, and that
                                    she had better come to terms at once.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Neumann leaves here on the next steamer, probably with a
                                    power to act for the Queen, with authority derived from her out
                                    of these circumstances.</p>
                                <p>The question occurs to my mind whether, if the United States
                                    desired the adjustment as probably agreed on, it had better not
                                    be accomplished through its representative here, either myself
                                    or the successor of Mr. Stevens as minister here, that assurance
                                    might be had that the action of the Government was free from any
                                    suspicion of indirection in the transaction.</p>
                                <p>I know the American minister, Mr. Stevens, has said that he had
                                    learned that Mr. Blount believed that such a settlement as
                                    indicated would simplify the situation, I called on him
                                    yesterday and told him that I did not think it was proper for
                                    him to speak of my views on the subject; that declarations of
                                    that sort coming from him would give rise to the suspicion that
                                    the Government of the United States was behind Dr. Bowen and Mr.
                                    Sewall in whatever they might see fit to represent in regard to
                                    the views of the President. During this interview I called his
                                    attention to the following conversation between Mr. Spreckels
                                    and myself on the 21st instant: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Blount</hi>. Please state
                                            whether or not you have had any message from the
                                            American minister, and whether any conversation with
                                            him.</p>
                                        <p>A. I have.</p>
                                        <p>Q. Be kind enough to state it.</p>
                                        <p>A. He sent down on Tuesday about 3 o’clock, whether I
                                            would be kind enough to come-up to his house to see him.
                                            I took a carriage and saw him at 4 o’clock that Tuesday
                                            afternoon. He told me that Mr. Parker had no influence
                                            with the Queen, but that Paul Neumann could control her,
                                            and, if I would, I could control Paul Neumann; that Paul
                                            Neumann tell the Queen that she be in favor of
                                            annexation, and tell the Kanakas, who follow her, to go
                                            all for annexation. He said that he expected to be here
                                            only thirty or forty days, and he would like for
                                            annexation to be before he left. Some words to that
                                            effect.</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>He said he thought Mr. Spreckels misunderstood him as to his
                                    declaration that he wanted to finish up annexation before he
                                    left. I then told him that I felt assured that it would be
                                    displeasing to the Secretary of State and the President if they
                                    were informed that he was seeking to mold opinion here on the
                                    matter of annexation of these islands; that I was here
                                    instructed in part to inquire into that very subject; that it
                                    was certainly very unseemly, while I was making the inquiry, for
                                    him to be urging annexation; that he must know by the fact of my
                                    presence alone that he was not authorized to represent the views
                                    of the present administration in relation to any matter growing
                                    out of the <pb facs="0488" n="482" xml:id="pg_482"/> proposition
                                    to annex these islands to the United States. At first he said
                                    that his position had been made known through the publication of
                                    his dispatches, and that he never could go back on them.</p>
                                <p>To this I replied that the proposition of going back on his
                                    dispatches was one thing, and that his undertaking to form
                                    public opinion here on the subject of annexation at this time
                                    for an Administration not of his own political party, and when I
                                    was present to represent it especially in such matters, scarcely
                                    seemed fair in the light of the courtesy which had been
                                    manifested towards him. I said to him that I hoped in future
                                    that he would not undertake to advance or retard the cause of
                                    annexation or to represent the Government in any way in that
                                    connection, and that whenever it was necessary for him to speak
                                    on the matter that he would refer persons to me. This he agreed
                                    to. All this colloquy was characterized by kindliness on my
                                    part, and, so far as I could observe, by courtesy on the part of
                                    Mr. Stevens. He complained somewhat that I did not confide in
                                    him and did not seek his opinion about men and things here. I
                                    replied that I was engaged on certain lines of inquiry and might
                                    in the future find occasion to seek his opinion.</p>
                                <p>On Tuesday, the 18th instant, President Dole sent Mr. Prank
                                    Hastings, his private secretary, to say that Mr. Stevens had
                                    requested, on application from Admiral Skerrett, permission for
                                    the United States troops to land for the purpose of drilling,
                                    and said that he thought proper, before consenting to it, he
                                    should make this fact known to me. I replied that I did not
                                    desire the troops to land. I then sent for Admiral Skerrett and
                                    told him that there were circumstances of a political character
                                    which made the landing of the troops for any purpose at this
                                    time inadvisable. This was entirely satisfactory to him.</p>
                                <p>On the 21st the aforesaid Mr. Hastings called and asked how he
                                    should answer Mr. Stevens’ note for permission to land the
                                    troops. 1 replied by simply saying that the Commissioner had
                                    informed him that he disapproved of it.</p>
                                <p>The landing of the troops, pending negotiations between the Queen
                                    and President Dole, might be used to impress the former with
                                    fear that troops were landed to lend force to the Provisional
                                    Government in bringing her to an adjustment. I did not think
                                    proper to communicate this reason to Mr. Stevens or any other
                                    person, save Admiral Skerrett, and to him confidentially.</p>
                                <p>A great many hearings have been given to persons classed as
                                    Reformers or as Royalists. The former justify the dethronement
                                    of the Queen, because of her revolutionary attempt to subvert
                                    the constitution of 1887, and by proclamation to create a new
                                    constitution in lieu thereof, containing provisions restoring to
                                    the Crown the right of appointing nobles and of appointing
                                    ministers responsible only to it. In speaking of the controversy
                                    they refer to one party as whites and the other as natives. They
                                    represent the political contests for the last ten or twelve
                                    years as running parallel with racial lines. A confidence is
                                    sometimes expressed that the revolution of 1887 taught the
                                    whites that whenever they desired they could do whatever they
                                    willed in determining the form of government for these islands,
                                    and had likewise taught the natives that they would be unable to
                                    resist the will of the whites.</p>
                                <p>It is urged that the aid of the Government of the United States
                                    was not needed to make the revolution successful. Closer
                                    scrutiny reveals the fact that they regarded the revolution as
                                    successful when they should be able to proclaim a constitution
                                    from some public building, believing that the presence of the
                                    United States troops signified their use for the preservation of
                                    public order, which latter, in the minds of <pb facs="0489" n="483" xml:id="pg_483"/> the people of Honolulu, means the
                                    prevention of hostile com opposing parties. Whatever may be the
                                    truth, I am unable to discover in all the testimony any
                                    apprehension that the troops would be inimical to the
                                    revolutionary movement. In all of the examinations of persons
                                    thus far this fear has never manifested itself for an instant.
                                    The natives, on the other hand, insist that the Queen never
                                    contemplated proclaiming a new constitution without the assent
                                    of the ministry. They argue that the establishment of a new
                                    constitution by the proclamation of the Queen was as justifiable
                                    as that of 1887, in which a mass meeting of whites in the city
                                    of Honolulu extorted the proclamation of a new constitution from
                                    King Kalakaua, which had never been ratified by any vote of the
                                    people. They represent that the proclamation of a new
                                    constitution by the Queen was founded on the universal wish of
                                    the native population, which is in overwhelming majority over
                                    other races participating in the affairs of this Government.</p>
                                <p>They allege that on the day the Queen sought to proclaim a new
                                    constitution a committee representing the Hui Kalaiaina were
                                    waiting on her by direction of that organization. They represent
                                    that various petitions had been presented to the Queen and to
                                    the legislature for a series of years, asking for a new
                                    constitution similar to that existing prior to the revolution of
                                    1887. Testimony on these two lines of thought has been taken. In
                                    addition to this, very much evidence has been given in the form
                                    of voluntary statements as to the causes of the revolution and
                                    the circumstances attending it, especially as to how far the
                                    whites compelled the Queen to acquiesce in their movement on the
                                    one side, and on the other as to the entire success of the
                                    movement of the whites, depending on the action of the United
                                    States troops and the American Minister in support of this
                                    movement.</p>
                                <p>It is not my purpose at this time to enter into an elaborate
                                    consideration of the evidence which has been adduced, because
                                    many other statements are yet to be made, which will be
                                    considered.</p>
                                <p>I invite your attention to the following copy of a memorial from
                                    the Hui Kalaiaina, because of its striking disclosure of the
                                    native Hawaiian mind in its aspirations as to the form of
                                    government, and, in connection with that, a colloquy between
                                    myself and a committee of that organization taken down by a
                                    stenographer and approved by them: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Statement of facts
                                                made by the Hui Kalaiaina</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hawaiian Political Association</hi>) <hi rend="italic">in behalf of the people to J. H.
                                                Blount, the United States Commissioner, showing why
                                                the people urged the Queen to promulgate a new
                                                constitution for the Hawaiian people.</hi></p>
                                        <p rend="flushleft">To the Honorable J. H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Blount</hi>, the United States
                                            Commissioner, greeting:</p>
                                        <p>We, the Hawaiian Political Association, in behalf of the
                                            people of the Hawaiian islands—an association organized
                                            in the city of Honolulu, with branches organized all
                                            over these islands, which association has been in
                                            existence since the overthrow of the constitution of
                                            Kamehameha IV by the descendants of the sons of
                                            missionaries who are seeking to usurp the Kingdom of our
                                            Queen for themselves—</p>
                                        <p>And for this reason the people did ask King Kalakaua to
                                            revise the constitution of 1887 now in force, and during
                                            his reign many petitions were made to him and to the
                                            Legislature with thousands of signatures attached, but
                                            the desire of the people was never fulfilled.</p>
                                        <p>Therefore, the people petitioned to him for redress
                                            according to these statements now submitted to you: <list>
                                                <item>First. This constitution deprived the Grown of
                                                  Hawaiian Islands of its ancient
                                                  prerogatives.</item>
                                                <item>Second. This constitution based the principles
                                                  of government on the forms and spirit of
                                                  republican governments.</item>
                                                <item>Third. This constitution opens the way to a
                                                  republican government.</item>
                                                <item>Fourth. This constitution has taken the
                                                  sovereign power and vested it outside of the King
                                                  sitting on the throne of the Hawaiian
                                                  Kingdom.</item>
                                                <item>Fifth. This constitution has limited the
                                                  franchise of the native Hawaiians.</item>
                                            </list></p>
                                        <pb facs="0490" n="484" xml:id="pg_484"/>
                                        <p>For these five reasons was King Kalakaua petitioned by
                                            his people to revise the constitution, but it never was
                                            carried out until the time of his death.</p>
                                        <p>During the reign of Queen Liliuokalani the same thing
                                            happened. Numerous petitions were laid before her by and
                                            from the people, and from this association to the
                                            Legislature and to the Queen. These petitions contain
                                            over eight thousand names, and this Hawaaian Political
                                            Association did repeatedly petition the Queen to revise
                                            and amend or to make a new constitution, to which she
                                            finally consented to lay this request from her people
                                            before the cabinet, but the wishes of the people were
                                            not carried out.</p>
                                        <p>On the 14th of January, 1893, at the time of the
                                            prorogation of the Legislature, in the afternoon, this
                                            political association came and petitioned Her Majesty
                                            Liliuokalani to issue a new constitution for the people,
                                            to which she consented, with the intention of listening
                                            to the desires of her people, but her cabinet
                                            refused.</p>
                                        <p>A short while afterwards the descendants of the
                                            missionaries came forward in their second attempt to
                                            usurp the Kingdom of our Queen Liliuokalani, and said
                                            attempt would not have succeeded had it not been for the
                                            support given it by the American Minister
                                            Stevens—therefore our Queen yielded the Kingdom into
                                            their hands through the superior force presented by the
                                            men of the American warships, who had been landed on the
                                            Hawaiian soil.</p>
                                        <p>Queen Liliuokalani yielded her Kingdom into their hands,
                                            not with good will, but because she could not defend it,
                                            and because the Queen did not desire to see the blood of
                                            her Hawaiian people shed on this land of peace.</p>
                                        <p>Therefore, we submit to you our humble petition and
                                            statements, as you are in possession of vast powers in
                                            your mission to do justice to the Hawaiian people, our
                                            independence, the throne, and the Hawaiian flag; we beg
                                            you to restore our beloved Queen Liliuokalani to the
                                            throne with the independence of the Hawaiian people, as
                                            you have restored the Hawaiian flag.</p>
                                        <p>Submitting these statements and petitions to you we pray
                                            that the Almighty God would assist you in your
                                            responsible duties, that the prayers of our people may
                                            be granted, that continued friendship may exist between
                                            us and the American nation.</p>
                                        <p>We, the undersigned subscribers of the Hawaiian Political
                                            Association.</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">W. L.
                                            Holokahiki</hi>,</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="italic">Chairman.</hi></p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">John Keeui</hi>,</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">J. Alapai</hi>,</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">J. Akahoonei</hi>,</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">J. B. Kurha</hi>,</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">J. Kean</hi>,</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">D. W.
                                            Kanoelehua</hi>,</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">T. C.
                                                Pohikapa</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Committee</hi>.</p>
                                        <p>In accepting the copy of the resolutions Mr. Blount
                                            responded as follows:</p>
                                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: Very much of the
                                            duties of my mission I cannot communicate to you. I will
                                            say, however, that your papers which have been presented
                                            I will accept and forward to the President in the nature
                                            of information indicating the opinions of your people in
                                            these Islands in reference to the inclination on your
                                            part to support the existing condition of things—that is
                                            to say, whether you are in favor of the Provisional
                                            Government and annexation, or whether your preference is
                                            for royalty. I am gathering information on these lines
                                            for the purpose of submitting it to the President. That
                                            is the extent of what I can say to you by way of
                                            response. I would like to ask, however, a few questions.
                                            Which is the chairman of your committee?</p>
                                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Interpreter</hi>. W. L. Holokahiki,
                                            of Honolulu.</p>
                                        <p>(These questions were given and answered through the
                                            interpreter.)</p>
                                        <p>Q. On the day of the prorogation of the Legislature a
                                            number of natives are reported to have gone in to see
                                            the Queen—about thirty in number—and that their object
                                            was to ask for a new constitution. Was that a committee
                                            from this organization?</p>
                                        <p>A. Yes, sir.</p>
                                        <p>Q. How many voters—people who vote for
                                            representatives—are there in this order?</p>
                                        <p>A. Some thousands; as we have it in our books about 3,000
                                            of native Hawaiians.</p>
                                        <p>Q. What did the Queen say in response to your
                                            request?</p>
                                        <p>A. That she was quite ready to give a new constitution,
                                            but her cabinet is opposed to it. Her cabinet refused it
                                            so that she could not do otherwise. She told the people
                                            that they had to go home quietly and wait for the next
                                            session of the Legislature.</p>
                                        <p>Q. When would that be if the Government had not been
                                            overthrown?</p>
                                        <p>A. The time, according to our laws, was two years, and
                                            that would run us up to 1894.</p>
                                        <p>Q. Then the information was that nothing could be done
                                            under two years on account of the disapproval of the
                                            cabinet?</p>
                                        <p>A. Yes; the Queen could do nothing.</p>
                                        <pb facs="0491" n="485" xml:id="pg_485"/>
                                        <p>Q. She said she could do nothing?</p>
                                        <p>A. Yes; because the constitution said she could do
                                            nothing without being approved by her Cabinet.</p>
                                        <p>Q. What did the committee do when they went out? Did they
                                            give this information to the native people?</p>
                                        <p>A. Yes, sir. This committee shortly after they came
                                            out—they told the people they could do nothing now; that
                                            they would have to wait until the next session. Also,
                                            the Queen came out and told the people she could not
                                            give them any constitution now because the law
                                            forbids.</p>
                                        <p>A great many petitions were exhibited—sometimes they were
                                            to the Queen and sometimes to the Legislature—asking for
                                            a new constitution.</p>
                                        <p>A book was also shown containing the names of members of
                                            the organization throughout the island, and giving the
                                            numbers as follows:</p>
                                        <p>Oahu, 2,320; Maui, 384; Hawaii, 266; Kauai, 222, and
                                            Molokai, 263.</p>
                                        <p>Q. (To interpreter.) Why don’t other natives join the
                                            organization?</p>
                                        <p>A. They sometimes go to meetings. When anything happens
                                            they go together.</p>
                                        <p>Q. These are active members of the organization?</p>
                                        <p>A. Yes.</p>
                                        <p>Q. In matters of this sort the natives followed the lead
                                            of this organigation?</p>
                                        <p>A. Yes, sir.</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>Prior to the constitution of 1887 the nobles were appointed by
                                    the Crown and the representatives were elected by the people,
                                    with but little obstruction in the qualification of the elector.
                                    The number of nobles was 20 and the number of representatives
                                    was 28, and these, constituting one body, enacted the laws. The
                                    cabinet was only responsible to the King. The majority of voters
                                    was overwhelmingly native. It is easy to understand how
                                    completely the native people could, if they desired, control the
                                    Government as against the white race. Under the constitution of
                                    1887 the number of nobles and representatives is equal. The
                                    qualification of an elector of a noble required him to own
                                    property of the value of $3,000, unincumbered, or an income of
                                    $600. Practically this vested the power of electing nobles in
                                    the white population, or, as it is sometimes termed, the reform
                                    party. A cabinet could not be removed by the Crown except on a
                                    vote of want of confidence by the Legislature. The ability to
                                    elect a small number, even one of the representatives, enabled
                                    the white race to control legislation and to vote out any
                                    ministry not in accord with them. This placed the political
                                    power in the hands of the white race. I use the words “white”
                                    and “native” as distinguishing the persons in the political
                                    contests here, because they are generally used by the people
                                    here in communicating their views to me.</p>
                                <p>I had supposed up to the appearance of this memorial that the
                                    real demand of the native was for a just proportion of power in
                                    the election of nobles by the reduction of the money
                                    qualification of an elector. This I had derived from interviews
                                    with some of the intelligent half-castes. This memorial
                                    indicates an opposition to the new constitution because it takes
                                    away from the Crown the right to appoint nobles and the right to
                                    appoint and remove cabinets at will. There is no aspiration in
                                    it for the advancement of the right of the masses to participate
                                    in the control of public affairs, but an eager, trustful
                                    devotion to the Crown as an absolute monarchy. I had wondered
                                    whether or not this race of people, which up to 1843 had no
                                    rights of property, and over whom the king and chiefs had
                                    absolute power of life and death, had fully cast off the old
                                    system and conceived the modern ideas in the United States of
                                    the control of the government by equal participation by every
                                    citizen in the selection of its rulers. Up to the appearance of
                                    this memorial I had received but little satisfaction on this
                                    line of thought.</p>
                                <p>In this connection I invite your attention to Inclosure No. 2,
                                    being a copy of resolutions presented on the 16th instant by a
                                    committee of the “Hui Aloha Aina”—the Hawaiian Patriotic
                                    League.</p>
                                <pb facs="0492" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/>
                                <p>Taken in connection with the foregoing memorial of the Hui
                                    Kalaiaina, it is strongly suggestive of blind devotion to
                                    arbitrary power vested in the crown worn by a person of native
                                    blood. I have forwarded these two documents because they present
                                    a phase of thought which had not been so well defined in
                                    anything I had seen in publications relating to these islands.
                                    They seem to go very far in the matter of the capacity of these
                                    people for self-government.</p>
                                <p>I have received communications from every source when offered,
                                    not to support any theory, but simply to see what might be
                                    derived from them in the way of information. I have studiously
                                    avoided any suggestion that the President contemplated the
                                    consideration of the restoration of the Queen, the support of
                                    the existing Government, or the question of annexation on any
                                    terms. I have intended to invite the freest expression of
                                    thought without any indication that it was to be considered with
                                    a view of guiding the action of the Government in the
                                    determination of any proposition. In all this I find my action
                                    most heartily approved by both whites and natives.</p>
                                <p>In several local papers, beginning with the 13th instant,
                                    editorials have appeared advising in terms somewhat indefinite,
                                    and yet pointing to the extreme action which should be taken
                                    towards the Queen and her adherents, and deploring the want of
                                    such action on the part of the Provisional Government. On the
                                    night of the 14th instant a prominent half-caste called upon me.
                                    He had always assured me hitherto of the quiet intention of the
                                    native population. On this latter occasion he said: “We are in
                                    trouble. It is said the Queen is to be put out of the way by
                                    assassination, and her prominent followers to be prosecuted for
                                    treason or deported.”</p>
                                <p>These apprehensions naturally grew out of the editorials alluded
                                    to. I said to him I had no idea there was any foundation for his
                                    fears in the purposes of the Government. Before he left me he
                                    seemed to be relieved.</p>
                                <p>On the morning of the 15th I called on President Dole, and
                                    invited his attention to the newspaper articles above referred
                                    to and to the visit of the half-caste, with his expressions of
                                    fear and my response. I said to him that perhaps I had gone
                                    farther than propriety would suggest in my opinion to the
                                    half-caste on the evening before, but that I was impelled solely
                                    by that humane feeling which would regret to see disorder and
                                    bloodshed inflicted on any portion of the community. I also
                                    intimated that if he deemed it desirable, owing to the kindly
                                    feeling the native population had manifested towards me, I
                                    might, without pretending to represent the Government, allay
                                    their anxieties and contribute to the public peace by assuring
                                    them that the extreme measures advocated by the press I did not
                                    believe were approved by the Government. To this he responded
                                    that it would be very gratifying to him and to those in
                                    political accord with him for me to act as I had suggested. He
                                    furthermore declared that it was the purpose of the Government
                                    to confine its action only to the preservation of order, and to
                                    take no extreme steps against any parties here unless it should
                                    be to meet a forcible attack on the Government.</p>
                                <p>When the ensign was hauled down and the troops ordered to the
                                    vessels there was some comment on the omission to recite in the
                                    order or by some public declaration the exact import of this
                                    action.</p>
                                <p>In the above conversation I referred to the subject and said that
                                    at the time I believed that any speech or written declaration
                                    might be liable to many and false constructions, and that the
                                    action of hauling down the ensign and the removal of the troops
                                    would in a few hours <pb facs="0493" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/>
                                    tell with more simplicity and accuracy and with better results
                                    than any utterances of mine could do.</p>
                                <p>To this he replied that at first there was some criticism, but
                                    that all minds had come to the conclusion that I had taken the
                                    wiser course.</p>
                                <p>He took occasion to say to me that all men everywhere could only
                                    think that I was governed by the highest motives in all my
                                    actions here.</p>
                                <p>At 10 o’clock on the morning of the 22d instant Mr. Spreckels
                                    called to see me. He assured me that Mr. Neumann was going to
                                    San Francisco and then to Japan. I said to him: “But he is going
                                    to Washington.” He said: “Yes; but in order to take some
                                    dispatches from Mr. Stevens to the Washington Government.”</p>
                                <p>On the 21st, in the conversation with Mr. Stevens, to which
                                    reference has already been made, he told me for the first time
                                    of a letter he had written to you concerning certain matters
                                    which had passed between him and the Japanese commissioner at
                                    this place. The extent of it was that by representations that
                                    the United States was opposed to the presence of a Japanese war
                                    vessel here that it was determined that the Japanese Minister
                                    should ask his Government to cause the aforesaid vessel to be
                                    withdrawn.</p>
                                <p>In view of my instructions, I felt bound to give assurances to
                                    the Japanese commissioner that the present Administration does
                                    not view with displeasure or suspicion the presence of one of
                                    her war vessels here.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Paul Neumann is generally regarded here as a bright,
                                    plausible, unscrupulous person. Permit me to suggest that if the
                                    Administration should entertain any proposition from Mr. Neumann
                                    in connection with a contract between the Queen and the
                                    Provisional Government in the matter of her abdication, the
                                    consummation of it is surrounded by so many circumstances
                                    indicating that the Government of the United States has been
                                    made to appear to the Queen as favoring such action on her part
                                    that it would be far better to decline to entertain anything
                                    from Mr. Neumann, but for the Government to accomplish its
                                    purpose in a more direct manner. If such an adjustment is
                                    desirable, instructions to the American representative here to
                                    endea.vor to bring about such an arrangement would be a much
                                    more honorable course on the part of the United States.</p>
                                <p>The representatives of the Provisional Government are conscious
                                    that the movement inaugurated on the 14th of January last for
                                    the dethronement of the Queen and annexation to the United
                                    States is a much more desperate one than they then realized.</p>
                                <p>The white race, or what may be termed the Reform party,
                                    constitute the intelligence and own most of the property in
                                    these islands and are desperately eager to be a part of the
                                    United States on any terms rather than take the chances of being
                                    subjected to the control of the natives. With them we can
                                    dictate any terms. The feeling of the natives is that while they
                                    do not want annexation, if the United States does it will be
                                    accomplished, and they will acquiesce. The situation is so
                                    completely under our control that I should regret to see Mr.
                                    Neumann’s agency in the matter of abdication of the Queen, with
                                    his connection with Dr. Bowen and others and the attendant
                                    circumstances, recognized by the Government. You will readily
                                    understand that this is not intended as impertinence, but only
                                    as a suggestion.</p>
                                <p>Since writing the foregoing portion of my letter relating to
                                    attempts to represent the views of the President of the United
                                    States by unauthorized persons in connection with the subject of
                                    an agreement between ex-Queen Liliuokalani and the Provisional
                                    Government, I have deemed it proper to have an interview with
                                    the former in order to understand, <pb facs="0494" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/> as far as I might, from her whether any
                                    negotiations had been authorized by her, and if so, how far they
                                    had gone. Before doing so, I called on President Dole and
                                    informed him of my purpose to see her in connection with this
                                    subject, stating to him that I was not willing that persons
                                    should make fraudulent representations to her as to that matter.
                                    I told him that I had abstained from seeing her lest my visit
                                    might be construed in a way to produce disorders, but now I felt
                                    all danger of this had passed. He concurred in my views as to
                                    the propriety of my calling, if I saw fit to do so.</p>
                                <p>I said to the ex-Queen that I had been informed that certain
                                    persons had sought to impress her with the idea that the
                                    President desired some such adjustment as indicated to be made 5
                                    that I wished to say that no person was authorized by the
                                    President nor by myself to place the Government of the United
                                    States in such an attitude; that, while I would interpose no
                                    objection to such negotiation, I wanted her to know that
                                    whatever she did in the matter was free from any moral influence
                                    from the Government of the United States. I further said to her
                                    that I desired to be able to inform my Government whether she
                                    had been engaged in such negotiations or contemplated them, or
                                    whether anybody was authorized to act for her in any such
                                    matter; that I wished the information simply to put the
                                    Government at Washington in possession of the true state of
                                    facts.</p>
                                <p>She replied that parties who had represented her in other matters
                                    had talked to her on the subject; that she had declined to
                                    indicate any disposition to act in the matter; that she had said
                                    to some of them that she would wait until President Dole came to
                                    see her in person, and had heard what he had to say; that she
                                    did not intend to enter into any negotiations until the
                                    Government at Washington had taken action on the information
                                    derived through my report. She said she had sent Mr. Neumann to
                                    Washington to prevent the ratification of the treaty and to have
                                    a commission sent out here, and he reported that he had been
                                    successful in both. I then asked her what she desired me to say
                                    to the Government at Washington as to her purpose in the matter
                                    of this negotiation. She expressed a wish that I should say from
                                    her that no one was authorized to act in her behalf in this
                                    matter and that she should take no action until the Government
                                    at Washington had passed upon the information derived through
                                    the Commissioner.</p>
                                <p>Lest she might make improper inferences from my visit or
                                    something I had said I told her that one of the objects of my
                                    visit was to get all the facts connected with her dethronement
                                    and the disposition of the people of the Islands in relation to
                                    the present Government; that she could readily see that that was
                                    a matter to be hereafter considered by the Government in such
                                    manner as it saw fit. Without any apparent connection with what
                                    had been said, she remarked that much depended on Mr. Spreckels
                                    as to the future; that he and Mr. Bishop had been in the habit
                                    of furnishing money to the Government, and that if Mr. Spreckels
                                    did not advance to the Government she thought it would go to
                                    pieces. To this I made no response. It is evident that she is
                                    being impressed with the idea that the present Government could
                                    not get money enough to run itself long.</p>
                                <p>I am not sufficiently informed to express any views on this
                                    proposition at this time.</p>
                                <p>I think the operations of Dr. Bowen and Mr. Sewall have been
                                    conducted through Mr. Neumann. I shall, perhaps, know more
                                    before closing this communication.</p>
                                <p>I send you a map, marked Inclosure No. 3. You will find it useful
                                        <pb facs="0495" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/> in considering the
                                    location of the various military forces connected with the
                                    revolution, to which I may refer in this and especially in
                                    subsequent communications.</p>
                                <p>I send you a written statement from F. Wundenburg (Inclosure No.
                                    4), who says that his information is derived from being
                                    personally present in all the conferences of the committee of
                                    safety and that his utterances are based on his personal
                                    knowledge. He appears to be an intelligent man. He says that he
                                    acted with the committee in good faith until the American flag
                                    was hoisted, and then he ceased communication with them. He is
                                    at this time deputy clerk of the supreme court. I think in my
                                    next communication I may be able to give you information
                                    strongly corroborating all that Mr. Wundenburg has said.</p>
                                <p>I may say that the peaceful surroundings of the revolution are
                                    confirmed by all persons with whom I have communicated, and that
                                    Judge Cooper, who was and is an intense annexationist, let drop,
                                    in answer to a question of mine, that when the Government
                                    building was entered by the committee of safety and the
                                    proclamation dethroning the Queen and establishing the new
                                    Government was read by him there was not a soldier of the
                                    Provisional Government or of the Queen on the ground.</p>
                                <p>I send you, in original, a communication from Mr. William H. Corn
                                    well, a member of the Queen’s cabinet at the time of her
                                    dethronement (Inclosure No. 5).</p>
                                <p>I also send you, in original, a communication from Mr. John F.
                                    Colburn, a member of the Ex-Queen’s cabinet and a half-caste
                                    (Inclosure No. 6).</p>
                                <p>These are forwarded in advance of the testimony or voluntary
                                    statements in response to interrogatories by himself, because
                                    they present the views of these gentlemen as to the
                                    circumstances attending the revolution and which do not appear
                                    in any of the papers relating to the annexation of the Hawaiian
                                    Islands printed by the United States so far as I have been
                                    furnished with them.</p>
                                <p>It is my purpose to examine them in person so as to have an
                                    opportunity of thoroughly sifting them.</p>
                                <p>I inclose you a copy of a communication from the committee of
                                    public safety—which conceived and executed the dethronement of
                                    the Queen—addressed to the American Minister (Inclosure No. 7).
                                    On page 12 of Executive Document No. 76, Fifty-second Congress,
                                    second session, this paper issimply referred to in the following
                                    language: “A copy of the call of the committee of public safety
                                    for aid is inclosed.” It appears significant enough to have
                                    justified its being printed in full. To be imploring protection
                                    from the Government of the United States on the 16th and
                                    establishing the provisional government and dethroning the Queen
                                    without firing a gun on the next day—without any reference to
                                    the presence of United States troops— is quite a draft on my
                                    credulity.</p>
                                <p>This paper may have been overlooked, and hence my calling your
                                    attention to it.</p>
                                <p>I send you a pamphlet, entitled “Papers of the Hawaiian
                                    Historical Society No. 3” (Inclosure No. 8),<note n="*" xml:id="d254fn1">Footnote omitted on account of
                                        length.</note> on the subject of the evolution of the
                                    Hawaiian land tenures. To this I will add further information in
                                    relation to the tenure of lands in these islands. It appears
                                    from all information attainable that the great mass of the
                                    natives have at all times had but little interest in real
                                    property. This will throw some light on the little development
                                    attained by them, and how the real property <pb facs="0496" n="490" xml:id="pg_490"/> has, by virtue of the operation of
                                    these laws, resulted in the ownership by large landed
                                    proprietors, mostly of foreign birth.</p>
                                <p>I see in the newspapers that the War Department is issuing in a
                                    documentary form information of various sorts in relation to the
                                    islands. In one of them it is stated that the natives generally
                                    speak the English language. This is quite contradictory to my
                                    information from intelligent persons here and my own
                                    observation. In Honolulu, where the situation is most favorable
                                    to development, the groups of children playing along the streets
                                    use their native tongue. The natives of mature age whom you meet
                                    are generally unable to converse with you in English or to
                                    understand what is said to them. They learn in the schools the
                                    English text-books as an American child would learn the Latin or
                                    Greek languages. This done, their capacity to think or speak
                                    English seems very slight.</p>
                                <p>I am very much impressed with a belief that a large majority of
                                    the people of these islands are opposed to annexation and that
                                    the proofs being taken will verify this opinion.</p>
                                <p>I have not indicated any purposes of the United States on the
                                    subject of annexation in seeking to ascertain the sentiment of
                                    the people towards existing authority. A response to this
                                    necessarily involves the question of how the people feel towards
                                    annexation. The Provisional Government being avowedly a part of
                                    a scheme towards annexation, and the opposition taking the form
                                    of opposing it, I have from necessity been compelled to put my
                                    inquiries more or less in a form answering to this division of
                                    sentiment. I have never claimed to mold the disposition of the
                                    administration on that question nor indicated my own.</p>
                                <p>The condition of the public mind is very peaceful. I think it
                                    important to maintain this situation that a representative of
                                    the United States should be here before my departure who will
                                    maintain the attitude of noninterference in local affairs which
                                    I have observed. The contrary course on the part of an American
                                    representative would immediately produce much bitterness and
                                    discontent in one or the other of the parties now dividing the
                                    people. I can see no advantage in my remaining here longer than
                                    the month of May. I trust that you will consent to my return at
                                    such time during the month of June as I may choose. I prefer to
                                    write my report on my return to Washington rather than while
                                    here. Interruptions on the part of people who are constantly
                                    seeking my attention make this preferable.</p>
                                <p>It is difficult to get passage from here to the United States on
                                    account of the great amount of travel and arrangements must be
                                    made some weeks in advance.</p>
                                <p>Please be kind enough to telegraph me in response to the subject
                                    of my return.</p>
                                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James H. Blount</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Special Commissioner of the United
                                            States.</hi></signed></closer>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                        3.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Power of attorney for Mr.
                                        Neumann.</hi></head>
                                    <p>To all persons and to the Government of the United States of
                                        America and to all other Governments whatsoever: To all
                                        bodies corporate as well as bodies politic, and more
                                        especially to the President and to the Secretary of the
                                        Department of State of the United States of America, I,
                                        Liliuokalani, of the city of Honolulu, in the Island of
                                        Oahu, one of the Hawaiian Islands, send greeting:</p>
                                    <pb facs="0497" n="491" xml:id="pg_491"/>
                                    <p>Whereas on the seventeenth day of January, A. D. 1893, at the
                                        city of Honolulu aforesaid, I did yield to the Provisional
                                        Government of the Hawaiian Islands my authority as Sovereign
                                        of the Hawaiian Islands under protest;</p>
                                    <p>And whereas by so doing I claim to be entitled by
                                        international law and in the high forum of conscience and
                                        equity to receive consideration and provision both for
                                        myself and family and for Kaiulani, who was my legally
                                        appointed successor as such Sovereign;</p>
                                    <p>And whereas it is my intention and desire by these presents
                                        to authorize, secure, accomplish, and finally complete and
                                        to ratify by such arrangements as may conduce to the
                                        greatest welfare and benefit of all the people of the
                                        Hawaiian Islands and also of myself and family and the said
                                        Kaiulani;</p>
                                    <p>And whereas I repose the fullest confidence in the ability,
                                        integrity, and fidelity of Paul Neumann, esq., of the city
                                        of Honolulu aforesaid, counsellor at law, and have entrusted
                                        him with full power and authority to act for me in the
                                        premises;</p>
                                    <p>Now, therefore, know ye, that in consideration of the
                                        premises, I, Lilioukalani, aforesaid, have made,
                                        constituted, and appointed, and by these presents do hereby
                                        make, constitute, and appoint the aforesaid Paul Neumann,
                                        esq., my true, lawful, and sufficient attorney, for me and
                                        in my name, place, and stead, to negotiate, arrange, and
                                        agree with the United States of America and the President
                                        and the Secretary of the Department of State thereof, and
                                        with any other (if any) representative or official thereof
                                        having authority in the premises for such official, or the
                                        consideration, benefit, and advantage as in the opinion of
                                        my said attorney shall, may, or can be obtained from the
                                        United States of America as well for myself and family as
                                        for the said Kaiulani, in consideration of existing
                                        conditions and circumstances. And if no official
                                        consideration for myself or said Kaiulani shall in the
                                        opinion of my said attorney be attainable from the United
                                        States of America, then and thereupon, and in such case to
                                        arrange and agree upon such pecuniary considerations,
                                        benefits, and advantages as can or may be secured for myself
                                        and family, and for said Kaiulani, from the United States of
                                        America, and whether the same shall be in the form of
                                        payment at one time of a sum of money to myself <hi rend="italic">for</hi> of distinct sums of money to
                                        myself and said Kaiulani, or in payment of stated sums of
                                        money annually, or oftener, for a fixed period or periods of
                                        time, and upon ascertaining that such pecuniary
                                        considerations, benefits, advantages, or payments of money
                                        from and on the part of the said United States can be
                                        secured to agree upon, receive, and accept the same, and in
                                        my name and behalf to make, execute, and deliver such
                                        agreements, releases, and acquittances of ail my claims,
                                        demands, and pretensions whatsoever upon the throne of the
                                        Hawaiian Islands and upon the Government of the United
                                        States of America, as well as of the Hawaiian Islands and
                                        upon all persons having had anything to do with or having
                                        been or being in any way concerned in the said Provisional
                                        Government as shall be requisite to accomplish and secure
                                        such pecuniary considerations, benefits, advantages, and
                                        payments, or which shall be required therefor by the
                                        President or the Secretary of the Department of State
                                        aforesaid, or by any other (if any) representative or
                                        official of the United States authorized to act or agree ix
                                        the premises, and all that my said attorney shall do or
                                        cause to be done in the premises I do hereby for myself and
                                        my successors, executors, administrators, and assigns ratify
                                        and confirm, and further I do hereby covenant with my said
                                        attorney and his executors and administrators and with the
                                        President of the United States of America and with any other
                                        person and persons representing the said United States of
                                        America in the premises, and with each of them, and with
                                        their respective successors both jointly and severally that
                                        all and whatsoever my said attorney shall in my behalf agree
                                        to do or cause to be done or agreed upon by virtue of these
                                        presents I will and my successors, heirs, executors, and
                                        administrators shall ratify and confirm, and that I will at
                                        any time thereafter execute, sign, seal, acknowledge, and
                                        deliver such other and further releases, acquittances,
                                        assurances and instruments in writing, as shall in the
                                        opinion of my said attorney or in the opinion of the
                                        President of the United States of America or of any officer
                                        or representative thereof having the matter in charge be
                                        requisite and proper in order to carry out the full intent
                                        and meaning of these presents.</p>
                                    <p>In witness whereof I hereunto and also to two other
                                        instruments of the same date and time have set my hands and
                                        seals at the city of Honolulu aforesaid this day of in the
                                        year A. D. 1893.</p>
                                </frus:attachment>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                        3.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss type="from">Hawaiian Patriotic
                                                League</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Blount</persName>.</hi></head>
                                    <p>We, the women of the Hawaiian Islands, for our families and
                                        the happiness of our homes, desire peace and political
                                        quiet, and we pray that man’s greed for power and spoils
                                        shall not be allowed to disturb the otherwise happy life of
                                        these islands, and <pb facs="0498" n="492" xml:id="pg_492"/>
                                        that the revolutionary agitations and disturbances
                                        inaugurated here since 1887, by a few foreigners, may be
                                        forever suppressed.</p>
                                    <p>To that effect we believe that, in the light of recent
                                        events, the peace, welfare, and honor of both America and
                                        Hawaii will be better served, for the present, if the
                                        Government of the great American Republic does not
                                        countenance the illegal conduct and interference of its
                                        representatives here and the rash wish of a minority of
                                        foreigners for annexation.</p>
                                    <p>Therefore, we respectfully but earnestly pray that Hawaii may
                                        be granted the preservation of its independent autonomy and
                                        the restoration of its legitimate native monarchy under our
                                        Queen Liliuokalani, in whom we have full confidence.</p>
                                    <p>And we hope that the distinguished citizen, who so wisely
                                        presides over the United States, may kindly receive this our
                                        petition, for which we shall evermore pray for God’s
                                        blessing on him and his Government.</p>
                                    <closer><signed><list>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. James Campbell</hi>,
                                                  <hi rend="italic">President.</hi></item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. J. A. Cummins</hi>,
                                                  <hi rend="italic">Vice-President.</hi></item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. Al. Fernandez</hi>,
                                                  <hi rend="italic">Treasurer.</hi></item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. C. K. Stillman</hi>,
                                                  <hi rend="italic">Secretary.</hi></item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. Joseph
                                                  Nauahi</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. Junius
                                                  Kaae</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Miss Hattie
                                                  Hiram</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. M.
                                                  Kahai</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. Lulia
                                                  Aholo</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. L. Kekupuwolui
                                                  Mahelona</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. W. H.
                                                  Aldrich</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. M. A.
                                                  Lemon</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Executive
                                                  Committee.</hi></item>
                                            </list>
                                        </signed></closer>
                                    <postscript>
                                        <p>They were evidently persons of intelligence, and refined
                                            in their deportment. After reading the papers handed to
                                            me I responded that I would forward them to my
                                            Government as a matter of information, but that I could
                                            not enter into any discussion of the situation; that I
                                            would accept and transmit their papers, as I did all
                                            other facts, for purposes of information. To this they
                                            responded that they did not expect me to communicate
                                            anything to them as to my views or the disposition of
                                            the Government of the United States.</p>
                                    </postscript>
                                </frus:attachment>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No.
                                        3.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">A report from Mr. <persName type="from">Wundenburg</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Blount</persName>.</hi></head>
                                    <p>The committee of safety met at the office of W. O. Smith in
                                        Fort street, Honolulu, at about 4 o’clock in the afternoon
                                        of Monday, the 16th day of January, 1893, for the purpose of
                                        discussing the necessary steps to be taken in forming a new
                                        government.</p>
                                    <p>Shortly after the committee met it was decided that they were
                                        not ready for the landing of the American troops, and a
                                        committee of three, with Thurston as the chairman, was
                                        immediately dispatched to the American legation to prevail
                                        upon Mr. Stevens to delay the landing of the <hi rend="italic">Boston’s</hi> men. The committee returned
                                        shortly and reported that Mr. Stevens had said to them:
                                        “Gentlemen, the troops of the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>
                                        land this afternoon at 5 o’clock, whether you are ready or
                                        not.”</p>
                                    <p>The foregoing report of Mr. Stevens’s reply to the committee
                                        is as near literal as can be remembered, and gives a correct
                                        idea of the meaning conveyed. The committee of safety
                                        adjourned to meet the same evening, at 7:30 o’clock, at the
                                        house of Henry Waterhouse, in Nuuanu Valley. The American
                                        troops landed at 5 o’clock, as Mr. Stevens had told the
                                        committee they would, and marched up Fort street to
                                        Merchant, and along Merchant street, halting in King street,
                                        between the palace and Government building.</p>
                                    <p>At the time the men landed the town was perfectly quiet,
                                        business hours were about over, and the people—men, women,
                                        and children—were in the streets, and nothing unusual was to
                                        be seen except the landing of a formidable armed force with
                                        Gatling guns, evidently fully prepared to remain on shore
                                        for an indefinite length of time, as the men were supplied
                                        with double cartridge belts filled with ammunition, also
                                        haversacks and canteens, and were attended by a hospital
                                        corps with stretchers and medical supplies. The curiosity of
                                        the people on the streets was aroused, and the youngsters
                                        more particularly, followed the troops to see what it was
                                        all about. Nobody seemed to know, so when the troops found
                                        quarters the populace dispersed, the most of them going to
                                        the band concert at the hotel, which was very fully
                                        attended, as it was a beautiful moonlight evening, all who
                                        were not in the secret still wondering at the military
                                        demonstration.</p>
                                    <p>The committee met at Mr. Waterhouse’s residence, according to
                                        adjournment, <pb facs="0499" n="493" xml:id="pg_493"/> at
                                        7:30–o’clock p.m. of the same day, January 16. The formation
                                        of some sort of government was under discussion, and it was
                                        decided that a commander in chief of the forces supporting
                                        the proposed new government should be appointed. The
                                        position was offered to Mr. John H. Soper, who demurred, as
                                        he did not see any backing whatever to support the movement.
                                        Mr. Soper was answered by members of the committee that the
                                        American minister would support the move with the troops of
                                        the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>. Mr. Soper still doubted,
                                        so a couple of the committee escorted him over to the
                                        legation, which, by the way, was in the adjoining premises,
                                        and the three came back after a time, reporting that Mr.
                                        Stevens had given them the full assurance that any
                                        proclamation of the Government put forward at the Government
                                        building, or any other building in Honolulu for that matter,
                                        would receive his immediate recognition and the support of
                                        the <hi rend="italic">Boston’s</hi> men. This assurance
                                        seemed to satisfy Mr. Soper, and he accepted the
                                        position.</p>
                                    <p>On Tuesday afternoon, January 17, the committee of thirteen,
                                        or committee of safety, proceeded from the office of W. O.
                                        Smith up Merchant street to the Government building and read
                                        the proclamation of a new government at 2.40 o’clock, there
                                        being practically no audience whatever. As the reading
                                        proceeded a dozen or so loungers gathered, and near the
                                        close of the ceremony about thirty supporters, variously
                                        armed, came running into the side and back entrances of the
                                        yard and gathered a-bout the committee.</p>
                                    <p>At this moment the United States troops, in the temporary
                                        quarters in the rear of the Music Hall (less than 100 yards
                                        from where the committee stood) appeared to be under arms
                                        and were evidently prepared for any emergency.</p>
                                    <p>During all the deliberations of the committee, and in fact
                                        throughout the whole proceedings connected with plans for
                                        the move up to the final issue, the basis of action was the
                                        general understanding that Minister Stevens would keep his
                                        promise to support the movement with the men from the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>, and the statement is now
                                        advisedly made (with a full knowledge of the lack of arms,
                                        ammunition, and men, also the utter absence of organization
                                        at all adequate to the undertaking), that without the
                                        previous assurance of support from the American minister and
                                        the actual presence of the United States troops no movement
                                        would have been attempted, and if attempted, would have been
                                        a dismal failure resulting in the capture or death of the
                                        participants in a very short time.</p>
                                    <p>(Having been present at the several meetings referred to in
                                        this statement, I hereby certify that the same is correct in
                                        every essential particular. F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Wundenburg.</hi>)</p>
                                    <p>(<hi rend="smallcaps">Note.</hi>—This person appears to be
                                        highly esteemed here. He was tendered the position of
                                        collector of customs recently by the Provisional Government
                                        and declined it. I send an extract from the Daily Pacific
                                        Commercial Advertiser, showing its esteem of him.):</p>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">a projected
                                            appointment.</hi></p>
                                    <p>It is stated that the council at its meeting yesterday
                                        recommended the appointment of F. W. Wundenberg as
                                        collector-general of customs. The appointment would be in
                                        all respects a worthy one. Mr. Wundenberg is thoroughly
                                        qualified by long business experience for the position. He
                                        is a man of great energy and character, and of unimpeachable
                                        integrity. If made collector he may be trusted to make no
                                        compromise with evil, but to fight it to the bitter end.</p>
                                    <p>Mr. Wundenberg was identified with the revolution from the
                                        14th of January until the danger was over. He was placed in
                                        charge of the police station at a time when everything
                                        depended on reliable leadership, and if an uprising should
                                        occur he would follow the cause into the cannon’s mouth
                                        to-day. As a recognition of valuable service at a critical
                                        moment his appointment would be peculiarly appropriate.</p>
                                    <p>Mr. Wundenberg has an abundant crop of enemies. In this he
                                        does not differ from most men of positive traits. The fact
                                        will recommend him to all who desire to see a strong and
                                        fearless man collector-general.</p>
                                </frus:attachment>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No.
                                        3.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cornwell</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Blount</persName>.</hi></head>
                                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Honolulu</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-04-24"><hi rend="italic">April 24,
                                            1893</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                                    <p>The following statement does not purport to be an exhaustive
                                        or full history or report of the resolution of the 17th day
                                        of January, but are simply plain facts relating to that
                                        political incident as they came within my personal knowledge
                                        and observation as a minister in Her Majesty’s cabinet.</p>
                                    <p>On the 14th of January Her Majesty prorogued the Legislature,
                                        with the usual ceremony pertaining to such occasion. It was
                                        noted that the foreign members of <pb facs="0500" n="494" xml:id="pg_494"/> the Legislature absented themselves as
                                        an expression of their disapproval and opposition to the
                                        cabinet, thereby indicating their threatening attitude
                                        against the Government and giving color to the rumors, which
                                        already, then, had reached us, that the reform party was
                                        conspiring to take some steps to, if possible, recover their
                                        lost power. After prorogation Her Majesty informed the
                                        cabinet that she wished to see them at the palace, and we
                                        responded to her order at about 1:30 p.m. After our arrival
                                        the Queen stated to us that, at the request of some 8,000 of
                                        her native subjects, she had decided to promulgate a new
                                        constitution, in which the grievances of her petitioning
                                        subjects would be remedied, and she asked us to sign the
                                        document with her. We all declined to become a party to this
                                        move and refused to comply with her request, and we
                                        earnestly advised her to give up her intention, although we
                                        were well aware that more than two-thirds of the electors of
                                        the country were in favor of the change, and that nearly all
                                        the representatives in the Legislature were elected on a
                                        platform in which the main plank was a new constitution.
                                        However, after talking with her and explaining the
                                        impossibility of taking such a step, she admitted that we
                                        were in the right, although calling our attention to the
                                        precedent which the Reform party had created by the
                                        revolutionary constitution which was promulgated in
                                        1887.</p>
                                    <p>The Queen then told the people’s delegates, who were
                                        assembled in the throne room, that she could not grant their
                                        request at this time, but asked them all to return home
                                        quietly and await in peace the time when a proper course
                                        could be adopted to carry out the will of the people. The
                                        people dispersed quietly, and in a short time there were no
                                        Hawaiians in the palace grounds. A few remarks were made by
                                        the Hon. William White, the representative for Lahaina, to
                                        the effect that, while the people regretted the Queen’s
                                        inability to grant the wishes of the people, they would
                                        accept the assurances of the Queen and await the proper
                                        time, which, if they were successful at the next election to
                                        be held, would be at the meeting of the Legislature in 1894.
                                        The insurgents have falsely reported the remarks of Mr.
                                        White, and in their press and otherwise represented him as
                                        making an incendiary and threatening speech. The falsehood
                                        of such statement, well known, to us who were witnesses at
                                        the scene, will shortly be proven in the courts of justice,
                                        as Mr. White has retained counsel for the purpose of
                                        bringing a damage suit for malicious libel against the
                                        Pacific Commercial Advertiser, the principal organ of the
                                        reform party. Saturday evening and night were as peaceful
                                        and quiet as at any other time, but the conspirators were at
                                        work.</p>
                                    <p>On Sunday morning, January 15, Mr. Thurston, the head of the
                                        revolutionary party, called on my colleagues, Ministers Col
                                        burn and Peterson, and asked them to join with himself and
                                        others in deposing the Queen, assuring them that such
                                        movement would be perfectly safe, as Minister Stevens had
                                        promised them the support of the United States forces and
                                        also that he would recognize and support a provisional
                                        government as soon as such a step could be taken. My
                                        colleagues naturally refused to entertain the infamous
                                        proposition of Mr. Thurston, and immediately communicated
                                        with myself and Minister Parker. The cabinet held several
                                        consultations with leading citizens of known loyalty to the
                                        Queen, and, knowing the strength of our forces, we felt
                                        confident that we easily could cope with any insurrection of
                                        the few malcontents.</p>
                                    <p>On Monday, the 16th, we were informed that the conspirators
                                        had decided to establish a revolutionary government, giving
                                        as a reason that Her Majesty had attempted to violate the
                                        constitution, but the cabinet still felt sure that no such
                                        attempt could succeed if the insurgents depended on their
                                        own forces. The cabinet then advised the Queen to issue a
                                        proclamation to the people, in. which she explained her
                                        reasons for desiring to promulgate a new constitution, and
                                        at the same time assured them that she would not make any
                                        further attempt or proposition to gain that object. This was
                                        done, and at 11 a.m. the proclamation was printed and
                                        distributed all over town. Assurances to a similar end were
                                        also sent to the foreign representatives and accepted as
                                        satisfactory. In the afternoon two mass meetings took place,
                                        one at the armory, where the actions so far taken by the
                                        so-called safety committee were indorsed, and one on Palace
                                        square, where the proclamation of the Queen was accepted and
                                        responded to in a resolution.</p>
                                    <p>I will here state that of the large number of citizens who
                                        gathered at the armory meeting, perhaps not fifty understood
                                        or desired that any further steps should or would be taken.
                                        Of this I have been assured by a number of prominent
                                        citizens with whom I am on terms of friendship, although
                                        differing with them politically, and who went to that
                                        meeting simply for the purpose of giving a public expression
                                        that the community disapproved of the step which the Queen
                                        had desired to take, and who believed that the matter would
                                        be dropped right there. The issue of the Queen’s
                                        proclamation was done after a consultation which the cabinet
                                        held Monday morning with the foreign representatives. We
                                        stated to the members of the corps diplomatique, who were
                                        present, what we intended to do, and were told that it was
                                        considered a wise step which they believed would be
                                        satisfactory. Present at the consultation were the
                                        representatives of England, France, Japan, and Portugal. <pb facs="0501" n="495" xml:id="pg_495"/> Minister Stevens
                                        declined to be present, which did not surprise us, knowing
                                        his sympathy for the revolutionists. At about 4 p.m. we were
                                        informed that the United States forces were landing.</p>
                                    <p>Ministers Parker and Peterson immediately called upon
                                        Minister Stevens and gave him to understand that the
                                        Government was perfectly able to take care of the situation,
                                        and requested him to keep the troops on board. He answered
                                        that he had landed the troops for the protection of American
                                        life and property and proposed to keep them ashore. The
                                        troops then marched up by the palace, passed as far out on
                                        King street as the residence of Mr. J. B. Atherton, a
                                        distance of about 600 yards, and later on returned and
                                        quartered for the night in the Arion hall, a building
                                        opposite the government building and the palace. It is
                                        noteworthy that the Arion hail and all the buildings in the
                                        immediate vicinity are not American property, so if the
                                        troops were landed solely for the protection of American
                                        property, the placing of them so far away from the center of
                                        the property of Americans and so very close to the property
                                        of the Hawaiian Government was remarkable and very
                                        suggestive.</p>
                                    <p>On Tuesday, the 17th, we were informed that the insurgents
                                        would proclaim a provisional government in the afternoon,
                                        and the cabinet called upon Minister Stevens, asking him if
                                        he would afford any assistance to the legal and lawful
                                        Government of the country to which he was accredited in case
                                        that such assistance should be required. He refused in
                                        unmistakable terms, and made us understand that he should
                                        acknowledge and support the revolutionary government as soon
                                        as it was established. We then proceeded to the station
                                        house, where we held a council of war. Our forces were
                                        enthusiastic, and volunteers enrolled so rapidly that it
                                        became necessary to close the doors of the station house. A
                                        little after 3 o’clock p.m. we were informed that a handful
                                        of citizens had entered the government building and that a
                                        proclamation had been read claiming that a provisional
                                        government had been established and that the Queen was
                                        deposed, and also that the United States forces, under
                                        command of Capt. Wiitse, were marched up ready for action,
                                        with sharp loaded cannon and guns.</p>
                                    <p>The Government had decided not to place forces in the
                                        Government building, as the immediate vicinity of the United
                                        States troops would endanger the lives of the men from the
                                            <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> in case of a conflict with
                                        the rebels, and the Government desired, at all hazards, to
                                        avoid giving Minister Stevens any excuse or pretense for his
                                        hostile actions. After the information relating to the
                                        establishing of the Provisional Government had been received
                                        the cabinet wrote a letter from the station house to
                                        Minister Stevens and sent it to him by Mr. Charles Hopkins,
                                        a noble of the Legislature. The letter was a request to the
                                        American minister to inform the Queen’s Government if he
                                        intended to recognize or support the lawful Government or
                                        the revolutionary government, which it was claimed was in
                                        existence. Mr. Stevens received the letter, and, through his
                                        daughter, informed Mr. Hopkins that he would answer it in
                                        due time. Mr. Hopkins demanded, cautiously but firmly, an
                                        immediate answer, and after considerable waiting a letter
                                        was handed to him addressed to His Excellency Samuel Parker,
                                        Minister of Foreign Affairs, in which Mr. Stevens stated
                                        that he had recognized the Provisional Government because
                                        they were in possession of the Government building, and that
                                        he intended to support them.</p>
                                    <p>We realized then that any steps from our side to dislodge and
                                        arrest the rebels would unavoidably lead us into a conflict
                                        with the United States forces, and we decided to surrender
                                        to the Provisional Government with the full understanding
                                        that such surrender was under protest, the United States
                                        Government to decide if the action of their minister and the
                                        use of their forces to destroy a friendly Government was
                                        justifiable and according to American principles. The
                                        conference between the Provisional Government was carried on
                                        by Mr. S. M. Damon on their behalf and the cabinet on behalf
                                        of the Queen. Other stipulations were agreed upon, the
                                        Provisional Government showing itself ready to promise
                                        anything so long as a fight could be avoided, but all such
                                        stipulations and promises were totally ignored after the
                                        surrender was made. It was after 7 o’clock p.m. when finally
                                        the arms and ammunition of the Queen’s Government were
                                        turned over to the Provisional Government, or about three
                                        hours after Minister Stevens had acknowledged that he had
                                        recognized the revolutionary government.</p>
                                    <p>As a man who, for years, has taken an active part in Hawaiian
                                        politics, and as a practical sugar planter of many years’
                                        experience, it is not difficult for me to realize the true
                                        cause for the late revolution and for the subsequent desire
                                        for annexation. The depression in the sugar business which,
                                        since the passage of the McKinley bill, has made havoc with
                                        the handsome dividends which we have enjoyed since 1875 and
                                        the loss of power by the reform party were the only and true
                                        reasons for the revolution. The prospects of the sugar
                                        bounty was and is the main motive for the desire to be
                                        annexed on the part of the handful of responsible men who
                                        still desire such step to be taken. That such plans were
                                        fully in accord with the policy of the late American
                                        Government, from which Mr. Stevens received his
                                        instructions, was the only reason why the scheme became
                                        feasible. The very idea of losing their independence as a
                                        nation is distasteful to the Hawaiians, and I say
                                        unhesitatingly, <pb facs="0502" n="496" xml:id="pg_496"/>
                                        although I am an American citizen, to a large contingent of
                                        the foreign residents here.</p>
                                    <p>The Queen’s attempt to give a new constitution is not the
                                        only reason which is given by the insurgents as an excuse
                                        for the revolution. The passage of the lottery bill and the
                                        opium license bill has also been used both by Mr. Stevens
                                        and the insurgents as extenuating circumstances. I opposed
                                        and voted against the lottery bill, although it was a
                                        measure of my party, because I do not believe in the
                                        principle of such a law. But the measure was favored and
                                        supported by nearly all the Americans in Honolulu, the very
                                        men who revolted and who now claim that the lottery was the
                                        cause of the revolution.</p>
                                    <p>On the day of the prorogation of the Legislature Minister
                                        Stevens returned to town, after a visit to Hawaii, too late
                                        to be present at the ceremony of the prorogation, but he
                                        called at the Government building where he saw Minister
                                        Parker and myself. After having made his excuses for not
                                        attending the prorogation he asked if the Queen had signed
                                        the lottery bill. Answered in the affimative, he became very
                                        excited, and striking the table with his clenched fist he
                                        exclaimed, over and over again: “Gentlemen, this is a direct
                                        attack on the United States Government.” I told him that the
                                        Queen had signed the bill because the measure seemed to be
                                        the wish of the people, and that the petitions favoring the
                                        bill from Honolulu contained a large number of names of
                                        prominent and responsible men, and although I was personally
                                        opposed to the bill I did not consider it justifiable for
                                        the cabinet to advise the Queen to veto it.</p>
                                    <p>The opium license act I consider a wise measure, and as an
                                        employer of a large number of men I claim that the regular
                                        sale of opium is of greater advantage to all classes than
                                        the prohibition of it, which no government can enforce owing
                                        to the facility for smuggling offered by the large territory
                                        of coast on the islands. The opium license law was passed
                                        not alone as a revenue measure, but for the purpose of
                                        checking the wholesale corruption which the smuggling of the
                                        drug carried with it, and was, if anything, a measure in
                                        favor of the morality of the country rather than a measure
                                        of corruption. The bill was supported by many of the leading
                                        men in the present Government and also by many planters,
                                        irrespective of political sentiments or party.</p>
                                    <p>In concluding this statement I wish to call attention to the
                                        fact that Minister J. L. Stevens, in one of his official
                                        dispatches to Secretary Foster, now published, has expressed
                                        himself to the effect that I am entertaining feelings of
                                        hostility and enmity towards him. I am not aware of ever
                                        having given Mr. Stevens any reason for making such an
                                        assertion, which is utterly without foundation, and I only
                                        call the attention to the matter to avoid a possible
                                        impression that anything which I have here stated should be
                                        construed as biased or influenced by any private motives or
                                        the result of any alleged unfriendly relations with the
                                        American minister.</p>
                                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wm. H.
                                            Cornwell.</hi></signed></closer>
                                </frus:attachment>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in No.
                                        3.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Colburn</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Blount</persName>.</hi></head>
                                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Honolulu</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-04-15"><hi rend="italic">April 15,
                                            1893</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As a member of Her Majesty
                                        Liliuokalani’s cabinet that was deposed with her by a
                                        handful of citizens backed by the troops of the good ship
                                            <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> of the U. S. Navy, I
                                        called on you on the evening of Saturday, April 8, and paid
                                        my respects to you. You received me kindly, and during our
                                        conversation you asked me to prepare for you a statement of
                                        the facts connected with the Hawaiian revolution and all
                                        that was incident to it, and other important matters <hi rend="italic">in re</hi> Hawaii, from my own knowledge
                                        and observation.</p>
                                    <p>In response to your request I submit to you the following,
                                        trusting that it may be of value to you in summing up your
                                        conclusions in all that has happened, and the position of
                                        Queen Liliuokalani and the Hawaiian people.</p>
                                    <p>In opening up my statement, I desire first to introduce
                                        myself thoroughly to yon, so that you will recognize at once
                                        that I propose to take the responsibility of all that I
                                        write, and will produce to the extent of my ability, all
                                        such evidence as you may require, to corroborate what I
                                        write should you so desire it.</p>
                                    <p>My name in full is John Francis Colburn. I was born on the
                                        30th day of September, 1859; my father was an American and
                                        my mother a Hawaiian. My father died when I was but 2 years
                                        of age, and I, with my brother and sister, was brought up by
                                        my mother, who labored and toiled for our support with a
                                        sewing machine. I have received the whole of my education
                                        right here and have never traveled further than beyond San
                                        Francisco, Cal., when my presence was called there on
                                        business, and I made four different trips to that large
                                        city. At the age of 16 years I entered <pb facs="0503" n="497" xml:id="pg_497"/> into employment, receiving
                                        such from the firm of Lewers &amp; Cooke, the latter being
                                        one of the commissioners of the Provisional Government who
                                        went to Washington to secure annexation. At the age of 20
                                        years I was married, and have living to-day five children;
                                        for the last seven years I have conducted a large hay,
                                        grain, and feed business on my own account, and am still
                                        following that pursuit. I omitted to mention that I had a
                                        large number of relatives on my father’s side residing in
                                        different parts of the United States, chief among them being
                                        the husband of my father’s own sister, J. H. Gans, residing
                                        in Red Bud, Ill., a strong Democrat and an applicant to
                                        President Cleveland for the position of American minister to
                                        this country in place of J. L. Stevens. My great
                                        grandfather, Thomas Colburn, was the first man killed at the
                                        battle of Bunker Hill in 1775, fighting as a patriotic
                                        American.</p>
                                    <p>Liliuokalani was proclaimed Queen of the Hawaiian Islands
                                        January 29, 1891; her first cabinet had Mr. Samuel Parker as
                                        premier; he and his colleagues were voted out by a
                                        resolution of want of confidence, introduced by Mr. W. C.
                                        Wilder, one of the commissioners to Washington to seek
                                        annexation. After they were voted out the Queen appointed
                                        and commissioned a cabinet with E. C. Macfarlane as premier;
                                        they reported to the legislature and immediately upon sight
                                        L. A. Thurston moved an adjournment for two days. After
                                        adjournment, and when the members had taken their seats, W.
                                        O. Smith, the present attorney-general of the Provisional
                                        Government, introduced a resolution of want of confidence.
                                        After a long and heated discussion a vote was taken, and
                                        only twenty-four members responded to adopting the
                                        resolution; it was only lost to be resurrected again at
                                        another day. Time rolled on, and two weeks after another
                                        resolution of want of confidence was introduced against this
                                        same cabinet, but this time, through the intrigue of
                                        Thurston and his party, it was brought in and read by a
                                        native member. A vote was taken and a sufficient number of
                                        votes were cast to oust them.</p>
                                    <p>They retired and the Queen, appointed another cabinet, of
                                        which W. H. Cornwell was premier. This cabinet, as soon as
                                        it presented itself to the house, was voted out on sight;
                                        the reason of it was, that the intrigue was worked so well
                                        on some of the native members of the legislature by paying
                                        them bribes and a weekly support, that they agreed with
                                        Thurston and his faction to vote out any cabinet the Queen
                                        chose to send to the legislature, unless it be a certain
                                        four of their own party, who they wanted to get in as the
                                        cabinet, and control the affairs of the country. The funds
                                        put up for this purpose was partly by S. M. Damon and C.
                                        Bolte, also by Mr. H. P. Baldwin, a large sugar plantation
                                        owner. When the Cornwell cabinet was voted out the Queen was
                                        puzzled as to what to do. She looked upon this reform party,
                                        who was doing all this work, as bringing about a conflict
                                        with her and the legislature; this reform party wanted to
                                        dictate to the Queen who the cabinet should be, and she, on
                                        the other hand, did not wish to recognize them to that
                                        extent, because the whole of the opposition, who had been
                                        voting cabinets out, were a mixture of three different
                                        political parties, and she was well informed that bribery
                                        was at the bottom of the whole affair.</p>
                                    <p>She stood the Legislature off for a week or ten days; in the
                                        meantime she asked several well-to-do conservative business
                                        men to consult with her as to what course she should pursue,
                                        and considerable advice was given her to make the
                                        appointments of the persons whom the reform party was
                                        clamoring for, so as to bring about quiet and contentment in
                                        the business community, who was worked up to a certain pitch
                                        about the fact that the only work the Legislature was doing
                                        was to oust cabinets, and it was affecting business. The
                                        Queen paid heed to this advice given, and commissioned what
                                        was known as the Wilcox or the missionary cabinet. They
                                        reported to the Legislature, and to show you that they were
                                        not a popular cabinet, twenty-five members were ready to
                                        vote them right out, and it was only through the influence
                                        of some of us that the resolution was not introduced then,
                                        so that this cabinet could have a fair trial. It staid in
                                        power two months when, on the 12th day of January, 1893, a
                                        resolution was introduced and they were voted out. The
                                        reform party or the missionaries, as they are better named
                                        and called, were disgruntled and dissatisfied and
                                        discouraged at this work, and openly said we will get even
                                        with you, meaning the Hawaiians. They knew this vote meant
                                        their losing their power and influence in this country for
                                        years to come, and they were hostile. However, the majority
                                        of the people were satisfied that they were voted out, and
                                        looked to the prospects of the Queen appointing a cabinet
                                        with at least two Hawaiians in it, so that the race
                                        prejudice which had been created for quite a while would
                                        wear away and the Hawaians and foreigners would work
                                        together; the Queen also realized this matter as of great
                                        importance, and on Friday, January 13, 1893, she summoned
                                        and appointed the writer, minister of interior; Samuel
                                        Parker, minister of foreign affairs; W. H. Cornwell,
                                        minister of finance, and A. P. Peterson, attorney-general;
                                        the first two of us being the Hawaiian representation and
                                        the last two the foreign.</p>
                                    <p>We repaired to the Legislature who was waiting for the
                                        Queen’s new cabinet, and as this cabinet approached the
                                        Government building from the palace the former was thronged
                                        with people who were anxious to see the new cabinet and
                                        extend their <pb facs="0504" n="498" xml:id="pg_498"/>
                                        congratulations to us. That was a scene that has never
                                        before been witnessed upon the appointment of former
                                        cabinets; however, we arrived at the Legislature and amidst
                                        great cheering we took our seats. The house went through its
                                        work and then adjourned. The next day was the time that had
                                        been previously set for proroguing the Legislature. At 10
                                        o’clock of that day, January 14, 1893, Mr Peterson informed
                                        me that he had heard it rumored that it was the Queen’s
                                        intention to promulgate a new constitution. I replied to him
                                        that she was making a mistake and I would oppose her if she
                                        really intended to do it. I called out to Messrs. Parker and
                                        Cornwell, and the four of us consulted over the matter. We
                                        all agreed that if the Queen was determined upon doing this
                                        work, and pleasing only the native element, we would oppose
                                        her. Mr. Parker went over at once to the palace to find out
                                        correctly if there was any truth to this rumor, but he was
                                        unable to see her, as she was preparing herself to prorogue
                                        the Legislature. He returned and informed us that he could
                                        not see her, and we decided to wait until the closing of
                                        Parliament.</p>
                                    <p>In the meantime, however, I felt as though we should place
                                        ourselves in the right light before the foreign element of
                                        the community, and to get their view on the matter in case
                                        the Queen’s intentions were really as rumored and she would
                                        make it an issue with us, I left my colleagues at the
                                        Government building and repaired at once with all haste to
                                        the office of A. S. Hartwell, an old and esteemed friend of
                                        mine, and told him about the rumor we had heard, the
                                        consultation we had had, and the position we would take if
                                        the Queen could not be guided by our advice, and that was to
                                        resign. He asked me if he could ask Messrs. Thurston and
                                        Smith (the Provisional Government commissioner at Washington
                                        and the present attorney-general of the Provisional
                                        Government) to be together with him, and we would all
                                        consult the matter over together. I consented and he
                                        summoned them. When they arrived I went over what I had told
                                        Mr. Hartwell a short time previous and when I got through
                                        Thurston spoke up and said, “Colburn, don’t you resign under
                                        any conditions; if the Queen makes this an issue with you,
                                        we (meaning the foreign element) will back you up and I feel
                                        sure Minister Stevens will.” He further asked, are you alone
                                        in your stand?” and I replied, “no, I was positive Peterson
                                        took the same view as I did.” He spoke up again, “bring
                                        Peterson down here; we want to talk to him.”</p>
                                    <p>I repaired at once to the Government building, told Peterson
                                        what I had done, and asked him to come down to Hartwell’s
                                        office with me. He consented, and we both came down. Upon
                                        arriving there we held a consultation. Thurston submitted in
                                        writing a plan for action in case the Queen was going to
                                        carry out her desire. We took the document, which was
                                        written by Thurston himself, and told him we would await
                                        developments. We then left them and went to the Government
                                        building. This was now approaching the noon hour. At 12 m.,
                                        precisely, the Queen arrived at the Government building and
                                        prorogued the Legislature. Immediately after the Queen had
                                        left to return to the palace, Mr. Parker came up and said to
                                        us that the diplomatic corps wanted to have an interview
                                        with us at once in the foreign affairs office. We all
                                        consented and went directly upstairs to meet them.</p>
                                    <p>After we were all seated, Mr. Wodehouse opened the
                                        conversation by asking us if we knew that a knew
                                        constitution was to be promulgated that afternoon by the
                                        Queen? Mr. Parke? replied that the cabinet were not aware of
                                        it, but they had heard rumors of it; he asked again what
                                        position the cabinet would take if the Queen did attempt to
                                        promulgate a new constitution, and Mr. Parker replied that
                                        the cabinet would oppose it. The conversation then drifted
                                        into their inquiring as to what reason could prompt the
                                        Queen to do anything like this, if the rumors that they and
                                        ourselves had heard were true, and we answered that it must
                                        be from the petition the natives had got up, signed, and
                                        presented to her. Mr. Wodehouse then said the Queen must not
                                        promulgate a new constitution, and if she had any idea of it
                                        she must abandon it. We assured him we would do all in our
                                        power to avoid anything of this kind happening. During all
                                        this conversation Mr. J. L. Stevens, who had kept perfectly
                                        quiet, not saying anything, spoke up now and asked if the
                                        Queen had signed the lottery bill? Mr. Parker replied in the
                                        affirmative; he asked again, did the cabinet advise the
                                        Queen to sign it? Mr. Peterson replied that the Queen
                                        considered that the bill having passed the Legislature by a
                                        majority the should sign it as she had no reason for vetoing
                                        it, and the cabinet acquiesced in her action. Mr. Stevens
                                        instantly raised his cane and stamped it on the floor and
                                        said the passing of the lottery bill and the signing of it
                                        by the Queen is a direct attack upon the United States; and
                                        he picked up his hat and walked out of the room, but before
                                        he was fairly out he spoke up and said, he wanted the
                                        cabinet to inform him at once if the Queen was going to
                                        attempt what we had a little while before discussed; we
                                        replied to him that we would, and we parted company.</p>
                                    <p>The cabinet then went directly from the Government building
                                        to the palace where there was in waiting the Queen, members
                                        of the legislature, members of several political societies,
                                        and a large number of the public. Upon our arrival at the
                                        palace we entered the blue room and met the Queen. After
                                        seating ourselves she said to us that she had received a
                                        petition signed by nine thousand of her native subjects
                                        asking <pb facs="0505" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/> her for a
                                        new constitution; and she thought this was an opportune time
                                        to grant them their prayer and asked us to countersign her
                                        signature that she wanted to place on the document. Each one
                                        of us got up, one after the other, and told her that we
                                        could not accede to her wishes, and advised her to abandon
                                        the idea. She was very determined at first, and said she
                                        should promulgate it anyway. We reasoned with her and left
                                        her to think the matter over again, and at the same time
                                        take rest.</p>
                                    <p>Messrs. Cornwell, Peterson, and myself left the palace and
                                        went to the Government building; we held a consultation and
                                        sent a message to each of the diplomatic corps; they all
                                        arrived and we entered into consultation again. The
                                        gentlemen of the diplomatic corps urged us very strongly to
                                        return to the palace and inform Her Majesty that she must
                                        abandon the idea at once. While this was going on at the
                                        Government building, Thurston and others who had heard of
                                        this matter were enrolling names down town with the avowed
                                        object of supporting the Cabinet in their positions and the
                                        stand they had taken. Thurston then came up to me and said
                                        to oppose the Queen’s intention as the foreign element of
                                        the community did not want a new constitution, and we could
                                        receive support, all that we wanted, even if it was
                                        necessary to depose her. At 3 o’clock, of that day we left
                                        the Government building again, and started over to the
                                        palace as the Queen had just sent us a message she wanted to
                                        see us at once.</p>
                                    <p>As we were hurrying over there, and just before I had got out
                                        of the gate at the entrance of the Government building yard,
                                        W. O. Smith, the present attorney-general, came rushing in
                                        in a hack very much excited, and said, Colburn, don’t be
                                        alarmed; buck the Queen all you can; the troops of the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> will assist in supporting you
                                        in your stand; make all the haste you can. Mr. Stevens has
                                        sent an order to the captain of the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>, and his men with their guns and ammunition
                                        are already in the boats of the ship ready to come ashore at
                                        once.” I made no reply to him except telling him we were
                                        then on our way to the palace. He left me and I sung out to
                                        my colleagues, and told them what Smith had said to me. We
                                        arrived at the palace, and the Queen, who was waiting for
                                        us, asked us if we would read the new constitution she
                                        wanted to promulgate, and compare it with the one forced
                                        upon the late King Kalakaua by the Reform party in the
                                        revolution of 1887, and also the one promulgated by
                                        Kamehameha V in 1864. We replied that we would, sat down,
                                        and after comparing it we found some defects in it and
                                        pointed them out to her and advised her again to abandon the
                                        idea. After a little while she spoke up, and asked us if we
                                        were a unit in our advice, and we all replied yes. She then
                                        said she would pay heed to it and would inform her people
                                        who were still waiting, that she could not give them what
                                        they wanted, and to endure their grievances (this implied to
                                        the Constitution of 1887). She did so, and the people
                                        departed for their homes.</p>
                                    <p>Mr. Peterson and myself went down town to the office of W. O.
                                        Smith, where there was a large gathering of the foreigners,
                                        and they asked me to speak to them. I did so and told them
                                        all that happened; some of them asked if we did not think
                                        the Queen would promulgate it at some other time, and I
                                        assured them we would never allow her to do it as long as
                                        the people who lived here were not a unit on such a Subject.
                                        A little later about 4:30 p.m. of that day, Mr. Thurston
                                        came to me with a document written out by him and said,
                                        “Colburn, this is a request on Minister Stevens and Capt.
                                        Wiltse to land the troops from the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> and render you support; you and Peterson
                                        and Cornwell must sign it and place it in my hands so that
                                        in case you are imprisoned by the Queen’s orders that she
                                        can put this project of hers through, then this letter can
                                        be delivered.” I replied to him that I did not think it was
                                        necessary, as I felt sure the Queen had abandoned the idea
                                        altogether; he insisted on my taking it, and I took it and
                                        handed it to Peterson; where it now is I do not know, but we
                                        never signed it, as there was no reason for it.</p>
                                    <p>The next morning, Sunday, January 15, 1893 at 6 a.m.,
                                        Thurston came to my house and asked me to go with him to
                                        Peterson’s house. I asked him what he wanted with us at such
                                        an early hour, and his reply was, pressing business. I
                                        consented and accompanied him to Peterson’s house. Upon our
                                        arriving there we entered the room, and when we were seated,
                                        the three of us, he said that he represented a committee of
                                        safety who had had a meeting at his house on Saturday
                                        evening and decided to send him to us with a proposition,
                                        and that was that we, Peterson and Colburn, should depose
                                        the Queen. We asked him who this committee of safety was,
                                        and he replied thirteen gentlemen picked out from all those
                                        that had enrolled to support the cabinet in opposing the
                                        Queen against her desires <hi rend="italic">in re</hi> new
                                        constitution. We asked him to furnish their names and he did
                                        so. He then said, it is the desire of this committee you two
                                        should depose the Queen and declare a provisional
                                        government. Don’t say a word about it to Parker and
                                        Cornwell, as Parker is a treacherous liar, and Cornwell is
                                        not fit for anything, and simply does what Parker tells him
                                        to do. He went on to say that it was their desire to get a
                                        division in the cabinet, and the deposing of the Queen
                                        should appear to be done by a part of her own cabinet, or a
                                        portion of the Goverment itself; and he went on to say that
                                        he could inform us that <pb facs="0506" n="500" xml:id="pg_500"/> Mr. Stevens had given this committee
                                        the assurance that if we two signed a request to him to land
                                        the troops of the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> he would
                                        immediately comply with the request and have them landed to
                                        assist in carrying out this work; and further, that if we
                                        did not agree to the proposition that we could not receive
                                        aid and support from them in the future if we needed it. We
                                        told him that we would have to take the matter under
                                        advisement and would inform him as to our conclusions later
                                        on. He pressed for an answer then, hut we refused to give it
                                        to him.</p>
                                    <p>After his departure we sent for Parker and Cornwell, and
                                        imparted to them what Thurston had proposed to us, and we
                                        entered into consultation. We decided to summon at least six
                                        responsible and conservative business men of the community
                                        to consult with us, and to get their views. We did so, and,
                                        at 1:30 p.m. of that Sunday, the following gentlemen met us:
                                        Messrs. F. A. Schaeffer, J. O. Carter, S. M. Damon, W. M.
                                        Giffard, S. C. Allen, and E. C. Macfarlane. We told them
                                        what Thurston, on behalf of the committee of thirteen, had
                                        proposed, and asked them for their views. Each one asked if
                                        the Queen had given up the idea of promulgating a new
                                        constitution altogether, and we replied in the affirmative.
                                        They said, in that case the Queen and cabinet should issue a
                                        proclamation, giving the community the assurance that this
                                        matter was at an end.</p>
                                    <p>We asked them to dictate a proclamation and they did so; they
                                        one and all decided that we should inform this committee
                                        that we could not consider their proposition, and ask them
                                        to accept the assurances that were to be given in the
                                        proclamation. They also asked if the Government was in a
                                        position to suppress any uprising, and we told these
                                        gentlemen that the Government was ready and able to cope
                                        with any emergency that might happen, and to suppress any
                                        revolt. Mr. S. M. Damon spoke up and said the troops of the
                                            “<hi rend="italic">Boston</hi>” are going to be landed.
                                        Before proceeding further, I may say right here that Mr.
                                        Damon’s remark seemed insignificant at the time, but as
                                        things turned out he was in with the revolutionists and knew
                                        perfectly well the attitude af Mr. Stevens, and when he made
                                        the remark at our meeting it signified a good deal; it meant
                                        that those forces were going to depose Queen Liliuokalani
                                        and place the situation of the country in the position that
                                        it is in to-day.</p>
                                    <p>The next day (Monday) the proclamation dictated by these
                                        gentlemen was printed and posted and distributed all over
                                        town. Later on in the day two mass meetings were held, one
                                        by the native element and the other by the foreign element.
                                        At the former the natives accepted the proclamation,
                                        although it was directly contrary to what they wanted (a new
                                        constitution), and the latter denounced the Queen and left
                                        everything in the hands of the committee of safety spoken
                                        about. At 5 p.m. of that day the troops of the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> were landed. Immediately upon
                                        the information being conveyed to the cabinet that such was
                                        the case, Mr. Parker and myself drove with all haste to the
                                        residence of J. L. Stevens. When we arrived there, we asked
                                        him the reason the troops were being landed, and his reply
                                        was that he had received a request from a committee of
                                        safety, and he had consulted with Capt, Wiltse. He went on
                                        to say that there were a number of women and old men in the
                                        town besides children that were alarmed with the rumors of a
                                        revolution, and he wanted to offer protection. Mr. Parker
                                        replied that the Government was in a position to offer
                                        everyone protection, was able to suppress any rebellion, and
                                        would offer protection to him (Stevens) and noted his
                                        protest. Mr. Stevens replied that he was informed that the
                                        Government <hi rend="italic">was</hi> in a strong position
                                        to suppress any revolt, but he could not help the matter of
                                        landing, and as the troops were ashore they would stay
                                        ashore. I asked him if he intended to annex the country and
                                        he replied “No,” and further said those troops are ashore to
                                        preserve the Queen on her throne, you gentlemen in your
                                        offices, and to offer protection to the community at large.
                                        We fold him again we did not want the troops ashore, and we
                                        could preserve law and order ourselves. He replied by saying
                                        make your protest in writing, and if you make it in a
                                        friendly spirit I will answer in the same tone.</p>
                                    <p>On Tuesday information was conveyed to us that the Queen was
                                        to be deposed and a Provisional Government declared; we got
                                        everything in readiness to suppress the revolt expected; we
                                        had under arms 600 men with rifles, and 30,000 rounds of
                                        ammunition, 8 brass Austrian field cannon, and 2 Gatling
                                        guns. A little before 2 p.m. of that day the cabinet drove
                                        up to Mr. Stevens’s residence to inquire of him as to the
                                        position he was going to take in this matter, as we were
                                        informed and suspected from ail that Thurston and his
                                        followers had said that the American troops were going to
                                        assist these usurpers, who everyone knew would not attempt
                                        to bring about any such change as they were going to if they
                                        were not assured of support by the American forces. We
                                        arrived at Stevens’s house and after talking quite awhile
                                        with him he gave us no definite answer and we left him and
                                        returned to the police station to make our headquarters
                                        there and to write to Mr. Stevens about his position. While
                                        the letter to Stevens was being dictated by Mr. Peterson,
                                        information was brought to us that about 30 unarmed men had
                                        taken possession of the Government Building, had read their
                                        proclamation, and had committed acts of treason.</p>
                                    <p>We paid no attention to them but sent our letter with all
                                        haste at a few minutes before 3 p.m., by Mr. C. L. Hopkins
                                        to Mr. Stevens. After Stevens read the letter, <pb facs="0507" n="501" xml:id="pg_501"/> he told Hopkins to
                                        go away and come back again in an hour. Hopkins replied that
                                        the cabinet had instructed him to bring a reply forthwith,
                                        so that they would know how to act, and Stevens refused. He
                                        kept Hopkins waiting on his veranda one hour and then handed
                                        him a reply to us. While Stevens was keeping Hopkins
                                        waiting, the usurpers were preparing to resist the
                                        Government in case of attack, and we did nothing, but kept
                                        our men ready for action. The letter from Stevens carried by
                                        Hopkins to us reached us 5 minutes of 4 p.m., and after
                                        reading its contents, we concluded to surrender and yield to
                                        America.</p>
                                    <p>I want to impress upon you that we never surrendered the
                                        palace, police station, and barracks till after we had
                                        received Stevens’s letter, and not until we had filed our
                                        protest with the Provisional Government. The surrender was a
                                        little after 6 in the evening; these usurpers could never
                                        have overthrown the Government, as they did not have
                                        sufficient arms and ammunition; and on the other hand, it
                                        will be admitted by themselves, I think, that the munitions
                                        of war that we had would have annihilated them were it not
                                        for the United States troops and Minister Stevens.</p>
                                    <p>I remain, etc.,</p>
                                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John F.
                                            Colburn.</hi></signed></closer>
                                </frus:attachment>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 7 in No.
                                        3.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss type="from">Citizens’ committee
                                                of safety</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Stevens</persName>.</hi></head>
                                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Hawaiian Islands</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Honolulu</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-16"><hi rend="italic">January 16,
                                            1893.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: We, the undersigned citizens
                                        and residents of Honolulu, respectfully represent that, in
                                        view of recent public events in this Kingdom, culminating in
                                        the revolutionary acts of Queen Lilioukalani on Saturday
                                        last, the public safety is menaced, and lives and property
                                        are in peril, and we appeal to you and the United States
                                        forces at your command for assistance.</p>
                                    <p>The Queen, with the aid of armed force, and accompanied by
                                        threats of violence and bloodshed from those with whom she
                                        was acting, attempted to proclaim a new constitution; and,
                                        while prevented for the time from accomplishing her object,
                                        declared publicly that she would only defer her action.</p>
                                    <p>This conduct and action was upon an occasion and under
                                        circumstances which have created general alarm and
                                        terror.</p>
                                    <p>We are unable to protect ourselves without aid and therefore
                                        pray for the protection of the United States forces.</p>
                                    <closer><signed>
                                            <list>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry E.
                                                  Cooper</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">F. W.
                                                  McChesney</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">W. C. Wilder</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">C. Bolte</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">A. Brown</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">William O.
                                                  Smith</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry
                                                  Waterhouse</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Theo. F.
                                                  Lansing</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Ed. Suhr</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">L. A.
                                                  Thurston</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">John
                                                  Emmeluth</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Wm. R.
                                                  Castle</hi>,</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">J. A.
                                                  McCandless</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Citizens’
                                                  Committee of Safety.</hi></item>
                                            </list>
                                        </signed></closer>
                                </frus:attachment>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>