<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-05-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="256" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d256">
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blount</persName>
                                        to Mr. <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 8. <lb/> No. 5.]</seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Honolulu, Hawaiian
                                            Islands</hi></placeName>,<lb/><date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-05-06"><hi rend="italic">May 6,
                                            1893.</hi></date></dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Since my last dispatch I examined
                                    Mr. Bolte, a member of the advisory council. He and Mr.
                                    Waterhouse, whose evidence I forwarded to you, stated positively
                                    that the station house and barracks were <pb facs="0532" n="526" xml:id="pg_526"/> delivered up before Mr. Stevens recognized
                                    the Provisional Government. The manner of their testimony caused
                                    me to suspect their truthfulness. I had learned from members of
                                    the cabinet of the ex-Queen of correspondence with Mr. Stevens
                                    which contradicted these assertions. Some weeks ago I had called
                                    upon him for the legation records, and was furnished with a book
                                    containing correspondence with the State Department. This threw
                                    no light on the question of fact I was seeking to settle.</p>
                                <p>On the 5th instant I went to the legation, feeling that such
                                    papers must be there in some form.</p>
                                <p>In the conversation he spoke of a paper from the Queen which was
                                    in his files 5 said that these files were put in a volume when
                                    there were enough to make up one. I said I would like to have
                                    the volume for January. He said it had not been made up. I then
                                    asked him if he had a paper which the ministry had addressed to
                                    him inquiring if he had recognized the Provisional Government.
                                    He went out to look for it and returned with a book entitled
                                    “Correspondence with Hawaiian Government.” In this he showed me
                                    a memorandum he had made of a reply to a communication from the
                                    ministers, a copy of which I send (Inclosure No. 1).</p>
                                <p>Believing that he must have the communication itself, this
                                    morning I sent my secretary, Mr. Mills, to ask for it. He
                                    returned with the paper saying that before giving it to him Mr.
                                    Stevens seemed to be at a loss as to whether he had such a
                                    paper. This same difficulty occurred when I called upon him for
                                    the communication from the committee of safety asking for the
                                    landing of the troops of the <hi rend="italic">Boston.</hi></p>
                                <p>I inclose herewith a copy of the letter in question (Inclosure
                                    No. 2).</p>
                                <p>You will see that in the memorandum referred to he says the
                                    letter was received about 4 or 5 p.m. on January 17 and that he
                                    informed them that he had already recognized the Provisional
                                    Government.</p>
                                <p>In the conversation I had with him when he turned over the record
                                    of the correspondence with the Hawaiian Government he said he
                                    had recognized the Provisional Government before the barracks
                                    and station house had been surrendered, that he did not consider
                                    their surrender of any importance.</p>
                                <p>In my last dispatch Lieut. Swinburne fixes the surrender of the
                                    station house at about half-past 7 o’clock. This morning he
                                    called and informed me that Lieut. Draper had said to him
                                    yesterday that the station house was not surrendered until after
                                    dark. I sent for Lieut. Draper and obtained from him a
                                    statement, which I inclose (Inclosure No. 3).</p>
                                <p>I consider that it is now established beyond controversy that Mr.
                                    Stevens recognized the Provisional Government before the
                                    barracks and station house had been surrendered or agreed to be
                                    surrendered.</p>
                                <p>Before the committee of thirteen went up to proclaim the
                                    Provisional Government they sent a gentleman to see if there
                                    were any troops in the Government building. On learning the fact
                                    that there were none, the committee quietly went up in two or
                                    more squads and, uniting at the Government building, read their
                                    proclamation.</p>
                                <p>Without making any demand for the surrender of the palace, in
                                    which were the Queen and her friends, with some 50 soldiers; the
                                    barracks, a little beyond the palace, with about 80 men, well
                                    equipped with small arms and artillery, and with the station
                                    house, some 600 yards off, occupied by some 200 men, well armed
                                    and equipped, they asked and obtained from the American minister
                                    recognition as a Government <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>. On
                                    this basis the minds of the cabinet and Queen were operated upon
                                    to give up the barracks and station house <pb facs="0533" n="527" xml:id="pg_527"/> and to have her surrender to the
                                    Provisional Government. In this way the revolution reached its
                                    solution.</p>
                                <p>I invite your attention to a letter, dated on the 16th of
                                    January, 1893, from Mr. Stevens to Mr. W. M. Giffard, as
                                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">United States
                                                Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Honolulu,
                                                January 16, 1893</hi>.</p>
                                        <p rend="flushleft">Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">W. M.
                                                Giffard</hi>:</p>
                                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Please allow Capt. Wiltse
                                            and his men the use of the opera house hall for a fair
                                            compensation for the same.</p>
                                        <p>Yours, truly,</p>
                                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">John L.
                                            Stevens.</hi></p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>This letter was obtained from Mr. Giffard, who had charge of the
                                    building as agent for Spreckels &amp; Co. He declined to let Mr.
                                    Stevens have it, because, he said, if any damage occurred while
                                    the American troops occupied it it would affect the insurance,
                                    as the building was liable to be damaged; that in the
                                    insurrection of 1889, when Wilcox and his followers had obtained
                                    possession of the palace, the Government forces had used the
                                    upper portion of this building to fire on the insurrectionists
                                    and that more than $1,000 worth of damage was then done to it by
                                    the cannon used by Wilcox and his followers.</p>
                                <p>This building, Lieut. Swinburne informs me, was agreed upon on
                                    board the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> before the troops were
                                    landed as the best place for the location of the <hi rend="italic">Boston’s</hi> men. He suggested on shipboard
                                    that the troops be quartered near the wharf, so as to be near to
                                    their base of supply, the same having been so done when Admiral
                                    Skerrett landed troops in 1874. Capt. Wiltse and Mr. Stevens
                                    thought it was better that they should be located in the opera
                                    house. Failing to get this building, Arion hall, which is on a
                                    line with it and adjoins it, and is across the street from the
                                    Government building, was obtained for the location of the
                                    troops. The men were placed in the rear of Arion hall, but in
                                    full view of the palace. A street intervened between the
                                    Government building and the palace. It was about 350 yards from
                                    one of these buildings to the other.</p>
                                <p>The American troops were on the same side of the latter street
                                    with the Provisional Government troops, which did not probably
                                    number 100 men. You will see from the map prepared by Mr.
                                    Loevenstein, which I have previously forwarded to you, the
                                    location of Arion hall, the Government building, the palace, the
                                    barracks, the station house, and the armory. If the Queen’s
                                    troops should have attacked the Provisional Government troops
                                    our men were in danger of being injured, which might have
                                    brought them into collision with the Queen’s troops. The same is
                                    true if the Provisional Government troops had advanced on the
                                    palace. If the American troops were landed to protect American
                                    property and the persons of American citizens, their location at
                                    this place, unfortunately, signified a different purpose.</p>
                                <p>The Queen, her cabinet, and her followers undoubtedly believed,
                                    from the location of the American troops and the quick
                                    recognition of the Provisional Government by Mr. Stevens, that
                                    the United States forces would aid the Provisional Government
                                    forces in the event of a conflict.</p>
                                <p>The request of the committee of safety, on which the landing of
                                    the troops was made, did not ask for the protection of the
                                    property and persons of American citizens. This paper you have
                                    already in your possession. It was signed by Germans, Americans,
                                    and natives. Mr. W. O. Smith and Mr. L. A. Thurston, the leading
                                    men signing this paper, are natives of these islands, and seemed
                                    to be concerned to have <pb facs="0534" n="528" xml:id="pg_528"/> the troops protect themselves and all others in the islands
                                    from the operation of the Queen’s forces.</p>
                                <p>In one of the local papers, yesterday morning, there appeared an
                                    alleged interview with Mr. Loud, a member of Congress from
                                    California, in which he is reported as criticising the
                                    authorities for not having arrested and sent Liliuokalani out of
                                    the island. In view of your telegraphic instruction of the 25th
                                    ultimo (which was received by me on the 4th instant) and the
                                    possibility that Mr. Loud’s alleged advice might be pursued and
                                    that hostile collision between the friends of the Queen and the
                                    Provisional Government might grow out of it, I had an interview
                                    this morning with the attorney-general, Mr. W. O. Smith, in
                                    which I invited his attention to the reported interview with Mr.
                                    Loud. I asked him if he felt free to say to me whether or not
                                    the arrest of the Queen was contemplated; that I desired the
                                    information because such action on the part of the Provisional
                                    Government might produce a condition of affairs which required
                                    action on my part. He said that this action was not contemplated
                                    by the Provisional Government, but that they were prepared, in
                                    the event of hostilities, to take care of certain prominent
                                    persons amongst the Royalists. Iasked him if those included the
                                    Queen. He answered, “confidentially, Yes.”</p>
                                <p>The feeling of the annexationists is very intense, and doubtless
                                    the Provisional Government is very much pressed to take action
                                    against the person of the Queen by confinement or deportation.
                                    Should this occur I believe that it will produce a bloody
                                    conflict.</p>
                                <p>It is my purpose soon to announce to American citizens that if
                                    they participate in any conflict in behalf of either party I
                                    shall direct that the American troops shall not be used for
                                    their protection. This, I think, to be in line with your views.
                                    I believe that it will tend to prevent extreme action on the
                                    part of the Provisional Government.</p>
                                <p>I have not and shall not intimate any desire to the Provisional
                                    Government as to what they should do with the Queen or with any
                                    other person connected with the royal cause.</p>
                                <p>I do not see any occasion for my remaining longer here for the
                                    purpose of making further inquiry as to the condition of affairs
                                    in the islands. I believe, however, that my departure prior to
                                    your sending out a successor to Mr. Stevens would result in
                                    serious trouble. The attorney-general said to me this morning
                                    there would be no trouble while I remained here, but he had some
                                    apprehensions if I should leave.</p>
                                <p>The native population seem to have great respect for me, growing
                                    out of the idea that I represent the President of the United
                                    States in an effort to get at the causes of the revolution and a
                                    hope that out of that investigation they will regain the
                                    political power they have lost.</p>
                                <p>I have been careful every moment to avoid making an impression on
                                    either party that I was here to interfere in their domestic
                                    affairs or for any purpose other than that of inquiry, or to
                                    indicate what disposition you or the President might make of any
                                    information I should report.</p>
                                <p>Do not infer from these observations that I have any desire to
                                    remain here any longer.</p>
                                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James H. Blount</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Special Commissioner of the United
                                            States</hi>.</signed></closer>
                                <postscript>
                                    <p>P. S.—Since closing the foregoing dispatch the affidavits
                                        marked 4, 5, 6, 7, and 8 have been handed to me.</p>
                                    <p>(Filed with other affidavits.)<note n="*" xml:id="d256fn1">Published with affidavits.</note></p>
                                </postscript>
                                <pb facs="0535" n="529" xml:id="pg_529"/>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                        5.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Extract from records of the United
                                            States legation</hi>.</head>
                                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States
                                                  Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Honolulu</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-17"><hi rend="italic">January 17,
                                            1893</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">correspondence with
                                            hawaiian government.</hi></p>
                                    <p>About 4 to 5 p.m. of this date—am not certain of the precise
                                        time—the note on file from the four ministers of the deposed
                                        Queen, inquiring if I had recognized the Provisional
                                        Government came to my hands, while I was lying sick on the
                                        couch. Not far from 5 p.m.—I did not think to look at the
                                        watch—I addressed a short note to Hon. Samuel Parker, Hon.
                                        Wm. H. Cornwell, Hon. John F. Colburn, and Hon. A. P.
                                        Peterson—no longer regarding them ministers—informing them
                                        that I had recognized the Provisional Government.</p>
                                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John L.
                                                Stevens</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                                Minister</hi>.</signed></closer>
                                </frus:attachment>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                        5.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss type="from">Queen’s
                                                ministers</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Stevens</persName>.</hi></head>
                                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign
                                                  Affairs</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Honolulu</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-17"><hi rend="italic">January 17,
                                            1893</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                                    <p rend="flushleft">His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">John L.
                                            Stevens</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Envoy Extraordinary
                                            and Minister Plenipotentiary:</hi></p>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Her Hawaiian Majesty’s
                                        Government having been informed that certain persons to them
                                        unknown have issued proclamation declaring a Provisional
                                        Government to exist in opposition to Her Majesty’s
                                        Government, and having pretended to depose the Queen, her
                                        cabinet and marshal, and that certain treason able persons
                                        at present occupy the Government building in Honolulu with
                                        an armed force, and pretending that your excellency, in
                                        behalf of the United States of America, has recognized such
                                        Provisional Government, Her Majesty’s cabinet asks
                                        respectfully: Has your excellency recognized said
                                        Provisional Government? and if not, Her Majesty’s
                                        Government, under the above existing circumstances,
                                        respectfully requests the assistance of your Government in
                                        preserving the peace of the country.</p>
                                    <p>We have the honor to be your excellency’s obedient
                                        servants,</p>
                                    <closer><signed>
                                            <list>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel
                                                  Parker</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Minister of
                                                  Foreign Affairs</hi>.</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Wm. H.
                                                  Cornwell</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Minister of
                                                  Finance</hi>.</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">John F.
                                                  Colburn</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Minister of
                                                  the Interior</hi>.</item>
                                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">A. P.
                                                  Peterson</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Attorney-General.</hi></item>
                                            </list>
                                        </signed></closer>
                                </frus:attachment>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                                        5.]</seg></opener>
                                    <head><hi rend="italic">Statement of Lieut. Draper.</hi></head>
                                    <p>May 5, 1893. Herbert L. Draper, Lieutenant Marine Corps,
                                        attached to Boston:</p>
                                    <p>I was at the United States consulate-general at the time the
                                        Provisional Government troops went to the station house and
                                        it was turned over to them by Marshal Wilson. It was about
                                        half past 7 o’clock, The station house is near the
                                        consulate-general on the same street. As soon as it happened
                                        I telephoned it to the ship. I wanted my commanding officer
                                        to know, as I regarded it as an especially important
                                        thing.</p>
                                    <p>I was the commanding officer at the consulate-general. There
                                        was no other United States officer there at the time
                                        excepting myself.</p>
                                    <p>The above is a correct statement.</p>
                                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Herbert L.
                                                Draper</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">First Lieutenant,
                                                U. S. Marine Corps.</hi></signed></closer>
                                </frus:attachment>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>