<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Everett to
                                    Mr. Legare.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1894app2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1843-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1843-06-01T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185" lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1843-06-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1843-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Everett</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Legare</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 40.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1843-06-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 1,
                                    1843</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">H. S. Legare</hi>,
                                    Esq.,<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>:</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>The immediate object of my interview with Lord Aberdeen was to make
                                inquiry relative to a report contained in the papers of the week,
                                that the sovereignty of the Sandwich Islands had been ceded to the
                                Queen of Great Britain, and possession taken by Lord George Paulet,
                                of the ship of war <hi rend="italic">Carysfort</hi>, the British
                                officer commanding in those seas. This report will no doubt have
                                attracted your notice; and following so closely after the official
                                recognition of the independence of these islands by the United
                                States and Great Britian herself is well calculated to produce
                                uneasiness and suprise, and in this light I spoke of it to Lord
                                Aberdeen.</p>
                <p>He said they were entirely without information on the subject beyond
                                what the newspapers contained and had no other reason to believe in
                                the fact of the occupation. He could only say, at present, that if
                                any such thing had taken place it was entirely without authority or
                                instructions, as I could easily infer from the recent official
                                recognition of the independence of the islands by Great Britain,
                                which was made known to me at the time. I observed to Lord Aberdeen
                                that, of course, if the islands had been thus without authority
                                taken possession of, the act would be immediately disavowed by Her
                                Majesty’s Government. He said it might not be proper for him, in the
                                absence of all information, under an entire ignorance of what had
                                been done, to pledge the Government to any course; but he was quite
                                willing to say that the intelligence <pb facs="0118" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/> had produced no change in the opinions and
                                feelings which led him to advise the recognition, and that he still
                                remained without the least wish for any addition to their colonial
                                possessions. He told me they had several times declined to accept
                                the sovereignty of different groups of islands in the Pacific which
                                had beed offered to them. If the report was founded in truth, he
                                thought the cession might have proceeded from apprehensions on the
                                part of the government of the Sandwich Islands that the French were
                                meditating also the occupation of that group and that aversion to
                                the French might have led them, in the absence of Mr. Richards, to
                                wish to place themselves under British protection. I told Lord
                                Aberdeen that I had understood from a private source of information
                                that the Hawaiian Commissioners at Washington had offered to place
                                the islands under the protection of the United States; that I could
                                not vouch for the truth of the report, but that if the offer were
                                made it was certainly, as he was aware, declined.</p>
                <p>In reference to the reserve with which he had spoken of giving up the
                                islands, if possession as reported had been taken of them, Lord
                                Aberdeen said this reserve was only <hi rend="italic">in majorem
                                    cautelam</hi>, in consideration of his total ignorance of the
                                circumstances of the case, and not because his opinions and feelings
                                as to the expediency of the measure were at all varied by the
                                rumored fact of the occupation. On my remarking that in one version
                                of the newspaper report the cession was said to have been accepted
                                by Lord George Paulet in full satisfaction for demands of
                                compensation for injuries sustained by British subjects from the
                                Government of the Sandwich Islands, he said he was not acquainted
                                with any such demands and should be doubly unwilling to sanction a
                                cession made on that basis. Upon the whole, when I reflect how
                                distinctly and how recently this Government is pledged to the United
                                States, to France, and to the Sandwich Islands themselves to
                                recognize their independence I cannot doubt that thfe act of the
                                commander of the <hi rend="italic">Carysfort</hi> will be readily
                                disavowed.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I am, sir, respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward
                                Everett.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
