<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-05-03T05:29:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-04-25T05:30:00-05:00" n="368" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d368">
                                <head>No. 21.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Edmund
                                            Norrie</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">C. B.
                                            Wilson</persName>.</hi></head>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1893-05-02T23:59:59-10:30" notBefore="1893-04-25T00:00:00-10:30">undated</date>.]</dateline></opener>
                                <p rend="flushleft">Hon. C. B. <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Honolulu:</hi></p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In response to your request to
                                    reduce to writing the verbal report which I made to you on
                                    January 17 in regard to the situation at the Government building
                                    and surroundings at the time of the proclamation of the
                                    Provisional Government I beg to submit it as follows:</p>
                                <p>I entered the Government building about 1 o’clock p.m. and went
                                    to the foreign office where I, from the window in the minister’s
                                    private <pb facs="1073" n="1067" xml:id="pg_1067"/> office,
                                    watched the movements of the United States forces which were
                                    stationed on the Hayselden premises. The attached roughly-drawn
                                    diagram shows that the sailors were marched up from Kekaulike
                                    street through the alleyway between the opera house and the
                                    Arion Hall, and stood in the yard belonging to the premises
                                    occupied by Mr. Nakayama, inspector of Japanese.</p>
                                <p>Two Gatling guns were placed at the entrance to the said alley,
                                    trailed on the main entrance of the Government building. About
                                    1:45 p.m. the placing of the troops was accomplished and the men
                                    stood at “attention,” the infantry with arms “ordered,” the
                                    artillerists with the drawing ropes of the guns in their hand s
                                    ready to move. I estimated that one company with the half
                                    battery of Gatlings occupied Kekaulike street and the alley,
                                    while the rest of the sailors with two other guns were in the
                                    yard between the Arion Hall and Nakayama’s house. I went down to
                                    Palace Square to see if the insurgents were beginning to move on
                                    the Government building as expected. In the gateway of
                                    Nakayama’s premises towards Palace Square stood two officers of
                                    the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> with drawn swords looking
                                    towards the town. I now saw Mr. Dole and a body of men coming up
                                    through Merchant street towards the Government buildings. They
                                    were crossing Alake street when I saw them. The <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> officers saw them at the same time
                                    and immediately went to Arion Hall. I returned to the foreign
                                    office and took up my place at the window overlooking the Arion
                                    Hall.</p>
                                <p>I noticed that all the <hi rend="italic">Boston</hi> officers had
                                    placed themselves in the proper positions with their men ready
                                    to make a move. At this time Mr. Charles L. Carter came riding
                                    on horseback very fast towards the Arion Hall from Queen street
                                    [indicated by arrow on diagram] and stopped outside the Arion
                                    Hall, dismounted and entered the gate. Capt. Wiltse and another
                                    officer were sitting on the veranda of the hall facing the
                                    Government building. Mr. Carter approached Capt. Wiltse and
                                    handed him a large envelope, which he opened, and after having
                                    read the contents placed it in his pocket. He said something to
                                    the officer with him, who left, and going among the troops spoke
                                    to the different officers. Mr. Carter remounted and left by the
                                    same route along Queen street. A few minutes after Mr. Dole and
                                    party turned the corner of Palace Square and entered the
                                    Government yard from Kekaulike street and thence to the main
                                    entrance of the building, where they stopped and Mr. Cooper read
                                    the proclamation. As soon as he had finished I left and reported
                                    to you.</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Edmund
                                    Norrie</hi>.</signed></closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>