<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-07-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-07-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="405" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d405">
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Merrill</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 52.]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-07-12"><hi rend="italic">July 12,
                                        1887</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The tenor of your late dispatches
                                coincides with other reports from the Hawaiian Kingdom, and
                                indicates the most unsatisfactory and disturbed condition of affairs
                                in the government of that country, which renders it essential that
                                the strictest vigilance should be exercised by <pb facs="1173" n="1167" xml:id="pg_1167"/> those charged with the care of the
                                rights of American citizens within that jurisdiction, as well as the
                                rights of the United States secured under existing international
                                conventions.</p>
                            <p>Whilst regretting deeply the existence of domestic disorders in
                                Hawaii, and with no disposition whatever to interfere therein or to
                                obtrude counsel unasked, yet the consequences which may possibly
                                result to the interests of American citizens which have grown up
                                under the extension of the commerce between that country and the
                                United States, under the guaranties of existing treaty, must not be
                                jeopardized by internal confusion in the government of these
                                islands, and it is the duty of the United States to see that these
                                interests are not imperiled or injured and to do all things
                                necessary for their just protection.</p>
                            <p>The existing treaty between the United States and Hawaii, as was
                                contemplated and intended by the parties thereto, has created and
                                fostered commercial relations more intimate in their nature and of
                                incomparably greater volume and value than Hawaii ever had or ever
                                can have with any other government.</p>
                            <p>The growth of this commerce and the consequent advancement of these
                                Islands in wealth and importance has been most satisfactory to the
                                United States, and by reason of their geographical position and
                                comparative propinquity to our own territory they possess an
                                interest and importance to us far exceeding that with which they can
                                be regarded by any other power. In the absence of any detailed
                                information from you of the late regrettable disorders in the
                                domestic control of Hawaii and the changes which have taken place in
                                the official corps of that Government, I am not able to give you
                                other than general instructions, which may be communicated in
                                substance to the commanding officer of the vessel or vessels of this
                                Government in the waters of Hawaii, with whom you will freely
                                confer, in order that such prompt and efficient action may be taken
                                as the circumstances may make necessary.</p>
                            <p>Whilst we abstain from interference with the domestic affairs of
                                Hawaii, in accordance with the policy and practice of this
                                Government, yet obstruction to the channels of legitimate commerce
                                under existing treaty must not be allowed, and American citizens in
                                Hawaii must be protected in their persons and property by the
                                representatives of their country’s law and power, and no internal
                                discord must be suffered to impair them. Your own aid and counsel,
                                as well as the assistance of the officers of our Government vessels,
                                if found necessary, will therefore be promptly afforded to promote
                                the reign of law and respect for orderly government in Hawaii.</p>
                            <p>As is well known, no intent is cherished or policy entertained by the
                                United States which is otherwise than friendly to the autonomical
                                control and independence of Hawaii, and no other member of the
                                family of nations has so great and immediate an interest in the
                                welfare and prosperity of Hawaii on such a basis as this
                                Republic.</p>
                            <p>The vast line of our national territory on the Pacific coast, and its
                                neighborhood to the Hawaiian group, indicate the recognized
                                predominance of our interests in the regions of these Islands.</p>
                            <p>This superiority of interest in the welfare of the Hawaiian Islands
                                is accompanied by an appreciation of the right of these friendly
                                inhabitants and their Government to our good offices, which we
                                freely tender whenever they can be efficacious in-securing the
                                safety and promoting the welfare of that island group.</p>
                            <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">T. F.
                                Bayard.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>