<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Willis to Mr.
                                    Gresham.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1894app2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1894-07-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1894-07-08T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoco7SW1Tkt0mwM" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007735" lcsh-match="exact">Sports</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185" lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="law-of-the-sea" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271" lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379" lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664" lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871" lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131" lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="reci0GubnZFV3spJe" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011003316" lcsh-match="bad_close">Infant</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647" lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1894-07-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1894-07-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="505" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d505">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Willis</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 64.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                        the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Honolulu,
                                        Hawaiian Islands</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-07-08">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 8,
                                        1894</hi>
                        </date>. (Received July 27.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It has been customary in these islands for
                            the citizens of the United States to celebrate the Fourth of July with
                            athletic sports, boat races, fireworks, etc., together with literary
                            exercises, at which the American minister usually presides. The
                            Hawaiians and citizens of all nationalities heartily participate in the
                            observance of the day. Last <pb facs="1350" n="1344" xml:id="pg_1344"/>
                            year Mr. Blount presided, and prior to that under the monarchy the
                            custom has prevailed for many years. The day was celebrated this year
                            with more than ordinary enthusiasm. The English, Japanese, and American
                            war vessels were dressed, flags were displayed from all the legations
                            and consulates, public buildings and a large number of private
                            residences were elaborately decorated, and the national salute fired at
                            noon.</p>
                <p>The reception at the United States legation was attended by several
                            hundred persons, including representatives of the home and foreign
                            governments and prominent citizens of all potitical parties.</p>
                <p>I inclose newspaper clippings, giving some of the particulars of the
                            celebration and also the principal address on the occasion.</p>
                <p>With sentiments of high esteem, I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert S.
                            Willis</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 64.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">a fitting celebration—the great holiday of
                                    america and of hawaii—exercises at little britain—the full text
                                    of the orations made by various speaker—spatriotic speeches
                                    which all have the ring of true republicanism—a large
                                    audience.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The one hundred and eighteenth anniversary of the Declaration of the
                                Independence of the United States was marked, besides the one great
                                event of the day, the forming of the Republic, by enthusiastic
                                ceremonies at J. N. Wright’s place, Little Britain. At half after
                                10, the hour set for the literary exercises to commence, the large
                                pavilion was filled with those who came to celebrate the day in the
                                good old way by listening to patriotic speeches, and hearing the
                                Declaration of Independence, one of, if not the grandest of the
                                world’s documents, read.</p>
                    <p>The pavilion had been gaily decorated with American flags and with
                                ferns. On the platform were President Dole, Minister Willis, Admiral
                                Walker, Capt. Barker, Capt. Cochrane, J. B. Atherton, P. C. Jones,
                                Prof. W. W. Lovejoy, Leo Cooper, and the newspaper
                                representatives.</p>
                    <p>Minister Willis, the president of the day, was introduced by J. B.
                                Atherton. He said:</p>
                    <p>“I thank the committee for having given me the honor of presiding on
                                this occasion, and in the name of the great Republic whose
                                representative I am, I extend to the citizens of the United States
                                and to all others who sympathize with republican institutions, a
                                heartfelt welcome.”</p>
                    <p>Prof. Lovejoy then offered a prayer, after which the song “The Battle
                                Cry of Freedom” was sung by the audience. Mr. Leo Cooper then read
                                the Declaration of Independence, which was greeted with much
                                applause.</p>
                    <p>J. B. Castle was next introduced, and said that the paper he was
                                going to read had been prepared by W. N. Armstrong, who had asked
                                him to read it, as he was away</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 64.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">capt. cochrane’s address.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Chairman, Ladies, and Gentlemen</hi>: I
                                would that I could also say “fellow-citizens,” but I see so many
                                here who are not yet Americans that perhaps it were better to employ
                                a new expression—fellow-denizens. [This reference to possible
                                annexation, and to the article so much discussed by the late
                                convention, met with instant recognition.] When your committee did
                                me the honor to invite me to address you upon this famous
                                anniversary, I accepted with much pleasure. It was understood that I
                                was to make a short address on the Declaration of Independence, and
                                that the oration—a larger contract—was to be awarded to another.
                                Later, I was asked if I would change places, and as the difference
                                was only one of degrees, I readily consented. I met the gentleman
                                who was to be my colleague, ex-Attorney-General Armstrong, and we
                                agreed to have a conference, that we might not collide. Next I
                                learned that Mr. Armstrong was going to Hilo and that there would be
                                no other speaker. You can therefore imagine my surprise at learning
                                just now that friend Armstrong had left his oration behind.</p>
                    <pb facs="1351" n="1345" xml:id="pg_1345"/>
                    <p>In order to ascertain what was done on the last Fourth of July, I
                                went to your very excellent public library and looked over a file of
                                old papers. There I saw that you had had a spread-eagle oration, and
                                that a Mr. P. C. Jones had made a very interesting and pleasing
                                address. I felt thankful that Mr. Jones was not to compete this
                                year. Now, where do I find myself? Mr. Armstrong and Mr. Jones are
                                both in the field, and some of my thunder is surely stolen. Anyhow,
                                I had the usual assortment of grandfathers, as well as Mr. Jones,
                                but they had the misfortune to land at Philadelphia instead of
                                Boston, and though they did not help to throw any tea overboard they
                                had the Declaration of Independence and plenty of dried apple
                                pies.</p>
                    <p>My gray head and scanty locks reveal the fact that I have seen many
                                Fourths of July, and I may add—thanks to the wandering life those of
                                my profession necessarily lead—that they have been celebrated in
                                different foreign countries and in many of the States of the
                                American Union.</p>
                    <p>On the Atlantic and Pacific coasts, on the shores of the Great Lakes
                                and the yet greater Gulf of Mexico, on the Mississippi, in the West
                                Indies, in Central and South America, in Europe, in Africa, and on
                                the high seas have I passed Independence Day, but never before in
                                Polynesia. Thanksgiving, Christmas, and New Years, yes, but not the
                                “glorious Fourth;” so I am especially glad to be with you on this
                                delightful and memorable occasion.</p>
                    <p>Yesterday I thought that there was but one other country on earth
                                where the Fourth is more highly regarded or more generally
                                celebrated than in Hawaii. Today I am not sure that there is any. I
                                have seen great Paris ablaze, but it was the work of the State and
                                not the people.</p>
                    <p>It seems strange that one, 2,000 miles and more from home, can be in
                                an atmosphere so overwhelmingly American as this. Where in all
                                Yankeedom, or in all Christendom, is there a community of this size,
                                or any size for the matter of that, which is honoring the
                                Declaration of Independence, that colossal indictment and grand
                                compendium of human rights, with greater zeal and enthusiasm than is
                                the community of Honolulu? Where else is such a mixing of races agog
                                and afoot with such hearty and simple impulse? I’ve just left a
                                thousand “tars” wild with excitement, and a Yankee man-of-war
                                proselyting the entire harbor.</p>
                    <p>Where else, Mr. Chairman, is the day too short for all of the
                                exercises, sports, and festivities which it is desired to crowd into
                                it? Where else are the decorations of streets and houses more lavish
                                or more beautiful; where are handsomer prizes offered to the
                                decorators, and where is there a more magnificent flag than that of
                                the American League?</p>
                    <p>Where, also, have the subscriptions been so liberal that they had to
                                be stopped; and, finally, let me ask, where else has there been
                                promulgated, as the first act after the guns of dawn, and in
                                especial honor and recognition of this great day, a national
                                constitution, bringing into being a new republic?</p>
                    <p>The banks, stores, warehouses, and schools are closed, the water
                                craft and plantations are resting, the stars and stripes are flying,
                                and the people are rejoicing. I hope that the gentlemen of the
                                press, if there be any here, will let the vast and friendly
                                population of the States distinctly know that they are not all
                                Americans who are doing this. Please tell them that the German, the
                                Dane, the Greek, the Portuguese, the Frenchman, the children of
                                Asia, the gentle Hawaiian and the irrepressible Irishman are
                                “assisting,” and I strongly suspect that some of the hardy sons of
                                Great Britain, who are pleased to say that “blood is thicker than
                                water,” are taking a quiet hand to-day at Little Britain.</p>
                    <p>The stranger may say that the celebration of the Fourth of July in
                                the Hawaiian Islands is a new thing, born of revolution or gotten up
                                for dramatic effect, but such is not the case. One learns upon
                                inquiry that “it has always been so,” and that the tie which binds
                                multitudes of this people, rich and poor, brown as well as white, to
                                the land of liberty is stronger perhaps than any of them fully
                                realize. If I mistake not, the day is not far distant when this
                                feeling will assert itself with a unanimity and result alike amazing
                                in every island of the banner group of the Pacific.</p>
                    <p>Fully eighty years ago it first began, and that was six years before
                                the missionaries first arrived. The idols had not yet been destroyed
                                when Kamehameha I, surnamed the Great, began the custom of
                                celebrating the Fourth of July.</p>
                    <p>There was a joyousness in the proceedings which commended them to
                                native tastes, and the custom took hold and grew until it became the
                                holiday of all the year. The Kamehameha folks, if not misrepresented
                                by the esteemed historian, Prof. Alexander, fully understood the art
                                of celebrating, and could put a cardinal hue on a village of grass
                                huts with “neatness and dispatch.”</p>
                    <p>Though not exactly a Kamaaina, I am far from being a stranger here.
                                Four and twenty years have passed since I first beheld the bold
                                front and rugged sides of Diamond Head, but my recollections of
                                these charming islands remain clear and strong, and my interest in
                                them has never flagged. As I had resided for some time with the
                                ex-queen, then Mrs. Dominis, and her sister, the Princess Likelike,
                                at <pb facs="1352" n="1346" xml:id="pg_1346"/> Washington Place, and
                                had assisted Prince David Kalakaua, their brother, with some
                                military instruction for the funeral of the Dowager Queen Kalama
                                when he was a clerk in the foreign office and an officer of the
                                volunteers, their subsequent careers always excited a friendly
                                interest. Kamehameha V (Prince Lot) was king during that visit, and
                                although there appeared to be then profound content, the seed had
                                been sown and the American leaven was working.</p>
                    <p>I remember particularly a visit made to Hilo in the old <hi rend="italic">Kilauea</hi>, the pioneer and only inter-island
                                steamer then plying. Now you have two fleets. Her speed, never
                                alarming, had become so reduced that they could see her smoke at
                                Lahaina seven or eight hours before she arrived, and it was decided
                                to overhaul her. Maj. C. H. Judd, better known to you as “Charley
                                Judd,” was then her agent, and after she-was restored to 8 knots on
                                a level he advertised her for a trip to Hilo if enough passengers
                                could be had who wanted to visit the volcano. Enough were booked,
                                and we rolled over there in the month of October, 1870. There were
                                several young officers in the party who belonged to the U. S. sloop
                                    <hi rend="italic">Jamestown</hi>, then in this port, and finding
                                no hotel in Hilo, we were very thankful to be invited by the veteran
                                Capt. Tom Spencer to make our headquarters at his hospitable house.
                                After a grand bath in a running stream of cold water, and an
                                excellent dinner, we were treated to a serenade by a small band
                                composed of some native boys, friends of poor Bill Ragsdale. The
                                music would not have suited Mozart or Beethoven, perhaps, but we
                                liked it. Was it the melodious “Aloha Oe,” or “Ahi Wela,” you ask.
                                No, not a bit of it. Those boys made the cocoanut palms and bamboo
                                clumps rustle with “John Brown’s Body,” “Sherman’s March to the
                                Sea,” and “Columbia’s the Gem of the Ocean,” and we felt that it was
                                only a couple of miles from Rainbow Falls to the Golden Gate.</p>
                    <p>About eighteen months ago I was announced to lecture in Metropolitan
                                Temple, San Francisco. On my way to the building in a streetcar, on
                                January 27, I saw hanging in a great plate-glass window of the
                                Chronicle office, on Market street, a small placard which made known
                                to passers-by that James G. Blaine, the distinguished statesman and
                                friend of Hawaii, had died that morning, in Washington. The sad news
                                was the topic of conversation everywhere, and I referred to it in my
                                lecture, which was attended by about 1,700 people. Among those
                                people there were several newspapermen, and one especially
                                well-known was Mr. M. H. DeYoung. I mention this because his
                                presence aroused in me considerable interest to see what criticism
                                of my humble effort his paper, the Chronicle, might contain next
                                day. Immediately after breakfast I bought a copy and found that I
                                had been crowded out. A black, schooner-rigged, iron steamer, called
                                the <hi rend="italic">Claudine</hi>, had unexpectedly arrived in the
                                night and the Chronicle and San Francisco were alike taken up with
                                the news of “A revolt in Hawaii.” Even Blaine was for the time being
                                forgotten, and column after column was filled with the details of
                                the incidents which led up to the crisis of January, 17, 1893. I
                                bear no malice.</p>
                    <p>Picking up aback number of the Pacific Commercial Advertiser a few
                                days since I noticed in it a short article which again suggested
                                that time often invests with peculiar interest things once laid
                                aside as of little moment. The article in question was copied from a
                                great Democratic newspaper, the New York Sun, and seems very
                                appropriate to this occasion. It is entitled “Free Hawaii’s
                                birthday,” and says:</p>
                    <p>“To-day is the first anniversary of the establishment of the
                                provisional government in Hawaii on the ruins of monarchical and
                                despotic ideas. We congratulate President Dole and his able and
                                patriotic associates upon the success of their administration, and
                                upon the strength of their position before the world.</p>
                    <p>“Probably never in the course of the ages have the affairs of any
                                infant nation been managed more ably, wisely, or honestly. These men
                                of American blood and American sympathies are of the same sort as
                                those who founded our own Republic. No wonder the hearts of the
                                people of the United States have gone out towards them.</p>
                    <p>“For a time, longer or shorter, according to circumstances which it
                                is now impossible to foresee, January 17 will hold in Hawaii’s
                                calendar similar to the Fourth of July in our own. Then in the
                                inevitable progress of destiny January 17 in Hawaii will be merged
                                in July Fourth, and islands and continent will celebrate together
                                and in common the nation’s birth.”—New York Sun.</p>
                    <p>How little did that able writer know that but half a year would be
                                needed to witness the beginning of the fulfillment of his prophecy,
                                and that the very next succeeding Fourth of July would find what he
                                calls the “inevitable progress of destiny “so far advanced that “the
                                islands” could celebrate the birthday of two nations instead of
                                one.</p>
                    <p>It was only by dint of most diligent effort on the part of the late
                                convention that this has been made a doubly great historic day, not
                                for Hawaii alone, but for all of the earth, for when at eventide the
                                life-giving sun shall sink below the horizon it will set for the
                                first time upon a hemisphere of independent republics.</p>
                    <p>The vast Empire of Brazil was thought stable and secure. It long held
                                its own by reason of the personality of its estimable monarch, but
                                suddenly the end came. Almost as suddenly the end came here. Vain
                                efforts have been made to restore “the <pb facs="1353" n="1347" xml:id="pg_1347"/> divine right of kings,” but “revolutions
                                rarely go backward.” Kind friends rise up and extend a helping hand
                                to those who struggle for liberty, fraternity, and equality, and the
                                good Lord seems to approve.</p>
                    <p>At 8 o’clock this morning the Provisional Government stepped down and
                                out, and the infant Republic stepped in. As I stood in front of the
                                Executive building and gazed upon the great, orderly, clean,
                                well-dressed, and intelligent assemblage that occupied the steps and
                                portico and surrounded your distinguished President as he proclaimed
                                the new constitution and was sworn in by the chief justice to
                                support it, I saw a scene of which any country might well be
                                proud.</p>
                    <p>It speaks volumes for the good sense and love of order of those who
                                entertain different views from the party in power that they have
                                thus far confined their objections to lawful protests. It is to be
                                hoped that they will adhere to this course. Nothing is so illogical
                                as war, and few things more costly than undertakers’ charges. All
                                know that perfect men and perfect governments do not exist and it is
                                idle to expect them. A fair and patient trial of the new
                                constitution and Government should not be denied. Your universally
                                esteemed President expects, in due time, to have a successor, and I
                                venture to say that he desires that successor to be in every way a
                                worthy man. I understand that an ex-premier has recently considered
                                the possibility of his filling the place. It is a legitimate
                                ambition, and the political movement essential to that end might
                                prove no disadvantage to the nation. Two healthy political parties
                                are, indeed, the salvation of a republic. It may seem a little out
                                of place for me, a soldier, to plead thus, but I was raised among
                                William Penn Quakers, and they cultivated peace. I remember when it
                                was believed that the civil troubles in America could never be
                                composed; and later, when it was boldly asserted that the clashing
                                in France between royalty and democracy would utterly destroy that
                                wonderful nation; but those opinions were ill founded.</p>
                    <p>The outcome in each case was of special interest, because I was
                                engaged in the four years of our sad and bloody conflict and, by a
                                strange coincidence, had the distinguished honor of welcoming, five
                                years later, the advent of the great French Republic with a short
                                address on French soil. This happened at Tahiti, in the Society
                                Islands, in November, 1870. That address was partly in French and
                                partly in English, but there was one sentence ill it that everybody
                                understood—and that was Vive la Republique!</p>
                    <p>Mr. T. B. Murray, President of the American League, then proposed
                                three cheers for Capt. Cochrane, which were given with a will and
                                followed by a “tiger.”</p>
                    <p>Mr. Willis being about to step to the front, Capt. Cochrane arose and
                                begged him to delay a moment, adding: “Fellow denizens [laughter]:
                                If it is not altogether improper, let us give three cheers for the
                                latest addition to the family—the infant Republic.”</p>
                    <p>The grandest song possible to singthe song that will move anyone with
                                a drop of American blood in his veinswas next sung by the audience.
                                The strains of “America” rolled out upon the air and sent a thrill
                                through all those who heard it. The band played a melody of American
                                airs, and the people left the building. The exercises of the day
                                were over.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 64From the Hawaiian
                                    Gazette.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the events of the day.—the various doings of
                                    the people yesterday.—what there was to see and do.—aquatic and
                                    athletic sports, baseball, a reception and the fireworks in the
                                    evening keep everyone busy on the greatest of all
                                holidays</hi>.</head>
                    <p>The stores and dwelling places in Honolulu were never decorated as
                                they were yesterday. The patriotic feeling made itself felt in all
                                quarters and the result proved to many strangers that Honolulu has
                                as much love for the great American holiday as any other of its size
                                in the United States. Along the business streets nothing but flags
                                and bunting greeted the eyes, and the captains of the merchant
                                vessels in the harbor did their share toward making the decorative
                                feature a success. Every vessel, with one or two exceptions, was
                                decorated with all the bunting available, and conspicuous among them
                                were the ships <hi rend="italic">Marie Hackfeld</hi> and the
                                schooner <hi rend="italic">R. W. Bartlett</hi>. Of course the war
                                vessels were decorated from stem to stern and each presented a
                                pretty sight.</p>
                    <p>The Fourth of July committee offered 5 prizes for the best decorated
                                buildings, and it was left with the Art League to decide. D. Howard
                                Hitchcock was the chairman. The members of the league visited every
                                portion of the city, and finally decided that the house of Castle
                                &amp; Cooke was entitled to the first prize. They considered that,
                                as an emblematical design and as an artistic decoration, it was far
                                and <pb facs="1354" n="1348" xml:id="pg_1348"/> away the finest
                                displayed. The following is a brief description of the decoration:
                                Crowning the center is a large silver star over the legend “Hawaii,”
                                flanked by a number of banners in red, white, and blue. Draped
                                across the center of the building are large American and Hawaiian
                                flags balanced by tricolored draperies. Offsetting the whole is a
                                base of dark-blue cloth trimmed with green maile and finished at
                                either corner with Hawaiian and American shields. The second prize
                                was awarded to the Inter-Island Steamship Company; third prize, Oahu
                                jail; fourth prize, Safe Deposit Company; fifth prize, Pantheon
                                saloon. A number of other buildings were wondrously decorated.
                                Lewers &amp; Cooke had a gorgeous display, and No. 2 engine house
                                deserves special mention.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">sports in the harbor</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The sports on the bay drew a large crowd to the water front
                                yesterday. The decks of every vessel from which a good view could be
                                obtained were crowded with people. The officers of the war vessels
                                in port invited their friends to go on board, and-the invitation was
                                accepted by a great many. The programme as a whole was interesting
                                and was well carried out. The most exciting race of the day was the
                                12-oar barge race between a native crew and crews from both the <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The course was around the spar buoy, the natives winning in 19
                                minutes and 40 seconds, followed 14 seconds later by the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> crew.</p>
                    <p>A great deal of interest was centered in the race between the Myrtle
                                and Healani boat clubs. The crew of the first-named club won easily
                                in 17 minutes and 8 seconds.</p>
                    <p>The following is the full programme of the day and the winners:</p>
                    <p>The first race between the Myrtles and the Healanis over the spar
                                buoy course was won as previously mentioned.</p>
                    <p>The second race was between a number of boat boys in single-oared
                                boats. The course was around a buoy fastened in the neighborhood of
                                the Myrtle boathouse. The race was won by John Mahuku in 14
                                minutes.</p>
                    <p>The third race was contested for by crews of the war vessels in port,
                                in cutters, 12 men in each, around the spar buoy; won by the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> crew in 21 minutes and 13
                                seconds.</p>
                    <p>The fourth race was in six-oared gigs from the American and Japanese
                                men-of-war. Owing to an accident, which laid up the <hi rend="italic">Champion’s</hi> gig for repairs, the Englishmen
                                did not participate. The <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia’s</hi> crew
                                won again. Time, 21 minutes and 41 seconds.</p>
                    <p>The fifth race was in shells. The contestents were R. Dexter and W.
                                Harris. Dexter won in 9 minutes and 36 seconds.</p>
                    <p>The sixth race was won by a native crew in 24 minutes and 16 seconds.
                                It was a four-oared race between three crews—the natives, a crew
                                from the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> and a crew from the <hi rend="italic">Kongo.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The catamaran race was the next on the programme. It was contested
                                for by men from the <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Kongo</hi>. It was easily won by the Japanese.</p>
                    <p>The swimming race was won by a native named Pua. He was followed
                                closely by a seaman named Skuse, belonging to the <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi>. The distance was about one-eighth of a mile.</p>
                    <p>The second-class yacht race had four entries: <hi rend="italic">Edith
                                    L., Coral Queen, Pokii</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Mary
                                    Walding</hi>. It was won by the <hi rend="italic">Mary
                                    Waiding.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The sailing-launch race between the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi> was won
                                by the <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi> boat.</p>
                    <p>The following gentlemen had charge of the aquatic sports: Judges,
                                Lieut. W. M. Wood, Lieut. F. K. C. Gibbons, Lieut. R. Ide, Capt.
                                Campbell, and Capt. Fuller; starter, C. B. Wilson; timekeeper, Frank
                                Kruger.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the athletic sports</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The literary exercises were not all, by any means, that occurred at
                                Little Britain during the day. In the afternoon the dancing pavilion
                                and the athletic sports drew a big crowd in that direction, in spite
                                of the other events. Dancing was kept up in the pavilion until
                                nearly 6 o’clock.</p>
                    <p>The sports were very interesting and were greatly enjoyed. The
                                winners of the different events, and the time and distances made,
                                follows: <list>
                            <item>One hundred yards race—Tom Pryce, J. I. Richardson, 11¾
                                        seconds.</item>
                            <item>Standing broad jump—John Caustino, Tom Pryce, 11½
                                        feet.</item>
                            <item>Running broad jump—A. Tyrrell, H. Hapai, 18 feet 10½
                                        inches.</item>
                            <item>Basket potato race (juvenile)—John Aylett, Schichi.</item>
                            <item>One hundred yards race (juvenile)—Arthur Giles, Reuben
                                        Kinney, 12 seconds.</item>
                            <pb facs="1355" n="1349" xml:id="pg_1349"/>
                            <item>Pole vault—Gr. Angus, W. Halstead, 8 feet 7 inches.</item>
                            <item>Quarter-mile race—J. L. King, W. D. Armstrong, 1 minute
                                        and 1 second.</item>
                            <item>Boot and shoe race (juvenile)—W. Roland, J. Aylett.</item>
                            <item>Hop, step, and jump—A Tyrrell, T. White, 38 feet 7½
                                        inches.</item>
                            <item>Match race, 100 yards—W. B. Bolster and C. J. Dietz.
                                        Boltzer won. Time, 12f¾seconds.</item>
                            <item>Three-legged race (juvenile)—W. Austin and J. Aylett, M.
                                        Botelho and J. Suarez.</item>
                            <item>One hundred and twenty yards hurdle race—Vida Thrum, J.
                                        Wright, 18 seconds.</item>
                            <item>Running high jump—A. Tyrrell, J. Caustino, 4 feet 9
                                        inches.</item>
                            <item>Potato race (juvenile)—J. Santos, Kamanao.</item>
                            <item>Jim Kaharna race—F. Ferreira.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the afternoon reception</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The public reception held by Minister Willis and his charming wife in
                                the afternoon was certainly not less successful than the other
                                events of the glorious Fourth. The reception toot place in the
                                parlors of the Hawaiian Hotel, and from 3 o’clock until 5 a host of
                                people streamed in, all eager to pay their respects to the American
                                minister. The band of the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> was
                                stationed in the stand in the hotel grounds, and the Hawaiian
                                Quintette Club were in attendance on the Lanai, where an elegant
                                collation was served.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the baseball game</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Kamehamehas added to their laurels again yesterday, beating the
                                Hawaiis by a score of 7 to 4, 5 of the 7 being made in one inning.
                                There was a very large attendance. The game was not a brilliant one,
                                but was marked by the steady playing of the Kamehamehas.</p>
                    <table cols="5" rend="bordered" rows="4">
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Games won.</cell>
                            <cell>Games lost.</cell>
                            <cell>Games played.</cell>
                            <cell>Percentage.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Kamehamehas</cell>
                            <cell role="num">6</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2</cell>
                            <cell role="num">8</cell>
                            <cell role="num">.750</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Hawaiis</cell>
                            <cell role="num">3</cell>
                            <cell role="num">4</cell>
                            <cell role="num">7</cell>
                            <cell role="num">.428</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Crescents</cell>
                            <cell role="num">2</cell>
                            <cell role="num">5</cell>
                            <cell role="num">7</cell>
                            <cell role="num">.286</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">at the butts</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Hawaiian Rifle Association held its regular semiannual shoot at
                                its range near King street yesterday. The attendance was not as
                                large as usual, owing to the large number of counter attractions.
                                The heavy wind blowing made high scores almost an impossibility,
                                especially at the long ranges. No records were broken in the
                                association matches, and only one prize was won for the last time,
                                the Queen’s trophy. In the citizens’ match the honors were easy,
                                there being a large list of prizes.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the fireworks</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The display at the executive building in the evening was magnificent.
                                The grounds were hung with Chinese lanterns. The building itself was
                                beautifully decorated. A long row of electric lanterns had been
                                stretched from either side over the tops of the three front flag
                                poles, and each balcony had rows of lanterns. The chef-d’oeuvre of
                                the decorations, however, was a large 8-pointed star, in different
                                colors, that was placed on the front of the building. In its center,
                                in blue lights, were the figures “94.” The whole star was most
                                brilliant.</p>
                    <p>The fireworks were, of course, the feature of the evening. The
                                grounds, the balconies, and the streets outside were crowded with
                                people watching the beautiful pyrotechnic display. The Japanese
                                fireworks seemed to be the favorites, though there were some
                                beautiful rockets and Roman candles. The display was continued until
                                about 9 o’clock.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
