<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1894-09-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1894-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="509" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d509">
                            <head>No. 2.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Willis</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Gresham</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Honolulu, H. I.</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-09-29"><hi rend="italic">September 29, 1894</hi></date>. (Received October
                                    20.)</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your instruction of the 31st ultimo, inclosing a dispatch
                                of Rear-Admiral Walker of August 17.</p>
                            <p>After a lengthy statement seriously reflecting upon the late British
                                minister and the commanding officer of the <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi> and expressing such apprehensions touching the
                                political situation here as necessitated the detention of the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi>, the Admiral, in the eleventh
                                paragraph, says: “Before reaching this conclusion [to postpone the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia’s</hi> departure] I consulted
                                with the United States minister, whose views entirely coincided with
                                my own.”</p>
                            <p>Your dispatch indicates that these words of the Admiral have been
                                given a wider meaning than could have been intended by him. A brief
                                recital of the facts may therefore be proper.</p>
                            <p>On the 5th day of August I was informed by the Admiral that he would
                                leave with the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> on the 8th. On
                                the 6th the British minister, Major Wodehouse, having been succeeded
                                by Mr. Hawes, made his farewell official visit to this legation,
                                during which he mentioned the fact that the <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi> had intended to leave on that day, but some of
                                the English residents had become nervous when they heard that the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> also was to leave, and
                                yielding to their request, the <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi> would
                                remain until the <hi rend="italic">Hyacinth</hi> arrived. Upon the
                                same morning I made a parting call to the officers of the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi>, when the Admiral told me that
                                several citizens had expressed their regret at the departure of the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> before the arrival of the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Charleston</hi>, which vessel was daily
                                expected. He also expressed some surprise at the change of plans of
                                the <hi rend="italic">Champion</hi>. In view of these facts, he
                                asked my opinion in regard to the detention of the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi>. I replied that as the steamer <hi rend="italic">Australia</hi> was due here August 11, at 8 a.m.,
                                which would probably bring correct advices as to the <hi rend="italic">Charleston’s</hi> movements, I saw no reason, if
                                not in conflict with his orders (as to the nature of which I was not
                                informed), why the <hi rend="italic">Philadelphia</hi> should not
                                wait until then. When the <hi rend="italic">Australia</hi> arrived,
                                I immediately notified the Admiral that no news warranting his
                                further stay had been received. He left the next morning.</p>
                            <p>It is this conversation and the unimportant result following it with
                                which the Admiral connects me.</p>
                            <p>The statement as to the conduct and sentiments of the British
                                minister and captain of the British cruiser, and especially as to
                                their purpose to land troops for political advantage, and the
                                dangers resulting therefrom to American interests, I can not confirm
                                either from personal knowledge or reliable information. If called
                                upon to express an opinion, I should be constrained to say that
                                during the past six months, and especially since the proclamation of
                                the Republic, the presence or absence of British war vessels here
                                ought to have been regarded with indifference by our Government, as
                                it is now by this Government.</p>
                            <p>The “petition of citizens” referred to by the Admiral I did not
                                receive until the day after our conversation. The conditions here
                                for many months had been extremely orderly and peaceful. As stated
                                by the petition itself, there was “no reason to doubt the ability of
                                the Government of the Republic of Hawaii to support and sustain
                                itself <pb facs="1384" n="1378" xml:id="pg_1378"/> and furnish full
                                protection to the lives and property of all residents in its
                                territory.” In this opinion even the enemies of the Government
                                concurred, furthermore, on the day after receiving the petition, Mr.
                                Hatch, the minister of foreign affairs, expressed to me his regret
                                that it had been sent, as those he represented welcomed the
                                opportunity to prove to the world that they were able to take care
                                of themselves. These I deemed sufficient reasons for not forwarding
                                the petition.</p>
                            <p>With renewed assurances, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Albert S.
                                Willis.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>