<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1895-02-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1895-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="514" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d514">
                        <head>[Untitled]</head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">February</hi> 4, 1895.—Referred to the
                            Committee on Foreign Affairs and ordered to be printed.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">To the House of
                            Representatives:</hi></p>
                        <p>In response to the resolution of the House of Representatives of the 1st
                            instant, calling for certain information touching the recent
                            insurrection in the Hawaiian Islands, I transmit herewith a report of
                            the Secretary of State, with accompanying papers.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grover Cleveland.</hi></signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">Executive
                                        Mansion</hi>,<lb/><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-02-04"><hi rend="italic">February 4,
                                1895</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <p rend="flushleft">To the <hi rend="smallcaps">President</hi>:</p>
                            <p>The Secretary of State, to whom was referred the resolution of the
                                House of Representatives, dated February 1, 1895, requesting the
                                President— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>To transmit to the House of Representatives, if not
                                        incompatible with the public interests, all correspondence,
                                        documents, or other information, if any, in the possession
                                        of the Government, in regard to arms having been furnished
                                        by British subjects to persons in rebellion against the
                                        Government of the Hawaiian Islands; or in regard to any
                                        intervention by representatives of Great Britain to prevent
                                        the application of martial law as proclaimed by said
                                        Government to those concerned in said rebellion who claim to
                                        be British subjects,</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">has the honor to report that the Department has no
                                information in regard to arms having been furnished by British
                                subjects to persons in rebellion against the Government of the
                                Hawaiian Islands; but, in a telegram from the United States minister
                                at Honolulu, January 11, forwarded by way of San Francisco, Mr.
                                Willis says: “Arms reported to have been brought from Vancouver by
                                    <hi rend="italic">Norma</hi>.”</p>
                            <pb facs="1398" n="1392" xml:id="pg_1392"/>
                            <p>This telegram and Mr. Willis’s dispatch, No. 81, of the same date,
                                were given to the press on their receipt. Copies are also hereto
                                appended.</p>
                            <p>Although not directly responsive to the resolution, copies are
                                submitted of correspondence exchanged with the United States
                                legation at Honolulu in regard to alleged filibustering movements
                                and apprehended shipments of arms from San Francisco in November
                                last.</p>
                            <p>The Department of State has no information in regard to any
                                intervention by representatives of Great Britain to prevent the
                                application of martial law as proclaimed by the Hawaiian Government
                                to those concerned in the recent rebellion who claim to be British
                                subjects, or of any foreign representations whatever in the case
                                other than a statement, contained in a note of the Hawaiian minister
                                to the undersigned under date of January 20 last, that “the British
                                commissioner at Honolulu, Mr. Hawes, has called upon the Government
                                of Hawaii to give him assurances that no capital punishment will be
                                inflicted upon the insurrectionists, there being fifteen Englishmen
                                under arrest, which requested assurance the Government has refused
                                to give.” Copies of this note of Mr. Thurston and of the reply of
                                the undersigned are also annexed.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully submitted.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. Q. Gresham.</hi></signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <dateline rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of
                                        State</hi>,<lb/><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1895-02-04"><hi rend="italic">February 4,
                                        1895</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>