<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>1. Memorandum From the Deputy Director for Coordination, Bureau of
                    Intelligence and Research (Scott) to the ) to the Special Group</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-01-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-01-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rechWxPReovs7qx7u" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Urban</term>
                    <term ref="recHrSmzhfG78SwqX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recbqzzF4Eebaylpi" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="border-administration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006007505"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Border control</term>
                    <term ref="recknGihgxWN67bUp" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Coup attempt</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-01-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-01-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="1"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1">
                <head>1. Memorandum From the Deputy Director for Coordination, Bureau of
                    Intelligence and Research (<persName type="from">Scott</persName>) to the <gloss
                        type="to">Special Group</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d1fn1">Source: Department of State,<gloss
                            target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/IL Historical Files, Special Group
                        Meetings. Secret; Eyes Only.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-01-17">January 17, 1964</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Report of the Subcommittee on United States Support of Foreign
                        Paramilitary Forces</item>
                </list>
                <p>At a meeting of the Special Group (5412) on November 14, 1963,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d1fn2">A memorandum of that meeting is ibid.</note> General
                        <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> proposed that an ad hoc
                    subcommittee be formed to review United States programs involving support of
                    foreign paramilitary forces. Fourteen countries were listed as having internal
                    security problems and having received U.S. support for paramilitary
                    organizations. Of these fourteen countries, however, only two (Laos [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line of source not declassified</hi>]) are now
                    receiving covert U.S. support for their paramilitary forces. The remaining
                    twelve countries receive overt U.S. support for their paramilitary forces.
                    Accordingly, the ad hoc subcommittee has limited itself to a review of the
                    covert paramilitary support programs in Laos [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line
                        of source not declassified</hi>]. Reports on these programs are attached at
                    Tabs I and II,<note n="3" xml:id="d1fn3">Tab II is not printed.</note>
                    respectively.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Paramilitary forces being aided by the U.S. covertly in Laos [<hi rend="italic"
                        >less than 1 line of source not declassified</hi>] are remote from the urban
                    centers, diffused throughout rural areas, and small in number in relation to the
                    regular <pb facs="0034" n="2" xml:id="pg_2"/> military forces. Consequently,
                    they are unlikely to develop into power centers rivalling the established
                    governments or to be involved directly as a major influence in a struggle for
                    power in the foreseeable future. Aid given to Lao [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                        line of source not declassified</hi>] paramilitary forces has not lessened
                    the confidence of these governments in the United States or been inimical to
                    United States interests.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Subcommittee recommends that the Special Group (5412): <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Accept this report on covert United States aid to paramilitary
                            organizations in Laos [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source not
                                declassified</hi>]; and</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Refer overt United States programs of paramilitary assistance
                            supported by <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> and <gloss
                                target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> in the remaining countries listed in
                            the minutes of the meeting of the Special Group (5412) on November 14,
                            1963, to the Special Group (Counterinsurgency) with the suggestion that
                            it review these programs in the light of General <persName
                                corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>’s memorandum on this subject,
                            dated October 15, 1963.<note n="4" xml:id="d1fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>’s memorandum of
                                October 15, 1963, has not been found. The Special Group accepted
                                these recommendations at its meeting of January 23. (Department of
                                State, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>/IL Historical Files,
                                Special Group Meetings)</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName>Joseph Scott</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Tab I</head>
                    <p rend="center">Laos</p>
                    <p>The U.S. is engaged in overt and covert support to paramilitary forces in
                        Laos but in large part the elements being aided are remote from the centers
                        of power and unlikely to be involved in any future power struggle. Military
                        assistance is being provided overtly to the regular non-communist forces, at
                        the request and with the approval of Prime Minister Prince <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>. These regular forces
                        include the conservative Forces Armees du Royaume (<gloss target="#t_FAR1"
                            >FAR</gloss>) under General <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                        and the neutralist forces loyal to Prince <persName corresp="#p_SPP1"
                            >Souvanna Phouma</persName> under <persName corresp="#p_KLG1">General
                            Kong Le</persName>. This overt assistance is in accordance with Article
                        6 of the Protocol of the Geneva Agreements, although we attempt to avoid
                        publicizing it.</p>
                    <p>Covert support is given to paramilitary guerrilla and intelligence collecting
                        groups which consist primarily of tribal members. General <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> is, in general, familiar with our
                        assistance to these groups but not in detail. Although Prince Souvanna is
                        generally aware of our activities in this area, he is less so than <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>.</p>
                    <pb facs="0035" n="3" xml:id="pg_3"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Paramilitary Forces</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The principal paramilitary forces in Laos are those receiving covert U.S.
                        support through <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>. In addition, however,
                        certain organizations of the <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> can be
                        considered to have a paramilitary character. These are the Auto Defense de
                        Choc (ADC) units and the Directorate of National Coordination (<gloss
                            target="#t_DNC1">DNC</gloss>).</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> Supported Covert Paramilitary
                            Program</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The genesis of this program stems from high level U.S. Government approval in
                        late 1960 and early 1961 in response to a recommendation by the U.S.
                        Ambassador in Laos that <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> enlist tribal
                        support to fight communism. The main effort in this program has been
                        development of the Meo, the largest non-Lao ethnic group in Laos, as an
                        effective guerrilla force and the provision of plausibly deniable U.S. air
                        support for the program.</p>
                    <p>Since the program’s inception <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has worked
                        with the two key Meo leaders, Touby Lyfong and <persName corresp="#p_VP1"
                            >Vang Pao</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_VP1">Vang Pao</persName>,
                        the commander of the Meo forces, is a regular <gloss target="#t_FAR1"
                            >FAR</gloss> officer and the Meo forces are technically considered to be
                            <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> ADC units. As authorized by the
                        Special Group in June 1963, this program has expanded to a present force of
                        approximately 19,000 armed Meo guerrillas (23,000 authorized) engaged in
                        village defense and guerrilla activities against the Pathet Lao. [<hi
                            rend="italic">7 lines of source text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                    <p>In addition to the Meos, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has developed,
                        with Special Group approval, paramilitary and intelligence assets among the
                        Yaos in northwest Laos (currently 1700; 2500 authorized) and the Khas in
                        south Laos (currently 400; 1,000 authorized) and Lao in central Laos
                        (currently 1,200; 2,000 authorized). The latter assets (Lao in central Laos)
                        operate under <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> cover.</p>
                    <p>In support of the above forces <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has
                        employed covert air support designed to fulfill resupply requirements, as
                        well as meet <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> and neutralist paramilitary
                        and military requirements. This air support, conducted by an ostensibly
                        private and commercial company, has been able to continue operations in Laos
                        under <gloss target="#t_USAID1">USAID</gloss> contractual arrangements and
                        through the flexibility of <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>’s cover and
                        funding mechanisms.</p>
                    <p>During the development, employment and support of the above covert tribal
                        paramilitary program in Laos, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> has
                        provided World War II weapons and associated ammunition; salary and
                        subsistence and miscellaneous support items. The budget for the Laos tribal
                        program for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1963 was $11,625,000 and for
                            <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1964 $14,008,000.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">ADC</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> ADC units, which are not part of the
                        Meo ADC force, have a total strength of about 9,000 and are essentially home
                        guard or militia-type <pb facs="0036" n="4" xml:id="pg_4"/> military units
                        concerned with local village or urban defense. On occasion, however, they
                        have been used as regular forces. The ADC’s are considered to be part of the
                            <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> and come under its organizational
                        command. Thus, General Phoumi controls these units, as he does the regular
                            <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> troops. <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> provides some support to the ADC’s from US military
                        assistance but the amount is probably minimal. The neutralists have also
                        begun recently to develop some ADC elements which will presumably be
                        controlled and maintained by the regular neutralist forces under <persName
                            corresp="#p_KLG1">Kong Le</persName>.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_DNC1">DNC</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Directorate of National Coordination is an organization of the <gloss
                            target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> charged primarily with security and police
                        responsibilities. (A national police force has not been reconstituted as
                        yet.) In addition to acting as the police force in Vientiane and other
                        areas, the <gloss target="#t_DNC1">DNC</gloss> is engaged in intelligence,
                        customs and border control activities on behalf of the <gloss
                            target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_DNC1">DNC</gloss> units
                        are stationed in the few cities and large towns and penetrate slightly into
                        the country side in scattered gendarmerie posts of four or five men. The
                            <gloss target="#t_DNC1">DNC</gloss> numbers some 7,800 men under Col.
                        Siho, of which 3,600 are engaged in police and 4,200 in military-type
                        activities. Three battalions of the latter in the Vientiane area are the
                        most important elements of the <gloss target="#t_DNC1">DNC</gloss> in terms
                        of any political involvement. As part of the <gloss target="#t_FAR1"
                            >FAR</gloss> and because of <persName corresp="#p_SL1">Siho</persName>’s
                        relationship with him, General <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                        controls the <gloss target="#t_DNC1">DNC</gloss>.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Power Rivalries</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The basic power rivalry in Laos is between the pro-Communist Pathet Lao
                            (<gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>) and the non-Communist Lao. Although
                        rivalries continue to exist between the neutralist and conservative
                        factions, the aggressive <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> posture toward
                        the neutralists since a year ago has resulted in a more cooperative
                        neutralist-conservative relationship, especially between Souvanna and
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>, and also between the
                        military in the field. Rivalries also exist within each of the two
                        non-Communist factions. Growing restiveness has been reported within
                        conservative ranks. It is generally recognized, however, that any attempt to
                        create a new power alignment among the non-Communist leadership requires
                        U.S. support if it is to succeed. We have made our position clear to all
                        concerned that the U.S. continues to support Prime Minister Souvanna and the
                        Geneva settlement and we consider any changes in the existing setup inimical
                        to U.S. and Lao interests.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, the danger always exists that some ambitious or misled group
                        might attempt to upset the present fragile balance. A coup attempt could,
                        for example, come from within the <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> ranks
                        by generals disillusioned with <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                        >Phoumi</persName>’s leadership. It could also result from a power play by
                        Col. <persName corresp="#p_SL1">Siho</persName> and the <gloss
                            target="#t_DNC1">DNC</gloss>, although this would probably require <pb
                            facs="0037" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/> support by other <gloss
                            target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> elements. General <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> claims to have the situation under
                        control. We can expect, however, to continue to hear rumors about such coup
                        plotting. In addition, rivalries between neutralist military leaders will
                        continue to produce rumors about efforts of one neutralist group to gain
                        ascendancy over <persName corresp="#p_KLG1">Kong Le</persName>’s position.
                        These moves, however, among conservative or neutralist groups, involve
                        primarily regular military forces.</p>
                    <p>The danger of an attempt to gain power by the principal paramilitary group,
                        the Meo, is more remote. The Meo, as all tribal groups in Laos, are isolated
                        from the country’s political arena and are not integrated into Lao society.
                        They are located away from the main centers of the country, living in
                        scattered villages at the higher elevations (the Yao and Kha tribal groups
                        are even more isolated and too few in number to pose a threat). Moreover,
                        the Meo are subject to U.S. guidance and direction. The development of the
                        Meo as a rival center of armed power with political objectives in a national
                        Lao context does not seem to be a realistic possibility. The main problem
                        posed by the Meo, and all other tribal groups in Laos, is the need for their
                        eventual integration into Lao society and identification with the Lao
                        nation. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> is beginning to
                        recognize this, as is Meo leader <persName corresp="#p_VP1">Vang
                            Pao</persName> who has recently also established a working relationship
                        with <persName corresp="#p_KLG1">Kong Le</persName> in the Plaine des Jarres
                        area. Other Lao leaders, however, including Souvanna, continue to view the
                        Meo and other tribal peoples in the traditional Lao manner of the tribal
                        people being separate and apart from the Lao. Souvanna even seems to feel
                        that military support for the Meo could lead to a greater autonomous status
                        for them. He has expressed opposition to the use of Thai in support of the
                        Meo. In terms of U.S. interests, however, the Meo will continue to play an
                        essential and useful military role as an anti-Communist guerrilla force. At
                        the same time it is important to continue efforts to impress on the Meo the
                        need for national identification with Laos and the Lao government. The first
                        steps in this respect give some reason for encouragement, although a better
                        relationship with and acceptance by Souvanna is still essential.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
