<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>108. Memorandum From the Director of the Bureau of Intelligence and Research
                    (Hughes) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d108</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">108</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recDV1FNGQhoilizZ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90000897"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconstitution</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recyb5QQsNI4WeVPs" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military capabilities</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="108"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d108">
                <head>108. Memorandum From the Director of the Bureau of Intelligence and Research
                        (<persName corresp="#p_HTL1" type="from">Hughes</persName>) to Secretary of
                    State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="to">Rusk</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d108fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Country File, Laos, Vol. VII, Memos, 7/64. Secret; No Foreign
                        Dissem.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">RFE–47</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-07-01">July 1, 1964</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Laos: The Situation and our Options</item>
                </list>
                <p>We have attempted to weigh US options in Laos against the background of the
                    changes that have occurred there over the past year. The courses of action open
                    to us fall into four general categories: 1) continuing in our present stance; 2)
                    attempting to reconstitute the neutral solution; 3) opting for formal or “hard”
                    partition essentially along present lines of control; and 4) seeking this
                    partition with expanded non-Communist territorial holdings.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Although, in many respects, the situation we now face in Laos is similar to that
                    of twelve months ago, certain differences alter our position and outlook: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>The neutralists’ status has changed markedly. The April coup has
                            undermined Souvanna’s position as a neutral, although the unravelling of
                            the coup under international pressure may have strengthened him somewhat
                            in his role as leader of all non-Communist forces. Militarily, the
                            territorial base of <persName corresp="#p_KLG1">Kong Le</persName>’s
                            neutralist forces is all but lost.</item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>The image of the Vientiane government as a three forces coalition has
                            eroded further. The Pathet Lao, continuing to reject Souvanna’s right to
                            take action as head of the national government in the absence of
                            unanimous agreement by all three parties, has charged that Souvanna is a
                            captive of the right and the United States. It has declared that it
                            cannot regard him as premier as long as he continues on his present
                            course, and has announced that it will withdraw its entire
                            representation from Vientiane. Souvanna has designated non-Communists to
                            act for the long-absent Pathet Lao cabinet members without formally
                            replacing them. The possibility that the Communists are prepared at a
                            time of their own choosing to establish a rival government is suggested
                            by reports that they have organized a “true” neutralist-Pathet Lao
                            shadow government.</item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>The right wing has become both more militant and more fractured.
                            Differences between Phoumi and the Sannanikones have come closer to the
                            surface and <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>’s power
                            position is something of an enigma.</item>
                        <pb facs="0254" n="222" xml:id="pg_222"/>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>There have been further defections from <persName corresp="#p_KLG1"
                                >Kong Le</persName>’s forces to the “true” neutralists. Khamouane
                            Boupha also appears to have allied himself with the “true” neutralists.
                            Should the Pathet Lao attempt to portray their neutralists as the sole
                            remaining neutralist faction, the adherence of Khamouane Boupha with his
                            territorial base in Phong Saly and his control of 1500 troops could lend
                            greater credibility to their claims.</item>
                        <label>5)</label>
                        <item>The Pathet Lao, with North Vietnamese support, have extended their
                            control over almost all of the territory they occupied jointly with the
                            neutralists before 1962. They have also done considerable damage to the
                            Meo. We continue to believe, however, that they do not propose to move
                            to the Mekong at this juncture.</item>
                        <label>6)</label>
                        <item>The United States, to the limited degree implied by our air
                            activities, has become an open military participant in the
                            hostilities.</item>
                        <label>7)</label>
                        <item>North Vietnam has responded to American escalation signals by
                            expressing its determination to defend itself and by practical defensive
                            measures. However, even if Asian Communist demands for reconvening the
                            Geneva Conference primarily reflect fear of escalation, this fear has
                            not yet caused them to modify their negotiating terms nor is it yet
                            clear that they have abandoned their military advance in Laos.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Prospects</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Together these developments certainly make it even more difficult to sustain the
                    argument that Laos can be effectively neutralized by international action. To
                    some degree also, the real world of Laos has been altered in that the de facto
                    partition has been geographically sharpened by the Communist advance in the
                    Plaine des Jarres and the consequent removal from most of that area of
                    neutralist forces formerly intermingled with the Pathet Lao. Whether the closer
                    relationship that has developed between the right and the neutralists
                    constitutes a corresponding advantage for us is open to some question; the
                    relationship is a tenuous one at best.</p>
                <p>These alterations, however, do not eliminate the prospect, which is indeed
                    fortified by the advent of the rainy season, that we are in for another period
                    of stalemated negotiations and relative military quiet.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Our Options—The Present Course</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Under these circumstances, we have the option of accepting Laotian marching and
                    countermarching as tolerable since our vital interests lie in Vietnam and
                    friendly forces hold the Mekong. This stance, in essence a continuation of the
                    posture we have adopted to date, permits us to claim the support of the Geneva
                    Accords for Souvanna as Prime Minister and thereby justify our assistance to
                    him. Our continued diplomatic activity and limited retaliatory measures will
                    probably keep credible our Mekong deterrent. This will spur Moscow to use what
                    little leverage it has to keep Laos below the boiling point.</p>
                <pb facs="0255" n="223" xml:id="pg_223"/>
                <p>Meanwhile, we can continue to press for effective utilization of the Geneva
                    machinery and support Souvanna’s efforts to secure acceptable terms from the
                    Pathet Lao through our diplomatic and military moves. By pushing for full
                    implementation of the Geneva Accords, we will maintain credit with those
                    neutrals and allies who are anxious to avoid a further spread of hostilities.
                    Our own military involvement and commitment would thus remain at a low
                    level.</p>
                <p>As time goes on, however, particularly if Pathet Lao territorial nibblings are
                    not met with at least some successful <gloss target="#t_FAR1"
                    >FAR</gloss>/neutralist counter nibbles, morale in Vientiane may reach a
                    critical point. Souvanna’s position at this stage may present us with one of two
                    problems. If he continues his present militancy, he may demand US moves that
                    will destroy the uneasy status quo or destroy it himself by leaving the scene.
                    If, on the other hand, he tolerates continuing the status quo with only limited
                    retaliatory measures against the Communists, he will face moves from the right
                    to overthrow him which, if successful, would intensify the pressures on the
                    United States to alter its stance.</p>
                <p>We will face also the problem of adjusting our interventions on behalf of
                    friendly forces to meet two somewhat conflicting objectives: maintaining the
                    plausibility of our ultimate deterrent and avoiding premature escalation. This
                    problem is likely to grow progressively more difficult and acute. On the one
                    hand, restraint may make our actions ineffectual, with all the obvious impact on
                    Lao morale and on domestic and international opinion. On the other hand, we will
                    be uncertain whether moves of greater force will induce Communist restraint or a
                    sharply-increased response. In any case we will remain under continuing
                    pressures to accept a new Geneva Conference. Moreover, these pressures will
                    increase in direct ratio to the threat of escalation of US and Chinese Communist
                    involvement.</p>
                <p>The difficulties and frustrations of this stance have been amply demonstrated
                    over the past two years. It remains an open question, however, whether other
                    courses would be both feasible and more profitable. Omitting measures focused
                    essentially outside Laos, which in any case would have to be directly related to
                    measures within Laos itself, alternative policies fall into two general
                    categories: a concerted effort to reconstitute the neutral solution; or a more
                    open acceptance and exploitation of the partition.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">A Reconstituted Neutral Solution</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In our present stance, reconstitution of the neutral solution remains our
                    ostensible objective. However, existing circumstances make achievement of this
                    objective highly unlikely. As the contenders are now disposed, restoration of
                    the tripartite government in any real sense would require concessions
                    unacceptable to one side or the other. For Souvanna at this juncture to
                    disassociate himself from the right in terms acceptable <pb facs="0256" n="224"
                        xml:id="pg_224"/> to the Pathet Lao would require him in effect to surrender
                    a position that he has reached with our encouragement over a considerable period
                    of time. Any alternative leader prepared to abandon this position would be
                    difficult to find outside the ranks of pro-Pathet Lao neutralists who would be
                    unacceptable to the right. Even if Souvanna were prepared to abandon his
                    position, moreover, it is difficult to see how he could secure right-wing
                    acquiescence; another coup in Vientiane would thus become highly likely. If we
                    acceded to Souvanna’s abandonment of his terms and increased the pressures on
                    the right to acquiesce, this reversal of our public position would call into
                    question our basic resolve, particularly in the minds of the Thai and South
                    Vietnamese.</p>
                <p>For the Pathet Lao and their Chinese and Vietnamese supporters, on the other
                    hand, Souvanna’s present terms can hold no interest unless rejecting them
                    presents unacceptable dangers. It is possible, although unlikely, that the
                    cumulative effects of our present air activities could induce the Communists to
                    modify their current stance in order to secure a recess that would leave open
                    the possibility of forward movement at a later date. <persName
                        corresp="#p_Souphanouvong1">Souphanouvong</persName>’s apparent acceptance
                    of the Polish proposal for tripartite negotiations may be a move in this
                    direction. It is more likely, however, that to raise the level of threat and to
                    bring about effective Soviet leverage would require US military intervention on
                    a considerably more substantial scale. At best, this intervention on behalf of
                    the neutral solution could lend credence to the viability and defensibility of
                    that solution, restore the territorial balance (perhaps more fully observed and
                    effectively policed) and restore the tripartite stalemate in Vientiane. At
                    worst, it could lead to prolonged hostilities and higher levels of outside
                    Communist support for the Pathet Lao, with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss> constrained to provide at least diplomatic and propaganda
                    backing for the Communist side. Between these extremes, and perhaps most likely,
                    we could anticipate intensified pressures for an immediate, unconditional
                    reconvocation of the Geneva signatories.</p>
                <p>Weighing the risks of this course against the very limited likely advantages
                    suggests that if American military power is to be applied on any significant
                    scale in Laos it should be in pursuit of broader objectives than those
                    attainable through an effort to reconstitute a neutral solution, which has not
                    proved successful in the past and which holds little prospect for greater
                    success in the future.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Exploitation of Partition—Present Territorial
                        Arrangements</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As a result of military action over the past year there is now less intermingling
                    of friendly and hostile forces and, therefore, a somewhat more coherent
                    territorial base for the transformation of the “soft” partition that has existed
                    in Laos since the signing of the Geneva Accords into a more formal division
                    under rival regimes. There is also some possibility that both Souvanna, now
                    completely disenchanted with the Communists, <pb facs="0257" n="225"
                        xml:id="pg_225"/> and the Pathet Lao, close to a break with Souvanna and in
                    a stronger territorial position, might find such a division more attractive than
                    would have been the case a year ago. However, a “hard” partition on the basis of
                    present territorial holdings would be of questionable advantage to the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>The principal area in which friendly and Communist forces were intermingled—the
                    Plaine des Jarres—has now come largely under Communist control and is unlikely
                    to be negotiable. Intermingling remains a problem south of Luang Prabang and
                    south and west of the Mekong between Ban Houei Sai and Luang Prabang.
                    Territorial adjustments in this area have been largely in favor of friendly
                    forces and, under a partition proposal, shifts might be negotiable. Khammouane
                    Boupha’s sector of Phong Saly, however, would probably move from its present
                    still somewhat anomalous status to complete identification with the Pathet Lao
                    side. Meo positions are almost entirely within Pathet Lao territory, and the Meo
                    would be difficult if not impossible to move to another area as a fighting
                    force.</p>
                <p>Without the Plaine des Jarres, <gloss target="#t_RLG1">RLG</gloss> territorial
                    holdings would be more compactly disposed, more defensible by Lao forces, and
                    more effectively fortified by conventional means against further nibbling. Were
                    we, however, to initiate or accept a firm partition after having lost the
                    Plaine, we would be seen as moving or reacting from weakness and the
                    plausibility of our Mekong deterrent, although not necessarily weakened, would
                    certainly not be enhanced.</p>
                <p>Under such partition, we might wish to continue to uphold the concept of
                    international neutrality for our zone in Laos, without, however, compromising
                    its right to request and receive defensive support from friendly powers. This
                    stance would offer the prospect of maximizing international acceptability and
                    support of a reconstituted Royal Lao Government and might even provide some
                    basis for the continued use of the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>, at least
                    as a device to keep its members involved in the Laos problem and to publicize
                    Communist violations. In a partitioned Laos, however, efforts by us to maintain
                    Souvanna’s position against erosion from the right could no longer rely so
                    completely upon the importance of his international acceptability, with the
                    danger that our role in Lao internal arrangements would be more vulnerable to
                    charges of external dictation. At the same time, the retention of Souvanna
                    himself in this situation would be less vital to our interests, particularly
                    after a successful transition had been made to the new arrangements, although
                    the problem of coming forward with a competent successor able to unify the
                    various factions will remain. In any event our involvement with the Lao
                    government would be likely to increase, with past performance holding little
                    promise that even the complete elimination of the Pathet Lao factor in the <pb
                        facs="0258" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/> non-Communist zone would result in a
                    government notably more united, dedicated, or capable.</p>
                <p>Although the complete collapse of the Geneva arrangements might remove formal
                    restraints on our assistance to the Vientiane government, the practical effects
                    of this removal could be rather limited except insofar as we wished to inject
                    our own or Thai and perhaps other ground forces. Already Souvanna has been
                    willing to legitimize a fairly wide range of overt military assistance. Such Meo
                    and similar activities as we wished to continue in the Pathet Lao zone would
                    require covert support in any case, and there are distinct limitations on the
                    amount of assistance that <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> and neutralist
                    forces themselves can absorb.</p>
                <p>Partition of Laos on this basis would provide no more real protection against
                    subversion than did the partition of Vietnam in 1954, the question here being
                    whether the Pathet Lao supported by the North Vietnamese would be as effective
                    in this role as the Viet Cong. Certainly the long border, approximately 1,000
                    miles, could not be closed effectively against infiltration from the Communist
                    side.</p>
                <p>Finally, partition of Laos along existing territorial lines would leave the
                    Communists in control of the corridor into South Vietnam. As the same time, in
                    considering operations to restrict Communist use of the corridor based in South
                    Vietnam or elsewhere, we would no longer need to be restrained by the effects of
                    such operations upon tripartite arrangements in Laos.</p>
                <p>Exploitation of Partition—New Territorial Arrangements</p>
                <p>To establish a partition based on territorial arrangements other than those that
                    now exist would almost certainly require the intervention of United States
                    forces on some significant scale, especially if the territorial arrangement were
                    to be genuinely advantageous. To be advantageous in a partition, such an
                    arrangement should be the Mekong Valley plus the panhandle rather than the
                    Mekong Valley plus the Plaine des Jarres.</p>
                <p>In our contingency planning of the past, a move into the panhandle has usually
                    been envisaged as a response to a clear Communist military threat to the Mekong.
                    If, however, the panhandle is seen as seizable and worth seizing in the
                    interests of our position in Vietnam, it is questionable whether we benefit by
                    waiting for the Communists to provide us with a trigger only to maximize the
                    international legitimacy of our position. Our posture, for some time, has
                    communicated our determination to move more decisively if necessary to protect
                    the Royal Lao Government and South Vietnam. We have the evidence on which to
                    present a strong case against Communist violations of the Geneva Accords.
                    Moreover, for many of the countries making up the numerical majority in the
                    world community, the <pb facs="0259" n="227" xml:id="pg_227"/> question is not
                    so much who is right in Indochina as who is likely to win. For our allies, as
                    well as for friendly neutrals, the question is not so much whether the United
                    States should apply its power more forcefully as it is whether there are means
                    of applying this power that we are prepared to employ and that can be effective
                    in stemming the Communist advance without precipitating major hostilities.
                    Especially, for those countries that might be expected to participate usefully
                    in our action to greater or less degree—Thailand, the GVN, the Philippines, the
                    United Kingdom, and Australia—the most significant issues are thus those of
                    scope and effectiveness.</p>
                <p>We could certainly expect a vigorous Communist response to an effort to seize the
                    panhandle, including: a significantly greater use of North Vietnamese forces, an
                    enhanced supply effort, and, simultaneously, redoubled appeals for an immediate
                    Geneva Conference backed with threats of further escalation. If, however, our
                    advance were to go no further north than would be required to secure the Pathet
                    Lao road net fanning out of the Mu Ghia Pass, we would not be posing a direct
                    threat to vital North Vietnamese or Chinese Communist territory and would
                    thereby minimize the prospect of a genuinely escalatory military reaction.</p>
                <p>If we were to embark upon such an action we would of course have to accept the
                    indefinite commitment of United States ground forces, in an area that lends
                    itself by terrain and forest cover to prolonged and effective guerrilla
                    resistance. By the same token, although reducing infiltration into South
                    Vietnam, we probably would be unable to seal it off completely and infiltration
                    efforts through other routes (e.g., the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>, the
                    sea, and Cambodia) would continue. Finally, the effect of interdiction of
                    infiltration routes on the Viet Cong effort would be primarily psychological
                    and, in terms of military capabilities, long-run rather than immediate, and
                    would not provide a substitute for more vigorous and successful
                    politico-military action in South Vietnam itself.</p>
                <p>Our ability to seize, hold, and at least partially seal the panhandle, even
                    though not significantly reducing Viet Cong capability in the short-run, could
                    bolster morale in South Vietnam as evidence of effective action against the
                    enemy in what has become his territory. Similarly Thai confidence in our
                    intentions and capabilities would be reinforced and there might be some positive
                    impact also on defeatist “wave of the future” attitudes elsewhere in Asia. At
                    the same time, there would exist the danger of becoming involved in a prolonged
                    and inconclusive campaign—not to speak of a failure—which would tend to
                    reinforce the belief that a Western power, if it denies itself its ultimate
                    weapons, is ineffective against a determined military/subversive campaign in
                    areas bordering on Communist Asia.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
