<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-02-26T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-02-26T04:00:00-05:00" n="168" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d168">
                        <head>168. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Laos</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d168fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, POL 27 VIET S. Top Secret; Priority; Exdis. Repeated to
                                Bangkok, Saigon, <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>, sent
                                with instructions that the Department pass a copy to the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> and Saigon a copy to <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Vientiane</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-02-26T16:00:00+07:00">February 26, 1965, 4
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>1365. During recent <gloss target="#t_SEACOORD1">SEACOORD</gloss>
                                meeting,<note n="2" xml:id="d168fn2">Reference is to the <gloss target="#t_SEACOORD1">SEACOORD</gloss> meeting of February
                                22–23, reports of which are in telegram 2771 from Saigon, February
                                23, and telegram 1347 from Vientiane, February 23. (Both
                                ibid.)</note> General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> showed me copy of message he had sent
                                <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> February 13<note n="3" xml:id="d168fn3">Not found.</note> recommending coordinated package
                            of operations against <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>. In this
                            message, he suggested that Rolling Thunder, 34–A, <gloss target="#t_BarrelRoll1">Barrel Roll</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_YankeeTeam1">Yankee Team</gloss> operations be
                            consolidated into single program.</p>
                        <p>While I fully sympathize with General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>’s desire have orchestrated operations in
                                <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> to include armed route
                            reconnaissance and low/medium level photography, I wish enter note of
                            caution insofar as his proposal may be interpreted as desire extend
                            current <gloss target="#t_BarrelRoll1">Barrel Roll</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_YankeeTeam1">Yankee Team</gloss> operations from Laos
                            into <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>. I have discussed this matter
                            with General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> and
                            have advised him of my intention write this message. I think he and I
                            are in agreement on this subject but do not presume speak for him in
                            this message. He will doubtless wish comment separately.</p>
                        <p>Problem in brief is as follows: Laos, unlike South Vietnam, is incapable
                            protecting itself against ground action by <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> and does not have US commitment assure such protection.
                            It therefore becomes highly important to Souvanna to be able to state
                            that his territory and air space are not being used for actions against
                                <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>. If he can maintain this
                            posture, he believes he will have continuing general support from Soviet
                            Union and its support will provide check against overt <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> incursions into Laos. Fragile as this
                            belief may be, we must accept it as basic element Souvanna’s outlook and
                            respect it if we are to expect his continued cooperation in other
                            enterprises this area.</p>
                        <p>He has no objection to massive US punishment of <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> within <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> itself. He
                            has no objection to clandestine US punishment of <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> and Pathet Lao within Laos. However, he strictly
                            insists two must be kept separate so that he can maintain aforementioned
                            sophistry of innocence in his international dealings, particularly with
                            Soviets. This is a very tricky balance, but one which I think we can
                            respect with a little extra effort on our part.</p>
                        <pb facs="0371" n="339" xml:id="pg_339"/>
                        <p>To maintain this respect, I would therefore take exception to concept of
                            extending <gloss target="#t_BarrelRoll1">Barrel Roll</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_YankeeTeam1">Yankee Team</gloss> into <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>. These two programs were developed for
                            operations exclusively in Laos, and I believe tricky nature our
                            operations require them to stay (however artificially) in that same
                            compartment. If armed <gloss target="#t_recce1">recce</gloss> and
                            low/medium level photography programs established for DRV, I believe
                            they should be separate from Lao programs and not ignore international
                            boundary between Laos and <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Partly because of need preserve this artificial distinction as well as
                            because of material advantages to be gained, I have welcomed <gloss target="#t_PACAF1">PACAF</gloss> proposals establish <gloss target="#t_YankeeTeam1">Yankee Team</gloss> out of Udorn. It seems
                            to me that this small group of aircraft and pilots, operating
                            exclusively over Laos, will develop special skills which will materially
                            improve the quality of intelligence we accumulate here.</p>
                        <p>The thought arises, although I will not advance it here, that there might
                            be some prospect for compartmentalizing and specializing <gloss target="#t_BarrelRoll1">Barrel Roll</gloss> in this same manner.
                            Especially as Rolling Thunder program gains momentum and occupies both
                            Second Air Divison and Fleet air assets, it may be of some value to
                            designate some separate unit, to be based in Thailand, for specific
                            purpose conducting our relatively modest <gloss target="#t_BarrelRoll1">Barrel Roll</gloss> program. As layman, I have been impressed with
                            capabilities of A–1–H aircraft in <gloss target="#t_BarrelRoll1">Barrel
                                Roll</gloss> operations, and particularly with their ability
                            (relative to jets) to absorb anti-aircraft damage. This factor is of
                            significant concern to us in connection with our <gloss target="#t_SAR1">SAR</gloss> responsibilities, which we take very seriously. I won’t
                            ask in this message whether there would be an A–1–H equipped marine air
                            unit available for such duty, since I feel this would be unwarranted
                            intrusion into the very complex problem of US air dispositions in this
                            overall theater, something well beyond our perspective as we peer out
                            from the jungle canopy of Laos. However, from our very limited
                            perspective, such a disposition would have its attractions.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Sullivan</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>