<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-04-19T10:10:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-04-19T10:10:00-05:00" n="23" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                        <head>23. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d23fn1">Source: Johnson Library, <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">John
                                    McCone</persName> Memoranda, Meetings with the President,
                                4/30/64–5/20/64. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">Colby</persName> on April 20, who mistakenly characterized this
                                as an <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting. It was not an
                                official numbered meeting of the National Security Council.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-04-19T10:10:00-05:00">April 19, 1964, 10:10
                                    a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>National Security Council Meeting—19 April 1964</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>The President</item>
                            <item>State: Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, Deputy Under Secretary
                                    <persName>Johnson</persName>, Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BGM1">Barbis</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Defense: Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, General <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNJT1">McNaughton</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>White House: Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                                    Bundy</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FMV1">Forrestal</persName>, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SAE1">Stevenson</persName> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>: Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">Colby</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Prior to the President’s arrival there was a discussion of the
                                traffic from Laos and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGM1">Barbis</persName> gave a short review of the 1958–1960 series
                                of Lao coups. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>
                                identified the basic question as one of determining a U.S. position
                                which would disassociate ourselves from the coup but at the same
                                time not encourage the Pathet Lao and Vietnamese to move against the
                                Lao Government. Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> asked what pressures
                                we have on the Right Wing and it was agreed we had considerable
                                power but that our experience had shown it could not be exercised in
                                the short term.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The President then entered. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> briefed him on the situation and the basic
                                problem of disassociating ourselves without inviting action by the
                                Communists. He pointed out the State Department release of Saturday
                                night deploring the coup<note n="2" xml:id="d23fn2">See <ref target="#d22fn2">footnote 2, Document 22</ref>.</note> and
                                commented that we were in the process of making approaches to other
                                governments involved in the Geneva Agreements to reiterate our
                                non-involvement.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The President suggested that Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> who is
                                in Saigon be sent to Vientiane for a first hand look prior to his
                                return to Washington. He commented that he agreed with the U.S.
                                support of the Geneva Agreements but that he would not do much
                                urging of action until we see the situation more clearly than we do
                                now. He returned to this point several times during the meeting,
                                indicating some displeasure with the final sentence of State’s
                                    release.<note n="3" xml:id="d23fn3">The final sentence of the
                                    release reads: “We are therefore categorically opposed to any
                                    seizure of power and are urging immediate release of neutralists
                                    as a first step to restoring the situation.”</note> He stated he
                                agreed that some word should be <pb facs="0077" n="45" xml:id="pg_45"/> gotten to Hanoi to hold them back from any idea
                                of moving in Laos. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> mentioned the possibility of some involvement
                                of General <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> in the
                                course of the <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                                discussions about two weeks ago.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The President also agreed that we take the position with the other
                                Geneva powers that the cease-fire in Laos must be maintained and he
                                agreed that other governments be approached, especially the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>, along these lines. He then asked
                                that recommendations for action be prepared by Mr.
                                    <persName>Bundy</persName> in conjunction with Ambassador
                                    <persName corresp="#p_UL1">Unger</persName> and that meanwhile
                                no other public statements be made.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The President then departed and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> requested that the group remain for a
                                general review of the problem. It was pointed out that the balance
                                of forces in Laos generally favored the Pathet Lao with their Viet
                                Minh cadres but General <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> stated that he did not expect any immediate
                                full scale move which would involve Viet Minh units. The <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> was believed by General <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> not to be much better than
                                it ever was, despite some reports of improvement we have heard in
                                the past. <persName corresp="#p_KLG1">Kong Le</persName> offers more
                                a political than a military force. The chances of substantial
                                support to the non-communists from Thailand or South Vietnam were
                                not considered great. Among the actions considered were the
                                possibility of reinforcing the Thais with a U.S. unit (which it was
                                agreed was complicated as the Thais would exact some assurances on
                                our policy in Laos), and the movement of U.S. naval units off North
                                Vietnam. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>
                                suggested that we tie our actions in Laos to the public discussion
                                of possible action against North Vietnam, which he believed has a
                                useful effect on the Communists.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>There was then some discussion as to whether it would be possible
                                to restore a neutral government in Laos or whether it would develop
                                into a formal partition. It was agreed that the assistance of the
                                King should be sought but that no great hopes could rest upon him,
                                and that one of the critical figures was <persName corresp="#p_KLG1">Kong Le</persName>.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> summarized the actions required as
                                determining: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>Whether and how we reestablish the neutral solution (i.e.
                                        “put Humpty Dumpty together again”). In this context the
                                        position of <persName corresp="#p_KLG1">Kong Le</persName>
                                        is important.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>The degree of South Vietnamese involvement, encouragement
                                        or potential in the Lao situation.</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>How to maintain the cease-fire, getting word to the
                                        Communist side and especially Hanoi to do so.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>The reactions of our Ambassadors in various countries to
                                        the prospect of a new Geneva meeting on Laos and whether
                                        this would involve Cambodia, Vietnam, etc.</item>
                                    <label>e.</label>
                                    <item>The effects of a formal North-South partition on the
                                        situation in Vietnam, i.e. whether this would substantially
                                        improve the North Vietnamese capabilities of supporting the
                                        Viet Cong.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0078" n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/>
                                    <label>f.</label>
                                    <item>Alerting various intelligence activities to any
                                        indications of early action by the Communist side. In this
                                        context the Department of Defense will ensure a full
                                        coverage by high level reconnaissance on Southeast Laos and
                                            <gloss target="#t_NSA1">NSA</gloss> will be altered to
                                        follow the traffic analysis in Laos and Vietnam.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>After the meeting Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> discussed the problem informally, Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> indicating it
                                might be necessary soon to move to Geneva from a real position of
                                strength with the U.S. fleet pointing at Hai Phong. Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> indicated he
                                agreed with this position.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">WE Colby</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Chief, Far East Division</hi>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>