<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>293. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-06-21T19:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-06-21T22:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-06-21T22:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-06-21T19:15:00-05:00" n="293"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d293">
                <head>293. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d293fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, POL US–<gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Drafted
                        by Stoessel and approved in <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s
                        office on June 27. The dinner meeting was held at the Secretary’s apartment
                        in the Waldorf Towers. The conversation on Laos is one part of seven
                        memoranda of conversation. All are ibid., Kohler Files: Lot 71 D 460,
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                            >Gromyko</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1967-06-21T20:15:00-04:00" to="1967-06-21T23:00:00-04:00"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date">June 21, 1967, 8:15–11 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Secretary’s Dinner for Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                            >Gromyko</persName>: Laos</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Side:</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Ambassador Goldberg</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Walter J. Stoessel, Jr.</persName>, EUR</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Soviet Side:</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">A.A.
                                    Gromyko</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Anatoliy
                                    Dobrynin</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador Nikolai Fedorenko</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Aleksandr Soldatov</persName>, Dep. Minister of Fon.
                                Aff.</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Viktor Sukhodrev</persName>, interpreter</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The Secretary wondered if there were any possibility of solving the situation in
                    Laos. We thought it could be solved in 8 hours. Did Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> see any way to proceed?</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said that the broadening of
                    U.S. interference in Laos is the problem. U.S. aviation and U.S. military
                    activities had increased. He was sorry about the U.S. behavior in Laos, which
                    weakened Soviet arguments for maintaining the Laos agreements. The U.S. knows
                    that the Soviet Union is not in Laos and is not active there.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked if the Soviet Union was prepared to go to 1000% agreement of
                    all parties in Laos.</p>
                <pb facs="0619" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> asked if the U.S. was ready to
                    do so tonight, to which the Secretary replied affirmatively. But, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said, the U.S. is in Laos tonight.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that 6,000 North Vietnamese troops had been left behind in
                    Northern Laos after the agreement had been signed.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said this was one-sided
                    information which he could not accept as factual. However, it was a fact that
                    the U.S. was in Laos. How could the U.S. say it was not interfering?</p>
                <p>The Secretary said it should be understood that if a North Vietnamese division
                    moves into Laos, we will bomb it. We don’t want to do so, but this is what will
                    happen.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said that if the U.S. was not
                    in Laos it could talk of no interference with the observance of the agreement.
                    But the U.S. is in Laos. There is not one Soviet soldier there.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that North Vietnamese troops are there. If we got out, would
                    they get out? He suggested that the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> should
                    use its influence, as co-Chairman, to bring about the departure of the North
                    Vietnamese troops.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said that the U.S. was not a
                    good example for others. At one time, the U.S. was not in Laos openly. We had
                    military personnel there but they were in civilian clothes. Now the U.S.
                    military operates openly. The U.S. is present, and this weakens the Soviet
                    position as co-Chairman, and makes it difficult to use its influence
                    positively.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked if the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would join with
                    the other co-Chairman to get all of the parties out of Laos.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> thought it would be better for
                    the Control Commission to take such responsibility. There are three groups in
                    Laos. They should coordinate their actions better than they do. This difficulty
                    is probably a result of U.S. influence on certain factions. If the U.S. used its
                    influence correctly, there could be better cooperation among the 3.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said it was our understanding of the English text of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>-Pushkin agreement<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d293fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> is apparently referring to the
                        Protocol to the Declaration on the Neutrality of Laos; for text, see
                        American Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1962, pp. 1078–1083.</note> that
                    none of the three powers of the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> could use
                    the veto to restrict <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> activities.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said they had a different
                    interpretation. He continued that the U.S. position on Laos is weak—weaker than
                    before. The U.S. is not only present, but it is present in a new way.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked what Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    thought about the North Vietnamese presence, but Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> said the problem was the United States presence.</p>
                <pb facs="0620" n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/>
                <p>The Secretary said that we had an agreement with the Soviet Union in 1962, but
                    the North Vietnamese didn’t recognize it for a moment.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> thought there should be a
                    discussion between the three groups in Laos. He thought the U.S. had more
                    influence with <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> than the
                    Soviets. It probably was the U.S. which complicated efforts at coordination
                    among the three groups. If one compared the U.S. position in Laos with that of
                    the Soviets, the U.S. position was worse.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said this was not the point. The North Vietnamese are there and
                    that is against the agreement.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, in something of a non
                    sequitur, said that the killing of a well-known leader of one of the political
                    factions—Foreign Minister Pholsena<note n="3" xml:id="d293fn3">Minister Quinim
                        Pholsena was assassinated on April 1, 1963.</note>—had complicated the
                    situation.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said the circumstances of this were unclear. Some said Pholsena had
                    been involved in the assassination of other figures.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> reacted strongly, saying there
                    was not a grain of truth in this story. Had there been an investigation?
                    Pholsena had been a neutralist, a <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna
                        Phouma</persName> man. In any event, the Soviets were sorry that the
                    situation in Laos had become worse. They had wanted agreement. He did not
                    exclude that the Soviets would revert to the Laos problem again.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked why we could not all act to support the original agreement in
                    Laos.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said that the Soviets would be
                    prepared to consider realistic problems without prejudice, but that we should
                    not complicate the situation with false stories. (The latter was apparently in
                    reference to the discussion about Pholsena.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
