<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>95. Memorandum for the Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recLVNRPFsjSN7TW4" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89004334"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contingency plan</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="95"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d95">
                <head>95. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d95fn1">Source:
                        Central Intelligence Agency, DCI (<persName corresp="#p_MCJA1"
                            >McCone</persName>) Files, Job 80–B01285A, Memos for the Record, 6 Apr-8
                        July 1964. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">Colby</persName>
                        on June 16. The meeting lasted from 6 to approximately 7:20 p.m. (Johnson
                        Library, <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> Appointment Book)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-06-15">June 15, 1964</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Executive Committee Meeting on Southeast Asia, 15 June 1964</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, Under Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, Under Secretary
                            <persName>Johnson</persName>, Assistant Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName>, Assistant Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRJ1">Manning</persName>, Assistant Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJH1">Cleveland</persName>, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SWH1"
                            >Sullivan</persName>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="0218" n="186" xml:id="pg_186"/>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, Deputy
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>, General <persName
                            corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>, Assistant Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNJT1">McNaughton</persName>, General <persName
                            corresp="#p_GLGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_FMV1">Forrestal</persName>, Mr. <persName>Cater</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_GWS1">Gaud</persName>, Mr. <persName>Stoneman</persName>,
                        Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WDM1">Don Wilson</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWE1"
                            >Colby</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Concern was expressed about South Vietnamese morale and the need for assurances
                    of U.S. determination. There was some obscurity as to the Country Team position
                    on the eight province program which will be clarified by further cables.</p>
                <p>It was concluded that a Congressional Resolution is not now feasible but that an
                    effort is needed to develop a better base of understanding in the Congress, and
                    support of the Administration’s policy, through speeches. Part of this must come
                    from an increase of third country participation in the struggle in South
                    Vietnam. It was agreed that a contingency plan is needed for specific military
                    reactions to possible Pathet Lao or Viet <persName corresp="#p_HCM1"
                        >Minh</persName> advances in Laos. Additional escorted U.S. photo missions
                    over Laos will be authorized but will be run in a safer manner.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>The meeting opened with a discussion of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SWH1"
                                >Sullivan</persName>’s 15 June paper on Vietnam.<note n="2"
                                xml:id="d95fn2">According to a June 15 memorandum from <persName
                                    corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName> to <persName
                                    corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, the purpose of this
                                meeting was to consider five papers. The principal question for
                                discussion was whether the group should recommend to the President
                                that he seek a Congressional resolution on Southeast Asia. A second
                                question, according to <persName>Bundy</persName>, was what action
                                should be suggested if a resolution was not recommended.
                                    <persName>Bundy</persName>’s memorandum to <persName
                                    corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, its four papers, and one
                                supplemental paper, are in <ref target="frus1964-68v01#pg_500"
                                    >Foreign Relations, 1964–1968, vol. I, pp. 500</ref>–<ref
                                    target="frus1964-68v01#pg_518">518</ref>.</note> This led to a
                            rather inconclusive discussion of South Vietnamese morale and the degree
                            to which it was dependent upon a conviction of U.S. determination to
                            support Vietnam.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow continued discussion of Vietnam, a possible Congressional
                            resolution, and <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s discussions
                            with members of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee on Vietnam.]</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The meeting reviewed Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                            Bundy</persName>’s attached paper on a policy without a Congressional
                            Resolution.<note n="3" xml:id="d95fn3">Dated June 15, the paper was one
                            of the five prepared for this meeting. (<ref
                                target="frus1964-68v01#pg_516">Ibid., pp. 516</ref>–<ref
                                target="frus1964-68v01#pg_518">518</ref>) It examined potential
                            policy decisions if the United States did not decide upon a
                            Congressional resolution and major military action against North
                            Vietnam. Included as possible military actions in Laos were
                            reconnaissance, reconnaissance-strikes, <gloss target="#t_T281"
                                >T–28</gloss> operations, and South Vietnamese Air Force strikes in
                            the Laos corridor. Political actions relating to Laos included support
                            for a diplomatic track, an effort to sustain the Souvanna government by
                            restraining the right-wing Lao forces, and support for <persName
                                corresp="#p_KLG1">Kong Le</persName>.</note> Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName> expressed the need for a
                        scenario for appropriate reactions to small scale Pathet Lao or Viet
                            <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Minh</persName> advances, such as additional
                            <gloss target="#t_T281">T–28</gloss>s at Udorn but with non-U.S.
                        military pilots. It was agreed that planners should meet for this purpose
                            [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                        declassified</hi>]. Mr. <persName>Bundy</persName> also felt that a
                        contingency plan should be drawn up for the possible loss of <pb facs="0219"
                            n="187" xml:id="pg_187"/> Saravane or Attopeu, which he thought should
                        be replied to by Vietnamese Air Force strikes in the corridor. Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> recommended that a
                        specific plan be drawn up along this line and that at least initial
                        conversation on it be held with <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna
                            Phouma</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                            Bundy</persName> asked what the objective of such action would be,
                        whether to punish the Pathet Lao or to roll them back. Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> replied that the purpose would be
                        to slow the Pathet Lao advance and to assist South Vietnamese morale. Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> emphasized his concern
                        over the absence of a contingency plan for our reactions and that he felt
                        the President should have a much better view of what we are thinking of over
                        the next two weeks. General <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>
                        suggested that we try to define what is meant by a “push to the Mekong”.
                        With respect to the Polish Conference Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName> commented that we will try to drag it out, Mr.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName> suggested that the
                        present indication is that one will not take place and Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName> expounded on the effort he is
                        making to bring it about. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1"
                            >Rusk</persName> terminated this discussion by requesting that a plan
                        for reaction to specific military contingencies be staffed out.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> then raised the
                        desirability of an additional photo mission over the Plaine des Jarres.
                        General <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName> said that <gloss
                            target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> recommended a medium level (10,000 feet
                        above terrain) flight wherever weather permitted, for greater safety against
                        anti-aircraft. In the Plaine des Jarres and in other difficult areas he
                        recommended that there be no low level operations unless there is a strong
                        military or political reason. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName> stated there is a political motivation for a
                        mission during this week but that this need not be in a hot area; therefore
                        he recommended a mission over Nape, escorted [sic]. Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> believed that U.S. jets over Laos
                        provide a good political signal and he approved the Nape idea. Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName> said that we will at
                        sometime have to return to the Plaine des Jarres or we will not show the
                        proper signal of strength but that is not an immediate necessity.<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d95fn4">
                            <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName> also prepared a
                            paper dated June 12—the second of the five papers—on the case for the
                            Congressional resolution entitled “Memorandum on Southeast Asia,” which
                            dealt primarily with Laos. <persName>Bundy</persName> noted that “now
                            that we have worked through the immediate problem of shooting down of
                            our aircraft over Laos and have <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna
                                Phouma</persName>’s clear understanding that reconnaissance flights
                            may continue over the Plaine des Jarres and ‘South Laos’ and with escort
                            as necessary, we should now draw back and examine the total picture as
                            it may develop in the next three to four months and what our plan should
                            be.” For text, see <ref target="frus1964-68v01#pg_507">ibid., pp.
                                507</ref>–<ref target="frus1964-68v01#pg_512">512</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">WE Colby</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chief, Far East Division</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
