<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>145. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d145</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">145</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec0252ZNz4fHrq9C" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="vietnam-conflict">Vietnamization</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Troop withdrawal</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="145"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d145">
                <head>145. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d145fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 140,
                        Vietnam Country Files, Vietnam, Vol. XII, 1–15 November 1969. Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_NODIS1">Nodis</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_HJH1"
                            >Holdridge</persName> sent this memorandum to <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> under cover of a memorandum of
                        November 12, on which <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        wrote: “note change on p. 3. No distribution. HK” Prior to this discussion,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> talked on the telephone at 3:10
                        p.m. on November 4. According to notes of the discussion, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_SWH1"
                            >Sullivan</persName> that “<persName corresp="#p_HPC1">Habib</persName>
                        was not to make any modifications on what he had previously said” and that
                        “the President was determined that we don’t make any new proposals in
                        Paris…. On threat of death <gloss target="#t_K1">K</gloss> said there will
                        be no new proposals.” (Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 361, Telephone
                        Conversations, Chronological File)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1969-11-05">November 5,
                            1969</date>, noon.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Marshall Green</persName>, Assistant Secretary of
                        State for East Asian and Pacific Affairs</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">William Sullivan</persName>, Deputy
                        Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian and Pacific Affairs</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, Assistant
                        to the President for National Security Affairs <persName corresp="#p_HJH1"
                            >John H. Holdridge</persName>, Senior Staff Member, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Remarks by Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> Concerning
                        Vietnam</item>
                </list>
                <p>After a few opening comments concerning the President’s speech<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d145fn2">See <ref target="#d144">Document 144</ref>.</note> and the
                    desirability of getting reactions in as soon as possible, the conversation
                    focussed on recent developments in Vietnam. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> asked what might happen next in Paris, to which
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> replied that the
                    Communists in his opinion were likely to stone wall in Paris while increasing
                    military pressure in the field. He mentioned that a step-up in the rate of
                    infiltration had taken place since October 23, and that over 5,000 <gloss
                        target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> troops were now in the pipeline—as many as had
                    infiltrated in the whole period from April to October. <pb facs="0515" n="479"
                        xml:id="pg_479"/> A build-up north of the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1"
                        >DMZ</gloss> was also possible, with perhaps an attack directly across the
                        <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>. If military action of this sort
                    occurred, we would need to take appropriate measures, perhaps even bombing north
                    of the <gloss target="#t_DMZ1">DMZ</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> mentioned that the Communist
                    build-up in the Delta was obvious to everybody, and asked if there was any plan
                    on what to do about it. <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> said
                    that nothing more than the normal increase of South Vietnamese forces was
                    contemplated, but dismissed the Communist build-up as not being big enough to
                    worry about. To him, the Communist threat to the special forces camps of Bu
                    Prang and Duc Lap was politically more significant, and the Communists had the
                    capability to take these camps. However, it was <persName corresp="#p_AGCW1"
                        >General Abrams</persName>’ view that the situation was not all that
                    serious. The number of 5,000 infiltrators was not in itself of major
                    significance.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wondered if the Communists
                    had ever meant to settle the war by negotiations. He noted that in May and June
                    it had looked as if things might get moving. Could we have done more, and what
                    froze the Communists up? Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName>
                    and <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> said in reply that the
                    Communists had in their negotiating position blasted Vietnamization and <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> troop withdrawals as a major factor, and they
                    were inclined to take the Communist rationale at face value.</p>
                <p>Continuing, <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> mentioned that what
                    had intrigued him most in that period was the May 31 speech of <persName
                        corresp="#p_LDT1">Le Duc Tho</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d145fn3">See <ref target="#d75">Document
                    75</ref>.</note>—Tho had asked if we would agree to discuss everything on the
                    table, i.e., both the 8 point and 10 point programs, and have a cease-fire.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> speculated, though, that
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi Minh</persName>’s illness plus the
                    influence of the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> peacenicks and the growing
                    American intellectual split had caused the Communists to back off.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName> noted that our
                    intelligence had brought out a coincidence between the July 20 Plaine de Jarres
                    offensive and the South Vietnam situation. This has been an important
                    anniversary, and we all had reached the conclusion it was a big date. Perhaps
                    the Communists had then anticipated that a major move was to be expected from
                    the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>, such as proposing a cease-fire. There
                    therefore might have been something significant in the Communist pull-back from
                    Muong Soui. He had been told by both Khampan and Champassak that they were
                    dissatisfied with the explanation that the Communist forces pulled back from
                    Muong Soui solely because they ran out of food.</p>
                <p>The conversation then turned to the question of a cease-fire, with Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> asking why the Communists might want
                    one. <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName>
                    <pb facs="0516" n="480" xml:id="pg_480"/> spoke of the attrition of Communist
                    forces, which was continuing to the point where they were not contesting the
                        <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s pacification efforts. He thought that
                    in a few more months the Communists would be put in a position of making the
                    choice between stepping up the war and making a major infiltration effort, or
                    else taking some steps to protect the integrity of their forces. A cease-fire
                    would be such a step. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                    recalled that there had been no discussion of a cease-fire by the Communists, to
                    which <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> speculated that they would
                    prefer the offer to come from us rather than from them. Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted that all they needed to do was
                    to send the Soviets to us on this issue and ask us what we meant.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> mentioned the effort being
                    launched by the Archbishops of Saigon and Danang to contact all four parties in
                    Paris. He thought that this effort was probably in connection with a cease-fire
                    proposal, which we for our part would not oppose.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> doubted that if the
                    Communists were in such bad shape as <persName corresp="#p_SWH1"
                        >Sullivan</persName> had suggested, they would favor a cease-fire. He could
                    not see the logic. <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> speculated
                    that if the Communists took the initiative they could gain a propaganda
                    advantage by linking a cease-fire appeal, which would be popular in the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>, with a coalition government. He thought,
                    therefore, that we should propose a cease-fire first so as to preempt the
                    Communists. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> felt that we
                    could easily explore with <persName corresp="#p_TNV1">Thieu</persName> the
                    meaning of a cease-fire without asking for one.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> remarked upon the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> domestic implications of a cease-fire and
                    wondered whether there was a desire for one which we were blocking because we
                    simply didn’t understand the implications. Should the President have proposed
                    one? <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> thought that such a
                    proposal would have been a gimmick, but Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GM1"
                        >Green</persName> thought that it might be useful as an argument to the
                    people back here as well as to head the Communists off.</p>
                <p>After a few references to the <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName>
                    Hearings on Vietnam, <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> elaborated
                    on the advantages of a cease-fire, by noting that if our position remained
                    unchanged and the Communists did revert to stepped-up military action, they
                    could give us a great problem with Saigon as well as with public opinion here by
                    at some later stage proposing a cease-fire linked with a coalition government.
                    Again, he thought that we should get there first.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> pointed out that if we were
                    to make the offer first, the Communists could always counter by calling for a
                    complete <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> troop withdrawal and a coalition
                    government.</p>
                <p>Following some further discussion of the pros and cons of a cease-fire, with some
                    reference to the possibility of increased Communist military action occurring
                    next February or March, as Deputy Ambassador <pb facs="0517" n="481"
                        xml:id="pg_481"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BSR1">Berger</persName> believed might happen, Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> stated that if a paper
                    containing a recommendation on a cease-fire came from them, Ambassadors
                        <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SWH1"
                        >Sullivan</persName>, he would see that it was considered by the President
                    even if it did not have <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> clearance.
                    (Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName> noted that the absence
                    of such clearance on a paper already extant was the reason it had not been
                    sent.)</p>
                <p>The conversation shifted back to the fact that Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> had been authorized to discuss a
                    cease-fire with <persName corresp="#p_TNV1">Thieu</persName>, along with other
                    issues, but nothing had been heard from him. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName> raised the possibility that <persName
                        corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> might have been communicating directly
                    with the White House by “back channels”, to which Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> emphatically rejected the idea that
                    any such communication had taken place on the subject of a cease-fire.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d145fn4">At this point, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> crossed out “or would take place” and wrote “on
                        the subject of a ceasefire.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>In conclusion, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName> raised the
                    matter of our Ambassador in Warsaw making contact with the Chinese Communist
                    Chargé. The first opportunity to make such contact at a social occasion would
                    come at the end of the month, but was there any objection to operating overtly?
                    Direct contact could be made via a call at the Chinese Embassy. Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> said that he saw no objection to such
                    direct contacts, but added that there was no problem either, in getting together
                    overtly—in fact we preferred it.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
