<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-01-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="168" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d168">
                    <head>168. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to
                        President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d168fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 94, Vietnam Subject Files,
                            Vietnam, U.S. <gloss target="#t_POW1">POW</gloss>s in North Vietnam to
                            April 1970. Secret. Sent for action.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-01-13">January 13, 1970</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Prisoners of War</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> has sent
                        you a memorandum (Tab A)<note n="2" xml:id="d168fn2">Dated December 20,
                            1969; attached but not printed.</note> suggesting specific actions in
                        response to your desire to assign the highest priority to the prisoner of
                        war question. These actions are: <list>
                            <item>—Your designating a special Presidential emissary (perhaps Arthur
                                Goldberg or Ralph Bunche) who could visit the capitals of countries
                                which previously have expressed a concern for our prisoners of war
                                for the purpose of confirming with appropriate government officials
                                the high priority you have assigned to this matter.</item>
                            <item>—Alternatively, your designating a joint White House/<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>/Defense team to visit the same
                                areas for the same purpose.</item>
                            <item>—Instructing our delegation in Paris to develop a series of
                                hard-hitting statements on the prisoner question.</item>
                            <item>—Your reconsidering the proposal of designating the Vice President
                                as your personal representative on prisoner matters.</item>
                            <item>—Your continuing, in your speeches and statements, to include
                                prisoner of war references where appropriate.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>On December 30 Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName> forwarded State’s comments on Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>’s memorandum (Tab B).<note n="3" xml:id="d168fn3">Attached but not printed.</note> He expressed general
                        agreement with the strategy outlined by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>, but had the following specific
                        remarks concerning each of Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>’s proposed actions: <pb facs="0568" n="532" xml:id="pg_532"/>
                        <list>
                            <item>—The idea of a special Presidential emissary could have merit if
                                the individual were carefully chosen and care taken to assure that
                                his mission did not become enmeshed in other aspects of Vietnam
                                diplomacy.</item>
                            <item>—The alternative suggestion of a briefing team could also have
                                value. However, the Acting Secretary believed that the State
                                Department should be represented.</item>
                            <item>—Our delegation in Paris has already raised the prisoner issue
                                repeatedly in the talks. This approach should, of course, be
                                continued.</item>
                            <item>—The Acting Secretary referred to his previous comments on the
                                possibility of putting the Vice President in charge of prisoner
                                matters, and while welcoming the Vice President’s interest in this
                                matter, expressed the view that your own demonstrated personal
                                interest would be the best way of showing that this is a subject of
                                highest importance.</item>
                            <item>—Accordingly, the Acting Secretary joined in the hope in the last
                                point of Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>’s
                                memorandum that you will continue to speak out on prisoners of war,
                                and offered to provide material for this purpose as
                                appropriate.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although State’s reaction to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>’s proposed actions suggests some minor reservations, I
                        believe the Acting Secretary’s response is fairly close to the line
                        suggested by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>. I
                        consider the designation of a special Presidential emissary as useful, but
                        agree with State that the selection must be a careful and judicious one. For
                        example, Arthur Goldberg does not impress me as being an appropriate choice
                        in view of his opposition to your Vietnam policy. The suggestion of a
                        special briefing team to perform the same function as a special Presidential
                        envoy if a suitable candidate cannot be found also appears desirable. As
                        noted in Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName>’s comments, I believe that State should be
                        represented. The delegation in Paris of course should continue to press the
                        North Vietnamese on the prisoner issue. Concerning the Vice President’s
                        role, I feel that this might better be finessed for the time being in favor
                        of stressing the part that you yourself might play in spotlighting your own
                        and the Administration’s concern over the treatment of our prisoners. I am
                        sure that you will wish to keep up your personal efforts on behalf of the
                        prisoners, and that materials from State and Defense will be useful in this
                        regard.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:<note n="4" xml:id="d168fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> approved all the
                                options on January 16. On January 22 <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> sent <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> a memorandum asking them to take joint action
                                to initiate the first two and last two recommendations. (National
                                Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 94,
                                Vietnam Subject Files, Vietnam, U.S. <gloss target="#t_POW1">POW</gloss>s in North Vietnam to April 1970)</note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>That you authorize State and Defense to nominate a suitable individual to be
                        designated by you as a special Presidential emissary on prisoners of
                        war.</p>
                    <pb facs="0569" n="533" xml:id="pg_533"/>
                    <p>That you authorize the organization of a Defense/White House/ <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>/State team to perform the functions of a
                        special Presidential emissary if a suitable candidate cannot be found.</p>
                    <p>That you authorize the issuance of instructions to our delegation in Paris to
                        continue to press the North Vietnamese on the prisoner issue, and to prepare
                        a series of hard-hitting statements for this purpose.</p>
                    <p>That you hold in abeyance any change in the Vice President’s role with
                        respect to the prisoners.</p>
                    <p>That you authorize State and Defense to provide materials for your use in
                        dealing with the prisoner issue in speeches and public statements.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>