<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-02-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="181" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                    <head>181. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to
                        President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d181fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 546, Country Files, Far
                            East, Laos, Vol. IV, 1 February 1970–31 March 1970. Secret. According to
                            an attached undated note from <persName corresp="#p_HAMJ1">Haig</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SWR1">Smyser</persName>
                            prepared this estimate of North Vietnam’s current intention with regard
                            to Laos.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-02-12">February 12, 1970</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Current Hanoi Intentions In Laos</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>My staff has developed the following estimate of current North Vietnamese
                        intentions in Laos:</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Military</hi>: The Communists will certainly try to retake
                        the Plain of Jars, whose recent capture by General <persName corresp="#p_VPG1">Vang Pao</persName>’s Meo Forces they considered an
                        incursion into “their” territory. They may also try to move against Van
                        Vieng, the headquarters of Premier <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna
                            Phouma</persName>’s neutralist forces, so as to install their own
                        “neutralists” there. They may even try to move close to the royal capital
                        Luang Prabang and perhaps Vientiane to increase their pressure on the King
                        and the Lao Government. We doubt that they would make a massive push to the
                        Mekong River, which would involve too high a political risk and probably
                        also too high a military price.</p>
                    <p>An important Communist objective, beyond territorial gains, is to crush the
                        Meo Forces or at least to inflict such staggering losses that the Meo can be
                        disregarded as a military factor for a long time. Hanoi also wants to punish
                        the Meo enough so that they will not again presume to venture into
                        Communist-held areas. With the Meo out of the military picture, and the
                            pro-<persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> neutralists also
                        nullified, <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName>’s military
                        strength would be greatly eroded.</p>
                    <p>The timing of the Communist offensive is still unclear. Their main attack
                        yesterday was against the Xieng Khouang airfield, and may have been intended
                        to prevent the King from landing there as planned. (He instead went to
                            <persName corresp="#p_VPG1">Vang Pao</persName>’s headquarters.) The
                        Communists also took advantage of low cloud cover which hampered tactical
                        air. Thus we still cannot be sure whether yesterday’s action heralded a
                        massive sharp push or whether the Communists will develop their attack over
                        a period of time, in accordance with meteorological and political
                        considerations.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Political</hi>: Hanoi’s principal political purpose is
                        probably to drive a wedge between the U.S. and <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>. If the Meo and the <pb facs="0604" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/> neutralist forces can be badly defeated or even
                        decimated, <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> and his
                        government may want very much to reach an accommodation which would save
                        what is left. At that point, <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName>
                        might be ready to ask for a U.S. bombing halt in the panhandle in exchange
                        for Communist promises to relent. The bombing in southern Laos benefits us
                        more than <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName>, and the
                        Communists would try to take advantage of that divergence of interests.</p>
                    <p>Political considerations might help force the Communists to exercise some
                        restraint. If they move too far they might risk a massive U.S. air reaction
                        in Laos and perhaps U.S. military moves in Thailand. This would tend to make
                            <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> more dependent on us and
                        might encourage him to hold on.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Negotiations Front</hi>: We do not believe the Communists
                        now want to negotiate a new agreement on Laos. They will probably not want a
                        separate Lao accord before Vietnam has been settled. But the Communists may
                        hope that military pressure can persuade <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> to accept some “understanding” under which the
                        Communist hold on the Lao Government structure would be increased without
                        revising the 1962 Geneva Accords.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the United States, Communist actions would be intended to warn
                        us that we cannot get peace in Southeast Asia without dealing with Hanoi.
                        Even though Vietnamization may ease our problems in Vietnam, it cannot help
                        us in Laos.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Problems for Hanoi</hi>: All this is not so simple as it
                        sounds. There is evidence that even the North Vietnamese forces in Laos,
                        which used to sweep up the battlefield against Government forces whenever
                        they entered into action, are not quite what they used to be. (This is also
                        true in South Vietnam.) They are younger, less well trained, and less well
                        led. Recent reports indicate that some units were very demoralized by
                        tactical air raids against their positions. General <persName corresp="#p_VPG1">Vang Pao</persName>’s Meo Forces are tried but tough.
                        This does not mean that Hanoi cannot achieve many and perhaps all its
                        military objectives. But the action may well not be as easy as they would
                        wish, particularly if the weather permits a sustained tactical air effort in
                        support of <persName corresp="#p_VPG1">Vang Pao</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d181fn2">In a February 12 memorandum to the President, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> responded to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s request for a report on air
                            drops of food and material in Laos. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> summarized two attached papers by <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> on “Food Drops in Laos” and “Air
                            America Operations in Laos.” <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> wrote the following comment on the summary of Air
                            America Operations: “K. Sounds like a good operation—unless the amount
                            of good is less than the obviously very heavy cost of the program.”
                            (Ibid.)</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>