<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-04-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-04-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="242" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                    <head>242. Memorandum From Director of Central Intelligence <persName corresp="#p_HRM1" type="from">Helms</persName> to the President’s
                        Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d242fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 506, Country Files, Far East, Cambodia, Vol.
                            III, 10 April 1970–23 April 1970. Secret; Sensitive. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> summarized this memorandum
                            for <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> on April 22, but that
                            memorandum was not initialed and there is no indication it was sent to
                            the President. (ibid.)</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-04-21">April 21, 1970</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Conveying the Word to Hanoi</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0876" n="840" xml:id="pg_840"/>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>At the President’s request, we have taken several steps to give the
                            North Vietnamese leadership clear reason to believe that if Vietnamese
                            Communist forces in Cambodia attack Phnom Penh, United States forces
                            will hit them from the rear by mounting sharp attacks on Vietnamese
                            Communist sanctuaries.<note n="2" xml:id="d242fn2">On April 24
                                    <persName>Helms</persName> sent a memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> reporting that <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> official [<hi rend="italic">text
                                    not declassified</hi>] was given a convincing written report
                                indicating that the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and U.S.
                                intended to invade Cambodia. According to the <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> memorandum, “[<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] became very nervous,
                                shaking his legs and feet nervously” when he heard the report. “[<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>] remained in an
                                agitated condition throughout the meeting. [<hi rend="italic">name
                                    not declassified</hi>] stated that the National Liberation Front
                                ‘expected United States intervention in Cambodia but not so soon.’”
                                When queried about <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and North
                                Vietnamese troops in Cambodia, [<hi rend="italic">text not
                                    declassified</hi>] acknowledged their presence, but stated “it
                                would be political suicide for us to admit it.” (Ibid., Box 207,
                                Agency Files, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, Vol. II, 1
                                January 1970 to 30 June 1970)</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>To get this word across, we have arranged for one basic story to be
                                pipelined into several channels that should get it back quickly, and
                                credibly, to Hanoi.<note n="3" xml:id="d242fn3">The message was
                                    passed to <persName corresp="#p_MVB1">Mai Van Bo</persName> in
                                    Paris on April 29. <persName corresp="#p_MVB1">Bo</persName> was
                                    “deeply interested, probed extensively for additional details,
                                    and during the meeting revealed that the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> apparently had not felt the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> would send its own forces into
                                    Cambodia for fear of adverse reaction from the ‘Senate Foreign
                                    Relations Committee, the Congress, public opinion and eventually
                                    the electorate at the polls.’” (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, May 1; ibid., Box
                                    579, Cambodia Operations (1970), Actions in Cambodia, Vol.
                                    1)</note> The basic theme planted with all our sources used runs
                                as follows, though there have been suitable variations in each
                                specific instance:</p>
                            <p>The <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> have long felt that Vietnam internal security
                                problems can never be really solved so long as the Communists have
                                sanctuaries in nearby Cambodia. Hence, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> have
                                long itched to attack these sanctuaries and the Communist troops
                                resting or refitting in them. Recent events in Cambodia have
                                considerably whetted American and South Vietnamese appetites, but
                                the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> (particularly) has felt the
                                Vietnamese Communist muscle flexing in neutral Cambodia was giving
                                Hanoi such a propaganda black eye worldwide—particularly within the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> itself—that the United States
                                Government was reluctant to see the waters muddied by allied
                                military involvement in the Cambodian-<gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> fight. However,
                                if the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> forces make further military moves against Phnom
                                Penh, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> is set to take prompt
                                advantage of world opinion focus on Cambodia’s plight in the face of
                                North Vietnamese invasion and clear up the sanctuary problem by
                                attacking <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> forces from the rear.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>[<hi rend="italic">17 lines of source text not
                            declassified</hi>]</item>
                        <pb facs="0877" n="841" xml:id="pg_841"/>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>In line with the above considerations, the following moves are now in
                            train:</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>[Omitted here is detailed discussion.]</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>In both tone and content, the President’s 20 April speech<note n="4" xml:id="d242fn4">Reference is to the President’s Address to the
                                Nation broadcast at 6 p.m. on April 20 from San Clemente,
                                California, in which <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                                reported “no progress” on the negotiation front and announced his
                                intention of withdrawing from Vietnam an additional 150,000 forces
                                over the next year. (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, 1970</hi>, pp.
                                373–377)</note> will make this message more credible to Hanoi. From
                            a strictly operational perspective, the best possible support for this
                            story’s (and our sources’) credibility would be the movement of selected
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> troops to the immediate vicinity
                            of the Cambodian Frontier of South Vietnam.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName>
                                <hi rend="strong">Dick</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>