<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-07-21T22:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="334" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d334">
                    <head>334. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>No minutes have been found for the Washington Special Actions Group meeting
                        of June 24, 1970. According to a June 23 briefing memorandum for <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry Kissinger</persName>, prepared by <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">John Holdridge</persName>, the main purpose of this
                        meeting was to have a quick rundown of steps being taken to aid Cambodia
                        before President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s departure
                        for San Clemente on June 25. In addition <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> that “our aid to Cambodia is running into big
                        money:” $25 million for the Cambodian Military Assistance Program for fiscal
                        year 1971, $59 million projected as added on to the Military Assistance
                        Programs for Thailand and South Vietnam for Cambodian-related expenses, a
                        potential additional $75 million for paramilitary forces in the southeast
                        Laos–northeast Cambodia–northwest South Vietnam triangle, and unspecified
                        funding for Indonesian support to Cambodia. The Department of Defense and
                        Central Intelligence Agency were both having difficulties with the funding.
                        Finally <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> alerted <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> to the fact that the <persName corresp="#p_LNG1">Lon Nol</persName> government was running out of money
                        and might be out of cash within a month or so. <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> suggested <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> review the Washington Special Actions Group
                        Working Group plan for paramilitary operations in south Laos, northeastern
                        Cambodia and northwestern South Vietnam. Plans to drop propaganda leaflets
                        over Cambodia and to use enemy documents captured in Cambodia were
                        “unexceptional” and could be discussesd if time permitted. (National
                        Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H-Files), Box H–078,
                            <gloss target="#t_WSAG1">WSAG</gloss> Meeting, Cambodia, 6/24/70)</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>