<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>76. Backchannel Message From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs ( Message From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to the Ambassador to Vietnam () to the Ambassador to Vietnam
                    (Bunker))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d76</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">76</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-06-01T13:44:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-06-01T13:44:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Troop withdrawal</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Joint statement</term>
                    <term ref="rec0252ZNz4fHrq9C" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="vietnam-conflict">Vietnamization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-06-01T13:44:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-06-01T13:44:00-05:00" n="76"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                <head>76. <gloss target="#t_Backchannel1">Backchannel</gloss> Message From the
                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to the Ambassador to Vietnam (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BE1" type="to">Bunker</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d76fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> Files, Box 65, Vietnam Subject Files, 8–A, All <gloss
                            target="#t_Backchannel1">Backchannel</gloss>. Top Secret; Sensitive;
                        Eyes Only.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-06-01T18:44:00+00:00">June 1, 1969, 1844Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>W<gloss target="#t_WH1">WH</gloss>90761. Exclusively Eyes Only for the Ambassador
                    (hold for arrival in Saigon).</p>
                <p>The President has asked that you convey to <persName corresp="#p_TNV1"
                        >Thieu</persName> the importance that he places upon the forthcoming Midway
                    meeting. He is aware that press speculation here has probably aroused some
                    concern on the coalition government issue, and wishes <persName
                        corresp="#p_TNV1">Thieu</persName> to be assured that we are determined to
                    hold the line on this. I gave this message to <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bui
                        Diem</persName> yesterday. However, it is essential that we retain tactical
                    flexibility. Our major problem here is to gain time and to enable us to combat
                    the growing public pressures. This is why troop withdrawal announcement is so
                    crucial.</p>
                <p>Press is speculating that Midway meeting was convened to remedy a growing
                    divergence between Saigon and Washington. Therefore, it is most important that
                    troop withdrawal announcement be made in context of <persName corresp="#p_TNV1"
                        >Thieu</persName> initiative in order to maintain his image here. It will
                    strengthen our ability to help him on political front.</p>
                <p>At Midway, we currently visualize that President and <persName corresp="#p_TNV1"
                        >Thieu</persName> will meet privately from 11:30 until 1:00 p.m., and then
                    issue a very brief joint announcement on troop withdrawal along lines of my
                    earlier message.<note n="2" xml:id="d76fn2">See <ref target="#d70">Document
                            70</ref>.</note> This will produce a maximum impact especially if it is
                    unexpected. Following lunch, the entire group will meet, then at 5:00 p.m., a
                    formal joint statement will be made on other matters dealt with at the
                    conference.</p>
                <p>Because of the psychological implications of the troop withdrawal statement, it
                    is absolutely essential that there be no leaks beforehand that announcement is
                    to be made. For this reason, this matter has been held strictly to the
                    President, myself, and Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>
                    and <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>. It is equally important that
                    similar restrictions be retained on this information at your end. You will note
                    that some references have been made to troop withdrawal and Vietnamization in
                    regular State traffic concerned with the formal joint statement at the
                    conclusion of the meeting and preparatory coordination of respective positions.
                    These references have been made by drafters unaware of the decision to proceed
                        <pb facs="0274" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/> with a separate announcement at
                    Midway and serve as an additional cover to maintain the necessary security.</p>
                <p>Request your views on foregoing, as soon as possible.<note n="3" xml:id="d76fn3"
                        >In <gloss target="#t_Backchannel1">backchannel</gloss> message 802 from
                        Saigon, June 2, <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> reported that
                        he did not expect problems with <persName corresp="#p_TNV1">Thieu</persName>
                        on troop withdrawals and <persName corresp="#p_TNV1">Thieu</persName> would
                        be reassured by <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s assurances on
                        a coalition government. <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> also
                        reported that <persName corresp="#p_AGCW1">Abrams</persName> hoped to
                        maintain flexibility in withdrawals. (National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 65, Vietnam Subject Files, 8–A,
                        All <gloss target="#t_Backchannel1">Backchannel</gloss>)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
