<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Bowen to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1905</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1119</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1119</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1905-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1905-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="1119"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1119">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Bowen</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram.—Paraphrase.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Caracas</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-02-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 5, 1905</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>(Reports that the Venezuelan chargé d’affaires cabled the President yesterday
                    that Department said the difficulties with Venezuela could be arranged. The
                    President cabled for details. The Venezuelan chargé d’affaires replied that
                    Department asked him why does not the President accept a general arbitration
                    treaty, adding, if he would, all would be settled amicably and Venezuela would
                    never have a better friend than the United States. The President cabled back to
                    tell Department that he never asked for anything except to submit everything to
                    arbitration, but that Mr. Bowen prevented everything. Mr. Bowen says that
                    statement is false. The President refused to submit to arbitration pending
                    questions and asked for a general arbitration for the future. Mr. Bowen adds
                    that Department instructions to him stated the United States would consider
                    negotiating a general arbitration treaty only after pending questions are
                    settled. As the President claims cases before his courts are not diplomatic
                    questions, it would be useless to make a general arbitration treaty unless he
                    accepts the Department’s definition of a diplomatic question.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
