<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-06-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="115" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Belgian Chargé</gloss> to
                                Acting Secretary of State <persName type="to">Loomis</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Belgian
                                        Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-06-07"><hi rend="italic">June 7,
                                1905</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: The Belgian legation has
                            just received the text of the exposition of the motives accompanying the
                            proposed law submitted to the Belgian chambers for the approval of the
                            obligatory treaties of arbitration concluded between Belgium and other
                            governments.</p>
                        <p>I hasten to place one copy of the same at your disposal.</p>
                        <p>Please accept, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">E. Havenith.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Inclosure.—Translation.]</head>
                            <p>His Majesty the King of the Belgians and his Majesty the Emperor of
                                all the Russias, desiring to settle as far as possible by pacific
                                means the differences which may arise between their countries, have
                                decided to conclude for this purpose a convention of obligatory
                                arbitration, and have appointed as their plenipotentiaries, to wit: <list>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of the Belgians—</item>
                                    <item>Count Degrelle Rogier, his envoy extraordinary and
                                        minister plenipotentiary at the Imperial court of Russia,
                                        and</item>
                                    <item>His Majesty the Emperor of all the Russias—</item>
                                    <item>Count Lamsdorf, his secretary of state, actual privy
                                        councilor and minister of foreign affairs;</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Who, after having communicated to each other their full powers, which
                                were found in good and due form, have agreed on the following
                                articles:</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties agree to submit to the Permanent Court
                                of Arbitration established at The Hague by the convention of July
                                29, 1899, the differences which may arise between them in the cases
                                enumerated in article 3, in so far as they affect neither the
                                independence, <pb facs="0199" n="79" xml:id="pg_79"/> the honor, the
                                vital interests, nor the exercise of sovereignty of the contracting
                                countries, and provided it has been impossible to obtain an amicable
                                solution by means of direct diplomatic negotiations or by any other
                                method of conciliation.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                            <p>It shall be the privilege of each of the high contracting parties to
                                decide whether the difference which has arisen involves its vital
                                interests, its honor, its independence, or the exercise of its
                                sovereignty, and is consequently of such a nature as to be comprised
                                among those which are excepted from obligatory arbitration according
                                to the foregoing article.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                            <p>Arbitration shall be obligatory between the high contracting parties
                                in the following cases: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes concerning the application or
                                        interpretation of any convention concluded or to be
                                        concluded between the high contracting parties and relating— <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>To matters of international private law;</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>To the management of companies;</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>To matters of procedure, either civil or criminal,
                                                and to extradition.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes concerning pecuniary claims based on
                                        damages, when the principle of indemnity has been recognized
                                        by the parties.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Differences which may arise with regard to the interpretation or
                                application of a convention concluded or to be concluded between the
                                high contracting parties and in which third powers have participated
                                or to which they have adhered shall be excluded from settlement by
                                arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be applicable even if the disputes which
                                arise shall have originated in acts prior to its conclusion.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                            <p>When there shall be an occasion for arbitration between them, the
                                high contracting parties shall, in the absence of compromising
                                clauses to the contrary, conform in all that concerns the
                                appointment of the arbitrators and the arbitral procedure to the
                                rules established by the convention signed at The Hague July 29,
                                1899, for the pacific settlement of international controversies,
                                except as regards the points indicated hereinbelow.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6.</p>
                            <p>Neither of the arbitrators shall be a subject of either of the
                                nations signing the present convention, nor be domiciled in their
                                territories, nor be interested in the questions forming the subject
                                of arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7.</p>
                            <p>The agreement provided for by Article 31 of the convention of July
                                29, 1899, shall fix a period within which the exchange between the
                                two parties of the memoranda and documents relating to the subject
                                of the litigation shall take place. This exchange shall be completed
                                at all events before the opening of the sessions of the court of
                                arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8.</p>
                            <p>The agreement mentioned in the foregoing article shall likewise fix
                                the sum which the high contracting parties are to place at the
                                disposal of the Permanent Bureau of the Court of Arbitration in
                                order to cover the expenses of arbitration in accordance with
                                Article 57 of the convention of July 29, 1899.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 9.</p>
                            <p>The arbitral sentence shall specify the periods within which it is to
                                be executed.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 10.</p>
                            <p>The present convention is concluded for the period of ten years. It
                                shall take effect one month after the exchange of ratifications. In
                                case neither of the high contracting parties has made known, six
                                months before the end of said period, its intention to bring it to
                                an end, the convention shall remain binding until the expiration of
                                one year from the day on which one or the other of the high
                                contracting parties shall have denounced it.</p>
                            <pb facs="0200" n="80" xml:id="pg_80"/>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 11.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be ratified within the shortest possible
                                period, and the ratifications shall be exchanged at St.
                                Petersburg.</p>
                            <p>In witness whereof the plenipotentiaries have signed the present
                                convention and affixed thereto the seal of their arms.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>St.
                                        Petersburg</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian julian" when="1904-10-30">October 30/17, 1904</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Count Degrelle
                                            Rogier.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Count Lamsdorff.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">declaration.</hi></head>
                            <p>At the moment of proceeding to sign the arbitration convention, which
                                has been agreed upon between Belgium and Russia, the undersigned
                                plenipotentiaries, being duly authorized for this purpose, have
                                agreed on the following:</p>
                            <p>It is understood that the said convention, in accordance with the
                                previous declarations of the plenipotentiary of His Majesty the King
                                of the Belgians, made at the Peace Conference at The Hague, does not
                                in any way modify, as far as the high contracting parties are
                                concerned, the rights and obligations accruing to them from the
                                treaty of April 19, 1839, which guarantees the independence and
                                neutrality of Belgium, and the stipulations of which can not be
                                affected by the said convention of arbitration.</p>
                            <p>The present declaration shall have the same value and the same
                                duration as if it had been embodied in the aforementioned
                                convention. It shall be ratified at the same time.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Done in duplicate at <placeName>St.
                                        Petersburg</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian julian" when="1904-10-30">October 30/17, 1904</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Count Degrelle
                                            Rogier.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Count Lamsdorff.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Untitled]</head>
                            <p>His Majesty the King of the Belgians and the Federal Council of the
                                Swiss Confederation, desiring to settle as far as possible by means
                                of arbitration the differences which may arise between their
                                countries, have decided to conclude for this purpose a convention
                                and have appointed as their plenipotentiaries, to wit: <list>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of the Belgians—</item>
                                    <item>His excellency Count de Lichtervelde, officer of the Order
                                        of Leopold, etc., his envoy extraordinary and minister
                                        plenipotentiary to the Swiss Confederation, and</item>
                                    <item>The Federal Council of the Swiss Confederation—</item>
                                    <item>Mr. Robert Comtesse, president of the Swiss Confederation
                                        and chief of the political department;</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Who, after having communicated to each other their full powers, which
                                were found in good and due form, have agreed on the following
                                articles:</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties agree to submit to the Permanent Court
                                of Arbitration established at The Hague by the convention of July
                                29, 1899, the differences which may arise between them in the cases
                                enumerated in Article 3 in so far as they effect neither the honor,
                                the independence, nor the sovereignty of the contracting countries,
                                and provided it has been imposssible to secure an amicable
                                settlement by direct diplomatic negotiations or by any other method
                                of conciliation.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                            <p>It shall be the privilege of each of the high contracting parties to
                                decide whether the difference which has arisen involves its honor,
                                its independence, or its sovereignty, and is consequently of such a
                                nature as to be comprised among those which are excepted from
                                obligatory arbitration according to the foregoing article.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                            <p>With the reservations indicated in Article 1 arbitration shall be
                                obligatory between the high contracting parties in the following
                                cases: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes concerning the application or
                                        interpretation of any convention concluded or to be
                                        concluded between them with the exception of those in which
                                        third powers have participated or to which they have
                                        adhered.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes regarding pecuniary claims based on
                                        damages, when the principle of indemnity is recognized by
                                        the parties.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="0201" n="81" xml:id="pg_81"/>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be applicable even if the disputes which
                                arise have had their origin in acts prior to its conclusion.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                            <p>When there shall be an occasion for arbitration between them, the
                                high contracting parties shall, in the absence of compromising
                                clauses to the contrary, conform in everything that concerns the
                                appointment of the arbitrators and the arbitral procedure to the
                                rules established by the convention signed at The Hague on July 29,
                                1899, for the pacific settlement of international controversies,
                                except as far as the points indicated herein below are
                                concerned.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6.</p>
                            <p>None of the arbitrators shall be a subject of either of the nations
                                signing this convention, nor domiciled in their territories, nor
                                interested in the questions which form the subject of
                                arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7.</p>
                            <p>The agreement provided for by Article 31 of the convention of July
                                29, 1899, shall fix a period during which the exchange between the
                                two parties of the memoranda and documents relating to the subject
                                of litigation shall take place. This exchange shall be completed at
                                all events before the opening of the sessions of the court of
                                arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8.</p>
                            <p>The agreement shall fix the sum which the high contracting parties
                                are to place immediately at the disposal of the Permanent Bureau of
                                the Court of Arbitration in order to cover the expenses of
                                procedure, in conformity with Article 57 of the convention of July
                                29, 1899.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 9.</p>
                            <p>The arbitral sentence shall specify the periods within which it is to
                                be executed.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 10.</p>
                            <p>The present convention is concluded for the period of ten years. It
                                shall take effect one month after the exchange of ratifications. In
                                case neither of the high contracting parties has given notice, six
                                months before the end of said period, of its intention to terminate
                                it, the convention shall remain binding until the expiration of a
                                year from the day on which either of the high contracting parties
                                shall have denounced it.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 11.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be ratified within the shortest possible
                                period, and the ratifications shall be exchanged at Bern.</p>
                            <p>In witness whereof the plenipotentiaries have signed the present
                                convention and affixed thereto their seals.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Bern</placeName>, in
                                    duplicate, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-11-15">November
                                        15, 1904</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Lichtervelde.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">R. Comtesse.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Untitled]</head>
                            <p>His Majesty the King of the Belgians and His Majesty the King of
                                Sweden and Norway, being signatories of the convention for the
                                pacific settlement of international controversies concluded at The
                                Hague on July 29, 1899, and desiring in order to apply the
                                principles set forth in Articles 15 to 19 of the said convention to
                                enter into negotiations for the conclusion of a convention of
                                obligatory arbitration, have appointed as their plenipotentiaries,
                                to wit: <list>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of the Belgians—</item>
                                    <item>Baron de Favereau, Knight of the Order of Leopold, etc., a
                                        senator, his minister of foreign affairs; and</item>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of Sweden and Norway—</item>
                                    <item>Count Wrangel, commander of the first class of the Order
                                        of the Polar Star, commander of the second class of the
                                        Order of Wasa, etc., his envoy extraordinary and minister
                                        plenipotentiary to His Majesty the King of the
                                        Belgians;</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Who after having communicated to each other their full powers, which
                                were found in good and due form, have agreed on the following
                                articles:</p>
                            <pb facs="0202" n="82" xml:id="pg_82"/>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties agree to submit to the Permanent Court
                                of Arbitration, established at The Hague by the convention of July
                                29, 1899, the differences which may arise between them in the cases
                                enumerated in article 3, in so far as they affect neither the
                                independence, the sovereignty, nor the vital interests of the
                                respective countries, and provided it as been impossible to secure
                                an amicable settlement by means of direct diplomatic
                                negotiations.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                            <p>It shall be the privilege of each of the high contracting parties to
                                decide whether the difference which has arisen involves its vital
                                interests, its independence, or its sovereignty, and whether it is
                                consequently of such a nature as to be comprised among those which
                                are excepted from obligatory arbitration according to the foregoing
                                article.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                            <p>Arbitration shall be obligatory between the high contracting parties
                                in the following cases: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>With the reservations contained in Article 1 in case of
                                        disputes concerning the application or interpretation of all
                                        conventions concluded or to be concluded between them, with
                                        the exception of those in which third powers have
                                        participated or to which they have adhered.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes regarding pecuniary claims based on
                                        damages, when the principle of indemnity is recognized by
                                        the signatory nations.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties waive the right of availing themselves
                                in this latter case of the above-mentioned reservations.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be applicable even if the disputes which
                                arise have originated in acts prior to its conclusion.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                            <p>When there shall be an occasion for arbitration between them, the
                                high contracting parties shall, in the absence of compromising
                                clauses to the contrary, conform, in all that regards the
                                appointment of the arbitrators and the arbitral procedure, to the
                                rules established by the convention of July 29, 1899, except as
                                regards the points indicated herein below.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6.</p>
                            <p>None of the arbitrators shall be a subject of the signatory nations,
                                nor be domiciled within their territories, nor be concerned in the
                                questions forming the subject of arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7.</p>
                            <p>The agreement provided for by Article 31 of the convention of July
                                29, 1899, shall fix a term within which the exchange between the two
                                parties of the memoranda and documents relating to the subject of
                                litigation shall take place. This exchange shall at all events be
                                completed before the opening of the sessions of the court of
                                arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8.</p>
                            <p>The arbitral sentence shall specify the periods within which it is to
                                be executed, if there is occasion for it.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 9.</p>
                            <p>The present convention is concluded for a period of ten years. It
                                shall take effect one month after the exchange of ratifications. In
                                case neither of the high contracting parties has given notice, six
                                months before the end of said period, of its intention to terminate
                                it, the convention shall remain binding until the expiration of one
                                year from the day on which one or the other of the high contracting
                                parties shall have denounced it.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 10.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be ratified within the shortest possible
                                time, and the ratifications shall be exchanged at Brussels.</p>
                            <p>In witness thereof, the plenipotentiaries have signed the present
                                convention and have affixed thereto their seals.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Brussels</placeName>,
                                    in duplicate, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-11-30">November 30, 1904</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Favereau.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Wrangel.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0203" n="83" xml:id="pg_83"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">signature protocol.</hi></head>
                            <p>At the moment of proceeding to sign the convention on arbitration,
                                concluded to-day, the the undersigned plenipotentiaries make the
                                following declaration:</p>
                            <p>It is understood that the convention does not abrogate the provisions
                                of Article 20 of the treaty regulating the relations of commerce and
                                navigation between Belgium and Sweden, concluded at Brussels June
                                11, 1895, nor the provisions of Article 20 of the treaty regulating
                                the relations of commerce and navigation between Belgium and Norway,
                                concluded at Brussels the same day; it is likewise understood that
                                the stipulations of Article 7 of the convention in no wise affect
                                the stipulations of the convention concluded at The Hague July 29,
                                1899, concerning the second phase of the arbitral procedure provided
                                for in Article 39, and especially the stipulations of Article 43 to
                                49.</p>
                            <p>In witness whereof the respective plenipotentiaries have drawn up the
                                present signature protocol, which shall have the same force and
                                value as if the provisions which it contains had been embodied in
                                the convention itself.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Brussels</placeName>,
                                    in duplicate, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1904-11-30">November 30, 1904</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Favereau.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Wrangel.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Untitled]</head>
                            <p>His Majesty the King of the Belgians and His Majesty the King of
                                Spain, desiring to settle as far as possible by means of arbitration
                                the differences which may arise between their countries, have
                                decided to conclude a convention for this purpose and have appointed
                                as their plenipotentiaries, to wit: <list>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of the Belgians—</item>
                                    <item>His Excellency Baron Joostens, officer of the Order of
                                        Leopold, commander of the Royal Order of Isabel the
                                        Catholic, knight of the Royal and Distinguished Order of
                                        Charles III of Spain, his envoy extraordinary and minister
                                        plenipotentiary to his Catholic Majesty; and</item>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of Spain—</item>
                                    <item>His Excellency Ventura Garcia Sancho é Harrondo, Marquis
                                        de Aguilar de Campoo et de Torre Blanca, his minister of
                                        state, senator for life, chamberlain of His Majesty the King
                                        of Spain as a grandee of Spain, Grand Cross of the Royal and
                                        Distinguished Order of Charles III and of Isabel the
                                        Catholic, of the Legion of Honor, of the Iron Crown of
                                        Austria, of Christ of Portugal, Knight of St. John of
                                        Jerusalem, etc.,</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Who, after having communicated to each other their full powers, which
                                were found in good and due form, have agreed on the following
                                articles:</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties agree to submit to the Permanent Court
                                of Arbitration established at The Hague by the convention of July
                                29, 1899, the differences which may arise between them, in the cases
                                enumerated in Article 3, in so far as they affect neither the honor,
                                the independence, nor the sovereignty of the contracting countries,
                                and provided it has been impossible to reach an amicable settlement
                                by means of direct diplomatic negotiations or by any other method of
                                conciliation.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                            <p>It shall be the privilege of each of the high contracting parties to
                                decide whether the difference which shall have arisen involves its
                                honor, its independence, or its sovereignty, and whether it is
                                consequently of such a nature as to be comprised among those which
                                are excepted from obligatory arbitration according to the preceding
                                article.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                            <p>Under the reservations indicated in Article 1, arbitration shall be
                                obligatory between the high contracting parties: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes concerning the application or
                                        interpretation of any conventions concluded or to be
                                        concluded between them, with the exception of those in which
                                        third powers have participated or to which they have
                                        adhered.</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes concerning pecuniary claims based on
                                        damages, when the principle of indemnity is recognized by
                                        the parties.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                            <p>When there shall be an occasion for arbitration between them, the
                                high contracting parties shall, in the absence of compromising
                                clauses to the contrary, conform, in all that concerns the
                                appointment of arbitrators and the arbitral procedure, to the rules
                                established by the convention signed at The Hague of July 29, 1899,
                                for the pacific settlement of international controversies, except as
                                regards the points indicated hereinbelow.</p>
                            <pb facs="0204" n="84" xml:id="pg_84"/>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                            <p>Neither of the arbitrators shall be a citizen of either of the
                                nations signing the present convention, nor be domiciled within
                                their territories, nor be concerned in the questions forming the
                                subject of arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6.</p>
                            <p>The agreement provided for by Article 31 of the convention of July
                                29, 1899, shall fix a period during which the exchange between the
                                parties of the memoranda and documents relating to the subject of
                                litigation shall take place. This exchange shall be terminated in
                                all cases before the beginning of the sessions of the arbitral
                                tribunal.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7.</p>
                            <p>The agreement shall fix the sum which the high contracting parties
                                shall place at once at the disposal of the Permanent Bureau of the
                                Court of Arbitration in order to cover the expenses of procedure, in
                                accordance with Article 57 of the convention of July 29, 1899.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8.</p>
                            <p>The arbitral sentence shall specify the periods within which it is to
                                be executed if there is occasion for it.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 9.</p>
                            <p>The present convention is concluded for a period of ten years. It
                                shall take effect one month after the exchange of ratifications. In
                                case neither of the high contracting parties shall have made known
                                six months before the end of the said period its intention of
                                terminating it the convention shall remain obligatory until the
                                expiration of one year from the day on which either of the high
                                contracting parties shall have denounced it.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 10.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be ratified within the shortest possible
                                time and the ratifications shall be exchanged at Madrid.</p>
                            <p>In witness whereof the plenipotentiaries have signed the present
                                convention and have affixed thereto their seals.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Madrid</placeName>,
                                    in duplicate, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-01-23">January 23, 1905</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Joostans.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">The Marquis de Aguilar de
                                                Campoo.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Untitled]</head>
                            <p>His Majesty the King of the Belgians and His Majesty the King of
                                Denmark, desiring to settle as far as possible by means of
                                arbitration the differences which may arise between their countries,
                                have decided to conclude for this purpose a convention and have
                                appointed as their plenipotentiaries, to wit: <list>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of the Belgians—</item>
                                    <item>Baron de Favereau, knight of the Order of Leopold, etc.,
                                        senator, his minister of foreign affairs, and</item>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of Denmark—</item>
                                    <item>Mr. Johan-Wilhelm de Grevenkop-Castenkiold, his
                                        chamberlain and chargé d’affaires at Brussels, knight of the
                                        Order of Danebrog,</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Who, after having communicated to each other their full powers, which
                                were found in good and due form, have agreed on the following
                                articles:</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties agree to submit to the Permanent Court
                                of Arbitration established at The Hague by the convention of July
                                29, 1899, the differences which may arise between them in the cases
                                enumerated in article 3 in so far as they affect neither the vital
                                interests nor the independence of the contracting countries, and
                                provided it has been impossible to reach an amicable settlement by
                                means of direct diplomatic negotiations or by any Other method of
                                conciliation.</p>
                            <pb facs="0205" n="85" xml:id="pg_85"/>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                            <p>It shall be the privilege of the high contracting parties to decide
                                whether the difference which shall have arisen involving its vital
                                interests or its independence and whether it is consequently of such
                                a nature as to be comprised among those which are excepted from
                                obligatory arbitration according to the preceding article.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                            <p>Arbitration shall be obligatory between the high contracting parties— <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Under the reservations indicated in Article 1 in case of
                                        dispute concerning the application or interpretation of any
                                        conventions concluded or to be concluded between them, with
                                        the exception of those in which third powers have
                                        participated or to which they have adhered.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes regarding pecuniary claims when the
                                        obligation to pay is recognized in principle by the high
                                        contracting parties and when the dispute is solely
                                        concerning the amount to be paid. In these cases the
                                        signatory powers renounce the right to avail themselves of
                                        the reservations mentioned above.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be applicable even if the disputes which
                                arise have had their origin in events prior to its conclusion.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                            <p>It is understood that the foregoing article shall not be applicable
                                to differences which may arise between a citizen of one of the
                                parties and the other contracting nation when the courts are
                                competent to decide the controversy according to the laws of that
                                nation.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6.</p>
                            <p>When there shall be an occasion for arbitration between them, the
                                high contracting parties shall, in the absence of compromising
                                clauses to the contrary, conform in all that regards the appointment
                                of the arbitrators and the arbitral procedure to the rules
                                established by the convention signed at The Hague on July 29, 1899,
                                for the pacific settlement of international controversies, except as
                                regards the points indicated hereinbelow.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7.</p>
                            <p>None of the arbitrators shall be a subject of either of the nations
                                signing the present convention nor be domiciled within their
                                territories nor be concerned in the questions which form the subject
                                of arbitration.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8.</p>
                            <p>The agreement provided for by Article 31 of the convention of July
                                29, 1899, shall fix a period within which the exchange shall take
                                place between the two parties of the memoranda and documents
                                relating to the subject of the litigation. This exchange shall be
                                completed at all events before the commencement of the sessions of
                                the arbitral court.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 9.</p>
                            <p>The agreement shall specify the sum which the high contracting
                                parties are to place immediately at the disposal of the permanent
                                bureau of the court of arbitration in order to cover the expenses of
                                procedure in accordance with article 57 of the convention of July
                                29, 1899.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 10.</p>
                            <p>The arbitral sentence shall specify the periods within which it is to
                                be executed.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 11.</p>
                            <p>The present convention is concluded for a period of ten years. It
                                shall take effect one month after the exchange of ratifications. In
                                case neither of the high contracting parties should have given
                                notice six months before the end of said period of its intention to
                                terminate it the convention shall remain obligatory until the
                                expiration of a year from the date on which one of the high
                                contracting parties shall have denounced it.</p>
                            <pb facs="0206" n="86" xml:id="pg_86"/>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 12.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be ratified within the shortest possible
                                period and the ratifications shall be exchanged at Brussels.</p>
                            <p>In witness whereof the plenipotentiaries have signed the present
                                convention and have affixed thereto their seals.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Brussels</placeName>,
                                    in duplicate, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-04-26">April
                                        26, 1905</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Favereau.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">J. W. de
                                                Grevenkop-Castenkiold.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Untitled]</head>
                            <p>His Majesty the King of the Belgians and His Majesty the King of the
                                Hellenes, desiring to settle as far as possible by means of
                                arbitration the differences which may arise between their countries,
                                have decided to conclude for this purpose a convention and have
                                appointed as their plenipotentiaries, to wit: <list>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of the Belgians—</item>
                                    <item>Baron de Groote, knight of the Order of Leopold, etc., his
                                        envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary to His
                                        Majesty the King of the Hellenes; and</item>
                                    <item>His Majesty the King of the Hellenes—</item>
                                    <item>Mr. A. G. Skousès, commander of the Royal Order of the
                                        Saviour, etc., his minister of foreign affairs,</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Who, after having communicated to each other their full powers, which
                                were found in good and due form, have agreed on the following
                                articles:</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties agree to submit to the Permanent Court
                                of Arbitration established at The Hague by the convention of July
                                29, 1899, the differences which may arise between them in the cases
                                enumerated in Article 5 in so far as they affect neither the vital
                                interests, the honor, nor the independence or sovereignty of the
                                contracting countries, and provided it has been impossible to reach
                                an amicable settlement by means of direct diplomatic negotiations or
                                by any other method of conciliation.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                            <p>It shall be the privilege of the high contracting parties to decide
                                whether the difference which has arisen involves its vital
                                interests, its independence, or its sovereignty, and whether it is
                                consequently of such a nature as to be comprised among those which
                                are excepted from obligatory arbitration according to the preceding
                                article.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                            <p>Under the reservations indicated in Article 1 arbitration shall be
                                obligatory between the high contracting parties— <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes concerning the application or
                                        interpretation of any conventions concluded between them,
                                        with the exception of those in which third powers may have
                                        participated or to which they have adhered.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>In case of disputes relating to pecuniary claims between
                                        the two contracting parties based on damages when the
                                        principle of indemnity is recognized by the parties.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                            <p>The obligatory arbitration which is accepted on the matters mentioned
                                in Article 3 shall not be claimed for acts prior to the present
                                convention.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 5.</p>
                            <p>When there shall be an occasion for arbitration between them, the
                                high contracting parties shall, in the absence of compromising
                                clauses to the contrary, conform in all that concerns the
                                appointment of the arbitrators and the arbitral procedure to the
                                rules established by the convention signed at The Hague on July 29,
                                1899, for the pacific settlement of international controversies,
                                except as regards the points indicated herein below.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 6.</p>
                            <p>None of the arbitrators shall be a citizen of either of the nations
                                signing the present convention nor be domiciled within their
                                territories, nor be interested in the questions which form the
                                subject of arbitration.</p>
                            <pb facs="0207" n="87" xml:id="pg_87"/>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 7.</p>
                            <p>The agreement provided for by Article 31 of the convention of July
                                29, 1899, shall fix a term during which the exchange shall take
                                place between the two parties of the memoranda and documents
                                relative to the subject of litigation. This exchange shall be
                                completed at all events before the beginning of the sessions of the
                                arbitral court.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 8.</p>
                            <p>The arbitral sentence shall specify the period within which it is to
                                be executed.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 9.</p>
                            <p>The present convention is concluded for a period of five years. It
                                will take effect one month after the exchange of ratifications. In
                                case neither of the high contracting parties should have given
                                notice six months before the end of said period of its intention to
                                terminate it, the convention shall remain obligatory until the
                                expiration of a year from the day on which one or the other of the
                                high contracting parties shall have denounced it.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 10.</p>
                            <p>The present convention shall be ratified in the shortest possible
                                times and the ratification, shall be exchanged at Athens.</p>
                            <p>In witness whereof the plenipotentiaries have signed the present
                                convention and have affixed thereto their seals.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>Athens</placeName> in
                                    duplicate, <date calendar="julian gregorian" when="1905-05-02">April 19 (May 2), 1905</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">P. de Groote.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">A. Skousès.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>