<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chinese Minister.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1905</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d135</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">135</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1905-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1905-01-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-01-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="135"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d135">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Chinese Minister</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-01-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 20, 1905</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 56.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I had the honor to refer to the Secretary of the
                    Navy a copy of your note of the 4th instant in regard to the case of the late Ho
                    Choy Yeen, a Chinese subject, whose death by drowning at Canton in September
                    last is said to have been caused by American sailors.</p>
                <pb facs="0235" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/>
                <p>Under date of the 7th instant the Secretary of the Navy forwards to this
                    Department a copy of a report on the subject by the commander of the Philippine
                    Squadron, from which report I quote the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>On the evening of the day in question, September 24, 1904, the Chinaman
                            was thrown, or fell, from the bridge crossing the Pearl River, a narrow
                            and shallow stream dividing the city of Canton from the island of
                            Shameon, on which are the residences of the entire foreign population.
                            Although the bridge is crowded with passengers at all times, there seem
                            to have been no witnesses near enough to the occurrence to have been
                            able to identify any of the persons connected therewith. The only
                            evidence connecting the sailors of the <hi rend="italic">Helena</hi>
                            with the affair was that witnesses testified it was committed by foreign
                            sailors wearing a certain white uniform and that sailors from the <hi
                                rend="italic">Helena</hi> were ashore at the time. The occurrence
                            took place after dusk. The men from the <hi rend="italic">Helena</hi>
                            were special first class and very few in number, each of whom
                            satisfactorily accounted for himself at the time of this occurrence.
                            Every opportunity was given the witnesses by the captain of the <hi
                                rend="italic">Helena</hi> to identify the members of his crew who
                            might have committed the crime, but no identification was made, the only
                            man being identified having satisfactorily proven that he was elsewhere
                            at the time of the occurrence. It appears that men from an English
                            gunboat were ashore at the time and in practically the same uniform. I
                            am of the opinion, therefore, that there is no case against any member
                            of the crew of the <hi rend="italic">Helena.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I am informed that a subscription has been taken up which will furnish
                            the widow of the unfortunate victim a sufficient sum to support her
                            during her lifetime.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>From the foregoing it would appear that no proof has been advanced to show that
                    American sailors were responsible for the drowning of the unfortunate man.</p>
                <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
