<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Rockhill to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1905</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d235</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">235</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1905-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1905-09-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019102796"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Boycott</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-09-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="235"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d235">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Rockhill</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-09-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 5, 1905</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 84.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith a
                    translation of a note which I received yesterday from Prince Ch’ing in reply to
                    mine of the 27th of August, copy of which I transmitted to you in my dispatch
                    No. 77 of August 29.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>The statement made by the prince “that hereafter all classes of Chinese will
                    certainly be able to go to America without receiving any illtreatment” might be
                    thought to show a complete misunderstanding of the formal and often-repeated
                    declarations we have made him that the coming of Chinese laborers to the United
                    States is absolutely prohibited. Read, however, in conjunction with the clear
                    terms of my note of August 27 and his own statement in the first lines of this
                    note, there is no doubt that he perfectly understands the position of our
                    government.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. W. Rockhill.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0346" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss type="from">Prince Ch’ing</gloss> to Minister <persName type="to"
                                >Rockhill</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your excellency’s dispatch of
                        August 27, in which you said that the Government of the United States was
                        most desirous to meet, so far as the general interests of your country
                        permitted, the wishes of the Imperial Government concerning the coming of
                        Chinese subjects to the United States, other than those of the laboring
                        classes. Your excellency then quoted from the President’s order of June 24
                        last (a copy of which order you had previously sent to my board), making it
                        clear that “the purpose of the Government of the United States is to show
                        the widest and heartiest courtesy toward all merchants, teachers, students,
                        and travelers who may come to the United States,” and you assured me that
                        the President could not take any step beyond the issuance of these orders
                        until further action of Congress on the matter, as his action is limited by
                        the laws and statutes of the United States. Your excellency then further
                        stated that notwithstanding all this my government has allowed the agitation
                        to continue, to the great pecuniary loss of our people, as well as yours,
                        and you asked why the Chinese Government had not taken such action as would
                        have shown the people the real friendship which we have for the United
                        States.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to state that upon the receipt of this dispatch from your
                        excellency I made inquiry into the boycott matter and found that an imperial
                        edict had recently been issued, and a copy of it had been sent to you by my
                        board. From this it is evident that the Chinese Government has taken
                        thorough action in the matter, to the end that neither Chinese nor American
                        citizens may suffer pecuniary losses.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency has said that the President can not take any further step in
                        the matter until Congress has taken some action, and I may say that the
                        Chinese Government has great confidence that the President will certainly
                        take some such further action later on. Word has already been sent to the
                        various viceroys and governors directing them to inform their people that
                        both the President of the United States and your excellency have a deep
                        feeling of friendship for China in your hearts, and that hereafter all
                        classes of Chinese will certainly be able to go to America without receiving
                        any ill treatment.</p>
                    <p>But now that the date of the next opening of Congress is not far distant we
                        ought to take up again the discussion of the coolie immigration treaty, in
                        order to have it all ready for their consideration and approval.</p>
                    <p>It becomes my duty to send this dispatch to your excellency, that you may
                        inform the Department of State of the matter, and I desire to state that a
                        reply hereto would be appreciated.</p>
                    <p>A necessary dispateh.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <date
                                calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar                         gregorian"
                                when="1905-09-04">Kuanghsü, XXXI year, 8th moon, 6th day (September
                                4, 1905)</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <seg rendition="#left">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</seg>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
