<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Tower to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1905</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1905-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1905-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="397"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d397">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Tower</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-11-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 14, 1905</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 798.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the Honor to report to you for your
                    information the case of one Maurice Kahn, a native of Alsace naturalized as an
                    American citizen, who has been fined 600 marks for nonperformance of military
                    service and whose application for the removal of that fine has recently been
                    rejected by the German authorities upon the ground that as he was born in Alsace
                    he is held to be still a German subject.</p>
                <p>It appears that Maurice Kahn was born at Biesheim, Kreis Colmar, in Ober-Elsass,
                    on the 30th of June, 1879, and emigrated to the United States in 1891 or 1892.
                    He does not remember the exact date of his emigration, though he says that he
                    was 12 or 13 3years of age at the time. Since the date of his emigration he has
                    not returned to Germany, but was naturalized as a citizen of the United States
                    before the district court of the third judicial district of Oklahoma on October
                    18, 1904, in proof of which he has exhibited at this embassy the certificate of
                    his naturalization in due form issued by that court.</p>
                <p>He applied to this embassy in June, 1905, for permission to return to
                    Alsace-Lorraine for the purpose of making a visit and I addressed a note to the
                    Imperial German ministry for foreign affairs on the 25th of July, setting forth
                    his request for permission to revisit his former home and asking that, if the
                    facts of his case as presented by him were found to be substantially true, his
                    desire might be acceded to.</p>
                <p>I have received a reply from the ministry for foreign affairs, under date of the
                    28th of October, 1905, in which the ministry declares that Maurice Kahn was
                    condemend by the Imperial provincial court at Colmar on the 9th of December,
                    1903, to pay a fine of 600 marks for evasion of military service and that orders
                    were issued to the police officials for his arrest. The ministry declares that
                    “as Kahn is still a subject of Alsace-Lorraine he requires no especial
                    permission to reside within this country, but if he should return he would be
                    liable to fulfill the sentence passed upon him, as well as to the ultimate
                    performance of his military service.”</p>
                <p>This case, which is similar to those of Emil B. Kauffman (<ref
                        target="frus1896#pg_186">Foreign Relations, 1896, p. 186</ref>), Casimir
                    Hartmann (<ref target="frus1897#pg_230">Foreign Relations 1897, p. 230</ref>),
                    Jacob Roos (<ref target="frus1903#pg_442">Foreign Relations 1903, p. 442</ref>),
                    and Emil Vibert (<ref target="frus1904#pg_317">Foreign Relations 1904, p.
                        317</ref>), indicates that the German Government still maintains its
                    attitude in regard to the connection of the Reichsland provinces of Alsace and
                    Lorraine with the Empire and confirms its determination hitherto frequently
                    announced not to admit that the treaty of naturalization with the United States
                    entered into in 1868 extends to those provinces as well as to other portions of
                    the Empire.</p>
                <p>Since receiving the note of the 28th of October from the Imperial ministry for
                    foreign affairs I have made a verbal inquiry there as to whether the authorities
                    would be willing to grant permission to Mr. Kahn to return to his native country
                    upon a further request of this embassy and in view of his naturalization as an
                    American citizen: but I have received a verbal reply that as the naturalization
                    treaty with the United States is not considered by the German Government <pb
                        facs="0591" n="471" xml:id="pg_471"/> to apply to Alsace-Lorraine the German
                    authorities still regard Kahn as a subject of those provinces.</p>
                <p>The situation is a singular one in view of the extraordinary privileges of
                    autonomy and protective control enjoyed by the provinces of Alsace and Lorraine,
                    which were fully discussed in Mr. Olney’s dispatch of the 3d of March, 1896, to
                    Mr. Jackson (<ref target="frus1896#pg_187">Foreign Relations 1896, p.
                    187</ref>). But until the United States and Germany shall agree upon some terms
                    by which American naturalization may be recognized equally throughout the whole
                    Empire there appears to be no method by which a native of Alsace-Lorraine can
                    claim in those provinces the privileges of American citizenship, even after his
                    naturalization in the United States.</p>
                <p>I have discussed this question at considerable length with the authorities at the
                    Imperial German ministry for foreign affairs upon several occasions since I have
                    been at this post, and the general impression that I have obtained is that the
                    difficulty does not arise exclusively in regard to the naturalization in America
                    of subjects of those provinces, but that the relation of the Reichsland to the
                    whole of the Empire is such in view of the fact that when Alsace and Lorraine
                    were ceded to Germany the present federation had already been formed and the
                    Empire established, in consequence of which the provinces belong to the
                    federation as a whole and not to any particular state, no one of the federated
                    states of the Empire having any greater rights or authority in the Reichsland
                    than has any other; that consequently there are a number of quite delicate
                    questions in connection with these provinces still in abeyance between the
                    different federated states of the Empire which the government is unwilling to
                    take up at present and which may not be definitively settled for some years to
                    come. I have gained the impression that it is chiefly this consideration which
                    prevents an agreement with us in regard to Alsace-Lorraine, lest the extension
                    at present of our treaty of naturalization to the provinces of the Reichsland
                    should create a precedent that might be found embarrassing hereafter in the
                    adjustment of certain unsettled claims between the States of the Empire
                    themselves.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charlemagne Tower.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
