<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-06-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="416" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d416">
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">By the President of the United States of
                                America.</hi></head>
                        <p rend="center">A PROCLAMATION.</p>
                        <p>Whereas a Convention between the United States of America and His Majesty
                            the King of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the
                            British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India acting in the name
                            of His Highness the Sultan of Zanzibar, by which the United States
                            agrees to renounce in the British Protectorate of Zanzibar, and in that
                            part of the mainland dominions of His Highness, the Sultan of Zanzibar
                            which lies within the Protectorate of <pb facs="0606" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/> British East Africa, its extraterritoral rights in
                            favor of the British courts therein established, was concluded and
                            signed by their respective Plenipotentiaries at Washington, on the
                            twenty-fifth day of February, one thousand nine hundred and five, the
                            original of which Convention is word for word as follows:</p>
                        <p>The United States of America and His Majesty the King of the United
                            Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond
                            the Seas, Emperor of India, acting in the name of His Highness the
                            Sultan of Zanzibar, have, for the purposes hereinafter stated, appointed
                            as their Plenipotentiaries, namely:</p>
                        <p>The President of the United States of America, the Honorable John Hay,
                            Secretary of State of the United States of America; and</p>
                        <p>His Brittanic Majesty, the Right Honorable Sir Henry Mortimer Durand, G.
                            C. M. G., K. C. S. I., K. C. I. E., his Ambassador Extraordinary and
                            Plenipotentiary near the Government of the United States;</p>
                        <p>Who, after having communicated each to the other their respective full
                            powers, found in good and due form, have agreed upon the following
                            articles:</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The United States of America agrees to renounce in the British
                            Protectorate of Zanzibar, and in that part of the mainland dominions of
                            His Highness the Sultan of Zanzibar which lies within the Protectorate
                            of British East Africa, the extraterritorial rights secured to it by the
                            treaty of September 21, 1833, between the United States and the Sultan
                            of Muscat, and the treaty of July 3, 1886, between the United States and
                            Zanzibar.</p>
                        <p>The jurisdiction exercised thereunder by consular courts of the United
                            States in the British Protectorate of Zanzibar and in that part of the
                            mainland dominions of His Highness the Sultan of Zanzibar which is under
                            British Protection, and all the exceptional privileges, exemptions, and
                            immunities enjoyed by citizens of the United States as a part of or
                            appurtenant to such jurisdiction, shall absolutely cease and determine.
                            It being understood, however, that this renunciation shall not take
                            effect until such time as the rights of extraterritoriality enjoyed in
                            Zanzibar by other nations shall have been likewise renounced.</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.</p>
                        <p>In consideration of this renunciation by the United States of America,
                            the Government of His Brittanic Majesty agrees to empower the competent
                            British courts which have been established in the British Protectorate
                            of Zanzibar and in that part of the mainland dominions of His Highness
                            the Sultan of Zanzibar which is under British protection, to exercise
                            jurisdiction over citizens of the United States the same as over British
                            subjects and British protected persons, and that citizens of the United
                            States shall have in and before said courts all the rights and
                            privileges that belong and are accorded therein to British subjects and
                            to British protected persons.</p>
                        <pb facs="0607" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The present Convention shall be ratified by the President of the United
                            States of America, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate
                            thereof, and by His Brittanic Majesty, and the ratifications shall be
                            exchanged at Washington as soon as possible.</p>
                        <p>In faith whereof, we, the respective Plenipotentiaries, have signed this
                            Convention and have hereunto affixed our seals.</p>
                        <p>Done in duplicate at the City of Washington this twenty-fifth day of
                            February, in the year of our Lord one thousand nine hundred and
                            five.</p>
                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay</hi> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</p>
                        <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">H M Durand</hi> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</p>
                        <p>And whereas the said Convention has been duly ratified on both parts, and
                            the ratifications of the two governments were exchanged in the City of
                            Washington, on the twelfth day of June, one thousand nine hundred and
                            five;</p>
                        <p>Now, therefore, be it known that I, <hi rend="smallcaps">Theodore
                                Roosevelt</hi>, President of the United States of America, have
                            caused the said Convention to be made public, to the end that the same
                            and every article and clause thereof may be observed and fulfilled with
                            good faith by the United States and the citizens thereof.</p>
                        <p>In testimony whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and caused the seal of
                            the United States of America to be affixed.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <seg type="margin">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>]</seg> Done at
                                the city of <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian us-republic" when="1905-06-12">this twelfth
                                    day of June, in the year of our Lord one thousand nine hundred
                                    and five, and of the independence of the United States of
                                    America the one hundred and twenty-ninth</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Theodore Roosevelt</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>By the President:<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">Francis B.
                                    Loomis</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary of
                                    State.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>