<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-11-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="602" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d602">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-11-30"><hi rend="italic">November 30,
                                    1905</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 346.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your telegraphic instructions received the 25th instant.</p>
                        <p>On the same day I dispatched a note to the minister for foreign affairs
                            informing him of my instructions in the above sense and stating that
                            accordingly I should thenceforth have the honor of addressing him in
                            regard to American diplomatic interests in Korea.</p>
                        <p>The reply of Count Katsura expresses the profound satisfaction of the
                            Japanese Government at the prompt withdrawal of the legation of the
                            United States from Seoul.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to inclose herewith copies of the above-mentioned
                            notes.</p>
                        <p>Your action in immediately suppressing the legation at Seoul and
                            initiating the conduct of diplomatic relations vis-a-vis Korea through
                            the medium of Japan is much appreciated here. It is received as a
                            welcome expression of America’s willing acquiescence in the order of
                            things determined by the new Japan-Korea agreement; and the fact that
                            the Government of the United States has been the first to take this step
                            is esteemed as a very graceful and friendly act. The inclosed
                            translation of an editorial from the “Jiji Shimbo” [not printed] of this
                            date indicates the feeling of the Japanese on this subject.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington
                            Wilson.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">Wilson</persName>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Minister of Foreign
                                    Affairs</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-11-25"><hi rend="italic">November 25,
                                        1905</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: I have the honor to
                                communicate to your excellency the fact that I have to-day received
                                from the Secretary of State telegraphic instructions, whereby I am
                                informed that in view of the recent convention between Japan and
                                Korea, in virtue of which the foreign relations of Korea are to be
                                conducted through your excellency’s government, the American
                                legation at Seoul has been withdrawn.</p>
                            <p>The Secretary of State, therefore directs that this legation assume
                                the representation of the United States in diplomatic matters
                                affecting rights of treaty, persons, and property in Korea.</p>
                            <p>Accordingly I shall hereafter have the honor of addressing your
                                excellency in dealing with such questions.</p>
                            <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington
                                Wilson.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure
                                2.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister of Foreign
                                        Affairs</gloss> to Chargé <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-11-28"><hi rend="italic">November 28, 1905</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your note of the 25th instant, informing me that in view
                                of the recent convention between Japan and Korea, in virtue of which
                                the foreign relations of Korea are to be conducted through the
                                Imperial Government, the United States have withdrawn their legation
                                at Seoul, that their legation at Tokyo will assume the
                                representation of the United States in diplomatic matters affecting
                                American <pb facs="0736" n="616" xml:id="pg_616"/> rights of treaty,
                                persons, and property in Korea, and that you will hereafter address
                                me in dealing with such questions.</p>
                            <p>In reply I beg to state that the Imperial Government are profoundly
                                satisfied with the prompt and just steps which the United States
                                Government have taken in the matter.</p>
                            <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed>Count <hi rend="smallcaps">Katsura
                                Taro.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>