<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Clayton to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1905</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d635</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">635</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1905-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1905-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-03-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="635"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d635">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Clayton</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-03-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 16, 1905</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2708.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    the Department’s telegraphic instruction of the 14th instant relative to the
                    question of protection, by the Mexican authorities, of the Yaqui Copper Company
                    against alleged threatened Indian outrages upon said company.</p>
                <p>Pursuant to said instruction, I called upon Mr. Mariscal yesterday, and, after
                    discussing the Yaqui Indian question, so far as relates to American citizens and
                    their interests, I left with him a copy of said telegraphic instruction.</p>
                <p>I called Mr. Mariscal’s attention to the fact that the Indian outrages of late
                    appeared to have been directed almost entirely against Americans carrying on
                    legitimate business in the state of Sonora; that my information from various
                    sources was to the effect that, while the state authorities had adopted very
                    drastic measures against the apparently peaceful Yaquis employed as laborers on
                    the plantations of Mr. Carlos H. Johnson and others, they had not, in any case
                    where Americans had been massacred, made any effective pursuit of the band or
                    bands responsible for the same; that my information had impressed me strongly
                    with the belief that all of the massacres referred to were perpetrated by the
                    same roving band of wild Indians; that, from the accounts of the different
                    massacres given by different eye-witnesses, the band or bands were comparatively
                    small; that, with great respect for the governor of Sonora, my information
                    impressed me strongly with the belief that his drastic measures against the
                    apparently peaceful Indians had been barren of results. I remarked that the
                    local authorities had, at least in one instance (that of Carlos H. Johnson),
                    denied to an American, who had been a great sufferer growing out of said
                    depredations, the right to bear arms for the defense of himself, family, and
                    employees; and, under such circumstances, it would seem but just and proper that
                    the Mexican authorities should break up the small band or bands of Indians who
                    have so long terrorized the region in question.</p>
                <p>Mr. Mariscal replied that, at present, they had 100 soldiers in the disturbed
                    region; that they had given orders to increase this number to 200; that the
                    great bulk of the Yaqui Indians had been deported from Sonora to Yucatan; that
                    he would transmit by telegram, to the governor of Sonora, a copy of your
                    aforesaid telegraphic instructions, with proper recommendations, and that he
                    would communicate with him by letter the views that I had just expressed to
                    him.</p>
                <p>He informed me that he had in the course of preparation, and early delivery, a
                    note to me, in reply to mine upon this subject of the 11th ultimo. This note
                    grew out of your instruction No. 1220, of the 1st ultimo, inclosing a copy of a
                    communication from the Mina Grande Mining Company, and out of a communication to
                    this embassy, under date of the 28th of January last, from the Yaqui Smelting
                    and Refining Company.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Powell Clayton.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
