<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-03-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="646" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d646">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Mexican Ambassador</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy
                                        of Mexico<lb/>to the United States of America</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-03-11"><hi rend="italic">March
                                        11, 1905</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 130.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Most Excellent Sir</hi>: Pursuant to special
                            instructions from my government, that are set forth in the copy inclosed
                            with this note, which will acquaint you with all the particulars of the
                            matter therein dealt with, I have the honor to apply to you with a
                            request that the proper measures be taken in the case by the Government
                            of the United States and that you may be pleased to advise me of
                            whatever decision may be reached, so that I may in turn report to the
                            Government of Mexico.</p>
                        <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">M. de Azpíroz.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Inclosure.—Translation.]</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Relations</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-02-11"><hi rend="italic">February 11, 1905</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>The secretary of government, in an official letter numbered 6814, of
                                the 26th of September last, makes the following statement:</p>
                            <p>“The chairman of the superior board of health writes the following to
                                this department under date of the 22d instant:</p>
                            <p>“‘At the meeting held yesterday by this board an opinion of the
                                counsel member of the corporation, here quoted, was approved: The
                                counsel of the board has acquainted himself with the case that
                                occurred at Progreso on the 13th day of July last in connection with
                                the disinfection of the English steamer <hi rend="italic">Atheniana</hi> by Dr. J. F. Harrison, a physician in the
                                sanitary federal service, effected under such conditions that 80
                                bales of henequen were set on fire. By direction of the chairman of
                                the board an inquiry was instituted, from which it appears that Mr.
                                Harrison does, in the character above described, disinfect vessels
                                clearing from Progreso for American ports, and while the said
                                gentleman asserts that he only disinfects vessels when requested by
                                the agents or masters, as there may be truth in the common report
                                that unless disinfected by the said American physician vessels are
                                not admitted into ports of the United States, the undersigned
                                believes that the department of foreign relations should be fully
                                apprised of the incident and send it a copy of the investigation
                                conducted by the sanitary delegate to the end that such measures as
                                may be appropriate be, if necessary, taken through the diplomatic
                                channel.’”</p>
                            <p>This department has examined the case in the light of the fact that
                                the Mexican Government never intended to admit American physicians
                                into the national territory in an official capacity. This was made
                                quite clear by the last quarantine decreed by the government of the
                                State of Texas against Mexico on account of the yellow fever, and
                                again when the American Government asked permission to have the
                                disinfecting barge <hi rend="italic">Sanator</hi> stationed in Vera
                                Cruz for the disinfection of vessels clearing from that port for the
                                United States. On that occasion the permission was refused because
                                the said port possessed facilities for every kind of disinfection
                                and because the Second International American Conference had
                                declared that all matters pertaining to international sanitary
                                police remained subject to the jurisdiction of each government
                                within its own territory. Lastly, when Mr. Barlow, then
                                consul-general of the United States at Mexico City, claimed that
                                Doctor Cofer should be recognized in the federal district as the
                                physician whose duty it was to issue bills of health to persons
                                intending to visit the United States, Mr. Barlow could not carry his
                                points and confined himself to issuing the said certificates
                                personally, and instructed the consuls under his jurisdiction to do
                                likewise. <pb facs="0770" n="650" xml:id="pg_650"/> In the issuance
                                of such certificates Mr. Barlow was assisted by two physicians who
                                had no official character.</p>
                            <p>In view of the foregoing, I have the honor to communicate to you the
                                above-quoted official dispatches in order that you bring the matter
                                to the knowledge of the Department of State in the light of the
                                precedents in the case to the end that appropriate measures be taken
                                in the matter herein referred to.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>