<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minister Jackson to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1905</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d668</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">668</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1905-12-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1905-12-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-12-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-12-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="668"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d668">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Jackson</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Athens</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-12-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 26, 1905</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 23. Montenegrin series.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report the receipt to-day of
                    a note from the minister of foreign affairs at Cettinje, dated the 6/19th
                    instant, informing me that deputies had assembled that day, the Skupshtina had
                    been opened by a speech from the throne delivered by His Royal Highness the
                    Prince of Montenegro, and the constitution had been solemnly proclaimed. I am
                    requested to inform you that “by this act, so important and so memorable for the
                    people of Montenegro, who are filled with gratitude and devotion to their
                    magnanimous master (Maitre), the Principality which has heretofore been governed
                    under an autocratic régime, has become a constitutional monarchy.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Voucovitch writes that, “guided by ardent and profound affection for his
                    subjects, the Prince, during the forty-six years of his reign, has ever been
                    vigilant in behalf of the safety and prosperity of his country, and has never
                    failed to interest himself sincerely in assuring their intellectual and economic
                    development. In accord with the spirit of the age, His Royal Highness came to
                    the conclusion that every man belonging to a cultivated state should at the same
                    time be a free citizen, and in consequence he had decided of his own free will
                    to institute a constitutional and representative régime.” The proclamation <pb
                        facs="0787" n="667" xml:id="pg_667"/> of the 18/31st of October and
                    subsequent decrees providing for elections on the principle of suffrage,
                    universal, equal, and direct, was the result.</p>
                <p>In the speech from the throne the Prince refers to the reciprocal confidence
                    between Prince and people which has existed in Montenegro for generations and
                    which has resulted in the formation of a state whose independence has been
                    recognized for centuries. The constitution is granted, the Prince says, not
                    because the development of the state and its prosperity have been hindered by an
                    autocratic government, but because the time has come, in his opinion, when a
                    more progressive régime should be introduced. This constitution the Prince
                    characterized as “an inheritance from his liberal ancestors, who had always been
                    the first to inculcate ideas of liberty upon the hearts and minds of their
                    subjects.”</p>
                <p>In his speech the Prince refers to the good relations existing between Orthodox
                    and Mohammedans in the Principality, while the sufferings of the Serbs in Old
                    Servia and Macedonia “find an echo in the hearts of all Montenegrins.” Relations
                    with Turkey are, however, described as friendly. In speaking of foreign
                    relations the Prince mentions Russia first, “to whom, after God, Montenegro owes
                    the most gratitude,” and then the Emperor Francis Joseph, with whom his personal
                    relations “have never been troubled.” He also refers to the family ties
                    connecting Montenegro and Italy, and to the promise made by the German Emperor
                    to accredit a representative at Cettinje, as well as to the friendly relations
                    existing with Great Britain and France. He adds that among the countries which
                    have shown evidences of friendliness “must not be forgotten the United States of
                    America, which has recently accredited a representative to my court.” He also
                    mentions the good relations between Montenegro and Servia and Bulgaria. After
                    reading the speech, the Prince took the oath to support the constitution.</p>
                <p>The Skupshtina has already adjourned, and the mandates of its members are
                    considered as having expired. New elections are to be held next October for
                    members of the first regular Skupshtina, and in the meantime the government is
                    to be carried on by the ministry just appointed by the Prince.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John B. Jackson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
