<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-12-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="915" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d915">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Meyer</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">St
                                        Petersburg</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-12-13"><hi rend="italic">December 13,
                                    1905</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 341.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In conformity with the Department’s cable
                            instructions of October 16 and 23, I have the honor to forward herewith
                            twelve copies of the treaty of peace, concluded between Russia and Japan
                            on the 5th of September, 1905, at Portsmouth.</p>
                        <p>In this connection I cabled the Department to-day as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Am forwarding to-day to Department twelve copies Portsmouth
                                    Treaty.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">G. v. L. Meyer.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Ratification of the treaty of peace signed at
                                    Portsmouth August 23, 1905, between Russia and
                                Japan.</hi></head>
                            <p>By the helping grace of God, we, Nicholas II, Emperor and Autocrat of
                                all the Russias etc., hereby declare that, in consequence of a
                                mutual agreement between us and His Majesty, the Emperor of Japan,
                                our plenipotentiaries concluded and signed at Portsmouth, August 23,
                                1905, a treaty of peace which, word for word, reads as follows:</p>
                            <p>His Majesty, the Emperor of all the Russias, on the one hand, and His
                                Majesty, the Emperor of Japan, on the other hand, being animated by
                                the desire to restore the benefits <pb facs="0945" n="825" xml:id="pg_825"/> of peace for their countries and their
                                peoples, have decided to conclude a treaty of peace and have
                                appointed for this purpose their plenipotentiaries, to wit: <list>
                                    <item>His Majesty the Emperor of Russia—</item>
                                    <item>His Excellency, Mr. Sergius Witte, his secretary of state
                                        and president of the committee of ministers of the Empire of
                                        Russia, and</item>
                                    <item>His Excellency, Baron Roman Rosen, master of the Imperial
                                        Court of Russia and his ambassador extraordinary and
                                        plenipotentiary to the United States of America;</item>
                                    <item>And His Majesty, the Emperor of Japan—</item>
                                    <item>His Excellency, Baron Komura Iutaro, Iusammi, knight of
                                        the Imperial Order of the Rising Sun, his minister of
                                        foreign affairs, and</item>
                                    <item>His Excellency, Mr. Takahira Kogoro, Iusammi, knight of
                                        the Imperial Order of the Sacred Treasure, his envoy
                                        extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary to the United
                                        States of America;</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>Who, after having exchanged their full powers, found in good and due
                                form, concluded the following articles:</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.</p>
                            <p>There shall be in the future peace and friendship between Their
                                Majesties the Emperor of all the Russias and the Emperor of Japan,
                                as well as between their respective nations and subjects.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The Imperial Government of Russia, recognizing that Japan has
                                predominant political, military, and economic interests in Korea,
                                agrees not to interfere or place obstacles in the way of any measure
                                of direction, protection, and supervision which the Imperial
                                Government of Japan may deem necessary to adopt in Korea.</p>
                            <p>It is agreed that Russian subjects in Korea shall be treated in
                                exactly the same manner as the citizens of other foreign countries;
                                that is, that they shall be placed on the same footing as the
                                citizens of the most-favored nation.</p>
                            <p>It is likewise agreed that, in order to avoid any cause of
                                misunderstanding, the two high contracting parties shall refrain
                                from adopting, on the Russo-Korean frontier, any military measures
                                which might menace the security of the Russian or Korean
                                territory.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Russia and Japan mutually engage: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>To completely and simultaneously evacuate Manchuria, with
                                        the exception of the territory over which the lease of the
                                        peninsula of Liaotung extends, in accordance with the
                                        provisions of additional Article I annexed to this treaty,
                                        and</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>To entirely and completely restore to the exclusive
                                        administration of China all parts of Manchuria now occupied
                                        by Russian and Japanese troops, or which are under their
                                        control, with the exception of the above-mentioned
                                        territory.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>The Imperial Government of Russia declares that it has no territorial
                                advantages or preferential or exclusive concessions in Manchuria of
                                such a nature as to impair the sovereignty of China or which are
                                incompatible with the principle of equal opportunity.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Russia and Japan mutually pledge themselves not to place any obstacle
                                in the way of general measures which apply equally to all nations
                                and which China might adopt for the development of commerce and
                                industry in Manchuria.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article V</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The Imperial Government of Russia cedes to the Imperial Government of
                                Japan, with the consent of the Government of China, the lease of
                                Port Arthur, of Talien, and of the adjacent territories and
                                territorial waters, as well as the rights, privileges, and
                                concessions connected with this lease or forming part thereof, and
                                it likewise cedes to the Imperial Government of Japan all the public
                                works and property within the territory over which the
                                above-mentioned lease extends.</p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties mutually engage to obtain from the
                                Government of China the consent mentioned in the foregoing
                                clause.</p>
                            <p>The Imperial Government of Japan gives on its part the assurance that
                                the property rights of Russian subjects within the above-mentioned
                                territory shall be absolutely respected.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article VI</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The Imperial Government of Russia obligates itself to yield to the
                                Imperial Government of Japan, without compensation and with the
                                consent of the Chinese Government, the <pb facs="0946" n="826" xml:id="pg_826"/> Chan-chun (Kwan-Chien-Tsi) and Port Arthur
                                Railroad and all its branches, with all the rights, privileges, and
                                property thereunto belonging within this region, as well as all the
                                coal mines in said region belonging to this railroad or being
                                operated for its benefit.</p>
                            <p>The two high contracting parties mutually pledge themselves to obtain
                                from the Chinese Government the consent mentioned in the foregoing
                                clause.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article VII</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Russia and Japan agree to operate their respective railroads in
                                Manchuria for commercial and industrial purposes exclusively, but by
                                no means for strategic purposes.</p>
                            <p>It is agreed that this restriction does not apply to the railroads
                                within the territory covered by the lease of the Liao-tung
                                peninsula.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article VIII</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The Imperial Governments of Russia and Japan, with a view to favoring
                                and facilitating relations and traffic, shall conclude, as soon as
                                possible, a separate convention to govern their operations of repair
                                on the railroads in Manchuria.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article IX</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The Imperial Government of Russia cedes to the Imperial Government of
                                Japan, in perpetuity and full sovereignty, the southern part of the
                                island of Saghalin, and all the islands adjacent thereto, as well as
                                all the public works and property there situated. The fiftieth
                                parallel of north latitude is adopted as the limit of the ceded
                                territory. The exact boundary line of this territory shall be
                                determined in accordance with the provisions of additional Article
                                II annexed to this treaty.</p>
                            <p>Japan and Russia mutually agree not to construct within their
                                respective possessions on the island of Saghalin, and the islands
                                adjacent thereto, any fortification or similar military work. They
                                likewise mutually agree not to adopt any military measures which
                                might hinder the free navigation of the Straits of La Perouse and
                                Tartary.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article X</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The right is reserved to Russian subjects inhabiting the territory
                                ceded to Japan to sell their real property and return to their
                                country; however, if they prefer to remain in the ceded territory,
                                they shall be guarded and protected in the full enjoyment of their
                                property rights and the exercise of their industries provided they
                                submit to the laws and jurisdiction of Japan. Japan shall have
                                perfect liberty to withdraw the right of residence in this territory
                                from all inhabitants laboring under political or administrative
                                incapacity, or to deport them from this territory. It pledges
                                itself, however, to fully respect the property rights of these
                                inhabitants.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article XI</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Russia obligates itself to reach an understanding with Japan in order
                                to grant to Japanese subjects fishing rights along the coast of the
                                Russian possessions in the Seas of Japan, Okhotsk, and Bering.</p>
                            <p>It is agreed that the above-mentioned obligation shall not impair the
                                rights already belonging to Russian or foreign subjects in these
                                regions.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article XII</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The treaty of commerce and navigation between Russia and Japan having
                                been annulled by the war, the Imperial Governments of Russia and
                                Japan agree to adopt as a basis for their commercial relations,
                                until the conclusion of a new treaty of commerce and navigation on
                                the basis of the treaty in force before the present war, the system
                                of reciprocity on the principle of the most favored nation,
                                including import and export tariffs, custom-house formalities,
                                transit and tonnage dues, and the admission and treatment of the
                                agents, subjects, and vessels of one country in the territory of the
                                other.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article XIII</hi>.</p>
                            <p>As soon as possible after the present treaty takes effect, all
                                prisoners of war shall be mutually returned. The Imperial
                                Governments of Russia and Japan shall each appoint a special
                                commissioner to take charge of the prisoners. All prisoners in the
                                custody of one of the governments shall be delivered to the
                                commissioner of the other government or to his duly authorized
                                representative, who shall receive them in such number and in such
                                suitable ports of the surrendering nation as the latter shall notify
                                in advance to the commissioner of the receiving nation.</p>
                            <pb facs="0947" n="827" xml:id="pg_827"/>
                            <p>The Governments of Russia and Japan shall present to each other, as
                                soon as possible after the delivery of the prisoners has been
                                completed, a verified account of the direct expenditures made by
                                them respectively for the care and maintenance of the prisoners from
                                the date of capture or surrender until the date of their death or
                                return. Russia agrees to refund to Japan, as soon as possible after
                                the exchange of these accounts, as above stipulated, the difference
                                between the actual amount thus spent by Japan and the actual amount
                                likewise expended by Russia.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article XIV</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The present treaty shall be ratified by Their Majesties the Emperor
                                of all the Russias and the Emperor of Japan. This ratification
                                shall, within the shortest possible time and at all events not later
                                than fifty days from the date of the signature of the treaty, be
                                notified to the Imperial Governments of Russia and Japan,
                                respectively, through the ambassador of the United States of America
                                at St. Petersburg and the minister of France at Tokyo, and from and
                                after the date of the last of these notifications this treaty shall
                                enter into full force in all its parts.</p>
                            <p>The formal exchange of the ratifications shall take place at
                                Washington as soon as possible.</p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article XV</hi>.</p>
                            <p>The present treaty shall be signed in duplicate, in the French and
                                English languages. The two texts are absolutely alike; however, in
                                case of difference of interpretation the French text shall
                                prevail.</p>
                            <p>In witness whereof the respective plenipotentiaries have signed the
                                present treaty of peace and affixed thereto their seals.</p>
                            <p>Done at Portsmouth, New Hampshire, the twenty-third day of August
                                (fifth of September) of the year one thousand nine hundred and five,
                                corresponding to the fifth day of the ninth month of the
                                thirty-eighth year of Meiji.</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Iutaro Komura</hi>. [<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>]</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">K. Takahira</hi>. [<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>]</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sergius Witte</hi>. [<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>]</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rosen</hi>. [<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>]</p>
                            <p>In conformity with the provisions of Articles II and IX of the treaty
                                of peace between Russia and Japan under this date, the undersigned
                                plenipotentiaries have concluded the following additional
                                articles:</p>
                            <p>I. To Article III:</p>
                            <p>The Imperial Governments of Russia and Japan mutually agree to begin
                                the withdrawal of their military forces from the territory of
                                Manchuria simultaneously and immediately after the entrance into
                                force of the treaty of peace; and within a period of eighteen months
                                from this date the armies of the two powers shall be entirely
                                withdrawn from Manchuria, with the exception of the leased territory
                                of the peninsula of Liao-tung.</p>
                            <p>The forces of the two powers occupying advanced positions shall be
                                withdrawn first.</p>
                            <p>The high contracting parties reserve the right to maintain guards for
                                the protection of their respective railroad lines in Manchuria.</p>
                            <p>The number of these guards shall not exceed 15 men per kilometer, and
                                within the limit of this maximum number the commanders of the
                                Russian and Japanese armies shall, by mutual agreement, fix the
                                number of guards who are to be employed, this number being as low as
                                possible and in accordance with actual requirements. The commanders
                                of the Russian and Japanese forces in Manchuria shall reach an
                                understanding regarding all the details connected with the
                                evacuation, in conformity with the principles herein above set
                                forth, and shall, by mutual agreement, adopt the measures necessary
                                to carry out the evacuation as soon as possible and at all events
                                within a period not exceeding eighteen months.</p>
                            <p>II. To Article IX:</p>
                            <p>As soon as possible after the present treaty takes effect, a boundary
                                commission composed of an equal number of members appointed
                                respectively by the two high contracting parties shall mark on the
                                spot and in a permanent manner the exact line between the Russian
                                and Japanese possessions on the island of Saghalin. The commission
                                shall be obliged, as far as topographical conditions permit, to
                                follow the 50th parallel of north latitude for the line of
                                demarcation, and in case any deviations from this line are found
                                necessary at certain points compensation shall be made therefor by
                                making corresponding deviations at other points. It shall also be
                                the duty of said commission to prepare a list and description of the
                                adjacent islands which are comprised within the cession, and finally
                                the commission shall prepare and sign maps showing the boundaries of
                                the ceded territory. The labors of the commission shall be submitted
                                to the approval of the high contracting parties.</p>
                            <p>The additional articles mentioned hereinabove shall be considered as
                                being ratified by the ratification of the treaty of peace, to which
                                they are annexed.</p>
                            <pb facs="0948" n="828" xml:id="pg_828"/>
                            <p>Portsmouth, August 23 (September 5), 1905, corresponding to the 5th
                                day, 9th month, and 28th year of Meiji.</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Iutaro Komura</hi>.</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">K. Takahira</hi>.</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sergius Witte</hi>.</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rosen</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Therefore, after mature consideration of this treaty and the two
                                additional articles, we approved, confirmed, and ratified them, and
                                do hereby approve, confirm, and ratify them in their full purport,
                                pledging our imperial word, for ourselves, our successors, and our
                                heirs, that everything set forth in the above-mentioned acts shall
                                be inviolably observed. In witness whereof we, having signed this,
                                our imperial ratification, with our own hand, have ordered affixed
                                thereto our imperial seal.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Given at
                                        <placeName>Peterhoff</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-10-01">the first day of October, in the year of
                                        our Lord one thousand nine hundred and five and of our reign
                                        the eleventh</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/> On the original is written in His Imperial Majesty’s own
                                    hand:<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>. <signed>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Nicholas</hi>.”</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>countersigned:<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">Count
                                        Lamsdorff</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretary of State,
                                        Minister of Foreign Affairs.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>