<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Russian Ambassador.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1905</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">918</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1905-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1905-10-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1905-10-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1905-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="918"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d918">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Russian Ambassador</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-10-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 12, 1905</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Ambassador</hi>: Responding to the wish expressed
                    in your personal note of the 5th instant, I have the pleasure to send you
                    herewith a memorandum communicating the reply of the President to the message of
                    His Imperial Majesty the Tsar, which you delivered to the President on the 13th
                    ultimo, relative to the convocation of a Second International Peace Conference
                    at The Hague.</p>
                <p>I have taken note of the preliminary inquiry addressed to all the other
                    governments looking to their acquiescence in the calling of such a conference by
                    the formal invitation of His Majesty.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Elihu Root.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">memorandum.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1905-10-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">October 12, 1905</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>On the 13th of last month, at Sagamore Hill, his excellency the ambassador of
                        Russia presented to the President a memorandum, being a message from His
                        Majesty the Tsar to <pb facs="0950" n="830" xml:id="pg_830"/> the President,
                        to the effect that in view of the termination, with the cordial cooperation
                        of the President, of the war, and of the conclusion of peace between Russia
                        and Japan, His Imperial Majesty, as initiator of the International Peace
                        Conference of 1899, deems the present a favorable moment for further
                        developing and systematizing the labors of that conference, and that to this
                        end, upon being assured in advance of the sympathy of the President, who
                        last year pronounced himself in favor of such a project, His Majesty desires
                        to approach the President with a proposal to the effect that the Government
                        of the United States take part in a new international conference, which
                        could be called together at The Hague as soon as favorable replies may be
                        obtained from all the other states to which a similar proposal is to be
                        made.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary of State, by direction of the President, has the honor to
                        confirm to his excellency the ambassador of Russia the assurances which the
                        President had the sincere pleasure to give to his excellency at the time of
                        the presentation of the memorandum of September 13. The President’s
                        circulars to the powers, partiesto the acts of The Hague Conference, which
                        the late Secretary of State communicated to the several signatory states
                        through the American envoys accredited thereto, dated, respectively, October
                        21 and December 16 of last year, have demonstrated the President’s keen
                        desire that upon a favorable occasion the labors of the First International
                        Peace Conference might be supplemented and completed by an accord to be
                        reached by a second conference of the powers. The suggestion so put forth
                        having been accepted in principle by the signatories, it only remained for
                        the opportune moment to come for the powers to agree upon the place and time
                        for their renewed assemblage in order to perfect the beneficial agreements
                        of the first conference.</p>
                    <p>The President most gladly welcomes the offer of His Imperial Majesty to again
                        take upon himself the initiation of the steps requisite to convene a Second
                        International Peace Conference, as the necessary sequence to the first
                        conference, brought about through His Majesty’s efforts, and in view of the
                        cordial responses to the President’s suggestion of October, 1904, he doubts
                        not that the project will meet with complete acceptation and that the result
                        will be to bring the nations of the earth still more closely together in
                        their common endeavor to advance the ends of peace.</p>
                    <p>As respects the further statement of his excellency’s memorandum of September
                        13, that, as the late war has given rise to a number of questions which are
                        of the greatest importance and closely related to the acts of the first
                        conference, the plenipotentiaries of Russia, at the future meeting, will lay
                        before the conference a detailed programme which could serve as a starting
                        point for its deliberations, the President finds it in consonance with the
                        indications of his circular of October 21, 1904, touching the questions to
                        come before a second conference for discussion, and the importance of
                        completing the work of the first conference by ample exchange of views and,
                        it is to be hoped, full concord upon the broad questions specifically
                        relegated by the final act of The Hague to the consideration of a future
                        conference.</p>
                    <p rend="center">[Continued in <ref target="frus1906p1">Foreign Relations,
                            1906</ref>.]</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
