<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-09-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-09-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="113" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d113">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Council of Foreign Ministers Files: Lot M–88:
                        CFM London Documents</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Proposals by the Australian Minister for External
                            Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Evatt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Council of Foreign Ministers</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">C.F.M.(45) 32</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-09-20">20 September,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Italian Peace Treaty</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">city and port of trieste</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The following are the proposals, in the form of draft headings for inclusion
                        in the treaty of peace with Italy, concerning the disposition of the City
                        and Port of Trieste, which were referred to by Dr. H. V. Evatt in his
                        statement to the tenth meeting of the Council,<note n="*" xml:id="d113fn14">C.F.M.(P) (45) 10th Meeting, Minute 1. [Footnote in the
                            original.]</note> held on 18th September, 1945:— <pb facs="0297" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Italy to renounce in favour of the United Nations her Sovereignty
                                over the City and Port of Trieste and immediately adjoining
                                territory.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>Trieste to be neutralised and demilitarised.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>Trieste to be made administratively independent according to a
                                constitution which will accord a substantially equal share in the
                                local administration to Italian and Yugoslav residents, the
                                constitution to be drawn up by or on behalf of the United Nations
                                after consultation with representatives of Italian and Yugoslavian
                                interests.</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>A convention to be drawn up between Italy and Yugoslavia, Central
                                European Countries and the autonomous City of Trieste, providing for
                                the institution of a free port at Trieste and the facilitation of
                                rail and other communications to and from Trieste for the purpose of
                                international trading. Such convention to be embodied in the
                                treaties of Peace.</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>The constitution of the independent City to be placed under the
                                guarantee of the United Nations which will provide appropriate means
                                of general supervision or specific control over the local
                                administration and of associating the representatives of other
                                countries with such administration.</item>
                            <label>(6)</label>
                            <item>The full protection of civil and religious liberties shall be
                                guaranteed in the convention and made enforceable in the Courts of
                                Justice.</item>
                            <label>(7)</label>
                            <item>Arrangements regarding retention or change of residence or
                                nationality and the right of disposal or retention of
                                property.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>