<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-21T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-21T11:00:00-05:00" n="245" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d245">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/12–1545: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-21T11:00:00-05:00">December 21,
                                1945—11 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>2604. Secdel 30. For the Secretary. The President discussed with me this
                        morning Whaley Eaton <hi rend="italic">Foreign Letter</hi> and <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> stories concerning reported
                        disagreement between you and Senators from the Foreign Relations and Atomic
                        Energy Committees (Deptel 2585, December 20, Secdel 24<note n="80" xml:id="d245fn80">Not printed; it transmitted the texts of a story in
                            the Whaley–Eaton news service of December 18 and a story by James Reston
                            in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> for December 20 (740.00119
                            Council/12–1545).</note>). The President was most anxious that these
                        reports and my telegram concerning his meeting with Senators December 14
                        (Deptel 2531, December 15, Secdel 10) should not alarm you. He asked me to
                        make clear that he was not disturbed by these incidents and that the reports
                        were being sent to you merely for your information and so that you would not
                        be confused by any accounts of these matters you might receive indirectly.
                        He approves of the proposal set forth in your tel 4196, December 17, Delsec
                            10.<note n="81" xml:id="d245fn81">Not printed (740.00119
                            Council/12–1745); it transmitted the text of the United States proposals
                            on atomic energy presented to the Conference and included as enclosure 3
                            to the United States delegation minutes of the Third Formal Session,
                            December 18, 4 p.m., <ref target="#pg_663">p. 663</ref>.</note> He
                        suggests (but only if you think it would be helpful in promoting cooperation
                        and useful discussion) that you also say to the Soviet <pb facs="0722" n="710" xml:id="pg_710"/> Government at some appropriate time that
                        United States Government does not purport to have solution to the very
                        troublesome questions involved in the atomic energy problem, but is eager
                        and willing to work with the Soviet Union and other nations toward the
                        establishment as rapidly as possible of mutually acceptable arrangements for
                        full collaboration in respect to the problem and that to this end the United
                        States will be glad to consider such proposals as the Soviet Government may
                        wish to make in respect to any phase of the problem and to discuss them with
                        the Soviet Government both in the United Nations Commission and
                        separately.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>