<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Winant
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d288</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">288</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-05T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-05T18:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-05T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-05T18:00:00-05:00" n="288" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d288">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112A EW/10–145: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-05T18:00:00-05:00">October 5, 1945—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>8833. Urtel 10198 Oct l.<note n="54" xml:id="d288fn54">Not printed.</note> PL
                    Committee has been giving careful consideration to various plans re future of
                    List, particularly that suggested to Brit in letter reported your 10197 Oct.
                        1.<note n="55" xml:id="d288fn55">Not printed. This proposal was that the
                        date of complete withdrawal of the lists might be advanced to February 1946.
                        In that case Washington wished “to consider the advantages of omitting
                        intermediate bulk deletions and maintaining the lists at approximately their
                        present size up to such earlier date of complete elimination.” (740.00112A
                        EW/10–145)</note> Committee was disturbed by Brit reply since it in effect
                    rejected possible US counterproposal prior to receipt. In view of Brit position,
                    we are willing to adhere to present formula, namely, reduction of List to hard
                    core in Nov and withdrawal of Lists in May 1946. It is necessary however that
                    Brit agree in return that procedure for determining hard core be acceptance of
                    results of working parties. This means acceptance, on Western Hemisphere side,
                    of names presently approved by working party for hard core plus such additions
                    as may be made by working party in future. It appears to us that only in this
                    way can implementation on a fair and expeditious basis be made of program for
                    hard core reduction in Nov and elimination in May. Otherwise, reexamination of
                    entire program would be necessary.</p>
                <p>It should be pointed out that we will use same procedure re working party on
                    Eastern Hemisphere. Dept and other agencies concerned with PL are accepting hard
                    core for Eastern Hemisphere which has been worked out in London and we are
                    neither making nor intend to make independent review. We feel Brit should do
                    same with regard to Western Hemisphere, Gravity of situation in WH is
                    demonstrated by chart being forwarded to you by air mail. Statistical analysis
                    indicates sharp disagreement between Brit in London and recommendations of
                    missions and working party.</p>
                <p>You are requested to address MEWFO immediately on this subject. You should make
                    it clear that this Govt’s reaffirmation of adherence to original formula is
                    conditioned upon Brit acceptance of working party list for Western
                        Hemisphere.<note n="56" xml:id="d288fn56">Summary of this telegram
                        transmitted in circular telegram of October 11, 1945, noon, to the
                        Diplomatic Officers at Paris, Brussels, Moscow, Madrid, Lisbon, Bern, Cairo,
                        Caserta, Ankara, Stockholm, Berlin, Belgrade, Bucharest, Helsinki, Warsaw,
                        Copenhagen, Oslo, Sofia, and Athens.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In order to assure you first opportunity of informing Brit, Dept will not advise
                    Brit Emb here of this proposal until Oct 9.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
