<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="303" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d303">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">800.515/5–945</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 5543</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-09">May 9,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received May 30.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Department’s
                        telegram 802, May 3, 1945, 6 PM,<note n="71" xml:id="d303fn71">Not
                            printed.</note> to the Legation, repeated to London, number unknown,
                        approving certain changes in the text of the provision to be incorporated in
                        the so-called “Tripartite Interim Trade Agreement” and the “Tripartite Post
                        Hostilities Supply Agreement”, and to transmit herewith five copies of the
                        final draft of Annex A to this agreement as informally presented to the
                        Swedish Government.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Herschel</hi> V. <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Draft Provision for Inclusion in Tripartite Trade
                                Agreement</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>It is agreed that the following provision shall be incorporated in the
                            so-called “Tripartite Interim Trade Agreement” and the “Tripartite Post
                            Hostilities Supply Agreement”:</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“The Government of Sweden as an integral part of this agreement
                                agrees to adhere to the terms and spirit of Bretton Woods Resolution
                                VI, the United Nations’ declaration of January 5, 1943, and the gold
                                declaration of February 22, 1944. The Government of Sweden agrees
                                further to implement this undertaking by continuing in force such
                                measures as have already been instituted by it for this purpose and
                                to institute and maintain the additional measures set forth in Annex
                                A to this agreement and made a part hereof, and to give favorable
                                consideration to such other measures as may in the future be
                                necessary for the full execution of this undertaking.”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p rend="center">ANNEX A</p>
                        <p>The Government of Sweden, pursuant to its undertaking as set forth in
                            paragraph . . . . . of the Anglo-American-Swedish Trade Agreement (the
                            Tripartite Post Hostilities Supply Agreement), undertakes to assist
                            fully the United Nations in carrying out the spirit and purposes of
                            Resolution VI of the Bretton Woods Conference and in all other ways
                            within its power to prevent the use by Axis interests of the laws,
                            territory, and institutions of Sweden for Axis purposes during the
                            present war and thereafter. For the purpose of accomplishing this
                            objective the Government of Sweden agrees to put into force without
                            delay the following measures and to give favorable consideration to
                            instituting such other measures as may in the light of experience and
                            changing conditions be necessary to the execution and effectiveness of
                            this undertaking. For their part the United <pb facs="0894" n="882" xml:id="pg_882"/> States and the United Kingdom recognize that the
                            Government of Sweden has already instituted certain measures directed at
                            the implementation of certain of the provisions set forth below. The
                            term Axis as used throughout this agreement includes Germany, including
                            Bohemia and Moravia, and Japan.</p>
                        <p>1. The Government of Sweden agrees formally to make known its decision to
                            adhere fully to the terms and spirit of Bretton Woods Resolution VI, the
                            United Nations’ declaration of January 5, 1943, and the gold declaration
                            of February 22, 1944, all attached hereto and made a part of this
                            agreement.</p>
                        <p>2. The Government of Sweden agrees to freeze immediately all assets
                            referred to in items 3 and 4 below, and other such assets as may be
                            subsequently uncovered by the Government of Sweden or brought to its
                            attention by the United States and United Kingdom. It shall be deemed
                            sufficient for the Government of Sweden to freeze any Axis interest in
                            an asset, as such interest is referred to in paragraph 4 below, rather
                            than the asset itself, provided that such interest is so limited as not
                            to make necessary the freezing of the asset in order to freeze
                            effectively such interest in the asset, and provided further that such
                            action is first agreed to by the governments concerned.</p>
                        <p>The principles on which the licensing of transactions involving the
                            assignment, transfer, withdrawal, payment, hypothecation, or other
                            disposition of such assets may be made, shall be a matter for
                            arrangement between the governments concerned. It is further agreed that
                            full information on all licenses issued shall be made available to the
                            United States and United Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>3. In order to execute fully its undertaking the Government of Sweden
                            agrees further to immobilize and to dispose of any looted assets as such
                            assets are described in Bretton Woods Resolution VI, regardless of
                            present ownership of such assets, in accordance with the terms and
                            spirit of Bretton Woods Resolution VI.</p>
                        <p>4. The Government of Sweden agrees further to conduct a detailed census
                            of all assets regardless of form located in Sweden or held abroad
                            through persons or firms in Sweden which, or any interest in which,
                            direct or indirect, is owned or controlled or held by, in behalf of, or
                            in the name of, persons and firms who are nationals or residents of or
                            domiciled in Axis countries. The census shall be constructed to include
                            full information about such aforesaid ownership, control, interest or
                            holding where such ownership, control, interest or holding has not been
                            lost as the result of, or has been obtained through, any transaction
                            involving the transfer of assets to Sweden or a change in assets located
                            in, or managed from, Sweden, where the transaction has occurred since
                            January 1, 1939, between Swedish subjects or persons subject to Swedish
                            law or persons acting on the behalf of such <pb facs="0895" n="883" xml:id="pg_883"/> persons, on the one hand, and persons or subjects
                            of Axis countries, or persons, wherever situated, acting on their
                            behalf, on the other hand, including cases where the assets were
                            transferred without the payment of adequate or appropriate
                            compensation.</p>
                        <p>The term assets as used in this agreement shall include but not by way of
                            limitation any real property or interest therein, enterprise
                            (commercial, industrial, financial or scientific), security, interest,
                            patent rights, corporate and contractual rights including management
                            contracts, patents, licenses and arrangements, trademarks, insurance
                            policies and reinsurance contracts, money, checks, drafts and all other
                            negotiable and non-negotiable instruments, bank accounts and deposits,
                            including trusteeship accounts and safe deposit boxes and vaults and
                            their contents, gold and other precious metals and stones, personal
                            property, options and any other types of arrangements or undertakings
                            written or unwritten. The Government of Sweden agrees further to make
                            available to the United States and United Kingdom the information
                            obtained from the census, and in accordance with existing practice to
                            permit Swedish nationals or persons subject to its jurisdiction to make
                            available any information directed to the purposes of this undertaking
                            to the United States or the United Kingdom, either directly or through
                            the Government of Sweden.</p>
                        <p>The Government of Sweden agrees further to conduct a similar census on
                            all assets located in Sweden or held abroad through persons or firms in
                            Sweden which, or any interest in which, direct or indirect, is owned or
                            controlled or held by, in behalf of, or in the name of, persons and
                            firms who are nationals or residents of or domiciled in Axis satellite
                            countries, such census to be taken only at such time as the Governments
                            of the United States and United Kingdom may request with respect to all
                            or any one of such countries. Similarly, at the time of such request the
                            Government of Sweden agrees to make available all information concerning
                            such census to the United States and United Kingdom and further that the
                            provisions of section 2 above shall be made applicable to the
                            investigation and freezing of such Axis satellites’ assets. The term
                            “Axis satellites” shall for the purposes of this provision include
                            Bulgaria, Rumania and Hungary and shall also include Austria as
                            constituted prior to March 15, 1938, and Italy.</p>
                        <p>5. The Government of Sweden will provide the United States and the United
                            Kingdom with full information concerning all persons in Sweden who
                            possess the nationality of Axis countries and of those formerly of Axis
                            nationality who have entered into Sweden since January 1, 1939, and who
                            are presently in Sweden, where the evidence reveals that such persons
                            may themselves be hiding, or may be assisting <pb facs="0896" n="884" xml:id="pg_884"/> in or may be parties to or may have knowledge of
                            the hiding of, assets owned or controlled by, or in which an interest is
                            held by, Axis countries, or persons located in such countries or persons
                            acting on their behalf. Such information shall include details as to
                            their residence, occupation, travels from Sweden made since initial
                            entry into Sweden and such other information as will be relevant to the
                            purpose for which such information is desired. The Government of Sweden
                            also agrees to submit similar information on all other persons who have
                            come to Sweden since January 1, 1939, where the evidence reveals that
                            such persons may themselves be hiding, or may be assisting in or may be
                            parties to or may have knowledge of the hiding of, assets owned or
                            controlled by, or in which an interest is held by, Axis countries, or
                            persons located in such countries or persons acting on their behalf. The
                            Government of Sweden agrees further to submit similar information to the
                            United States and the United Kingdom on all persons who during the
                            remaining period of hostilities may enter Sweden from Axis countries and
                            such other persons as may be referred to the Government of Sweden by the
                            United States and United Kingdom, for the purpose of determining whether
                            such persons are themselves hiding, or assisting in or are parties to or
                            have knowledge of the hiding of, assets owned or controlled by, or in
                            which an interest is held by, Axis countries or persons located in such
                            countries, or persons acting on their behalf.</p>
                        <p>6. The Government of Sweden will establish effective controls with
                            respect to any transaction with the Axis or Axis controlled countries,
                            or the nationals of such countries in order to prevent entry into Sweden
                            from such countries of any assets or the removal from Sweden to such
                            countries of any assets. The principles on which transactions may be
                            licensed shall be a matter of arrangement between the governments
                            concerned. It is further agreed that full information on all licenses
                            issued shall be made available to the United States and the United
                            Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>7. The Government of Sweden after the foregoing measures have been put
                            into effect agrees to investigate all suspicious cases including but not
                            limited to cases referred to it as being in such category by the United
                            States or United Kingdom and to report the results of all such
                            investigations to the United States and the United Kingdom. The
                            Government of Sweden further agrees to prosecute vigorously violations
                            of the measures referred to in this agreement and to take such other
                            steps as are necessary to obtain rigid enforcement of such measures.</p>
                        <p>8. In order to facilitate the execution of this agreement the Government
                            of Sweden agrees that the facilities of the Joint Standing
                                Committees<note n="72" xml:id="d303fn72">These bodies, consisting of
                                United States, United Kingdom, and Swedish representatives, were
                                established to assure the Allied Governments that Swedish policy was
                                in accordance with various wartime trade agreements.</note>
                            <pb facs="0897" n="885" xml:id="pg_885"/> in Stockholm, London and
                            Washington, or sub-committees thereof shall be made available for
                            handling of questions related to this agreement or to the execution of
                            the terms of this agreement.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>