<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Minister in Denmark (
                        Davis
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d328</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">328</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-12-17T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-17T09:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="finance" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885" lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-17T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-17T09:00:00-05:00" n="328" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d328">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.515/12–1745: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Denmark</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-17T15:00:00+01:00">December 17, 1945—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 6:04 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>693. To Dept and Treasury as 693 from Legation and Feig.<note n="61" xml:id="d328fn61">Bernard Feig, member of the United States Treasury
                        Department delegation in the United Kingdom, temporarily assigned to
                        Denmark.</note> Meeting held on December 15 with Danish Ministers for
                    Foreign Affairs, Finance and Commerce<note n="62" xml:id="d328fn62">Gustav
                        Rasmussen, Thorkil Kristensen, Jens Villemoes, respectively.</note> at which
                    my British colleague<note n="63" xml:id="d328fn63">Alec Walter George
                        Randall.</note> and I requested effective <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi> program in Denmark. We referred specifically to failure thus
                    far of Danish Govt in implementing satisfactorily existing <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi> legislation and strongly stressed need for immediate and
                    vigorous action.</p>
                <p>We took approach that we felt certain that Danish Govt agrees in principle and
                    that we are ready to lend all possible assistance and give full cooperation
                    toward this end.</p>
                <p>As indication of our desire to cooperate we submitted an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> containing <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi> outline of
                    broad <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi> objectives, suggested measures
                    necessary and important to an effective <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi>
                    program, suggestion for an Anglo-American-Danish working party, and specific
                    case summaries involving some leading enemy firms against which action appeared
                    inadequate. Copy of <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> will be transmitted by
                        despatch.<note n="64" xml:id="d328fn64">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Feig explained in some detail the implications, operation and other technical
                    aspects of an effective <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi> program and pointed
                    out some of shortcomings of present Danish program.</p>
                <p>I stressed importance of quick, effective action with respect to <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi> program because of its influence on other
                    important matters such as defrosting.</p>
                <p>Minister of Foreign Affairs expressed appreciation for proffered assistance and
                    stated his agreement in principle. He said he was prepared to take steps
                    immediately to expedite <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi> program and that he
                    welcomed suggestion for a tripartite working party. Such a working party was
                    formed on the spot and first meeting arranged for December 18. Feig is to act as
                    technical advisor to working party.</p>
                <p>My reaction to meeting is (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Danes now fully appreciate
                    that US and British Govts are seriously interested in <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi> problem (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) leading Govt ministers
                    and other officials appear disposed to carry out an effective <hi rend="smallcaps">Safehaven</hi> rapidly in implementation of such a program
                        (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the working party will provide an effective
                    medium through which <pb facs="0935" n="923" xml:id="pg_923"/> to expedite
                    implementation particularly if Legation can retain services of Feig to guide
                    working party.</p>
                <p>From Danish Govt official we learned informally that Danes have under
                    consideration an enemy property sequestration measure.</p>
                <p>Legation and Feig feel that we should await some more definitive and positive
                    results of meeting before proceeding to conclusion of defrosting agreement.</p>
                <p>Repeated London for Embassy and Taylor as 188.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
