<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the United States Political Adviser for Germany (
                        Murphy
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d343</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">343</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-09-11T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-09-11T19:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-09-11T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-09-11T19:00:00-05:00" n="343" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d343">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.515/9–1045: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-09-11T20:00:00-04:00">September 11, 1945—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>446. Reurtel 484; Sep 10.<note n="44" xml:id="d343fn44">Not printed; it requested
                        the text of the announcement to be made regarding the transfer of art to the
                        United States (800.515/9–1945).</note> Text of announcement of removal of
                    German art as revised and approved by Dept is as follows:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The US Govt is removing from Germany to Continental US certain art objects
                        not readily identifiable as looted property with the sole intention of
                        keeping such treasures safe and in trust for the people of Germany or the
                        other rightful owners. The US Govt will retain these objects of art in its
                        possession only as long as will be necessary to insure their physical safety
                        or until such time as it may be possible to determine the rightful
                        owners.</p>
                    <p>When the appropriate Allied bodies determine the rightful owners or the
                        return of conditions in Germany whereby the safety of these <pb facs="0961" n="949" xml:id="pg_949"/> objects can be definitely assured, they will
                        be distributed according to the directives of such Allied groups.”<note n="45" xml:id="d343fn45">In telegram 532, September 15, 1945, 6 p. ,m.,
                            from Berlin, Mr. Murphy notified the Secretary of State that the United
                            States Group Control Council planned to make an announcement concerning
                            the removal of art to the United States on September 17. The
                            announcement would employ the wording transmitted by the Department with
                            the additional paragraph: “The return of readily identifiable art
                            objects to the liberated countries is already underway.”
                            (800.515/9–1545)</note>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <p>It is expected that more detailed announcement will have to be made in Washington
                    in the near future to counter rumors and anticipated criticism concerning
                    action. Dept will advise you in advance regarding date of such announcement in
                    order to synchronize it with announcement in Germany.<note n="46" xml:id="d343fn46">For the press release from the White House, dated
                        September 26, concerning the transfer, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, September 30, 1945, p. 499.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
