<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Chairman of the House Appropriations Committee (
                        Cannon
                    )A letter of substantially the same
                        purport was sent on November 7, 1945, to Senator Kenneth McKellar, President
                        Pro Tempore of the Senate.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d416</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">416</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recy94pCDcRAr4voG" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="freedom-of-expression" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003012251" lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of speech</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="416" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d416">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50 UNRRA/10–3145</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chairman of the House Appropriations Committee</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cannon</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="18" xml:id="d416fn18">A letter of substantially the same
                        purport was sent on November 7, 1945, to Senator Kenneth McKellar, President
                        Pro Tempore of the Senate.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-31">October 31,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Cannon</hi>: In my letter to you of October 22,
                        1945,<note n="19" xml:id="d416fn19">Reference here is presumably to a letter
                        of October 22, 1945, from the Assistant Secretary of State (Clayton) to Mr.
                        Cannon, not printed.</note> I expressed the view that it would be
                    unfortunate to include new and restrictive conditions in the pending UNRRA
                    appropriation legislation. In this connection I would like to refer to one of
                    the conditions which has been proposed in various forms relating to the freedom
                    of properly accredited representatives of the press of the United Nations to
                    enter areas receiving UNRRA assistance. I have already indicated to you that I
                    did not believe this proposal, in any of its forms, should be accepted.</p>
                <p>I want, particularly, to explain my views on this matter. The reason for my
                    belief, as I am sure you know, has nothing to do with the intrinsic merit of the
                    suggestion: I am thoroughly in favor of that.</p>
                <p>I do not believe, however, that the bill appropriating the remaining funds
                    already authorized for our participation in UNRRA is the appropriate device
                    through which to seek the result we all desire.</p>
                <p>It would be fortunate indeed if we could provide succor under ideal conditions of
                    all kinds, but hunger and cold and tragedy will not wait upon perfection. We
                    cannot put ourselves in the position of denying promised relief to millions of
                    human beings because we have failed to secure our other objectives in
                    advance.</p>
                <p>It is my firm hope that all people may soon enjoy complete access to the news as
                    well as freedom of speech and of belief and of assembly, but I fear that the
                    attachment of conditions in our appropriation bill may hurt rather than help us
                    in our efforts to achieve these ends.</p>
                <p>To carry on our foreign relations we have regular mechanisms of international
                    intercourse. We are using these with vigor to implement our foreign policy. We
                    have already met with a considerable degree of success in providing our
                    correspondents access to the news, and I am convinced that the course we are
                    following is the correct one. We must seek our ends by negotiation and
                    agreement, not by ultimatum.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
