<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Colonel C. Tyler Wood, Special Assistant
                        to the Assistant Secretary of State (
                        Clayton
                    ), to the Director of the United Nations Belief and
                        Rehabilitation Administration (
                        Lehman
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d424</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">424</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-01T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="424" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d424">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50 UNRRA/12–445</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName>C. Tyler Wood</persName>, Special Assistant
                        to the Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clayton</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the United Nations Belief and
                        Rehabilitation Administration</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lehman</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-01">December 1,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Governor Lehman</hi>: As you know, supplies for
                    Italy from the United States are presently being procured through the use of the
                    Italian dollar account and through a joint FEA-Army account which was approved
                    by Congress. The Italian dollar account will be fully obligated by December 31,
                    1945, but, because of the nature of the goods programmed, deliveries will extend
                    through the early months of 1946. The FEA-Army account, used for the procurement
                    of basic subsistence supplies, will be sufficient only to provide such supplies
                    for loadings through the month of December.</p>
                <p>By December 10, 1945, arrangements must be made and commitments must be entered
                    into for procurement of coal, petroleum, food and shipping services in order to
                    have goods go forward to Italy during the month of January. Similarly additional
                    commitments must be made by January 10, 1946, in order to have supplies go
                    forward during the month of February 1946.</p>
                <p>On November 14 you informed the Central Committee of UNRRA that UNRRA would be
                    willing to provide approximately $60,000,000 necessary for the procurement of
                    supplies for Italy for the month of January 1946, contingent upon Congressional
                    approval of the $550,000,000 appropriation. If the $550,000,000 appropriation
                    now before Congress is approved before December 10,<note n="41" xml:id="d424fn41">For information concerning Congressional action on this
                        appropriation see circular telegram, December 15, <ref target="#pg_1055">p.
                            1055</ref>.</note> I assume therefore that you will make available out
                    of such appropriation the funds necessary for procurement and shipment in
                    January to Italy of supplies in an amount believed to be approximately
                    $60,000,000. While <pb facs="1057" n="1045" xml:id="pg_1045"/> it is realized
                    that UNRRA always retains the power of diversion to other destinations, you will
                    recognize that there would be no other funds or supplies available under this
                    arrangement for procurement for Italy for this month should such diversion take
                    place.</p>
                <p>If UNRRA undertakes this commitment a similar problem will arise by January 10 in
                    connection with February shipments for Italy. At this time it is of importance
                    to us to have some understanding as to your intentions with regard to the
                    February shipments. Could you inform us that you will allocate to Italy a
                    proportionate share of any supplies available for February shipment, provided
                    that by January 10 the progress of the proposed legislation for the
                    authorization of an additional $1,350,000,000 from the United States appears
                    reasonably satisfactory to you?<note n="42" xml:id="d424fn42">For information
                        concerning Congressional action on additional funds, see telegram 2458,
                        December 29, to Rome, <ref target="#pg_1057">p. 1057</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>While it is exceedingly difficult for you at this time to make positive
                    commitments until funds have been appropriated, nevertheless you will realize
                    that we need the information requested above in order to present to responsible
                    American authorities the grave situation which would exist in Italy should UNRRA
                    be unable to give the Department the requested assurances or should the
                    appropriation be unduly delayed or not approved.</p>
                <p>I think it important to point out that it is not our view that Italy should be
                    treated preferentially with respect to other countries receiving UNRRA’s
                    assistance. However, because there has been in existence a supply program for
                    Italy separate from UNRRA and hi support of a military occupation, it is
                    necessary for us to see to the establishment of an orderly transition from one
                    program to the other and to provide against a break in the pipeline of
                    supplies.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Tyler Wood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
