<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-04T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-04T17:00:00-05:00" n="463" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d463">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50/4–445: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>)<note n="48" xml:id="d463fn48">Repeated on
                            the same date to London as No. 2614, for the Mission to the Norwegian
                            Government as No. 10, and for the Mission to the Netherlands Government
                            as No. 18; to Brussels as No. 256; to Caserta for the American Political
                            Adviser as No. 301; to the Mission to the Yugoslav Government as No. 39;
                            to Luxembourg as No. 9; and to Athens as No. 295.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-04T18:00:00-04:00">April 4,
                                1945—6 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1339. Department has today addressed notes<note n="49" xml:id="d463fn49">None
                            printed.</note> to missions in Washington of French, Belgian,
                        Netherlands, Luxembourg, Norwegian, Greek, and Yugoslav Governments
                        informing them that payment will be expected for civilian supplies delivered
                        to them during the period of military responsibility and that bills for such
                        supplies will be rendered to them by the combined military authorities.
                        Details as to desired payment arrangements will be communicated at the time
                        of the first billing (which is expected to be in the relatively near
                        future). Text of note will be sent you by mail. Department understands
                        British and Canadian Governments are addressing similar notes today to these
                        Governments through their missions accredited to the Governments.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Additional paragraph to be included in telegrams to Athens
                            and London.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In the case of Greece and Yugoslavia, the missions were informed orally that
                        we recognize the difficulties of their financial position will not permit
                        them to make current payment for the supplies and that the <pb facs="1097" n="1085" xml:id="pg_1085"/> purpose of the note is primarily to record
                        the fact of their indebtedness. For your information, we desire that the
                        onus of stating the inability of these Governments to make payment should
                        rest upon them.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>