<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Winant
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d482</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">482</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-01T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="482" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d482">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50/12–145: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-01">December 1,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received December 1—8:25 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>12592. Sal 26.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Following paper will be reported to EECE on 13 December by Subcommittee on
                        Enemy Exports and is transmitted to you for your advance information.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <item>(I) At the 12th meeting of the Emergency Economic Committee for
                                Europe held on 1st November representatives of a number of member
                                countries expressed their anxiety about the difficulties in trading
                                with Germany under the existing financial arrangements. The various
                                problems raised were referred to the Enemy Exports Subcommittee for
                                further discussion. The Subcommittee, after discussion, has prepared
                                the following statement in an attempt to set forth concisely the
                                present German trade situation and the financial regulations issued
                                to meet it.</item>
                            <item>(II) The effect on the E.E.C.E. countries. It is difficult to
                                forecast with any certainty the pattern of German trade over the
                                next few years. However, it now appears probable that for the year
                                1946 there will be not only a deficit on the current trading account
                                (more imports will be required than can be paid for by exports) but
                                also a “dollar” deficit. Even if all exports from Germany were paid
                                for in full in dollars there would still be insufficient dollars to
                                pay for the essential imports required from the dollar area. In
                                order to prevent Germany from becoming a financial liability to the
                                countries responsible for the control of Germany, it was stated in
                                the Potsdam Declaration that “In working out the economic balance of
                                Germany the necessary means must be provided to pay for imports
                                approved by the Control Council in Germany. The proceeds of exports
                                from current production and stocks shall be available in the first
                                place for payment for such imports,”<note n="92" xml:id="d482fn92">
                                    <ref target="frus1945Berlinv02#pg_1505">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conference of
                                        Berlin (The Potsdam Conference), 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 1505</ref>.</note> In view
                                of the requirement for paying for imports with the proceeds of
                                export and of the fact that a large proportion of the imports can be
                                procured only in the dollar area, the American and British
                                Governments have found it necessary to issue parallel notes
                                requiring payment for all exports from Germany other than exports of
                                capital equipment available as reparations or looted property
                                subject to restitution. For the time being payment is required to be
                                made in dollars but it is specifically stated that in special cases
                                it may later prove possible to arrange for payment in some other
                                currencies acceptable to the Control Council. It is understood that
                                the French Government will shortly make a similar
                                declaration.</item>
                            <item>(III) The trade situation summarized above and the financial
                                regulations issued by the American and British Governments to meet
                                it have made it difficult for the Allied countries of Europe to
                                import from Germany the goods they urgently require; most countries
                                have <pb facs="1126" n="1114" xml:id="pg_1114"/> a shortage of
                                dollars. This means that these countries are not able to buy from
                                Germany goods which are available and which they would purchase if
                                they now had sufficient dollars. Or if they pay dollars for
                                essential goods available in Germany these countries have to forego
                                goods from other sources which are needed for their reconstruction
                                and rehabilitation. Furthermore, it may mean that in order to avoid
                                having to use dollars from other sources in order to buy German
                                goods, countries which are short of dollars will [apparent garble]
                                to sell to Germany goods which they would normally sell elsewhere in
                                order to procure the necessary purchasing powder there. Some
                                countries are not only short of dollars but also of goods. For them
                                the present regulations virtually preclude the import of any goods
                                from Germany.</item>
                            <item>(IV) It is clearly in the interest of all countries requiring
                                goods from Germany that the method of payment be made as easy as
                                possible. Given the immediate necessity of meeting the situation
                                outlined in section II above, and even within the principles which
                                underlie the present financial negotiations, there are some steps
                                which might be taken to alleviate the present difficulties. A
                                further paper concerning the steps suggested for dealing with the
                                problems set forth here will be prepared at the earliest possible
                                date.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Various suggestions to facilitate payments arising from German trade have
                        been advanced by Norway, Netherlands and other EECE countries not
                        represented among controlling powers. Subcommittee on Enemy Exports has
                        agreed US and French request to defer consideration of suggestions
                        concerning foreign exchange until foregoing statement of problem had been
                        referred to governments of the controlling powers for comment.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Repeated to Berlin for Fred Winant<note n="93" xml:id="d482fn93">In the office of
                        the United States Political Adviser for Germany.</note> as 340.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
