<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="572" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d572">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">800.4016 DP/11–2945</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the Secretary of War</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Patterson</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-28">December 28,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I have received your letter
                        of November 29, 1945 with reference to the status of planning or activity
                        for the resettlement of stateless and non-repatriable displaced persons who
                        are now a United States military responsibility in Germany and Austria.</p>
                    <p>The eventual disposition of these persons is a matter of constant concern to
                        the Department of State, and is receiving every possible attention. As you
                        have been previously advised, the Department has made strong representations
                        to the British Government in efforts to secure the collaboration of that
                        Government in the expansion of the activities of the Intergovernmental
                        Committee. The position of the Intergovernmental Committee is that it cannot
                        assume responsibility <pb facs="1232" n="1220" xml:id="pg_1220"/> in Germany
                        and Austria for others than the juridically stateless during the period in
                        which UNRRA has the responsibility for the care of displaced persons. Even
                        as to the juridically stateless, responsibility is limited to preparation
                        for resettlement. The British Government supports this position strongly on
                        the ground that there should be no overlapping of functions by UNRRA and the
                        Intergovernmental Committee.</p>
                    <p>The British Government particularly takes the position that the
                        Intergovernmental Committee should not assume responsibility for persons
                        such as Poles who possess a nationality or have the protection of a
                        government, but who are unwilling to return to their country as this would
                        constitute a formal acceptance of their nonrepatriability. Such action in
                        the view of the British Government would tend to increase the numbers of
                        nonrepatriables during a period in which it is agreed by both Governments
                        that every possible effort should be made to repatriate as large numbers as
                        possible.</p>
                    <p>In the view of this Government much can be said in support of the foregoing.
                        On the other hand, it appears unrealistic to delay further recognition of
                        the fact that there will inevitably remain considerable numbers for whom
                        some other solution than repatriation will have to be found. Considering the
                        necessity of continuing support for those whose repatriation cannot be
                        achieved, it appears essential to this Government to initiate planning now
                        looking toward the ultimate disposition of these persons, difficult as this
                        may prove to be under existing circumstances.</p>
                    <p>The lack of available transport to remove such persons to other areas, the
                        uncertainties as to the specific persons who should be removed, the
                        political resistance to such removal on the part of their countries of
                        origin, and the lack of opportunities of immigration to other areas in
                        Western Europe and overseas suggest the unlikelihood that large numbers of
                        such persons may soon be removed from Germany and Austria. However, a
                        realistic appraisal of the problem suggests the possibility that as soon as
                        communications are available between Germany, Austria, and other countries
                        permitting the displaced persons involved to communicate with relatives and
                        friends in other countries, many of the non-repatriables will be able within
                        a few months, assuming also the availability of shipping, to find places of
                        residence for themselves in other countries. There is also the possibility
                        that the Intergovernmental Committee after the period of UNRRA
                        responsibility is over will be able to arrange possibilities of immigration
                        for groups of persons to countries of potential immigration both overseas
                        and in Western Europe. This latter effort presents political difficulties in
                        that potential countries of immigration <pb facs="1233" n="1221" xml:id="pg_1221"/> are unwilling at present to consider the admission of
                        persons whose movement would not have the support of their countries of
                        origin.</p>
                    <p>I can assure you that the Department of State will do everything within its
                        power to secure the expansion of the activities of the Intergovernmental
                        Committee and to find other ways and means of liquidating the problem.
                        Specifically, it is anticipated that further negotiations with the British
                        Government will be held early in the next year, and that the political
                        situation will be clarified further at the next meeting of the Council of
                        UNRRA. Whatever favorable results may attend these efforts, it must be
                        expected that some of the non-repatriables at least will eventually have to
                        be absorbed in the German economy because of the lack of immigration
                        possibilities for them in other countries. I shall, of course, keep you
                        currently informed on developments.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>