<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Czechoslovakia (
                    (Steinhardt))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d629</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">629</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-10-19T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-19T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-19T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-19T16:00:00-05:00" n="629"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d629">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/10–1045:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Czechoslovakia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-19T16:00:00-05:00"
                            >October 19, 1945—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>317. With reference to questions raised in urtel 417 Oct 3 Dept transmits
                    following comments for your guidance in discussing population transfers with
                    Zecho Govt:</p>
                <pb facs="1305" n="1293" xml:id="pg_1293"/>
                <p>US recognizes importance Zecho Govt attaches to transfer of German population and
                    is cognizant of long background of this problem. In Potsdam Agreement paragraph
                    13 the three powers recognized in principle that transfers would have to be
                    made, but agreed that transfers should take place under international control in
                    order to prevent chaos and undue suffering which would arise through mass
                    expulsions on a unilateral basis. This decision was consistent with earlier
                    replies by US to Zecho notes on German population question. On agreeing to
                    international action, the three powers did not single out Zecho for unique
                    treatment but linked Zecho with Poland and Hungary as most important area
                    involving principle of international control and direction of population
                    movements. Procedure was established in these three states as a matter of
                    urgency prior to any general agreement on population movements for Europe as a
                    whole.</p>
                <p>Information has already been transmitted to you in Berlin’s 46 Oct 10<note n="50"
                        xml:id="d629fn50">See last paragraph of telegram 739, October 10, 7 p.m.,
                        from Berlin, <ref target="#pg_1288">p. 1288</ref>.</note> that Zecho
                    delegation chosen from proposed military mission to be accredited to Allied
                    Control authorities will be received to present Zecho plan for orderly transfer.
                    Dept wishes to make clear that throughout negotiations in Control Council US
                    representative acted consistently on instructions that Zecho delegation should
                    be received and plan studied before any decision was reached on postponement of
                    population transfer. An examination of proceedings will show that activities of
                    US representative can not be construed as dilatory tactics. You may wish to make
                    it clear to Zecho Govt that US, having recognized principle of population
                    transfer at Potsdam, has always been prepared to receive and discuss Zecho plan
                    in Control Council but that assent of other three powers was necessary. Record
                    of proceedings in Control Council does not show that other three powers,
                    including Soviets, shared US position on this point.</p>
                <p>It should be made clear that transfer of Germans from Zecho does not have to be
                    made exclusively into US zone in Germany. US adheres to principle that Reich
                    Germans in Zecho should be expelled to zone in which they previously resided. As
                    for other Germans expelled by Zecho, Potsdam Agreement explicitly states that
                    Control Council should examine question of equitable distribution among several
                    zones of occupation. US can not assume unilateral responsibility for reception
                    and care of Germans transferred from Zecho to US zone. Likewise, Dept is aware
                    of fact that frontier area between Zecho and Germany is also occupied by Soviet
                    troops as well as US troops. Reported action of Soviets (urtel 448 Oct 10<note
                        n="51" xml:id="d629fn51">Not printed; it reported that a Praha newspaper had
                        published a Reuters news despatch from Berlin to the effect that Marshal
                        Zhukov had agreed to the expulsion of 6,000 Germans daily from
                        Czechoslovakia into the Soviet zone of occupation in Germany (740.00119
                        Control (Germany)/10–1045).</note>) in <pb facs="1306" n="1294"
                        xml:id="pg_1294"/> admitting six thousand Germans daily is not consistent
                    with Soviet position in Control Council.</p>
                <p>Dept agrees that immediate expulsion of Reich Germans from Zecho is four power
                    responsibility and that Zecho should not be called on to support them during
                    coming winter. As result of decision on reception of Zecho delegation, US is
                    sending instructions to USPolAd to urge that Control Council agree to immediate
                    transfer of Reich Germans who fled into Zecho in closing days of war (urtel 368
                    Sep 20). With regard to Sudeten population as denned by Presidential decree of
                    Aug 2,<note n="52" xml:id="d629fn52">See footnote 97, <ref target="#pg_1276">p.
                            1276</ref>.</note> Dept insists that international action as defined in
                    Potsdam Agreement is desirable and that four power decision in Control Council
                    is necessary before action can be taken. You are therefore urged to correct
                    impression that US is blocking the orderly repeat orderly expulsion of
                    Germans.</p>
                <p>Dept wishes to point out for your background information that many complaints
                    have been received from US military personnel stationed in Zecho concerning
                    treatment of Germans in that country. Although long and complicated background
                    of German problem may not be known to US military personnel, their attitude is
                    paralleled by indications of a growing public feeling in this country that Zecho
                    state is not fulfilling response to Potsdam note and is employing methods which
                    will ultimately affect excellent position which Zecho now has in western
                    opinion.</p>
                <p>We should also point out that Potsdam Agreement only recognized that the transfer
                    of German populations or elements thereof would have to be undertaken. So far as
                    we were concerned we wished to slow down indiscriminate and disorderly
                    expulsions and avoid unnecessary hardships on the transferees and unnecessary
                    burdens on the zones to which transfers were to be made. We recognized that
                    certain transfers were unavoidable, but we did not intend at Potsdam to
                    encourage or commit ourselves to transfers in cases where other means of
                    adjustment were practicable.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
