<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-03-30T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-03-30T12:00:00-05:00" n="707" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d707">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.70/3–3045: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-03-30T13:00:00-04:00">March 30,
                                1945—1 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>2454. For EITO Delegation. British Embassy has proposed revival of interim
                        arrangement for European inland transport advanced last January,<note n="34" xml:id="d707fn34">See telegram 427, February 3, 1 p.m., to Paris, <ref target="#pg_1395">p. 1395</ref>.</note> with following
                        modifications: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Draft Agreement should be put in final form by U.S., U.K., French,
                                Netherlands, Belgian and Luxembourg Delegations and an understanding
                                should be reached to apply it, without prejudice to subsequent
                                amendments if and when other governments participate, on informal
                                and experimental basis in areas where they have
                                responsibility.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Temporary Executive Board would be set up composed of
                                representatives of U.S., U.K., France and Belgium, and Hondelink
                                would be appointed Chief Officer, but not a member of the
                                Board.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>U.S., U.K. and French Ambassadors in Moscow would then inform
                                Soviet Government they could not agree to representation by the
                                Lublin Poles at the EITO Conference and that, if Soviet Government
                                was unwilling to eliminate all Polish representation pending
                                settlement of the Polish Government question, the three governments
                                would be obliged to put into effect the interim arrangement as above
                                indicated. Soviet Government would be invited to participate in
                                whatever way they considered appropriate, but the setting up of the
                                interim organization would not be in any way delayed by their
                                failure to do so.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Interim arrangement would be considered as extending to the SACMED
                                area but, in view of possible complications with Soviets <pb facs="1413" n="1401" xml:id="pg_1401"/> arising from Yugoslav
                                participation, none of the national governments in that area would
                                be invited to participate. Insofar as possible the Agreement would
                                be made operative in the area by means of EITO representation at
                                Allied Force Headquarters and closest possible working arrangements
                                with UNEBA.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>Department has expressed its approval<note n="35" xml:id="d707fn35">Letter from Mr. Walter Radius of the Office of
                                    Transportation and Communications to the Second Secretary of the
                                    British Embassy (Maclean), March 30, 1945, not printed.</note>
                                of this proposal and you are therefore authorized to take all steps
                                appropriate to bring it into effect as soon as possible.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Repeated to Paris and Moscow.<note n="36" xml:id="d707fn36">As telegrams 1246
                            and 740, respectively.</note>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>