<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Ambassador in Iran (
                        Murray
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d797</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">797</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="finance" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885" lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recg3iRrscBAKUZil" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="narcotics" subject="opium" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85095095" lcsh-match="exact">Opium</term>
                    <term ref="rec99jdV9ZgPMHimw" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="narcotics" subject="narcotics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85089815" lcsh-match="exact">Narcotics</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="797" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d797">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">891.114 Narcotics/9–1945</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murray</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 288</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-13">November 13,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Reference is made to your despatch no. 95 of
                    September 19, 1945,<note n="25" xml:id="d797fn25">Not printed.</note>
                    transmitting an English translation of portions of a recent address by Mr.
                    Mahmoud Bader, Minister of Finance, on the policy of the Iranian Government
                    regarding opium.<note n="26" xml:id="d797fn26">Delivered in Tehran on August 26
                        at a meeting of the Anti-Opium Society.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The statements made by Mr. Bader putting the Iranian Government on record on
                    certain phases of this subject are appreciated and are helpful in moving toward
                    a solution of the problem. The Department is pleased that the Minister of
                    Finance has made an address on opium, that he has presented a bill to the Majlis
                    providing for the ratification of the Geneva Drug Convention of 1925, and that
                    he has issued instructions on the control of exports. It is regretted that he
                    did not also present a bill providing for the ratification of The Hague Opium
                    Convention of 1912 without reservation as to article 3<hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</p>
                <p>The Department does not feel, however, that it should at this time give publicity
                    to and congratulate the Iranian Government on the position now taken, as there
                    is no visible manifestation of any positive action. The formal reply of the
                    Iranian Government to the Embassy’s note pursuant to the Judd Resolution is
                    still being awaited. Upon receipt of that reply and with the consent of the
                    Iranian Government, the Department proposes to publish in the “Department of
                    State Bulletin” the text of the exchange of notes. It is hoped that <pb facs="1551" n="1539" xml:id="pg_1539"/> the Iranian Government in its reply
                    will set forth clearly its position on the question of the limitation of the
                    production of opium.</p>
                <p>The Treasury Department and this Department are still interested in having
                    information on the subjects listed in the first paragraph of the Department’s
                    telegram no. 406 of August 7, 1945.<note n="27" xml:id="d797fn27">Not printed;
                        the first paragraph requested information on the following aspects of
                        Iranian opium: production, 1940–45; quantity in possession of the Government
                        and farmers; exports, 1940–45; control of opium in international trade by
                        use of import-export permits; extent of addiction and quantity of opium
                        consumed in Iran; measures to enforce narcotics laws; the system of
                        licensing smokers and eaters of opium; smuggling and steps taken to prevent
                        it; the cost and time required to shift from producing opium to other
                        products; attitude toward joining the Turkish-Yugoslav opium agreement; and
                        attitude toward the Judd Resolution (891.114 Narcotics/3145).</note> Mr.
                    Bader failed to disclose whether the Iranian Government has complete statistics
                    or will establish a system whereby accurate information can be obtained in
                    regard to opium production, stocks, exports and consumption. If the Embassy
                    itself has been able to obtain information concerning the first nine topics
                    listed in the above-mentioned telegram, the Department would be glad to receive
                    it.</p>
                <p>With regard to Mr. Bader’s instructions concerning the export of opium from Iran,
                    the Embassy may wish to inquire of him whether in future he proposes to issue
                    export permits only on the basis of import permits signed by authorized
                    authorities. In the opinion of American narcotics authorities this is far more
                    important than the matter of merely taking care to see that each export is
                    covered by an export permit. From information in their possession, the American
                    authorities believe that Iran on many occasions between 1933 and 1940 made
                    shipments to the Far East on the basis of import permits issued by persons who
                    were not charged in their countries with the responsibility of issuing import
                    permits. Although request has been made of the Iranian Government for permission
                    to see the import permits on which the Iranian Government made export shipments,
                    that Government has never consented to produce the import permits from its
                    records for examination.</p>
                <p>[Here follow additional comments on Mr. Bader’s speech before the Anti-Opium
                    Society.]</p>
                <p>The Department is pleased with the forceful manner in which you have drawn the
                    attention of the Iranian Government to the opium problem. It trusts that you
                    will continue to keep the subject before the Iranian authorities. The
                    Department, in particular, desires that you again urge the Iranian authorities
                    to make a reply without further <pb facs="1552" n="1540" xml:id="pg_1540"/>
                    delay to the Embassy’s note of September 20, 1944<note n="29" xml:id="d797fn29">The note of September 20, 1944, to the Iranian Ministry for Foreign Affairs
                        was not answered. However, on April 10, 1946, the Iranian Government issued
                        a decree forbidding cultivation of the opium poppy after the harvesting of
                        that year’s crop. The Iranian Government, on June 26, 1946, made it unlawful
                        to use opium and as of November 22, 1946, prohibited its sale to the public.
                        In a conversation with an officer of the Embassy on November 22, 1948, the
                        Iranian Prime Minister stated that henceforth Iran would export opium for
                        medicinal purposes only and prohibit aU exports of opium to the Far East. On
                        March 19, 1949, a decree of the Iranian Council of Ministers revoked the
                        prohibition of April 10, 1946, but limited opium production to local and
                        international scientific and medical requirements. This was followed, later,
                        by the enactment of legislation by the Majlis on October 7, 1955, under
                        which the cultivation of the opium poppy was banned.</note> pursuant to the
                    Judd Eesolution, and that you continue to endeaver to obtain from the Iranian
                    Government a statement regarding its willingness to become a party to the
                    Turkish-Yugoslav Opium Sales Agreement. You may point out that if Iran were to
                    be included in that agreement, Iran would be accorded a definite share of the
                    international opium market and would be assured of a fair price for its
                    opium.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William L. Clayton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[Participation by the United States in cooperative efforts for international
                        control of the traffic in and suppression of the abuses of opium and other
                        dangerous drugs had continued at the United Nations Conference on
                        International Organization, San Francisco, April 25–June 26, 1945.<note n="30" xml:id="d797fn30">For documentation on the San Francisco
                            Conference, see <ref target="frus1945v01#pg_1">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff.</note> There, with regard to the
                        establishment of a United Nations Economic and Social Council, the United
                        States delegation went on record as hoping that the Organization would be
                        entrusted with supervision over the execution of existing or future
                        international agreements with regard to the control of the legitimate
                        traffic in opium and other dangerous drugs, and the suppression of illicit
                        traffic in and abuse of such drugs; that there should be established an
                        advisory body to advise directly the Economic and Social Council on these
                        matters; and that the existing agencies be regarded as autonomous agencies
                        to be related directly to the Economic and Social Council.<note n="31" xml:id="d797fn31">Department of State Conference Series No. 71, June 26,
                            1945: <hi rend="italic">Report to the President on the Results of the
                                San Francisco Conference by the Chairman of the United States
                                Delegation, The Secretary of State</hi>, p. 122.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Subsequently, the Commission on Narcotic Drugs was created on February 18,
                        1946, by the United Nations Economic and Social Council.<note n="32" xml:id="d797fn32">
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Economic and Social Council</hi>, No.
                            12, pp. 129–130. See also George A. Morlock, “International Control of
                            Dangerous Drugs; Preview of Commission on Narcotic Drugs”, Department of
                            State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November 17, 1946, pp.
                            885–888.</note>]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
