<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-10-27T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-10-27T07:00:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                        <head>123. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the United
                                Kingdom</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d123fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 764.00/10–2756. Confidential;
                                    <gloss target="#t_niact1">Niact</gloss>. Received at 9:09 a.m.
                                Repeated to Paris.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>London</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-10-27T12:00:00+00:00">October 27,
                                        1956—noon</date></hi>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>2316. For the Secretary. Paris for Ambassador. Reference: <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 3008.<note n="2" xml:id="d123fn2"><ref target="#d122"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> with <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>’s approval agrees to joint US–UK
                            inscription Hungary on Security Council agenda under Article 34. Also
                            concurs action should be taken at once today. Immediate instructions
                            being sent to Dixon New York to collaborate with us. Broad discretion
                            being given him as to language in which item to be inscribed. British
                            request joint announcement inscription as soon as action taken. Please
                            confirm.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> said felt essential French be
                            given chance to join US–UK in this inscription although action should be
                            taken today in any event without awaiting French reaction if not
                            forthcoming in time.<note n="3" xml:id="d123fn3"><persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> called <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> at 10:05 a.m. and advised
                                him to contact Dixon. He further stated that it was all right for
                                him to consult with the French afterwards. (<persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> Papers, General Telephone
                                Conversations) Telegram 2002 from Paris, October 27, received at
                                10:39 a.m., reported that the French were prepared to join with the
                                United States and the United Kingdom in presenting a resolution on
                                Hungary to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> Security Council.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, 764.00/10–2756) At 1 p.m. on
                                October 27, Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>, Dixon, and Cornut-Gentille addressed a letter
                                to the President of the Security Council requesting inclusion of an
                                item entitled “The Situation in Hungary” on the Security Council
                                agenda. (<gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> doc. S/3690) Ambassador
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> in Moscow
                                acknowledged the psychological and political difficulties for the
                                Soviet Union from a Western appeal to the Security Council. But he
                                warned that if Nagy were anxious to follow the Polish and Yugoslav
                                examples then such an appeal might drive him closer to the Soviets.
                                However, if Nagy were considered a prisoner of the Soviets then the
                                move in the United Nations could only be an advantage. (Telegram 969
                                from Moscow, October 27; Department of State, Central Files,
                                660.61/10–2756)</note> Foreign Office urgently informing French
                            Ambassador.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KSIA1">Kirkpatrick</persName> who was with him did not
                            seem to have any specific thoughts on course Security Council
                            consideration might take nor clear view as to optimum presentation.
                            However both felt ample justification for bringing case under Article 34
                            particularly with reference to possible request Security Council
                            “investigate”. Clearly believed Soviets could be put on spot by this and
                            at minimum forced to take positions which could be used against them
                            subsequently. At same time noted obvious Soviet defense on grounds
                            Soviet action at request Hungarian government which if not a lawful and
                            representative government at least recognized internationally.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AWW1"><hi rend="strong">Aldrich</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>