<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>148. Telegram From the Legation in Hungary to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d148</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">148</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-10-31T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-10-31T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recEKBMJ0utJPbJXo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Troop withdrawal</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recIMvblVMopWEA1k" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019002541"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Anti-Semitic</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-10-31T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-10-31T07:00:00-05:00" n="148"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d148">
                <head>148. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Legation in Hungary</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d148fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 764.00/10–3156. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_niact1"
                        >Niact</gloss>. Sent also to Vienna for <persName corresp="#p_WET1">Edward
                            T. Wailes</persName> who was then on his way to Hungary to assume his
                        post.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Budapest</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1956-10-31T13:00:00+01:00">October 31, 1956—1 p.m.</date>
                        </hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>200. Legtel 198.<note n="2" xml:id="d148fn2">Telegram 198 from Budapest, October
                        31, reported that the Soviets had withdrawn from Budapest except for some
                        key locations. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.)</note> In dramatic overnight
                    change, it became virtually certain in Budapest this morning that this Hungarian
                    revolution now fact of history. Personal observations, newspaper stories, and
                    radio content tend to confirm complete Soviet troop withdrawal from city,
                    apparently under Hungarian protection. <gloss target="#t_TASS1">TASS</gloss>
                    report that Soviets would begin negotiations on removing troops from Hungary
                    confirmed <pb facs="0380" n="350" xml:id="pg_350"/> Nagy’s statement (Legtel
                        176<note n="3" xml:id="d148fn3">Telegram 176 from Budapest, October 29,
                        summarized Nagy’s October 28 speech. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                        764.00/10–2956)</note>) which population obviously mistrusted completely at
                    first. Crucial point, however, in our belief, was actual beginning of withdrawal
                    of troops from Budapest.</p>
                <p>During events of past week, Legation was doubtful that what has happened could be
                    achieved without strongest Western support. That it is taking place is
                    additional evidence of tremendous strength of popular movement, which
                    undoubtedly having profound effect on Soviet policy. Appears logical premise
                    that Soviets, having unilaterally decided to abandon military position in city
                    without guarantee of ultimate nature of government that springs up behind, must
                    be seriously considering departure from Hungary within relatively short
                    period.</p>
                <p>In view attitude Hungarian army, Legation believes public order will be
                    reasonably maintained. Partisan ferreting out of <gloss target="#t_AVH1"
                        >AVH</gloss> units already beginning this morning, however, with some
                    sporadic shooting audible, and will probably go on for some time. Virtually no
                    looting has occurred, as far as Legation is aware, nor has any evidence of
                    anti-Semitic outbursts become known to Legation.</p>
                <p>Question of political future, of course, much more cloudy. Legation informed that
                    Social Democrats now meeting to choose members coalition group. Also informed by
                    partisan that nothing less than American-type western democracy would satisfy
                    population. Present coalition, in any event, appears as transitional government
                    pending emergence of more permanent political parties. Speed and nature of this
                    process by no means clear as yet.</p>
                <p>Future US role in Hungary also not clear, but seems certain to be very different
                    from past. Hungarian radio phoned this a.m. for foreign news bulletin and
                    Legation attempting obtain same by Telex from Vienna.</p>
                <p>Our initial view this morning, which may only be highly preliminary, is that
                    would be desirable for President to make statement in very near future. This
                    might indicate US willingness to initiate some type of immediate economic aid,
                    to be followed by broader political and economic discussions. Suggestions for
                    statement follow.<note n="4" xml:id="d148fn4">
                        <p>Telegram 201 from Budapest, October 31, suggested the following
                            statement:</p>
                        <p>“Entire world has been watching dramatic events in Hungary, as Hungarian
                            people, as on many other occasions, have given their lives for
                            independence from foreign masters. It appears today that new Hungary is
                            emerging before world: A Hungary which we hope from our hearts will reap
                            full benefits of nationhood. To witness this historic moment of national
                            re-emergence of great people is emotionally rewarding experience.</p>
                        <p>“The US has already joined with many other countries in sending medical
                            assistance to Hungary’s wounded. We shall give immediate consideration
                            to economic assistance, and hopeful within short time for increased
                            contacts with Hungary in all fields.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                            764.00/10–3156)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BNS1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Barnes</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
