<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>163. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-01-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-12-27T18:47:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="receNc7LQFkxnPn2F" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-12-27T18:47:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="163" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d163">
                <head>163. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>According to <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Multiple Exposure</hi>, pages 71–72), <persName corresp="#p_HHCJ1"
                        >Hoover</persName> called him around 2 a.m. on November 4 (8 a.m. in
                    Budapest) to say that “he had received a clandestine message” that Cardinal
                    Mindszenty and his secretary (Egon Turchányi) were about to seek asylum at the
                    American Legation. When asked for his advice, <persName corresp="#p_BJD1"
                        >Beam</persName> replied that while the United States opposed asylum in
                    principle, nevertheless it was justified in this case since “it involved hot
                    pursuit endangering human life.” <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName>
                    later learned that <persName corresp="#p_HHCJ1">Hoover</persName> checked with
                    the President before the Hungarians were admitted.</p>
                <p>In a memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_LHP1">Leverich</persName> on this
                    subject, dated November 5, 1957, <persName corresp="#p_SJS1"
                        >Sutterlin</persName> wrote: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“<persName corresp="#p_WET1">Tom Wailes</persName> recalls that a coded
                            message was received by the Legation about 6 a.m. on November the 4th
                            and that it was decoded just before the Cardinal appeared at the door.
                            It is his impression that this message authorized the extension of
                            refuge or asylum to the Cardinal. He remembers that he was somewhat
                            surprised that Washington should have had prior knowledge of the
                            Cardinal’s intention to seek safety in the Legation . . . .” (Department
                            of State, Hungary Desk Files: Lot 75 D 45, Refuge for Cardinal
                            Mindszenty—1956–57 )</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>In an unsigned and undated memorandum bearing the handwritten notation “Nov.
                    1956,” <persName corresp="#p_MLC1">Meeker</persName> recollected a message that
                    reads: “Dept has just received info . . . that Cardinal Mindszenty will shortly
                    come to the American Legation. You are authorized to admit him.” In another
                    version, the message said “that Cardinal Mindszenty <pb facs="0417" n="387"
                        xml:id="pg_387"/> wishes seek asylum with Legation. Approval granted.” The
                    message was thought to have come over regular channels and both parties
                    remembered that it bore the Secretary’s name. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                    Budapest Post Files: Lot 75 F 163, Mindszenty 1956–57)</p>
                <p>Mindszenty writes otherwise in his <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, page 212. He
                    relates that when Parliament was sealed off by Soviet troops, he took sanctuary
                    in the American Legation because it was the nearest. He notes that 30 minutes or
                    so after his arrival, cabled permission for him to enter was received from
                    President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> and that 4 hours
                    later Turchányi was admitted. He does mention subsequent foreign press reports
                    to the effect that Nagy had requested United States asylum on his behalf the day
                    before. In any event, he recalls that he was surprised by the speed with which
                    his case was handled.</p>
                <p>On November 8, <persName corresp="#p_BJD1">Beam</persName> sent a memorandum to
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> on the subject of asylum for
                    the Cardinal. He noted that the United States in the past had “strongly
                    disapproved of the principle of diplomatic asylum,” but had been willing to
                    afford temporary refuge in order to save human life. Section 225.2 of the
                    Foreign Service Regulations (“Restrictions on Extending Asylum”), was cited. It
                    reads: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“As a rule, a diplomatic or consular officer shall not extend asylum to
                            persons outside of his official or personal household. Refuge may be
                            afforded to uninvited fugitives whose lives are in imminent danger from
                            mob violence but only for the period during which active danger
                            continues. Refuge shall be refused to persons fleeing from legitimate
                            agents of the local government. In case such persons have been admitted
                            to the diplomatic or consular premises, they must be surrendered or
                            dismissed from such mission or consular office.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Since the Cardinal’s life had been in jeopardy as he was in flight from a foreign
                    invader, the provision of sanctuary was considered justified. (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Ibid</hi>., Hungary Desk Files: Lot 75 D 45, Refuge for Cardinal
                    Mindszenty—1956–57)</p>
                <p>Turchányi was later apprehended by the <gloss target="#t_AVH1">AVH</gloss> on
                    November 10 while attempting to flee Hungary in the company of Leslie Bain who
                    recorded this development in <hi rend="italic">Reluctant Satellites</hi>, page
                    172. Turchányi was thereafter sentenced to life imprisonment. The subject of how
                    the Cardinal came to the Legation is also dealt with in despatch 415 from
                    Budapest, March 8, 1957. (Department of State, Central Files, 764.00/3–857)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
