<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-12-26T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-12-26T11:00:00-05:00" n="218" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d218">
                        <head>218. Notes of a Meeting With the President, White House, Washington,
                            December 26, 1956, 11 a.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d218fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library,
                                Whitman File, International File. Prepared by Ann C. Whitman. The
                                meeting took place in the President’s office.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-12-26T11:00:00-05:00">December 26, 1956, 11
                                    a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PRESENT</head>
                            <item>The Vice President; <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Loy W.
                                    Henderson</persName>, Deputy Undersecretary of State; <persName corresp="#p_HJB1">John B. Hollister</persName>, Director, <gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss>; William P. Rogers, Deputy Attorney
                                General; Tracy Voorhees<note n="2" xml:id="d218fn2">On December 12,
                                    President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                                    announced the establishment of the President’s Committee for
                                    Hungarian Refugee Relief chaired by Tracy S. Voorhees. He was
                                    charged with seeing to it that the voluntary agencies worked
                                    effectively with each other and with the government agencies
                                    involved in the relief effort. William Hallam Tuck was
                                    designated to act for the committee in Austria in a liaison
                                    capacity with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>. Voorhees had earlier been appointed on
                                    November 28 to be the President’s representative concerning
                                    resettlement activities and refugee relief.</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0565" n="535" xml:id="pg_535"/>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>STAFF MEMBERS</head>
                            <item>Persons, Murray Snyder and <persName corresp="#p_GCAJ1">Goodpaster</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Vice President reported on his trip to Austria in connection with the
                            Hungarian refugee problem.<note n="3" xml:id="d218fn3"><persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> spoke with <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> on December 7 regarding a
                                trip to Austria. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                                suggested various ways of dramatizing the mission including having
                                Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> or Mrs.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> go over on the
                                Presidential plane to pick up a planeload of women and children. He
                                later stated, however, that he did not wish to go if it appeared
                                like a “grandstand play.” (Memorandum of telephone conversation by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BPD1">Bernau</persName>, December 7;
                                    <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> Papers, General
                                Telephone Conversations) In his memoirs, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> stated that the President recalled him to
                                Washington on December 13 and asked him to meet with <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> who informed him that it had
                                been decided to have him undertake the mission to Austria (Operation
                                Mercy). (<hi rend="italic">RN: Memoirs of <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard Nixon</persName>;</hi> p. 182) The
                                announcement of the Vice President’s trip to Austria as the
                                President’s personal representative was made on December 12. He
                                departed on December 18 and returned on December 24. Subsequently,
                                on December 27, he visited the refugee facility at Camp Kilmer. For
                                text of his January 1, 1957, “Report to the President on Hungarian
                                Refugees,” see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                                January 21, 1957, pp. 94–99.</note> On that trip he was accompanied
                            by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HJB1">Hollister</persName> and Mr.
                            Rogers.</p>
                        <p>His first point was that the U.S. should not continue to speak of the <hi rend="italic">numbers</hi> of refugees it is admitting. The British
                            and French take credit for an unlimited number, though actually they do
                            have limitation. He came back to this point a number of times.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President is going to prepare a brief summary report for the
                            leaders’ meetings next Monday and Tuesday.<note n="4" xml:id="d218fn4">Following <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s report and
                                his meeting with Congressional leaders on January 1, the President
                                announced that, pending Congressional action, the Attorney General
                                would continue to parole Hungarian refugees into the United States.
                                (Telegram 3045 to Vienna, January 3; Department of State, Central
                                Files, 764.00/1–357)</note></p>
                        <p>Under his general comments, the Vice President first stressed that
                            despite the confusion, generally speaking a very good job is being done
                            for the refugees. There are some big camps, some smaller ones, some
                            people housed in schoolhouses and barracks, and Salzburg and Munich and
                            other places have taken some. The Salzburg camp is probably the best
                            one.</p>
                        <p>He praised particularly the work Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>, in Austria, of the Immigration people, and
                            talked at some length about the voluntary efforts of service people at
                            various spots along the way to provide packages and extraordinarily
                            thoughtful things for the Hungarians. The President asked <persName corresp="#p_GCAJ1">Colonel Goodpaster</persName> to prepare for him
                            a letter to General Max Taylor commending the service people and wives.
                            He also said parenthetically that the situation at Camp Kilmer had
                            greatly improved from the early first days. The President also suggested
                            that if the Vice President spoke again on television, he should put in a
                            word about the service people.</p>
                        <pb facs="0566" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/>
                        <p>The Vice President’s next general comment was about the high calibre of
                            the refugees. They are young, in most cases the people “had” to leave
                            the country—i.e. the leadership type—to avoid deportation. The President
                            recalled that <persName corresp="#p_ZMGK1">Marshal Zhukov</persName> had
                            once said if you got rid of the leaders of a country, you could do
                            anything you wanted to.</p>
                        <p>About the security problem, the Vice President minimised the danger,
                            particularly because there are so many people coming out that everyone
                            is known to a lot of the others and it is hard in that way to slip into
                            them a person who might be planted for spying purposes. However, some of
                            the Congressional leaders are worrying about that. The President thinks
                            such danger is almost zero—and said the Communists did not have to go to
                            such elaborate means as would be necessary in this case, in order to get
                            “spies” into our country.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President said the other countries regard these particular
                            refugees as tremendous assets, rather than liabilities—pointed out that
                            Holland, overcrowded as it is, had taken 300 and wanted more. Germany is
                            taking 10% of all that come over—they are experts in handling refugees.
                            The Hungarians are productive people—later in the discussion the
                            President pointed out what a tremendous thing it would be for the Mid
                            East people to take in some of these industrious people.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President next went to the size of the problem, though there are
                            so many imponderables it is difficult to be accurate. Approximately
                            151,000 have come out to date, of these 70,000 are still in
                            Austria—80,000 having moved on into other countries. We have taken about
                            14,000—and have processed remaining 7,000 that at present we may take.
                            The transportation of these 7,000 will require until January 10th. They
                            are still coming out at rate of 800 a day, and no one can say for how
                            long that will go on. There is feeling that the Russians are soon going
                            to have a major decision to make—one that might start the tide going
                            back (if any change in government in Hungary)—or the Russians may clamp
                            down on exodus.</p>
                        <p>The President had been advised that it would be cheaper to keep these
                            people in Austria, the U.S. paying the costs, but the Vice President
                            emphatically disagreed.</p>
                        <p>Back to the figures, there are about 63,000 in Austria as yet unplaced,
                            of which 10,000 will be taken by other countries. Austria has said that
                            they can absorb 30,000 (but there is a joker in that, since they put as
                            a condition the money to build housing facilities—and, it was later
                            said, any houses that might be built would undoubtedly go to the local
                            politicos rather than the refugees). At any rate that would leave about
                            20,000 odd thousand for whom places must be found, plus the 800 a day
                            coming in.</p>
                        <pb facs="0567" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/>
                        <p>The Vice President pointed out the danger in leaving people too long in
                            refugee camps because of morale problem. The President said that the
                            danger was really based on the nature of the people, that the Latvians
                            and Estonians, etc., had, during the war, conducted model camps—because
                            of their very nature. But the Hungarians are volatile and impulsive—and
                            the camps would be breeding grounds for Communist propaganda.</p>
                        <p>An additional problem is that a number of the refugees have gone to other
                            countries, with the promise that they will be brought to America as soon
                            as possible (however, the other countries will take replacements). The
                            President said Britain should work out an arrangement with the
                            Commonwealth—Australia, however, is taking 4,000. The President said he
                            had asked Nehru to take a certain token number, despite India’s
                            overcrowded condition.<note n="5" xml:id="d218fn5">Nehru visited the
                                United States between December 16 and 20, 1956.</note> The ones in
                            Italy must be taken out as soon as possible. The President suggested to
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Henderson</persName> that the State
                            Department should work with the Latin American nations to try to get
                            them to take a certain number each—they are in general underpopulated
                            and can use the skills the Hungarians have.</p>
                        <p>The question is where do we go from there? The President suggested that,
                            pending action on the part of Congress, processing be continued on a
                            temporary basis—and at the same time the refugees be processed by other
                            countries, with the explanation given to them that the United States
                            cannot at the moment definitely guarantee them entry. Bill Rogers said
                            that the Attorney General was not willing to guarantee more “parolees”
                            without at least an understanding with the Congressional leaders that
                            such action would be approved by Congress. The President pointed out
                            that he did not want to stop processing, particularly since if we do,
                            the pick of the refugees will go to other countries.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that the matter should be presented to the bipartisan
                            meeting of Congress, rather than to the Republicans alone.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Rogers suggested that something on the order of “suspension
                            deportation” arrangements can be worked out.</p>
                        <p>The President brought up what he had heard was lack of response to the
                            Red Cross appeal. The Vice President said appeal had picked up, and it
                            was agreed that the money would probably come in in the quantity
                            necessary. The President hopes it does, because that would indicate the
                            people of the country are behind the movement—and if so, Congress will
                            go along. The Vice President emphasized that it is important that the
                            United States not drag its feet—that it stay in the forefront of the
                            moment, that we continue to take applications at current rate. The
                            President said we could take the applications—could say that we will
                            take our “full share” or “decent share” of refugees. He <pb facs="0568" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/> pointed out that what we were talking
                            about was really a small number of those that might come in, if, for
                            instance, Poland and Czechoslovakia should have upheavals similar to the
                            Hungarian one. He also said we have got to have every country in the
                            world feel some responsibility. The United Nations ought to pass a
                            Resolution commending each nation for its readiness to open its
                            doors.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President suggested that <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Cabot
                                Lodge</persName> might make as a primary order of business the
                            urging of the Ambassadors to the United Nations that their countries
                            accept this responsibility.</p>
                        <p>There was some question as to how quickly Congress would act (in matter
                            of increasing number of people the US could take)—the Vice President
                            said two months; it was hoped not that long. The President said,
                            incidentally, that he was willing to see Congressman Walter<note n="6" xml:id="d218fn6">Democratic Congressman Francis E. Walter of
                                Pennsylvania was a member of the Joint Committee on Immigration and
                                Nationality Policy.</note> if that would be helpful in enlisting his
                            energetic cooperation.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President urged that here was an opportunity to get needed
                            flexibility into our Immigration laws. He pointed out also the seeming
                            injustice to the 10,000 Eastern European refugees who are anxious to
                            come to this country—who crawled under barbed wire to come out—and who
                            have been long in camps, mainly in Germany. The Justice Department is
                            going to recommend such flexibility.</p>
                        <p>Turning to the economic side—there was discussion of the amounts needed
                            (which of course depends on the number that will continue to come out)
                            and whether Congress should be asked for a special appropriation.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HJB1">Hollister</persName> spoke about the
                            magnitude of the problem and said, with money available in <gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss>, he could absorb some $60-65 million of
                            the cost, assuming that Mid East projects for which money was
                            appropriated did not materialize. However, the President said that he
                            hoped that at least part of that money would be used for the Mid East.
                            It was agreed that the U.S. was going to have to shoulder the burden of
                            the major part of the financing. A payment of some $5 million has been
                            made to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, but it was questioned
                            whether other members of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> had put
                            in their share.<note n="7" xml:id="d218fn7">On December 15, in response
                                to General Assembly Resolution 1007 (ES–II), the President declared
                                that the United States would make $4 million available to the United
                                Nations to assist Hungarian refugees. This was in addition to the
                                earlier $1 million contribution. See Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, January 9, 1957, p. 9.</note> If
                            they do not, President agrees money should go direct to Austria. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HJB1">Hollister</persName> pointed out there
                            were three distinct projects: general refugee problem; refugees coming
                            to this country; and the situation in Hungary itself. There are the
                            private agencies; there is the International Red Cross; and there are
                            the other red cross teams operating in Austria. He recommended a
                            “dictator” under Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> to handle the details of payments, etc.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HJB1">Hollister</persName> hopes to make as
                            many payments as possible in <pb facs="0569" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/>
                            commodities and in a deal that will utilize some shillings he has in
                            reserve. <persName corresp="#p_HJB1">Hollister</persName> told the
                            President of the “bill” the Austrian government presented them, for
                            expenses for people already there, for anticipated people, and, again,
                            for the housing they hope to build with American funds. The Vice
                            President thought it would be well to ask the Congress for $30-40
                            million for the purpose—he is inclined to think it would be a good idea
                            to let the Congress see this refugee problem in its entirety—as a single
                            package. The President may want to discuss this with Congressional
                            leaders.</p>
                        <p>Tracy Voorhees presented two or three points. To prevent piling up of
                            refugees at Camp Kilmer, it may be necessary for the government to
                            provide transportation and other assistance to some of the private
                            charities, specifically Catholic Charities. Secondly, he has contracted
                            with a public relations firm, to be paid for independently, a program
                            for creating a “suction effort” throught the country. So far it has been
                            a “retail” job. He hopes this suction effort will prevent later
                            repercussions about placement of refugees. There is needed also some way
                            of “dividing” up the refugees among the voluntary agencies. We ought to
                            have something to say about which agencies will be the sponsoring
                            agencies.</p>
                        <p>About the transportation from abroad, he said the Pentagon wanted it all
                            contracted for. The President has little patience with the grumblings of
                            the services.</p>
                        <p>At the conclusion Mr. Voorhees told the President of the reception his
                            letter to the refugees had had at Camp Kilmer.<note n="8" xml:id="d218fn8">In his letter, which was undated, the President
                                welcomed the Hungarians to American soil and concluded: “We realize
                                that you ardently hope for a time when all Hungarians can enjoy the
                                blessings of individual freedom in their Hungarian mother-country.
                                We join in that hope. And we give you this present assurance—if,
                                when that day dawns once more, you should choose to go back to your
                                native homes in Hungary, America will do its best in helping you to
                                return.” (<persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library,
                                Whitman File, International File)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>