<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-01-18T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-01-18T08:00:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                        <head>226. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Italy</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d226fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 864.413/1–1857. Secret; Limit Distribution. Repeated to
                                Budapest.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Rome</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-01-18T14:00:00+01:00">January 18, 1957—2
                                        p.m.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p>2971. News stories reporting alleged secret negotiations between
                                <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Kadar</persName> regime and American
                            Legation Budapest re disposition Cardinal Mindszenty have prompted
                            Vatican official approach Embassy representative for information re
                            truth or falsity reports. Official showed concern re fate Cardinal and
                            Vatican Secretariat of State would appreciate being informed any plans
                            affecting future of Cardinal.</p>
                        <p>In this connection Embassy representative was told in strict confidence
                            Holy See would pose no objection to Cardinal’s decision leave Hungary
                            but would not attempt officially to influence Cardinal one way or
                                other.<note n="2" xml:id="d226fn2">Despatch 877 from Rome, January
                                3, reported that a Vatican official indicated that the Holy See
                                preferred that the Cardinal remain in Hungary. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 848.413/1–357) Telegram 525 from Budapest, January
                                10, described an approach from the AVO to a “reliable source” who
                                was asked to contact the Legation to convey the Hungarian
                                Government’s assurance of a guarantee of safe conduct for the
                                Cardinal to leave the country. The motivation was supposed to have
                                been a desire to bring about improved relations with the United
                                States. <persName corresp="#p_WET1">Wailes</persName> doubted the
                                Cardinal wished to leave and thought the Hungarian Government was
                                content with the way things were. Moreover, he believed the Cardinal
                                would be arrested if he left the Legation. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 864.413/1–1057) Telegram 5 to Rome, January 21,
                                instructed the Embassy to inform the Vatican that the Legation was
                                not conducting negotiations with the <persName corresp="#p_KJ1">Kádár</persName> government concerning the Cardinal. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 864.413/1–2157)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JJD1"><hi rend="strong">Jernegan</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>