<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>51. Instruction From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Poland</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec26FVg4SV48wXxH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124118"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Socialism</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recORcNZq5ClDOVNg" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046356"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exhibit</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recoco7SW1Tkt0mwM" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007735"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sports</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="51"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                <head>51. Instruction From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Poland</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d51fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 611.48/3–2856. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_LGT1"
                            >Lister</persName> and approved in <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_USIA1"
                            >USIA</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_P1">P</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">A–199</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1956-03-28">March 28, 1956</date>
                        </hi>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>American Relations with Poland</item>
                </list>
                <p>Reference is made to Embassy despatch No. 238 of January 10, 1956,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d51fn2">In despatch 238, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JJE1"
                            >Jacobs</persName> reported on a continuing exchange of views between
                        him and the British Ambassador in Warsaw as to the nature of Polish
                        communism and the Polish Government. The British Ambassador, Sir Andrew
                        Noble, held that a definite Polish policy was emerging in Warsaw, and the
                        Western powers, particularly the United States and United Kingdom, should
                        take advantage of the post-Geneva Conference relaxation of East-West
                        tensions to support and encourage Warsaw’s independent policy, thus
                        weakening Soviet domination of Poland. Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_JJE1">Jacobs</persName> believed that encouraging the
                        present Polish Government would mean bolstering the prestige of a regime
                        which the United States publicly condemned. <persName corresp="#p_JJE1"
                            >Jacobs</persName> held that the relaxation of Soviet control in Poland
                        was only superficial; Poles still had no real freedom of action in foreign
                        affairs. Such friendly overtures as suggested by Ambassador Noble in the
                        fields of cultural, economic, political, information, and sports affairs,
                        were, from <persName corresp="#p_JJE1">Jacobs</persName>’ point of view,
                        inadvisable at the present time. Attached to despatch 238 was a copy of
                        Noble’s despatch to London outlining his policy suggestions. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 641.48/1–1056)</note> and to previous Embassy
                    despatches and telegrams setting forth the views and recommendations of the
                    Embassy, as well as those of the British Ambassador, with respect to our present
                    relations with Poland and inviting the Department’s comments and guidance.</p>
                <p>The Embassy’s views as reported in despatches 76 of September 12, 1955<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d51fn3">In despatch 76, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JJE1"
                            >Jacobs</persName> commented on the differences of opinion between him
                        and Ambassador Noble along the lines of despatch 238. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid</hi>., 611.00/9–1255)</note> and 238 of January 10, 1956, and
                    cogently expressed to Sir Andrew Noble on December 30, 1955,<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d51fn4">According to despatch 238, Noble and <persName
                            corresp="#p_JJE1">Jacobs</persName> had their main exchange of views on
                        Poland on December 30.</note> correspond in general to the Department’s
                    position except as qualified by the following comments.</p>
                <p>It is the Department’s present belief that until or unless some basic and drastic
                    change occurs, either in the nature of Soviet policies or in the power
                    relationship between the Free World and the Soviet Bloc, Poland will continue to
                    be ruled by men whose decisions are based primarily on their understanding and
                    interpretation of the desires and intentions of the Kremlin. The Department
                    views such manifestations of “relaxation” as the reorganization of the Polish
                    security police, the recent “thaw” in Polish literature, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Nowe Drogi</hi>
                    <pb facs="0162" n="132" xml:id="pg_132"/> reference to a Polish road to
                    Socialism as significant and noteworthy changes in Communist tactics in Poland,
                    but not as evidence of the emergence of an independent “Polish policy”, as that
                    term is usually understood. Possibly these recent developments cannot be
                    explained solely as window dressing attributable to: 1) Moscow’s desire for
                    relaxation of international tension following Stalin’s death and in view of
                    growing Western unity against Communist aggression; 2) the reconciliation with
                    Tito and the Belgrade communiqué of last June; and 3) the President’s and the
                    Secretary’s clear statements at Geneva that the satellites would be watched as a
                    barometer of Soviet intentions. Nevertheless the Department has seen no proof of
                    any fundamental relaxation in the real bases of Soviet power in Poland, namely
                    Soviet Party, police and military controls, plus the overwhelming and encircling
                    strength of the USSR.</p>
                <p>Thus, even making allowances for the many reservations and qualifications with
                    which the British Ambassador has supported his analysis of present Soviet-Polish
                    relations, the Department cannot agree with his basic thesis that a definite
                    Polish policy independent of Moscow is now emerging.</p>
                <p>As indicated above, there are good reasons for both Moscow and Warsaw to
                    encourage the Free World in various ways to hope and believe that Polish foreign
                    and domestic policies are not controlled by Moscow and that the Polish
                    Communists are pursuing a Polish policy of gradual but basic liberalization.
                    Ambassador Winiewiez, for one, has long represented the Polish Government in
                    exactly this light with great tact and personal charm. Occasionally these
                    tactics bear fruit even with intelligent observers, as apparently occurred in
                    the case of Hugh Delargy’s judgment and interpretation of the activities and
                    motives of Boleslaw Piasecki (reference despatch 173 of November 22, 1955).<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d51fn5">In despatch 173, the Embassy referred to the view of
                        British Labor M.P. Hugh Delargy, who had visited Poland in November 1955 to
                        examine church–state relations, that Boleslaw Piasecki, a so-called Catholic
                        collaborator with the Polish Government, was a courageous and formidable
                        patriot. (Department of State, Central Files, 032/11–2255)</note> The
                    British Ambassador’s opinions and recommendations, on the other hand, may have
                    arisen not so much from a real misunderstanding of the situation in Poland as
                    from a hope of finding something a little more satisfying than simple
                    unqualified and “unconstructive” opposition to the Soviet and Polish Communist
                    authorities.</p>
                <p>However, the Department is by no means in agreement with the argument that there
                    is no alternative between accepting present Polish policy as independent or
                    semi-independent and, on the other hand, abandoning all attempts at flexibility
                    and maneuver and simply dismissing the Poles “as permanent vassals of the
                    Kremlin and therefore not worth much attention” (reference paragraph 7 of the
                    enclosure to <pb facs="0163" n="133" xml:id="pg_133"/> despatch 238 of January
                    10, 1956). The Department feels with Sir Andrew that the overwhelming majority
                    of Poles are still anti-Communist and deserving and potentially very useful
                    allies of the Free World (although continued Communist rule may change this
                    situation more rapidly than the Ambassador now foresees). Moreover, not only is
                    Poland the Soviet Union’s most important East European satellite, politically
                    and strategically, but it is also clear that American policy towards the Warsaw
                    regime is closely linked to our relations with the USSR and can affect and
                    influence these relations in many ways. For exactly this reason it is essential
                    that the shadow of the recent “thaw” in Poland not be accepted as the substance
                    of a genuine Soviet withdrawal.</p>
                <p>The Department has stated repeatedly that it is not reconciled to the continued
                    enslavement of Poland and other Eastern European countries by the USSR and
                    strenuous efforts are being made, and will be continued, to encourage as well as
                    to inform the Polish people despite the artificial barriers imposed by Moscow.
                    Developments in Poland will be followed and studied as closely and objectively
                    as possible and consolidation and extension of Communist power and prestige in
                    that country will be opposed within the limits, and by the methods, prescribed
                    by Soviet-Free World relations. Policy will be flexible but realistically based
                    on the main course of Communist performance and on the essentials of Communist
                    power rather than on its more superficial aspects or on the hope of luring the
                    present Polish Communist leaders away from Moscow by concessions or
                    “friendship”. The Department will be guided by the conviction that a firm and
                    realistic policy vis-à-vis Soviet rule in the satellites will eventually yield
                    more results than attempts at appeasement or cooperation with Polish
                    Communists.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, the Department believes that the situation in Poland is by no means
                    frozen and that it would be a mistake to adopt frozen attitudes which failed to
                    take cognizance of potential fluidity and any incipient signs and trends of
                    development favorable to the United States. It is a firm postulate of United
                    States foreign policy, confirmed at the highest level of this Government, to
                    seek to promote evolutionary changes in the policies and conduct of the Soviet
                    and satellite regimes which will be in United States interest. In so doing, it
                    will of course be desirable to influence these regimes toward the choice of
                    those alternative lines of action which, while in their national interests, do
                    not conflict with those of the United States. With respect to Poland this means
                    among other things that we should be ready to encourage and foster any bona fide
                    tendencies toward independence and national freedom from Moscow which may reveal
                    themselves in Party and official circles. As indicated above, we do not intend
                    to accept, or make concessions to, a sham independence nor do we intend to make
                        <pb facs="0164" n="134" xml:id="pg_134"/> concessions in the hope that the
                    Warsaw regime might some day seek independence from Moscow. But were there any
                    bona fide signs of a favorable development, we should of course shape our
                    actions in cognizance thereof.</p>
                <p>Also we believe that it would even be appropriate to take suitable actions in
                    hope of stimulating an independent Polish policy, insofar as such actions did
                    not represent concessions on our part nor serve to enhance the prestige of the
                    existing regime. We believe that the personal relations of our diplomatic
                    representatives with Polish officials may have a certain flexibility as a
                    consequence of this consideration.</p>
                <p>Thus, although the Department does not believe that the USSR is relinquishing any
                    basic controls in Poland, or is planning to do so in the future, it is apparent
                    that developments in Poland and Polish public opinion are factors to be taken
                    into consideration in determining American policy and that the continuation of
                    Soviet rule in Poland need not deprive American policy and Embassy activity of
                    all significance or flexibility.</p>
                <p>Some comments on various aspects of Polish-American relations touched upon in
                    recent Embassy communications are set forth below. It is hardly necessary to
                    point out that most of these cannot be regarded as hard and fast rules
                    applicable under all circumstances and must in the last analysis depend to a
                    very great degree upon the Embassy’s judgment of any given situation.</p>
                <gap/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> Broadcasts:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department is opposed to “softening” the content or tone of <gloss
                        target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> broadcasts to Poland in the hope that the
                    Polish Government might reduce or abandon jamming. Presumably the Polish
                    authorities would not sanction so extreme a measure unless <gloss
                        target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> programs were drastically altered and such a
                    change would be exceedingly difficult to explain or justify to Polish listeners.
                    At the same time the Polish Government would no longer bear the onus of jamming
                    and there would be a strong implication that similar changes were justified in
                    all <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> as well as <gloss target="#t_RFE1"
                        >RFE</gloss> and other Free World programs to Eastern Europe. Contrary to
                    Communist allegations, <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> Polish language
                    broadcasts do not indulge in simple vituperation and haranguing and they do give
                    recognition to postwar achievements in Poland, although these are rightly
                    attributed to the efforts and sacrifices of the Polish people rather than to
                    those of the Communist authorities. The present <gloss target="#t_VOA1"
                        >VOA</gloss> policy is to inform and encourage the Polish people, in
                    vigorous, expressive and explicit language, without deliberate misrepresentation
                    or incitement to open and fruitless resistance. Any fundamental and <pb
                        facs="0165" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/> genuine liberalization of Communist
                    controls in Poland would of course be duly praised and encouraged in <gloss
                        target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> broadcasts. But the Department feels it would
                    be extremely unwise to appear sensitive to Communist complaints and maneuvers
                    against <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss>, which constitute in a way the best
                    proof of its effectiveness.</p>
                <p>Present differences in subject matter and tone among <gloss target="#t_VOA1"
                        >VOA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_BBC1">BBC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_RFE1"
                        >RFE</gloss> and other Free World programs appear to have little
                    significance and are probably even desirable in that they afford the listener
                    some selection to suit his preference. However, it would unquestionably be
                    helpful for Moscow’s propaganda purposes if (as appears now in no way likely)
                        <gloss target="#t_BBC1">BBC</gloss> Polish broadcasts were sweetened to an
                    extent which would obviate Communist jamming.</p>
                <p>The Department is presently considering the advisability of increasing <gloss
                        target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> Polish-language broadcast time in view of
                    Poland’s relative importance in the Soviet system and in response to the
                    inauguration of Warsaw’s “Radio Kraj” service.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Exchange and Dissemination of Information:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There is no reason to believe that the tremendous disparity between information
                    available to this Government in Poland and to the Polish Government in America
                    will be overcome or even significantly modified within the near future.
                    Nevertheless the Department would prefer to maintain reciprocity in exchanges of
                    information through formal channels, and the Embassy should therefore continue
                    to refer official requests for Government publications or information of any
                    importance to Washington, even though the Embassy will usually be the channel of
                    ultimate distribution in Poland.</p>
                <p>Naturally this rule need not, and should not, be applied to all official
                    inquiries. Possibly it would have been both useful and appropriate for the
                    Embassy to provide or promise the Polish Press Agency representative mentioned
                    in Embassy despatch 57 of August 30, 1955<note n="6" xml:id="d51fn6">Not
                        printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 948.62/8–3055)</note> suitable
                    general unclassified data on American economic and cultural achievements.
                    Decisions in such cases must depend on the Embassy’s judgment of the particular
                    situation. In general, Iron Curtain countries should not be provided with
                    technical information or other useful data without securing some substantial
                    quid pro quo. On the other hand, it would seem desirable to furnish whatever
                    unclassified material is available in the Embassy including Government
                    publications, reflecting political or economic and social progress in America.
                    If no objection is perceived it is suggested that the Embassy resume sending
                    American publications directly to Polish addresses (reference despatch 76).</p>
                <pb facs="0166" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/>
                <p>The Embassy’s despatch 161 of November 8, 1955<note n="7" xml:id="d51fn7">Not
                        printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 024.648/11–855)</note> provided an
                    example of what appears to be a good opportunity for useful informational
                    activity. Possibly Polish material of some value could be obtained for the
                    American agricultural publications and dictionary, although reciprocity in such
                    cases would not be necessary.<note n="8" xml:id="d51fn8">The Department of
                        Agriculture states it forwarded the agricultural publications requested in
                        despatch 161 on March 26. [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                </p>
                <p>As regards private, informal requests for unclassified information, the
                    Department feels that they should not only be fulfilled by the Embassy whenever
                    feasible but that every appropriate opportunity should be utilized for the
                    casual distribution of suitable reading material. The Department was pleased to
                    note the Embassy’s work in this field as reported in despatches 186 of December
                    5, 1955<note n="9" xml:id="d51fn9">In despatch 186, the Embassy reported it was
                        providing American popular publications on a handout basis to persons who
                        could make the best use of them and who would pass them on to others.
                        (Department of State, Central Files, 511.482/12–555)</note> and 236 of
                    January 10, 1956<note n="10" xml:id="d51fn10">In despatch 236, the Embassy
                        requested guidance on the informal request of a Polish Foreign Ministry
                        official for a commercial showing of a Walt Disney film. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid</hi>., 511.485/11–1555)</note> and hopes that this type of
                    distribution can gradually be expanded.</p>
                <p>As the Embassy is aware the Polish Embassy in Washington conducts many
                    informational and propaganda activities, including the preparation and
                    distribution of press releases, the distribution of magazines, pamphlets and
                    books, and the promotion of exhibits depicting Polish cultural achievements. So
                    far as can be ascertained this propaganda work has enjoyed relatively little
                    success in America and rather than attempting to curtail it it is hoped that it
                    may serve as a justification, or if need be a bargaining point, for increasing
                    similar Embassy activity in Poland.</p>
                <p>To achieve this purpose it is believed that it would be preferable not to make a
                    formal request of the Polish authorities to reopen a <gloss target="#t_USIA1"
                        >USIA</gloss> office or library in Warsaw, at least at this time, but rather
                    to increase the Embassy’s informal activities in this line under circumstances
                    in which the Poles would find it awkward or embarrassing to protest. Perhaps it
                    would therefore be desirable to cease referring Polish inquirers to the Polish
                    Embassy in Washington because of the closure of Embassy informational activities
                    in 1951.</p>
                <p>For the Embassy’s information there is now being assembled an exhibit of some
                    100–150 carefully selected photographs taken in America during the last ten
                    years. Within the near future the Polish authorities will be asked to indicate
                    where and when the exhibit can be shown in Warsaw, Krakow and other cities. In
                    the event permission <pb facs="0167" n="137" xml:id="pg_137"/> is refused the
                    Department will consider the advisability of requesting, with suitable
                    publicity, the Polish Embassy to withdraw its exhibits from this country.</p>
                <p>A representative of the Museum of Modern Art has recently been discussing with
                    Soviet officials the possibility of sending an American art exhibit to Moscow
                    this year (reference Embassy telegram 353 of December 11, 1955).<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d51fn11">Not printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                        748.00/9–2856)</note> Thus far to the Department’s knowledge no decision has
                    been reached. It is quite possible that if the Polish Government agrees such an
                    exhibit would be sent to Warsaw following Moscow.</p>
                <p>Despatch 167 of November 15, 1955<note n="12" xml:id="d51fn12">Not printed. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 511.485/11–1555)</note> reported Polish
                    interest in showing <hi rend="italic">The Living Desert</hi>, a suggestion which
                    was properly referred to the Walt Disney Corporation in New York. The Department
                    should be advised of any future inquiries of this nature so that it may also, if
                    it wishes, get in touch with the American firm concerned. The Department is now
                    discussing the general subject of American pictures behind the Curtain with the
                    Motion Pictures Association.</p>
                <p>It is hoped that additional films will be forthcoming from the Department of
                    Agriculture and <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> (reference despatch 283 of
                    February 7, 1956). It may be desirable to prepare Polish sound tracks for two or
                    three of the most appropriate and request the Polish authorities to give them
                    wide popular distribution rather than restricting them to official and technical
                    circles.</p>
                <p>It had been hoped that more success would be achieved this year than last in
                    connection with an exhibit for the Poznan Fair. However, as the Embassy has
                    already been informed, it has not proved possible to complete arrangements for
                    American participation.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Exchange of Persons and Groups:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department hopes that any future exchanges of persons and groups will have
                    some relevance and advantage from our point of view and not lend themselves to
                    interpretation by Communist propaganda as indicative of relaxation of tension
                    and further recognition of the Polish Government and the status quo. For this
                    reason the Department would prefer to avoid exchanges on the official level and
                    to concentrate on private individuals and small groups in the fields of culture,
                    education, sports, etc. Obviously it will not be desirable to leave the
                    initiative in suggesting and selecting exchanges to the Polish Government, and
                    the possibilities of exploiting defections or Polish refusals to accept
                    invitations should be taken into account.</p>
                <pb facs="0168" n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/>
                <p>The Porgy and Bess visit to Poland appears to have served a useful purpose and
                    the Halina Czerny-Stefanska tour in America boomeranged against Warsaw to some
                    extent because of the protests and adverse publicity which arose when Communist
                    propaganda linked her performances with the Mickiewicz celebrations.</p>
                <p>The Department feels that any good effects of air force or military visits of the
                    type suggested by the British Ambassador would be more than offset by Polish
                    Communist propaganda exploitation designed to increase the prestige of the
                    Warsaw regime.</p>
                <p>Nor does the Department favor extending invitations to top ranking Polish
                    agricultural representatives to duplicate the visit of their Soviet
                    counterparts.</p>
                <p>The Department has no reliable information on what plans, if any, are being made
                    to bring the Mazowsze ensemble here.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Credits and Trade Restrictions:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Department is opposed to granting credits to Poland at the present time and
                    there seems to be little likelihood of a further relaxation of trade
                    restrictions within the near future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
