<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-04-12T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-04-12T12:00:00-05:00" n="53" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d53">
                        <head>53. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Legation in Hungary</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d53fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 764.00/4–51256. Confidential. Repeated to
                            Tehran.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Budapest</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-04-12T18:00:00+01:00">April 12, 1956—6
                                        p.m.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p>385. Legation strongly endorses Ambassador Chapin’s proposals to take
                            advantage Rajk trial disavowals<note n="2" xml:id="d53fn2">On March 27,
                                Rákosi announced that the case of Hungarian Communist leader Laszlo
                                Rajk, who was tried, found guilty, and executed in 1949 for
                                allegedly working for the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and
                                Yugoslav secret police, had been reviewed and Rajk was being
                                posthumously exonerated and rehabilitated.</note> to force issue re
                                Mindszenty,<note n="3" xml:id="d53fn3">József Cardinal Mindszenty,
                                Roman Catholic Archbishop of Esztergom and Prince-Primate of
                                Hungary, was arrested in Budapest on December 27, 1948, and charged
                                with attempting to overthrow the Hungarian state, treason, and
                                currency violations. Mindszenty along with six codefendents was
                                tried on February 3–4, 1949, found guilty, and sentenced to life
                                imprisonment.</note> to clear US Government officials involved in
                            those procedures and, through extension, to bring new pressure to bear
                            to gain release all Hungarian employees of Legation still imprisoned
                                (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 243).<note n="4" xml:id="d53fn4">In this telegram, April 6, the Department repeated
                                to Budapest Chapin’s proposals contained in telegram 1518 from
                                Tehran, April 3, and asked for the Legation’s comments. In his
                                telegram, Chapin wrote: “I suggest that by extension, case could now
                                be made for impugning entire procedure and testimony Mindszenty
                                trial, emphasizing the complete fabrication of alleged USG
                                involvement and calling for release of Cardinal. Stress might be put
                                on obvious inconsistency of allegations that US was involved at one
                                and same time in restoration Hapsburg Dynasty and working with Tito
                                re his Balkan Federation plans. As admitted by Rajk in his trial,
                                there might also be some propaganda value in requesting a retraction
                                of accusations in both trials made against me as American Minister
                                on evidence which at least in Rajk trial would seem admitted by
                                Hungarian Government to be falsified.” (Department of State, Central
                                Files, 746.00/4–356)</note></p>
                        <p>In Legation’s view situation obtaining here at moment is riper for
                            exploitation than it ever has been. Rakosi is clearly having his
                            difficulties. Whatever his standing in Moscow, he is facing mounting
                            antagonism from his old right wing opponents and growing opposition from
                            some of his late followers here and, with his personal prestige probably
                            at an all-time low, resulting situation is highly volatile. Moreover,
                            Rakosi’s Stalinist background, his unsavory record and his current
                            political acrobatics make him an extremely vulnerable target. A
                            carefully prepared diplomatic offensive with coordinated propaganda
                            exploitation could not only provide his opponents with valuable
                            ammunition but possibly even render his position untenable in eyes of
                            Moscow. Even failing latter objective, it would appear inadmissible for
                            US fail take total advantage opportunities now open for exacerbating
                            internal dissension and promoting already existing dissaffection towards
                            Rakosi.</p>
                        <pb facs="0178" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/>
                        <p>On international level, Legation also believes that Hungary today offers
                            US and west their most vulnerable target for purposes demonstrating to
                            world at large wide contradiction between what Communists are professing
                            and what practicing, and also real under-the-surface leaning of recent
                            tactical shifts. Case histories of what being carried out here with left
                            hand while right is distributing “peaceful coexistence” leaflets are so
                            striking as to present a most convincing picture if properly
                            exploited.</p>
                        <p>Above considerations prompted recommendations contained Legation
                            telegrams 374 and 375.<note n="5" xml:id="d53fn5">In telegrams 374 and
                                375, April 3 and 4, the Legation suggested using recent harassment
                                and arrest of Legation personnel by Hungarian secret police as the
                                basis of a protest to the Hungarian Government that these actions
                                were not in keeping with supposedly improving Hungarian-American
                                relations. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 120.162164/4–356 and
                                123–Tiedtke, Fred, respectively)</note> If moves suggested therein
                            were closely followed by presentation notes incorporating ideas
                            suggested by Chapin and whole offensive properly orchestrated, Legation
                            believes that great deal could be accomplished both on internal and
                            international levels. Legation strongly of opinion that, in any event,
                            Rakosi should not be permitted write end to Rajk affair at point he has
                            chosen and we hope, therefore, that Department will see its way clear to
                            move forward promptly in effort wring advantage from opportunities which
                            recent events have opened to US.</p>
                        <p>To be most effective, Chapin suggestions would appear require rather
                            careful research project to provide background for selection most
                            telling quotations, which due absence files here covering this period,
                            can probably be best done by Department.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Ravndal</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>