<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>75. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for International
                    Organization Affairs (Wilcox) to the ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-07-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-07-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rece9c3648fe9d1e98" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="mutual-security-program">Mutual Security Program</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-07-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-07-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="75"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d75">
                <head>75. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for International
                    Organization Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_WFO1" type="from">Wilcox</persName>)
                    to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d75fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 748.00/7–656. Confidential. Drafted by Elizabeth A. Brown (<gloss
                            target="#t_IOUNP1">IO/UNP</gloss>). Also sent to <persName
                            corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>; a note on the source text indicates
                        it was seen by <persName corresp="#p_HHCJ1">Hoover</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>. This memorandum is a reworking of a
                        previous memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> to
                            <persName corresp="#p_HHCJ1">Hoover</persName> through <persName
                            corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>, July 5, in which <persName
                            corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> argued against positive action in
                        the United Nations on Poznań on the grounds that many members would see it
                        as interference in Poland’s domestic affairs and would be reluctant to
                        involve themselves in essentially a propaganda issue where constructive
                        action was unlikely. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> suggested
                        the more limited approach of raising the issue in <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1"
                            >ECOSOC</gloss> and sending a note based on the <gloss
                            target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> statement to the <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> Secretary-General for distribution. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 748.00/7–556)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1956-07-06">July 6, 1956</date>
                        </hi>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Arguments Re <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Action on the Polish
                        Situation</item>
                </list>
                <p>Pursuant to your request, IO has examined the arguments that can be adduced with
                    respect to possible <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action on the Poznan
                    riots. As was indicated in our meeting with you today,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d75fn2">Apparent reference to the Acting Secretary’s Staff Meeting
                        of July 6, 9:15 a.m., during which the matter was briefly discussed. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., Secretary’s Staff Meetings: Lot 63 D 75) At
                        the Acting Secretary’s Staff Meeting of July 5, 9:15 a.m., IO was directed
                        to “prepare for the Secretary’s information a memorandum setting forth our
                        views with regard to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action on the Poznan
                        riots.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.)</note> the reasons why it is not
                    feasible to seek United Nations action at this time on the Polish situation are
                    more suitable for private discussion with members of the Congress most directly
                    interested in the Polish situation than for use in public statements. However,
                    should it become necessary for the Department to issue a public statement, I
                    believe we can reexamine the arguments and adapt them to this purpose.</p>
                <p>As you requested at our meeting, I am undertaking, in collaboration with <gloss
                        target="#t_H1">H</gloss>, to telephone certain key members of the Congress.
                    Following are the arguments that we plan to use with members of the Congress:
                        <pb facs="0228" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Article 2(7) of the Charter states that the United Nations is not
                            authorized to intervene in matters essentially within the domestic
                            jurisdiction of any state. A majority of Members, including the colonial
                            powers who desire to maintain intact the application of Article 2(7) to
                            colonial issues, could be expected to regard the Polish situation as
                            essentially a domestic problem. Their position would be modified only if
                            we could show conclusively that the situation in Poland actually
                            threatens international peace and security. Moreover, even if we could
                            successfully overcome their arguments in this instance, it would open
                            the way to requests from the Communist bloc and from the Afro-Asian
                            states to consider other matters also of a domestic character, such as
                            the Negro question in the United States, lynchings, or potentially
                            embarrassing domestic situations elsewhere. The Latin American states,
                            for example, frequently have to cope with mob action and would be
                            unlikely to favor any action suggesting <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                                >UN</gloss> competence in such cases.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Many Members are reluctant to have the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                                >UN</gloss> consider what they regard as propaganda issues in the
                            cold war on which no constructive action can be expected. They fear
                            that, if the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> deals with matters of
                            this character, its prestige will suffer and its ability to deal with
                            problems outside the East-West conflict may be reduced. At this time
                            particularly, even though the Geneva spirit is somewhat tarnished, it
                            would be extremely difficult to obtain support for what a majority of
                            Members would regard as a cold war maneuver.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>If we nevertheless succeeded in getting the Polish case before the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, we must anticipate a strong
                            counter-attack from the USSR and its satellites on the ground that the
                            US played a role itself in instigating the riots. Certain aspects of the
                            Mutual Security Program would be cited in support of this allegation.
                            Despite our ability to refute such baseless charges, <gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> discussion would create enough doubt to
                            deprive us of a decisive moral verdict.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>If we sought <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action unsuccessfully
                            or with inconclusive results, it could adversely affect continued US
                            support for the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. Indecisive <gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action might also give the USSR a
                            propaganda advantage in the present situation it would otherwise not
                            enjoy.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
