<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            Embassy in the United Kingdom</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1007</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1007</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-10-25T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-10-25T17:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-10-25T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-10-25T17:00:00-05:00" n="1007" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1007">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/10–2548: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-10-25T17:00:00-05:00">October 25, 1949—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3828. US continues favor incorporation Arab Pal in Jordan but Dept considers
                    action premature this time (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 3768 Oct
                        19<note n="1" xml:id="d1007fn1">Not printed; it summarized the conversation
                        of Messrs. Wilkins and Greenhill on October 14; see <ref target="#pg_1426">p. 1426</ref>.</note>). Re action after <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 4218 Oct 20<note n="2" xml:id="d1007fn2">Not printed; it conveyed what was described as the
                        impression of the British Foreign Office that the United States might be
                        “willing agree incorporation Arab Palestine in Jordan after <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.” (867N.014/10–2049)</note>) Dept believes
                    matter might be reconsidered then in light <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                    action re Pal and gen polit and econ developments in <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss>. We have discussed matter informally with <pb facs="1468" n="1452" xml:id="pg_1452"/> Brit Emb rep but made clear further
                    consideration depended on developments.<note n="3" xml:id="d1007fn3">Messrs.
                        Wilkins and Greenhill discussed the Palestine problem again on October 21.
                        The latter stated that “Adequate arrangements should be made for the safety
                        of the Holy Places and access to them.” Later in the discussion, he said
                        that “The United Kingdom was prepared to give general support to the
                        Palestine Conciliation Commission’s plan for the internationalization of the
                        Jerusalem area … It was not anxious, however, to take the initiative or to
                        bring pressure to bear on Israel or the Arab states with regard to the
                        plan.” He also stated that his Government would avoid discussing the
                        incorporation of Arab Palestine into Jordan during the current session of
                        the General Assembly but would wish such action realized at the end of the
                            session.<p>Mr. Wilkins’ memorandum of conversation notes that “I pointed
                            out that the views of the Foreign Office with regard to Jerusalem were
                            not completely clear to me. I said that if the United Kingdom Delegation
                            confined its remarks in the General Assembly to the safety of the Holy
                            Places and access to them, the impression might be created in the
                            General Assembly that the United Kingdom did not generally support the
                            internationalization of the Jerusalem area. Mr. Greenhill said this was
                            not the British intention and that he would bring this point to London’s
                            attention.”</p>
                        <p>Concerning the formal union of Arab Palestine and Jordan, Mr. Wilkins
                            writes that “I again pointed out that it was too early to tell what
                            action might be taken on this score as it would be necessary to await
                            developments in the General Assembly and to consider the situation in
                            the Near East after the end of the General Assembly before we would be
                            in a position to determine what action could be taken” regarding the
                            matter. (501.BB Palestine/10–2149)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
