<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Wells Stabler of the Office of African and
                    Near Eastern Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1019</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1019</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="1019"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1019">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/11–349</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Wells Stabler of the Office
                        of African and Near Eastern Affairs</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d1019fn1">Initialed by Mr. McGhee.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-03">November 3,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Boisanger, French Representative, <gloss target="#t_PCC1"
                                >PCC</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Yalcin, Turkish Representative, <gloss target="#t_PCC1"
                                >PCC</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Dr. Azcarate, Principal Secretary, <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. de la Tour du Pin, French Advisor</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Benard, First Secretary, French Embassy</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Esenbel, First Secretary, Turkish Embassy</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>—Mr. McGhee</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_UNA1">UNA</gloss>—Mr. Sandifer</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>—Mr. Bancroft</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Halderman</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_ANE1">ANE</gloss>—Mr. Berry</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Mattison</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Wilkins</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Rockwell</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Stabler</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Problem:</hi> To discuss with the French and Turkish
                    Representative on the Palestine Conciliation Commission the present and future
                    situation in connection with the Palestine problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Action Required:</hi> None</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Action Assigned to:</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_ANE1">ANE</gloss>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1482" n="1466" xml:id="pg_1466"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi> Mr. McGhee welcomed the members of the
                    Commission and said that he was glad to have the opportunity to exchange views
                    with them concerning present and future developments with respect to
                    Palestine.</p>
                <p>Mr. Boisanger said that the principal matter of concern to the Commission was the
                    Israeli note of October 27 and felt that the Commission should make an
                    unequivocal reply to that note refuting the assertions made by Israel. He
                    mentioned that the Commission had received a telegram today from the United
                    Nations Press Representative in Jerusalem indicating that the Israeli Government
                    had stated that the note did not mean that Israel refused further negotiations
                    with the Commission. However, it was necessary for the Commission to make a
                    definite reply in order that there should be no misunderstanding. Mr. McGhee
                    said he agreed with this point of view.</p>
                <p>Mr. McGhee then suggested it was desirable that the Commission should make
                    continued efforts to urge the parties to undertake direct talks. He understood
                    that the American representatives on the Commission had themselves urged these
                    direct talks and assumed the Commission as a whole believed that such talks
                    would be desirable. Mr. Boisanger said that he agreed that direct talks were
                    desirable but pointed out that while the Commission should insist on direct
                    talks, there was nothing in the December 11 Resolution which obliged the parties
                    to undertake such talks. He felt that the Arabs because of their previous firm
                    stand would be unwilling to enter into direct talks. He also pointed out that
                    previous experience indicated that when the Arabs and Israelis did get together
                    for direct talks they were not successful. Mr. Bunche and Mr. Vigier had stated
                    that from their experience it was always necessary for a third party to be
                    present. However, both Mr. Boisanger and Mr. Yalcin agreed that it would be most
                    desirable to urge the parties to meet together with the Commission and the
                    Commission intended to pursue its efforts in this connection.</p>
                <p>Mr. McGhee said that we fully understood the difficulties involved but felt that
                    every effort should be made along these lines.</p>
                <p>Mr. Boisanger then referred to the statement made by the Arabs that they felt
                    conciliation had failed and therefore wished the Commission to undertake
                    mediation. The Commission proposed to inform the Israelis of this view and to
                    ask whether Israel would agree to mediation. He indicated that Israel feared
                    that the Commission might produce a new plan which might deprive them of
                    territory which they now held. However, he believed that it was desirable to
                    establish at least the principle of mediation and he felt that Israel, if it
                    refused mediation in principle would be placed in a very bad moral position with
                    respect to the United Nations. Mr. Boisanger considered that there were a number
                    of points on which mediation could take place <pb facs="1483" n="1467"
                        xml:id="pg_1467"/> without at the outset going into the more difficult
                    questions. Mr. Yalcin wondered whether the United States Government would have
                    the patience to bear with the mediation since this course of action would
                    undoubtedly take a very long time.</p>
                <p>Mr. McGhee said that he agreed that the Commission should inform the Israelis of
                    the Arab desire for mediation and also felt that if Israel refused, it would
                    place itself in a bad light. He suggested that there were a number of smaller
                    matters which could be dealt with through mediation and suggested that the
                    question of Mount Scopus might be one of them.</p>
                <p>Mr. Sandifer indicated his belief that the Commission could undertake the
                    mediation functions in that the Commission was empowered to conciliate which was
                    a broader concept than mediation. It was pointed out that under the General
                    Assembly Resolution of December 11, 1948 the Palestine Conciliation Commission
                    had, in any event, inherited Count Bernadotte’s mediation functions under the
                    General Assembly Resolution of May 14, 1948.</p>
                <p>Mr. McGhee then explained briefly our views on the proposed organization of
                    United Nations functions with respect to the Palestine case and indicated our
                    belief that it was desirable to have a United Nations coordinating agent who
                    could ensure that the three operating groups, <gloss target="#t_PCC1"
                        >PCC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_UNRPR1">UNRPR</gloss>, and <gloss
                        target="#t_NEDA1">NEDA</gloss> were functioning in unison. Since all the
                    questions involved in the Palestine problem are inter-related, it is desirable
                    that the three groups be coordinated. Mr. McGhee emphasized that these plans are
                    entirely tentative.</p>
                <p>Mr. Boisanger said that he was in general agreement with the proposed
                    organization but felt it very important that in the General Assembly no
                    substantive questions be raised. In this connection, he felt that the <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> should remain as it is in order that its terms
                    of reference under the December 11 Resolution would remain the same. With
                    respect to <gloss target="#t_NEDA1">NEDA</gloss> he said that he was worried by
                    the possibility that Russia could join the organization. Mr. Yalcin expressed
                    the same concern. It was explained that <gloss target="#t_NEDA1">NEDA</gloss>
                    would be formed by the participating governments and additional membership could
                    be limited by those governments. It could be assumed, therefore, that the
                    Governments concerned would not permit Russia to join. Mr. Yalcin pointed out
                    that if the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> consisted of representatives of
                    Governments, it would not be possible for the United Nations Coordinating Agent
                    to instruct the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> on political matters.</p>
                <p>Mr. McGhee said that we agreed that it was desirable to limit the debate in the
                    General Assembly to procedural matters if possible and we felt that the proposed
                    resolution on organization could confine the debate.</p>
                <pb facs="1484" n="1468" xml:id="pg_1468"/>
                <p>Mr. McGhee then said that we were considerably worried by the lack of security in
                    the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> and we had been embarrassed by the fact
                    that every time the United States representative made a statement, it was made
                    available to the press. He felt that the Commission should address itself to
                    this problem and if necessary could obtain a completely new staff. Mr. Yalcin
                    emphasized that in any case this lack of security could not be attributed to Dr.
                    Azcarate, Principal Secretary of the Commission. Mr. McGhee responded that he
                    was not accusing anybody but he felt it was a matter to be dealt with.</p>
                <p>The discussion then turned to the question of Jerusalem. Mr. McGhee informed
                    Messrs. Boisanger and Yalcin that the United States gave its general support to
                    the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> proposals for an international regime in
                    Jerusalem. However, we realized that amendments would be offered and we would be
                    prepared to consider them in the light of their individual merits in
                    contributing to the workability and acceptability of the plan. Mr. Boisanger and
                    Mr. Yalcin expressed agreement with this point of view and said their
                    delegations in New York shared the same view. Mr. Boisanger expressed the hope
                    that it would be possible for the United States, French and Turkish delegations
                    in New York to meet prior to the General Assembly consideration of the various
                    Palestine problems in order to coordinate their action. Mr. McGhee said he
                    thought this would be useful.</p>
                <p>Mr. Boisanger hoped that it would be possible to enlist the assistance of the
                    Chairman of Committee I in confining the discussion in Committee I to
                    consideration of such procedural resolutions which may be presented. He
                    expressed the view that the resolutions should not be too detailed. He said that
                    all delegates, of course, would have to be heard but that after they made their
                    speeches he hoped it would be possible for the Chairman of the Committee to
                    channel further debate into consideration of the resolutions.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
