<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Yugoslavia (
                        Cannon
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d179</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">179</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-06-09T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-06-09T17:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-06-09T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-09T17:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860H.00/6–949: Telegram</note>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]<note n="1" xml:id="d179fn1">For full text of
                            this telegram, see <ref target="frus1949v05#pg_896">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 896</ref>.</note>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Yugoslavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cannon</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Belgrade</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-06-09T23:00:00+01:00">June 9, 1949—11 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>577. Had more than two hours with Kardelj<note n="2" xml:id="d179fn2">Edvard
                        Kardelj, Yugoslav Minister for Foreign Affairs; member of the Politburo of
                        the Yugoslav Communist Party.</note> and Bebler<note n="3" xml:id="d179fn3">Aleš Bebler, Yugoslav Assistant Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note>
                    yesterday reviewing internal and external affairs. Kardelj’s chief points:</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Greece: With rebels now hostile to Yugoslavia material aid is not going over. I
                    pressed him hard for more details. What about logistical advantages? Harboring,
                    re-outfitting and returning escaped rebels? Perhaps individual frontier
                    authorities are still doing more than Belgrade intends? He did not deny aid in
                    past but “now it’s all different.” I found this part not very forthright. He
                    seemed unhappy and sick of Greek involvement and rather lamely said “perhaps
                    something ‘will come of Gromyko’s proposal.” He did not refer to last week’s
                    charge that <gloss target="#t_GNA1">GNA</gloss> had air strafed Yugoslav village
                    even though in order to prod him I led close to it. I made a little speech about
                    contradiction in our disposition to aid Yugoslavia when Yugoslavia works against
                    Greek independence. He said “but we have no friends there any more” and started
                    talking about Hungary again. He made no mention whatever of Macedonia (which as
                    already reported Yugoslavia thinks it has in hand).<note n="4" xml:id="d179fn4">According to a June 14, 1949, entry in his diary, <hi rend="italic">New
                            York Times</hi> chief foreign correspondent Cyrus L. Sulzberger was
                        shown a copy of this telegram by Ambassador Cannon in Paris (Cyrus L.
                        Sulzberger, <hi rend="italic">A Long Row of handles: Memoirs and Diaries
                            1934–1954</hi> (The Macmillan Company, 1969), p. 448.) During a call at
                        the Department of State on June 16, Greek Ambassador Dendramis was apprised
                        of the substance of the Greek portion of this telegram. On June 22 Greek
                        Minister Counselor Economou-Gouras called at the Department of State to
                        express the great appreciation of the Greek Foreign Ministry for Ambassador
                        Cannon’s action in speaking with Kardelj and Bebler of the question of
                        Yugoslav aid to the Greek guerrillas (memorandum of conversation by Cromie,
                        June 22: 868.00/6–2249).</note> …</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cannon</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
