<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in Yugoslavia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d203</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">203</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-08-11T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-08-11T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-08-11T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-08-11T16:00:00-05:00" n="203"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d203">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">760H.68/8–1149: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Yugoslavia</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d203fn1">Repeated to Athens as 1273, London as 2860, Paris
                        as 2980, and Moscow as 575.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-08-11T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 11, 1949—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>450. Reurtel 755 Aug 4. Dept appreciates Yugo must act with caution in moving
                    toward closer relations with Greece. Accordingly, timing of attempts to
                    encourage that evolution and apply pressure left to your judgment. Bebler’s
                    receptive attitude on opening railway to Salonika and on free zones indicates
                    time may be ripe for Grk approach to Yugo on those subjects. Grk Emb here has
                    been informed Yugo <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> showed interest and
                    favorable attitude as reported <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 755. Grk
                    Emb believes railway line in running order on Grk side. Athens pls confirm.</p>
                <p>Recently completed <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> report to fourth
                    session <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>,<note n="2" xml:id="d203fn2">Regarding
                        the Report of the United Nations Special Committee on the Balkans to the
                        Fourth Session of the General Assembly, see the second editorial note, <ref
                            target="#pg_379">p. 379</ref>.</note> which bears down hard on Alb and
                    Bulg while stating Yugo aid “has diminished and may have ceased”, makes possible
                        <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> recommendations next month
                    differentiating between Yugo on one hand and Alb and Bulg on other. You may be
                    able get from <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> indication re line Yugo
                    intends to pursue in <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> discussions on Grk
                    question (re Athens tel 1553 Aug 6 <gloss target="#t_Combal1">Combal</gloss>
                        466<note n="3" xml:id="d203fn3">Not printed; it reported that a Yugoslav
                        official had told an <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> official of
                        Yugoslavia’s great dissatisfaction with the activities of the Special
                        Committee (501.BB. Balkan/8–649).</note>) and prospects for normalization
                    Grk-Yugo relations before or during <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> session.
                    Some concrete progress this direction wld be helpful to <gloss
                        target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> in handling Greek case <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>You will recall that in UN conciliation talks last year Evatt proposed draft
                    Grk-Yugo declaration Dec 1, 1948 which Yugo turned down on ground matter cld not
                    be considered alone but only as part of entire problem involving also Alb and
                    Bulg, and Northern Epirus question blocked Grk-Alb accord (See <gloss
                        target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1527 Dec 11, 1948 and H. N. Howard memo
                    of March 10, 1949 on conciliation talks, Appendix XIV, pouched to you<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d203fn4">Neither printed. For authoritative accounts of the
                        preparation of the draft declaration under reference, see the articles cited
                        in footnote 4 to telegram 308, <gloss target="#t_Combal1">Combal</gloss>
                        368, February 19, from Athens, <ref target="#pg_254">p. 254</ref>.</note>).
                    You might inquire of Yugos whether consideration for Alb and Bulg position which
                    held up their consent last year has same weight now. You may say that US
                    believes Yugo-Grk agreement on lines Dec 1 draft wld be sound basis for
                    stabilizing frontier, to advantage both states, and for more normal relations in
                    future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
