<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="332" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d332">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">891.77/11–1849</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation by, the Secretary of
                                    State</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d332fn1">Drafted by Mr.
                                    Jernegan.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-18">November 18,
                                        1949</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Request by the Shah of Iran for Help in
                                Obtaining Railroad Equipment</p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell>The Shah of Iran</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Hussein Ala, Iranian Ambassador</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>The Secretary of State</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Willard Thorp, Assistant Secretary for Economic
                                        Affairs</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>George C. McGhee, Assistant Secretary for Near Eastern,
                                        South Asian, and African Affairs</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>John D. Jernegan, Director, Office of Greek, Turkish, and
                                        Iranian Affairs</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <pb facs="0597" n="581" xml:id="pg_581"/>
                            <p>The Shah opened the conversation by saying that he was most anxious
                                to obtain promptly locomotives, freight cars and rails to meet the
                                immediate transport crisis in Iran. He was told that we had already
                                made some inquiries with respect to locomotives and understood a
                                large number in used condition were readily available. He replied
                                that unfortunately these locomotives were not of the right type for
                                use in Iran and, furthermore, they were not new. His Government had
                                made inquiries in Germany and elsewhere and had found that new
                                locomotives could be produced in Germany in about ten months, but
                                Iran could not wait that long. He hoped that it would be possible to
                                get quicker delivery in the United States. The rolling stock was
                                needed in three or four months.</p>
                            <p>The Department’s representatives indicated that it would be very
                                difficult to obtain new rolling stock in so short a time, especially
                                in view of the fact that orders for steel were probably backing up
                                as a result of the recent steel strike.</p>
                            <p>The Shah then asked whether it would be possible to obtain credit
                                from the Export-Import Bank to finance whatever transaction might be
                                arranged. In reply to a question he said that the Iranian
                                authorities had not yet approached the bank. Mr. Thorp said that he
                                saw no fundamental objection to an Export-Import Bank credit in this
                                connection but he thought Iran would be well advised first to look
                                to the International Bank for help. It was pointed out that the
                                International Bank liked to make loans of this type and had in fact
                                recently extended a credit to India for the precise purpose of
                                buying railroad rolling stock. Mr. Thorp said that the Department of
                                State would be able to give strong support to an Iranian request for
                                an International Bank credit for purchase of the equipment in
                                question. The Shah indicated that he would consider the suggestions
                                regarding the means of financing the transaction but said that this
                                was not the most important aspect of the question; the essential
                                element was the time within which the equipment could be made
                                available.</p>
                            <p>It was agreed that the Department would make every effort to locate
                                locomotives, freight cars and rails of the sort which the Iranian
                                Government wished to obtain.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>