<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-02T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-02T09:00:00-05:00" n="344" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d344">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/1–249: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Special Representative of the United States in
                                    Israel</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McDonald</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <dateline>
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tel Aviv</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-02T16:00:00+02:00">January 2,
                                    1949—4 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p>3. Following verbatim text statement issued by Foreign Office on
                                December 31:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“It is a month and a half since Egypt and Israel were ordered by
                                    the Security Council to enter into armistice negotiations.
                                    Israel accepted immediately, thus once more affirming its desire
                                    to make peace without delay. The Egyptian Government not only
                                    ignored the Security Council resolution, but renewed their
                                    military activities in the Negev. They shelled Nirim, Mivtachim
                                    and Imara, captured and occupied certain fresh heights, such as
                                    Tel-el-Jamah, Tel-el-Farah and Kirbet Kutshan, carried out
                                    widespread sabotage against roads and water installations in the
                                    area, and launched armored attacks on Israeli positions and
                                    settlements, using tanks which had newly arrived from Egypt.
                                    These were the subject repeated complaints by the Israeli
                                    authorities to UN observer to no avail. These Egyptian
                                    activities, covered by delaying tactics regarding an armistice,
                                    went on for weeks.</p>
                                <p>When Egypt finally indicated its acceptance in principle of the
                                    armistice resolution, it coupled this with conditions which the
                                    resolution did not justify. The Acting Mediator, Dr.
                                        Bunche,<note n="1" xml:id="d344fn1">Ralph J. Bunche, United
                                        Nations Acting Mediator on Palestine.</note> then made
                                    certain proposals whereby the Egyptian forces at Faluja could be
                                    evacuated in stages concurrently with armistice talks. Once
                                    again the Israeli Government accepted these proposals, and its
                                    attitude was officially described by Dr. Bunche as highly
                                    satisfactory. The Egyptian commanders pretended at first that
                                    they were willing to cooperate, but when General Riley<note n="2" xml:id="d344fn2">Brig. Gen. William E. Riley, United
                                        Nations Chief of Staff charged with supervision of the truce
                                        in Palestine and senior United States military observer in
                                        Palestine.</note> went to Cairo to arrange a time and a
                                    place for an armistice meeting, and to obtain the name of the
                                    Egyptian representative, the Egyptian Government reverted to its
                                    earlier uncompromising attitude, thereby recreating the
                                    deadlock. It appears that the resolution on Palestine adopted in
                                    the meantime by the UN General Assembly, and the failure of the
                                    Security Council to approve Israel’s application for membership
                                    of the UN,<note n="3" xml:id="d344fn3">See footnote 3, <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. 1, Part
                                        2, p. 1677.</note> had encouraged Egypt to revive its
                                    intransigence. The refusal of Egypt to enter into armistice
                                    negotiations could have no other meaning than that it was set on
                                    the prosecution of the war. Faced with the choice between
                                    embarking on a course leading to peace or pursuing further the
                                    line of aggressive invasion, Egypt chose the latter. Israel
                                    could not possibly acquiesce in a situation exposing its safety
                                    and territorial integrity to an ever present menace and
                                    compelling it to carry in definitely the burdens of war
                                    readiness. The attacks perpetrated by Egyptian forces against
                                    Israeli positions at every convenient opportunity as well as the
                                    flow from Egypt of fresh men and equipment <pb facs="0614" n="598" xml:id="pg_598"/> left no doubt as to the intentions
                                    of the Egyptian Government. Under those circumstances, not only
                                    the release of the Egyptian brigade encircled at Faluja was
                                    inconceivable, but the Government of Israel found itself
                                    constrained to resume its freedom of action in order once and
                                    for all to put an end to the intolerable situation and stabilize
                                    Israel’s security. It was Egypt’s choice that determined
                                    Israel’s action. In the course of that action, as in any war,
                                    only military considerations decided the fixing of the
                                    establishment of positions. The new facts created in that regard
                                    need not determine the final territorial settlement which awaits
                                    the conclusion of permanent peace between Israel and her
                                    neighbors.</p>
                                <p>For such a final and lasting peace settlement the Government of
                                    Israel is ever ready, in the firm conviction that the sooner it
                                    is achieved, the better it will be for all concerned.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">McDonald</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>