<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="384" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d384">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">IO Files</note>
                            <note n="1" xml:id="d384fn1">Master files of the Reference and Documents
                                Section of the Bureau of International Organization Affairs.</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Message Released by the United Nations Security
                                    Council on January 13, 1949</hi>
                            </head>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-13">January 13, 1949</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/1205</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Cablegram Dated</hi> 12 <hi rend="smallcaps">January</hi> 1949 <hi rend="smallcaps">From the Acting Mediator
                                    to the Secretary-General Transmitting a Report to the President
                                    of the Security Council Concerning the Opening of Negotiations
                                    Between Egypt and the Provisional Government of Israel</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>For transmission to President of Security Council:</p>
                            <p>I have the honour to inform you, pursuant to my Report of 6
                                    January<note n="2" xml:id="d384fn2">See editorial note, <ref target="#pg_621">p. 621</ref>.</note> on the agreement of
                                Egypt and Israel, to order a cease fire in the Negev and to
                                undertake negotiations on the 4 and 16 November resolutions, that
                                the first stage in the negotiations between representatives of the
                                two Governments on the implementation of these resolutions was
                                reached today, 12 January, with the arrival in Rhodes of both the
                                Egyptian and Israeli delegations. The Egyptian delegation, headed by
                                Colonel Mohamed Ibrahim Seif el Dine, arrived at Rhodes early in the
                                afternoon and the Israeli delegation, headed by Dr. W. Eytan<note n="3" xml:id="d384fn3">Walter Eytan, Director General of the
                                    Israeli Foreign Office.</note> arrived later in the afternoon.
                                Both delegations are empowered to negotiate, conclude and initial an
                                armistice agreement, subject to its final ratification by their
                                respective Governments.</p>
                            <p>I have today met each delegation separately and discussed with them
                                questions of procedure and agenda for subsequent joint discussions.
                                I <pb facs="0666" n="650" xml:id="pg_650"/> shall hold further
                                meetings with each delegation tomorrow morning, 13 January, and the
                                first joint meeting under United Nations chairmanship is fixed for
                                3:30 p. m. on the same day. These preliminary meetings have been
                                encouraging in that both delegations have evinced a sincere desire
                                for a successful outcome of the discussions and a readiness to reach
                                with as little delay as possible discussion of substantive
                                matters.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>