<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Iraq ( (Dorsz) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d475</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">475</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-02-20T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-02-20T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-20T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-20T04:00:00-05:00" n="475"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d475">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/2–2049: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Iraq</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dorsz</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Baghdad</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-20T12:00:00+03:00"
                            >February 20, 1949—noon</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>71. After delivering <hi rend="italic">note verbale</hi> (<gloss
                        target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 70, February 20<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d475fn1">Not printed; it stated that Foreign Minister Hafidh had
                        handed the note to Chargé Dorsz on the morning of February 20 (501.BB
                        Palestine/2–2049). The two main points of the note are embodied in comments
                        numbered 5(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) in
                        telegram 71. <p>On February 23, Foreign Minister Hafidh handed a similar <hi
                                rend="italic">note verbale</hi> to the British Ambassador and
                            expressed the hope that the United Kingdom, in concert with the United
                            States, would do everything possible to force Israel to accept the
                            return of the refugees. He noted that the Arab States had met at Cairo
                            on February 5 and had agreed to ask for such British assurances. The
                            point concerning Jerusalem as an Arab city was an Iraqi idea not cleared
                            with the other Arab States. Little effort was made to “sell” this point,
                            (telegram 72, February 24, 11 a. m., from Baghdad, 501.BB
                            Palestine/2–2449)</p>
                    </note>) which he said Prime Minister asked him hand to me, Foreign Minister
                    made comments along following lines: (1) <gloss target="#t_UNPCC1">UNPCC</gloss>
                    wanted Iraq Government <pb facs="0774" n="758" xml:id="pg_758"/> express its
                    views re conditions for Israel prepared go towards reaching settlement or what
                    steps would be taken to make Israel abide by settlement; (2) before expressing
                    its views, Iraq Government feels that some practical action designed enforce
                    compliance by Israel of such settlement as may be reached must be worked out;
                    (3) UN resolutions have time and again been violated by Israel. Instead taking
                    measures to enforce resolutions, big powers and particularly US have looked
                    aside and helped Jews through such acts as extension <hi rend="italic">de
                        jure</hi> recognition, sponsoring Israel admission to UN, granting of huge
                    loan, etc; (4) in these circumstances, Arabs have lost confidence in US
                    contention it sincerely desires create conditions in Middle East favorable to
                    restoration of stability and security this area; (5) US could improve situation
                    immeasurably by proving its “good faith towards Arabs” by putting pressure on
                    Israel to accept principles re (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) right refugees return
                    to Palestine and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Jerusalem remain Arab city; (6)
                    unless US Government makes Israel accept these principles, Arab world will
                    continue drifting towards chaos from which only Communists can profit; (7) Iraq
                    Government therefore hopes US will give assurances desired as this would help
                    Arab Governments in their efforts to overcome deep and intense feeling against
                    US now prevailing Arab world and enable Arab Governments working constructively;
                    (8) other Arab Governments are expected make similar representations to US and
                    British Governments; and (9) identical note verbale would be delivered British
                    Embassy.</p>
                <p>I mentioned that UN resolution December 11 which created <gloss
                        target="#t_UNPCC1">UNPCC</gloss> contained principle that refugees who
                    desire should have right return to their homes in Palestine. Foreign Minister
                    said this was not good enough; Jews had previously violated other resolutions
                    and had exhibited no intention accepting this principle in December 11
                    resolution. Iraq therefore wants US show good faith by giving desired
                    assurances; otherwise Iraq must assume US trying avoid direct responsibility of
                    seeing that Jews abide by resolutions.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister made it plain that any reference by US for Arabs to look to UN
                    for enforcement of resolution would not be constructive suggestion but merely
                    another indication of US unwillingness to assume necessary responsibility of
                    trying rectify to some extent great injustice Arabs claim US has been chiefly
                    instrumental in imposing upon them.<note n="2" xml:id="d475fn2">Marginal
                        notation in the handwriting of Mr. McClintock: “what
                        responsibility?”.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Department 71, repeated Amman for <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> 3, Beirut 23, Damascus 13, London 28,
                    Jerusalem 3, Tel Aviv 3, Cairo 21, Jidda 4.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dorsz</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
