<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Coordinator on Palestine Refugee
                        Matters (
                        McGhee
                    )In this position, Mr. McGhee served as
                        Special Assistant to the Secretary of State.
                    to the Under Secretary of State (
                        Webb
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d533</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">533</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-03-15T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="533" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d533">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/3–1549</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Coordinator on Palestine Refugee
                        Matters</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McGhee</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d533fn1">In this position, Mr. McGhee served as
                        Special Assistant to the Secretary of State.</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Webb</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-15">March 15,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Attached are policy recommendations with respect to Palestine refugees, together
                    with a supporting policy paper which contains on page 20 a statement of
                    recommended planning objectives.<note n="2" xml:id="d533fn2">These papers are
                        printed as Annexes 1 and 2, below. The planning objectives on page 20 are
                        the 10 recommendations in Annex 2.</note> These have been approved by Mr.
                    Rusk, who hopes that they can be discussed at your regular staff meeting at the
                    earliest opportunity.</p>
                <p>Since I plan to leave for Beirut the morning of March 17, I would like to discuss
                    this paper with you tomorrow, together with proposed plan of action and planning
                    with respect to the refugee problem which are dealt with in papers attached.</p>
                <p>After you have given consideration to these papers, I hope then to be able to
                    discuss them with the Secretary, who has indicated his willingness to do so and
                    to advise me of the President’s views with respect to this matter.<note n="3" xml:id="d533fn3">Filed with this memorandum is an undated memorandum,
                        prepared presumably by Mr. McGhee and entitled Plan of Action [regarding]
                        Palestine Refugee Problem,” not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex 1]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Coordinator on Palestine Refugee
                            Matters</hi> (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">McGhee</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-15">March 15,
                                1949</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Policy Recommendations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>It is recommended that: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>It be recognized as in the national interest of the United States
                                that an early and effective solution be found to the problem of the
                                Palestine refugees. Such solution should make possible their
                                repatriation or resettlement in such a manner as to minimize present
                                and potential political and economic tensions prejudicial to United
                                States interests in the area affected.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>The United States be prepared to contribute such technical and
                                financial assistance to the solution of this problem as it considers
                                necessary, while at the same time refusing to accept sole
                                responsibility for solution of the problem and seeking to confine
                                U.S. financial assistance thereto within limits consistent with its
                                national interests.</item>
                            <pb facs="0844" n="828" xml:id="pg_828"/>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>A plan be developed as a matter of urgency for the implementation
                                of this policy, including proposals for relief, rehabilitation, and
                                long-range resettlement projects, estimated costs, and expected
                                sources of funds, and operational procedures, including the part to
                                be played by the U.S., the governments in the affected area, other
                                interested governments, and the United Nations.<note n="4" xml:id="d533fn4">According to a memorandum of April 21, the
                                    numbered paragraphs were accepted as a “Policy Decision, March
                                    15, 1949.” The authorship of the memorandum is not indicated
                                    (867N.48/4–2249). The word “be” in each of the first two
                                    paragraphs above was changed to “is” in the memorandum of April
                                    21 and the word “should” was added as the third word in
                                    paragraph 3.</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex 2]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_MA1">MA</gloss>
                        Palestine/3–1749</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Policy Paper Prepared in the Department of State</hi>
                        <note n="5" xml:id="d533fn5">The specific authorship of this paper is not
                            indicated. The first six sections, except for 6(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>), and the 10 recommendations at the end of the paper were
                            largely quoted from memoranda prepared separately by the Office of Near
                            Eastern and African Affairs and the Office of United Nations Affairs.
                            The former was sent to Mr. McGhee in a memorandum of March 12 by Mr.
                            Satterthwaite as provisional views on “Policy and recommendations
                            concerning solution of the Arab refugee question” (867N.01/3–1249). The
                            latter was in the form of a memorandum by Mr. McClintock to Mr. McGhee
                            on March 14 and dealt with the “Attitudes of UN, individual governments,
                            and refugees themselves toward Palestine refugee problem”
                            (867N.48/3–1449). The Policy Paper begins with a table of contents, here
                            omitted.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-15">March 15,
                                1949</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Palestine Refugees</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the problem</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The problem is to determine the nature and extent of United States interest
                        in the question of some 725,000 Arab refugees from the Palestine
                        hostilities, and in the light of the findings, to make recommendations
                        concerning United States policy towards the long-range disposition of this
                        question.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">discussion</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Background:</hi> As a result of hostilities in
                        Palestine preceding land following the termination of the British Mandate
                        and establishment of the State of Israel on May 15, 1948, almost the entire
                        Arab population of Palestine fled or was expelled from the area under Jewish
                        occupation. These Arabs, now estimated at 725,000, took refuge in
                        Arab-controlled areas of Palestine and in the neighboring Arab states. The
                        present distribution of the refugees is approximately the following: <pb facs="0845" n="829" xml:id="pg_829"/>
                        <table cols="12" rows="11">
                            <row>
                                <cell>Lebanon</cell>
                                <cell role="num">100,000-</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>an</cell>
                                <cell>addition</cell>
                                <cell>of</cell>
                                <cell>10–</cell>
                                <cell>10.5%</cell>
                                <cell>to</cell>
                                <cell>the</cell>
                                <cell>normal</cell>
                                <cell>population</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">105,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Syria</cell>
                                <cell role="num">85,000–</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>3.5–</cell>
                                <cell>4%</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">100,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>TransJordan</cell>
                                <cell role="num">85,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>21%</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Iraq</cell>
                                <cell role="num">5,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>0.1%</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Egypt</cell>
                                <cell role="num">8,000–</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>0.04–</cell>
                                <cell>0.05%</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                                <cell>“</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">10,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Palestine</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell> North</cell>
                                <cell role="num">230,000</cell>
                                <cell role="brace" rows="2">}</cell>
                                <cell cols="7" rows="2">areas under Egyptian, Iraqi, and
                                    Transjordanian military occupation</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell> South</cell>
                                <cell role="num">225,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>No accurate statistical breakdown of the refugees exists. However, the
                        International Children’s Emergency Fund considers 425,000 or 58% of the
                        refugees eligible for assistance under its program: this group consists of
                        infants, young children, pregnant women, and nursing mothers. Approximately
                        15% of the refugees are aged, sick, and infirm. It would appear that the
                        able-bodied men and women amount to a maximum of 25 percent of the total, or
                        180,000.</p>
                    <p>The condition of these refugees, dependent upon their own slender resources
                        and upon those of the neighboring states, rapidly became acute. Since the
                        Government of Israel refused to permit repatriation of Arab refugees into
                        Israeli territory while a state of war existed, and since relief assistance
                        enlisted by the United Nations Mediator for Palestine in August was wholly
                        inadequate to meet a problem of this magnitude, the Mediator referred the
                        problem to the General Assembly in September, with a renewed appeal for
                        assistance. This appeal was reiterated by the Acting Mediator in a report to
                        the United Nations on October 18, 1948,<note n="6" xml:id="d533fn6">United
                            Nations, <hi rend="italic">Official Records of the General Assembly,
                                Third Session</hi>, Supplement No. 11A. For the proposed United
                            States draft resolution based on the needs of the refugees as set forth
                            in this report, see telegram <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss>
                            411, October 20, 1948, from Paris, <ref target="frus1948v05p2#pg_1497">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, Part 2, p. 1497</ref>.</note> in which
                        he made recommendations for the establishment of a United Nations relief
                        program for assistance to the refugees.</p>
                    <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Action taken up to present</hi>.</p>
                    <p>In response to the Mediator’s initial request in August for emergency
                        supplies, the Department’s only recourse, in the absence of authorized
                        public funds, was to appeal to American voluntary agencies. As a result of
                        this action, funds and supplies exceeding $1,500,000 have been contributed
                        by American voluntary sources as of March 1, 1949.</p>
                    <p>On November 19, 1948, the General Assembly unanimously passed a joint
                        US-UK-Belgian-Dutch resolution calling for a United Nations program for the
                        relief of Palestinian refugees. This resolution declared that a sum of
                        $32,000,000 would be required for a nine months’ program, to be raised by
                        voluntary contributions, and authorized an immediate advance of $5,000,000
                        from the UN working capital fund.</p>
                    <pb facs="0846" n="830" xml:id="pg_830"/>
                    <p>This Government granted a leave of absence to Stanton Griffis, American
                        Ambassador to Egypt, to enable him to accept the appointment as Director of
                        United Nations Belief for Palestine Refugees.</p>
                    <p>On December 7, President Truman announced his intention of recommending to
                        the Congress that the United States contribute 50 percent of the amount
                        called for in the United Nations resolution, or $16,000,000.<note n="7" xml:id="d533fn7">For text of statement by President Truman, see telegram
                            Gadel 688, December 6, 1948, to Paris, <ref target="frus1948v05p2#pg_1648">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, Part 2, p. 1648</ref>.</note> The
                        authorizing legislation for this appropriation has been passed by the
                        Senate, and is now pending in the House of Representatives.</p>
                    <p>The General Assembly resolution of December 11, 1948, establishing a
                        Conciliation Commission far Palestine resolves “that the refugees wishing to
                        return to their homes and live at peace with their neighbors should be
                        permitted to do so at the earliest practicable date, and that compensation
                        should be paid for the property of those choosing not to return and for loss
                        of or damage to property which, under principles of international law or in
                        equity, should be made good by the Governments or authorities responsible”.
                        A machinery for implementing these objectives is provided by the resolution,
                        which “instructs the Conciliation Commission to facilitate the repatriation,
                        resettlement and economic and social rehabilitation of the refugees and the
                        payment of compensation, and to maintain close relations with the Director
                        of the United Nations Relief for Palestine Refugees and, through him, with
                        the appropriate organs and agencies of the United Nations.” We strongly
                        supported the resolution of December 11, and have instructed the American
                        member of the Conciliation Commission to be guided, with respect to the
                        refugee question, by its terms.</p>
                    <p>With respect to the attitude of the Israeli Government towards the question
                        of repatriation, we have undertaken and are undertaking action on the
                        diplomatic level in two respects: (1) with the underlying purpose of
                        safeguarding Arab absentee property interests in Israel against application
                        of the Israeli ordinance of December 12, 1948 authorizing sale of such
                        property, we are urging Israel not to take unilateral action which would
                        prejudice achievement of an agreed settlement on the return of refugees to
                        their homes and return of property to refugee owners; (2) we are urging
                        Israel to implement the purposes of the December 11 resolution, as a means
                        of facilitating political settlement of the Palestine problem and preparing
                        the way for a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> with the Arab states.</p>
                    <p>If Israel indicates agreement in principle with the December 11 resolution,
                        or expresses its willingness to cooperate in resolving the refugee question,
                        we also contemplate making representations to the <pb facs="0847" n="831" xml:id="pg_831"/> Arab states, with a view to their adoption of a more
                        realistic attitude towards the question of accepting a share of the refugees
                        on a permanent basis and with a view to stimulating them to make
                        constructive plans to this end.</p>
                    <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">Assumptions that can be made with respect to the
                            problem</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Failure to liquidate or materially reduce the magnitude of the Arab refugee
                        problem would have important consequences. The Arab states presently
                        represent a highly vulnerable area for Soviet exploitation, and the presence
                        of over 700,000 destitute, idle refugees provides the likeliest channel for
                        such exploitation. In addition, their continued presence will further
                        undermine the weakened economy of the Arab states, and may well provide the
                        motivation for the overthrow of certain of the Arab Governments. Moreover,
                        failure to liquidate the problem would adversely affect the possibility of a
                        permanent settlement in Palestine, and would create a permanent source of
                        friction between Israel and the Arab states.</p>
                    <p>Conversely, speedy action looking to the equitable solution of the refugee
                        problem would further the restoration of peace and security and contribute
                        to the stabilization of the Near East. It would prevent the exploitation of
                        the refugee problem by foreign interests inimical to the best interests of
                        the peoples of the Near East.</p>
                    <p>In view of the stated position of Israel towards the question of
                        repatriation, and the large-scale preemption of Arab lands and housing by
                        Jewish immigrants, who are entering Israel at the rate of 25,000 monthly, it
                        would be wholly unrealistic to expect Israel to agree to the repatriation of
                        all those so desiring. Although the Jews originally accepted the partition
                        resolution of November 29, 1947, under which the Arab population of the
                        Jewish state would have numbered 500,000, it is doubtful that the State of
                        Israel would now permit more than a small number of refugees to return to
                        Israel. If Israel could be persuaded to accept any substantial number, it is
                        probable that it would request financial assistance in carrying out their
                        repatriation.</p>
                    <p>It is reasonable to assume that as many as 600,000 refugees will have to be
                        permanently settled in the Arab states. The Arab states, however, will be
                        unable to accomplish the resettlement of this number without adverse
                        economic and political repercussions, unless material assistance is
                        forthcoming.</p>
                    <p>It can also be assumed that any machinery and resources which are placed at
                        the disposal of the Conciliation Commission to implement its task will be
                        inadequate to deal with a resettlement problem of this magnitude. Moreover,
                        the resources of the United Nations and its specialized agencies are
                        presently inadequate to handle this problem and, to judge from the response
                        of the member states to the appeal for funds to implement the November 19
                        resolution establishing a relief <pb facs="0848" n="832" xml:id="pg_832"/>
                        program, the member states would not be willing to contribute the material
                        resources required to carry out a mass resettlement program if such action
                        were proposed in the United Nations.</p>
                    <p>Finally, it can be assumed that Great Britain is the only major foreign power
                        whose degree of interest in the liquidation of the refugee question is
                        sufficient to insure any significant participation in its solution.
                        (Attention should be called in this respect to Great Britain’s close treaty
                        relations with Egypt and Iraq, and to her special position with respect to
                        Transjordan, the latter two of which would probably be heavily involved in
                        any mass resettlement program.)</p>
                    <p>(4) <hi rend="italic">United States interests and policy in the Near
                            East</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Near Eastern area, which consists of Israel and the Arab states, is an
                        area of vital strategic importance, a communications center, and a major
                        source of petroleum. As such, it is an area of special concern to all the
                        great powers and to certain lesser powers. During recent years our chief
                        objective in the Near East was to prevent inherent rivalries and conflicting
                        interests in that area from developing into conditions which might lead to a
                        third world war, an objective dictated by our primary interest in
                        safeguarding the security of the United States.</p>
                    <p>Because of the special significance of Palestine, the conflicting interests
                        and aspirations of the Near East as a whole have had a primary focus in that
                        country and, during the past year, found expression in open hostilities.
                        Prior to the outbreak of hostilities, this Government took a leading part in
                        seeking a solution of the Palestine problem which would be acceptable to the
                        interested parties. Since the failure of these attempts, we have been active
                        in supporting measures designed to end the conflict, and to achieve a
                        permanent settlement of the Palestine problem. These efforts, carried on
                        within the framework of the United Nations, have been governed by our desire
                        to support in the Near East the principles of the United Nations, and to put
                        an end to the threat to international security and to American strategic
                        interests in the Near East which the present situation represents.</p>
                    <p>In conjunction with our efforts to achieve the permanent settlement of
                        Arab-Jewish differences with respect to Palestine, we are striving to
                        promote the establishment of cooperative relationships between Israel and
                        the Arab states, as a condition to the stabilization and peaceful
                        development of the area.</p>
                    <p>On a regional basis, it is our policy to assist the Near Eastern countries in
                        maintaining their independence, to strengthen their orientation towards the
                        West, and to discourage any tendencies towards the development of
                        authoritarian and unrepresentative forms of government. Such efforts are
                        designed both to minimize the debilitating <pb facs="0849" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/> effects of internal discontent, and to strengthen the
                        determination of these states to resist external pressures and
                        intervention.</p>
                    <p>(5) <hi rend="italic">Effect of the refugee problem upon United States
                            interests and policy</hi>.</p>
                    <p>From the political point of view, the stabilization of the Near East is a
                        major objective of American foreign policy. The refugee problem, therefore,
                        as a focal point for continued unrest within the Arab states, a source of
                        continuing friction between Israel and the Arabs, and a likely channel for
                        Soviet exploitation, is directly related to our national interests.</p>
                    <p>From the strategic point of view, the Joint Chiefs of Staff, on September 22,
                        1948, with specific reference to the Arab refugee question, characterized
                        the Near Eastern area as an area of critical strategic importance, and
                        emphasized the necessity, from a military standpoint, of maintaining the
                        Arab world oriented towards the United States and the United Kingdom. They
                        therefore recommended that, as a measure to strengthen our military
                        position, the United States should make provision for generous assistance to
                        the Arab refugees from Palestine.<note n="8" xml:id="d533fn8">See telegram
                                <gloss target="#t_Telmar1">Telmar</gloss> 19, September 28, 1948, to
                            Paris, <ref target="frus1948v05p2#pg_1427">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, Part 2, p. 1427</ref>.</note> The
                        Secretary of Defense on January 25, 1949, charterized the presence of the
                        refugees in the Near East as a serious threat to the political, economic and
                        social stability of this region, and a serious danger to the health and
                        welfare of the peoples of the Arab states and Israel.<note n="9" xml:id="d533fn9">See Secretary Forrestal’s letter to Chairman Bloom,
                            January 25, <ref target="#pg_697">p. 697</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Our present policy with respect to Palestinian refugees, as set forth in the
                        Secretary’s Policy Problem Book, is the following:</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>We should use our best efforts, through the Conciliation Commission and
                            through diplomatic channels, to insure the implementation of the General
                            Assembly resolution of December 11, 1948;</p>
                        <p>We should endeavor to persuade Israel to accept the return of those
                            refugees who so desire, in the interests of justice and as an evidence
                            of its desire to establish amicable relations with the Arab world;</p>
                        <p>We should furnish advice and guidance to the governments of the Arab
                            states in the task of absorbing into their economic and social
                            structures those refugees who do not wish to return to Israel.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>(6) <hi rend="italic">Attitudes of UN, individual governments, and refugees
                            themselves toward the problem</hi>.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Attitude of the UN</hi>.</p>
                    <p>Count Bernadotte, the slain Palestine Mediator, very early established the
                        principle of UN responsibility for the Palestine refugees. In <pb facs="0850" n="834" xml:id="pg_834"/> Conclusion (<gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>) of his report, dated September 16, in Part Three (Assistance
                        to Refugees), he said:</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“So long as large numbers of the refugees remain in distress, I believe
                            that responsibility for their relief should be assumed by the United
                            Nations in conjunction with the neighbouring Arab States, the
                            Provisional Government of Israel, the specialized agencies, and also all
                            the voluntary bodies or organizations of a humanitarian and
                            non-political character.”</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>However, at the Third Session of the General Assembly in Paris, the United
                        States Delegation was careful to insist in conversations with other
                        Delegations that there was no <hi rend="italic">legal</hi> responsibility
                        for refugee relief devolving upon the United Nations. The United States
                        Delegation succeeded in eliminating from the United Kingdom draft of the
                        Preamble of the resolution before the Third Committee providing for an
                        emergency relief program, a paragraph which would have established United
                        Nations responsibility for this problem. The issue was placed before the
                        Third Committee and the Assembly on its own merits as a question involving
                        humanitarian as well as political elements which would have to be met on an
                            <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> basis without establishing a precedent for
                        similar United Nations action in other cases.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, in the eyes of the refugees themselves and to an even greater
                        extent in the view of the Arab Governments, there is a United Nations
                        responsibility for the care of the refugees only slightly less than an
                        imagined United States responsibility, since the Arab Governments are prone
                        to insist that Israel would not have come into existence without United
                        States support and, had there been no Israel, there would have been no
                        refugees.</p>
                    <p>Subsequent to the passage of the resolution, the UN in the field, under the
                        directorship of Ambassador Stanton Griffis, has undertaken primary
                        responsibility for the emergency phase of refugee relief. There is no doubt
                        that the Secretary General, Mr. Trygve Lie, feels convinced that the United
                        Nations must continue to show effective leadership in meeting this problem.
                        However, in essence, the continuing participation of the United Nations in
                        dealing with the interim and long-range phases of the matter will depend on
                        the attitudes of the Governments who compose the United Nations.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Attitudes of
                        Governments</hi>.</p>
                    <p>It was significant that when the Palestine refugee problem was considered by
                        Committee 3 in Paris last autumn, support was more verbal than valuable in
                        tangible terms. Mr. Mayhew of the British Delegation, at the very
                        commencement of the session, insisted that the Third Committee should
                        immediately devise measures to meet the refugee problem. When asked,
                        however, what measures the United Kingdom <pb facs="0851" n="835" xml:id="pg_835"/> had in mind or even if its delegation had a draft
                        resolution, Mr. Mayhew confessed that they had neither ideas nor the
                        embodiment of ideas in resolution form. The British attitude seemed to be
                        one of viewing with great alarm, but most of the spade work in developing
                        the resolution which was finally adopted by the Assembly was done by the
                        United States Delegation. It is probable, however, that it was due to
                        British influence that the Netherlands and Belgium associated themselves
                        with the United Kingdom, and the United States, in jointly sponsoring a
                        resolution. Unfortunately, however, the interest of these governments in
                        contributing to the refugee relief in more tangible terms than sponsorship
                        of a resolution has not proved to be very great. Although the Belgian
                        Government has contributed approximately one-half a million dollars, the
                        Dutch have given nothing, while the French contribution still awaits
                        Parliamentary approval. The British contribution totals one million
                        pounds.</p>
                    <p>The response of other governments has been even less enthusiastic. In fact,
                        the great brunt of relief expenditures has been borne, perforce, by the Arab
                        States, on whom these refugees are quartered. Dr. Bayard Dodge estimates
                        that from the time the first refugees escaped from Haifa and Jaffa in the
                        spring of 1948, to December 1 in that year, the Arab Governments contributed
                        $11 million in cash or kind to their sustenance. This sum, in light of the
                        very slender budgets of most of these Governments, is relatively
                            enormous.<note n="*" xml:id="d533fn13">The total direct relief offered
                            the Arab refugees by the Israeli Government to date consists of 500
                            cases of oranges. [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The conclusion seems inescapable, therefore, that even though the United
                        Nations should formulate a program for the interim and long-range relief
                        periods, its constituent Governments cannot be relied upon for very
                        effective contributions with the possible exception of the United
                        Kingdom.</p>
                    <p>The United Kingdom has definitely indicated its mounting concern at the
                        refugee problem, realizing as it does how the presence of 700,000
                        demoralized and hungry people can threaten the entire stability of the
                        strategic Middle East in which the United Kingdom has a vital interest.
                        Thus, the British Foreign Secretary on March 2 spoke to Ambassador Douglas
                        in London of the depth of his concern regarding the plight of the Arab
                        refugees. Mr. Bevin felt that this was a problem of alarming proportions
                        which “deserves the utmost efforts of the United States and United Kingdom
                        as well as the United Nations”, to say nothing of being a political problem
                        of the first magnitude for the reestablishment of peace in the Middle East
                        (London telegram 787, March 3<note n="10" xml:id="d533fn10">Not
                            printed.</note>).</p>
                    <pb facs="0852" n="836" xml:id="pg_836"/>
                    <p>Although this was the attitude of the British Foreign Secretary, his Foreign
                        Office has as yet not formulated concrete proposals for meeting the problem.
                        Nevertheless, British Missions in the Middle East have been circularized
                        with a questionnaire and the Foreign Secretary, who displays a keen personal
                        interest in the matter, in the last week of February directed that the views
                        of the Commonwealth Governments regarding the refugee problem be
                        ascertained, as they might be helpful not only in a material way but also in
                        the United Nations. Mr. Bevin thought that India and Pakistan, which have
                        wide experience in handling refugee problems, might be of particular help.
                        He felt also that the French Government should be consulted because of its
                        wide Moslem responsibilities. (London telegram 742, March 1<note n="11" xml:id="d533fn11">Not printed.</note>).</p>
                    <p>On the basis of this evidence, therefore, there would seem to be ground for
                        considerable spade work with the British. Through the British Middle East
                        Office the United Kingdom has extensive economic contact with the Arab
                        Governments and an immense reservoir of experience on which to draw.
                        Furthermore, in very concrete terms the British should be able to tap the
                        resources of such great engineering firms as Gibbs and Cox, who, it is
                        understood, have prepared detailed engineering plans for river development
                        projects and land improvement schemes in Transjordan and other areas where
                        Palestine refugees might be settled.</p>
                    <p>Since the British and American Governments are in concert as to their
                        strategic requirements in the Middle East, it would seem absolutely
                        essential that any program for that area in regard to refugee relief which
                        would be sponsored by this Government, either in the United Nations or as a
                        separate project, should be accomplished in the closest accord with the
                        United Kingdom Government.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Attitude of the Refugees
                            Themselves</hi>.</p>
                    <p>All reports from the field—i.e., those of Dr. Bayard Dodge and Mr. Colin Bell
                        of the Friends Service Committee, recently returned from Gaza, and of Mr.
                        St. Aubin, the Field Director in the Near East of the American Red Cross,
                        plus reports from United States Missions in that area—confirm that the great
                        bulk of the refugees wish to return to their homes and cling to the illusion
                        that it will be possible to do so.</p>
                    <p>The danger point will come when the refugees realize that it will be
                        impossible for the majority to return home. It is true that Mr. Stanton
                        Griffis in Cairo’s airgram <gloss target="#t_A1">A–</gloss>254, March
                            1,<note n="11" xml:id="d533fn14">Not printed.</note> expresses the
                        opinion that, once peace is restored, large numbers of refugees will
                        infiltrate across the Israeli border and return to their former abode.
                        Nevertheless, <pb facs="0853" n="837" xml:id="pg_837"/> the Representatives
                        of the Provisional Government of Israel have very clearly indicated that
                        Israel has no intention of taking back more than a portion of the refugees.
                        The Israeli Representative in Washington, Mr. Eliahu Elath, told Mr. Mark
                        Ethridge that he thought that maybe the Christian Arabs might be permitted
                        to return but that the Moslem Arabs would be an intractable element who
                        could not assimilate in Israel. Furthermore, Israeli authorities have
                        followed a systematic program of destroying Arab houses in such cities as
                        Haifa and in village communities in order to rebuild modern habitations for
                        the influx of Jewish immigrants from <gloss target="#t_DP1">DP</gloss> camps
                        in Europe. There are, thus, in many instances, literally no houses for the
                        refugees to return to. In other cases incoming Jewish immigrants have
                        occupied Arab dwellings and will most certainly not relinquish them in favor
                        of the refugees. Accordingly, it seems certain that the majority of these
                        unfortunate people will soon be confronted with the fact that they will not
                        be able to return home. Unless some alternative is prepared and some hope
                        offered them of an improved life in the future, it is certain that the
                        political, to say nothing of the social, repercussions of this discovery
                        will be very great.</p>
                    <p>If a proper program can be devised and implemented promptly, it is to be
                        anticipated that the refugees will cooperate in carrying out the program,
                        especially since they will in any case have no alternative. These people,
                        for the most part, have long been inured to hardship and to life on a
                        subsistence level. Although they have a very natural desire to return to
                        their local fig tree and vine, to use Ambassador Griffis’ phrase, it should
                        be possible, if they had a reasonable prospect of acquiring some other fig
                        tree and vine elsewhere, to maintain their morale and to put tools in their
                        hands for their own salvation. The danger will be, if through lack of a
                        proper program or adequate funds, they find themselves, on one hand, cut off
                        from a hope of return to their former homes and, on the other hand, bereft
                        of hope in establishing a new life for themselves elsewhere. If this should
                        transpire it seems almost a foregone conclusion that the ensuing conditions
                        of unrest and despair would provide a most fertile hotbed for the
                        implantation of Communism, and we should in that moment expect to see in the
                        vitally important strategic Middle East a reproduction of the present
                        debacle in China.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Attitude of the Arab
                        states</hi>.</p>
                    <p>It is the present policy of the Arab states to insist upon the repatriation
                        of all the Palestinian refugees, and none of the Arab states with the
                        exception of Transjordan contemplates the permanent settlement of any
                        refugees within its own territory. It can be assumed that the most virogous
                        efforts will have to be exerted by the Conciliation Commission <pb facs="0854" n="838" xml:id="pg_838"/> and by interested governments if
                        the Arab states are to be persuaded to adopt a more realistic and
                        cooperative attitude towards this question. Moreover, it can be assumed that
                        their active cooperation could only be obtained under the following
                        circumstances: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>they would require evidence that substantial material assistance
                                would be forthcoming from outside sources to aid in solving the
                                refugee problem:</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>they would require assurances that such aid would be of material
                                benefit to their countries and populations, as well as to the
                                refugees themselves;</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>they would require assurances that the administration of such aid
                                would involve no derogation of sovereignty; and</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>they would require evidence that Israel was prepared to cooperate
                                effectively in the liquidation of the refugee question.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>(7) <hi rend="italic">United States Public Attitude Toward the
                        Problem</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The American public, generally is unaware of the Palestine refugee problem,
                        since it has not been hammered away at by the press or radio. Aside from the
                            <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Herald
                            Tribune</hi>, which have done more faithful reporting than any other
                        papers, there has been very little coverage of the problem. With the
                        exception of a Sunday feature article by Max Boyd, the wire service stories,
                        if filed, have not been used. Editorial comment is still more sparse. Freda
                        Kirchwey in <hi rend="italic">Nation</hi>, a few editorials in <hi rend="italic">America</hi> (Catholic), an editorialized article in the
                            <hi rend="italic">New Leader</hi> and one editorial each in the <hi rend="italic">Baltimore Sun</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Des Moines
                            Register</hi> nearly exhausts the list. Most of the news articles and
                        editorials have had a friendly slant, except for the <hi rend="italic">New
                            York Post</hi>, which was violently opposed to helping the Arabs. While
                        some of the articles have addressed themselves to the question of the nature
                        of the settlement as regards repatriation or resettlement, none of them have
                        raised the question of continuing aid. Consequently one may conclude that,
                        barring any dramatic developments which would arouse prejudices or create
                        new issues, a continuing but not spectacular aid program would probably be
                        supported by the enlightened few, and would not, in all likelihood, run into
                        strong opposition.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Congressional Attitude</hi>.</p>
                    <p>In considering the authorizing legislation for the U.S. contribution of
                        $16,000,000, the Senate Foreign Relations Committee was chiefly concerned
                        with the fact that the U.S. Delegation at Paris had taken action which
                        appeared to commit the U.S. morally, if not legally, to a contribution thus
                        placing Congress in the position of being a rubber stamp. It was also
                        concerned about the establishment of a precedent under which the United
                        States might undertake other programs of this character which would not be
                        supported by all UN Members on the basis of the regular scale of
                        contributions. There was no challenge <pb facs="0855" n="839" xml:id="pg_839"/> of the thesis that the contribution was in the
                        national interest, an argument which, though valid, is apparently tiresome
                        because over-worked.</p>
                    <p>The House Committee on Foreign Affairs readily accepted the Senate action on
                        the U.S. contribution but raised questions concerning the possible
                        application of the matching principle as a condition for the U.S.
                        contribution. The point was not pressed in this instance but is one which
                        should be borne in mind in connection with any further program.</p>
                    <p>Neither the Senate nor the House Committee probed the problem of continuing
                        assistance. The Department rested its case on the need for relief over a
                        limited period of time on the basis that aid was essential to contribute to
                        the peace settlement and stabilization in the Near East. It also stressed
                        the General Assembly resolution declaring that the right of refugees to
                        return to their homes should be recognized, and the role of the Conciliation
                        Commission in facilitating the economic and social rehabilitation of the
                        refugees. An aside remark by one of the senators in the hearings that the
                        program might go on for three or five years was not taken up. This was the
                        only intimation that Congress might expect to be faced with a request for
                        some kind of continuing program. The fact that it was not picked up is
                        probably more significant in connection with the lack of opposition to the
                        present program than in relation to the possibility of a continuing program.
                        No statement has been made at any time that no further assistance would be
                        needed.</p>
                    <p>The Senate adopted the joint resolution without objection after the
                        presentation of the report of the Senate Committee (which was also adopted
                        unanimously) had been presented by Senator Connally. The House Committee was
                        unanimous in the adoption of its report to the House. The only hitch thus
                        far has been in the House Rules Committee which postponed action on the rule
                        to report the measure because its members had, with one exception, never
                        heard of the Arab Refugee problem.</p>
                    <p>It is perhaps not unreasonable to conclude from the foregoing that a
                        reasonable program for continuing aid would not meet with strong opposition
                        in Congress. However, the form of such aid, the question of whether it is
                        multilateral or unilateral, and its bearing upon other aid programs, are
                        matters on which the success or failure of continuing aid may hinge.</p>
                    <p>(8) <hi rend="italic">Attitude of Individuals and Groups Interested in the
                            Problem</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The private groups interested in the Palestine Refugee problem consist
                        primarily of the following: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the oil companies
                            (<gloss target="#t_ARAMCO1">ARAMCO</gloss>, Standard of N.J., Socony
                        Vacuum, Gulf Oil Company, American Independent Oil Company, Standard of
                        California, Standard <pb facs="0856" n="840" xml:id="pg_840"/> of New York,
                        and the Texas Company, all of whom have varying degrees of interest; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Church groups, particularly the American Friends
                        Service Committee, the Church World Service Committee, the National Catholic
                        Welfare Conference, the Lutheran World Relief and several small
                        denominations all of whom are associated directly or indirectly with welfare
                        or religious projects in the Near East; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) lay
                        groups such as the Near East Foundation, the Near East College Association,
                        Middle East Relief, Inc., Middle East Union, Committee for Holy Land Appeal
                        (an over-all body comprising most of the aforementioned groups for the
                        purpose of raising emergency funds) and the American Red Cross. A number of
                        interested individuals, some of whom are closely identified with one or more
                        of the above groups include the following: Winthrop Rockefeller, Nelson
                        Rockefeller, Bayard Dodge, Kermit Roosevelt, Harold Hoskins, Lowell Thomas,
                        Barclay Acheson, Dr. Patton, Edward Miller, Col. Eddy, Terry Duce, and
                        Garland Hopkins.</p>
                    <p>All of the foregoing would probably give strong support for public assistance
                        measures designed to stabilize the Near East and to promote the welfare of
                        those peoples. Most of these groups are associated with or might be
                        interested in contributing or raising funds from private sources for
                        long-range welfare projects in the area. A campaign is to be launched
                        shortly on the initiative of Kermit Roosevelt and Garland Hopkins to raise
                        funds for a refugee welfare program. Present thinking is that it should
                        extend over a five-year period. The oil companies when approached for relief
                        funds last autumn were reluctant to support a feeding program and indicated,
                        at that time, their greater concern and possible willingness to participate
                        financially in longer range projects which would be of permanent value to
                        the Near Eastern peoples. They will undoubtedly contribute through
                        appropriate channels to private projects of this character. The possibility
                        that some of them might also be induced to finance useful work projects in
                        certain areas should not be excluded in the event that funds from other
                        sources are inadequate. A $5 million figure was tossed about last autumn as
                        a tentative indication of oil company interest in long-range welfare
                        projects, but it would be unwise to accept this figure as even a tentative
                        target until the programs of voluntary agencies are more fully
                        developed.</p>
                    <p>Welfare programs are needed immediately in the refugee centers and every
                        effort should be made to induce the voluntary agencies to develop and
                        finance such programs. The campaign referred to above is the only major
                        effort being undertaken. However, it is unlikely that any program financed
                        from this source could be developed in the field for many months. Regardless
                        of the time factor it is important <pb facs="0857" n="841" xml:id="pg_841"/>
                        that any such program be coordinated with the planning of the continuing aid
                        program.</p>
                    <p>The first approach to the private groups should probably be made at an early
                        date in order to ascertain in more detail the nature of the projects
                        envisaged. We might wish to encourage in-camp training projects as the best
                        means to enable the refugees to adapt themselves to new conditions. We can
                        reveal our concern about continuing aid, but indicate that it is a difficult
                        and complex problem which cannot be quickly or easily implemented. Moreover,
                        an initial effort on the part of private groups will be of value in urging
                        public assistance as it becomes clear that the magnitude of the problem is
                        too great for them to cope with. Their fund-raising activities and the
                        attendant publicity will call attention to the continuing need and help pave
                        the way for Congressional action.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The following objectives are recommended as a basis for planning with respect
                        to the problem, subject to change as the plan develops: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>To stimulate the adoption of plans to expedite the transfer of the
                                problem from its present unproductive relief basis to a basis for a
                                definitive settlement;</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>To persuade Israel to accept the principle of repatriation of an
                                agreed number or category of refugees, with provision by Israel for
                                appropriate safeguards of civil and religious rights and on
                                condition that those repatriated desire to live at peace within
                                Israel and to extend full allegiance thereto;</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>To persuade Israel to initiate the gradual repatriation of an
                                agreed number or category as soon as possible;</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>To urge the Israeli Government to make equitable compensation for
                                the property and assets of those refugees who do not desire to
                                return and of those whose property and assets have been expropriated
                                or otherwise disposed of by the State of Israel;</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>To provide for the permanent settlement in Arab Palestine in the
                                near future of as large a number of the refugees as appears
                                economically practicable;</item>
                            <label>(6)</label>
                            <item>Under the assumption that Arab Palestine, or at least a large
                                portion thereof, will be allotted to Transjordan in the final peace
                                settlement, to undertake concerted planning with the British
                                Government with a view to the early integration of a large portion
                                of the refugee population into the economic and political structure
                                of the expanded state as a whole;</item>
                            <label>(7)</label>
                            <item>To examine the developmental resources common to Israel and the
                                expanded state of Transjordan, with special reference to their water
                                resources, with a view to stimulating cooperative economic
                                development projects, where feasible, for the mutual benefit of both
                                states;</item>
                            <label>(8)</label>
                            <item>If the repatriation of substantial number of refugees becomes
                                feasible, to give special consideration to those areas having the
                                greatest <pb facs="0858" n="842" xml:id="pg_842"/> relative
                                concentrations of refugees, particularly Lebanon, which is
                                undergoing serious economic pressures and facing potential political
                                pressures, and the Gaza area of southwestern Palestine, with its
                                limited developmental potentialities;</item>
                            <label>(9)</label>
                            <item>With respect to those refugees who cannot be assimilated in Israel
                                or the expanded state of Transjordan, to examine the potentialities
                                for permanent resettlement elsewhere in the Near East, bearing in
                                mind the capabilities of northeastern Syria and northern Iraq, where
                                basic manpower shortages and large cultivable areas exist;</item>
                            <label>(10)</label>
                            <item>Where feasible, in the resettlement of refugees, to plan on
                                utilization of projects which will contribute to the long-range
                                development of the productive capacity and economic potential of the
                                area, as contrasted with short-term projects which might be without
                                ultimate benefit to the countries involved.<note n="12" xml:id="d533fn12">In a memorandum of March 23 to Mr. McClintock,
                                    James Q. Reber of the Executive Secretariat stated that the
                                    Policy Paper had been shown informally to the Secretary of
                                    State, the Under Secretary, and Mr. Rusk and that the Secretary
                                    had informally approved the “conclusions” (actually, the
                                    recommendations). The memorandum also stated that “This approval
                                    and knowledge of the specific policy issues included in the
                                    paper are sufficient to permit Mr. McGhee’s operations to be
                                    initiated.” Mr. McClintock quoted the memorandum in telegram 147
                                    of March 25 to Mr. McGhee at Beirut. The memorandum and telegram
                                    are both filed under 501.<gloss target="#t_MA1">MA</gloss>
                                    Palestine/3–2249.</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
