<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-08-23T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-08-23T07:00:00-05:00" n="54" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d54">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.6363/8–2349: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-08-23T13:00:00+01:00">August
                                        23, 1949—1 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3333. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 2987, August 20.
                                Department’s reactions British program for reopening Haifa refinery
                                and pipeline communicated Burrows August 22. During latter part of
                                conversation, Le Roy of French Embassy joined meeting and gave
                                following comments his government: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>French Government dubious re likelihood Israeli Government
                                        making statement free port proposal for Haifa.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>In view foregoing, French Government feels it would be
                                        mistake to make approach to Iraqi Government conditional on
                                        Israeli statement. (Burrows pointed out Foreign Office did
                                        not propose make approach to Iraqis conditional on Israeli
                                        Government making proposed statement and had in fact
                                        indicated that even if Israel not willing make such
                                        statement, Foreign Office would wish proceed with rest of
                                        program—see paragraph 3(C) <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 3224, August 15.)</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>In event Israeli Government were willing make statement re
                                        free port, French Government did not feel British Government
                                        should approach Egypt on basis that since Israeli Government
                                        had stated willingness establish free port, Egyptian
                                        Government should permit passage tankers. French Government
                                        felt that such an approach <pb facs="0163" n="147" xml:id="pg_147"/> would constitute British recognition
                                        Egypt’s violation of 1888 Suez Canal agreement. (Burrows
                                        pointed out he had not proposed the two questions should be
                                        tied up in this fashion. Foreign Office would merely rely on
                                        publicity value of Israeli statement, hoping it would make
                                        Egypt more amenable permit passage tankers.)</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>2. Burrows stated that in light US and French views re unlikelihood
                                any success persuading Israel make statement for free port proposal,
                                Foreign Office would wish reconsider this aspect of problem and
                                would give us its views later. Meanwhile, Foreign Office and company
                                proceeding with remainder of program. First Western Hemisphere
                                tanker due arrive Haifa about September 18 and plans are proceeding
                                load Persian Gulf tankers which are now scheduled arrive shortly
                                before that date. Foreign Office looking into this question in order
                                arrange simultaneous arrival as originally planned.</p>
                            <p>3. Burrows attention was directed to numerous recent articles in
                                British press emanating from Tel Aviv to effect Israeli Government
                                applying pressure on company to reopen refinery, with attendant
                                threat take refineries over and operate them itself in event company
                                does not do so. Burrows stated that UK charge Tel Aviv has been told
                                by Israeli Foreign Office to take no notice these press statements.
                                Burrows admitted, however, press statements are worrying him since
                                now it will appear that <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> has been
                                forced take action by Israelis.</p>
                            <p>Sent Department 3333; repeated Baghdad 77, Cairo 118, Paris 645,
                                pouched Haifa.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>