<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="549" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d549">
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Statement by the President</hi><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d549fn1">Released by the White House on
                                    March 24; reprinted from Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, April 3, 1949, p. 419.</note>
                            </head>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-24">March 24, 1949</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p>It is with gratification that I have today signed Senate Joint
                                Resolution 36 authorizing a special contribution by the United
                                States of $.16 million for the relief of Palestine refugees.</p>
                            <p>The United Nations General Assembly on November 19, 1948, urged all
                                States members of the United Nations to make voluntary contributions
                                as soon as possible to a relief fund totaling $32 million. The
                                Secretary of State informs me that thus far fifteen other Members of
                                the United Nations have contributed and that other Governments have
                                signified their intention to send money or contributions in kind.
                                There is a pressing need for this fund, for seven hundred thousand
                                refugees are living almost on starvation level. It is the hope of
                                the United States that very promptly the total $32 million fund will
                                be subscribed by the members of the United Nations, or other
                                countries, which have not yet given to the fund.</p>
                            <p>I trust that before this relief program is ended means will be
                                devised for the permanent solution of the refugee problem, and that
                                the efforts of the Palestine Conciliation Commission to establish a
                                lasting peace will bring hope of a brighter future to these
                                destitute victims of the recent hostilities in the Holy Land.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>