<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Mark F. Ethridge to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d615</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">615</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-04-28T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-04-28T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-04-28T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-04-28T05:00:00-05:00" n="615"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d615">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/4–2849: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mark F. Ethridge</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lausanne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-28T11:00:00+01:00"
                            >April 28, 1949—11 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> 1. <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss>
                    136. From Ethridge. Scheduled commencement <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>
                    meeting with Israel and Arab states at Lausanne April 26 held up 24 hours on
                    account delayed arrival interested delegations. On April 27 <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> met separately with Israeli Delegation
                    consisting of Gershon Hirsch and Eliahu Sassoon, with Egyptian Delegation
                    consisting of Abdel Chafey el Labab and Mahmud Rhmazi and with Lebanese
                    Delegation consisting of Fuad Bey Amoun and Mohamed Ali Hamade. <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> meeting with Syrian Delegation consisting of
                    Adnan Atassi planned April 28. <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> informed
                    Transjordan Delegation will arrive this week. Saudi Arabia will not attend, but
                    will accept such arrangements as other Arab states make with Israel. Iraq
                    refused at Beirut to attend and has not yet sent expected informal observer.
                    Yemen understood maintain same position as Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <p>Substance of remarks by Israeli Delegation indicated Israel had not altered its
                    position re refugees and Jerusalem as stated by Ben Gurion, Sharett and Comay.
                    Hirsch made no allusion whatsoever to conciliatory statement re refugees nor
                    manifested any disposition to work with <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> on
                    possible plans for internationalization of Jerusalem. On contrary Hirsch
                    stressed conclusion of peace with Arab states was primary objective. Refugee
                    question and Jerusalem could not be discussed in advance, but could be
                    considered during peace talks. Hirsch and Sassoon strongly urged <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> recommend to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                    that it not debate refugees and Jerusalem at Lake Success while they were being
                    considered at Lausanne. Hirsch believed if full debate took place at Lake
                    Success public declarations on refugees and Jerusalem would undoubtedly be
                    required which would have important effect on quiet negotiations at Lausanne.
                    Hirsch stated that there was no disposition on part of Israeli Delegation now to
                    discuss current questions at Lausanne if debate took place at Lake Success. It
                    was made clear, nevertheless, that little progress could be expected at Lausanne
                    in interim.</p>
                <p>Hirsch also indicated Israeli Delegation would be unable to exchange views with
                    Syrian Delegation before present Israeli-Syrian armistice negotiations were
                    concluded. Peace talks with Arab States should be limited in each case to
                    subjects of common concern. Egypt, for example, had no more right to discuss
                    Jerusalem than Persia or Turkey. Israel hoped, therefore, that pertinent agenda
                    would be arranged between Israel and various Arab States. <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss>, on other hand, might have its own agendas with
                    Israel and Arab States respectively.</p>
                <pb facs="0972" n="956" xml:id="pg_956"/>
                <p>Egyptian and Lebanese Delegations both stated their presence at Lausanne
                    indicated cooperation with <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> and desire for
                    peace. Both considered, however, that solution for refugee problem and Jerusalem
                    were essential before peace talks could progress. Discussion re territorial
                    questions was premature at this stage. Amoun indicated, however, that Lebanese
                    Delegation was ready to discuss Jerusalem and Holy Places with Jerusalem
                    Committee immediately.</p>
                <p>Following meetings with Israeli, Egyptian and Lebanese Delegations, <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> considered Israeli request that <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> recommend to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                    that it not debate such questions as refugees and Jerusalem while <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> was discussing at Lausanne. <gloss
                        target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> decided it would be presumptuous on its part to
                    make such recommendation and felt that if it were subsequently necessary to
                    submit special or periodic report to <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> such
                    reports should be confined to statement of Israeli and Arab cooperation with
                        <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> and degree of acceptance of provisions
                    of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> resolution December 11.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Ethridge</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
