<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Minister in Syria (
                        Keeley
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d658</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">658</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-05-13T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-13T13:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-13T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-13T13:00:00-05:00" n="658" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d658">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/5–1349: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Syria</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Keeley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Damascus</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-13T20:00:00+02:00">May 13, 1949—8 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>281. General Riley informs me proposal set forth in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 209 May 12, is no longer valid and that modification thereof
                    already before delegations. At today’s meeting Israeli delegate requested
                    interpretation certain Aspects current proposal before considering it and is
                    presently seeking instructions Tel Aviv. In circumstances General Riley feels it
                    would serve no useful purpose for me make representations indicated by
                    Department; on contrary that such representations might well confuse
                    situation.</p>
                <p>Next meeting scheduled for Tuesday, May 17, when it is hoped modified proposal
                    will be discussed in joint session.</p>
                <p>General Riley suggests and I agree that I be authorized to support with Syrians,
                    at moment we may jointly consider appropriate, whatever compromise seems fairly
                    to safeguard interests both parties. Legation representations in support of
                    Israeli-weighted proposal in sense penultimate paragraph <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 209 can only have stiffening effect.</p>
                <p>Syria long ago became accustomed to its inability obtain justice in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. For US to remind Syria that this situation
                    likely to continue if she fails accept Israeli armistice terms will not. I feel
                    sure, be persuasive, particularly in light of favor currently being shown Israel
                    by US re Israel’s acceptance as UN member despite her continued disregard of
                    resolution of December 11 and her failure otherwise fully to live up to
                    standards of UN Charter.</p>
                <p>Sent Department; repeated Tel Aviv 30. Department pass <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> New York 5. Pouched Amman, Baghdad, Beirut, Cairo, Jerusalem,
                    Jidda, London, Paris, and Ankara.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Keeley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
