<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Transjordan ( (Stabler) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d688</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">688</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-05-24T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-24T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-24T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-24T07:00:00-05:00" n="688"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d688">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/5–2449: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Transjordan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stabler</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Amman</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-24T14:00:00+02:00"
                            >May 24, 1949—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>215. Situation now developing with respect to special committee talks has many of
                    earmarks which characterized “negotiations” on Arab triangle. Israelis are
                    presenting strong and irrevocable demands as well as insisting on what Arabs
                    should agree to receive in return. At same time Israelis are indicating that if
                    their demands are not satisfied, they will obtain them by other means. Thus
                    Israelis, in hope of intimidating Transjordan into acceptance, are starting
                    familiar pressure treatment, including veiled threat of force. It cannot be
                    doubted that Dayan’s visit to Jerusalem (Jerusalem telegram 370 to Dept<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d688fn1">Dated May 20, <ref target="#pg_1039">p. 1039</ref>
                    </note>) was calculated attempt to have word conveyed to Transjordan that
                    Israeli patience nearly exhausted.</p>
                <p>It is true that at Rhodes Transjordan accepted in principle solution to matters
                    mentioned in clause 2 Article 8 of Transjordan–Israel armistice agreement. (No
                    mention need be made at this time of fact that Israeli refused discuss question
                    of cease-fire until Transjordan had given agreement in principle to these
                    points.) Such acceptance in principle still exists and Transjordan still willing
                    to make agreements on these points provided Israel will satisfy certain
                    Transjordan demands. It is one thing for Transjordan to state what it wishes to
                    receive as compensation; it it another for Israel to state what Transjordan
                    should be willing to receive. (For example, Israel seems intent on providing
                    electricity for old city and on giving Arabs free use Bethlehem road. Israel
                    does not appear interested in fact that Arabs have no particular desire for
                    either.) Agreement on basis latter could hardly be defined as having been
                    reached by negotiations, and consent in genuine meaning those terms.</p>
                <p>Transjordan has been subjected to much criticism for giving in to Israeli demands
                    in triangle area for it has been argued that if Transjordan resisted and Israel
                    had resorted to force, world opinion would have been shocked and UN would have
                    instituted measures to restrain Israel. However, it cannot be said that US
                    response to Abdullah’s plea for assistance gave any such hopeful indication. As
                    result this storm bitter criticism by Palestine Arabs and many others, both King
                    and Governors, have been badly frightened and all indications point to <pb
                        facs="1066" n="1050" xml:id="pg_1050"/> fact they will refuse acquiesce in
                    any further attempts at “blackmail”. It can be said that Transjordan would
                    prefer Israelis to make good their demands by force rather than meekly submit to
                    threat of force. Only possibility for reaching agreement now would be for Israel
                    to curb its voracious territorial appetite and show some signs of “negotiations
                    and consent in genuine meaning those terms.”</p>
                <p>In adopting above policy there is no doubt Transjordan has support and
                    encouragement from certain non-Arab quarters. I also feel that Transjordan would
                    run grave risk, from Arab viewpoint, in submitting further to Israeli demands,
                    notwithstanding blandishments regarding “final territorial disposition”. However
                    it would not be surprising if Transjordan were even now subjected to criticism
                    by some quarters for not being “reasonable” and for not giving in to Israeli
                    demands in interests of “peace”.</p>
                <p>Basically, Arab demands boil down to return of certain Arab quarters Jerusalem
                    now held by Israelis and it is unlikely these demands can be altered. Much has
                    been said to effect that it would be in Israel’s own interests to make some
                    conciliatory gesture toward Arabs. Discussions regarding Jerusalem would seem to
                    offer good opportunity to make this gesture, but so far Israel has not accepted
                    this friendly advice nor has any power shown itself disposed to press Israel in
                    this respect. If it is still not possible for Israel to consider return certain
                    Arab quarters Jerusalem to Arabs without making unreasonable counter demands,
                    then it would seem preferable to bring adjournment special committee, leave <hi
                        rend="italic">status quo</hi> in Jerusalem and permit Lausanne conference to
                    deal with Palestine question, including Jerusalem, as whole.</p>
                <p>It would appear impractical to adopt courses of action suggested by Jerusalem in
                    its telegram 370. First proposal on overall settlement could hardly be carried
                    out without participation of UN which is precluded from special committee talks
                    by armistice agreement. Moreover, on third party mediation there would seem
                    little chance either side would agree on division of territories concerned.
                    Probably Israel would request areas in northern Jerusalem far in excess what it
                    is prepared give Arabs in southern Jerusalem. Consequently another deadlock
                    would ensue.</p>
                <p>Agreement on basis second proposal would appear to be difficult if not impossible
                    to reach as Transjordan would be giving up its principal bargaining point in
                    return for those concessions in which it is not particularly interested. Once
                    having given up this point there would be little, if any, chance of ever
                    obtaining satisfaction its main demand. Israel on other hand would obtain
                    desired free access to Mt. Scopus which it would gradually turn into its own
                    definition of “free access”. Since at this time there appears to be little
                    possibility <pb facs="1067" n="1051" xml:id="pg_1051"/> that special committee,
                    which seems to be operating in vacuum, can reach any peacefully arrived-at
                    agreement, it would in my opinion be better to adjourn it <hi rend="italic">sine
                        die</hi> and without prejudice and hand over matters under its jurisdiction
                    to <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> at Lausanne. In order to achieve this,
                    however, it will be necessary for <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> and US to
                    put pressure on Israel, which is at all times out to achieve its ends regardless
                    of means. It would seem unfortunate, after all work which has been done to bring
                    about peace in Jerusalem, to permit developing situation to imperil that
                    peace.</p>
                <p>Sent Department, repeated Bern 6 for <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> PPC,
                    pouched Arab capitals, London, Jerusalem.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stabler</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
