<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-26T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-26T13:00:00-05:00" n="696" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d696">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/5–2649:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mark F.
                                        Ethridge</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                                    </gloss>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lausanne</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-26T19:00:00+01:00">May
                                        26, 1949—7 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 167. Consult Rusk for
                                distribution. Reference <gloss target="#t_Unpal1">Unpal</gloss>
                                    116.<note n="1" xml:id="d696fn1">Identified also as telegram
                                    682, May 24, to Bern, <ref target="#pg_1051">p.
                                    1051</ref>.</note> I consider underlying policy accurate. Note
                                of this character would strengthen my hand at Lausanne. It may not
                                be as effective now as it might been at earlier date as Israeli
                                views regarding refugees and territory have crystallized such
                                extent, both privately and publicly, that it may be difficult for
                                them to change. I strongly recommend its despatch nevertheless, if
                                we are to attempt to achieve a peace in theme which will not
                                subsequently come apart at seams. I have several suggested changes: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>First paragraph, first sentence: Omit “as set forth to Mr.
                                        Mark Ethridge by Dr. Eytan on May 19, 1949 at Lausanne upon
                                        instruction of His Excellency, the Foreign Minister of
                                        Israel” and substitute “as set forth by the representatives
                                        of Israel at Lausanne in public and private meetings”.
                                            <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 160<note n="2" xml:id="d696fn2">Identified also as telegram 769, May
                                            20, from Bern, <ref target="#pg_1036">p.
                                            1036</ref>.</note> correctly reports Eytan’s views and
                                        views of his colleagues. There is no doubt they are views of
                                        Israeli <pb facs="1075" n="1059" xml:id="pg_1059"/>
                                        Government but to avoid technical evasion we suggest
                                        substitute phrase.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>First paragraph, second sentence: Add at end “although it
                                        has under consideration certain urgent measures of limited
                                        character”. Israeli Delegation recently informed <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> it had sent Tel Aviv for
                                        consideration urgent measures listed in <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 166.<note n="3" xml:id="d696fn3">Dated May 23, from Lausanne, <ref target="#pg_1044">p. 1044</ref>.</note> Department
                                        is doubtless aware general Israeli approach to urgent
                                        measures of this character from <gloss target="#t_Palun1">Palun</gloss> 145.<note n="4" xml:id="d696fn4">Identified also as telegram 410, May 10, from Geneva,
                                                <ref target="#pg_992">p. 992</ref>.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>First paragraph, third sentence: Omit “but an additional
                                            acquisition further territory both within and out
                                            Palestine” and substitute “but possibly an additional
                                            acquisition of further territory within Palestine”.
                                            Israeli Delegation May 26 revealed Israeli views
                                            regarding frontier with Transjordan which are being
                                            reported separately. In essence, Israeli Delegation
                                            proposes political boundary shall be boundary between
                                            former mandate and Transjordan; i.e. 1) southern end
                                            Lake Tiberias to junction armistice line with
                                            Transjordan border, east of Jenin and 2) middle of Dead
                                            Sea to Gulf of Aqaba. With regard to Central Palestine,
                                            present armistice lines from junction of armistice line
                                            with Transjordan border east of Jenin to middle of Dead
                                            Sea would be allowed to stand until it was determined
                                            whether Transjordan, independent government,
                                            international authority or some other form of government
                                            was in control. Modifications between Israel and that
                                            government might subsequently arise for discussion and
                                            its attitude would be determined by character of
                                            government. Meanwhile, Transjordan was in military
                                            occupation with which military changes might be
                                            discussed. Israeli Delegation stated it had not included
                                            Jerusalem area in its proposal.</p>
                                        <p>Reference to Israeli acquisition outside Palestine would
                                            not strengthen note and would cause controversy. Israel
                                            desires small parts of Lebanon and Syria and possibly in
                                            Transjordan for economic reasons but will undoubtedly
                                            have to approach on exchange basis as international
                                            frontiers are involved.</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Sixth paragraph, first sentence: Omit “both inside and
                                        outside” and substitute “within”.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>Undoubtedly Department has considered question of reference to
                                Jerusalem problem in note. I agree no reference should be made
                                because <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> plan will be considered
                                by <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> in September. I suggest,
                                however, that Department might orally suggest to Israeli Ambassador
                                that final settlement Palestine question would be facilitated if
                                meanwhile, Israeli Government were able to take such conciliatory
                                steps regarding Jerusalem as action indicating Israeli Government
                                was temporary trustee for Arab land and property within Jerusalem
                                area and postponment transfer Israeli Government functions to
                                Jerusalem.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Ethridge</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>