<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of
                            State to the President</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d697</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">697</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="697" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d697">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/5–2749</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-27">May 27,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Representation to Israeli Government on Territorial
                    Settlement in Palestine and Question of Palestinian Refugees.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Israeli Position toward Final
                        Settlement</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Mark Ethridge, United States Representative on the Palestine Conciliation
                    Commission, reports in a telegram dated May 20 (Tab A)<note n="1" xml:id="d697fn1">Not found attached; the telegram referred to is presumably
                        No. 769 from Bern, <ref target="#pg_1036">p. 1036</ref>.</note> that Israel
                    has now put forth its full territorial demands upon the Arab States. Under
                    authorization from the Israeli Foreign Minister, the Israeli representative at
                    Lausanne has stated as follows: (1) While Israel makes no demands upon Lebanon
                    at present, it would later like a portion of southeastern Lebanon considered
                    necessary to Israeli development plans. The Israeli delegate said Israel would
                    be willing to compensate Lebanon for this territory, but he did not specify in
                    what way this would be done; (2) Israel desires to acquire from Egypt the
                    Egyptian occupied Gaza strip, allotted to the Arabs under the partition
                    resolution of November 29, 1947; (3) Israel makes no demands upon Syria at
                    present, but will accept the international frontier with the proviso, also to be
                    applied to Lebanon, that if either state desires to open negotiations in the
                    future for border rectification, this may be done; (4) Israel will make further
                    demands upon Transjordan for territory in Arab Palestine considered necessary to
                    Israeli development plans. Israel has in mind giving Abdullah a few villages in
                    return; (5) Israel will retain occupied areas such as Western Galilee and Jaffa,
                    Lydda and Ramie allotted to the Arabs under the partition plan; (6) Israel will
                    relinquish none of the Negev. The Israeli delegate subsequently, however,
                    indicated to Mr. Ethridge the possibility that Israel might make some
                    compensation in the Negev in return for the Gaza strip.</p>
                <p>The Israeli delegate further stated that Israel will do nothing more concerning
                    the Arab refugees at the present time.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">United States Position</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the interest of achieving an equitable territorial settlement for Palestine,
                    this Government has consistently supported the position that Israel should offer
                    territorial compensation for any territorial acquisition which it expects to
                    obtain beyond the boundaries allotted to Israel in the resolution of November
                    29, 1947. Moreover, since the General Assembly resolution of December 11, 1948
                    calls for the repatriation <pb facs="1077" n="1061" xml:id="pg_1061"/> of those
                    refugees desiring to return to their homes and live at peace, and in view of the
                    impossibility of resettling the total number of refugees in the Arab States
                    within a reasonable period of time and at a reasonable cost, this Government has
                    recently made representations to the Israeli Government urging its agreement to
                    repatriation of a subtsantial number of refugees and the immediate commencement
                    of repatriation of some portion thereof. Despite the emphasis upon repatriation
                    in the resolution of December 11, we have urged upon the Arabs the necessity for
                    their agreement to the resettlement in the Arab States of a substantial portion
                    of the refugees, in view of the fact that the return to their homes of all the
                    refugees desiring to go back would be difficult because of the continuing
                    arrival in Israel of large numbers of European displaced persons.</p>
                <p>Our representations on these two questions have thus far met with no success with
                    the Israeli Government. Israeli officials have in fact informed our
                    representatives in Palestine that they intend to bring about a change in the
                    position of the United States Government on the above points, through means
                    available to them in the United States. There are also indications that the
                    Israelis are prepared to use the implied threat of force to obtain the
                    additional territory which they desire in Palestine.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Efforts of the Palestine Conciliation
                        Commission</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Conciliation Commission has vigorously endeavored to persuade the Israelis
                    and the Arabs to withdraw from their extreme positions concerning a final
                    Palestine settlement. With respect to refugees, the Commission has succeeded in
                    persuading the Arabs to give up their previous insistence upon repatriation as a
                    prerequisite to negotiations on other outstanding issues, and in persuading
                    certain of the Arab States to give favorable consideration to resettlement of a
                    portion of the refugees. The Commission has failed to obtain any concessions
                    from the Israelis on a territorial settlement or the refugee question. It is now
                    the considered opinion of Mr. Ethridge that the conference at Lausanne is likely
                    to break up when the Arabs learn of the present Israeli position toward a final
                    settlement and that there will exist no possibility of peace on any basis
                    heretofore envisioned by the United States Government unless Israel modifies its
                    demands. Mr. Ethridge believes that such modification is unlikely.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">4. <hi rend="italic">United States Interest</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The United States interest in the security and stability of the Near East has
                    been a principal motivation of our efforts, both in the United Nations and on
                    the diplomatic level, to urge both parties to the Palestine dispute to take
                    measures leading to a sound and equitable peace. The strategic interests of the
                    United States demand early termination <pb facs="1078" n="1062" xml:id="pg_1062"/> of the present conditions of instability and mutual suspicion, which provide
                    such a favorable atmosphere for Soviet penetration and exploitation of the Near
                    East. The present instability will certainly continue if the Lausanne talks
                    break down as a result of the new Israeli position, which is susceptible of
                    interpretation by the Arabs as confirming their constant fears of Israeli
                    territorial expansionism. Failure of the Israelis to modify their present
                    demands will inevitably aggravate Arab distrust of Israel and bring about
                    renewed Arab charges that the United States remains passive no matter how
                    unreasonable the demands of Israel. The Department of State is firmly convinced
                    that the Israelis as well as the Arabs must therefore be prepared to make some
                    concessions, and that, if Israel will modify its present demands, a solution can
                    be achieved which will be both advantageous to Israel and acceptable to the
                    Arabs.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">5. <hi rend="italic">Recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The Department believes that the time has come to make
                    a basic decision concerning our attitude toward Israel. The United States has
                    given generous support to the foundation of the Jewish State, since we believed
                    in the justice of this aspiration. We are convinced that there is no reason why
                    the Jews and the Arabs cannot live together in peace in the Near East, providing
                    they each adopt a reasonable attitude toward the other.</p>
                <p>In the light of all the foregoing, the Department considers that it is now
                    essential to inform the Israeli Government forcefully that, if it continues to
                    reject the friendly advice which this Government has offered solely in the
                    interest of a genuine peace in the Near East, this Government will be forced
                    with regret to revise its attitude toward Israel. There is attached a draft note
                    to the Israeli Government for your consideration (Tab B).<note n="2" xml:id="d697fn2">Not found attached; for note as actually sent, see telegram
                        322, May 28, to Tel Aviv, <ref target="#pg_1072">p. 1072</ref>.</note> This
                    note has been discussed with Mr. Ethridge, who believes that it would strengthen
                    his hand at Lausanne and strongly recommends that it be sent.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) If the Israeli Government does not respond favorably
                    to this proposed representation, it will be necessary to take measures designed
                    to convince Israel of the importance to this Government of a revision of
                    Israel’s present policy. Such measures, in addition to a generally negative
                    attitude in the future toward Israel, might include (1) refusing the request of
                    the Israeli Government for United States technical advisers and for the training
                    of Israeli officials in the United States; (2) withholding approval of the
                    $49,000,000 as yet unallocated of the $100,000,000 earmarked by the
                    Export-Import Bank for loan to Israel.</p>
                <pb facs="1079" n="1063" xml:id="pg_1063"/>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Although the Department of State is convinced of the
                    necessity of carrying out this plan of action in the light of our national
                    interest in the field of foreign policy and strongly recommends that you approve
                    this suggested course, the matter involves other important considerations, since
                    the proposed course of action would arouse strong opposition in American Jewish
                    circles. It is therefore suggested that you may wish to ask your advisers to
                    give careful consideration to the possible implications of the above
                    procedure.</p>
                <p>The Department hopes that it will receive your reply on a most urgent basis if
                    this Government is to achieve a modification of the Israeli attitude in time to
                    save the Lausanne meeting. Mr. Ethridge informed the Department by telephone on
                    May 23 that he does not believe the meeting can last much longer than a week
                    under the present circumstances. Dr. Bunche and General Riley concur.</p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
