<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            Embassy in the United Kingdom
                    
                    This telegram was repeated to Arab capitals.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d828</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">828</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-07-13T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-07-13T18:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="refugees" subject="refugees" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585" lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="confidence-building-measures" subject="safeguards" lcsh-match="no_match">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-07-13T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-13T18:00:00-05:00" n="828" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d828">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/7–1349: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d828fn1">This telegram was repeated to Arab capitals.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-07-13T19:00:00-04:00">July 13, 1949—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2432. Reps Brit Emb July 13 furnished Dept list points suggested by <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> as basis <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> approach solution Palestine problem. Fol substance points and
                    informal comments reps Dept.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1)</label>
                    <item>Acceptance of refugees by Arabs and Israelis for resettlement and
                        repatriation. Dept agreed and there was further accord that view
                        circumstances Israel latter could probably not be expected accept more than
                        quarter million refugees for repatriation.</item>
                    <label>2)</label>
                    <item>Israeli Gaza strip proposal should be accepted on condition safeguards
                        devised re future treatment Gaza refugees Israel and territorial
                        compensation made by Israel for strip. Dept agreed some kind international
                        supervision treatment of refugees in Israel essential. Re second condition
                        Dept in agreement provided Egypt desired compensation.</item>
                    <label>3)</label>
                    <item>Israel should make territorial compensation for areas outside 1947
                        boundaries retained by her. Dept agreed but pointed out danger creating
                        impression that US would not agree to any settlement which did not provide
                        for territorial compensation. US did not wish attempt <pb facs="1240" n="1224" xml:id="pg_1224"/> force Arab states accept compensation if
                        they did not desire, and if agreement reached between parties without duress
                        which did not include territorial compensation US would not oppose.</item>
                    <label>4)</label>
                    <item>If territorial compensation should take form of award to Jordan or to
                        Jordan and Egypt of part or whole of Southern Negev, thus providing-land
                        bridge between Egypt and Jordan, Israel should have “guaranteed” freedom of
                        access and communication to Bed Sea. Equally Arab states should have
                        “guaranteed” freedom of communication and access to Mediterranean through
                        ports of Gaza and Haifa. If another solution were adopted for Southern Negev
                        there should nonetheless be guaranteed freedom of communication and access
                        across it between Egypt and Jordan and between Israel and Red Sea.
                        Alternative method of providing for freedom of communication and access
                        might be neutral zone or zones. Dept stated opinion that continuity of land
                        communication between Arab states was most important territorial item in
                        Palestine settlement as far as Arabs were concerned. Felt it might be
                        possible for <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> informally make specific
                        territorial proposal to parties and that this might well take form suggested
                        arrangement involving transfer part of Southern Negev to Egypt and Jordan
                        with agreement for Israeli access Red Sea. Dept inquired how much of
                        Southern Negev UK thought would be necessary transfer to Arabs in order
                        assure effective land communications between Jordan and Egypt. Brit reps
                        said they would query <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss>. Dept
                        pointed out such proposal as Gaza-Dead Sea line obviously unfeasible. Dept
                        saw no reason for arranging access to Mediterranean for Arab states at Gaza
                        if similar arrangement made at Haifa.</item>
                    <label>5)</label>
                    <item>Free port at Haifa with arrangement by which Iraqi crude could be freely
                        exported in return for provision by Iraq of normal supplies for Haifa
                        refinery. Dept stated general agreement desirability establishment free zone
                        facilities Haifa Arab states but doubted possibility or desirability
                        establishment free port completely free of Israeli control.</item>
                    <label>6)</label>
                    <item>Partition of Jerusalem for administrative purposes with international
                        supervision, particularly of Holy Places. Dept stated its position on
                        Jerusalem in general agreement with this.</item>
                    <label>7)</label>
                    <item>Incorporation of Arab Palestine in Jordan. Dept agreed desirable this
                        should be done at appropriate time.</item>
                    <label>8)</label>
                    <item>Israel and Arab states concerned should agree to share for their mutual
                        benefit waters of Jordan and Yarmuk. Dept agreed.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
