<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-07-27T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-27T08:00:00-05:00" n="863" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d863">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/7–2749:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Jerusalem</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Burdett</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Jerusalem</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-07-27T16:00:00+03:00">July
                                        27, 1949—4 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>495. Consul General strongly favours second alternative <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 304, July 22.<note n="1" xml:id="d863fn1">This was a repeat of <gloss target="#t_Unpal1">Unpal</gloss> 199 to Bern, <ref target="#pg_1245">p.
                                        1245</ref>.</note> Believe impossible present realistic plan
                                providing for “effective UN control” without consideration matters
                                listed Article 8 and in addition questions such as demarcation
                                zones, means of access to holy places, status such sites as Jewish
                                cemetery on Mount of Olives and permission Jews reside in Jewish
                                quarters Old City. These points are of immediate practical concern
                                to parties directly involved and recommendations with respect to
                                them will vitally affect acceptability <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> proposals. Demarcation lines will also play major
                                part in determining stability UN regime and certain Christian
                                nations have great interest in exclusion their institutions from Jew
                                zone. Feel decision on such fundamental and far reaching issues
                                should be made by <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> and not postponed by reference to
                                Jerusalem authorities appointed by UN. Fear any failure at September
                                    <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> reach definite decision re
                                Jerusalem both as to nature international regime and on “practical”
                                questions would seriously jeopardize hope for any form
                                internationalization.</p>
                            <p>With refusal Israel to negotiate on basis Department proposal and
                                expressed determination Sharett resist return Arab quarters,
                                prospects agreement between parties or even start negotiations on
                                major questions now remote. Only relatively short time remains
                                before September <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> and delay while
                                waiting for agreement could prevent preparation <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> plan. Positions of Transjordan and
                                Israel particularly on question delimitation zones now appear so
                                diametrically opposed that imposed solution apparently inevitable.
                                Also Department suggestion that zones be delimited on basis <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> November 29, 1947 will require
                                imposition on Israel. Under circumstances decision by <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> would have much more weight and
                                chance of acceptance than one by UN Jerusalem authorities.</p>
                            <p>In view above Consul General suggests following procedure: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Continuation efforts to induce Israel negotiate with
                                        Transjordan on basis Department proposals. Agreement to
                                        maximum extent possible eminently desirable and negotiations
                                        could narrow zone within which <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> must make decision.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Elaboration on proposals by <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> Jerusalem subcommittee at same time and
                                        without waiting results Israel–Transjordan
                                        discussions.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="1276" n="1260" xml:id="pg_1260"/>
                            <p>This would assure readiness plan by September and any points agreed
                                to by Transjordan and Israel could be incorporated. Jerusalem
                                committee might wish return to Jerusalem or request representatives
                                of member governments on spot to advance suggestions.</p>
                            <p>Sent Department 495, repeated Tel Aviv 81, Geneva 46, Amman 53.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Burdett</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>