<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d958</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">958</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-09-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="refugees" subject="refugees" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585" lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="oil" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" subject="sovereignty" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="water" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="economic-development" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804" lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-09-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="958" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d958">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/9–1349</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-09-13">September 13,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Conversation with Mr. Bevin on the Middle East</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. Bevin<note n="1" xml:id="d958fn1">Mr. Bevin was in the United
                                States to attend the Fourth Regular Session of the General Assembly,
                                scheduled to meet at New York on September 20.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Dening<note n="2" xml:id="d958fn2">Maberly E. Dening, Assistant
                                Under Secretary of State in the British Foreign Office.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Acheson</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. McGhee</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Butterworth<note n="3" xml:id="d958fn3">W. Walton Butterworth,
                                Director of the Office of Far Eastern Affairs; on September 29, he
                                became the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                                Affairs.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Ambassador Douglas</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Ambassador Jessup</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Satterthwaite<note n="4" xml:id="d958fn4">Livingston L.
                                Satterthwaite, Chief of the Division of British Commonwealth
                                Affairs.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb facs="1393" n="1377" xml:id="pg_1377"/>
                <p>Bevin opened the discussion on the Middle East with a complaint about Palestine.
                    He said the United Nations appoint commissions which get nowhere and which lead
                    to more and more <hi rend="italic">faits accomplis</hi> which cannot be changed.
                    He said this has happened in the matters of Jerusalem, boundaries, and Arab
                    territories. Bevin said he was in favor of Abdullah having that portion of Arab
                    Palestine which he now occupied and if there were no boundaries there was no
                    Palestine. He said the present situation was unsatisfactory and the British were
                    getting nowhere with the carrying out of their Eight Point Program, although we
                    had approved it. McGhee said it was true that we had put forward no U.S.
                    territorial settlement but we had through our representative on the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> attempted to get both sides to get together.
                    The Arabs want considerable territory, the Israelis do not want to give up any
                    and their position in both territories and refugees are too far apart for hope
                    of settlement in the <gloss target="#t_PCC1">PCC</gloss> in the near future.
                    More flexible proposals are needed on both sides if there is to be hope of
                    conciliation. Bevin asked when it would come to a head? Mr. McGhee replied that
                    the present possibilities of the Commission through conciliation had been
                    exhausted. The Economic Commission although somewhat suspect by the Arab States,
                    we nevertheless hope can induce the Arabs to accept refugees for resettlement
                    and the Israelis to accept others for repatriation with offers of economic
                    assistance. If solution to the refugee problem can be found, perhaps normal
                    relations can in time be resumed. We do not think that there is much hope of a
                    territorial settlement at this time. Bevin again said that the Jews make <hi rend="italic">faits accomplis</hi> and the Arabs get nothing.</p>
                <p>Bevin then said that the British were making progress with Egypt toward an
                    important treaty. The discussions were going along quite well on military,
                    political, and economic levels. But failure to settle the Palestine problem was
                    blocking the whole Egyptian deal. McGhee again said that he thought we had to
                    cope with the problem for a while.</p>
                <p>Bevin then discussed the problem of getting oil out of Iraq. He said that what
                    was needed was “running rights” to Haifa. He had in mind a joint board to manage
                    the port of Haifa along the lines of the Port of London Authority. It could be
                    well and impartially run. He thought the Jews could easily grant “running
                    rights” without in any way involving the sovereignty question. This could be
                    done quickly and would start the port running again. Bevin said, as we knew, oil
                    was very important to Iraq and the rights could be given outside of any
                    territorial settlement. Mr. McGhee said the Israelis had talked only about a
                    free zone for Haifa like that at Salonika. Mr. Bevin said a free port would be
                    better than a free zone, which, unless the port were controlled impartially,
                    might not result in the oil and supplies being <pb facs="1394" n="1378" xml:id="pg_1378"/> loaded. Bevin said he thought the Arabs would take such a
                    deal. Mr. McGhee reminded him that the Arabs had up to now refused to cooperate
                    or even talk with the Israelis. Bevin said that the Regent of Iraq did not
                    reject this idea and he might be tempted to take the opportunity to share in the
                    management of the port. This also might ease the outlet to the Red Sea
                    Problem.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Douglas inquired whether territorial settlement involving Abdullah
                    might not complicate the whole Palestine situation. Bevin said that the Gaza
                    strip was not so important. Mr. McGhee said that the other Arab States would
                    probably oppose annexation of the occupied territory to Jordan and that the
                    inhabitants might even oppose it or prefer the Israelis. We agree that Abdullah
                    should eventually get it, but not until a general settlement had been reached.
                    Before that time such action would probably create more problems than it would
                    solve.</p>
                <p>Bevin then reiterated his concern regarding the effectiveness of the various
                    Commissions which had been set up. Getting to the refugee problem he said that
                    the British had put up half a million in sterling. Mr. McGhee said we were
                    optimistic for an ultimate solution and would be more so if it were not for the
                    recent revolution in Syria. He said that it seemed possible to take care of
                    nearly all of the refugees if the new Syrian Government would cooperate as Zaim
                    had indicated he was willing to do. Some refugees might be left for a second
                    bite.</p>
                <p>Bevin then got another plug in for his Haifa scheme and said that if Haifa
                    problems were settled Iraq might play ball on the refugees. I asked Bevin to
                    explain what he meant by “running rights”. He said that since the territory
                    behind Haifa and Haifa itself are in the hands of the Jews, the Arabs have no
                    truck, rail or pipe line rights to deep water. The Jews are always in the
                    position of stopping the trade at any time. He thought no one would agree to a
                    corridor. I asked him if the problem would be met if “running rights” were
                    granted temporarily for two years. Bevin said he would prefer to do it subject
                    to notice as he thought a fixed period would create a row before the period was
                    ended. Bevin again said he had no faith in the economic development commission
                    or any other commission and that Palestine was still a nightmare to him. I asked
                    Mr. McGhee to try to do something to stir the pot and Bevin said he thought if
                    we could only get one practical thing done, we would be better off than we are
                    now when everything is being frustrated.<note n="5" xml:id="d958fn5">For the
                        joint statement by the United States and the United Kingdom on the
                        Acheson–Bevin conversation, released by the Department of State on September
                        13, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, September 26,
                        1949, p. 467.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
