<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-01-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="147" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d147">
                    <head>147. Intelligence Assessment Prepared in the Central Intelligence
                            Agency<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d147fn1">Source: Central
                            Intelligence Agency, Office of the Director of Central Intelligence, Job
                            81B00401R: Subject Files of the Presidential Briefing Coordinator for
                                <gloss target="#t_DCI_1">DCI</gloss> (1977–81), Box 6, Afghan
                            Crisis—Pubs Soviet Moves/Options. Top Secret; [<hi rend="italic">codeword and handling restriction not declassified</hi>]. A
                            statement on the cover page reads: “This assessment was written by [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] based on
                            contributions from members of the <gloss target="#t_NFAC_1">NFAC</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>-Afghan Task Force, and the Office
                            of Strategic Research. It has been coordinated with the Office of
                            Political Analysis, the Office of Strategic Research, and with the
                            National Intelligence Officers for the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and for the Middle East.”</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">[<hi rend="italic">assessment number not
                                declassified</hi>]</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-01">January 1980</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>[Omitted here are the report cover, a security information page, and a cover
                        page.]</p>
                    <p rend="center">The <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> in Afghanistan: An
                        Interim Appraisal ([<hi rend="italic">classification marking not
                            declassified</hi>])</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Key Judgments</p>
                    <p>The growing insurgency that threatened to topple a pro-Soviet Marxist regime
                        and create further instability on Soviet borders was the major factor behind
                        Moscow’s invasion of Afghanistan and elimination of <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Amin</persName>. The Soviets thought the <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Amin</persName> regime was incapable of arresting the
                        disintegration and calculated that Soviet troops were necessary both to
                        change the Afghan leadership and to ensure that the new regime held onto
                        power.</p>
                    <p>The fall of a pro-Soviet government in Afghanistan would have dealt a major
                        blow to Soviet prestige, slowing the momentum behind the broad extension of
                        Soviet influence in the Third World. Moscow probably also thought that
                        dramatic, forceful action would enhance its role as a major regional actor
                        in the Middle East and South Asia and that a Soviet military presence in
                        Afghanistan would place pressure on Iran and Pakistan to accommodate.</p>
                    <p>From Moscow’s perspective, the time probably seemed propitious for the
                        invasion. US-Soviet relations were already at an ebb, and Moscow probably
                        discounted adverse political effects on its international position.</p>
                    <p>Once they decided to remove <persName corresp="#p_AH_2">Amin</persName>, the
                        Soviets acted decisively to ensure that the new regime would retain control
                        in the face of opposition from dissident Afghan military and insurgent
                        elements. On 27 December, Soviet airborne troops moved quickly to seize
                        control of Kabul. Simultaneously, Moscow moved two Ground Forces divisions
                        into Afghanistan to seize key cities and communication routes.</p>
                    <pb facs="0469" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/>
                    <p>So far, there is no reliable evidence that the Soviet forces now in
                        Afghanistan have launched a large-scale offensive against the insurgents.
                        The <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> may first want to see if the new
                        regime can command the loyalty of the Afghan Army.</p>
                    <p>The 50,000 or so Soviet troops now there are considerably below the number
                        that would be needed to conduct countrywide anti-insurgent operations.
                        Moscow would need a force upwards of three times that number and would have
                        to tailor it to the difficult Afghan environment.</p>
                    <p>The insurgents are likely to conduct continual harassment of the Soviets, but
                        in view of overwhelming Soviet military superiority, they will not stand and
                        fight against large units. The insurgents are not well organized, equipped
                        or led, but they know the country and have a long history of resistance to
                        foreign domination.</p>
                    <p>There is little prospect that the <persName corresp="#p_KB_1">Babrak
                            Karmal</persName> regime can end the insurgency on its own. Faced with
                        continual guerrilla harassment, the Soviets will be under pressure to engage
                        in aggressive military operations and to commit more troops. It is unlikely
                        that Moscow will be dissuaded from this by the prospect of even more damage
                        to its international position.</p>
                    <p>The Soviets probably can eventually suppress the insurgency with more troops
                        and ruthless military action. But political costs to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> are likely to mount as Soviet forces
                        engage in prolonged combat operations in an Islamic, Third World
                        country.</p>
                    <p>[Omitted here is the body of the assessment.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>