<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-07-22T03:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-07-22T03:50:00-05:00" n="27" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d27">
                    <head>27. Telegram From the Embassy in Afghanistan to the Department of
                            State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d27fn1">Source: National
                            Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                            File, D780301–0595. Confidential. Sent for information to Ankara,
                            Moscow, New Delhi, <gloss target="#t_USLO_1">USLO</gloss> Peking,
                            Tehran, <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC_1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD_1">POLAD</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_CINCEUR_1">CINCEUR</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD_1">POLAD</gloss>.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Kabul</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-07-22T03:50:00-05:00">July 22, 1978,
                            0350Z</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>5882. <gloss target="#t_Subj_1">Subj</gloss>: Soviet Ambassador’s Views on
                        Present Situation in Afghanistan.</p>
                    <p>1. During my initial courtesy call on Soviet Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Alexander M. Puzanov</persName> July 16, he provided
                        the following answers and observations to my questions:</p>
                    <p>A) Soviet-Afghan relations: <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName>
                        stated that there had never been any serious bilateral problems between
                        Kabul and Moscow during the sixty years since diplomatic relations were
                        established during the time of King Amanullah and V. I. Lenin. He observed
                        that the Soviets had enjoyed friendly, productive relations with the royal
                        and Daoudist regimes which had preceded the current <persName corresp="#p_TNM_1">Taraki</persName> government, and expected to
                        continue this positive relationship with the new regime.</p>
                    <p>B) Soviet military advisors: <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName>
                        explained that the recent increase in the number of Soviet military advisors
                        here has been necessary in order to train the Afghans to use armored, air
                        force, and communications equipment being supplied by the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. He claimed that the rate of increase of
                        advisors is not so high as that which followed Daoud’s 1973 overthrow of the
                            monarchy.<note n="2" xml:id="d27fn2">On the question of the Soviet role
                            during the 1973 revolution, see <ref target="frus1969-76ve08#d8"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, vol. E–8,
                                Documents on South Asia, 1973–1976, Document 8</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>C) Soviet economic assistance: <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> explained that the forty-odd Soviet-Afghan economic
                        assistance agreements signed since the April 27 revolution were already in
                        the pipeline. Although most are related to the basic assistance commitment
                        made to former President Mohammad Daoud during his 1975 State visit to the
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, some date back to the pre-1973
                        monarchical era. <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> stated that
                        negotiations for these proposed projects had become stalled during the
                        Daoudist period for “a number of reasons.”</p>
                    <p>D) Projected bridge over the Amu Darya (Oxus): <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> predicted that the projected Hariatan Bridge should
                        be ready to convey vehicular traffic over the river frontier between
                        Afghanistan and the Soviet Union in “four and one-half years.”</p>
                    <p>E) The People’s Democratic Party of Afghanistan (<gloss target="#t_PDPA_1">PDPA</gloss>): <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> did not
                        think that Politburo-Secretariat-Central Committee organiza<pb facs="0112" n="67" xml:id="pg_67"/>tion of the <gloss target="#t_PDPA_1">PDPA</gloss> necessarily related the Afghan party to the Communist
                        Party of the Soviet Union (<gloss target="#t_CPSU_1">CPSU</gloss>). He
                        thought that “all parties in the world” have similar organizational
                        structures. In reply to a question, <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> said there are no party ties between the <gloss target="#t_PDPA_1">PDPA</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_CPSU_1">CPSU</gloss>. He explained that, after its 1967 split, the Afghan party
                        had dissolved into “political groupings” which could not be regarded as
                        parties. Since the Khalqists and the Parchamists only recently reunited,
                        i.e., in mid-1977, there has not been sufficient opportunity for the <gloss target="#t_CPSU_1">CPSU</gloss> to react to this event. The Afghan party
                        had never participated in any international Communist meetings.</p>
                    <p>F) Membership of the <gloss target="#t_PDPA_1">PDPA</gloss> Politburo:
                            <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> thought that there are
                        “either nine or eleven members.” During a recent conversation with Chairman
                            <persName corresp="#p_TNM_1">Noor Mohammad Taraki</persName>, he got the
                        impression that the latter had not yet decided what to do about the
                        Politburo positions which had been occupied by (the diplomatically exiled
                        Parchamist leaders) <persName corresp="#p_KB_1">Babrak Karmal</persName> and
                        Noor Ahmad Noor. It is possible, he conjectured, that these two might retain
                        their Politburo seats.</p>
                    <p>G) Government decision-making: Although arguing that the governmental
                        decisions of the Democratic Republic of Afghanistan (<gloss target="#t_DRA_1">DRA</gloss>) are being made by the Revolutionary
                        Council, which he initially defined as the country’s “state and legislative
                        organ,” <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> acknowledged that
                        the Central Committee of the <gloss target="#t_PDPA_1">PDPA</gloss> provides
                        overall political guidance. <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName>
                        went on to describe the Afghan Cabinet as the “executive organ” and the
                        Revolutionary Council as the “legislative element” of the government.</p>
                    <p>H) Regional security: <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> noted
                        with satisfaction that there were no “border problems” between Iran and
                        Afghanistan. Observing that Afghanistan requires peace in order to be able
                        to resolve its domestic challenges, he asserted that the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> endorsed the Afghan regime’s stated
                        intention to negotiate peacefully Kabul’s major “political difference” with
                        Pakistan (i.e., the “Pushtunistan” issue). <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> welcomed warmly India’s willingness to expand its
                        political and economic contacts with Afghanistan. He noted benignly that
                        Kabul’s relations with the People’s Republic of China (<gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>) are “normal.”<note n="3" xml:id="d27fn3">China recognized the new government in Afghanistan on May 7.</note>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> recalled that the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> had offered the Daoudist regime a
                        60-million-dollar line-of-credit which had not yet been fully committed. He
                        cited as Chinese accomplishments here: Irrigation projects in Parwan
                        Province, textile-making assistance, and a hospital at Kandahar.</p>
                    <p>I) Afghanistan’s future: <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName>
                        noted that impoverished Afghanistan was now working on a five-year-plan
                        which will require help <pb facs="0113" n="68" xml:id="pg_68"/> from as many
                        friendly foreign donors as possible. He was optimistic that the regime’s
                        goals will be met.</p>
                    <p>2. Comment: Although <persName corresp="#p_PAM_1">Puzanov</persName> was
                        obviously dissembling on some points, such as the influx of Soviet military
                        advisers and the structure of the <gloss target="#t_PDPA_1">PDPA</gloss>, it
                        was clear that he was trying hard to portray post-revolutionary Afghanistan
                        as a country in need of outside assistance, as a nation which needs peaceful
                        relations with its neighbors, and as a non-destabilizing factor in this
                        region.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><persName corresp="#p_DA_2"><hi rend="strong">Dubs</hi></persName></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>