<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>62. Alert Memorandum Prepared in the Central Intelligence Agency</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">62</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-09-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="recaS4jGgE7dMA7hI" type="compound-subject"
                        category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="middle-east-and-north-african-relations">Afghan
                        insurgency</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Logistics</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-09-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="62"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d62">
                <head>62. Alert Memorandum Prepared in the Central Intelligence Agency<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d62fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, National
                        Intelligence Council Files, Job 94T00046R, Box2, SWS Products on
                        Afghanistan. Top Secret; [<hi rend="italic">codeword and handling
                            restriction not declassified</hi>]. Attached but not printed is a
                        September 14 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_TSM_1">Turner</persName>
                        to the National Security Council that read: “The Soviet leaders may be on
                        the threshold of a decision to commit their own forces to prevent the
                        collapse of the <persName corresp="#p_TNM_1">Taraki</persName> regime and
                        protect their sizable stake in Afghanistan. Small Soviet combat units may
                        already have arrived in the country. I am concerned that the Soviets may be
                        underestimating the difficulties of shoring up the regime and may find
                        themselves under growing pressures to escalate the scope of their
                        intervention in the next few months. Moreover, the Soviets may now be more
                        inclined to gamble on a substantial intervention in Afghanistan because of
                        their perception of a downturn in relations with the US and the uncertain
                        prospects for Senate approval of the <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>
                        treaty.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <idno type="document-identifier">NI IAM 79–10012K</idno>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-09-14">September 14, 1979</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">additional memorandum number not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">ALERT MEMORANDUM</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d62fn2">The Alert Memorandum is an interagency publication
                        issued by the Director of Central Intelligence on behalf of the Intelligence
                        Community. Its purpose is to ensure that senior policymakers are aware of
                        the serious implications for US interests of impending political
                        developments. It is not a prediction that these developments will occur.
                        This memorandum has been coordinated at the working level by <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>, [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                            declassified</hi>], <gloss target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss>, and
                            State/<gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss>. [Footnote is in the
                        original.]</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>-Afghanistan</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Soviets may have begun to give more serious consideration
                        to the spectrum of possibilities for direct combat intervention in
                        Afghanistan. We are watching Soviet forces near Afghanistan closely but our
                        collection capabilities there are poor, and we cannot confirm or deny
                        reports that the Soviets have introduced or are preparing to introduce small
                        combat units into Afghanistan; however, we do not see preparations for a
                        large scale ground force intervention. There are no indications of changes
                        in the status of the Soviet</hi> [<hi rend="italic">1 line not
                        declassified</hi>] <hi rend="italic">near the Soviet border.</hi> ([<hi
                        rend="italic">classification marking and handling restriction not
                        declassified</hi>])</p>
                <p>Our judgment of an increased Soviet concern is fortified by the mid-August
                    arrival in Kabul of General <persName corresp="#p_PIG_1">Pavlovskiy</persName>,
                    Commander of the Soviet Ground Forces, and a high-level delegation which
                    includes several other generals and colonels, reportedly to prepare a detailed
                    report on the Afghan insurgency and the Afghan military. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PIG_1">Pavlovskiy</persName> is probably charged with assessing
                    the extent of the threat to the Afghan government and preparing contingency
                    plans which will outline the amount and nature of Soviet military support needed
                    to contain that <pb facs="0224" n="179" xml:id="pg_179"/> threat, both in its
                    current stage and if it worsens.<note n="3" xml:id="d62fn3">The mission of the
                        Deputy Chief of the Soviet General Staff, General <persName
                            corresp="#p_PIG_1">I.G. Pavlovskiy</persName>, to Afghanistan,
                        August–October 1979, was reported in telegram 6604 from Kabul, September 2.
                        The Embassy surmised that the visit of the high-ranking general possibly
                        signaled a Soviet decision to lay a “detailed contingency groundwork for the
                        future intervention of Soviet forces in Afghanistan.” (National Archives,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D790400–1145)</note>([<hi rend="italic">classification marking and handling
                        restriction not declassified</hi>])</p>
                <p>As opposition to the Afghan government has increased over the past year, the
                    Soviets have gradually augmented their military advisory presence. Early this
                    year, at least five generals and an estimated 750–1000 military advisors were
                    stationed in the Kabul area, assisting newly promoted officers in the Ministry
                    of Defense and training Afghan recruits. Since then, the Soviet presence has
                    grown to at least 2,500. Moreover, the role of Soviet troops has increasingly
                    changed from a mere advisory one to active participation in and supervision of a
                    wide variety of activity including logistics and combat planning functions as
                    far down as some regimental and battalion-level units. They are apparently
                    heavily involved in guiding Afghan combat operations, as well as logistics and
                    administration. Some unconfirmed reports allege that Soviet helicopter pilots,
                    with Afghan co-pilots, have flown strike missions against the insurgents and
                    that Soviet tank personnel have participated in combat operations. In addition,
                    Soviet advisors have reportedly suffered about 80 casualties. If these reports
                    are true, the Soviets are also actively participating in combat on a small and
                    limited scale with Afghan units. ([<hi rend="italic">classification marking and
                        handling restriction not declassified</hi>])</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] in early September
                    that the Soviets have moved up to 3,600 troops into Kabul within the past two or
                    three weeks to protect Soviet facilities and personnel there. The information
                    has not been corroborated, but Embassy Kabul has submitted similar reports from
                    two other sources in the diplomatic community.<note n="4" xml:id="d62fn4">The
                        clandestine source reporting of early September was not found. [<hi
                            rend="italic">text, 1 line, and citation not declassified</hi>] In
                        telegram 6672 from Kabul, September 6, the Embassy estimated the number of
                        Soviet military advisers at between 3,000 and 3,500. (National Archives,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D790410–0099)</note> It is possible that such a force, without heavy
                    equipment, could have been brought into the city from the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> undetected by the US, particularly if this
                    was done incrementally over a few weeks or so as part of the ongoing airlift of
                    material for Afghanistan. Such a movement of forces by the Soviets would suggest
                    increased security precautions and an escalation of Soviet involvement beyond an
                    advisory role. The Soviets might consider such a move into Kabul to be prudent
                    in view of the uprisings that have occurred in Kabul this year and the
                    continuing <pb facs="0225" n="180" xml:id="pg_180"/> possibility of violence in
                    the capital. ([<hi rend="italic">classification marking, codeword, and handling
                        restriction not declassified</hi>])</p>
                <p>In expanding the level of their own involvement in Afghanistan, there is a danger
                    that the Soviets—consciously or unconsciously—will amplify their own stake in
                    the ultimate outcome, making it increasingly difficult for them to resist
                    raising the level of their participation still another notch should they feel it
                    necessary. ([<hi rend="italic">classification marking and handling restriction
                        not declassified</hi>])</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Section heading not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">2 paragraphs (10½ lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
