<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom ( (Matthews) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-01-01T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-01-01T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3b4QX8ohh76TF3" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004886"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Journalist</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recb6XG1ZU9Ik84CR" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Broadcasting</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-01T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-01T07:00:00-05:00" n="18"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d18">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/26856½: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-01T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >January 1, 1943—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received January 1—11:05 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1. Press discussion following the arrests<note n="7" xml:id="d18fn7">For an
                        account of the assassination of Adm. Jean François Darlan on December 24,
                        1942, and the arrest of several Frenchmen a few days later, see Henri
                        Giraud, <hi rend="italic">Un Seul But, La Victoire: Alger, 1942–1944</hi>
                        (Paris, 1949), pp. 69–81.</note> by General Giraud in North Africa has
                    served to emphasize with greater clarity the basic British policy with regard to
                    France namely that British prestige requires that General de Gaulle be given and
                    maintained in a position of political primacy both during the war and in any
                    early transitory period following the liberation of continental France. The
                    British Government accepts the President’s and the Department[’s] often
                    enunciated policy that the people of France alone must choose their form of
                    government. But this is accepted with the reservations that some French
                    authority, in effect if not in name a provisional government, must reign in
                    France from the time the Allies first arrive until conditions permit the
                    establishment of that permanent Government and during this period it must be de
                    Gaulle who exercises authority. I have been told by several sources, including a
                    high British secret intelligence official in direct contact with France itself
                    and an escaped French Officer who left the country only a fortnight ago, that
                    the name of Giraud and our operations in Africa are firing the imagination of
                    the people of France. But we must realize that the British Foreign Office will
                    persist in its buildup of General de Gaulle and in its full support of his
                    demands that all who bear the stamp of Vichy must be eliminated from the
                    “unified” France for which they so loudly call. If de Gaulle is a “symbol” to
                    the people of France, he is also a “symbol” to the British Government, a symbol
                    of justification for its whole French policy since June 1940. British prestige
                    requires that “the one Frenchman who stuck by us in the dark days of 1940” must
                    be installed in France when the day of liberation comes, however fleeting his
                    tenure may be and whatever the consequences for the people of France.</p>
                <pb facs="0037" n="25" xml:id="pg_25"/>
                <p>It was this policy which lay behind the Madagascar agreement.<note n="8"
                        xml:id="d18fn8">For correspondence relating to British occupation of
                        Madagascar, see <ref target="frus1942v02#pg_687">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 687</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1942v02#pg_708">708</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >passim</hi>.</note> It was this policy which motivated the determination
                    that Djibouti must join the Fighting French. It was this policy which caused the
                    Foreign Office to oppose the combined effort of General Eisenhower, Admiral
                        Cunningham<note n="9" xml:id="d18fn9">Adm. Sir Andrew Cunningham, British
                        Naval Commander of Allied Expeditionary Force in North Africa.</note> and
                    Darlan to bring over Godefroy’s<note n="10" xml:id="d18fn10">Vice Adm.
                        René-Emile Godefroy, Commander of French fleet at Alexandria.</note>
                    Alexandria fleet to the North African authorities. It was this policy that made
                    the Foreign Office so insistent that Macmillan or some other political officer
                    of Cabinet rank be sent to Algiers without delay. And it is this policy which is
                    behind the present campaign to emphasize Giraud as the military man and de
                    Gaulle as the political leader. The diplomatic correspondent of the London <hi
                        rend="italic">Times</hi> MacDonald, who is closer to the Foreign Office than
                    any other London journalist, has the following to say this morning: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“If anyone thought for a moment that Darlan’s murder would simplify
                            affairs in North Africa he must have been given a sharp jolt towards
                            reality yesterday. General Giraud as briefly reported in the later
                            editions of the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> yesterday announced on
                                Wednesday.<note n="11" xml:id="d18fn11">December 30, 1942.</note>
                            that, convinced that other would-be assassins were preparing their
                            weapons, he had acted first. He had arrested 12 Frenchmen. Four of them
                            were police officials, two or three others were men who had helped the
                            Allies before the landing, and some of the others were considered to be
                            pro-Vichy to the British and apparently to the American peoples. The
                            whole affair appears on first hearing to be wildly confusing. How is it
                            that pro-Allied Frenchmen can be arrested? An American broadcaster from
                            Algiers attempted an answer in remarkably frank terms. According to
                            Reuters, Charles Collingwood of the Columbia Broadcasting System
                            declared yesterday: There is an impression here that the fault of the
                            present government in North Africa is that it is made up of pro-Vichy
                            and anti-de Gaulle men. General Giraud said yesterday that he did not
                            see many pro-Vichy men in power. Be that as it may, the impression still
                            remains here; and acts like the arrest of a number of pro-Allied persons
                            do not help to remove that impression. I have talked to a great many
                            people about these arrests but I have heard no one blame Giraud. He is
                            still held by all parties here to be an incorruptible soldier, a man who
                            has dedicated himself to the task of defeating Germany. What worries
                            people here is not Giraud but the men who are General Giraud’s
                            government. That appears to be a fair summary of opinion in some
                            sections in Algiers. Among other sections the habit of Vichy still
                            persists and probably these sections are trying to increase their power
                            now that the High Commissioner does not touch politics. The whole
                            affair, still puzzling in some details increases the need for
                            establishing agreement between all forces of France now ranged against
                            the common enemy. Only after such agreement can a worthy and
                            representative civilian authority be set up.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0038" n="26" xml:id="pg_26"/>
                <p>The quotation from Collingwood’s broadcast appears in every London paper this
                    morning and was given prominence by the British Broadcasting Company. Vernon
                    Bartlett in this morning’s <hi rend="italic">News Chronicle</hi> comments on
                    Collingwood’s broadcast and says: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“There is no doubt that Giraud and de Gaulle hold each other in high
                            esteem. They would gladly cooperate but they have three obstacles to
                            overcome: one is this bitter hostility in North Africa to the revival or
                            development of democracy in France. The second is the question who
                            should take military and political precedence. The third which depends
                            less upon them than upon us and the Americans, is that in some quarters
                            de Gaulle is looked upon as the British candidate for power and Giraud
                            as the candidate of the United States.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I have given the Department this somewhat lengthy review of British policy not in
                    any spirit of criticism but because I think it essential that it should have an
                    accurate picture for its guidance. If we are prepared to go along with the
                    British view that something resembling a de Gaulle government should be set up
                    in Algiers, there will be no divergence between us and it probably can be
                    brought about. If we are prepared to continue what seems to me to have been our
                    past policy, of opposing the establishment of any French political authority
                    which may even “temporarily” impose its political will upon the French people,
                    there will be sharp differences which we must face. There will be efforts here
                    to depict General Giraud as a high minded but politically innocent tool of
                    “pro-Vichy and Fascist minded jobholders,” de Gaulle (who not so long ago was
                    himself in many circles charged with having “dictatorship” or extreme right
                    tendencies) will be displayed as the upholder of democracy, the hope of the <hi
                        rend="italic">front populaire</hi> elements, and the legitimate continuation
                    of the third republic. Parenthetically the picture is causing considerable
                    anxiety to such objective and dispassionate Frenchmen as Roger Cambon:<note
                        n="12" xml:id="d18fn12">Minister Plenipotentiary and Counsellor of the
                        French Embassy in London, 1924–1940; in residence in London during World War
                        II.</note> They think the ground is being laid for civil war in France. Be
                    that as it may one thing seems clear; if we do not intend to go along with the
                    French policy of our British friends we must take prompt, firm and articulate
                    steps so to indicate. Otherwise the dangers of a split between us, with all that
                    it means for the future of the war and the peace, are obvious and serious.</p>
                <p>I respectfully request that no summary of this telegram be inserted in the
                    special telegram.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
