<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-03-08T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-03-08T12:00:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">851.86/72: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Algiers</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wiley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-03-08T18:00:00+01:00">March 8,
                                    1943—6 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 7:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>351. From Murphy.<note n="56" xml:id="d180fn56">Robert D. Murphy, United
                                States Political Adviser on the staff of the Supreme Allied
                                Commander, Mediterranean Theater, and Personal Representative of the
                                President in North Africa.</note> London’s 1424, February 25. The
                            British have made representations to General Giraud urging the
                            importance of reaching an early recruiting agreement with General de
                            Gaulle, <pb facs="0225" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> the necessity of which
                            is admitted by Giraud, but no progress can be made until Catroux’s<note n="57" xml:id="d180fn57">Gen. Georges Catroux, being sent to North
                                Africa as representative of General de Gaulle.</note> arrival here.
                            The members of the de Gaulle mission now in Algiers have no authority
                            even to discuss this matter.</p>
                        <p>The Bethouart mission has informed Giraud that measures have been taken
                            in the United States to put an end to desertions from French ships
                            arriving in American ports and to recruiting among French North African
                            personnel on behalf of de Gaulle.</p>
                        <p>The Allied military and naval authorities here believe it is important to
                            make a distinction between civilian, including merchant seamen,
                            deserters and deserters from the French Armed Forces and that for
                            reasons of military security and discipline the latter should be
                            returned to their units if apprehended in American or British territory.
                            The British Minister’s office has been requested to make a similar
                            recommendation to London since the military authorities feel that
                            whatever action in this respect is taken outside the theater has
                            definite repercussions here. [Murphy.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wiley</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>