<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-07T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-07T16:00:00-05:00" n="186" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d186">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">851B.24/33: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Consul General in Martinique</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Malige</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-07T17:00:00-04:00">January 7,
                                    1943—5 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3. The following is for your own strictly confidential information. You
                            may wish to have a preliminary conversation with Lenoir<note n="66" xml:id="d186fn66">J. Lenoir, Comptroller for Admiral Robert.</note>
                            upon his return now scheduled for January 10, before discussing the
                            substance of this telegram with the High Commissioner.<note n="67" xml:id="d186fn67">Adm. Georges Robert, French High Commissioner in
                                the French West Indies.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>It must be obvious that Admiral Robert’s counter proposal<note n="68" xml:id="d186fn68">See Admiral Robert’s letter of December 29, 1942,
                                to the Consul General in Martinique, <ref target="frus1942v02#pg_652">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 652</ref>.</note> is thoroughly
                            unsatisfactory and we should not be prepared to accept it even as a
                            basis of discussion.</p>
                        <pb facs="0232" n="220" xml:id="pg_220"/>
                        <p>During his visit to the United States Lenoir was fully and completely
                            informed of the position of this Government of its proposal and of its
                            relations with other parts of the French Empire. He has likewise had
                            several conversations with General Giraud’s<note n="69" xml:id="d186fn69">Gen. Henri Honoré Giraud, French High Commissioner
                                of French North Africa.</note> special mission now in Washington and
                            was received by Admiral Horne.<note n="70" xml:id="d186fn70">Adm. F. J.
                                Horne, Vice Chief of Naval Operations.</note> At the latter meeting
                            Admiral Horne began by stating he had great admiration for Marshal
                                Pétain<note n="71" xml:id="d186fn71">Henri Philippe Pétain, French
                                Chief of State.</note> and sympathy for the Marshal’s position but
                            that it was clear no real government existed in Vichy any longer and
                            that the Marshal being a virtual prisoner of the Germans was no longer
                            able to help the French Empire. In the circumstances lie said that
                            communications between Martinique and Vichy would have to cease. He then
                            said that we were willing to deal with Admiral Robert on either of two
                            bases (1) as a person who collaborates with the French Army now fighting
                            the Axis in North Africa or (2) as a “quasi independent” agent in the
                            French possessions. He said that we do not believe in threats but that
                            we have reached a point where something must be done and that the
                            collaboration of Admiral Robert with us is essential. In reply to a
                            question Admiral Horne outlined the situation of French warships at
                            Dakar and Alexandria. Formal assurances were given to Lenoir that the
                            United States had no designs with respect to French sovereignty in the
                            Antilles and Guiana and that the French flag would continue to fly. It
                            was also added that whereas no useful purpose could be served by
                            discussing details regarding the protection to be afforded French ships
                            at this time it was nevertheless our definite intention to do our utmost
                            to see that French possessions received the supplies needed.</p>
                        <p>Whereas Admiral Robert’s indication that convoying of his ships could now
                            be envisaged as representing a step in the right direction we feel no
                            useful purpose will be served by discussing any such details as
                            contained in your no. 8 of January 5, 6 p.m.<note n="72" xml:id="d186fn72">Not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Lenoir is likewise fully informed regarding the Board of Economic
                            Warfare’s proposal to reclassify the French possessions for the purposes
                            of export control. Further details will be furnished you as soon as
                            practicable.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>