<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-06-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="258" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00113 European War 1939/938:
                            Airgram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">North African Economic
                                    Board</gloss>
                            </hi><note n="62" xml:id="d258fn62">The Department was charged by
                                President Roosevelt with responsibility for development and
                                execution of a plan for the economic support of North Africa,
                                subject to military exigencies, and, accordingly, the North African
                                Economic Board (NAEB) was set up in December 1942 to carry this plan
                                into effect. Communications from the Board (identified as BOC) for
                                the Department and other interested agencies in Washington were
                                transmitted through the War Department.</note>
                            <hi rend="italic">to the Combined Committee for French North and West
                                African Civil Affairs</hi><note n="63" xml:id="d258fn63">Representing the Combined Chiefs of Staff (United States–British)
                                in Washington. Communications from the Committee (CCNA) to the Board
                                were identified as COB.</note>
                            <hi rend="italic">and to the Secretary of the Treasury</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Morgenthau</hi></persName>)<note n="64" xml:id="d258fn64">Copy transmitted by the Department of State to the
                                Ambassador in the United Kingdom in instruction No. 2913, July 13,
                                1943 (not printed).</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-06-15">June 15, 1943</date>.<lb/>[Received June
                                19.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Property Changes under German Rule—Tunisia</p>
                        <p>BOC A–60. 1. Tunis, as the first sizeable city recaptured from Nazi
                            occupation, offers a realistic indication of the problems which will
                            arise in the return of property and the indemnification of discriminated
                            groups who have suffered at Nazi hands. Our preliminary study of this
                            matter, presented herewith, is based primarily on the treatment accorded
                            to Jewish people in Tunis and was gleaned from conferences with the
                            heads of Jewish groups and other persons in Tunis. Exact figures are not
                            available at present.</p>
                        <p>2. There are about 90,000 Jews in Tunisia as a whole. About 80,000 are
                            descendants of people who have been in the country 2,000 years. They are
                            not subjects of the French, but of the Bey. There are about 5,000–6,000
                            Italian Jews, sent to Tunisia as colonists about 150–200 years ago, who
                            have remained subjects of Italy. Lastly, there are about 5,000 Jews who
                            are French subjects.</p>
                        <p>3. Shortly after the arrival of the Germans in Tunisia on about 8
                            November, 1942, the Nazis commenced to requisition buildings of the Jews
                            for use as offices and dwelling houses. A typical case is the following:
                            A middle class Jewish family in Tunis was notified one evening in early
                            December that they would have to evacuate their apartment the next
                            morning, since it was to be taken over by Italian officers as a
                            residence. The family, more fortunate than many, packed up most of its
                            belongings during the night and moved out the next morning. After 8 May
                            with the departure of the Italians, the family returned. In many cases
                            in which houses were requisitioned for use by the Germans or Italians,
                            damage was done to fixtures and furniture. <pb facs="0293" n="281" xml:id="pg_281"/> Rugs, hangings, furniture, etc. were taken. The
                            Nazis also requisitioned the vehicles owned by Jewish people and obliged
                            them to turn in their radios, refrigerators, firearms, etc. Many of
                            these requisitioned vehicles were damaged and some were sent to Europe.
                            Most of the radios, refrigerators, etc. were sent to Europe. The total
                            cost of this phase of Nazi oppression was estimated at about 30,000,000
                            francs. While some of the requisitioned vehicles have been found and
                            returned, there is, as yet, no program developed for compensation for
                            losses incurred as the result of this type of activity.</p>
                        <p>4. On 6 December, 1942, the Council of the Jewish community in Tunis
                            received an order from the German authorities to produce 2,000 workers,
                            under an arrangement whereby food, clothing, wages, etc. were to be paid
                            for by the Jews. At the cost of an additional 1,000 laborers a 24-hour
                            extension was obtained. On 9 December, 1942, the request not having been
                            complied with, a reign of terror commenced, in which synagogues and
                            schools were broken into, Jews beaten and threatened, and obliged to
                            march long distances. At this point the Jewish Community organized
                            itself and set up services for drafting laborers, feeding, clothing and
                            paying them, as well as supplying them with transportation and medical
                            aid. About 4,000 workers were obtained, and put at work at the airport
                            and harbor in Tunis, at Bizerta, Mateur, Enfidaville, and Cheylus, all
                            points of nearly constant Allied air attacks. The Jews also had to act
                            as policemen, to insure that the workers remained at their jobs despite
                            heavy bombings and maltreatment.</p>
                        <p>5. The Jewish Community was obliged also to shoulder the financial burden
                            of caring for Jewish refugees who came to Tunis from Bizerta and
                            similarly destroyed cities as well as those who lost their homes by
                            other means.</p>
                        <p>6. The funds to meet the expenses referred to above including the costs
                            of feeding and care for the labor gangs were obtained by the Jewish
                            Community by imposing a capital levy of 10–15% upon the property of its
                            members. Mortgages, sales, etc. were resorted to to raise these funds,
                            which were estimated at 60,000,000 francs. At the present time, these
                            mortgages are still outstanding, and in the hands of banks
                            principally.</p>
                        <p>7. On 22 December 1942, the Germans imposed a levy of 20,000,000 francs
                            on the Jewish Community to “pay” for the Anglo-American bombings of
                            non-Jewish property, for which the Jews were said to be responsible
                            because they were friends of the Allies. The head of the Jewish
                            Community endeavored, without success, to raise these funds at the
                            private banks in Tunis, and was obliged to appeal to the Government for
                            aid. The latter authorized the Caisse Fonciere, a semi-public
                            institution, to advance these funds in the form of a loan at 8%
                            interest, with commissions and carrying charges running it up to about
                                <pb facs="0294" n="282" xml:id="pg_282"/> 12%. The loan was secured
                            by mortgages on Jewish estates, those in the country being insisted upon
                            because there was less danger from bombing. The Caisse Fonciere received
                            the funds from the Bank of Algeria, Tunis Branch, and we have been
                            advised that payment was made in Bank of France notes. It was said that
                            these Bank of France notes were subsequently distributed among the Arab
                            and Italian followers of the Nazis. The former head of the Jewish
                            Community has recently approached the Government in Tunisia with a view
                            toward adjusting or deferring the payment of this loan which the Jews
                            are not in a position to meet at present. The Caisse Fonciere threatened
                            foreclosure and a 6 months interest payment of 1,500,000 francs is due.
                            At first the Government was said to have advised the head of the Jewish
                            Community to repay the loan, with interest, and to place a claim against
                            the Germans after the war. The latest indications were that the French
                            authorities had not yet reached a definite decision of the question but
                            were thinking in terms of a moratorium.</p>
                        <p>8. On 15 February, 1943, the Germans, because many of the forced Jewish
                            laborers were leaving the work camps, imposed a fine of 3,000,000 francs
                            on the Community. This fine was paid without resort to the banks, by the
                            sale of jewels, etc. belonging to individual members of the
                            Community.</p>
                        <p>9. On the basis of present estimates, the measures taken by the Germans
                            and Italians against the Jews in the Tunis area, from 8 November, 1942
                            to 8 May, 1943 cost the latter about 100,000,000 francs. No
                            indemnification or relief measures have yet been taken by the French,
                            and, insofar as the bulk of the problem is concerned, none appears to be
                            contemplated.</p>
                        <p>10. From the fact that this memorandum is confined largely to the Jews,
                            it should not be inferred that this class stood alone in regard to
                            discrimination. The case of the Jews is probably the most glaring,
                            because the great majority of them could not be considered enemies of
                            the Nazis or Italians in the technical sense. Furthermore, there appears
                            to have been more physical hardships, and the imposition of fines seems
                            to be an additional measure of oppression. However, vehicles, houses,
                            factories, etc. were requisitioned from the French in Tunis. Machinery
                            was taken away, and forced labor was at least threatened, if not in fact
                            realized. We are canvassing this side of the picture more fully at the
                            present.</p>
                        <p>11. Likewise, a counterpart of this story which we will canvass if [<hi rend="italic">is?</hi>] the matter of increments to Italians and
                            Arabs as the result of this discrimination. Rumors as to these matters
                            have reached us, but it is, of course, more difficult to develop this
                            side of the problem.</p>
                        <p>12. We are also studying the question of real property transfers made
                            during the occupations and endeavoring to obtain as much information as
                            possible on this score.</p>
                        <pb facs="0295" n="283" xml:id="pg_283"/>
                        <p>13. We should appreciate your views on the problems. In this connection,
                            reference might be made to the United Nations Declaration on property
                                transfers.<note n="65" xml:id="d258fn65">For text of declaration of
                                January 5, 1943, see <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_444">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 444</ref>; for further
                                correspondence on this subject, see <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_439">
                                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 439</ref> ff.</note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>