<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom ( (Matthews) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-01-15T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-01-15T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-15T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-15T06:00:00-05:00" n="286"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d286">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/28233: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-15T12:00:00+01:00"
                            >January 15, 1943—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 12:33 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>382. For the President and the Secretary. I have just received the following
                    letter from Mr. Eden, dated January 14: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Thank you for your letter of the 24th December last (Department’s 6536,
                            December 23, 7 p.m.) in which you conveyed to me the views of the
                            Department of State on the recent Italian ‘peace feelers’, about which I
                            wrote to the Ambassador on the 17th December (Embassy’s 7188, December
                            18, 4 p.m.).</p>
                        <p>I am glad to notice that the State Department agree with the decision we
                            have reached not to pursue negotiations with representatives of the
                            Fascist regime such as the Italian diplomats at Lisbon. I fully concur
                            in the view of the State Department that the guarantees required by the
                            Duke of Aosta would need fuller investigation both from the military and
                            the diplomatic point of view. In order to furnish the State Department
                            with the views of His Majesty’s Government <pb facs="0331" n="319"
                                xml:id="pg_319"/> on the attitude which should be adopted towards
                            any opposition leaders who may come forward, I think it will be
                            necessary for me to summarize briefly the general policy which His
                            Majesty’s Government are in favor of pursuing towards Italy. Any
                            conclusions should not, of course, be interpreted as hard and fast
                            rules, and in fact it is our view that our policy towards Italy must to
                            a large extent be opportunist and readily adaptable to take advantage of
                            any change in the situation.</p>
                        <p>Our aim must be to knock Italy out of the war as quickly as possible and
                            this could be achieved with almost equal effect whether Italy made a
                            separate peace or whether dissatisfaction and disorder within the
                            country attained such serious proportions that the Germans were forced
                            to establish a full scale occupation. In the latter event it is to be
                            expected that the Germans would not only have to provide troops for the
                            occupation of Italy but would also be forced to replace the Italian
                            troops on the Russian front, in France and in the Balkans. Our own
                            military authorities share the doubts expressed in your letter as to the
                            value of Italy even as an ally against Germany. In their view it may
                            well be in our interest that Italy should, as a member of the Axis,
                            develop into a German commitment and become as such an increasing drain
                            on German strength.</p>
                        <p>We have considered the possibility of a party arising in Italy which
                            would be willing and able to conclude a separate peace. Before this
                            situation could occur, two prerequisites would in our view be essential.
                            The Germans would have to be so weakened as no longer to be able to
                            control events in Italy, and a national leader would have to emerge with
                            sufficient strength to displace Mussolini. Such evidence as we have
                            recently received does not suggest that either of these prerequisites
                            are likely to be fulfilled in the immediate future. In particular, there
                            is as yet no sign of an alternative leader to Mussolini appearing. Of
                            the Italians outside Italy, Count Sforza<note n="8" xml:id="d286fn8"
                                >Count Carlo Sforza, Italian Foreign Minister before the advent of
                                Mussolini; leader of Italian anti-Fascists, in North and South
                                America.</note> has probably the most influence, but we feel that he
                            has been out of the country for so long now that he could count on very
                            little support in Italy. In Italy itself there seems little prospect
                            that the Church will take a stand against the regime. The King is
                            regarded as a willing tool of Fascism and the Italian people appear no
                            longer to be looking to him as a leader. In spite of the recent approach
                            by the Duke of Aosta, we remain extremely doubtful of the willingness or
                            ability of any of the royal family to lead a revolt against Fascism. A
                            general with sufficient following in the Army, such as General Badoglio,
                            might at the right moment be able to overthrow the Government, but our
                            reports do not indicate that dissatisfaction in the Army has yet reached
                            the stage which would make this a practicable possibility. Finally,
                            there is the possibility that the moderate members of the Fascist Party
                            itself might take a stand against Mussolini. Such evidence as we have,
                            however, tends to show that the leaders of the Fascist Party as a whole
                            are still united and still convinced that cooperation with Germany and
                            the prosecution of the war is essential if their own position is to be
                            maintained.</p>
                        <p>The view of His Majesty’s Government is, therefore, that we should <pb
                                facs="0332" n="320" xml:id="pg_320"/> not count on the possibility
                            of a separate peace but should aim at provoking such disorder in Italy
                            as would necessitate a German occupation. We suggest that the best means
                            of achieving this aim is to intensify all forms of military operations
                            against Italy, particularly aerial bombardment, and to support the
                            military operations by a firm line in our propaganda.</p>
                        <p>We have given careful consideration to the question of attempting to
                            detach the Italian people from the regime by promising them lenient
                            peace terms, but we have decided that the moment has not yet come to
                            make any such assurances. The minimum which would be likely to appeal to
                            the Italian people would be a guarantee of the pre-war frontiers of
                            Metropolitan Italy, but since it may be desirable after the war to
                            effect frontier rectifications in favor of Yugoslavia and possibly of
                            Austria, it would in our view be most unwise to commit ourselves on this
                            point. Any assurances which fall short of this would be likely to react
                            against us by providing the Fascist Government with a powerful weapon of
                            propaganda. We hold, therefore, that our own propaganda policy should be
                            aimed at convincing the Italians that we shall win the war and that they
                            will suffer most grievously so long as they remain our enemies. We may
                            hope that once the Italian people have been convinced of this they will
                            be ready to take a stand against the present Government either without
                            prior assurances from us or on such terms as we shall be disposed to
                            offer them when the time comes.</p>
                        <p>The view of His Majesty’s Government is, therefore, that no reliance may
                            be put in the possibility of a separate peace in the near future. Should
                            offers be received they would be examined on their merits and military
                            considerations would naturally weigh very heavily in the balance.
                            Meanwhile, we should aim at provoking an internal collapse in Italy. In
                            pursuance of this policy we should as far as possible intensify our
                            military attack on Italy, stress in our political warfare the
                            hopelessness of Italy’s military position and the determination of the
                            United Nations to pursue the war with the utmost vigour against Italy,
                            and generally encourage and help the discontented elements in Italy
                            itself whenever we are able to do so without unduly committing ourselves
                            on political issues.</p>
                        <p>I shall be very glad to receive the views of the United States Government
                            on the policy suggested in this letter.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
