<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-07-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="298" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">President <persName type="from">Roosevelt</persName>
                                to the British Prime Minister</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Churchill</hi></persName>)<note n="33" type="source" xml:id="d298fn33">Copy of telegram obtained from the
                                Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park, N.Y.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-07-26">July 26, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>324. By coincidence I was again at Shangri La<note n="34" xml:id="d298fn34">Camp used by President Roosevelt in the Catoctin
                                Mountains, Maryland, about 65 miles from Washington.</note> this
                            afternoon when the news from Rome came,<note n="35" xml:id="d298fn35">The resignation of Prime Minister Benito Mussolini and his Cabinet
                                was announced by King Victor Emmanuel on July 25. Field Marshal
                                Pietro Badoglio was appointed Prime Minister.</note> but this time
                            it seems to be true. If any overtures come we must be certain of the use
                            of all Italian territory and transportation against the Germans in the
                            North and against the whole Balkan peninsula, as well as use of
                            airfields of all kinds. It is my thought that we should come as close as
                            possible to unconditional surrender followed by good treatment of the
                            Italian populace. But I think also that the head devil should be
                            surrendered together with his chief partners in crime. In no event
                            should our officers in the field fix on any general terms without your
                            approval and mine. Let me have your thoughts.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Roosevelt</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>