<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Vice Consul at Algiers ( (McBride) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d326</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">326</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-09-09T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-09-09T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recXODnXWMHfVPqSC" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances">Military cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-09-09T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-09-09T15:00:00-05:00" n="326"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d326">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 European War 1939/1692: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Vice Consul at Algiers</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McBride</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-09-09T21:00:00+01:00"
                            >September 9, 1943—9 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received September 10—12:14 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1565. From Murphy.<note n="78" xml:id="d326fn78">Robert D. Murphy, Chief Civil
                        Affairs Officer at Algiers; United States Political Adviser on the staff of
                        the Supreme Allied Commander, Mediterranean Theater; Personal Representative
                        of President Roosevelt in North Africa.</note> Refer <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Agwar</hi> telegrams J. 9411. Macmillan<note n="79" xml:id="d326fn79"
                        >Harold Macmillan, British Minister Resident at Allied Headquarters in North
                        Africa.</note> and I called on Massigli<note n="80" xml:id="d326fn80">René
                        Massigli, Commissioner for Foreign Affairs of the French Committee of
                        National Liberation.</note> at 5:30 p.m., September 8, to inform him of
                    impending announcement General Eisenhower of a military armistice with Italy.
                    Communicated to him text of General Eisenhower’s announcement.<note n="81"
                        xml:id="d326fn81">For text of General Eisenhower’s radio announcement on
                        September 8, 1943, of Italian military armistice, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >United States and Italy, 1936–1946</hi>, p. 50.</note> Massigli’s
                    satisfaction that Italy would cease hostilities against Allies was overshadowed
                    by his indignation and regret that French Committee of National Liberation had
                    not been consulted and kept informed of negotiations leading up to
                    armistice.</p>
                <pb facs="0374" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/>
                <p>In that connection it should be said that in complying with Department’s 1583,
                    August 28, 6 p.m.,<note n="82" xml:id="d326fn82">Not printed.</note> instructing
                    me to inform French of outline of complete armistice terms I carefully refrained
                    from any statement regarding active negotiations. Macmillan however in a
                    probably overzealous desire to quiet French apprehensions in this respect had
                    told French at the time that no negotiations were in progress. Massigli said he
                    could not advise us strongly enough that French be consulted a priori before
                    conclusion of complete armistice terms with Italy. He said that after all we
                    must recognize that France has a greater interest in Italy than some other
                    countries such as China and Brazil. In his opinion French people would never
                    understand or forgive us if we disregard French interests in our longer term
                    dealings with Italians.</p>
                <p>As General Giraud<note n="83" xml:id="d326fn83">Gen. Henri Honoré Giraud,
                        Co-Chairman of the French Committee of National Liberation.</note> is absent
                    on an inspection trip in Morocco, Macmillan and I in agreement with Chief of
                    Staff also called on de Gaulle<note n="84" xml:id="d326fn84">Gen. Charles de
                        Gaulle, Co-Chairman of the French Committee of National Liberation.</note> a
                    few minutes before broadcast of General Eisenhower’s declaration and conveyed
                    foregoing information to him. His reaction was milder than we had expected but
                    tinged with bitterness. He congratulated Allies on having obliged Italy to take
                    this decision but said that insofar as French were concerned their position
                    vis-à-vis Italy was unchanged. He failed to understand why French had not been
                    consulted because of obvious interests in it which they possess. We emphasized
                    that present arrangement is of a military character but he was quick to point
                    out that according to Eisenhower’s declaration the Governments of USA, Great
                    Britain and Soviet Union had approved [?] therefore political considerations
                    were involved and it was obvious France had been ignored and slighted. (De
                    Gaulle was visibly impressed by the news that approval of Soviet Union had been
                    given). De Gaulle also asserted that decision to accept Italian military
                    cooperation involved very definite political consideration on which French
                    authorities were entitled to have been consulted. We informed de Gaulle that as
                    our Governments regard armistice strictly as a military instrument signed by
                    soldiers and as French Commander-in-Chief has been kept generally informed of
                    steps leading to the armistice we considered that his objections are not well
                    founded. He shrugged his shoulders saying he did not understand this reference
                    to French Commander-in-Chief.</p>
                <p>Department might also be interested to know that when we emphasized that de
                    Gaulle as a soldier would be the first to understand military necessities
                    involved and appreciate that present action so advantageous <pb facs="0375"
                        n="363" xml:id="pg_363"/> to French people had many features of a <hi
                        rend="italic">ruse de guerre</hi> he promptly replied he was not a soldier
                    but he represented France’s political interests. At the time he spoke he was
                    wearing gun uniform of a Brigadier General in French Army which is his regular
                    costume.</p>
                <p>Thus far general sentiment on part of North African population is mixed. On the
                    one hand there is pleasure and satisfaction over Italian capitulation and on the
                    other a feeling that French interests have not been sufficiently stressed.</p>
                <p>After Committee meeting today Massigli called on me to state suspicion is rife
                    among membership that notwithstanding our declarations a political deal possibly
                    involving Tunisia is involved and that Allies intend to exclude French from
                    consultation regarding complete armistice terms and development of post
                    armistice stages, work of armistice commission, etc. I reassured Massigli
                    referring to our yesterday’s conversation when he was informed that present
                    armistice text of which was communicated informally by AHQ<note n="85"
                        xml:id="d326fn85">Army Headquarters.</note> [to] Giraud is limited to
                    military considerations. He also indicated that his personal situation by reason
                    of his failure to keep Committee informed of this development is adversely
                    affected.</p>
                <p>Massigli urges that Washington and London issue promptly a declaration to effect
                    that the French Committee of National Liberation will be associated in stages
                    which follow present Italian armistice on ground that Committee has
                    responsibility of defending very important French interests which armistice must
                    safeguard. In making that request Massigli emphasized French interest in it by
                    its close geographic and political relationship and fact that French have been
                    actively participating in war against Italians (I had mentioned that Greece and
                    Yugoslavia had not been consulted for some [<hi rend="italic">same?</hi>]
                    reasons though they also had special interests in Italy).</p>
                <p>Macmillan is telegraphing this suggestion to London. We both feel if some
                    comforting, if innocuous, communication could be made it would calm present
                    tempest in a tea cup. [Murphy.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">McBride</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
