<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="365" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d365">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 European War 1939/2024</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In the British Embassy’s memorandum of November 19th, reference was made
                            to the proposal to publish the full terms of the Italian surrender
                            together with the amending protocol.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>His Majesty’s Government feel that as the situation is now
                                developing it will become increasingly difficult to justify the
                                continued non-publication of these documents. Now that the public
                                are aware of the existence of the long terms of surrender, pressure
                                in the United Kingdom in favour of publication will increase, and it
                                will be difficult for His Majesty’s Government to find good reasons
                                for resisting this.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Two arguments may be advanced against publication: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>that it would have a bad effect on the Italian people and
                                        lessen their desire to cooperate, and;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>that it would weaken the Badoglio Government and perhaps
                                        bring on a second Governmental crisis before the Allied
                                        forces reach Rome.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>Neither of these arguments appear to His Majesty’s Government to
                                be particularly strong on close examination.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>As regards (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) it is apparent that most
                                Italians are so apathetic about the war and about politics in
                                general that they would be quite <pb facs="0408" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/> unmoved by the news that their Government had
                                signed a second armistice on the lines foreshadowed in the first But
                                even if there were any force in this argument it would apply equally
                                or more strongly at a later date when the armistice finally came to
                                be published, as at some stage it inevitably must be, and when the
                                disadvantages which are feared would be just as serious or still
                                more so.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The essence of argument (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) is that to
                                publish the armistice would weaken the position of the Badoglio
                                Government by publicly saddling it with the responsibility for what
                                might be regarded as a humiliating document. His Majesty’s
                                Government agree that within the limits permitted by the general
                                apathy referred to in the preceding paragraph there is a possibility
                                of this effect being produced, particularly if the publication took
                                place before the Government had got into its stride. On the other
                                hand the Badoglio Government will sooner or later be succeeded by a
                                new Government. There is a risk that unless the new Government are
                                informed about it and accept the armistice in advance they will
                                later repudiate it, or alternatively if they accept the armistice,
                                their followers, when the terms are eventually published, will
                                oblige them to repudiate it or try to overthrow them. The best way
                                to minimise a risk of this kind is to make the terms public well
                                before the Badoglio Government is likely to be changed. The
                                obligations and responsibilities of its successors will then be
                                clear for all to see.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The amending protocol has now been signed. The Badoglio Government
                                is now as firmly in the saddle as it can ever be expected to be. The
                                long terms and the amending protocol have been communicated to the
                                Allied Governments. His Majesty’s Government therefore feel that
                                this is the appropriate moment for publication of the terms, and
                                that continued failure to publish will expose them to considerable
                                criticism.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Although His Majesty’s Government do not believe that the Soviet
                                Government were a party to the original agreement to keep the long
                                terms secret, as suggested in General Eisenhower’s telegram to the
                                combined Chiefs of Staff, NAF 508 of November 6th, they would in any
                                case propose before proceeding to publication to ask His Majesty’s
                                Ambassador at Moscow to confirm that the Soviet Government have no
                                objection.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>His Majesty’s Government earnestly hope that the United States
                                Government will agree to early publication. They would be grateful
                                for a reply as soon as may be convenient.<note n="46" xml:id="d365fn46">See memorandum by the Under Secretary of
                                    State, December 1, 1943, <ref target="#pg_398">p.
                                    398</ref>.</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-23">November
                                    23, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>