<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-10-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-10-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="377"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d377">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Italy)/10–1643</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On October 2nd Mr. Wright<note n="71" xml:id="d377fn71">Michael Wright, First
                        Secretary of the British Embassy.</note> left with Mr. Dunn a copy of a
                    telegram from the Foreign Office in which it was suggested that it would be
                    desirable to offer the Soviet Government a satisfactory <pb facs="0421" n="409"
                        xml:id="pg_409"/> position on the Control Commission for Italy<note n="72"
                        xml:id="d377fn72">Regarding the establishment of the Control Commission, see
                            <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_793">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp.
                            793</ref>–<ref target="frus1943v01#pg_794">794</ref>.</note> or whatever
                    authority was set up to ensure the carrying out of the surrender terms (a copy
                    of this telegram is attached for convenience of reference<note n="73"
                        xml:id="d377fn73">Not printed.</note>).</p>
                <p>In a message to President Roosevelt of October 8th (No. 442<note n="74"
                        xml:id="d377fn74">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_384">p. 384</ref>.</note>),
                    Mr. Churchill suggested that it would be a good thing to tell Monsieur
                        Molotov<note n="75" xml:id="d377fn75">V. M. Molotov, People’s Commissar for
                        Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union.</note> that the Soviet Government’s
                    desire to play their part in the control of Italy was understood, and that it
                    was hoped to propose a scheme to them in the near future which should meet their
                    requirements. Mr. Churchill suggested that General Eisenhower should be asked to
                    submit a scheme for consideration. He understood from Mr. Macmillan, who was in
                    London, that this could be done without undue difficulty.</p>
                <p>Sir Ronald Campbell has now been instructed to repeat the suggestion that General
                    Eisenhower should be asked if he can devise a method of associating the U. S. S.
                    R., the French and the other interested Allies with the Italian Control
                    Commission.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-10-16">16 October,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
