<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Winant) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d494</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">494</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-10-13T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-10-13T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-10-13T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-10-13T14:00:00-05:00" n="494"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d494">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">741.53/135: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-10-13T20:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 13, 1943—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 13—5:21 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6993. On receiving your 6116 on October 4 I communicated its contents both to the
                    Prime Minister and to Mr. Eden. On October 8 I received your 6235 and replied
                    immediately on its decoding in my 6856, October 8, 12 midnight.<note n="81"
                        xml:id="d494fn81">Latter not printed; Ambassador Winant stated he believed
                        it was in the interest of the United States to postpone assuring Salazar of
                        American respect for sovereignty of Portuguese colonies (741.53/126).</note>
                    You in turn replied in your 6268, October 9<note n="82" xml:id="d494fn82">Not
                        printed (741.53/126); it reported that instructions had been sent to the
                        ChargS in Portugal simultaneously with the dispatch of Department’s telegram
                        No. 6235, October 8, to London, <ref target="#pg_550">p. 550</ref>.</note>
                    but followed it up with your 6308, October 9.<note n="83" xml:id="d494fn83">Not
                        printed; it reported that the Chargé in Portugal had been instructed to take
                        no further action pending new instructions from the Department
                        (741.53/130c).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Since then I have talked several times with the Prime Minister, Mr. Eden, Sir
                    Alexander Cadogan<note n="84" xml:id="d494fn84">Permanent Under Secretary of
                        State in the British Foreign Office.</note> and Mr. Roberts<note n="85"
                        xml:id="d494fn85">Frank K. Roberts, Acting Head of the Central Department of
                        the British Foreign Office.</note> of the Foreign <pb facs="0564" n="552"
                        xml:id="pg_552"/> Office who sat in with Ambassador Campbell during the
                    negotiations with Salazar. The outcome of these conversations which contains our
                    combined judgment is embodied in the directive given below forwarded by the
                    Foreign Office today to Ambassador Campbell and repeated to Washington. I hope
                    you will approve of my action and the approach therein suggested. The text below
                    is a direct quotation of the message referred to. It reestablishes the position
                    taken by the Department in its 6116 October 4, 2 p.m. You might want to send a
                    further explanatory to our Chargé d’Affaires in Lisbon.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>Begin directive:</p>
                    <p>“In view of original American decision reported in Washington telegram No.
                            4449<note n="86" xml:id="d494fn86">See telegram No. 6116, October 4, to
                            London, <ref target="#pg_547">p. 547</ref>.</note> to communicate United
                        States assurances if and only if requested to do so by Dr. Salazar, it was
                        felt, after discussion with United States Ambassador here, that we should
                        acquiesce in this decision and that we should ourselves make such use as we
                        could of the United States assurances when the time comes to approach Dr.
                        Salazar with a view to extending our facilities. (Further instructions on
                        this will follow in due course.)</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Later United States decision to communicate assurances without further
                            delay, although unexpected, was not unwelcome to us, and we were then
                            prepared to let matters take their course. United States Ambassador,
                            however, in view of earlier conversations referred to above himself
                            advised delay. Hence the countermanding instructions to United States
                            Chargé d’Affaires reported in paragraph 2 of your telegram No.
                            2062.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We have now advised United States Ambassador that in view (<hi
                                rend="italic">a</hi>) of our communication about United States
                            assurances made to Dr. Salazar last June, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                            of action already taken by United States Chargé d’Affaires with both Dr.
                            Salazar and Dr. Leitao, it might only arouse suspicion and prejudice the
                            atmosphere for our further conversations if United States assurances are
                            delayed any longer.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>I understand that United States Ambassador agrees, but he has
                            suggested that in order to explain the circumstances of United States
                            Chargé d’Affaires’ approach, the line should be taken with Dr. Salazar
                            that, having regard to the Portuguese desire to maintain neutrality and
                            to avoid unnecessary provocation to Germany, the United States
                            Government on reflection thought that it might only embarrass him to
                            receive the United States assurances just before public announcement of
                            the Azores Agreement. United States Government were however ready to
                            communicate these assurances now or at such time as Dr. Salazar
                            considered most appropriate.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Although actual communication on above lines must of course be left to
                            United States Chargé d’Affaires, you might, after explaining the
                            situation to him, also explain it to the Portuguese Government.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>You should inform your United States colleague of above, but no action
                            should be taken by you or by him pending receipt of further instructions
                            from Washington.”</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>End directive.</p>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
