<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-10-20T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-10-20T08:00:00-05:00" n="502" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d502">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.34553B/6: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kennan</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-10-20T14:00:00+01:00">October
                                    20, 1943—2 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 11:03 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2469. For the Under Secretary and Matthews. Department’s 1816, October
                            19, 1 p.m. My telegram was based on the belief that if we approach
                            Salazar with this entire program, at this time, he will not only refuse
                            us outright but will henceforth view with great suspicion even any minor
                            desiderata we may later advance with respect to the Azores. In other
                            words, he will slam the door entirely and it will not be easy to get him
                            to open it again. The reasons for this belief are as follows:</p>
                        <p>1. Salazar is not prepared for anything of this sort.</p>
                        <p>No mention of it was made to him during British negotiations. He assented
                            to British requests reluctantly and only in part. Even this assent was
                            given solely on basis of alliance and he thought that when he had given
                            it he had satisfied all demands.</p>
                        <p>2. He feels that he has strained his relations with the Germans to utmost
                            already and that he will be lucky if he gets off with sinking of a ship
                            or two and possibly some reprisals in Azores area. The idea of giving
                            the Germans further cause for offense at this moment would appall
                            him.</p>
                        <pb facs="0571" n="559" xml:id="pg_559"/>
                        <p>I cannot disagree with this analysis. German-Portuguese relations seem
                            indeed perilously close to the breaking point. Any further strain may
                            well cause complications which would run counter to our desire to keep
                            the Peninsula quiet at this juncture.</p>
                        <p>3. Salazar who fears association with us only slightly less than with the
                            Russians has made a great point of the argument that in dickering with
                            the British, he was only honoring an agreement which existed long before
                            this war began and that his concessions were not to the United Nations
                            as such, a temporary anti-Axis constellation, but only to Portugal’s
                            historic relationship to England. This was one of the arguments on which
                            he relied to keep the Germans quiet.</p>
                        <p>4. German propaganda directed to Portugal has recently plugged the line
                            “Now you’ll see what you’ve gotten yourselves in for; the British
                            agreement was only the beginning, other demands will follow from other
                            members of the United Nations, the Americans are in the background and
                            will soon want facilities of their own et cetera,”</p>
                        <p>5. What we are asking is not only much more than what the British got: It
                            considerably surpasses what they originally requested.</p>
                        <p>Our existing program advanced at this time would confirm Salazar’s fears
                            that we want nothing less than the whole archipelago, lock, stock and
                            barrel, and it might very well make him adamant against even the mildest
                            of further requests. It is true that when the Portuguese are willing to
                            dicker, it is well to start by asking for plenty. When they are afraid
                            to dicker and fear that their hand is going to be forced, the opposite
                            is more apt to apply.</p>
                        <p>6. I have no <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> to offer to Salazar.</p>
                        <p>While the British did not definitely undertake to defend the Portuguese
                            mainland, they went so far as they could in this direction and Salazar
                            probably feels that by honoring the alliance, he has in effect engaged
                            them to do the same. He knows that they have guaranteed to respect the
                            integrity of his empire. He also has their assurance that they will get
                            out of the islands when the war is over. He doubtless hopes that he has
                            committed them by implication to the support of his regime. He has also
                            obtained advantages in the line of supplies from overseas and merchant
                            shipping facilities for which he is inclined to thank the British.</p>
                        <p>7. The British Ambassador here has no instructions which would enable him
                            to support us in these requests.</p>
                        <p>He has in fact the impression that our program is the same one which was
                            at one time submitted to London by the American Committee of the Joint
                            Chiefs of Staff and was rejected by London as excessive, and he is at a
                            loss to explain its reappearance here. He has instructions to support us
                            only in certain specific requests for the use by us in individual
                            instances of facilities already granted to the British and in our
                            general desire to operate ferry service via the Azores. He fears that if
                            I go to Salazar with the existing program Salazar will only call him at
                            once to account and reproach him for not giving warning in the preceding
                            negotiations that any concessions made to England would be followed by
                            even greater demands from us.</p>
                        <p>8. A number of the facilities we are asking for are ones which were
                            flatly refused to the British.</p>
                        <p>Salazar in his talks with the British would not hear of facilities on São
                            Miguel Island for the reason that it is the center of Portuguese <pb facs="0572" n="560" xml:id="pg_560"/> administration in the islands.
                            The permission to use an airfield there occasionally for emergency
                            landings was granted only with much reluctance. Santa Maria and Flores
                            Islands never came into question. At no place did the British request a
                            full-fledged naval base of their own. Our desire to station naval
                            vessels in any Azores ports we like goes much beyond the British desire
                            to have a mercantile marine tanker and tug at Horta. Finally what we are
                            asking in the line of communications not only exceeds British requests
                            but would turn both British and American cable facilities in the islands
                            into relay stations for our conduct of the war in Europe.</p>
                        <p>So much for the negative side. The question now arises what can we then
                            do to gain our objective.</p>
                        <p>My answer to this is as follows:</p>
                        <p>Unless we are willing to connive at the overthrow of Dr. Salazar, which
                            would involve a responsibility I shudder to contemplate, we must gain
                            his confidence. Our assurances of last fall<note n="3" xml:id="d502fn3">Reference is to President Roosevelt’s letter of November 8, 1942,
                                to President Carmona of Portugal, assuring him that the presence of
                                American Forces in French North Africa presaged no threat to
                                Portugal or her island possessions; for text of letter, see
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November 14,
                                1942, p. 905.</note> and our forbearance during the British talks
                            have already made a beginning in this direction. I have reason to
                            believe that my recent talk with him was likewise helpful.</p>
                        <p>My suggestion would be that instead of calling upon him to make another
                            anti-German demonstration on the heels of the first one—which was quite
                            enough for his nerves—we now endeavor first to slip quietly and
                            gradually through the gap which the British have succeeded in opening
                            for us. …</p>
                        <p>I think that for the moment we should proceed in the most disarming and
                            inconspicuous manner possible to work in an occasional American ship and
                            plane to the use of the facilities, gradually increasing this practice,
                            according to the degree of resilience we encounter.</p>
                        <p>Once the Portuguese have been conditioned to the presence of American
                            planes and ships around the islands and we have thus gotten our foot in
                            the door, I think we could well approach Salazar with the proposition
                            that the intertwining of our war effort with that of England makes it
                            impossible for our Armed Forces to be excluded from bases used by
                            England but that administrative considerations require in some cases
                            that the physical facilities used by our forces at those bases be kept
                            separate from those of the British; that for this reason we must ask
                            Portugal to permit us to set up certain separate establishments of our
                            own in the islands similar—and wherever possible adjacent—to those of
                            the British. The British Ambassador would presumably be able to support
                            us in such a proposal and he could then make good use of the “friends of
                            friends” argument which is a brilliant and constructive thought. Whoever
                            negotiates the <pb facs="0573" n="561" xml:id="pg_561"/> agreement on
                            our behalf should be authorized to make judicial use at the proper time
                            of assurances to respect Portuguese sovereignty in all Portuguese
                            possessions and also not to retain the facilities after the war without
                            the agreement of the Portuguese Government. He should know just how far
                            he can go in promising military support in the event of repercussions
                            from Germany. He should be allowed also to play with our economic
                            warfare pressure which might well be built up in advance as a bargaining
                            factor. Finally, he should know whether it is the intention of our
                            Government to make an open agreement which would be published to the
                            world like the recent British arrangement; or whether we would be
                            prepared to make an informal arrangement and to play down publicity to
                            the maximum degree with a view to easing the shock to German-Portuguese
                            relations. The latter should not be technically impossible in view of
                            the rigid censorship in the islands; and it would undoubtedly sweeten
                            the pill for Salazar. The above procedure may not give us all that we
                            want. But it would reduce the risk of our getting nothing at all.</p>
                        <p>I appreciate deeply the President’s generosity in allowing me to state
                            these views. They reflect of course only a local outlook and are not
                            intended to constitute a general picture of all the broader factors
                            involved which I realize only the President is in a position to
                            survey.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Kennan</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>