<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Portugal ( (Crocker) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">505</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-10-31T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-10-31T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-10-31T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-10-31T12:00:00-05:00" n="505"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d505">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.34553B/16: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Crocker</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-10-31T17:00:00+00:00"
                            >October 31, 1943—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 10:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2599. For the Under Secretary and Matthews. For Kennan.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d505fn5">Mr. Kennan was temporarily in Washington for
                        consultation.</note> As a result of a previous conversation of which you
                    have knowledge <pb facs="0575" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/> between Solborg<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d505fn6">Col. Robert A. Solborg, American Military Attaché in
                        Portugal.</note> and Carvalhaes, the Under Secretary for War<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d505fn7">Fernando dos Santos Costa.</note> yesterday invited Solborg
                    to call upon him for the first time. The following is a brief resume of the
                    conversation: Carvalhaes stated that the substance of Solborg’s earlier
                    conversation with him had been conveyed to Salazar who reacted favorably and
                    consequently requested the Under Secretary to have this talk with Solborg. The
                    conversation began with a somewhat extended outline of Portugal’s early history
                    and the background of the Anglo-Portuguese Alliance which was based primarily
                    upon geographical considerations (here the Under Secretary pointed out in
                    support of this thesis that relations with Britain had not always been of the
                    best especially during the last war when Portuguese troops were not particularly
                    well treated in the field, et cetera). It was, of course, impossible to refuse
                    Britain’s request for facilities in the Azores under the terms of this Alliance.
                    He then stated that the geographical situation in the modern world had been
                    modified owing to astonishing advances in transportation, communications, modern
                    thought and other factors in such a way as to make it comprehensible and logical
                    that the United States should be brought closer to Portugal. “We are not
                    unmindful of this fact” he said.</p>
                <p>He emphasized, however, that Portugal’s primary doctrine was that of strict
                    neutrality which it was determined to preserve under all conditions.</p>
                <p>Solborg then pointed out that the United States and Britain were fighting this
                    war as allies and he wished to ask the Under Secretary whether he did not feel
                    that as an ally of Portugal’s ally—“Friends of Friends” so to speak—the United
                    States might not expect to enjoy a more favored position vis-á-vis Portugal than
                    say enemies of Portugal’s ally. The Under Secretary admitted that within certain
                    limitations such was undoubtedly the case. For instance, he continued,
                    recognizing the ever growing needs of the United States in connection with the
                    prosecution of the war, Portugal would favorably envisage, provided it remained
                    both a pattern of the Anglo-Portuguese Agreement, to accord to the United States
                    similar facilities, as for example, in connection with convoys.</p>
                <p>Solborg signified his assent to the foregoing and the subject was pursued no
                    further, the conversation turning on other matters chiefly in connection with
                    the desirability of an improvement in commercial relations in the postwar
                    world.</p>
                <p>These then are the highlights of the conversations and the points I have touched
                    upon have been carefully checked with Solborg as to their accuracy.</p>
                <pb facs="0576" n="564" xml:id="pg_564"/>
                <p>In conveying the foregoing to you I am not unmindful of the difficulty of
                    evaluating properly at such a distance the true import of this conversation. I
                    am, however, persuaded that we would be on safe ground in concluding that the
                    Under Secretary, probably reflecting Salazar’s thoughts, wished to create the
                    impression that he has at least an open mind in respect to an approach on the
                    question of granting certain facilities to us. Neither Solborg nor myself have
                    the impression that there was anything in the Under Secretary’s statements which
                    would justify the conclusion that we would necessarily be held within the
                    precise limits of the British agreement.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Crocker</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
