<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Spain ( (Hayes) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d590</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">590</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-11-22T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-11-22T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-22T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-22T14:00:00-05:00" n="590"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d590">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M) Spain/1191: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hayes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-22T20:00:00+01:00"
                            >November 22, 1943—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 23—1:05 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3449. Before presenting the memo contained in my 3398, November 18, 7 p.m., I
                    ascertained that British Embassy had not received instructions to support my
                    request. However, it agreed to do so in general terms although it has made no
                    representations in the matter since I submitted my memo. Furthermore in absence
                    of instructions in the matter the British Embassy is unwilling to specify a <hi
                        rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi>. It perceives no serious objection to
                    suppression of overcharges on goods originating in British Isles (we understand
                    only product in this category is copper sulphate) but is reluctant to recommend
                    suppression of overcharges on goods originating in Empire or Colonial areas.</p>
                <p>British Embassy furthermore does not favor interrupting proposed large purchases
                    of seasonal goods such as oranges. These, of course, must be purchased promptly
                    if they are to be purchased at all. Ellis-Rees<note n="91" xml:id="d590fn91"
                        >Hugh Ellis-Rees, Financial Adviser of the British Embassy in Spain.</note>
                    was informed by Ministry of Food that goods are needed for supply reasons and
                    British have already contracted for onions, bitter <pb facs="0671" n="659"
                        xml:id="pg_659"/> oranges and lemons, leaving some 110,000 tons of sweet
                    oranges yet to be negotiated for.</p>
                <p>Aside from purely seasonal aspect, which is of immediate importance, Spain is
                    normally important source of British food supplies and British Embassy is
                    reluctant to take action which might threaten that trade and they hesitate to
                    risk it by endeavoring to use it as a weapon in seeking wolfram embargo.</p>
                <p>In other words, we understand British here consider there are two obvious
                    difficulties: (1) Timing of effort to obtain wolfram embargo is bad since
                    seasonal purchases of foodstuffs from this year’s crop, which are being made at
                    insistence of Ministry of Food, must be made now or not at all, (2) retention of
                    Spain as a source of food and other supplies entering into British traditional
                    trade is an objective comparable in importance in eyes of British Embassy to
                    proposed wolfram embargo. British hesitate to risk first objective in seeking
                    second.</p>
                <p>My own view is that British attach insufficient weight to: (1) Spain’s urgent
                    need to sell surplus orange crop; (2) value to Spain of selling crop to British
                    and thus increasing its ability to purchase wide range of products available in
                    sterling area.</p>
                <p>In contrast to the British position we do not require any products which Spain
                    traditionally supplies to us and therefore the maintenance of our traditional
                    purchases in Spain is not an objective in itself. Furthermore since our normal
                    purchases average less than 10% of Spain’s exports while British purchases
                    average nearly 25%, our traditional trade is not as important as a source of
                    Spanish purchasing power and therefore is not as substantial a weapon as is
                    British traditional trade in our effort to obtain a wolfram embargo.</p>
                <p>On the other hand our ability to supply, and Spain’s dependence upon us for many
                    of its most essential requirements give to us a more potent withholding weapon
                    than the British possess. Of Spanish total imports we normally supplied 16-plus
                    percent whereas the United Kingdom supplies only 10%. In addition we now control
                    petroleum supplies.</p>
                <p>It is obvious that by forging together into a single weapon British traditional
                    purchases and American supplies our chances for obtaining the desired wolfram
                    embargo would be much better than if we rely solely upon the American supply and
                    purchase capacity.</p>
                <p>In order to overcome any possibility of objections of the British on the ground
                    of immediate needs, it might be helpful if we could assure them of supplies of
                    oranges in the event the wolfram negotiations are so long delayed that the
                    British may miss the opportunity of acquiring the incoming crop.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hayes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
