<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Winant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d729</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">729</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-11-19T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-11-19T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recUInGVZ0Y3MeuOS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-19T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-19T23:00:00-05:00" n="729"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d729">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">103.917/4711: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-20T00:00:00-04:00"
                            >November 20, 1943—midnight</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>7367. From Department and Stone, FEA. Reference your 7898 of Nov. 12 and
                    Stockholm’s 3539, Oct. 29<note n="15" xml:id="d729fn15">Latter not
                        printed.</note> repeated to you as the Legation’s 713. Department, FEA and
                    the military authorities are most disturbed about the very high level of iron
                    ore shipments in 1943. Department and FEA thoroughly agree with the Embassy and
                    MEW as to the desirability of making immediate representations to the Swedes
                    regarding this matter. However, we would prefer to have a joint memorandum along
                    the lines set forth below presented to the Swedes. Even if Mallet has already
                    made representations we believe the joint memorandum should nevertheless be
                    presented.</p>
                <pb facs="0832" n="820" xml:id="pg_820"/>
                <p>Although we may not be able to prevent exports in 1943 from reaching the level
                    mentioned by Hägglöf<note n="16" xml:id="d729fn16">Gunnar Hägglöf, head of the
                        Economic Division, Swedish Ministry for Foreign Affairs; he served as
                        Chairman of the Swedish Trade Delegation in London.</note> we fear that
                    protest is futile unless accompanied by a request for positive remedial action
                    on the part of the Swedes. We should attempt at least to reduce the harmful
                    effects of the high and unexpected rate of export in 1943 by insisting on a low
                    figure for the first quarter of 1944. Therefore, while leaving to you and MEW
                    the exact wording we believe the following points should be strongly emphasized
                    in the communication to the Swedes: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The United States and the United Kingdom Governments even before the
                            signing of the new agreement<note n="17" xml:id="d729fn17">On September
                                23, 1943, the War Trade Agreement between the United States, the
                                United Kingdom, and Sweden was initialed in London; for texts, see
                                enclosures to despatch No. 11348, September 24, from the Ambassador
                                in the United Kingdom, <ref target="#pg_806">pp. 806</ref>, <ref
                                    target="#pg_807">807</ref>, and <ref target="#pg_809"
                                >809</ref>.</note> fulfilled their obligations in full, even in
                            cases where the supply sacrifice involved was substantially greater than
                            had been anticipated during the negotiations.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The Swedish Government in Section IV of the new war trade agreement
                            undertakes to take measures to reduce Swedish exports to Germany and
                            associated countries and occupied territories until the end of 1943
                            wherever possible within the framework of existing obligations.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The United States and the United Kingdom are at a loss to reconcile
                            exports of iron ore in 1943 at the level forecast by Mr. Hägglöf with
                            the commitment cited above in Section IV of the Swedish Declaration or
                            with the spirit of the agreements reached in London. Swedish exports of
                            iron ore to Germany and associated countries and occupied territories
                            averaged 9,116,000 tons during the 3 years, 1940–41–42. If Mr. Hägglöf’s
                            forecast proves correct, and shipments of 8,893,000 tons during the
                            first 10 months of 1943 give every reason to anticipate that it will,
                            Swedish shipments of iron ore for 1943 will be at a very substantially
                            higher rate than during any war year.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The two governments are most concerned regarding the greatly increased
                            shipments this year since they tend to nullify the reduction which the
                            ceiling agreed to for 1944 was expected to achieve. As a result of the
                            discussions in London the Allied Governments assumed that Swedish iron
                            ore exports in 1943 would not exceed the 1942 level of 8.6 million tons.
                            Thus one of the most important benefits which we obtain in the new
                            agreement to compensate for our supply sacrifices is being
                            undermined.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The United States and the United Kingdom Governments appreciate the
                            action taken which resulted in the recent reduction of shipments from
                            Northern Baltic ports. They wish, however, that it <pb facs="0833"
                                n="821" xml:id="pg_821"/> might have been possible for the Swedish
                            Government to develop an equally successful method of similarly limiting
                            shipments from southern Baltic ports.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>The United States and the United Kingdom have always understood from
                            statements made by the Swedish authorities that the Swedish Government
                            has made no specific commitment to Germany on iron ore exports other
                            than a price agreement. The text of the German-Swedish War Trade
                            Agreement for 1943<note n="18" xml:id="d729fn18">Signed on December 19,
                                1942.</note> presented to the United States and the United Kingdom
                            negotiators in London confirms this and indicates that Swedish coal
                            imports are tied to Swedish exports of wood products rather than of iron
                            ore.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>In view of all the above circumstances the United States and the
                            United Kingdom Governments urgently request assurances that: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The Swedish Government will make every effort to keep
                                    shipments of iron ore during the full year 1943 as far below the
                                    ceiling limit of 9.9 million tons provided in the old
                                    Anglo-Swedish War Trade Agreement as is possible at this late
                                    date;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The Swedish Government will not permit shipments of iron ore
                                    during the first quarter of 1944 to exceed 488,000 tons and that
                                    no more than 200,000 tons will be shipped in any one month.
                                    (This proposed first quarter ceiling is based on the average of
                                    first quarter shipments in 1941 and 1942, the last climatically
                                    normal war years. We cannot include figures for the first
                                    quarter of 1943 in the average as we consider 1943 shipments
                                    abnormal.)</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>It might also be pointed out that the proposal outlined above is in the nature of
                    an application of the provision of the new war trade agreement limiting exports
                    in the first half of 1944 to the ratio of previous years.</p>
                <p>If you and MEW concur in the above suggested procedure, please telegraph to
                    Stockholm the agreed wording for the memorandum, requesting the Legation (unless
                    it has strong views to the contrary) to join with the British Legation in
                    presenting it to the Foreign Office, also repeating to Stockholm your 7898 of
                    November 12.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
