<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Winant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d751</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">751</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-06-15T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-06-15T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-06-15T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-06-15T19:00:00-05:00" n="751"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d751">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War 1939/8691d: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-06-15T20:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 15, 1943—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3708. Swiss Legation has presented a memorandum dated June 11<note n="34"
                        xml:id="d751fn34">Not found in Department files.</note> to the effect that
                    Swiss Legation in London recently approached British authorities to inquire
                    whether it would be acceptable to MEW and American delegation to reopen
                    suspended negotiations. The Swiss state that the Federal Council has taken a
                    decision to reopen the London negotiations as soon as possible with delegation
                    consisting of Sulzer and Keller and that they are prepared to submit proposals
                    concerning export restrictions including quotas for undesirable exports groups 3
                    and 4 and for dairy products. The Swiss expressed disappointment with the London
                    reception of this proposal and state that American and British Governments
                    intend to set down in writing the conditions which alone will permit reopening
                    of negotiations. They say that such a step would not be acceptable if the
                    contents of the hoped for negotiations should thereby be anticipated. The Swiss
                    specifically point out that some new credits will have to be given Germany in
                    order to reach an agreement enabling Switzerland to obtain necessary raw
                    materials and they suggest that if they meet us on quotas, further credits would
                    be of small significance. If a general agreement is reached, the Swiss are
                    willing to conclude the financial arrangements. The memorandum concludes with
                    the expression of hope that upon further consideration the proposed visit of the
                    Swiss delegation will be agreeable.</p>
                <pb facs="0859" n="847" xml:id="pg_847"/>
                <p>British Embassy informs Department that on June 9 after discussion with Riefler,
                    British Parliamentary Secretary sent a letter to the Swiss Minister doubting the
                    utility of reopening negotiations unless the Swiss were prepared to inform us in
                    advance as to the subjects they regard as open to discussion.</p>
                <p>We have not received your views or those of Riefler on the present status of
                    Swiss relations but our preliminary views follow: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>We think the Swiss must be under a misapprehension when they state
                            that London intends to impose written conditions to reopening of
                            negotiations. It would seem to us sufficient if the Swiss came to London
                            prepared to meet our desires in principle leaving to the negotiations
                            the precise form of commitment.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The memorandum presented in Washington being subsequent to the
                            approaches by the Swiss in London, may to some extent meet London’s
                            conditions for reopening the negotiations. The Washington memorandum
                            specifically refers to quotas on undesirable exports and to dairy
                            products.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>If really satisfactory quotas are obtained for undesirable exports, an
                            absolute prohibition of all credits may not necessarily be a <hi
                                rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> to a satisfactory solution. This
                            question would have to be examined in the light of concrete
                            proposals.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>On principle it seems wise to attempt to obtain an agreement with the
                            Swiss before they conclude negotiations with the Germans.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>To refuse to meet the Swiss may discourage them to the point where
                            they despair of reaching any agreement with us. This would weaken their
                            desire to resist German demands.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>It seems to us that the Washington memorandum at least provides a
                            basis for reopening the negotiations although amplification and
                            clarification may be desirable. We urgently request your views and those
                            of MEW and Riefler.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
