<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador to the Yugoslav Government in Exile ( (MacVeagh) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-12-16T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-12-16T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-16T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-16T03:00:00-05:00" n="893"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d893">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860H.01/580: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador to the Yugoslav Government in Exile</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-16T10:00:00+02:00"
                            >December 16, 1943—10 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received December 17—1 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5. Yugoslav Series. I secured yesterday from Ambassador Stevenson a copy of his
                    telegram to the Foreign Office reporting Mr. Churchill’s talk with King Peter
                    (see my telegram No. 4, Yugoslav series [<hi rend="italic">Greek 129?</hi>] of
                    December 12, 11 a.m.) and also a subsequent talk with Mr. Puritch. I believe the
                    Department may be interested in this telegram in connection with my No. 124,
                    Greek Series, December 8, 1 p.m., and as background to messages now being
                    prepared in this Embassy. I am therefore paraphrasing it as follows, forwarding
                    the original text by airgram: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“During the course of an audience with King Peter on December 10 Mr.
                            Churchill told him how much he was impressed by the Partisan movement’s
                            significance and strength. At the same time he informed King Peter that
                            the British Government possesses evidence which is irrefutable to the
                            effect that Michailovitch has been collaborating with the enemy and he
                            gave King Peter a warning that the desirability of eliminating
                            Michail[ovitch] from the Cabinet might be suggested to him in the fairly
                            near future by the British Government.</p>
                        <p>“Mr. Churchill saw the Yugoslav Prime Minister that same evening and
                            after repeating to him his impressions regarding the Partisans informed
                            him of the British Government’s intention both to continue and to
                            increase as much as possible British military support to their movement.
                            He then told the Prime Minister of the evidence we possess concerning
                            Michail[ovitch]’s collaboration with the enemy and told him that the
                            British Government’s decision in these circumstances might be to cease
                            supporting him.</p>
                        <p>“The Prime Minister reacted with a strong protest refusing to accept Mr.
                            Churchill’s allegations concerning the collaboration by Michail[ovitch]
                            and saying that the British Government would assume a terrible
                            responsibility should it withdraw its support from him since the country
                            would then be subjected to a bloodthirsty regime of communism which the
                            Yugoslav peasantry would resist desperately thus causing a long and
                            destructive civil war. He besought the British Government to think this
                            decision over very carefully in the light of its possible results which
                            he said would be a matter of life <pb facs="1041" n="1029"
                                xml:id="pg_1029"/> and death to Yugoslavia though doubtless of small
                            importance to Great Britain as a great power involved in a war of
                            world-wide dimensions.</p>
                        <p>[“]Claiming that the rise of the party’s power had been due to British
                            publicity organs and institutions and accusing the British Government of
                            putting a muzzle on his own Government and preventing it from talking
                            with its people, he added an appealing description of his country’s
                            suffering which he said involved losses exceeding those of the United
                            States and Great Britain put together.</p>
                        <p>“Pointing out that the armed forces of the Partisans now number more than
                            200,000 men, that they are containing about 14 divisions of the Germans
                            and that they are fighting strongly and with success against the enemy
                            while Michailovitch remains inactive, Mr. Churchill said that though the
                            latter’s reasons for such inaction might seem good to him it is
                            obviously to the advantage of the common cause that every assistance
                            that can be spared at present should be withheld from the forces which
                            are not fighting and given to those which are. In this connection he
                            also pointed out the great disparity between the numbers of Partisans
                            and the Chetniks and said this proves a similar disparity in the appeal
                            made to the Yugoslav people by the respective movements.</p>
                        <p>“The Yugoslav Prime Minister replied that he could not accept such a high
                            estimate of the Partisan forces or that they are containing so many
                            divisions of the enemy and stated that the reason for the presence of
                            all these enemy divisions in the northwestern and western parts of the
                            country is the resistance of the whole people of Yugoslavia encouraged
                            by Michail[ovitch’]s forces. He recalled that Michail[ovitch] himself
                            had made the statement that the whole Yugoslav people would rise up to
                            help the Allied troops once they set foot in the Balkans but that the
                            savageness of the reprisals of the Germans was something to which he
                            could not expose the civil population in the meantime should it engage
                            now in destroying communications and other sabotage.</p>
                        <p>“To the remark that the danger of reprisals was something which was not
                            bothering the Partisans, Mr. Puritch answered that so long as the ideas
                            of Moscow triumphed what might happen to the people did not concern the
                            Communists. Finally the interview was closed by Mr. Churchill with
                            regrets that he could not see eye to eye with Mr. Puritch though he was
                            happy to have been able to learn his ideas. He said that the Ambassador
                            would communicate the British decision to Mr. Puritch in due
                            course.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
