<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-23T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-23T10:00:00-05:00" n="898" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d898">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860H.01/592: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador to the Yugoslav Government in
                                Exile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-23T17:00:00+02:00">December
                                    23, 1943—5 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received December 27—10:20 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>14. [Yugoslav Series.] Following text of communication dated December 21,
                            1943, from Yugoslav Prime Minister is transmitted at Mr. Puritch’s
                            request: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I shall be very grateful to you if you would be so good as to
                                    communicate the following to the Government of the United States
                                    of America:</p>
                                <p>“The Royal Yugoslav Government have the honor to transmit
                                    herewith the declaration issued on November 29 by the
                                    ‘anti-Fascist council of Yugoslavia’ and broadcast by the radio
                                    station ‘free Yugoslavia’ on December 18, 1943, which appears to
                                    be in complete discordance with the public and official
                                    statements made by the British and American responsible
                                    statesmen in connection with the military aid given to the
                                    Partisans.</p>
                                <p>“The Royal Yugoslav Government feel themselves obliged to point
                                    out the incoherence of the adopted policy to support in every
                                    possible way a revolutionary movement which claims to be ‘this
                                    supreme and the only representative of the sovereignty of the
                                    Yugoslav peoples and is trying to impose—by the force of the
                                    arms received, too—to the whole of Yugoslav territories a
                                    definite social and political organization. No military reason
                                    seems to be sufficient to justify to [<hi rend="italic">the</hi>] support afforded to such a movement both in materials
                                    and moral backing by all available means of.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The declaration referred to summarized in my telegram No. 8 of December
                            18, 10 p.m., and transmitted in full in my A–2, December 20, 11
                                a.m.<note n="77" xml:id="d898fn77">Latter not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>