<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-09-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="9" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">859.00/1068</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary
                                of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-09-09">September 9, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Danish Minister came in to see me at his request. He referred to his
                            recent conversation with the President, and with Mr. Hull, and the
                            proposed statement he hoped the President would issue. According to him
                            the President had agreed. He said Secretary Hull had suggested that he
                            go and see Steve Early.<note n="14" xml:id="d9fn14">Executive Secretary
                                to President Roosevelt.</note> He did not wish to do that since he
                            had confined his relations exclusively to the State Department. He
                            wondered how the matter stood.</p>
                        <p>I told him I could not say. The matter was, of course, receiving study. I
                            would inquire of the Secretary whether he had any views on the
                            subject.</p>
                        <p>The Minister said that he felt something ought to be done. The Danish
                            people had revolted; two thousand of them had died, and thus far the
                            only recognition of that fact had been advice from the British
                            Broadcasting System for them to be “cautious”. The Danes were telling
                            the British that they were fools to risk their necks since nobody
                            bothered about it. He was grateful for the note the Secretary had sent
                            him; but rather hoped something could be done to release the Danish
                            people further on the side against it. He was a bit emotional about
                            it.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. A. Berle, Jr.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>