<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-04-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="1264" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1264">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 811.741/160</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of the Navy</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_DJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Daniels</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the</hi>
                            <gloss type="to">
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State</hi>
                            </gloss>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-04-27">
                                    <hi rend="italic">April 27, 1915</hi>.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your letter of April 21, 1915, with reference to the
                            transmission of messages in cipher between the German Ambassador and his
                            Government via <pb facs="1145" n="887" xml:id="pg_887"/> the Tuckerton
                            radio station, and also to acknowledge the receipt of the two copies of
                            the key to the code which will be used.</p>
                        <p>A copy of this key has been delivered to the censor at Tuckerton, and
                            messages received from the German Embassy through your Department are
                            being forwarded in due course.</p>
                        <p>The following procedure, which I understand meets with your approval, is
                            being followed in handling messages of this class:</p>
                        <p>Outgoing messages are received from the State Department accompanied by a
                            translation in English they are then transmitted in code to the censor
                            at Tuckerton, who deciphers, paraphrases, enciphers, and transmits the
                            paraphrased message in code to Germany. At the same time the censor
                            forwards to this Department a copy of his translation of the message for
                            comparison with the translation received from the German Embassy.</p>
                        <p>In the case of incoming messages the censor deciphers the code words,
                            censors the message, and, if he finds nothing objectionable,
                            paraphrases, enciphers, and forwards the message by land wire in code to
                            the German Ambassador, at the same time forwarding a copy of his
                            translation to this Department in order that the contents of each
                            message may be made known to your Department. In case the censor is in
                            any doubt as to the neutral character of any incoming message he will
                            forward it through this Department, and it will be referred to your
                            Department for an opinion as to whether it should be allowed to go
                            forward to the German Embassy.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DJ1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Josephus Daniels</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>