<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Germany ( (Gerard) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915Supp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d183</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">183</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-03-01T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-03-01T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-03-01T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-03-01T13:00:00-05:00" n="183"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/1534</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_GJW1"
                        type="from">Gerard</persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to"
                            >Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d183fn1">Repeated to the Ambassador in Great Britain March
                        4, No. 1224.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-03-01T19:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 1, 1915, 7 p. m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received March 2, midnight.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1717. Following is translation of the German reply:<note n="3" xml:id="d183fn2"
                        >See identical note No. 1169 of February 20, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>,
                            <ref target="#pg_119">p. 119</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>The undersigned has the honor to inform his excellency, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_GJW1">James W. Gerard</persName>, Ambassador of the United
                        States of America, in reply to the note of the 22d instant that the Imperial
                        German Government have taken note with great interest of the suggestion of
                        the American Government that certain principles for the conduct of maritime
                        war on the part of Germany and England be agreed upon for the protection of
                        neutral shipping. They see therein new evidence of the friendly feelings of
                        the American Government towards the German Government which are fully
                        reciprocated by Germany.</p>
                    <p>It is in accordance with Germany’s wishes also to have maritime war conducted
                        according to rules which without discriminately restricting one or the other
                        of the belligerent powers in the use of their means of warfare are equally
                            <pb facs="0388" n="130" xml:id="pg_130"/> considerate of the interests
                        of neutrals and the dictates of humanity. Consequently it was intimated in
                        the German note of the 16th instant that observation of the Declaration of
                        London on the part of Germany’s adversaries would create a new situation
                        from which the German Government would gladly draw the proper
                        conclusions.</p>
                    <p>Proceeding from this view, the German Government have carefully examined the
                        suggestion of the American Government and believe that they can actually see
                        in it a suitable basis for the practical solution of the questions which
                        have arisen.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the various points of the American note they beg to make the
                        following remarks:<list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>With regard to the sowing of mines, the German Government would be
                                willing to agree as suggested not to use floating mines and to have
                                anchored mines [constructed] as indicated. Moreover, they agree to
                                put the stamp of the Government on all mines to be planted. On the
                                other hand, it does not appear to them to be feasible for the
                                belligerents wholly to forego the use of anchored mines for
                                offensive purposes.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The German Government would undertake not to use their submarines
                                to attack mercantile of any flag except when necessary to enforce
                                the right of visit and search. Should the enemy nationality of the
                                vessel or the presence of contraband be ascertained submarine would
                                proceed in accordance with the general rules of international
                                law.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>As provided in the American note, this restriction of the use of
                                the submarines is contingent on the fact that enemy mercantile
                                abstain from the use of the neutral flag and other neutral
                                distinctive marks. It would appear to be a matter of course that
                                such mercantile also abstain from arming themselves and from all
                                resistance by force, since such procedure contrary to international
                                law would render impossible any action of the submarines in
                                accordance with international law.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The regulation of legitimate importations of food into Germany
                                suggested by the American Government appears to be in general
                                acceptable. Such regulation would, of course, be confined to
                                importations by sea, but [would] on the other hand include indirect
                                importations by way of neutral ports. The German Government would,
                                therefore, be willing to make the declarations of the nature
                                provided in the American note so that the use of the imported food
                                and foodstuffs solely by the non-combatant population would be
                                guaranteed. The Imperial Government must, however, in addition
                                [attach importance to] having the importation of other raw material
                                used by the economic system of non-combatants including forage
                                permitted. To that end the enemy Governments would have to permit
                                the free entry into Germany of the raw material mentioned, in the
                                free list of the Declaration of London and to treat materials
                                included in the list of conditional contraband according to the same
                                principles as food and foodstuffs.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The German Government venture to hope that the agreement for which the
                        American Government have paved the way may be reached after due
                        consideration of the remarks made above, and that in this way peaceable
                        neutral shipping and trade will not have to suffer any more than is
                        absolutely necessary from the unavoidable effects of maritime war. These
                        effects could be still further reduced if, as was pointed out in the German
                        note of the 16th instant, some way could be found to exclude the shipping of
                        munitions of War from neutral countries to belligerents on ships of any
                        nationality.</p>
                    <p>The German Government must, of course, reserve a definite statement of their
                        position until such time as they may receive further information from the
                        American Government enabling them to see what obligations the British
                        Government are on their part willing to assume.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned avails himself [etc.]</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>, <lb/>
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-02-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 28, 1915</hi>.</date>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="right">
                        <persName corresp="#p_JGEGV1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Von Jagow</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GJW1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gerard</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
