<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-02-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-02-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="193" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/1585</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MIN1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Morris</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 114]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-02-18">
                                        <hi rend="italic">February 18, 1915</hi>.</date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received March 15.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Legation’s
                                telegrams No. 21 of February 16<note n="1" xml:id="d193fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_109">p.
                                    109</ref>.</note> and No. 22 of this date,<note n="2" xml:id="d193fn2">No. 22 not printed.</note> I have the honor to
                                enclose herewith copies and translations of the notes delivered by
                                Sweden to the British and German Governments, protesting against the
                                condition of neutral shipping at sea.<note n="3" xml:id="d193fn3">Copies of identical notes delivered by the Norwegian Government
                                    were forwarded by the Minister in Norway with his No. 74, March
                                    15 (File No. 763.72/1636).</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Foreign Office states that these notes are confidential as yet,
                                as the contents of same have not been made generally known.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MIN1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ira N. Morris</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1—Translation]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Swedish Ministry of Foreign Affairs to the
                                        British Legation</hi>
                                </head>
                                <p>In the course of the present war, the Royal Government has found
                                    it necessary, more than once, to protest against the measures
                                    taken by the belligerents without the regard due to the rights
                                    and interests of neutrals. As far as the relations between the
                                    belligerents themselves are concerned, it is not necessary to
                                    examine whether these measures are just fled by the necessities
                                    of the war or according to the principles of lawful retaliation.
                                    In any case, such considerations could not be appealed to to the
                                    detriment of neutral powers who are in no way responsible,
                                    either for the war or for the means employed by one or other of
                                    the belligerents in order to harm the enemy.</p>
                                <p>Nevertheless, the neutral powers have seen their losses and
                                    difficulties multiply, and the state of affairs is becoming
                                    gradually worse, on account of the intention of the belligerents
                                    to retaliate by measures of the same character to attacks which
                                    they consider to be unlawful.</p>
                                <p>In this respect, a new outlook of the most threatening nature has
                                    just been opened up.</p>
                                <p>The German Government, citing the intention manifested in Great
                                    Britain to try to protect British commercial navigation by the
                                    use of neutral flags, comes to the conclusion that ships flying
                                    neutral flags are open to suspicion and that, for this reason,
                                    even vessels which are really neutral will be exposed to the
                                    most serious dangers. The Royal Government has not delayed in
                                    addressing a protest to the German Government claiming for
                                    neutral navigation, and more especially for Swedish navigat on,
                                    all the security which is assured to it by the application of
                                    the rules of the law of nations. It must, at the same time,
                                    protest against any misuse of its flag, a misuse which, under
                                    the present circumstances, might lead to the most disastrous
                                    consequences. The tolerance which may have been accorded to
                                    isolated incidents in the past is no longer possible under the
                                    present conditions of the war, especially since it has become a
                                    question of systematic and premeditated misuse. The Royal
                                    Government hopes, therefore, that the Royal British Government
                                    will employ all the means in its power to prevent such misuse,
                                    and reserves all its rights with regard to the damage’s and
                                    losses which might result, should this hope not be realized.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi>
                                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-02-15">
                                            <hi rend="italic">February 15,
                                        1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2—Translation]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Swedish Ministry of Foreign Affairs to the
                                        German Legation</hi>
                                </head>
                                <p>The Royal Government has just received, through the intermediary
                                    of the Swedish Legation at Berlin, the notification signed on
                                    the 4th of February <pb facs="0398" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/> by
                                    the Chief of the General Staff of the German Navy, as well as
                                    the memorandum of the Imperial Government annexed thereto.</p>
                                <p>The Royal Government does not consider it necessary to discuss
                                    the means which the Imperial Government intends to put into
                                    force with a view to making war on its enemies, that is to say
                                    with questions which directly interest the belligerents, in so
                                    far as these documents relate only to them. But, on the other
                                    hand, these measures are of such a nature as also deeply to
                                    concern the interests of the neutral powers. Likewise, the
                                    Imperial Government has believed it to be its duty to cite
                                    circumstances intended to prove that the neutral powers had lost
                                    the right to complain of what might happen to them as a
                                    consequence of the operations of war which the Imperial
                                    Government is preparing in the waters surrounding the British
                                    Isles.</p>
                                <p>The Royal Government cannot recognize the forfeiture of this
                                    right. It has openly protested against all applicat on of the
                                    doctrine, according to which the necessities of war would
                                    justify violations of the law of nations. In this respect, it
                                    calls to mind, firstly, the note of November 12 addressed to the
                                    representatives of Germany, of France, of Great Britain, and of
                                    Russia. Moreover, at the time of the British proclamation
                                    regarding the North Sea, the Royal Government did not fail to
                                    declare immediately and in the most definite terms that it could
                                    not recognize the right of a belligerent to limit, as far as
                                    neutral nations are concerned, the use of the open sea and of
                                    other routes common to all. If it is the intention of the
                                    Imperial Government to put us in the wrong because we thought it
                                    sufficient to enter a protest, purely and simply, it must be
                                    called to mind that inasmuch as the belligerents have within the
                                    limits of the law of nations, the choice of means, neutral
                                    powers likewise enjoy the same liberty, provided they observe
                                    the neutrality which they have proclaimed.</p>
                                <p>It has been stated above that Sweden protested when Great
                                    Britain, upon declaring a certain portion of the North Sea to be
                                    a military zone, claimed the right to limit the routes of
                                    neutral navigation. These protests have been repeated in the
                                    above-mentioned note of November 12. The Royal Government still
                                    maintains the same point of view. It, therefore, makes all due
                                    reservations concerning the declaration which has just been
                                    published by the Imperial Government.</p>
                                <p>While presuming that the German authorities will do all in their
                                    power to remove the dangers which threaten Swedish navigation,
                                    the Royal Government cannot conceal the fact that it is aware of
                                    the risks to which this navigation will nevertheless be exposed.
                                    It has made a formal protest to the British Government for the
                                    purpose of providing against any misuse of the national
                                    flag.</p>
                                <p>The Royal Government has the right to expect that the Swedish
                                    flag shall be respected by all parties and under all
                                    circumstances. It, therefore, hopes that Swedish vessels will
                                    not be exposed to the measures announced by the German
                                    authorities and makes all due reservations as regards any
                                    damages and losses which might result from the carrying out of
                                    such measures.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi>
                                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-02-05">
                                            <hi rend="italic">February 5,
                                        1915</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>