<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Great Britain ( (Page) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915Supp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d456</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">456</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-01-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nickel</term>
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-01-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="456"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d456">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72112/627</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_PWH1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Page</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 728]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-01-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 7, 1915</hi>.</date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received January 18.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Just a day or two before the receipt of your note
                    to the British Government about shipping, I received from the Foreign Office a
                    memorandum covering the several kinds of difficulties that we encounter. I do
                    not know that this memorandum is now of any particular value, nevertheless I
                    herewith enclose a copy to you.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PWH1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Walter Hines Page</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Foreign Office</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">American Embassy</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>In view of some of the criticisms to which the measures taken by His
                            Majesty’s Government for checking the sea-borne trade in contraband have
                            been exposed, they desire to state that the sole object of those
                            measures has been to prevent contraband from reaching their enemies,
                            whether direct or through neutral countries.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Their task has of late been lightened, and consequently the
                            unavoidable inconvenience caused to neutral shipping by the exercise of
                            the belligerent right of search reduced, by the fact that several of the
                            neutral countries contiguous to Germany and Austria have, for the
                            protection of their home markets, prohibited the exportation from their
                            respective territories of large classes of commodities. Where articles
                            on the lists of contraband are covered by such prohibitions of export
                            from a particular neutral country, the belligerents find themselves
                            relieved of the necessity of enquiring as to any ulterior destination of
                            goods consigned to that country, provided the prohibition is effectively
                            enforced.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Lists of the commodities of which the export is at this moment
                            prohibited from Italy, Switzerland, the three Scandinavian countries and
                            Holland, are attached hereto.<note n="1" xml:id="d456fn1">Not
                                printed.</note> It should be observed that these lists are not
                            final, but are being added to from time to time.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Under the rules in force in the Scandinavian countries, the
                            exportation of all the articles on their respective prohibited lists
                            remains freely permitted from each one of them to either of the others
                            and as their lists are not uniform—some comprising items which are not
                            included in the others—this system of exceptions has to a certain extent
                            neutralized the effect of the prohibition, and so failed to afford the
                            belligerents any certainty that shipments of a particular commodity,
                            whilst ostensibly consigned to one of these neutral States, are not in
                            fact destined for the enemy, intended to reach him by the roundabout way
                            of reexportation through a neighboring neutral country.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>There is, however, a growing tendency on the part of the three
                            Scandinavian States to assimilate their enactments, in this respect, and
                            to the extent that their lists of prohibited exports are approaching
                            uniformity, it will become easier to distinguish the <hi rend="italic"
                                >bona fide</hi> import trade into these countries of goods having a
                            potentially contraband character from frankly contraband trade really
                            intended merely to pass through them in transit to enemy
                            territory.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Another difficulty of a more general kind, which arises specially in
                            the case of certain metals on the contraband list, such as copper,
                            nickel, lead, and aluminium, and also of rubber, is that the prices
                            ruling in the enemy countries are so high as to make it profitable to
                            import even goods manufactured from those raw materials, or their
                            alloys, for the purpose of melting them down. Where the export of the
                            manufactured article is not also prohibited, this difficulty is in some
                            cases met by the importing firms giving special guarantees that the
                            goods to be manufactured from the imported metals or rubber will not in
                            fact reach the enemy.</item>
                        <pb facs="0568" n="310" xml:id="pg_310"/>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Subject to the above safeguards, no difficulty is now, practically,
                            made in allowing cargoes of goods on the lists of exports prohibited
                            respectively from Italy, Sweden, Norway, and Denmark to pass freely to
                            those countries if addressed to named <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi>
                            consignees, except of course in cases where His Majesty’s Government are
                            in possession of special information that particular shipments have in
                            fact an enemy destination.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>The case of Switzerland is somewhat different, as the Federal
                            Government maintain the right to grant unlimited dispensations from
                            their prohibitions of export, which moreover do not include articles
                            manufactured from the contraband metals, or rubber. In these
                            circumstances, His Majesty’s Government feel compelled to enquire into
                            the ulterior destination of individual shipments, at least of certain
                            classes of goods, such as copper and the other contraband metals,
                            rubber, and petroleum, whilst allowing most other commodities on the
                            contraband lists freely to pass to Italian ports in transit for
                            Switzerland if consigned to named persons on through bills of lading.
                            There are indications that Switzerland may gradually harmonize her
                            system of prohibitions with that enforced in Italy by eliminating some
                            of the features which at present make it necessary for the belligerents
                            to take special measures of precaution in the case of shipments with a
                            Swiss destination.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>It may here be observed that the effect of the Italian decree of
                            November 13, 1914, absolutely prohibiting the reexportation of certain
                            classes of goods landed at Italian ports, has been to hold up in Italy a
                            large number of cargoes which, although consigned on the bills of lading
                            to Italian ports, were really intended for Switzerland. The Swiss
                            Government have been most anxious that the British Government should
                            press at Rome for the release of such cargoes, but the British
                            Government have had to point out the difficulties in the way of their
                            inviting Italy to weaken the operation of her decrees of prohibition,
                            whose effective enforcement is a matter of great practical importance to
                            them: for the Italian Government, if they were to accede to this Swiss
                            request at the instance of Great Britain, would not thereafter be in a
                            position to refuse analogous demands for dispensations on the part of
                            Germany and Austria which might be made under conditions ensuring that
                            consignments of particular goods found their way to those countries. His
                            Majesty’s Ambassador at Rome has however been instructed to use his good
                            offices with the view of facilitating an amicable arrangement between
                            the Swiss and Italian Governments in so far as cargoes are concerned
                            which were shipped before the date of the Italian decree (November 13),
                            and it is hoped and believed that a satisfactory settlement will in this
                            way be arrived at.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>A system of prohibitions of export is equally in force in the
                            Netherlands. Owing however to the provisions of the Rhine conventions,
                            these prohibitions are entirely ineffective as regards cargoes arriving
                            in the ordinary way oversea, since, under those conventions, all goods
                            even although accompanied by bills of lading to named consignees in
                            Holland may, on arrival at Rotterdam, be declared to be in transit, so
                            that, not being technically classed as imports, they automatically
                            escape the operation of the prohibitions of export. The fact, therefore,
                            that certain commodities appear on the Dutch list of prohibited exports,
                            affords no security that they will not in fact, on reaching Holland, be
                            allowed to pass direct into Germany. It has however been ascertained
                            that if goods are consigned either to the Netherlands Government
                            themselves, or to an association called the Netherlands Oversea Trust,
                            they are certainly destined for home consumption and will not be
                            permitted to leave the country save in exceptional circumstances. His
                            Majesty’s Government have accordingly decided not for the present to
                            interfere with any goods addressed either to the Netherlands Government
                            or to the Netherlands Oversea Trust and to restrict their scrutiny of
                            ultimate hostile destination to the case of cargoes going to Holland not
                            so consigned.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>In laying down the foregoing rules for the present guidance of the
                            several British authorities in dealing with cargoes of goods listed as
                            contraband that are on their way to neutral countries contiguous to
                            Germany or Austria, His Majesty’s Government must not be understood to
                            consider themselves bound by them indefinitely or in all circumstances.
                            Should it be found more particularly that in spite of the prohibitions
                            of export enacted by neutral countries, commodities on the prohibited
                            lists are nevertheless entering those countries in quantities obviously
                            exceeding any possible requirements of the respective home markets, His
                            Majesty’s Government reserve the right to enquire seriously into the <hi
                                rend="italic">bona fides</hi> of such large importations.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-12-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">December 29, 1914</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
