<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-05-11T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-05-11T08:00:00-05:00" n="572" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d572">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/2383</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PWH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Page</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-05-11T13:00:00+00:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">May 11, 1915, 1 p. m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received 8 p. m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2080. To the Secretary and the President: My telegram No. 2065
                                [2068], May 8.<note n="1" xml:id="d572fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_385">p.
                                    385</ref>.</note> Continuing my report of British feeling and
                                opinion. Every day without news of definite action by the American
                                government about the <hi rend="italic">Gulflight</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> deepens the British <pb facs="0650" n="392" xml:id="pg_392"/> suspicion into a conviction that our
                                Government will content itself with mere argumentative protests. The
                                respectful and sympathetic silence of the first few days’ excitement
                                is now giving way to open criticism of American failure to realize
                                the situation and of American unwillingness to act. There is a good
                                deal of contempt in British feeling. This contempt is not based upon
                                British wish for military help, but on the feeling that America
                                falls short morally to condemn German methods and has fallen victim
                                to German propaganda and does not properly rate German character, as
                                shown in war, nor understand German danger to all free institutions.
                                Fear grows of a moral failure on the part of the United States.</p>
                            <p>The most conservative action hoped for by the best friends of America
                                here is that diplomatic relations be severed with Germany pending
                                satisfactory settlement, and that Congress be convened so that the
                                voice of the nation may be heard.</p>
                            <p>The aristocratic element of English life which enjoys social and
                                governmental privileges and is what we should call reactionary,
                                consciously or unconsciously hopes for American inactivity to
                                justify their distrust of democratic institutions. Their feeling is
                                that Great Britain will emerge from the war far more powerful than
                                ever, and they are content that the United States should be of as
                                slight influence in the world as possible. The few expressions that
                                the United States will remain neutral and will refrain from breaking
                                off diplomatic relations with Germany come from this element of
                                English society and unofficially from governing circles.</p>
                            <p>Official life here is studiously silent to me. The few persons who
                                have called to express condolence or who have written letters of
                                sympathy about the <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> are all, I
                                think, more or less close personal friends who feel free to speak
                                for personal reasons.</p>
                            <p>The impression is clear that delay in definite action in some really
                                effective form or failure to act definitely will shut the United
                                States out of British, and I should guess, of all European respect
                                for a generation.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Ambassador</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>