<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in France ( (Sharp))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915Supp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d662</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">662</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-07-02T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-07-02T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-07-02T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-07-02T13:00:00-05:00" n="662"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d662">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 451.11B74/32</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SWG1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sharp</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-07-02T13:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 2, 1915, 1 p. m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>935. Your 830, June 16.<note n="1" xml:id="d662fn1">Not printed.</note> In order
                    to avoid any misunderstanding as to attitude of Government of the United States
                    toward <hi rend="italic">Dacia</hi> case, inform French Government that in view
                    of the differences which are understood to exist between the two Governments as
                    to the principles of law applicable to this case, the Government of the United
                    States desires to make clear to the French Government that it has postponed any
                    discussion of these differences until after the decision of the prize court on
                    account of the statement received from the French Government that it could not
                    discuss the principles of law to be expounded in the present case in advance of
                    the judgment of the prize court without infringing upon the jurisdiction of that
                    court, but this discussion is postponed on the distinct understanding that if
                    the decision of the prize court should make a discussion necessary, the
                    postponement of it is not to be taken as an admission on the part of the
                    Government of the United States that a judgment of the prize court can impair or
                    prejudice the rights of an American citizen under the principles of law which
                    the Government of the United States maintains are established by international
                    usage governing the purchase of belligerent vessels by neutrals after the
                    outbreak of hostilities, and the transfer of such vessels to a neutral flag.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lansing</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
