<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-07-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="740" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d740">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 841.857Ib3/9</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Cork</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Frost</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 94]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cork (Queenstown)</hi></placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-07-31">
                                        <hi rend="italic">July 31, 1915</hi>.</date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received August 16.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit hereby
                                confirmation copies of my three cable messages of even date with
                                reference to the sinking of the Leyland Line S. S. <hi rend="italic">Iberian</hi> on the 30th instant. I also transmit: herewith a
                                statement by Dr. <persName>Patrick S. Burns</persName>, ship’s
                                surgeon of the <hi rend="italic">Iberian</hi>, and a statement
                                jointly given by <persName>Harry N. Healy</persName> and
                                    <persName>George-Killeen</persName>, all the deponents being
                                American citizens.<note n="1" xml:id="d740fn1">Not printed.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>I think there cannot be the shadow of a doubt that the <hi rend="italic">Iberian</hi> was seeking to escape and evade visit
                                and search at the time she was shelled. Dr.
                                    <persName>Burns</persName>’ statement to me in the morning gave
                                me clearly that idea, but when he returned in the afternoon to sign
                                the statement which I had meanwhile drawn up, I found him much less
                                inclined to positiveness, and I suspect that the other ship’s
                                officers had been conversing with him in the meantime. I myself had
                                a conversation with Captain <persName>Jagoe</persName>, and he
                                sought to represent that the submarine had not given adequate
                                warning at the time the shell struck the <hi rend="italic">Iberian</hi>, causing the death of Wiley, the American citizen.
                                In this the crew, with the exception of the officers close to
                                Captain <persName>Jagoe</persName>, disagree decidedly. The
                                conversation between the commander of the submarine and Captain
                                    <persName>Jagoe</persName> was witnessed by eight or ten men and
                                recounted among the crew; and it appears that the submarine
                                commander passed the lie to Captain <persName>Jagoe</persName> when
                                the latter stated that he had stopped as soon as he could, and
                                succeeded in facing Captain <persName>Jagoe</persName> down on the
                                point. There was no doubt that the ship had zigzagged and made
                                special efforts to get up steam before the first shots were fired,
                                and that these efforts were continued after the shots were fired
                                until Captain <persName>Jagoe</persName> became convinced that
                                resistance was useless. The shelling appears to have been resorted
                                to by the submarine only in so far as was necessary to induce this
                                conviction. All unite in praising the courtesy and consideration
                                shown by the submarine in connection with the abandonment of the
                                ship. The commander inquired whether a wireless call for help had
                                been sent out, and learning that it had, he expressed regret that he
                                could not therefore venture to give the boats a tow toward land.</p>
                            <p>The statement by Healy and Killeen I regard as more trustworthy than
                                that by Dr. <persName>Burns</persName>, as these young men were
                                alert, intelligent, and naive in giving their experience. Dr.
                                    <persName>Burns</persName> was perhaps somewhat affected by his
                                nexus to the Leyland Line and the fact that <pb facs="0769" n="511" xml:id="pg_511"/> his captain had been placed on record in a
                                sense hardly compatible with that in which the doctor had at first
                                spoken.</p>
                            <p>One interesting feature of Dr. <persName>Burns</persName>’ statement
                                was his account of the habits of Mark Wiley, whom he knew fairly
                                well. It appears that Wiley was more or less of the vagabond type,
                                although a capable man and acting chief horse foreman on the <hi rend="italic">Iberian</hi>; and that he had been on a protracted
                                course of dissipation at Manchester after the horses from the <hi rend="italic">Iberian</hi> had been unloaded. So unstrung and
                                debilitated was he that he had come to Dr.
                                    <persName>Burns</persName>’ door in the middle of the night
                                preceding the attack, and Dr. <persName>Burns</persName> had given
                                him bromide of potassium to quiet his nerves. There seems to be no
                                doubt that death would not have occurred had it not been for Wiley’s
                                ill condition. Dr. <persName>Burns</persName> believes that Wiley’s
                                sisters have been supporting themselves, but would probably not feel
                                impelled to bring their brother’s body back to America at any
                                expense, as their ties with him were slight. Their residence he
                                believes was in Salem, Massachusetts; while Wiley himself had last
                                lodged at a sailors’ rest or sailors’ haven in South Boston,
                                Massachusetts.</p>
                            <p>There are rumors of others of the killed or wounded having American
                                nationality, but I think they are erroneous. The naval hospital
                                authorities assure me that none of the six wounded men admits being
                                other than a British subject; and the most probably American of the
                                dead men, one Carroll, is of Irish blood, with a wife in Liverpool,
                                and has for twenty-five years been on horse-ships between Boston and
                                England. It is possible that he may have taken out naturalization
                                papers at one time, but probably the presumption of expatriation
                                would have arisen against him.</p>
                            <p>In any, event, I conceive that the important feature of the
                                occurrence was the principle involved and not the number of
                                casualties. It seems clear to me that, in so far as the torpedoing
                                of the <hi rend="italic">Iberian</hi> can serve as an indication,
                                the German submarine policy will be tempered with efforts to effect
                                visit and search, or at least to give warning and opportunity for
                                abandonment of the vessels before torpedoing. As this is the first
                                instance which has arisen since the sending of the third <hi rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> note, I have taken pains to go into
                                it at some length, thinking it safer to overburden the Department
                                with details than to omit anything which might be of value.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_FW1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wesley Frost</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>