<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Messrs. Henry Veeder, , Charles J. Faulkner, , jr., and Luther M. Walter, ,
                    counsel for American packers, to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1915Supp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d822</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">822</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1915-10-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1915-10-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-10-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-10-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="822"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d822">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72112/1702</note>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Messrs. Henry Veeder</hi>
                    </persName>, <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Charles J. Faulkner</hi>
                    </persName>, <hi rend="italic">jr., and <persName>Luther M. Walter</persName>
                    </hi>, <hi rend="italic">counsel for American packers, to the <gloss type="to"
                            >Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-10-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 6, 1915</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On September 6 [16?], 1915, in the High Court of
                    Justice of Great Britain, judgment of confiscation as prize was pronounced on
                    shipments of Armour and Company, Swift and Company, <persName corresp="#p_MIN1"
                        >Morris</persName> and Company, and Sulzberger and Sons Company, composing
                    part of the cargoes of the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Kim, Alfred Nobel, Björnstjerne Björnson</hi>
                    </persName>, and <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Fridland</hi>
                    </persName>. This judgment and the principles upon which it was based, are so
                    contrary to the established principles of international law, and so subversive
                    of the rights of neutrals, that we, on behalf of these claimants, desire to
                    submit for your consideration our comments thereon.</p>
                <p>The judgment is unsupported by fact, and proceeds upon inferences and
                    presumptions. Direct evidence on behalf of the American firms interested was
                    given that none of said shipments had been sold, consigned, or destined to the
                    armed forces or the government of any enemy of Great Britain. This evidence was
                    wholly uncontradicted. The court, ignoring these established facts, and
                    admitting that there was no precedent of the English courts justifying the
                    seizure and condemnation of goods on their way to a neutral port, based its
                    judgment of condemnation on the grounds:<list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>That the goods were in excess of the normal consumption of Denmark,
                            raised a presumption that they were destined for, i. e., eventually
                            would find their way into; Germany.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>That, owing to the highly organized state of Germany, in a military
                            sense, there was practically no distinction between the civilian and
                            military population of that country, and therefore there is a
                            presumption that the goods, or a very large proportion of them, would
                            necessarily be used by the military forces of the German Empire.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>That the burden of proving that said goods were not destined for, i.
                            e., would not eventually get into the hands of, the German forces, must
                            be accepted and sustained by said American shippers.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>That a larger quantity of goods than usual were being imported into Denmark is no
                    proof that such goods, or such excess, was going to Germany. On a similar point,
                    the same court, in the <hi rend="italic">Antares</hi> case, March 8, 1915 (as
                    reported in <hi rend="italic">Lloyd’s List</hi>), pointed out that <pb
                        facs="0820" n="562" xml:id="pg_562"/> the export of American copper, for
                    neutral countries contiguous to Germany, had increased, for a period during the
                    war corresponding with a similar period before the war, from about seven
                    millions to thirty-five millions, and the court said, “I am not saying for a
                    moment that this is proof that this copper was intended for Germany.”</p>
                <p>Certainly such inference is not proof, and furnishes no grounds for any
                    presumption that such goods were not to be sold in Denmark to buyers there, or
                    were being shipped by the American firms to Germany for sale there. In the
                    instant cases, the court allowed the claims of certain Danish buyers who had
                    purchased goods from the American firms, without reference to whether the Danish
                    buyers intended to resell such goods to Germany. Are we to understand that under
                    this decision American shippers may not ship to their branches or agents or
                    regular consignees in Denmark, and there sell to whomsoever desires to purchase,
                    while Danish buyers may purchase the same goods from American firms and resell
                    them in Denmark to any purchaser, whether German or otherwise? Is this the
                    distinction upon which condemnation is to be pronounced by British prize
                    courts?</p>
                <p>The assumption of the court that, by reason of the highly organized state of
                    Germany in a military sense, all distinction between the civilian and military
                    population of that country has been abrogated, and that therefore goods going to
                    Germany were necessarily for the use of the armed forces of that country, is not
                    proof that the goods which were the subject of condemnation in the instant cases
                    were destined by the American firms interested to the armed forces or government
                    of the enemy of Great Britain. The judgment in this respect entirely abrogates
                    the distinction between absolute contraband, such as munitions of war, and
                    conditional contraband, such as foodstuffs. It holds that all foodstuffs going
                    to Germany are subject to seizure because, owing to the highly organized state
                    of Germany in a military sense, the distinction between civilian and military
                    population of that country no longer exists.</p>
                <p>This is wholly contrary and repugnant to the fundamental principles of
                    international law and subversive of the rights of neutrals. It is repugnant to
                    the principles announced by the Government of this country through the
                    Department of State on August 15, 1914, as a guide for its citizens. It is
                    repugnant to principles always upheld by Great Britain, and to the express
                    action of Great Britain, wherein she had, through her several contraband
                    proclamations, in effect at the time of the seizures in the instant cases,
                    declared foodstuffs to be conditional contraband. It is contrary to the action
                    of Great Britain in the case of the <persName corresp="#p_W1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilhelmina</hi>
                    </persName>, in which foodstuffs were consigned direct to a German port, and in
                    respect to which <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Sir Edward Grey</persName> stated,
                    in his note to this Government of February 9, 1915:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>They [the British Government] have not, so far, declared foodstuffs to be
                        absolute contraband. They have not interfered with any neutral vessels on
                        account of their carrying foodstuffs, except on the basis of such foodstuffs
                        being liable to capture if destined for the enemy forces or governments. In
                        so acting they have been guided by the general principle, of late
                        universally upheld by civilized nations and observed in practice, that the
                        civil populations of countries at war are not to be exposed to the treatment
                        rightly reserved or combatants.</p>
                </quote>
                <pb facs="0821" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/>
                <p>Likewise, the judgment of the court that the burden of proof that the goods were
                    not eventually to come into the hands of the armed forces or Government of
                    Germany must be sustained by the American firms interested, is contrary to the
                    well-established principle that the captor must justify his seizure by
                    affirmative proof (<hi rend="italic">The Resolution</hi>, 2 Dall. 19).</p>
                <p>In a similar case, that of the <hi rend="italic">Arabia</hi>, the cargo of which
                    was seized and confiscated by the judgment of a Russian prize court upon similar
                    reasons, Mr. <persName>John Hay</persName>, then Secretary of State, telegraphed
                    to the Ambassador of the United States to Russia protesting against such
                    decision, refusing to recognize the principles upon which it was based or the
                    policy which it indicated, in the following language:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>When war exists between powerful states, it is vital to the legitimate
                        maritime commerce of neutral states that there be no relaxation of the
                        rule—no deviation from the criterion for determining what constitutes
                        contraband of war, lawfully subject to belligerent capture; namely, warlike
                        nature, use, and destination. Articles which, like arms and ammunition, are
                        by their nature of self-evident warlike use, are contraband of war if
                        destined to enemy territory; but articles which, like coal, cotton, and
                        provisions, though of ordinarily innocent [use], are capable of warlike use,
                        are not subject to capture and confiscation unless shown by evidence to be
                        actually destined for the military or naval forces of a belligerent.</p>
                    <p>This substantive principle of the law of nations can not be overridden by
                        technical rule of the prize court that the owners of the captured cargo must
                        prove that no part of it may eventually come to the hands of the enemy
                        forces. The proof is of an impossible nature; and it can not be admitted
                        that the absence of proof in its nature impossible to make can justify the
                        seizure and condemnation. If it were otherwise, all neutral commerce with
                        the people of a belligerent state would be impossible; the innocent would
                        suffer inevitable condemnation with the guilty.</p>
                    <p>The established principle of discrimination between contraband and
                        non-contraband goods admits of no relaxation or refinement. It must be
                        either inflexibly adhered to or abandoned by all nations. There is and can
                        be no middle ground. The criterion of warlike usefulness and destination has
                        been adopted by the common consent of civilized nations, after centuries of
                        struggle in which each belligerent made indiscriminate warfare upon all
                        commerce of all neutral states with the people of the other belligerent, and
                        which led to reprisals as the mildest available remedy.</p>
                    <p>If the principle, which appears to have been declared by the Vladivostok
                        prize court and which has not so far been disavowed or explained by His
                        Imperial Majesty’s Government, is acquiesced in, it means, if carried into
                        full execution, the complete destruction of all neutral commerce with the
                        non-combatant population of Japan; it obviates the necessity of blockades;
                        it renders meaningless the principle of the Declaration of Paris set forth
                        in the imperial order of February 29 last, that a blockade, in order to be
                        obligatory, must be effective; it obliterates all distinction between
                        commerce in contraband and non-contraband goods; and is in effect a
                        declaration of war against commerce of every description between the people
                        of a neutral and those of a belligerent state.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>This protest resulted in immediate relief to American commerce.</p>
                <p>The judgment in the instant cases being based on principles so clearly at
                    variance with those recognized both by the Government of the United States and
                    hitherto by the Government of Great Britain—principles which do not admit of
                    arbitration—we submit that, such judgment having been rendered, this Government
                    should, without awaiting further appellate proceedings, take similar action to
                    that taken by it in the case of the <hi rend="italic">Arabia</hi> and make
                    earnest protest against and refuse to recognize the judgment and the principles
                    upon which it is based; and further make demand for reparation on behalf <pb
                        facs="0822" n="564" xml:id="pg_564"/> of these claimants for their losses
                    and damages growing out of the seizure, detention, and confiscation of the
                    shipments.</p>
                <p>Yours respectfully,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Veeder</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles J. Faulkner</hi>
                        </persName>, <hi rend="smallcaps">jr</hi>. <lb/>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Luther M. Walter</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
