<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-10-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="829" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d829">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 462.11Se8/49</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_GJW1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Gerard</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-10-12">
                                        <hi rend="italic">October 12, 1915</hi>.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2291. You are instructed to present the following note to the German
                                Minister of Foreign Affairs:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>In reply to your excellency’s note of September 19,<note n="1" xml:id="d829fn1">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_551">p.
                                            551</ref>.</note> on the subject of the claim for
                                    damages for the sinking of the American merchantman <persName>
                                        <hi rend="italic">William P. Frye</hi></persName>, I am
                                    instructed by the Government of the United States to say that it
                                    notes with satisfaction the willingness of the Imperial German
                                    Government to settle the questions at issue in this case by
                                    referring to a joint commission of experts the amount of the
                                    indemnity to be paid by the Imperial German Government under its
                                    admitted liability for the losses of the owners and captain on
                                    account of the destruction of the vessel, and by referring to
                                    arbitration the question of the interpretation of treaty rights.
                                    The Government of the United States further notes that, in
                                    agreeing to this arrangement, the Imperial German Government
                                    expressly states that in making payment it does not acknowledge
                                    the violation of the treaty as contended by the Government of
                                    the United States, and that the settlement of the question of
                                    indemnity does hot prejudice the arrangement of the differences
                                    of opinion between the two governments concerning the
                                    interpretation of the treaty rights. The Government of the
                                    United States understands that this arrangement will also be
                                    without prejudice to its own contention in accordance with the
                                    statement of its position in its note of August 10 last<note n="2" xml:id="d829fn2">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_504">p.
                                            504</ref>.</note> to your excellency on this subject,
                                    and the Government of the United States agrees to this
                                    arrangement on that understanding. Your excellency states that
                                    the Imperial German Government believes that the nomination of
                                    an umpire should be dispensed with, because it has been the
                                    experience of the Imperial German Government that the, experts
                                    named in such cases have always reached an agreement without
                                    difficulty, and that should they disagree on some point, it
                                    could probably be settled by diplomatic negotiation. The
                                    Government of the United States entirely concurs in the view
                                    that it is not necessary to nominate an umpire in advance. It is
                                    not to be assumed that the experts will be unable to agree, or
                                    that if they are, the point in dispute can not be settled by
                                    diplomatic negotiation, but the Government of the United States
                                    believes that in agreeing to this arrangement it should be
                                    understood in advance that in case the amount of indemnity is
                                    not settled by the joint commission of experts or by diplomatic
                                    negotiation, the question will then be referred to an umpire if
                                    that is desired by the Government of the United States.</p>
                                <p>Assuming that this understanding is acceptable to the German
                                    Government, it will only remain for the Government of the United
                                    States to nominate its expert to act with the expert already
                                    nominated by the German Government on the joint commission. It
                                    seems desirable to the Government of the United States that this
                                    joint commission of experts should meet without delay as soon as
                                    the American member is named and that its meetings should be
                                    held in the United States, because, as pointed out in my note to
                                    you of April 30 last, any evidence which the German Government
                                    may wish to have produced is more accessible and can more
                                    conveniently be examined there than elsewhere.</p>
                                <p>With reference to the agreement to submit to arbitration the
                                    question of treaty interpretation, the Government of the United
                                    States notes that in answer to its inquiry whether, pending the
                                    arbitral proceedings, the German Government will govern its
                                    naval operations in accordance with the German or American
                                    interpretation of the treaty stipulations in question, the reply
                                    of the German Government is that it “has issued orders to the
                                    German naval forces not to destroy American merchantmen which
                                    have loaded conditional contraband even when the conditions of
                                    international law are present, but to permit them to continue
                                    their voyage unhindered if it is not possible to take them into
                                    port,” and that “on the other hand, it must reserve to itself
                                    the right to destroy vessels carrying absolute contraband
                                    whenever such destruction is permissible according to the
                                    provisions of the Declaration of London.”</p>
                                <pb facs="0829" n="571" xml:id="pg_571"/>
                                <p>Without admitting that the Declaration of London is in force, and
                                    on the understanding that the requirement in Article 50 of the
                                    declaration that “before the vessel is destroyed all persons on
                                    board must be placed in safety” is not satisfied by merely
                                    giving them an opportunity to escape in lifeboats, the
                                    Government of the United States is willing, pending the arbitral
                                    award in this case, to accept the Declaration of London as the
                                    rule governing the conduct of the German Government in relation
                                    to the treatment of American vessels carrying cargoes of
                                    absolute contraband. On this understanding the Government of the
                                    United States agrees to refer to arbitration this question of
                                    treaty interpretation.</p>
                                <p>The Government of the United States concurs in the desire of the
                                    Imperial German Government that the negotiations relative to the
                                    signing of the <hi rend="italic">compromis</hi> referring this
                                    question of treaty interpretation to arbitration under the
                                    provisions of Article 52 of the Hague arbitration convention,
                                    should be conducted between the German Foreign Office and the
                                    American Embassy in Berlin, and the Government of the United
                                    States, will be glad to receive the draft <hi rend="italic">compromis</hi>, which you inform me the Foreign Office is
                                    prepared to submit to the American Ambassador in Berlin.
                                    Anticipating that it may be convenient for the Imperial German
                                    Government to know in advance of these negotiations the
                                    preference of the Government of the United States as to the form
                                    of arbitration to be arranged for in the <hi rend="italic">compromise</hi> my Government desires me to say that it
                                    would prefer, if agreeable to the Imperial Government, that the
                                    arbitration should be by summary procedure, based upon the
                                    provisions of Articles 86 to 90, inclusive, of the Hague
                                    arbitration convention, rather than the longer form of
                                    arbitration before the Permanent Count at The Hague.</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>Arrange for simultaneous publication of this note at earliest date
                                which will give you time to notify the Department.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LR1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lansing</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>