<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1915-01-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1915-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="941" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d941">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 195.1/304</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SRSCA1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Spring
                                Rice</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1915-01-12">
                                    <hi rend="italic">January 12, 1915</hi>.</date><note n="1" xml:id="d941fn1">Date of receipt not indicated.</note>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: You informed me yesterday
                            that an American gentleman was anxious to buy a German ship and employ
                            her in his business—especially in shipping mahogany to South and Central
                            American ports. You said that this gentleman was in doubt as to what
                            would be the attitude of my Government towards the transfer of the flag
                            and whether they would regard it as valid.</p>
                        <p>I beg to reply that it would not be in accordance with precedent to give
                            any definite pledge beforehand as to what would be the action of a prize
                            court should the question come before it for adjudication. I can however
                            inform you that speaking generally, my Government like your own does not
                            regard the transfer of the flag after the outbreak of hostilities as
                            illegal, although it considers that it is always to be regarded with
                            suspicion. In the present case, however, it would seem to me that the
                            purchaser would have nothing to fear if he is able to prove that he
                            bought the ship outright and unconditionally for commercial purposes, is
                            manning it with a neutral <pb facs="0936" n="678" xml:id="pg_678"/>
                            crew, and employs it on neutral business, trading between neutral
                            ports.</p>
                        <p>It would obviously be unsafe to send the ship on a voyage to an enemy
                            port or to a port which is used for supplying the enemy but if employed
                            on this side of the ocean, as long as she does not fall under the
                            suspicion of supplying enemy cruisers, I do not imagine she would be in
                            danger of seizure.</p>
                        <p>It would however be as well to inform the British Consul of the
                            circumstances of the sale in order that he might report on the matter to
                            London.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SRSCA1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cecil Spring Rice</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>