<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-11-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="17" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d17">
                        <head>17. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                            Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RSW1" type="from">Rockwell</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                            Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SJJ1" type="to">Sisco</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d17fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Bureau of
                                Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs, Office of Arabian Peninsula
                                Affairs, Lot 72D30, Records Relating to Saudi Arabia, Box 4, Saudi
                                Arabia <gloss target="#t_PET1">Pet</gloss>, Petroleum General 1969.
                                Confidential. A copy was sent to <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName>, <persName>Van Hollen</persName>, and all
                                    <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Country
                            Directors.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-11-14">November 14,
                                1969</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>SUBJECT <list>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SN1">Samuels</persName>’ Oil
                                        Meeting</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SN1">Samuels</persName>’ oil meeting today,
                                <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil Trezise</persName> reported on the
                            meeting last Saturday of the <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> Committee.<note n="2" xml:id="d17fn2">November 8;
                                see <ref target="#d15">Documents 15</ref> and <ref target="#d16">16</ref>.</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0096" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/>
                        <p>He said that a consensus has developed in the <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> group in favor of a tariff approach to the
                            problem. Although the situation is still highly tentative, the general
                            idea is that within a couple of years we would change over to a tariff
                            system preferential to the Western Hemisphere—i.e. Canada, Venezuela and
                            the rest of Latin America. The objective would be to establish tariff
                            levels which would bring about a price in the United States per barrel
                            of oil of $2.50, as against the present world price of $2.00 and the
                            present price in the United States of $3.30. This would be achieved by
                            setting a low tariff for Canada and Venezuela, say 10¢ per barrel, and a
                            much higher tariff for imports from elsewhere.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil</persName> said that this procedure
                            presented many difficult problems such as that represented by the
                            important <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> interests which depend on
                            the present quota system. The Department will have to negotiate with
                            Canada, Venezuela and others some kind of arrangement about assurances
                            and commitments. Some of these difficulties and pressures may be so
                            great that the President will not wish to confront them and perhaps the
                            outcome of all of this will be a decision to keep the present system
                            with some modification.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil</persName> made clear that the basis for
                            the trend in the <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> group
                            toward a tariff system discriminating in favor of the Western Hemisphere
                            was national security. There was a feeling in the <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> group that if we open the gates
                            to Middle Eastern oil a situation could develop where 50% of our oil
                            supplies would be coming from Kuwait and Libya. There was a strong
                            feeling that we should not become dependent upon Middle Eastern
                            suppliers because of the inherent instability in the area and the
                            likelihood of interruption of supply. Accordingly, said Phil, there was
                            “zero” chance of acceptance by the <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> group of the position that access to the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> market should be open to all suppliers,
                            without discrimination.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil</persName> commented that under a tariff
                            system Middle Eastern suppliers would be in a better position than they
                            are under the existing quota arrangement although he foresaw that most
                            of the oil coming into the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> under the
                            new arrangement would be Venezuelan or Canadian. However, Middle Eastern
                            suppliers could move into the European market now being supplied by
                            Venezuela. <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil</persName> could see no
                            particular way that Iran could obtain preferred access to <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> markets except by getting under the
                            tariff price. There was the possibility of company-to-company
                            arrangements but this might involve legal difficulties for the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Government.</p>
                        <p>Under the new arrangement the President would be given wide discretionary
                            powers to adjust tariffs up or down. Thus, if experience showed that the
                            tariff on non-Western Hemisphere oil was too high to permit achieving a
                            desired price in the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>, it could be
                            lowered. There <pb facs="0097" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/> might also be a
                            provision for a review of the structure every 4 years or so.</p>
                        <p>The new tariffs could be established by the President without new
                            legislative authority on grounds of the interest of national security.
                            In effect, <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil</persName> said, the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> consumer would be asked to pay for
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> security.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil</persName> said that the oil industry
                            has already got wind of this trend in the <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> Committee and is very opposed to it. The matter
                            is obviously a very delicate one and should not be discussed outside the
                            Department. We may be asked to take a formal position before too long on
                            a paper coming from the <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName>
                                group.<note n="3" xml:id="d17fn3">A handwritten notation reads:
                                “Nothing re gradual phase-out of tariff.”</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>