<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-03-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="174" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                        <head>174. Memorandum From the President’s Special Consultant for Energy
                                (<persName corresp="#p_DCJ1" type="from">DiBona</persName>) to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d174fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White
                                House Central Files, Staff Member and Office Files, Energy Policy
                                Office, Box 22, <persName corresp="#p_DCJ1">Charles J.
                                    DiBona</persName> Subject Files, Committee Memos. No
                                classification marking. Printed from an uninitialed
                            copy.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-03-19">March 19,
                                1973</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>SUBJECT <list>
                                    <item>Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Attached is a point paper on the Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> project “North Star.” Also attached is a Memorandum for
                            the Record of a discussion with <gloss target="#t_ExIm1">Ex-Im</gloss>
                                Bank.<note n="2" xml:id="d174fn2">In the attached March 10
                                memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_DCJ1">DiBona</persName>,
                                Schaefer informed him that <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Don
                                    Bostwick</persName>, Executive Vice President of the <gloss target="#t_ExIm1">Ex-Im</gloss> Bank, opposed the proposed
                                    <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> project “not so much because
                                of the large size of the loan, but on the merits.” Furthermore,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bostwick</persName> “believed that
                                the American companies were responsible for initiating the idea and
                                his information is that, initially at least, the Russians did not
                                like the project.” He also “strongly suggested” that an engineering
                                feasibility study be a requirement prior to any endorsement of the
                                project. Based on their conversation, Schaefer concluded: “<gloss target="#t_ExIm1">Ex-Im</gloss> has no requirements per se that
                                could block consummation of the Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> project; however, <gloss target="#t_ExIm1">Ex-Im</gloss> financing will provide a vehicle for
                                congressional debate of the merits and politics of the
                                project.”</note></p>
                        <p>For your information, Senator <persName corresp="#p_JHS1">Jackson</persName> is opposed to the project. He questioned
                                <persName corresp="#p_NJN1">Nassikas</persName>, Chairman of Federal
                            Power Commission, concerning the defense and economic aspects. <persName corresp="#p_JHS1">Jackson</persName> has also focused on the issue
                            of incremental pricing of gas imports. If the gas cannot be “rolled in”
                            so that its price is averaged with domestic gas, the project would
                            probably not fly. I’ve given a copy of <persName corresp="#p_NJN1">Nassikas</persName>’ answers to your staff.</p>
                        <p>In my meetings on the <persName corresp="#p_HRC1">Hill</persName>, this
                            issue has come up repeatedly, and unfavorably. I have responded by
                            stating: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>With rising <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> costs, the price
                                    could well be competitive. The project sponsors believe there
                                    will be a shortage of gas, even with deregulation, so they feel
                                    they will be able to sell it. The amount involved is a small
                                    fraction of total <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> projected
                                    consumption (2% or 3%).</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Attachment</head>
                            <p rend="center">SOVIET <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> PROJECTS</p>
                            <p>There are two major long-term projects to import Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> to the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> currently under consideration: <pb facs="0480" n="442" xml:id="pg_442"/>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>From the Urengoye gas field in Western Siberia to the East
                                        Coast of the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> (Project
                                        North Star).</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>From the Yakutsk gas field in Eastern Siberia to Japan and
                                        the West Coast of the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss></item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>The North Star Project is further along, but is still at the stage of
                                exploratory negotiations between the companies involved and the
                                Soviet Union. There have been no field studies made to date. (The
                                project is summarized in Tab A.)<note n="3" xml:id="d174fn3">Attached but not printed at Tab A is “Summary of North Star,”
                                    itemizing the costs associated with the project.</note></p>
                            <p>Details such as ship subsidies (possibly totaling $250 million for
                                the 10 <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> ships in the North Star
                                project), Soviet equity <gloss target="#t_Participation1">participation</gloss>, and financing are still wholly
                                speculative.</p>
                            <p>The sponsors of North Star will probably require government loan
                                guarantees of at least $4 billion from the Export-Import Bank or
                                through some new agency. If <gloss target="#t_ExIm1">EX–IM</gloss>
                                financing is required, there are no legal impediments which preclude
                                consummation of the Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss>
                                project. <gloss target="#t_ExIm1">EX–IM</gloss>’s current legal
                                limitations on the total loan and loan guarantee outstanding is
                                $27.5 billion. The Soviet project could be accommodated by spreading
                                the funding over five years. Although <gloss target="#t_ExIm1">EX–IM</gloss> does not utilize public funds, Congress does
                                approve the annual business plan; this would provide a vehicle for
                                congressional debate of the merits and politics of the project. The
                                    <gloss target="#t_ExIm1">EX–IM</gloss> staff currently is
                                negative on the project, believing that extensive engineering
                                studies should be performed prior to approval.</p>
                            <p>The question of deregulation of natural gas is directly related to
                                the Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> project. An unfilled
                                demand for natural gas under conditions less than economic
                                equilibrium (equilibrium could be achieved in 1978 under
                                deregulation) does not portend a need for additional supplies of gas
                                or <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> per se. Rather, market forces
                                will result in comparison of prices and their benefits for all
                                alternative fuels. Estimates of representative city gate prices of
                                alternative fuels are in Tab B,<note n="4" xml:id="d174fn4">Tab B is
                                    attached but not printed.</note> including supplemental gases
                                and specifically including Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>If the <gloss target="#t_Consortium1">consortium</gloss> and the
                                Soviets maintain a constant price of $1.25 to $1.40 throughout the
                                life of the contract, eventually the Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> will be comparable and possibly lower cost than
                                domestic alternatives. Assuming a base price in 1973 of $50/<gloss target="#t_MCF1">MCF</gloss> for domestic gas and assuming that
                                exploration and development will continue until the year 2000, but
                                at inflated costs, prices in the future would increase as shown
                                below. Transportation costs are held constant at $.25/<gloss target="#t_MCF1">MCF</gloss> as it is improbable that major new
                                pipelines would be built after 1980.</p>
                            <pb facs="0481" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/>
                            <table cols="3" rend="width: 70%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="4">
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell role="num"><hi rend="italic">At 3% Inflation</hi></cell>
                                    <cell role="num"><hi rend="italic">At 5% Inflation</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1973</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">$0.75</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">$0.75</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>1990</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">1.08</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">1.40</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>2000</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">1.36</cell>
                                    <cell role="num">2.10</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>There are a number of distinct political risks with an overt policy
                                of promoting the Soviet <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss>
                                projects. First, to date the press has focused on the comparative
                                costs of $1.40 Soviet gas versus the average current domestic cost
                                of $0.20 per <gloss target="#t_MCF1">MCF</gloss>. Simple
                                multiplication indicates that this apparent seven-fold increase will
                                cost some of the American gas buyers $876 million per year for the
                                North Star Project alone for apparently less secure fuel supplies
                                plus a pro-rata share of a $250 million ship construction
                                program.</p>
                            <p>The <gloss target="#t_Consortium1">consortium</gloss> must sell the
                                gasified <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> to distribution
                                companies and/or industrial sales. Unless new legislation is passed
                                which removes approval of <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss>
                                imports from the Federal Power Commission, approval of future <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> projects, including the Soviet
                                projects, will be subject to <gloss target="#t_FPC1">FPC</gloss>
                                approval. The <gloss target="#t_FPC1">FPC</gloss>’s opinions on
                                    <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss> projects to date have
                                indicated a keen interest in minimizing costs. The El Paso/Algeria
                                project, the only baseload project approved to date, involved prices
                                of $.77 to $.83 per <gloss target="#t_MCF1">MCF</gloss>. The <gloss target="#t_FPC1">FPC</gloss>’s opinion allowed distribution
                                companies to “roll in” the costs of higher priced supplemental fuels
                                to the consumer, including <gloss target="#t_LNG1">LNG</gloss>, but
                                required that the pipelines incrementally price these supplemental
                                fuels to the distribution companies. <gloss target="#t_FPC1">FPC</gloss> approval of projects estimated at $1.25 to
                                    $1.50/<gloss target="#t_MCF1">MCF</gloss> is considered by
                                knowledgeable observers as highly questionable.</p>
                            <p>Representatives of Tenneco state that the <gloss target="#t_Consortium1">consortium</gloss> is prepared to
                                proceed as soon as possible. They believe deregulation will probably
                                be delayed on the <persName corresp="#p_HRC1">Hill</persName> and
                                that there will always be inadequate supplies of domestic natural
                                gas. They plan to get long-term contracts from distributors and
                                utilities as early as possible (during the period of uncertainty),
                                believing that rolling in at the city gate will make the $1.25–$1.40
                                price acceptable. It is expected that the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> gasification facilities, as well as any additional
                                pipelines will be added to the pipeline company’s rate base and thus
                                provide for additional profits.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>