<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-11-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="234" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d234">
                        <head>234. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_CCA1" type="from">Charles
                                A. Cooper</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to
                            Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d234fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 321, Subject Files,
                                Energy Crisis, Nov 73–Feb 74. Secret. Sent for action.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-11-03">November 3,
                                1973</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>SUBJECT <list>
                                    <item>Arab Oil Embargo and Production <gloss target="#t_Cutback1">Cutback</gloss>s</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Early Reversal of the Embargo Not
                                Essential</hi></p>
                        <p>The economic implications of the Arab embargo for us are unlikely to
                            prove so burdensome that an early abandonment of the embargo is vital to
                            our interests. Although I am not an oil industry expert, there are
                            reasons to believe that while an Arab oil embargo against us will cause
                            serious economic difficulties, the problems that arise will not be so
                            serious that they cannot be tolerated: <list>
                                <item>—There is a difference between Arab rhetoric and
                                    performance—not only is it difficult for all the Arab nations to
                                    enforce their <gloss target="#t_Cutback1">cutback</gloss> and
                                    embargo policies, but there will be both economic and political
                                    incentives for them to rely more on words and less on deeds,
                                    particularly as time goes on and crisis atmosphere
                                    lessens.</item>
                                <item>—There are many circumstances short of a definitive settlement
                                    in the Middle East conflict under which the embargo <hi rend="italic">policy</hi> itself is likely to be
                                    modified.</item>
                                <pb facs="0701" n="663" xml:id="pg_663"/>
                                <item>—If the embargo is sustained, and somehow enforced with 100
                                    percent effectiveness, we can get through this winter. The
                                    measures to be announced next week<note n="2" xml:id="d234fn2">A
                                        reference to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s
                                        November 7 energy message; see <ref target="#d237">Document
                                            237</ref>.</note> to conserve the use of petroleum, and
                                    to increase our production, and to draw down stocks, together
                                    with some increased imports from non-Arab sources, will be
                                    effective even though politically and economically
                                    burdensome.</item>
                                <item>—As time passes, adjustments will be more effective and the
                                    economic consequences of the embargo less serious. The domestic
                                    oil policy which will be announced next week is drastic, but we
                                    would have had to take comparable conservation measures anyway
                                    over the next several years, given the basic change in Arab oil
                                    export policies.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Refusal as a Matter of Principle to
                                Accept the Legitimacy of a Link Between the Arab Oil Embargo and Our
                                Middle East Policy</hi></p>
                        <p>We should treat the Arab oil embargo as an illegitimate economic act,
                            which we will not allow in any way to influence the timing or substance
                            of our peace efforts in the Middle East. If we threaten to delay our
                            peace efforts unless the embargo is lifted, we put our own highest
                            priority foreign policy concern at hostage. Even if we put indirect
                            pressure on by calling attention to how hard it is for us to carry out
                            our diplomatic efforts, we tend to create the same problems. We should
                            instead take a line with the oil producers which emphasizes our
                            determination to keep separate our policy towards the Arab/Israeli
                            conflict and our policy towards the Arab oil embargo. The line outlined
                            below could be taken with King <persName corresp="#p_FIAAA2">Faisal</persName>, who is the key player, recognizing that while he
                            may be genuinely concerned over the Israelis, he also has other
                            considerations which may make him interested in a face-saving
                            alternative to confrontation with us.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Approach to <persName corresp="#p_FIAAA2">Faisal</persName></hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Inform him that we cannot allow ourselves to be influenced on a
                                foreign policy matter of such grave concern, and one where our
                                relations with the Soviet Union are so directly involved, by any
                                actions he might or might not take with respect to oil shipments to
                                us.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Express our concern that the repercussions of a continued embargo,
                                which are hard to predict or control in a situation so volatile,
                                could lead to a Soviet role in the Middle East which he might find
                                extremely uncomfortable and undesirable.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Assure him that we intend to continue our efforts to promote a
                                just and durable settlement of the Middle East conflict, though we
                                are concerned that public reaction to the Arab embargo may make it
                                harder <pb facs="0702" n="664" xml:id="pg_664"/> to carry forward
                                these efforts as actively and as constructively as we might
                                otherwise be able to.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Stress to him that we in no way believe the Arab oil embargo to be
                                legitimate or justifiable, but that we are ourselves fully prepared
                                to make whatever economic adjustments are needed if it
                                continues.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Point out that the Arab nations themselves have much to lose
                                economically, since we, and others, will inevitably be compelled to
                                adjust our own production and consumption, and our relationship with
                                other oil-producers, so as to reduce or eliminate our requirements
                                for Arab oil in the future.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Indicate that as a practical matter a continued embargo is likely
                                to have spill-over effects in many areas of our bilateral
                                relationship even though we value our traditional friendship with
                                his nation very highly and hope that it will continue in the
                                future.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Urge that he follow a moderate and prudent course, and that he
                                continue to keep in mind our deep desire for friendship with him and
                                our genuine interest in helping to achieve a settlement of the
                                conflict between the Arabs and Israelis.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>If <persName corresp="#p_FIAAA2">Faisal</persName> remains
                                non-conciliatory, you could make the following point:</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Warn him that if the economic hardships occasioned by the Arab
                                boycott and production <gloss target="#t_Cutback1">cutback</gloss>
                                become too severe, particularly in other countries more dependent on
                                Arab oil than we are, that economic countermeasures in which we
                                might participate cannot be ruled out, although we are not
                                considering any such actions at this time.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>If <persName corresp="#p_FIAAA2">Faisal</persName> shows signs of
                                looking for a face-saving way out, you might:</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Suggest that he may wish to take measures to sustain production so
                                that significant <gloss target="#t_Cutback1">cutback</gloss>s of oil
                                to such countries as Japan and the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> can be avoided, even though the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> embargo is formally continued, and
                                that in such circumstances we would seek to avoid actions or
                                statements which might add to any political pressures he may
                                face.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>