<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-08-03T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-03-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="5" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                        <head>5. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>The first meeting of the Cabinet Level Task Force on Oil Import Controls
                            took place on April 8, 1969, and served as its organizing meeting,
                            introducing <persName corresp="#p_OPA1">Philip Areeda</persName> as the
                            Executive Director. (Minutes of meeting, April 8; National Archives,
                                <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 174, Records of Secretary of Labor
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">George P. Shultz</persName>, 1969–1970,
                            Subject Files, Box 62, Cabinet Committee on Oil Imports, 1969 Cabinet
                            Committee on Oil Imports, January–April) In order to collect information
                            on the workings of the oil import system to date, the Task Force
                            submitted a lengthy questionnaire to all interested parties in both
                            governmental and private sectors through the <hi rend="italic">Federal
                                Register</hi>. (34 <hi rend="italic">Fed. Reg</hi>. 8055, May 22,
                            1969) The bulk of the responses are in the National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 174, Records of Secretary of Labor
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">George P. Shultz</persName>, 1969–1970,
                            Subject Files, Box 62, Cabinet Committee on Oil Imports, 1969 Cabinet
                            Committee on Oil Imports, January–April. Such varied governmental bodies
                            as the Anti-Trust Division of the Justice Department, the Department of
                            State’s Bureaus of Legal Affairs and Economic Affairs, the Department of
                            Defense, the Central Intelligence Agency, the Office of Emergency
                            Preparedness, other Cabinet level posts and agencies designated as Task
                            Force members, and almost every interested private sector oil-related
                            business responded. Absent was any overt input from the National
                            Security Council.</p>
                        <p>The Task Force weighed the responses from major oil producing states,
                            major oil companies, and the larger <gloss target="#t_Independents1">independents</gloss> involved in <gloss target="#t_Downstream1">downstream</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_upstream1">upstream</gloss> operations and produced counter-papers. As the
                            Task Force operations developed, governors, senators, and
                            representatives from oil producing states and oil dependent states
                            submitted responses. Concerned citizens added to the voluminous response
                            to the workings of the Task Force.</p>
                        <p>Although the Task Force did not meet between July and October 1969, it
                            engaged in the amassing of responses and the clarification of the
                            questions the final report should address. (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_SGP1">Shultz</persName> to the principals, September 10,
                            1969; ibid., 1969 Cabinet Committee on Oil Imports, September) By
                            mid-September the Task Force had created the A-Series papers, which were
                            referred to as “fact” papers and served as early versions of projected
                            chapters in a final report. The A-Series papers are ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 220, Records of the Cabinet Task Force on
                            Oil Import Control, Box 20, Fact Papers “A Draft” Series, September
                            1969.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>