<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>10. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-01-12T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-01-12T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="rec3U9TKkW5rS0s3i" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">Freedom of navigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-01-12T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-01-12T19:00:00-05:00" n="10"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                <head>10. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d10fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET S. Confidential; Exdis. Drafted by
                        Toon and approved in U on January 15.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1968-01-12T19:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 12, 1968, 7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Soviet Note on “Pereyaslavl-Zalesskiy” Incident</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Mr. Yuri N. Chernyakov, Soviet Chargé, a.i.</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Nicholas deB Katzenbach</persName>, Acting
                        Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. Malcolm Toon, Country Director, Soviet Union Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CY1">Chernyakov</persName> requested and was given an
                    appointment with the Acting Secretary in order to deliver a note from his
                    Government in reply to the United States Government note of January 5 with
                    regard to the bombing of the Soviet ship “Pereyaslavl-Zalesskiy” in the harbor
                    of Haiphong on January 4.<note n="2" xml:id="d10fn2">In its January 5 note, the
                        United States apologized for the incident but “neither substantiated nor
                        ruled out” the claim that the damage was caused by U.S. aircraft.
                        (Ibid.)</note> A translation of the note is attached.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d10fn3">Not printed. In its January 12 note, the Soviet Government
                        replied that it could not “acknowledge the reply of the USA Government to be
                        convincing, since it not only does not contain a clear recognition of the
                        guilt of the American armed forces in the perpetration of the marauding
                        attack upon a Soviet merchant vessel in violation of all norms of
                        international law and freedom of navigation, but actually admits the
                        possibility of the repetition of such aggressive acts by the American air
                        forces.” Since <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> had informed
                            <persName corresp="#p_DA2">Dobrynin</persName> on January 9 of the
                        accidental dropping of 17 undetonated bombs near Haiphong, the Department
                        was surprised that the Soviet reaction was so muted. (Telegram 96905 to
                        Moscow, January 10, and telegram 98440 to Moscow, January 13; both
                        ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0070" n="26" xml:id="pg_26"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> pointed out that the Soviet
                    Government must recognize that ships operating in an area of active hostilities
                    run certain risks and it was impossible to guarantee that accidents would not
                    happen. As had been made clear in the United States Government note of January
                    5, all that could be done was to offer assurances that careful precautions would
                    be taken to avoid damage to non-hostile shipping in and around North Vietnam.
                    The United States Government regretted the damage caused to the Soviet ship in
                    the port of Haiphong and hoped that such incidents could be avoided in the
                    future. It was for this reason that additional information, of which the Chargé
                    was undoubtedly aware, had been passed to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DA2"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> by the Secretary of State earlier this week. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> pointed out that there
                    could be no real guarantee against damage to Soviet shipping so long as Soviet
                    ships operated in the North Vietnamese waters.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CY1">Chernyakov</persName> said his instructions did not
                    go beyond the delivery of the note itself, but he would point out on a personal
                    basis that attacks on Soviet shipping were in contravention of international law
                    and violation of the principle of freedom of navigation. In <persName
                        corresp="#p_CY1">Chernyakov</persName>’s view the best way to avoid further
                    incidents would be to stop the bombing.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> replied that the bombing
                    could stop tomorrow if the North Vietnamese would comply with the Geneva accords
                    and withdraw their forces from South Vietnam. If this should be done, then
                    difficulties stemming from such developments as the January 4 incident involving
                    the “Pereyaslavl-Zalesskiy” would not arise between our two countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CY1">Chernyakov</persName> referred to <persName
                        corresp="#p_NDT1">Trinh</persName>’s statement of December 30<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d10fn4">See <ref target="#d1">Document 1</ref>.</note> and said that
                    it was clear that talks would take place if the bombing were stopped.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> said that the United States
                    Government’s position on cessation of bombing was clearly set forth by the
                    President in his San Antonio speech in which the President said that he would be
                    prepared to stop the bombing if it was clear that such action would lead to
                    productive talks. Was it <persName corresp="#p_CY1">Chernyakov</persName>’s view
                    that <persName corresp="#p_NDT1">Trinh</persName>’s offer was a serious one?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CY1">Chernyakov</persName> said that his Government
                    certainly regarded <persName corresp="#p_NDT1">Trinh</persName>’s offer as a
                    serious one and the only way to ascertain if talks could be productive would be
                    to stop the bombing in order to permit them to take place. He did not wish to
                    criticize the statements by President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                        >Johnson</persName>, but he would point out that whereas in the past the
                    President had said that the United States Government attached no preconditions
                    to talks, the San Antonio formula seemed to impose the condition that talks must
                    be productive.</p>
                <pb facs="0071" n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> felt that it was wrong to
                    regard the San Antonio formula as imposing conditions on talks. Obviously, if
                    the North Vietnamese should insist that the agenda for talks be limited to
                    Hanoi’s four points, then there would be no purpose in talks since obviously
                    they could not be productive. This was the meaning of the San Antonio formula in
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName>’s view.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CY1">Chernyakov</persName> said that he would only point
                    out that in his December 30 statement <persName corresp="#p_NDT1"
                        >Trinh</persName> made no mention of the four points.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CY1">Chernyakov</persName> was asked if his Government
                    planned to publicize the note which he had handed Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_CY1"
                        >Chernyakov</persName> had said his instructions did not refer to publicity
                    and he would point out on a personal basis that his Government’s note of January
                        4<note n="5" xml:id="d10fn5">The January 4 Soviet note demanded punishment
                        of those responsible for the incident and called for U.S. assurances that it
                        would not happen again. (Telegram 94518 to Moscow, January 6; National
                        Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET S)</note>
                    was made public.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
