<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>100. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d100</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">100</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-05-04T17:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recWMZ9EcUPmDYpbT" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006001993"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Interagency</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recSWpZOc8YpkYHHD" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-05-04T17:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="100" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d100">
                <head>100. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On March 2, 1968, the <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName> Task Force
                    began its comprehensive reassessment of Vietnam policy by considering a
                    preliminary draft of a memorandum to the President. This memorandum and its
                    accompanying backup materials were prepared in the Department of Defense by a
                    staff under the direction of <persName corresp="#p_GL1">Leslie Gelb</persName>
                    of the Office of International Security Affairs (<gloss target="#t_ISA1"
                        >ISA</gloss>) and was reviewed by the Assistant Secretary for International
                    Security Affairs <persName corresp="#p_WP1">Paul Warnke</persName>, Deputy
                    Assistant Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_HM1">Morton Halperin</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Richard Steadman</persName>, and Assistant
                    Secretary for Systems Analysis <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Alain
                        Enthoven</persName>. The staff compilers suggested that an increased level
                    of forces alone would not lead to the achievement of the U.S. political or
                    military objectives in South Vietnam. The enemy would match any augmentation,
                    the additional troops would be inadequate to drive the Communist forces out of
                    South Vietnam, having 700,000 troops would lead to a “total Americanization of
                    the war” which would serve to undermine the effectiveness of and confidence in
                    the South Vietnamese Government (<gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>), and the
                    call-up and consequent expenditures would lead to severe domestic problems
                    within the United States. The only way to achieve eventual success was for the
                        <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to provide effective military and
                    political leadership for its people. Thus, the preliminary memorandum concluded,
                    U.S. troops should no longer engage in attriting the enemy through search and
                    destroy operations. Instead, U.S. combat units should confine their operations
                    to providing security for the populace and to supporting operations undertaken
                    by the South Vietnamese Army (<gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>). For text
                    of this memorandum, see <hi rend="italic">The Pentagon Papers: The Senator
                        Gravel Edition</hi>, pages 561–568. The interagency memoranda and reports
                    comprising the backup material numbered over 40 attachments and are in the
                    Johnson Library, Alain Enthoven Papers, Draft Presidential Memorandum on Vietnam
                    1968.</p>
                <p>Notes of the meetings of the <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName>
                    group have not been found. However, the meetings are described in <persName
                        corresp="#p_HT1">Townsend Hoopes</persName>, <hi rend="italic">The Limits of
                        Intervention</hi> (New York: David McKay, 1969), pages 171–181; <hi
                        rend="italic">Larry Berman, <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon
                            Johnson</persName>’s War</hi> (New York: Norton, 1989), pages 176–180;
                    Herbert Schandler, <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon Johnson</persName> and Vietnam: The
                        Unmaking of a President</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1977),
                    pages 143–156; and <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clark Clifford</persName>, <hi
                        rend="italic">Counsel to the President,</hi> pages 492–496.</p>
                <p>In an article he wrote in 1969, <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName>
                    noted the general tenor of the answers to the questions he sought to address
                    during his review. <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName> received no
                    assurances that the additional 200,000 men would turn the tide; instead there
                    was “no way of knowing” how many more soldiers might be needed. He further found
                    that the augmentation <pb facs="0352" n="308" xml:id="pg_308"/> would require a
                    reserve call-up of approximately 280,000, an increased draft call, and an
                    extension of tours of duty. <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName> also
                    was told that the enemy could match the build-up, that the costs of the build-up
                    would be $12 billion by 1969, that bombing would not stop the war or decrease
                    U.S. casualties, that U.S. troops would continue to carry the load since the
                        <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> “were not yet ready to replace our
                    troops,” that there was “no plan for victory in the historic American sense,”
                    and that there was “no agreement on an answer” as to how long it would take to
                    win the war of attrition. See <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clark
                        Clifford</persName>, “A Viet Nam Reappraisal: The Personal History of One
                    Man’s View and How It Evolved,” <hi rend="italic">Foreign Affairs</hi> 47:4
                    (July 1969), pages 601–622.</p>
                <p>According to <hi rend="italic">The Pentagon Papers,</hi> the group did not reach
                    a consensus on a new strategy but requested that <persName corresp="#p_WP1"
                        >Warnke</persName> and Assistant Secretary of Defense for Public Affairs
                    Philip Goulding draft a new and “less controversial” paper than the preliminary
                    memorandum. The new Draft Presidential Memorandum was discussed by the <persName
                        corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName> group on March 3. It recommended: <list>
                        <item>“1. Meeting General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1"
                                >Westmoreland</persName>’s request by deploying as close to May 1 as
                            practical 20,000 additional troops (approximately 1/2 of which would be
                            combat).</item>
                        <item>“2. Approval of a Reserve call-up and an increased end strength
                            adequate to meet the balance of the request and to restore a strategic
                            reserve in the United States, adequate for possible
                            contingencies.</item>
                        <item>“3. Reservation of the decision to deploy the balance of General
                                <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>’s new request.
                            While we would be in a position to make these additional deployments,
                            the future decision to do so would be contingent upon: <list>
                                <item>“a. Continuous reexamination of the desirability of further
                                    deployments on a week-by-week basis as the situation
                                    develops;</item>
                                <item>“b. Improved political performance by the <gloss
                                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and increased contributions in
                                    effective military action by the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1"
                                        >ARVN</gloss>;</item>
                                <item>“c. The results of a study in depth, to be initiated
                                    immediately, of a possible new strategic guidance for the
                                    conduct of U.S. military operations in South Vietnam.” (<hi
                                        rend="italic">The Pentagon Papers: The Senator Gravel
                                        Edition</hi>, page 573)</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The final version of the Draft Presidential Memorandum is printed as <ref
                        target="#d103">Document 103</ref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
