<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>117. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d117</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">117</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-03-11T06:42:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-03-11T06:42:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recAWJwqRIM3ZNS4f" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="reciuru9i20NCuS5s" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recJwYAJf2vdRiALq" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039539"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Mobility</term>
                    <term ref="recowpyti3dV3RE8o" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066333"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Infrastructure</term>
                    <term ref="recBu49iaA1LjksYs" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general">Government reform</term>
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-03-11T06:42:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-03-11T06:42:00-05:00" n="117"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                <head>117. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d117fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET S. Top Secret; Immediate;
                        Nodis. Received at 10:48 a.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-03-11T11:42:00+00:00">March 11, 1968,
                        1142Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>21733. Ref: State 124584.<note n="2" xml:id="d117fn2">In telegram 124584 to
                        Saigon, March 5, the Department transmitted the text of the paper attached
                        as Tab B to <ref target="#d103">Document 103</ref>. (National Archives and
                        Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                        1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 VIET S)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>I agree that the question of additional US troops for Vietnam raises
                        fundamental questions regarding our policy here. As the paper contained in
                            <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> indicates, the positive and
                        negative effects of an increase on the Vietnamese Government and people
                        involve difficult judgments affecting both our long-range and short-term
                        objectives here.</item>
                    <pb facs="0404" n="360" xml:id="pg_360"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>A critical element in judging the effects of an increase in US forces is
                        obviously the size of that increase. General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1"
                            >Westmoreland</persName>, based on his understanding of the capabilities
                        of the military services to deploy trained units, has recommended that the
                        first increment should amount to an additional seven combat maneuver
                        battalions plus an MP battalion. These forces are needed to partially offset
                        troops which have already been dispatched to northern I Corps. If Pres
                        Thieu’s analysis of enemy strategy and capability is correct, <gloss
                            target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> forces
                        can be expected to mount another major offensive in the late spring or
                        summer. This offensive must be decisively defeated. Even though Vietnamese
                        forces will be building up during the time between now and summer, we can
                        not expect them to be fully trained, equipped and in place before this phase
                        occurs. I would therefore favor earliest deployment of the first increment
                        recommended by General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>.
                        The question of the dispatch of forces beyond this increment should be
                        reexamined at a later date in the light of the situation during the summer
                        months. The comments that follow relate to the general problems I forsee
                        resulting from additional US forces, although I believe these problems will
                        be manageable if the increase is limited to the numbers proposed under
                        General Westmoreland’s recommendation for a first increment. I am not
                        attempting to address in this message the effects of the proposed deployment
                        of additional US forces in terms of measures required in the US to back up
                        this action and give us the required reserve forces, since these are matters
                        which have to be determined in Washington.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>I agree that the deployment of additional US troops would probably stiffen
                        the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s will at a critical time and would
                        be a further affirmation of our commitment and of our capability to meet it.
                        The countervailing factor that it could tend to further Americanize the war
                        and give the Vietnamese an escape route from their responsibility is an
                        important consideration, however. The Tet attacks have given the
                        anti-Communist elements here both a shock and a shot in the arm, as <gloss
                            target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> indicates. The question now is how to
                        take advantage of this without imposing impossible demands on the
                        government, which will tend to make it throw up its hands and slip away from
                        its responsibility, leaving us to carry the main burden. I think the answer
                        to this will turn both on the size and deployment of additional US forces
                        and on the availability of equipment and other support needed to allow the
                            <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to increase its military effort
                        promptly. In other words, we need to maintain a careful balance between
                        modernization of <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss> and the build-up of
                        our own forces. One of the clear lessons of the past few weeks has been that
                        the Communists have given all out support in terms of military equipment and
                        supplies for the <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_VC1"
                            >VC</gloss> and they have been able to outgun those <gloss
                            target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss> forces that are still equipped with our
                        older weapons. Our modernization program for <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1"
                            >RVNAF</gloss> is just beginning to make progress. We cannot afford to
                        let this <pb facs="0405" n="361" xml:id="pg_361"/> program slip and must
                        examine each major item carefully to insure that <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1"
                            >RVNAF</gloss> gets a fair share and that the momentum and confidence
                        inspired by issue of the new items is not lost. The number of additional US
                        troops contemplated for deployment should not have any appreciable effect
                        upon the modernization and improvement of <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1"
                            >RVNAF</gloss>. In fact, these two matters should go hand in hand to
                        increase the momentum of the overall build-up of strength and capability in
                        country to progressively destroy the enemy. I consider it most urgent that
                        we get the weapons <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss> needs over here
                        as expeditiously as possible, in order to maintain the momentum of the
                            <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s present mobilization plans. I view
                        this matter as both a short and long term objective, while in contrast the
                        provision of additional US forces is a necessary but a short term
                        goal.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I am concerned about sizable additional US forces because of the effects
                        of our overwhelming presence here and the possibility that the destructive
                        effect of our type of warfare will nullify some of our basic purpose. By
                        this I mean that we will increasingly come to play the role of a colonial
                        power, whether intentionally or not. For this reason, I think we must
                        maintain a very careful balance between what we undertake to do ourselves
                        and what we can achieve through pressure on the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss>, always bearing in mind what the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss> is capable of in terms of its own human resources. However,
                        bringing in the additional US forces presently contemplated should not add
                        seriously to the problem of an overwhelming US presence at this time, since
                        these forces will be deployed in the hinterlands fighting <gloss
                            target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>
                        units, where destruction and visibility should be minimal. Additional forces
                        when added to the proposed <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss> build-up,
                        should permit us to regain our momentum and accelerate it beyond that of
                        1967. The foregoing general observations underlie some of the specific
                        comments which follow in the numbered paragraphs of the paper quoted in
                            <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>I agree with para 3 that the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> has the
                        capacity to improve the security and political climate, and thus its image
                        in the US, but the definition of this capacity must be a realizable one.
                        Therefore, the range of decisions and actions to be required of the
                        government must be keyed to a realistic assessment of what they can do,
                        rather than an ideal related primarily to what we or American public opinion
                        would like to see. No matter how much we achieve here, the American press
                        and probably certain of our own Congress will never regard it as sufficient,
                        given their tendency sometimes to demand standards of perfection which even
                        we have not attained. I am confident that we and the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss> can do what is necessary, but in deciding what this is, we
                        must take sufficiently into account the fact that this is an underdeveloped
                        Asian nation torn by decades of war and with limited human resources,
                        endeavoring to function under a new and unaccustomed form of government in
                        which it has had little practice and less tradition.</item>
                    <pb facs="0406" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Re para 5 I agree that a high-level mission to Saigon can play a helpful
                        psychological role in this situation and Sec Clifford would be the ideal
                        person to head it. I would be inclined, however, to recommend that the
                        mission come at a somewhat later date, perhaps in April, to evaluate what is
                        being done and to give an added push to our effort, I could then continue
                        with the task of laying before the government what we expect of it and of
                        getting this effort under way. I should note at this point that most of the
                        decisions and actions listed are ones on which we have already been pushing
                        the government and on which they have already begun to take encouraging
                        action. This does not mean they cannot do more, but merely underlines the
                        fact that we in the Mission, as well as the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                            >GVN</gloss>, are basically on the same wave-length with Washington in
                        terms of our objectives, and of the time-frame within which we are
                        working.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Re para 6—mobilization, I have already reported on Pres Thieu’s decision
                        to accelerate the mobilization process and his desire to provide between
                        100,000 and 125,000 additional men for the armed forces during the next six
                        months. In this regard Pres Thieu envisages the extensive use of units on
                        Fairfax type operations to protect the cities, their environs, and the
                            <gloss target="#t_LOC1">LOC</gloss>s. We are working with the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to maintain key civilians in their
                        government functions where they cannot be spared or replaced. Gen <persName
                            corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> informs me that <gloss
                            target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 68 program for the expansion of the
                        Vietnamese armed forces involves an increase of 64,000 men. Only
                        approximately 25,000 of this force increase has been realized. The current
                        approved program is therefore short approximately 40,000 men, for which
                        equipment has been programmed. In accordance with this program, these 40,000
                        men were to be used to fill existing units and to activate the following
                        major elements: approximately 80 <gloss target="#t_RF1">RF</gloss> companies
                        and 250 <gloss target="#t_PF1">PF</gloss> platoons, 1 artillery battalion, 1
                        engineer battalion, 1 separate infantry regiment, and 2 infantry battalions
                        to flesh out existing regiments. If additional men are mobilized, <gloss
                            target="#t_RF1">RF</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_PF1">PF</gloss> units could
                        be organized and equipped with WW II-type weapons available by virtue of
                        receipt of more modern weapons by <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>. Gen
                        Westmoreland’s proposed <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 69 program
                        involves an increase of 93,000. A formal request for approval has been
                        submitted through his channel. Therefore it is <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1"
                            >Gen Westmoreland</persName>’s opinion that the number of men Thieu
                        plans to mobilize can be conscripted, trained and equipped. Assuming that
                        125,000 men are mobilized during the next six months, this will result in a
                        net increase of approximately 60,000 men in <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1"
                            >RVNAF</gloss> over current strength in consideration of estimated
                        losses of approximately 10,000 per month through casualties and desertions.
                        There will be shortages of some equipment until <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                            >FY</gloss> 68 programmed quantities are delivered and until <gloss
                            target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 69 items are programmed and available from
                        production. Individual weapons will <pb facs="0407" n="363" xml:id="pg_363"
                        /> again be of the WW II type and vehicle shortages will have some effect on
                        mobility. However, these problems are believed to be manageable. The major
                        problem is one of leadership, where it is estimated that officer and NCO
                        requirements may be difficult to fill. We feel that we should encourage
                        Thieu and the Joint General Staff to proceed soonest with their
                        mobilization, not only to form additional units that are sorely needed and
                        to fill up their ranks, but to deny this manpower to the Viet Cong, who are,
                        themselves, in desperate need of manpower.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Re para 7—<persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>/<persName
                            corresp="#p_NCK1">Ky</persName> relationship, this has been one of many
                        main preoccupations since my arrival almost a year ago. This relationship
                        continues to have its peaks and valleys, and it is now in one of its
                        valleys, but I shall continue to devote my fullest energies to maintaining
                        it and to encouraging a greater unity of leadership on all sides. The
                        objectives outlined in paras 7 and 8 are those which have guided me in the
                        past and I will continue to pursue them vigorously.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Re para 9 and 10—getting the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> back into
                        the countryside, this is a point on which <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Gen
                            Westmoreland</persName> and I have been pressing the top leadership
                        continuously for the past few weeks, and as I have reported, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> are fully in accord with it. While there have been
                        circles in the military leadership who have been too conservative and
                        reluctant to move out into the countryside, we believe that some success has
                        already been achieved, and in most areas this effort is already well
                        underway. We will continue to press vigorously in this direction and to
                        furnish the necessary support to make it possible for the government to take
                        the initiative without fear. Westmoreland and I agree regarding the vital
                        role of the province chiefs and their staff and the sense of mission of the
                            <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> units and we intend to pursue the
                        evaluation process at all levels.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Re para 11—drive on the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> infrastructure,
                        I agree that the pres-ent situation offers an opportunity which must be
                        exploited promptly and vigorously and we are already engaged with the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> in this process. It will be pushed with
                        even greater vigor.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Re para 12—government reform and anti-corruption campaign, Pres Thieu is
                        as you recognize, already moving in the desired directions and we will keep
                        up the pressures on him to accelerate the reform and to assure that it
                        achieves the desired purposes. I agree that incompetent military commanders,
                        province chiefs and civilian officials must be removed and that we should
                        make our own views on such persons known. The way in which this is done,
                        however, is something on which the judgment should be left to those of us
                        here on the spot. We understand the objective and agree with it. The only
                        point I would like to make at this stage is to emphasize that these changes
                        involve very complicated relationships among the leaders here, especially in
                        the military, <pb facs="0408" n="364" xml:id="pg_364"/> and that we must not
                        allow our eagerness for change to outweigh the overall objectives of
                        maintaining unity of leadership. I recognize that <persName
                            corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> is overly cautious and reluctant to
                        move in such matters, and I will continue to press him as needed, but we
                        must accept the fact that the definition of what is possible must in the
                        last analysis remain his, since he is the President.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>Re para 13—the united front. I agree that in order to take fullest
                        advantage of the nationalist spirit of cooperation, we must prevent personal
                        rivalries and differences from undermining this effort. The <persName
                            corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_NCK1"
                            >Ky</persName> relationship, the relations between the executive and
                        legislative branches, and the inter-play of political groups and leaders all
                        bear on this picture. One cautioning note which I would like to sound here
                        is that when we choose to stimulate Vietnamese initiatives for national
                        unity, they should be related to the actual political situation here and
                        should have lasting meaning in Asian terms, not just American ideas of what
                        we think they should develop. The skepticism with which the National
                        Salvation Front is viewed by many Vietnamese as evidence that the
                        introspective Vietnamese often finds a hidden meaning and purpose in what to
                        us seems logical and reasonable. We will continue to press for meaningful
                        efforts to unity the nationalist elements here and to create the basis for
                        longer-term political activity.</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>Re paras 14–16, we will be formulating further proposals on economic
                        measures along the lines suggested in these paragraphs.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>I believe that the factors discussed in paras 17–19—US actions and
                        leverage, have already been addressed at the beginning of this message. I
                        would merely reiterate here my general feeling that the emphasis should
                        remain on enlarging and modernizing <gloss target="#t_RVNAF1">RVNAF</gloss>
                        and that US force increase should be limited to what we consider essential
                        to maintain the offensive and to overcome certain geographic advantages
                        which the enemy has, without unduly widening the war or over-Americanizing
                        it. I know that this definition requires careful spelling out but I would
                        hope that this could be our basic guideline in doing so.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BE2">Bunker</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
