<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>126. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of the Air Force (Hoopes) to
                    Secretary of Defense ) to Secretary of Defense Clifford</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d126</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">126</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recNBOveCHYDHbAqL" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="126"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d126">
                <head>126. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of the Air Force (<persName
                        corresp="#p_HT1" type="from">Hoopes</persName>) to Secretary of Defense
                        <persName corresp="#p_CCM1" type="to">Clifford</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d126fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                        Center, Department of Defense, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> Files:
                            <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 330 73 A 1250, VIET 381, 1968.
                        Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-03-14">March 14, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The Infeasibility of Military Victory in Vietnam</item>
                </list>
                <p>As a contribution to current deliberations and to your own ongoing review of the
                    situation, this memorandum argues the case that the idea of military victory in
                    Vietnam is a dangerous illusion, at any price that would be compatible with US
                    interests, the interests of the people of South Vietnam, or the cause of world
                    peace. Secretary Brown agrees that it should be forwarded for your
                    consideration.</p>
                <p>Military victory—that is, the destruction or ejection of <gloss target="#t_NVN1"
                        >NVN</gloss> forces and reduction of <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                    guerrilla forces to impotence or at least to a level that is manageable by
                        <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> alone—has been the implicit (though
                    not always clearly recognized) goal of US policy at least since the decision <pb
                        facs="0424" n="380" xml:id="pg_380"/> to build up American manpower in 1965.
                    It continues to be the unexamined assumption of General Westmoreland’s strategy,
                    of his request for additional forces, of the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                    support for his strategy and his requests, and of all other proposals for
                    intensifying or enlarging our war effort in Vietnam.</p>
                <p>Moreover, military victory (as defined above) appears to be a necessary
                    precondition for the realization of a US political objective which defines “free
                    choice” for the people of <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> as a process
                    necessarily excluding <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_VC1"
                        >VC</gloss> from participation in either elections or government. Whether or
                    not this definition reflects the true US intent, it is clearly the position of
                    the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and has not been rejected by the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>. As is known, even non-communist politicians
                    are now being jailed by the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> out of fear that
                    they will open a dialogue with the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>. These
                    facts suggest that if military victory is not feasible, the US political
                    objective must be redefined.</p>
                <p>One’s assumption about the necessity or feasibility of military victory is
                    therefore a critical fork in the road. Reaffirmation will lead in the direction
                    of a larger and wider war effort aimed at destroying the <gloss target="#t_NVN1"
                        >NVN</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> forces. Refutation will lead
                    to adoption of a far less ambitious strategy, aimed at protecting the people of
                    South Vietnam, permitting a stabilization of the US resource commitment at
                    tolerable levels, and followed by a prompt, utterly serious effort to achieve a
                    compromise settlement of the war that reflects the enduring political and
                    military realities in Vietnam. It is imperative, at this watershed in our
                    Vietnam experience, to subject the assumption to the most searching
                    re-examination. Our future ability to formulate rational policies for <gloss
                        target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> depends on this.</p>
                <p>The history of our involvement in Vietnam, particularly since 1965, has been
                    marked by repeated miscalculations as to the force and time required to “defeat
                    the aggression,” pacify the countryside, and make the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> viable without
                    massive US support. Each fresh increment of American power has been justified as
                    the last one needed to do the job. Responsible political and military officials
                    have consistently underestimated <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>/<gloss
                        target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> strength and tenacity, have promoted uncritical
                    notions of what US military power can accomplish in the political and
                    geographical environment of <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>, and have
                    indulged in persistently wishful thinking as regards the present capacity and
                    real potential of the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and the <gloss
                        target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss>. It is important that these misjudgments be
                    kept in mind as we weigh the alternatives that now lie before us.</p>
                <p>The following points contain some material that may already have come to your
                    attention. The purpose here is to combine all of the relevant arguments and
                    bring them to focus on the root question of whether military victory is
                    feasible.</p>
                <pb facs="0425" n="381" xml:id="pg_381"/>
                <p>[Omitted here is the body of the memorandum, in which Hoopes discussed several
                    factors that mitigated against continued escalation in Vietnam. Military action
                    had not increased popular support for the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>,
                    which was compounded by its inability to control its own territory.
                    Significantly, the bombing campaign had failed to deter the enemy because of
                    support provided the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> by the Soviets and
                    Chinese. In addition, the air war’s impact on manpower was minimal. As a
                    consequence, Hoopes argued, “on balance, <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> is
                    a stronger military power today than before the bombing.” The introduction of
                    the troops Westmoreland wanted would cause a number of difficulties and likely
                    would not make much difference in terms of proportional strength. The <gloss
                        target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> could “neutralize” the proposed augmentation of
                    206,000 U.S. troops by deploying only 50,000 new troops of its own. With so many
                    troops in South Vietnam, the casualty rates would rise with resultant political
                    costs to the administration but without altering the fundamental conditions of
                    stalemate in Vietnam. In addition, the impact of the force augmentation would be
                    detrimental to efforts to reform and invigorate the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss>, would have a deleterious impact on the U.S. economy, and could
                    significantly undermine the domestic political order. An alternative means of
                    attacking the enemy by intensive bombing that included crop destruction could be
                    more effective in terms of sapping enemy will but would prove too costly to
                    implement.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HT1">Townsend Hoopes</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
