<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="202" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d202">
                        <head>202. Memorandum From the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                                (<persName corresp="#p_WGE1" type="from">Wheeler</persName>) to
                            Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_CCM1" type="to">Clifford</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d202fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, Executive Registry Subject
                                Files, Job 80–R01580R, 284—Order of Battle. Top Secret. In the
                                attached covering note to <persName corresp="#p_HRR1">Helms</persName>, April 22, <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wheeler</persName> wrote: “Dear Dick: Attached is my memorandum
                                to <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clark</persName> outlining Westy’s
                                views on the current Order of Battle strength problem. I share
                                Westy’s concern in this matter. I cannot help but feel that airing
                                these greatly increased strength figures at this time would be
                                detrimental to our effort in the long run. Sincerely, Bus.” The
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>’s differences with <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> over Order of Battle estimates
                                had grown since the previous fall. The issue is outlined in a paper
                                Enthoven submitted to <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clifford</persName> on June 28 entitled “Uncertainties About
                                    <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> Force Levels.” (<persName>Johnson</persName>
                                Library, Alain Enthoven Papers, Statistics on the War) The <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> dissent to the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>’s analysis is in a joint <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>/PACOM memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_HRR1">Helms</persName>, April 19. (Central Intelligence Agency,
                                Executive Registry Subject Files, Job 80–R01580R, 284—Order of
                                Battle)</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_CM1">CM</gloss>-3230–68</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-04-22">April 22,
                                1968</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> Order of Battle</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>As you know, <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> representatives are in
                                Washington attempting to reconcile total enemy strength issues
                                growing out of the leak of <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                                figures in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>.<note n="2" xml:id="d202fn2">At the <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>
                                    conference, <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> refused to
                                    accept any substantive changes. (Memorandum <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> No. 07068/68 from Paul Walsh,
                                    Deputy Director, Economic Research, to <persName corresp="#p_HRR1">Helms</persName>, May 2; ibid., O/DDI
                                    Files, Job 78–T02095R, April 1968 OB Conference)</note> They
                                report that <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> representatives are
                                about to forward a paper to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HRR1">Helms</persName> with total enemy strength including political
                                infrastructure of 480,000 to 615,000, about twice the previously
                                agreed figures. They base these figures on essentially the same
                                evidence and argumentation which were <pb facs="0627" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/> reflected by USIB in the formulation of <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> 14/3/67.<note n="3" xml:id="d202fn3">See <ref target="frus1964-68v05#d397"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. V,
                                        Document 397</ref>.</note> The only new element in the
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> case was the correct
                                assertion that <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> OB figures do
                                not always reflect all-source evidence. <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> representatives have agreed to adjust figures on
                                this basis, but this has made no appreciable effect on the wide
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> divergence from the <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The primary item of <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>’s
                                disagreement is the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> position
                                that the so-called insurgency base, consisting of self defense
                                forces, secret self defense forces, assault youth, etc., should be
                                quantified at a strength of 210,000 to 230,000. The <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> position is that quantification
                                is not possible, and that it gives the enemy credit for thousands of
                                people who exert no military effect. <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss> holds that some quantification of the insurgency
                                base is possible.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>’s refusal to quantify the
                                insurgency base stems from the following factors: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>A representative cross section of prisoners picked up
                                        during the Tet offensive were questioned by <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>. Not one has admitted to
                                        being a member of any of the organizations which <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> would quantify as “the
                                        insurgency base.”</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>If there were these thousands of people armed and in
                                        sympathy with the enemy, that is, in the “insurgency base,”
                                        then it is likely that they would have joined the enemy
                                        during the recent Tet offensive. On the contrary, the
                                        population rejected the Viet Cong; they did not flock to
                                        their cause.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>There is a much larger issue involved here than intelligence
                                methodology. The acceptance of this inflated strength, which General
                                Westmoreland believes cannot even be estimated with any degree of
                                confidence, is contrary to our national interest. The effect that
                                its inevitable public announcement would have on the American
                                public, which recognizes no qualification in semantics between
                                “military” and “insurgency base,” is obvious. The enemy, for his
                                part, would be given a psychological tool of incalculable value in
                                any subsequent negotiations.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>I am substantially in agreement with General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Earle G.
                                Wheeler</persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>