<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-06-24T16:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-06-24T16:50:00-05:00" n="281" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d281">
                        <head>281. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d281fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, A/IM Files:
                                Lot 93 D 82, <gloss target="#t_Harvan1">HARVAN</gloss>-(Incoming)-June 1968. Secret; Immediate; Nodis. In a
                                memorandum transmitting a copy of this telegram to the President,
                                June 24, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> wrote:
                                “Herewith Zorin—hitherto silent and frozen—suggests the A–B–C
                                formula for private exploration by Vance on Wednesday to Shriver, in
                                the course of a courtesy call. This is probably <persName corresp="#p_KA1">Kosygin</persName>’s reply to you. I have
                                arranged that Shriver’s cable be flashed for comment to Secretary
                                Rusk and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE2">Bunker</persName>.
                                The sequence is clearly: A. We name to Hanoi a ‘date certain’ for
                                cessation of bombing, i.e., a date to come into effect when B is
                                agreed. B. We negotiate what they would do when bombing has stopped.
                                C. We stop; and they stop doing what we negotiate after a
                                pre-negotiated interval. This could be the turning point, notably if
                                shipments are not coming through China.” (Johnson Library, National
                                Security File, Country File, Vietnam, M–Q, Vol. II, Paris
                                Talks—Messages from Other Posts) </note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-06-24T21:50:00+00:00">June 24,
                                    1968, 2150Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>16928. Summary:</p>
                        <p>Soviet Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_ZV1">Zorin</persName> today
                            recommended to me that U.S. delegation should utilize “coffee break this
                            Wednesday” to propose to Xuan Thuy directly Phase A-Phase B plan. He
                            stated his belief that U.S. agreement in principle to stop bombing on a
                            date certain would be followed by willingness <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> to enter into unofficial, by which he meant non-public,
                            talks looking toward deciding on circumstances which would follow in
                            Phase B. Upon deciding Phase B circumstances Phase A would be executed.
                            Thereafter at an interval Phase B actions would be carried out. Though
                            Zorin emphasized he could not guarantee results he unequivocally
                            reiterated three times his belief that North Vietnamese would respond.
                            And he said we should not be put off from pursuing this approach even if
                                <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>’s first response was “nyet.”
                            (End Summary)</p>
                        <p>Having scheduled routine protocol visit with wife to Soviet Embassy I was
                            advised that Zorin preferred to see me alone on business. He opened
                            discussion by requesting my views on U.S. political situation to which I
                            responded fully. I outlined candidly my views on possibilities <persName corresp="#p_HHH1">Humphrey</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MCE1">McCarthy</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_RN1">Rockefeller</persName>. I emphasized
                            President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> much freer,
                            more knowledgeable on details and thus in better position than any
                            successor to reach understandings with Soviet Union on subject V–N. I
                            recalled Glassboro speech, new consular treaty ceremony and President’s
                            remarks at White House. Although Zorin started our conversation
                            professing little knowledge of domestic U.S. political picture, he
                            responded to my analysis by saying he agreed with me completely, that
                            precious time should not be wasted, and that U.S. should take first big
                            step by stopping the bombing. After I repeated our well-known position,
                            he repeated their litany.</p>
                        <pb facs="0854" n="810" xml:id="pg_810"/>
                        <p>Having unloaded himself of their regular incantations, he proceeded to
                            add his opinion that if we would set a specific date for stopping the
                            bombing the North Vietnamese would respond immediately by entering into
                            unofficial talks to achieve complete peace. I said talk was cheap, that
                            President could not stop bombing for an agreement to talk, that even if
                            President wanted to do so he would lose support of the country and lose
                            any chance of obtaining Congressional approval of his actions, that such
                            an action might well elect <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                            and thus make peace negotiations even more difficult for North
                            Vietnamese.</p>
                        <p>He appeared to accept these arguments and responded by introducing Phase
                            A-Phase B plan. (He did not use this phrase name for plan but was
                            obviously referring to Phase A–B concept.) I pointed out my belief this
                            plan had been brought to attention North Vietnamese with no results. He
                            asked if plan had actually been discussed with North Vietnamese,
                            directly. When I could neither affirm or deny exact details, he
                            recommended that plan be brought up directly by Vance with Xuan
                                Thuy.<note n="2" xml:id="d281fn2">In telegram 189086/Todel 521 to
                                Paris, June 24, <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> sent
                                the following message to Vance: “Dobrynin told Secretary and myself
                                that Hanoi representatives in Paris had informed the Soviet
                                Government they would talk to us in private but had not specified
                                how soon. You may find opportunity at tea break Wednesday to raise
                                this subject again without, of course, involving the Soviets.”
                                (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, IS/OIS Files: Lot 90 D 345, Paris
                                Peace Conference on Vietnam, 1968–1969, Todel Chron.) </note> To
                            assure myself <persName corresp="#p_ZV1">Zorin</persName>’s exact
                            intention I repeated to him my understanding his recommendation as set
                            forth in Summary above. He responded yes “Vance should say that” and he
                            thereupon lifted a heretofore untouched glass of wine and said “a votre
                            sante.”</p>
                        <p>Zorin’s manner today totally different than on occasion of embassy lunch
                            with <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, Perry and me.
                            Zorin was full of smiles, laughed out loud 2 or 3 times, and upon my
                            departure said he hoped Mrs. Shriver would soon call upon Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_ZV1">Zorin</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_ZV1">Zorin</persName> mentioned <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName>’s talk with Oberemko and was apparently aware that
                                <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName> had gotten nowhere with
                            Phase A-Phase B idea on that occasion.<note n="3" xml:id="d281fn3">See
                                    <ref target="#d280fn5">footnote 5, Document 280</ref>.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ZV1">Zorin</persName> also completely frank and
                            expansive on French elections which is subject of separate message.<note n="4" xml:id="d281fn4">Telegram 16929 from Paris, June 24. (National
                                Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, IS/OIS Files: Lot 90 D 345, Paris Peace
                                Conference on Vietnam, 1968–1969, Todel Chron.)</note></p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_VCR1">Vance</persName> has read this
                            cable.</p>
                        <closer><signed>Shriver</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>