<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>58. Notes of Meeting</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-02-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-02-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="58"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                <head>58. Notes of Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d58fn1">Source: Johnson
                        Library, <persName corresp="#p_JWTT1">Tom Johnson</persName>’s Notes of
                        Meetings. Top Secret. The meeting ran from 10:31 to 11:55 a.m. (Ibid.,
                        President’s Daily Diary)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-02-06">February 6, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">NOTES OF THE PRESIDENT’S MEETING WITH SENIOR FOREIGN POLICY
                    ADVISERS</p>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>THOSE ATTENDING WERE</head>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>General <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wheeler</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CCM1">Clark Clifford</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CGA2">George Christian</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JWTT1">Tom Johnson</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>There was a general discussion of the proposed speech to be given by the
                    President on the <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi> and Vietnam developments.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>: Some parts of the speech
                    are unnecessary. I do not think it should be given at this time. Extending tours
                    of duty in Vietnam could have a serious effect on the morale of the men.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wheeler</persName>: I agree with the
                    consensus here. I think this speech should be made when events are clearer in
                    Vietnam and Korea. I would counsel against public announcement of a decision to
                    extend tours of duty in Vietnam. It would alarm the American people rather than
                    reassure them.</p>
                <p>The President: We must lay out this situation in a clear logical explanation of
                    what happened. I do accept your advice that it would be ill advised for the
                    President to do this now.</p>
                <p>The President then asked <persName corresp="#p_JWTT1">Tom Johnson</persName> to
                    read the four points of criticism by Senator <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Robert
                        Byrd</persName> (West Virginia).<note n="2" xml:id="d58fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Byrd</persName> made his statement at the
                        President’s breakfast for the Congressional leadership that morning. In
                        response to <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Byrd</persName>’s statement, the
                        President replied: “I don’t agree with any of that. We knew that they
                        planned a general uprising around Tet. Our intelligence showed there was a
                        winter-spring offensive planned. We did not know the precise places that
                        were going to be hit. General <persName corresp="#p_AGC1">Abrams</persName>
                        said the Vietnamese are doing their best. There was no military victory for
                        the Communists. Just look at the casualties and the killed in action.”
                        (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_JWTT1">Tom Johnson</persName>’s Notes of
                        Meetings)</note> The four items follow: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Poor intelligence.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Poor preparations for these recent attacks.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Underestimated Viet Cong morale and vitality.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Overestimated support of South Vietnamese people and army.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0180" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/>
                <p>The President said he was alarmed at this and that the attitude expressed by
                    Senator <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Byrd</persName> seemed to be reflected by
                    much of the comment heard in Washington not only by politicians but by the
                    press.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CGA2">George Christian</persName>: The story circulating
                    now is that we must have a confrontation with the South Vietnamese government to
                    get them to do more.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>: We have more evidence now
                    than ever before about South Vietnam’s role in this recent series of attacks.
                    The government was cool. It never broke down. The Vietnamese military took the
                    brunt of the attacks. General <persName corresp="#p_AGC1">Abrams</persName>
                    gives them very high marks.</p>
                <p>The President: We should get to the Members of Congress information about all of
                    this so that when they return to their homes they know what line to follow.</p>
                <p>I want to send South Korea what they need. I am afraid that many people now are
                    working towards the objective of undermining support and destroying our
                    relationship with the South Vietnamese and with the South Koreans, and with many
                    people in this country. There seems to be a great effort to discredit this
                    government and its military establishment. Only yesterday I told Mr. Henry
                    Brandon of the London Daily Telegram that I fully support General <persName
                        corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> and that any talk of his removal
                    is absolutely untrue.<note n="3" xml:id="d58fn3">On the afternoon of February 5,
                        the President met with Brandon in an off-the-record session to discuss the
                            <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi>, Vietnam, and the domestic political
                        situation. (Ibid., President’s Daily Diary)</note> I took a bit of the steam
                    out of him by showing him an “Eyes Only” cable to General <persName
                        corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> expressing my full support for
                    him and his actions.<note n="4" xml:id="d58fn4">Telegram <gloss target="#t_CAP1"
                            >CAP</gloss> 80390 from the President to <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1"
                            >Westmoreland</persName>, February 5, reads: “There is some
                        irresponsible talk in the newspapers abroad and here today that we have lost
                        confidence in you. I wish to tell you in the bluntest and most direct way I
                        can that I have never dealt with a man in whom I had more confidence. You
                        and your Vietnamese colleagues have, in my judgment, dealt with the attack
                        on the cities well. It is my judgment that your leadership and <persName
                            corresp="#p_BE2">Ellsworth</persName>’s will bring us much further ahead
                        a month from now than we otherwise would have been. Let us make that happen.
                        I believe that everything you have asked for has been supplied. As you go
                        into this battle, you have my fullest possible confidence and support.”
                        (Ibid., National Security File, NSC History of the March 31st Speech) In
                        telegram <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss> 1719 to the President, February
                        7, <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> replied: “Am
                        grateful to you for your message of yesterday, wherein you expressed your
                        confidence in this command. Be assured we are doing all possible to deal the
                        Communist aggressor a severe blow. There are difficult days ahead, but we
                        are fully confident in our ability to prevail over the enemy. Faithfully
                        yours.” (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 407, Litigation Collection, <persName
                            corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> v. <gloss target="#t_CBS1"
                            >CBS</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> Backchannel Messages
                        from <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>, 1–12 Feb 1968
                        [Folder I])</note>
                </p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wheeler</persName>: I talked with General
                        <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> this morning and he
                    said he was deeply appreciative of the message from the President. He said that
                    General <persName corresp="#p_AGC1">Abrams</persName> would appear before the
                    Press Corps to outline how pleased he has been with the performance of the South
                    Vietnamese Army.</p>
                <pb facs="0181" n="137" xml:id="pg_137"/>
                <p>[Omitted here is a brief discussion of the <hi rend="italic">Pueblo</hi>
                    crisis.]</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>: I am very disturbed
                    about what the President said about the leadership, particularly Senator
                        <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Byrd</persName>. He treated Buzz rather badly in
                    testimony this week.</p>
                <p>The President: This is all part of a political offensive. They say we had the
                    people believing we were doing very well in Vietnam when we actually were
                    not.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_WGE1">Wheeler</persName>: This reminds me of the
                    time of the <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Battle</persName> of the Bulge. The
                    Germans did achieve tactical surprise both in method and in their timing. They
                    stretched the Seventh Army out like an accordion. The Germans did much like the
                    Viet Cong and the North Vietnamese, even to wearing United States uniforms. I
                    never heard at that time anybody who wanted to fire General <persName
                        corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> because of bad intelligence. It was
                    a severe defeat for at least one unit—the Army 99th Infantry Division. Having
                    been there, I do know that we lost some of our heavy artillery—15 of our 18
                    guns. We have had nothing like that during this current battle.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName> was aware and
                    concerned about these attacks. He had the highest possible state of alert. Had
                    he not done this, the situation would have been much worse.</p>
                <p>We cannot have the precise plans of the enemy without some amazing stroke of
                    luck.</p>
                <p>Frankly Senator <persName corresp="#p_BR1">Byrd</persName> surprises me on Khe
                    Sanh, I gave him the best response I could. I tried to put the military victory
                    in context.</p>
                <p>The President: I told him he should be defending us rather than attacking us. I
                    disagreed with all points that were made. I say this to let you know what is
                    going on.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>: If the war goes well, the
                    American people are with us. If the war goes badly they are against us. The only
                    way for us to answer this is for the military situation out there to come out
                    alright. I think the men in uniform now have the burden in determining how much
                    support or lack of support we get.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
