<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-11-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-11-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="102" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d102">
                    <head>102. Memorandum From the Assistant Director, Latin America, United States
                        Information Agency (<persName corresp="#p_CRL_1">Chatten</persName>) to the
                        Deputy Director (<persName corresp="#p_BCW_1">Bray</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d102fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, Office of the Director, Executive
                            Secretariat, Secretariat Staff, Correspondence Files, 1973–1980, Entry
                            P–104, Box 146, 7704660–7704669. Limited Official Use. Copies were sent
                            to <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1">Reinhardt</persName> and <gloss target="#t_IOP_1">IOP</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_BCW_1">Bray</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LT_1">Liu</persName>
                            initialed the memorandum, indicating that they saw it. In an undated
                            note to <persName corresp="#p_CRL_1">Chatten</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BCW_1">Bray</persName> commented, “Very interesting.
                            Suggest distribution to other areas and <gloss target="#t_DHA_1">D/HA</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_DPM_1">Derian</persName>. Will
                            you be following thru on basic ideas? <gloss target="#t_CB_1">CB</gloss>.” A notation in an unknown hand on the note reads, “11/14
                            Delivered orig. of note &amp; memo to <gloss target="#t_ILA_1">ILA</gloss>.” (Ibid.)</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-11-08">November 8, 1977</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Meeting with Southern Cone <gloss target="#t_PAO_1">PAOs</gloss> on
                            Human Rights Programming</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>I brought together the <gloss target="#t_PAO_1">PAOs</gloss> from the four
                        countries of the Southern Cone—Argentina, Chile, Paraguay, Uruguay—on my
                        recent trip to the area in order to discuss programing relating to human
                        rights themes. The following is a review of the highlights of that meeting
                        divided into four sections: the situation as the <gloss target="#t_PAO_1">PAOs</gloss> perceive it, our consensus on thematic emphases for
                        programs relating to their countries, the <gloss target="#t_PAO_1">PAOs</gloss>’ recommendations for support they could use from the media
                        elements and their recommendations for support from non-media elements.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Situation:</p>
                    <p>The width of the spectrum of definition of human rights frequently has proved
                        to be an impediment to their search for increased understanding and support
                        for United States positions. The conceptual framework set by the Secretary
                        of State of there being three groups of human rights seemed to suggest a
                        potentially productive approach.<note n="2" xml:id="d102fn2">In telegram
                            98034 to all diplomatic and consular posts, April 30, the Department
                            referenced <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>’s April 30
                            address at the University of Georgia School of Law (see <ref target="#d67fn15">footnote 15, Document 67</ref>), and outlined the
                            “high points” of the address, including the definition of human rights
                            as: “1) The right to be free from governmental violation of the
                            integrity of the person, such as torture, etc; 2) The right to the
                            fulfillment of such vital needs as food, shelter, health care and
                            education; and 3) The right to enjoy civil and political liberties, such
                            as freedom of thought. etc.” The telegram is printed in <ref target="frus1977-80v02#d39">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. II, Human
                                Rights and Humanitarian Affairs, Document 39</ref>.</note> These
                        groups have been called “clusters” by Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TTA_1">Todman</persName>. But during our meeting we used the
                        Helsinki terminology and called them basket one (Integrity of the Person),
                        basket two (Economic and Social Justice), and basket three (Civil and
                        Political Liberties). There was consensus that for many purposes of policy
                        explication it would be useful to confine the term “human rights” to
                        references to basket <pb facs="0345" n="296" xml:id="pg_296"/> one. This
                        would not preclude extensive programing on human rights in the basket two
                        and basket three areas, but it would dictate a more productive approach to
                        policy explication. It also would prevent defenders of offensive foreign
                        government policies from saying, as some are doing, “We have excellent
                        programs and are making measurable progress in economic and social justice
                        and, while we have for the moment non-democratic governments, there are
                        numerous civil and political liberties to which we point with pride. Since
                        that seems to make up the majority of what you Americans are talking about
                        when you say human rights, our area of dispute is only a small one over on
                        the ‛integrity of the person’ end of the scale.”</p>
                    <p>But problems of the basket one variety are everywhere. It is a revealing
                        commentary that the phrase “to disappear someone” has entered the language
                        down South.</p>
                    <p>The governments of all four countries are, to one degree or another, on the
                        outs with the United States, perceiving our approach to be all stick and no
                        carrot. Argentine Charge Max Chaplin, for example, was beset by the
                        implications of the basic, pragmatic problem of how to move President
                            <persName corresp="#p_VJR_1">Videla</persName> to action when much of
                        the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> approach puts distance between us
                        and him. The Uruguayan and Paraguayan governments are reluctant even to
                        admit they have human rights problems. The Argentine and Chilean governments
                        view threats to their institutions and general well-being as the motivation
                        for their actions. There is a widespread official belief that foreign media
                        distort situations in the Southern Cone. Any time a United States official
                        can be quoted as saying the U.S. media do not give a balanced picture of the
                        Hemisphere, governments (and others) leap upon the statement as support for
                        their positions.</p>
                    <p>The one problem thread which ran consistently through discussions of the
                        situation was the difficulty <gloss target="#t_PAO_1">PAOs</gloss> have in
                        answering critics who claim the United States is following a double standard
                        in its application of sanctions on human rights violators. There is
                        considerable resentment, especially at government levels, about people’s
                        perceptions that they are being singled out by the United States.</p>
                    <p>The cultural and historical context in which human rights are viewed is
                        important in all countries. The context, in brief, has “rights” on a
                        continuum with the institutional preservation of the state, church and
                        family taking precedence over individual rights. Thus, when governments and
                        others say they don’t understand what we are talking about, they are not
                        always motivated by mere self-interest or intransigence, as they are
                        sometimes accused of in Washington.</p>
                    <p>But while it is useful to remember that governments of Southern Cone
                        countries are not the only audiences to have furrowed brows over just what
                        is meant when U.S. Government spokesmen discuss <pb facs="0346" n="297" xml:id="pg_297"/> human rights, non-government audiences usually are
                        more attuned to the positive implications of the U.S. Government policy in
                        all three baskets. Media audiences are particularly important, since
                        out-of-office and opposition politicians congregate there and the media form
                        a traditional and usually not-yet-closed-off forum for debate and opposition
                        to government policies. The academic world is another key sector in which
                        there is considerable sympathy for and more constructive debate about United
                        States human rights policies in all areas. Businessmen and church leaders
                        are other audiences which offer not only promise but have been the locus of
                        some progress in post program efforts. There was unanimity that military
                        audiences should not be written off entirely as targets for <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> programing. The key to these seems to be
                        military educational institutions, which have received, in general, less
                        attention than their importance merits.</p>
                    <p>Receptivity for human rights related materials has increased everywhere,
                        doubling in two months in Argentina alone, and posts now have developed
                        lists of target audiences for these materials and programs.</p>
                    <p>In the program realm, all felt that official spokesmen have been particularly
                        good, with Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TTA_1">Todman</persName>, Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DPM_1">Derian</persName> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LAK_1">Lowenstein</persName> getting very good reviews as visitors.<note n="3" xml:id="d102fn3">
                            <persName corresp="#p_DPM_1">Derian</persName> traveled to Argentina in
                            April and August; <persName corresp="#p_LAK_1">Lowenstein</persName>
                            visited Chile in early August, as did <persName corresp="#p_TTA_1">Todman</persName>, who also traveled to Uruguay and Argentina.
                            (“Carter Rights Aide, Visiting Argentina, Warns on Violations,” <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, April 3, 1977, p. 11; Juan de
                            Onis, “Carter Aide Again in Argentina for Assessment of Human Rights,”
                                <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, August 9, 1977, p. 4;
                            “Brazil Rejects Visit by <persName corresp="#p_LAK_1">Lowenstein</persName>,” <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>,
                            August 12, 1977, p. A–5; John Dinges, “Visiting U.S. Official Praises
                            Progress on Human Rights in Chile,” <hi rend="italic">The Washington
                                Post</hi>, August 14, 1977, p. C4, and “U.S. Official Has Talks in
                            Argentina,” <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, August 16, 1977,
                            p. 6) Documents on <persName corresp="#p_DPM_1">Derian</persName>’s and
                                <persName corresp="#p_TTA_1">Todman</persName>’s visits are
                            scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1977-80v24">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XXIV,
                                South America; Latin America Region</ref>.</note> Some programs
                        built around non-official visitors have been quite good, with Judge
                        Christian and William Ascher topping the list. Others got more mixed
                        reviews. Jack Hopkins did well in Chile and Central America but somewhat
                        less well in Argentina and Uruguay.</p>
                    <p>Whatever <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Washington’s approach may be,
                        the overriding consideration for programing and focus is the perception of
                        the American Ambassador, who sets the tone of the Mission in all cases. The
                        most dramatic example of this has been in Uruguay, where Ambassador
                            <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName>’s approach to human
                        rights programing was notably different from Ambassador Pezzullo’s.</p>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> is uniquely fitted to approaching
                        certain audiences on this subject and the situation, now that the United
                        States Government’s interest in the subject seems to have been clearly
                        established, brings <pb facs="0347" n="298" xml:id="pg_298"/> the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> to a “point of dialogue” with various
                        audiences. Both in policy and in societal projection, <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> now has space in which to grow.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Themes:</p>
                    <p>Because of the possible confusion between human rights “baskets” and Helsinki
                        “baskets,” I recommend scrapping the terminology of our meeting and using at
                        least a working title of groups 1, 2 and 3.</p>
                    <p>The following thematic areas have the endorsement of the group for <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> focus in response to the situation as
                        they perceive it:</p>
                    <p>—The problem involved with human rights, their advocacy, their enforcement
                        and our perceptions are universal, not bilateral. To help meet the double
                        standard question, emphasis upon the universality of application of U.S.
                        criteria would be very useful. Belgrade was cited as a possible example,
                        recognizing the possible pitfalls if the United States were seen as
                        equivocal there.</p>
                    <p>—“Human rights” per se should refer wherever possible to group one type
                        cases. Groups two and three should be focused more in the area of “problems
                        of democracy” or “problems of development” in order to keep the distinction
                        clear but still leave us room to emphasize all. Thus human rights in the
                        context of democratic traditions would be a valuable thematic area for group
                        three emphasis.</p>
                    <p>—All felt that human rights materials related to the Soviets would be
                        particularly useful. If we criticize the Soviets on human rights, it
                        undercuts the notion that human rights violations are an unfortunate but
                        necessary result of fighting communism, a position advanced universally by
                        Southern Cone governments. Such materials also would help counter the
                        feeling that the United States is singling them out.</p>
                    <p>—Governments and other audiences are quite sensitive to their image abroad
                        and its decline as a result of human rights-related confrontations, a useful
                        theme to pursue.</p>
                    <p>—Though there was general awareness that U.S. reporting on human rights
                        developments elsewhere carries dangers of being counter-productive if people
                        were to see us as taking credit for progress, all felt that such information
                        should be made available to them for discreet use in policy explication. The
                        basic logic was that it now is no secret that the United States is focusing
                        many of its foreign policy concerns around human rights but that there
                        remains a sometimes critical shortage of additional information, especially
                        facts that would lend credence to our attempts to universalize the problem
                        and our approach to it.</p>
                    <p>—There was consensus endorsement of all materials developing the concept of
                        human rights over time and geography. E.g., there are historical roots
                        within U.S. society that could be emphasized in countering the notion that
                        the human rights policy is an aberration <pb facs="0348" n="299" xml:id="pg_299"/> which appeared on their doorsteps last January 20. The
                        world context of all three groups likewise is a productive theme, the <gloss target="#t_PAO_1">PAOs</gloss> felt.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Media Guidance:</p>
                    <p>Aside from reference to the previous section on themes, the <gloss target="#t_PAO_1">PAOs</gloss> can use well:</p>
                    <p>—Soon-as-possible receipt of all human rights-related statements of the State
                        Department spokesmen.</p>
                    <p>—All official human rights-related policy statements on videotape (16 <gloss target="#t_mm_1">mm</gloss> film for Argentina).</p>
                    <p>—A compendium of basic human rights documents from <gloss target="#t_RSC_1">RSC</gloss>, leading with the <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> statement,<note n="4" xml:id="d102fn4">Reference
                            is presumably to <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>’s
                            March 7 statement before the Subcommittee on Foreign Assistance of the
                            Senate Foreign Relations Committee. For the text, see Department of
                            State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, March 28, 1977, pp. 289–291. The
                            statement is also printed in <ref target="frus1977-80v01#d27">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. I,
                                Foundations of Foreign Policy, Document 27</ref>.</note> which all
                        believed was the most useful single policy declaration made to date.</p>
                    <p>—All speech texts and transcripts of testimony.</p>
                    <p>—Interpretive materials on all human rights-related votes in <gloss target="#t_IFI_1">IFI</gloss>s.</p>
                    <p>—Copies of any <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> commentaries on the
                        subject.</p>
                    <p>—A human rights focus in the magazines, but only if care is taken not to
                        allow this focus to exclude other materials. The logic was that <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> and the United States have great
                        credibility on a wide variety of other subjects ranging from science and
                        technology to culture and education. This credibility should be used to
                        associate with and enhance whatever we have to say about human rights.</p>
                    <p>—Uruguay can use tapes of testimony or speeches in order to make cassettes
                        for use on a special human rights tape deck set up in the library. Uruguay
                        also needs particular attention to radio materials since they are especially
                        useful there.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Other Support:</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_PAO_1">PAOs</gloss> also suggested as useful:</p>
                    <p>—Q and A papers or background think pieces on subjects related to all three
                        groups to send to their “human rights lists” or for use in preparing local
                        talks (Chile and Paraguay).</p>
                    <p>—A continuing availability of official visitors who could serve as spokesmen,
                        as long as peculiar local circumstances are taken fully into consideration,
                        as was the case of Uruguay and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LAK_1">Lowenstein</persName>.</p>
                    <p>—<gloss target="#t_IV_1">IV</gloss> grants from both media and military, for
                        reasons outlined in “situation”.</p>
                    <pb facs="0349" n="300" xml:id="pg_300"/>
                    <p>—Full sets of the State Department reports to Congress for placement in the
                        library reference sections, the reports which did so much set the human
                        rights policy ball rolling.<note n="5" xml:id="d102fn5">Reference is to the
                            annual human rights country reports produced by the Department of
                            State.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>—Books concentrating principally upon group three items—institutional
                        problems of democracy. Presentation copies in English are the minimum they
                        could use, but all hoped for program books in Spanish as well.</p>
                    <p>—Approximately four Washington-supplied speakers a year who need not bear any
                        labels of being “human rights speakers”. These would concentrate primarily
                        in the group two and three area. It was expected that official visitors
                        should concentrate on group one, with some background discussion on groups
                        two and three with the reverse being true for non-government spokesmen.
                        Argentina and Uruguay were particularly insistent upon “high quality”
                        speakers, with English speakers being acceptable if spokesmen are up to the
                        standards of, say, Judge Winslow Christian.<note n="6" xml:id="d102fn6">Christian was a justice on the California Court of Appeals and the
                            first executive director of the National Center for State Courts.</note>
                        Programers should avoid the mid-December through February period in which
                        programing of any sort is difficult. In Paraguay, that should be extended
                        back to the end of November.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>