<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>110. Memorandum From the Deputy Director of the United States Information
                    Agency (Bray) to the Director of the Policy Planning Staff () to the Director of
                    the Policy Planning Staff (Lake))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d110</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">110</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Public diplomacy</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Media reaction</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="110"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d110">
                <head>110. Memorandum From the Deputy Director of the United States Information
                    Agency (<persName corresp="#p_BCW_1">Bray</persName>) to the Director of the
                    Policy Planning Staff (<persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d110fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, Office of the Director, Executive
                        Secretariat, Secretariat Staff, Correspondence Files, 1973–1980, Entry
                        P–104, Box 149, 7705070–7705079. No classification marking. Another copy of
                        the memorandum indicates that it was drafted by Alan Carter, edited by
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCW_1">Bray</persName>, and cleared in draft by
                            <persName corresp="#p_SHF_1">Schneidman</persName>. (Ibid.) According to
                            <persName corresp="#p_RBM_1">Read</persName>’s December 28 memorandum to
                            <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> (see <ref
                            target="#d118">Document 118</ref>)<gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>
                        and <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> subsequently agreed that <gloss
                            target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> would assign officers on
                        non-reimbursable detail to <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-11-29">November 29, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Relationship with <gloss
                            target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Hal <persName corresp="#p_SHF_1">Schneidman</persName> has shared with me your
                    informal memorandum on the “<gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Slot in
                        <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>.”</p>
                <p>It is at considerable variance from <hi rend="italic">our</hi> institutional
                    need, which I will now present.</p>
                <pb facs="0363" n="314" xml:id="pg_314"/>
                <p>Our recent internal reorganization provided us with an Office of Planning and
                    Program Direction. One of the <hi rend="italic">most</hi> important functions of
                    this office is to relate to the central elements of the U.S. foreign affairs
                        agencies—<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SP_1"
                        >S/P</gloss>, Treasury, etc. The relations would allow us to identify the
                    mid-and long-term policy issues that can and should be addressed by <gloss
                        target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>’s programs of public diplomacy. We have gone
                    to particular lengths to staff this office with some of our best people.</p>
                <p>Each of them will have the responsibility of working with—not in—appropriate
                    elements of the Department and other agencies so that major foreign policy
                    issues can be “converted” into communications policy governing the programs we
                    produce in Washington for the field, as well as those produced by our posts
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>Because this is a substantive function, none of these officers would be involved
                    in the preparation of memos, speeches or press guidances for the Department’s
                    units to which they relate (the thrust of your proposal). They will spend most
                    of their time within <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>. They
                    can—illustratively—assure that we initiate the kinds of research and media
                    reaction projects that are relevant to your and our concerns. They can determine
                    within <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> what public diplomacy programs
                    ought to be considered to support foreign policies, as those policies are
                    shaped.</p>
                <p>In the case of <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>, we proposed to assign
                    whichever of our officers you feel most comfortable with to <gloss
                        target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> for a period of two to four weeks in order to
                    establish the most basic knowledge of your office. Thereafter, that officer
                    would call upon <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> as necessary and would
                    participate in appropriate planning meetings and discussions with members of
                    your staff. However, he would spend the vast majority of his time within <gloss
                        target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>, as I indicated above.</p>
                <p>I hope we can move to implement this as soon as possible. The functioning of the
                    Office of Planning and Program Direction is vital to our mutual purposes.</p>
                <p>If you need additional help on speeches, press guidance, memos, etc., we may be
                    able to help with one or more officers on detail, but let’s consider that
                    separate issue separately.</p>
                <pb facs="0364" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared by the Director of the Policy Planning
                            Staff (<persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>)<note n="2"
                                xml:id="d110fn2">No classification marking.</note>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                                ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1977-11-19">undated</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Slot on <gloss target="#t_SP_1"
                                >S/P</gloss>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>This position would provide <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> with the
                        perspective of “public diplomacy” considerations, to be factored into the
                        policy planning process. At the same time, it would give <gloss
                            target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> an ongoing link to the thinking of the
                        policy planning staff, to help in <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>
                        advance planning.</p>
                    <p>Incumbent would be considered, and would be expected to act, as a full-time
                        member of <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>, working under the supervision
                        of the Director of the Staff on whatever projects seem appropriate to his
                        particular abilities. This could include participation in the preparation of
                        memos to the Secretary or other Department principals, speeches or press
                        guidance papers, or any of the various other analytical studies in which
                            <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> is involved.</p>
                    <p>He would also be expected to maintain close contact with the appropriate
                        offices at <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>, providing them with
                        feedback on policy trends and directions as required.</p>
                    <p>His main contribution to <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> papers would
                        presumably be in the field of public affairs aspects of policy issues, how
                        policies might be formulated to take better account of potential problems—or
                        opportunities—in foreign countries. Toward this end, he would be expected to
                        summon up whatever field reports or analysis is available to <gloss
                            target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> that would relate to specific studies
                        underway at <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>Depending on subject matter and Staff needs, the <gloss target="#t_USIA_1"
                            >USIA</gloss> incumbent would be expected to serve as co-drafter or
                        principal drafter of papers, as well as participate in planning meetings and
                        discussions with other members of the Staff.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
