<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="203" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d203">
                    <head>203. Address by the Director of the International Communication Agency
                            (<persName corresp="#p_RJE_1">Reinhardt</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d203fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Historical Collection, Office of the Director,
                            Biographic Files Relating to <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>
                            Directors and Other Senior Officials, 1953–2000, Entry A–1 1069, Box 25,
                                <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1">John E. Reinhardt</persName>, Speeches,
                            1980. No classification marking. <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1">Reinhardt</persName> spoke before a meeting of the National Council
                            for International Visitors. His address is entitled “The Future of
                            Public Diplomacy.”</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-02-07">February 7, 1980</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>It’s good to be among colleagues; the snatches of conversation and discussion
                        I’ve heard here today are familiar—and heartening—<pb facs="0646" n="597" xml:id="pg_597"/>to someone who’s been engaged in this work at home and
                        abroad for over twenty years. Your expertise and professionalism go without
                        saying; it’s your continued enthusiasm that gives me a real lift. I’m
                        grateful and impressed.</p>
                    <p>As you know, the convention at workshops like this is for the guest speaker
                        to congratulate the participants and tell them that their hard work does not
                        go unappreciated. I certainly don’t intend to break that convention. But I
                        must, at the outset, make a further statement: without your efforts, my
                        agency would simply fall down on the job. Our partnerships—the many
                        partnerships represented here at this workshop—are <hi rend="italic">essential</hi> to the U.S. International Communication Agency’s mission
                        and to its institutional life. That’s a plain fact. And it’s as sound a
                        foundation as I can think of for my brief remarks here today.</p>
                    <p>You’re all familiar with—and you share in carrying out—<gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss>’s mission, which in its simplest terms,
                        is to encourage the sharing of ideas and experience between the people of
                        the United States and the people of other nations, with the object of
                        increasing mutual understanding. Our charter—drawn up by the President and
                        sanctioned by the Congress—states explicitly that it is in the national
                        interest to do this.<note n="2" xml:id="d203fn2">See <ref target="#d93">Documents 93</ref> and <ref target="#d121">121</ref>.</note> Later
                        in the month I will ask the Congress to appropriate almost 460 million
                        dollars of the taxpayers’ money to carry out this charter.</p>
                    <p>Before <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss> was created, most of you worked
                        with the State Department on exchange-of-persons programs designed to
                        increase mutual understanding among peoples, and you had at least some
                        knowledge of the part played by U.S. Information Agency officers abroad in
                        administering these same programs. So I won’t go into any organizational
                        history except to make three points, which I believe are especially
                        important today:</p>
                    <p>First, the importance of exchange programs—genuine two-way communication
                        between Americans and people of other societies and cultures—was recognized
                        from the beginning as too great to be entrusted solely to Government
                        functionaries. Private-sector partnership remains a necessity to <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss>;</p>
                    <p>Second, the old <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> and the Department’s
                        Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs worked harmoniously and
                        effectively together for many years on exchange matters in spite of
                        enormous, and sometimes absurd, bureaucratic obstacles;</p>
                    <p>Third, for 30 years exchange programs existed together with other
                        educational, cultural and information activities, often through periods of
                        international stress, division and bloodshed, without external or internal
                        compromise to their integrity.</p>
                    <pb facs="0647" n="598" xml:id="pg_598"/>
                    <p>We’re looking at a very grim world today, but not an impossible one. I
                        believe that the present international convulsions and confrontations
                        underscore the need for these efforts at mutual understanding that we call
                        public diplomacy, and with which you and I are intimately concerned. I’ve
                        just come back this week from a trip to China and the Philippines. In Manila
                        I met with our Public Affairs Officers from 14 countries in the Far East.
                        Over the past critical weeks, these <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss>
                        officers have been engaged in explaining our country’s policies and
                        clarifying America’s intentions and reactions in regard to Iran and
                        Afghanistan, as completely and as thoughtfully as they could. At the same
                        time, scholars, professional people, community leaders from those countries
                        have been <hi rend="italic">here</hi>, seeing for themselves the public
                        mood, and the knowledge—or lack of it—of international issues reflected by
                        their American hosts. These visitors have been explaining their own points
                        of view and their judgments as interested members of other societies to whom
                        the present international crises may have other implications.</p>
                    <p>I might add that what is most important in each of these efforts at
                        communication is not just the assurance or warning of the moment, but the
                        achievement of as accurate an understanding as possible of the social and
                        cultural context in which the conversation takes place.</p>
                    <p>I have been thinking about my trip to the Far East, and about the tensions
                        emanating from Southwest Asia, in connection with my appearance before the
                        Senate Appropriations Committee on the 20th of this month.<note n="3" xml:id="d203fn3">See <hi rend="italic">Departments of State, Justice,
                                and Commerce, The Judiciary, and Related Agencies Appropriations for
                                Fiscal Year 1981 Hearings Before a Subcommittee of the Committee on
                                Appropriations United States Senate Ninety-Sixth Congress Second
                                Session Part 1—(Pages 1-788).</hi> (Washington D.C.: Government
                            Printing Office, 1980)</note> As Dr. <persName corresp="#p_JLB_1">Johnson</persName> said, “The prospect of being hanged concentrates the
                        mind wonderfully.”</p>
                    <p>What have our efforts at cross-cultural communication done for us in Iran or
                        Afghanistan? In other parts of the world, have our exchange-of-persons
                        programs, our radio broadcasts on the Voice of America, our speakers and
                        seminars on economic and social subjects, our exhibits of painting and
                        sculpture, tempered the international climate to any appreciable degree?</p>
                    <p>After 40 years of official international visitor programs, do we—in
                        government or politics or private institutions of influence—have a better
                        understanding of others’ aspirations or fears or perspectives on the
                        world—an understanding that moderates our national behavior or
                        comprehension?</p>
                    <p>The answers to these questions are immensely more important than the 460
                        million dollars they’re associated with this year. And they’re questions
                        which you, more than anybody, know must be <pb facs="0648" n="599" xml:id="pg_599"/> answered—at least to a certain extent—on faith. We in
                        America must believe in the possibility of rational discourse. We must
                        believe that mutual understanding between peoples can actually be arrived
                        at. The alternative is too terrible to contemplate.</p>
                    <p>But we can buttress our faith with intelligent and worthwhile programs, like
                        the ones you work with every day.</p>
                    <p>—Influential international visitors from Yemen, Morocco and Oman, programmed
                        by <gloss target="#t_VPS_1">VPS</gloss>, will take part in a seminar on
                        Islam and the Modern World this weekend, jointly sponsored by American
                        University and the Islamic Center. We can assume that they will make
                        significant contributions to American understanding, and in the process,
                        contribute to an actual lessening of political and social frictions among
                        international opinion-makers.</p>
                    <p>—Last summer, nine young film-makers from five Arab countries toured the
                        United States from coast to coast by van and station wagon, in a program
                        arranged with the Academy for Educational Development. What they learned
                        about the United States is bound to have an effect on their work and
                        attitudes well beyond the techniques of documentary film-making. An <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> officer accompanying them saw—as you so
                        often do with international visitors—a dramatic lessening of suspicion, an
                        increasing warmth of response, as these intensely political, culturally
                        defensive professional communicators saw that the trip <hi rend="italic">was</hi> open, that they were not being guided toward conclusions or
                        shielded from controversy.</p>
                    <p>—A glance at the arrival lists of international visitors shows economists,
                        labor leaders, orchestra conductors, parliamentarians, university lecturers,
                        business executives, playwrights, being given this same open
                        experience—unique, I believe, to America—through the good offices and sure
                        professional touch of <gloss target="#t_AAI_1">AAI</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_IIE_1">IIE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_VPS_1">VPS</gloss>, The
                        Labor Department, the Office of Education, Commerce, Defense, <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>, our own voluntary visitor office and
                        others represented in this room. And you know, despite the headaches and
                        frustrations, the occasional impossible personality, that the programs
                        work—they do achieve and increase mutual understanding.</p>
                    <p>If I have one policy point to make today, it is that our mutual endeavors to
                        create understanding through international visitor programs, exchanges of
                        scholars and artists, through discussions and seminars, through reasoned
                        explication and sensitive listening, are most effective and meaningful when
                        they are all actively engaged in multiple and continuous communication.</p>
                    <p>I have been worried about the tendency of people inside and outside <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss> to see it as having a split personality,
                        with one soft, rather slow-moving cultural side, and one brisk, somewhat
                        argumentative information side. It just isn’t so. These facets of
                        communication—some <pb facs="0649" n="600" xml:id="pg_600"/> more resonant
                        than others—are all parts of a whole. To characterize them as long-range or
                        short-range, one-way or two-way, as cultural or informational, is to
                        stereotype and diminish them. What characterizes communication is the use to
                        which it’s put, by both sender and receiver, not the means of communication
                        itself. You could, if you chose, manipulate an exchange visit as easily as
                        we could fashion a tendentious message for the Voice of America. None of us
                        can, even if we choose, communicate only one message at a time.</p>
                    <p>At times of international crisis, people tend to simplify issues, and to
                        split them into “either-or” alternatives, often along “hawk” and “dove”
                        lines. A quick look at the papers these days will bear this out; either we
                        take one of a series of actions in Iran or Afghanistan, or we take another
                        series of actions.</p>
                    <p>The “either-or” approach to international relations may have its value—in
                        clearing the ambiguities from proposed actions or in sharpening distinctions
                        between policy options, for example—but one institution at least would be
                        very badly served by “either-or” divisions, or ideological cleavages among
                        its components or partners. That, of course, is <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss>. This brings me to the policy point about public
                        diplomacy and its future that I want to leave with you. If we are going to
                        strengthen—truly strengthen—mutual understanding between peoples, and if we
                        are truly going to strengthen rationality in international dialogue, we must
                        use wisely all the means of communication at our disposal. Those of us who
                        work in educational and cultural exchanges should see the <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> news and commentary as in a sense
                        extensions of our own activities, with all the critical interest and concern
                        that that implies. And the press officer in a post abroad who enunciates
                        official U.S. policy, should understand that the <persName corresp="#p_FJM_2">Fulbright</persName> and international visitor
                        programs provide increasing numbers of his audiences with background and
                        experience of our culture which brings that policy into perspective. We must
                        not only recognize the connections among the various channels of
                        communication we use as practitioners of public diplomacy—official and
                        unofficial—we must be aware that their complexities enrich the process, at
                        the same time they defy manipulation.</p>
                    <p>Two years ago, when <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss> was being
                        organized and the international atmosphere was fairly calm, there were fears
                        among people concerned with the State Department’s educational and cultural
                        exchange programs that these activities might be politicized by any
                        institutional links with the government’s overseas information and cultural
                        programs. I think most now agree that these fears have not been realized.
                        Now, with <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss> established and the
                        international atmosphere at the boiling point, I hear from some that the
                        Agency’s information function—the clear enunciation and explanation to the
                        world of American policy and opinion—might be dissipated by <pb facs="0650" n="601" xml:id="pg_601"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss>’s emphasis on educational and
                        cultural-exchange matters. I think this, too, is an unnecessary fear.</p>
                    <p>“Either-or” just does not apply to our business. We are obligated to listen,
                        to contribute to what is known in the exchanges community as the “American
                        Learning Experience,” and we are bound, in our two-way communication, to
                        reflect the plurality of American culture. But as the official component of
                        this country’s public diplomacy, supported by tax dollars, we cannot cut
                        ourselves loose from policy. Nor, in its day, could the Bureau of
                        Educational and Cultural Affairs.</p>
                    <p>Public diplomacy, skillfully and responsibly practiced, is necessary and
                        beneficial to the conduct of our international affairs. It is a counter to
                        the surges of irrationality and rage in the world which are activated by
                        ignorance and misapprehension.</p>
                    <p>And the exchange programs are a primary ingredient of public diplomacy. In my
                        view, they have never been more vital than now. I say this not out of any
                        naive belief that exchanges are a panacea for the world’s problems; yet no
                        foreign policy can be wholly realistic or complete which does not try to
                        bring together, across frontiers, people who honestly want to learn from and
                        about one another.</p>
                    <p>Many of you have heard what purports to be an ancient Chinese curse: “May you
                        live in interesting times.” We are certainly so cursed, and so
                        privileged.</p>
                    <p>As a remarkable blend of personal convictions and professional goals, this
                        workshop represents an active partnership and a pledge for the future—in
                        interesting times. I am proud to be a part of it.</p>
                    <p>Thank you.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>