<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>37. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Director, Information Center
                    Service, United States Information Agency (Schneidman) to the Director () to the
                    Director (Reinhardt))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d37</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">37</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="37"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d37">
                <head>37. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Director, Information Center
                    Service, United States Information Agency (<persName corresp="#p_SHF_1"
                        >Schneidman</persName>) to the Director (<persName corresp="#p_RJE_1"
                        >Reinhardt</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d37fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, Office of the
                        Director, Executive Secretariat, Secretariat Staff, Correspondence Files,
                        1973–1980, Entry P–104, Box 117, 7701170–7701179. No classification marking.
                            <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1">Reinhardt</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_FJM_1">Fraser</persName> initialed the memorandum,
                        indicating that they had seen it. A stamped notation on the reverse of the
                        first page of the memorandum indicates that it was received in <gloss
                            target="#t_ISS_1">I/SS</gloss> at 9:27 p.m. on April 19.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-04-18">April 18, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Propaganda in the United States</item>
                </list>
                <p>The continuing question is, “should any part of the dialogue being conducted
                    abroad be made available to the American people?”</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">DISCUSSION:</p>
                <p>1. Materials, in whatever format, developed by personnel of the U.S. Information
                    Agency or its successor, or conceived and commissioned by the Agency, are not
                    and should <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be available within the United States now
                    or in the future.<note n="2" xml:id="d37fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1">Reinhardt</persName> placed a vertical line in
                        the left-hand margin next to this point and wrote: “The <persName
                            corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName> film?” Reference is presumably to
                            <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">John F. Kennedy</persName>: Years of
                            Lightning, Day of Drums</hi>, a 1964 film produced by the United States
                        Information Agency as a memorial to <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1"
                            >Kennedy</persName>. Although <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>
                        films could not be shown domestically, in 1966, a special act of Congress
                        allowed for the film to be shown in commercial theaters in the United
                        States. Documentation on the film and its U.S. screening is scheduled for
                        publication in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1917–1972, Public
                        Diplomacy, 1964–1968.</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. It may be cruel to say so, but the material referred to in (1) above is not
                    the most important part of the Agency’s efforts and in my view we would not be
                    terminally disadvantaged were we to be denied this source of materials.</p>
                <p>3. The fruits of American society which are identified, acquired, and
                    disseminated abroad by the Agency, after they have been conceived and produced
                    here, are routinely available to the American people.</p>
                <p>4. Why then can we not gain approval, both political and legal, for making
                    available to the American people, materials conceived and produced by foreign
                    individuals and institutions as part of this dialogue and where Agency personnel
                    and funding come in to play only after the fact of creation?<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d37fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1">Reinhardt</persName> placed a vertical line in
                        the left-hand margin next to this point and wrote “can’t we?”</note>
                </p>
                <p>5. A case in point is a collection of papers by U.S. and foreign Americanists
                    resulting from the Bicentennial series of regional confer<pb facs="0149" n="100"
                        xml:id="pg_100"/>ences on American Studies that we sponsored.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d37fn4">For documentation on <gloss target="#t_USIA_1"
                        >USIA</gloss>’s planning efforts for the American Revolution Bicentennial,
                        see <ref target="frus1969-76v38p2#d85">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. XXXVIII, Part
                            2, Organization and Management of Foreign Policy; Public Diplomacy,
                            1973–1976, Documents 85</ref> and <ref target="frus1969-76v38p2#d86"
                            >86</ref>. Documentation on the planning efforts is also scheduled for
                        publication in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1917–1972, Public
                        Diplomacy, 1969–1972.</note> If we now publish the collection for our
                    foreign audiences, this not insignificant body of work will be forever denied to
                    Americans.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
