<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>50. Report Prepared by the Comptroller General of the United States
                    (Staats))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v30</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Public diplomacy</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="receuSgBSWw1dxuqH" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Cultural affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms control and disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recb6XG1ZU9Ik84CR" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Broadcasting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="50"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d50">
                <head>50. Report Prepared by the Comptroller General of the United States (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SEB_1">Staats</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d50fn1">Source: Comptroller General of the United States, <hi
                            rend="italic">Public Diplomacy In The Years Ahead—An Assessment Of
                            Proposals For Reorganization.</hi> Washington, D.C.: Government Printing
                        Office, 1977.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-05-05">May 5, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">DIGEST</p>
                <p>United States “public diplomacy”—international information, education, and
                    cultural relations—is being extensively reexamined in and out of Government.
                    Various proposals call for redefining the mission of public diplomacy, changing
                    or eliminating functions, and reorganizing the administering apparatus.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">STANTON PANEL REPORT</p>
                <p>The most prominent and comprehensive report suggesting changes in organizational
                    arrangements to conduct U.S. public diplomacy is that of the Panel on
                    International Information, Education, and Cultural Relations (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SF_1">Stanton</persName> Panel), a group of private
                    citizens.</p>
                <p>The report, published in March 1975, was endorsed 3 months later by the
                    Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign
                    Policy (<persName corresp="#p_MJT_2">Murphy</persName> Commission).<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d50fn2">See <ref target="#d30fn6">footnote 6, Document
                        30</ref>.</note> A number of other qualified persons have strongly opposed
                    several of the proposals. The State Department and the United States Information
                    Agency are on record against all but one of them.</p>
                <p>The report is being reviewed by the executive branch and is slated for
                    consideration in the Congress.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_GAO_1">GAO</gloss>’s review is confined to the <persName
                        corresp="#p_SF_1">Stanton</persName> Panel recommendations. In the final
                    chapter, however, <gloss target="#t_GAO_1">GAO</gloss> notes certain
                    nonorganizational changes that merit attention in the ongoing effort to improve
                    U.S. public diplomacy. (See pp. 34 to 36.)</p>
                <p>One of the Panel’s proposals would improve present operations; two others seem
                    promising but require further study; and the remainder—which contemplate a major
                    reorganization—seem more likely to hinder than to advance the efficiency and
                    effectiveness of U.S. public diplomacy. The latter proposals would achieve a
                    certain tidiness on paper at the expense of arrangements that essentially have
                    met the test of practicality and performance.</p>
                <pb facs="0186" n="137" xml:id="pg_137"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="italic">Policy information function</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Panel proposes to reassign to the State Department the U.S. Information
                    Agency’s role in articulating and advocating U.S. foreign policy overseas. This
                    is based on the Panel’s distinction between “policy” information—which covers
                    the Government’s “stance on foreign policy questions of immediate concern”—and
                    “general” information.</p>
                <p>Like many other observers, <gloss target="#t_GAO_1">GAO</gloss> believes the two
                    kinds of information are often mutually reinforcing and difficult in practice to
                    separate. The primary responsibility for articulating and advocating as well as
                    formulating U.S. foreign policy is vested in the President and the Secretary of
                    State. A role of the U.S. Information Agency is to give resonance abroad to
                    authoritative definitions and interpretations of that policy under State
                    Department guidance. For the most part this work appears to be done
                    professionally and to the State Department’s general satisfaction. <gloss
                        target="#t_GAO_1">GAO</gloss> believes the U.S. Information Agency should
                    retain its policy information role. (See pp. 9 to 13, 15, and 16.)</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="italic">Policy advisory function</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Panel also proposes to transfer to the State Department the U.S. Information
                    Agency’s function of advising U.S. policymakers on the policy implications of
                    foreign public opinion. This function is in fact performed by several Federal
                    agencies. The U.S. Information Agency’s cultural and media contacts abroad
                    enable it to make a distinctive advisory contribution.</p>
                <p>There have been complaints, echoed by the Panel, that this contribution has not
                    been properly utilized. How adequately it is utilized, how much it differs from
                    that of other agencies, and whether the “neglect” of U.S. Information Agency
                    policy advice can be corrected by means other than transferring the advisory
                    function are among the unanswered questions raised by this proposal. Pending
                    further study of such questions, the present arrangement should be left intact.
                    (See pp. 9, 10, 13, 14, and 16.)</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="italic">Establishment of new Information and Cultural Affairs
                        Agency</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Panel proposes to consolidate the cultural functions of the State
                    Department’s Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs and those of the U.S.
                    Information Agency. A single agency would be responsible for both the domestic
                    and overseas aspects of U.S. general information, educational, and cultural
                    programs. <gloss target="#t_GAO_1">GAO</gloss> believes, as do most persons
                    consulted, that this proposal is constructive. It would lead to more efficient
                    and consistent administration of U.S. cultural programs. (See pp. 17 to 24.)</p>
                <pb facs="0187" n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="italic">Relationship of new Information and Cultural Affairs Agency to
                        Department of State</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Panel proposes that the new information agency be placed “under—but not
                    in—the Department” as an “autonomous” agency on the model of the Arms Control
                    and Disarmament Agency.</p>
                <p>Both independent status for the information agency and the Panel’s alternative
                    have distinct advantages and shortcomings. Either could work well. The choice
                    should be based on a careful study of the pros and cons.</p>
                <p>If the agency were assigned to State, however, some safeguards and some vigilance
                    would be advisable to protect the agency’s professional integrity and its
                    ability to cover objectively not only the State Department but other agencies
                    and branches of Government as well as the private sector. (See pp. 19 to
                    24.)</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="italic">Field reorganization</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Panel proposes to reorganize U.S. overseas missions so that articulating
                    “policy” information would be the exclusive responsibility of State Department
                    officers while “general” information and cultural programs would be the province
                    of Information and Cultural Affairs Agency officers. This would fragment what
                    the Panel itself describes as “the unified organization which has worked so
                    effectively in the field for over twenty years.” The present trend toward closer
                    integration of those activities in the overseas missions should be encouraged.
                    (See pp. 25 to 27.)</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="italic">Voice of America</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Panel proposes to make the Voice of America an independent agency under its
                    own board, asserting that this “would enable the Voice of America to function as
                    a credible medium.”</p>
                <p>The Panel offers no evidence that present Voice of America broadcasts lack
                    credibility, credence, or listenership. Audience research by the U.S.
                    Information Agency and others in recent years suggests otherwise. Similarly, the
                    Panel implies without attempting to demonstrate that Voice of America does not
                    satisfy the needs of the Department of State. The evidence again points in the
                    other direction. Implementing this proposal would add considerably to costs of
                    operation.</p>
                <p>How U.S. foreign policy is reported and advocated, especially by fast media and
                    especially in moments of international crisis, can greatly affect the national
                    interest for good or ill. For an agency billed and perceived as “the” Voice of
                    America, there can be circumstances in which diplomatic needs ought to prevail
                    over journalistic concerns.</p>
                <p>It should be emphasized, however, that circumstances justifying State Department
                    or White House intervention in Voice of America <pb facs="0188" n="139"
                        xml:id="pg_139"/> broadcasting are highly unusual, and the prerogative
                    should be exercised with restraint and in full awareness of the need to protect
                    Voice of America’s professional integrity.</p>
                <p>The present structural relationship between the Voice of America, the U.S.
                    Information Agency, and the Department of State should be preserved, but efforts
                    should be made to improve the working relationships. (See pp. 28 to 33.)</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">AGENCY COMMENTS</p>
                <p>This report was submitted in draft to the interested agencies and advisory
                    commissions, as well as the Chairman of the <persName corresp="#p_SF_1"
                        >Stanton</persName> Panel, for their informal comments. All agreed that the
                    cultural functions of the U.S. Information Agency and the Bureau of Educational
                    and Cultural Affairs should be consolidated. <gloss target="#t_GAO_1"
                        >GAO</gloss>’s conclusions concerning the other Panel proposals have
                    elicited emphatic agreement and equally emphatic disagreement. All comments were
                    carefully considered.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here are Chapter 1: Introduction; Chapter 2: Transfer of <gloss
                        target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>’s Policy Articulation and Advisory Functions
                    to State Department; Chapter 3: Establishment of New Information and Cultural
                    Affairs Agency; Chapter 4: Field Reorganization; Chapter 5: Voice of America;
                    Chapter 6: A New Charter for U.S. Public Diplomacy; and Appendix I: Principal
                    Officers Concerned With the Subject of This Report.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
