<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-06-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-06-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                    <head>72. Testimony of the Deputy Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>) Before the Subcommittee on
                        International Operations of the House International Relations Committee<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d72fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Historical Collection, Subject Files, 1953–2000, Entry
                            A–1 1066, Box 43, <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss>,
                            Reorganization, 1974–1978. No classification marking. <persName corresp="#p_DJD_1">Duffey</persName> sent a copy of the testimony to
                                <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss> office and staff directors under
                            a June 21 memorandum. (Ibid.) For the full text of the Subcommittee’s
                            hearings, see <hi rend="italic">Public Diplomacy and the Future:
                                Hearings Before the Subcommittee on International Operations of the
                                Committee on International Relations, House of Representatives,
                                Ninety-Fifth Congress, First Session, June 8, 13, 14, 15, 16, 21,
                                22, 23, and 24,</hi> U.S. House Committee on International
                            Relations, Subcommittee on International Operations (Washington, D.C.:
                            Government Printing Office, 1977)</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-06-21">June 21, 1977</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. Chairman, Members of the Committee:</p>
                    <p>I welcome this opportunity to testify in the course of your hearings on
                        “Public Diplomacy and the future.” The Secretary and I are encouraged by the
                        careful attention you are giving to the inquiry, and by your interest in the
                        larger issues of international communications. I would like to pledge our
                        cooperation in working with the Congress in the review of policy in this
                        area.</p>
                    <p>Let me begin by putting public diplomacy into the context of its purpose and
                        place in the foreign policy structure of the United States.</p>
                    <p>The purposes of public diplomacy are</p>
                    <p>(1) To ensure that other nations more accurately understand this country, its
                        values, institutions, and policies;</p>
                    <p>(2) To ensure that our understanding of other nations and of our
                        interrelationship with them is informed and accurate;</p>
                    <p>(3) To ensure that this mutual understanding is bolstered by collaborative
                        individual and institutional relationships across cultural lines; and</p>
                    <p>(4) To ensure that, as the international policies of our government are
                        formed, we take into account the values, interests, and priorities of
                        publics abroad.</p>
                    <p>The audience for public diplomacy defines its vital place in the conduct of
                        American foreign policy. Public diplomacy compliments and reinforces
                        traditional government-to-government diplomacy by seeking to communicate
                        with the people of other nations. In particular, it seeks to establish a
                        dialogue with those who are importantly involved now or are likely to be
                        involved in the formulation and discussion of attitudes and ideas which
                        affect the United States. I speak here of people in other nations who are
                        active in the academic world, the <pb facs="0262" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/>
                        worlds of art and culture, in communications, or in government—those who are
                        future leaders of their nations.</p>
                    <p>As you have emphasized, Mr. Chairman, the issues of public diplomacy are far
                        broader than internal government organization. They also concern the wider
                        span of international communications in this age of information. This wider
                        span embraces such issues as satellite television transmissions, <gloss target="#t_COMSAT_1">COMSAT</gloss> receiver stations in underdeveloped
                        countries and the free dissemination of news. As you know, we are preparing
                        for international conferences which will consider some of these
                        problems.</p>
                    <p>We must address these individual issues within the context of a comprehensive
                        view by the United States. This comprehensive view is defined by three
                        governing principles:</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">First</hi>, we are committed to freedom of information and
                        expression and the fundamental human right of every individual to seek,
                        receive and impart information and ideas through any medium, and regardless
                        of frontiers;</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Second</hi>, we recognize the vital importance of
                        communications in the development of peoples and nations and of friendly
                        relations between them. All people should have a chance to share in the
                        potential benefits of modern mass communications. Thus, we are determined to
                        help develop and increase the means of communication among peoples. At the
                        same time, we are determined to preserve the multiplicity and independence
                        of sources of information;</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Third</hi>, the international flow of information and
                        ideas must be two-way. There is a current imbalance—for example, much more
                        information flows to the so-called Third World than flows <hi rend="italic">from</hi> the Third World. One example of our willingness to help
                        correct some of the imbalance is our long-standing offer to share our
                        knowledge and expertise in the use of our <gloss target="#t_ATS6_1">ATS–6</gloss> communications satellite.</p>
                    <p>The specific and concrete steps we take on the whole spectrum of
                        international communications will be consistent with these principles.</p>
                    <p>We reviewed public diplomacy from the perspective of its purposes as well as
                        the principles outlined above. In this connection we have identified five
                        specific functions of public diplomacy:</p>
                    <p>—“Cultural exchange,” which includes the exchange of people in both
                        directions and the forging of institutional links. The <persName corresp="#p_FJM_2">Fulbright</persName> program, which sends scholars
                        abroad and brings foreign scholars here to pursue their studies, is a major
                        example of this function. It is managed by the State Department at home and
                        by <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> overseas.</p>
                    <p>—“General information” consists of activities undertaken to project abroad
                        important aspects of American society. These activities include exhibits,
                        libraries, seminars, lectures and much of <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>’s programming. Most of these activities are managed abroad
                        by <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>. Programs such <pb facs="0263" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/> as tours of performing artists are managed at
                        home by the State Department and overseas by <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>—“Policy information” is a combination of background and policy guidance on
                        current and long-term issues for use in explaining our policies abroad. This
                        information is obtained from State Department sources and statements and is
                        disseminated by <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> to our posts overseas
                        and to <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> draws upon this information for the policy commentary and
                        analyses that it broadcasts. The subjects cover such issues as human rights,
                            <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> and the Middle East. I will note
                        in passing that I have differentiated between “general information” and
                        “policy information” because others have done so, but I regard the dichotomy
                        as somewhat artificial.</p>
                    <p>—“Public affairs advice” represents an attempt to assess and evaluate foreign
                        public opinion and attitudes and thus to inform the U.S. agencies involved
                        in foreign policy. For example, <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> was
                        able to provide a survey on European attitudes toward the issue of human
                        rights prior to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s
                        trip to Europe.<note n="2" xml:id="d72fn2">See <ref target="#d48">Document
                                48</ref>. The President departed Washington on May 5 in order to
                            attend the <gloss target="#t_G7_1">G–7</gloss> Economic Summit in London
                            May 7–8. He then attended a four-nation May 9 meeting on Berlin before
                            departing for Geneva to meet with Syrian President Asad. He then
                            returned to London for the May 10 North Atlantic Council meeting. The
                            President’s remarks in Washington and London, the transcript of a news
                            conference following the summit, and texts of the joint declaration of
                            the international summit meeting, the declaration on Berlin, and the
                                <gloss target="#t_NAC_1">NAC</gloss> communiqué are printed in
                            Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, June 6, 1977, pp.
                            581–607.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>—“News reporting” is performed principally by <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>. Factual and unbiased reporting of all the news is the key
                        to the integrity and credibility of the Voice. We must remain alert to
                        ensure that the news function reflects the highest standards of American
                        journalism.</p>
                    <p>It is through these five functions of public diplomacy that we are able, as a
                        nation, to seek respect for our opinions and to pay respect to the opinions
                        of others. We recognize that, in a world of information, it is no longer
                        sufficient to reach only existing power structures of other nations. Their
                        own policies are affected by the knowledge and attitudes of their citizens.
                        It is especially important to recognize that younger generations in other
                        countries will soon occupy positions of influence not only in government,
                        but in the media, the academic community, the cultural world and other
                        important segments of a society.</p>
                    <p>We are conducting a comprehensive review of our organization for public
                        diplomacy. In this review, we have taken into account other studies,
                        including, Mr. Chairman, your 1968 report on “The Future of <pb facs="0264" n="215" xml:id="pg_215"/> United States Diplomacy.”<note n="3" xml:id="d72fn3">On July 22, 1968, the House Foreign Affairs Subcommittee
                            on International Organizations and Movements convened a hearing on “The
                            Future of United States Public Diplomacy.” <persName corresp="#p_BEL_1">Bernays</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GGH_1">Gallup</persName>,
                            Free, <persName corresp="#p_GEA_1">Guillion</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SFX_1">Sutton</persName>, Smith, <persName corresp="#p_MLH_1">Marks</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SF_1">Stanton</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BEW_1">Barrett</persName> all testified before the Subcommittee.
                            (“Activities in Congress,” <hi rend="italic">The Washington Post,</hi>
                            July 22, 1968, p. B3) For the report, see <hi rend="italic">The Future
                                of United States Public Diplomacy: Report No. 6 together with Part
                                XI of the Hearings on Winning the Cold War: the U.S. Ideological
                                Offensive,</hi> U.S. House Committee on Foreign Affairs,
                            Subcommittee on International Organizations and Movements (Washington,
                            D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1968).</note> Through this process, we
                        identified important shortcomings in the present organizations.</p>
                    <p>We have found that the components of public diplomacy have been fragmented.
                        The responsibility for cultural exchanges and some of the general
                        information activities are split between <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> overseas and the State Department at home.</p>
                    <p>We have also concluded that our international relations in the years ahead
                        require more serious attention to public diplomacy than has been given in
                        the past. Public diplomacy has been too distant from the processes by which
                        our foreign policy is conducted—both for the contribution it should make
                        when policies are decided and the support it can provide when those policies
                        are in operation.</p>
                    <p>Specifically, the dissemination of accurate, ample, and timely policy
                        guidance to our missions overseas and to <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> has been hampered by the lack of full communication between
                        the State Department and <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>, despite the
                        good intentions of all concerned. Similarly, the use of public affairs
                        advice has been impaired by the lack of a close relationship between those
                        who prepare this analysis and those who rely on it in the State
                        Department.</p>
                    <p>Our review of the issues and questions involved has caused us to conclude
                        that reorganization is required. The form of the reorganization has been
                        under intensive study, but no final decision has been made by the President.
                        The Administration is following your hearings with interest and care, as we
                        proceed to shape our final recommendations and decisions.</p>
                    <p>Of course, Mr. Chairman, organizations are only as good as the people who
                        staff and run them. In this respect we are indeed fortunate. At <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>, Director <persName corresp="#p_RJE_1">John Reinhardt</persName> and Deputy Director <persName corresp="#p_BCW_1">Charles Bray</persName> are already providing the
                        kind of leadership that bodes well for public diplomacy. At State, Assistant
                        Secretary Joseph Duffy’s deep commitment to educational and cultural
                        exchange is already making itself felt. Equally important, <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>,
                        and <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss> are staffed by competent
                        professionals. The fact that present organizational arrangements work as
                        well as they do is a tribute to their skill and dedication.</p>
                    <pb facs="0265" n="216" xml:id="pg_216"/>
                    <p>In undertaking a reorganization of our public diplomacy program in the
                        contemporary world, we will test all present activities for their relevance
                        to current and future needs, and their effectiveness. We will identify new
                        activities that need to be undertaken and establish principles for the
                        management of these activities, to assure their efficiency and effectiveness
                        in furthering our long-term national interest.</p>
                    <p>This is an important opportunity for the Congress, the Administration, and
                        the American people. Therefore, I will be pleased to answer your questions,
                        but I also wish to hear your advice and comments.<note n="4" xml:id="d72fn4">In his June 21 Evening Report to the President, <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> highlighted that day’s
                            Subcommittee hearings: “The session was harmonious. <persName corresp="#p_FDB_1">Fascell</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BJH_1">John Buchanan</persName> stressed that the
                            Administration should act as quickly as possible on the reorganization
                            question. <persName corresp="#p_FDB_1">Fascell</persName> expressed
                            disagreement with the idea that exchange programs would be tainted by
                            closer association with <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>;
                            supported involving the <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Director
                            more closely in the foreign policy-making process; and plugged for more
                            money for <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> modernization and
                            cultural presentations abroad.” In the left-hand margin next to this
                            paragraph, the President noted: “We should expedite.” (Carter Library,
                            Plains File, Subject File, Box 37, State Department Evening Reports,
                            6/77)</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>