<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-08-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="84" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                    <head>84. Memorandum for the President<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d84fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306,
                                <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Historical Collection,
                            Subject Files, 1953–2000, Entry A–1 1066, Box 43, <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss>, Reorganization, 1974–1978. No
                            classification marking. <persName corresp="#p_FDB_1">Fascell</persName>
                            sent the letter to the President under an August 3 letter, indicating
                            that the House Subcommittee on International Operations had completed
                            its hearings on <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> reorganization.
                            In addition to <persName corresp="#p_FDB_1">Fascell</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_BJH_1">Buchanan</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RLJ_1">Ryan</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BJH_2">Burke</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_DCC_1">Diggs</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_MHS_1">Meyner</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Wolff</persName> signed the letter. (Ibid.) Both
                            letters are scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1977-80v27">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XXVII,
                                Organization and Management of Foreign Policy</ref>. The copy of the
                            memorandum printed here is part of a larger collection of documents
                            collated by <persName corresp="#p_MDN_1">Dwight Mason</persName> (<gloss target="#t_MMO_1">M/MO</gloss>) and attached to a November 11
                            memorandum entitled “Background Material on the Reorganization of <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 306, <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Historical
                            Collection, Subject Files, 1953–2000, Entry A–1 1066, Box 43, <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">USICA</gloss>, Reorganization, 1974–1978)</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-08-03">August 3, 1977</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>From June 8 to June 24, 1977 the Subcommittee on International Operations of
                        the House International Relations Committee heard testimony from 45
                        witnesses on issues related to reorganization of public diplomacy
                            programs.<note n="2" xml:id="d84fn2">See <ref target="#d72fn1">footnote
                                1, Document 72</ref>.</note> A list of witnesses is attached.<note n="3" xml:id="d84fn3">Not found attached.</note> In addition, the
                        Subcommittee received more than a score of additional unsolicited statements
                        for inclusion in the hearing record.</p>
                    <p>Based on the hearing record, the Subcommittee has reached the following
                        general conclusions.</p>
                    <p>1. The key to effective use of our public diplomacy resources is an awareness
                        of the utility of these resources and a willingness to use them to further
                        policy objectives. Reorganization is important, but only of marginal concern
                        in dealing with this basic problem.</p>
                    <p>2. The head of the <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> (or successor
                        agency) should be included in <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> and
                        Cabinet meetings. Participation by the <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Director will (a) substantially increase opportunities for
                        maximum effective use of public diplomacy resources, and (b) allow the
                        Agency to perform its responsibilities for explaining policy for the entire
                        government.</p>
                    <p>3. <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> should not be merged into the
                        Department of State. <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> must work
                        closely with the Department of State. It is important that <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> or a successor bureau or agency have
                        sufficient budgetary, personnel and administrative autonomy to ensure a
                        corps of officers qualified and inspired to carry out the full range of
                        public diplomacy in our national interests. The Director of <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> or his successor should be included in
                        all major policy decisions within the Department of State. Similarly, lower
                        level officials concerned with public diplomacy <pb facs="0287" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/> should be involved in all major policy formulation
                        sessions at all appropriate lower and intermediate levels.<note n="4" xml:id="d84fn4">An unknown hand placed two parallel lines in the
                            left-hand margin next to the last two sentences in this
                            paragraph.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>4. The programs administered by the Bureau of Educational and Cultural
                        Affairs should be merged into the <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>5. The <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> should remain in the <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>6. The present authority and organization of the Board for Foreign
                        Scholarships should be maintained.</p>
                    <p>7. The integrity of both our educational and cultural programs and of the
                        programming of the Voice of America is of paramount concern.</p>
                    <p>Inevitably conflicts will arise over both programs in an attempt to resolve
                        both (a) competitive short-term and long-term objectives, and (b) the
                        distinctions between government policy and divergent opinions in the country
                        as a whole.<note n="5" xml:id="d84fn5">An unknown hand placed two parallel
                            lines and an arrow in the left-hand margin next to this
                            paragraph.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>No structural reorganization including the establishment of separate agencies
                        for exchange activities or broadcasting will provide immunity from political
                        pressures. Changes can be made, however, which will minimize the abuse of
                        exchange programs or broadcasting activities.</p>
                    <p>8. The United States Advisory Commission on Information and the United States
                        Advisory Commission on International Educational and Cultural Affairs can be
                        restructured to more effectively safeguard the integrity of both exchange
                        programs and of Voice of America programming. The following measures can
                        ensure and safeguard the integrity and credibility vital to the success of
                        our long-term public diplomacy programs: (a) higher caliber membership, (b)
                        mandatory periodic reports, (c) independent staff to investigate alleged
                        improper actions,<note n="6" xml:id="d84fn6">An unknown hand underlined this
                            point.</note> (d) requirements for officials to notify the advisory
                        group of pressures which would contravene the mandate of the programs, and
                        (e) obligation of the Director to respond to the Administration and the
                        Congress on advisory commission reports and staff investigation
                        findings.</p>
                    <p>9. The <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> needs a fundamental internal
                        reorganization. There are far too many officials at the assistant director
                            level.<note n="7" xml:id="d84fn7">An unknown hand placed two parallel
                            lines in the left-hand margin next to this sentence.</note> It is
                        important, however, that if either or both the Bureau of Educational and
                        Cultural Affairs or the Voice of America are within a reorganized <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> that <pb facs="0288" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/> the Directors of these programs be at the highest
                        level beneath the Agency Director and that their independent access to
                        Congress be assured.<note n="8" xml:id="d84fn8">An unknown hand underlined
                            the portion of this sentence beginning with the word
                            “independent.”</note> This would further ensure the integrity and
                        credibility of these two programs.</p>
                    <p>10. Regardless of the future relationship of <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss> to the Department
                        of State, clear responsibility should be assigned to a high official of the
                        Department of State for (a) all issues relating to the freedom of
                        communication, (b) technical matters which may impinge on freedom of
                        communication, and (c) coordination of public diplomacy activities of
                        Defense, Treasury, Commerce, <gloss target="#t_HEW_1">HEW</gloss> and other
                            agencies.<note n="9" xml:id="d84fn9">An unknown hand placed two parallel
                            lines in the left-hand margin next to this paragraph.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>11. The mandate governing <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> operations
                        which was issued by President <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName><note n="10" xml:id="d84fn10">Reference is presumably
                            to a January 25, 1963, memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_KJF_1">Kennedy</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_MER_1">Murrow</persName>, printed in <ref target="frus1961-63v25#d144">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1961–1963, vol. XXV,
                                Organization of Foreign Policy; Information Policy; United Nations;
                                Scientific Matters, Document 144</ref>. In it, the President stated:
                            “The influencing of attitudes is to be carried out by overt use of the
                            various techniques of communication—personal contact, radio
                            broadcasting, libraries, book publication and distribution, press,
                            motion pictures, television, exhibits, English-language instruction, and
                            others.”</note> should be reviewed and updated.</p>
                    <p>12. While it is important to resolve the long debate about possible merger of
                            <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>, it should be recognized that a further reorganization may
                        be advisable once the President and Congress have more completely reviewed
                        the entire structure of the Federal Government and especially its foreign
                        policy agencies.<note n="11" xml:id="d84fn11">In a September 14 letter to
                                <persName corresp="#p_FDB_1">Fascell</persName>, the President
                            thanked him and his colleagues for their letter and memorandum, terming
                            them “very useful” in assisting him in his decisions on reorganization.
                            The President added, “I share your conviction that our information and
                            cultural exchange efforts are one of the most important aspects of our
                            foreign policy effort. I want to ensure that we have imaginative
                            programs in this area which are energetically managed and led. For the
                            money we spend, these are among the least costly operations of the
                            government; nevertheless, the effect can continue for years after the
                            money has been spent. When I ask for additional money for these fields,
                            I want the Congress to be able to feel confident that we are making the
                            best use of it we can. The reorganization we are now undertaking will
                            put us in a better position to do that.” (Carter Library, White House
                            Central Files, Subject File, Foreign Affairs, Information-Exchange
                            Activities, Executive, Box FO–35, FO–5 1/20/77–9/30/77)</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>