<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-07-01T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-07-01T03:00:00-05:00" n="104" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d104">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">124.57/40: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Germany</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Heath</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-07-01T10:00:00+02:00">July 1,
                                    1940—10 a.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 12:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2223. My 2221, June 30, 6 p.m.<note n="34" xml:id="d104fn34">Not
                                printed.</note> The following note was received this morning from
                            the Foreign Office. <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Foreign Office has the honor to inform the Embassy of the
                                    United States of America of the following:</p>
                                <p>“After the occupation by German troops of the entire territory of
                                    Norway, the Netherlands, Belgium and Luxembourg the authority of
                                    law (<hi rend="italic">Gesetz Maessige Gewalt</hi>) in those
                                    countries came into German hands. Moreover, the former
                                    Governments of those countries fled abroad so that they no
                                    longer exercise the legal functions of government. Under these
                                    circumstances the basis is removed for the activities of the
                                    diplomatic missions which were accredited to the former
                                    governments of those countries. If the Government of the United
                                    States of America wishes to discuss matters of a political
                                    nature affecting these countries this would have to be done by
                                    its diplomatic mission in Berlin at the Foreign Office.</p>
                                <p>“The Foreign Office accordingly requests the Embassy of the
                                    United States of America to be so good as to cause its
                                    Government to withdraw its diplomatic missions from Oslo, the
                                    Hague, Brussels and Luxembourg and to complete this not later
                                    than July 15, 1940. Until further notice the Reich Government
                                    consents to the continuation of the consular offices in the
                                    countries and territories indicated and further exercise <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> of the functions there.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>