<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Luxemburg Chargé ( (Le Gallais) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-09-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-09-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="173"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">850A.01/46</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Luxemburg Chargé</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Le Gallais</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-04">September 4,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: On instructions from the
                    Government of Her Royal Highness the Grand Duchess, I have the honor to make the
                    following known to Your Excellency:</p>
                <p>“Despite its word given at the beginning of the war to respect the integrity and
                    the neutrality of the Grand Duchy of Luxemburg, the Reich caused Luxemburg
                    territory to be invaded and occupied during the night of May 9–10 of this year.
                    To remove their activity from the pressure of the invader, Her Royal Highness
                    the Grand Duchess and her Government went to another country, in order there to
                    protest <pb facs="0227" n="215" xml:id="pg_215"/> against this act of force and
                    in order there freely to defend the interests of their country before other
                    nations.</p>
                <p>“To assure the civil administration of the country during the foreign military
                    occupation, the Government, before its departure, did not fail to give the
                    necessary instructions to the administrative authorities of Luxemburg who
                    remained at their posts. This in conformity with the principles of international
                    law.</p>
                <p>“Now, the acts of interference of the German authorities in the administration of
                    the Grand Duchy and the measures decreed by them since May 10 were not long in
                    revealing the true intentions of the Reich with respect to Luxemburg. In fact, a
                    few days after the invasion, the country was declared an enemy country and after
                    a brief transition period the military administration was replaced by a German
                    civil administration under the orders of a <hi rend="italic">Gauleiter</hi>. The
                    latter made his entrance into the city of Luxemburg at the head of German police
                    troops. In a speech which he made on that occasion, he proclaimed the German
                    character of the Luxemburg population. Successively, he has suppressed the use
                    of the French language, which has for centuries been the official language of
                    the country, required the exclusive use of the German language, declared the
                    Constitution abolished, relieved officials of their oath of fidelity to Her
                    Royal Highness the Grand Duchess and forbidden the use of the expressions ‘Grand
                    Duchy and Country of Luxemburg.’</p>
                <p>“Against the arbitrariness of these measures taken in violation of international
                    law, of treaties and of promises given by Germany, Her Royal Highness the Grand
                    Duchess and Her Government <hi rend="italic">formally</hi> protest. They will
                    never recognize their validity.</p>
                <p>“Neither in the past nor in the present has the attitude of the Sovereign nor the
                    attitude of Her Ministers and the attitude of the population furnished the
                    slightest pretext to the injustice which the Reich is in the act of committing
                    with respect to a small country, the most peaceful of all.</p>
                <p>“Although the authorities of the Reich have done everything since May 10 to
                    prevent Her Royal Highness the Grand Duchess and the Grand Ducal Government from
                    entering into contact with the Luxemburg population, Her Royal Highness the
                    Grand Duchess and the Government know that in making this protest, they are
                    acting in full accord with the Luxemburg people who, if they were free to
                    express their sentiments, would not fail to affirm their will to remain free and
                    independent, as scarcely a year ago, they had occasion to do in celebrating with
                    unanimous enthusiasm the Centennial of the Independence of the Grand Duchy.”</p>
                <p>I beg you to accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugues Le Gallais</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
