<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-06-14T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-06-14T18:00:00-05:00" n="220" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d220">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1938/3728<hi rend="superscript">5/6</hi>: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom (<persName type="from">Kennedy</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-06-15T00:00:00+01:00">June 15,
                                    1940—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received June 15—7 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1678. Personal for the President.</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“10:45 p.m., 15th June, 1940. President of the United States from
                                Former Naval Person.</p>
                            <p>Since sending you my message this afternoon<note n="6" xml:id="d220fn6">Presumably telegram No. 1677, June 15, 1940, 9
                                    p.m., <ref target="frus1940v03#pg_53">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 53</ref>.</note> I have heard that
                                Monsieur Reynaud, in a telegram which he has just sent to you, has
                                practically said that the decision of France to continue the war
                                from overseas depends on your being able to assure the French
                                Government that the United States of America will come into the war
                                at a very early date.</p>
                            <p>When I sent you my message just now I did not know that Monsieur
                                Reynaud had stated the dilemma in these terms, but I am afraid there
                                is no getting away from the fact that this is the choice before us
                                now.</p>
                            <p>Indeed, the British Ambassador in Bordeaux tells me that if your
                                reply does not contain the assurance asked for, the French will very
                                quickly ask for an armistice, and I much doubt whether it will be
                                possible in that event for us to keep the French fleet out of German
                                hands.</p>
                            <p>When I speak of the United States entering the war I am, of course,
                                not thinking in terms of an expeditionary force, which I know is out
                                of the question. What I have in mind is the tremendous moral effect
                                that such an American decision would produce not merely in France
                                but also in all the democratic countries of the world and in the
                                opposite sense of the German and Italian peoples.”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Kennedy</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>