<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-07-19T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-07-19T08:00:00-05:00" n="403" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860P.00/298: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Latvia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wiley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Riga</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-07-19T15:00:00+02:00">July 19,
                                    1940—3 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 3:29 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>207. Yesterday the population was turned out <hi rend="italic">en
                                masse</hi> to celebrate the “victory” of the Toilers.<note n="85" xml:id="d403fn85">Name of the political bloc which had put up the
                                unopposed list of candidates in the election.</note> The proceedings
                            were most orderly and well-organized with strategically placed groups of
                            cheer leaders. The majority of the placards carried slogans demanding
                            the incorporation of Latvia as the fourteenth Republic of the Union.
                            Following a speech by the Prime Minister attacking the previous regime
                            and praising that of the Soviets, a Communist speaker harangued the
                            crowd, proclaiming the “unanimous demand of the Latvian workers,
                            peasants, and intellectual toilers to incorporate Latvia into the great
                            Fatherland”. Vyshinski<note n="86" xml:id="d403fn86">Andrey Yanuaryevich
                                Vyshinsky, in Latvia on special mission.</note> also spoke calling
                            on Latvians to turn their faces eastward.</p>
                        <p>The new Parliament is to meet at noon on Sunday. I have been officially
                            invited to attend but shall be indisposed.</p>
                        <p>A Communist source believed reliable states that the new emphasis on <hi rend="italic">Anschluss</hi> with the Soviet Union is the result of
                            orders based on a decision reached in Moscow 2 days ago. Previously,
                            local Communists did not believe that <hi rend="italic">Anschluss</hi>
                            would take place. They attribute this new development to an
                            “international agreement”, meaning, I suppose, Germany.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wiley</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>