<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Turkey ( (MacMurray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d496</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">496</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-06-14T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-06-14T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-06-14T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-06-14T09:00:00-05:00" n="496"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d496">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/3810: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-06-14T16:00:00+02:00"
                            >June 14, 1940—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received June 15—7:05 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>86. For the Secretary and Under Secretary. Amplifying my next previous
                        telegram.<note n="32" xml:id="d496fn32">Telegram No. 85, June 14, 1 p.m.;
                        not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>It appears that although the British and French Ambassadors had been led
                        to expect that the Turkish Government would promptly give its undertaking to
                        adopt the measures (short of a declaration of war) indicated in my telegram
                        of 2 days ago<note n="33" xml:id="d496fn33">Telegram No. 77, June 12, 1
                            p.m.; not printed.</note> they were informed yesterday by the Minister
                        for Foreign Affairs that this Government had under the circumstances decided
                        provisionally not to take any action upon the requests of the Allies. The
                        reason stated was that his Government had reason to believe that such action
                        would involve it in hostilities with the Soviet Union and that the
                        obligation under article II of the Tripartite Treaty of October 19 was
                        therefore nullified by the second protocol thereto.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The Minister said in explanation that upon Italy’s declaration of war the
                        Turkish Ambassador in Moscow had mentioned to the Minister for Foreign
                        Affairs that his Government contemplated mobilization whereupon the latter
                        appeared displeased but made no comment. After the Allied <hi rend="italic"
                            >démarche</hi> the Ambassador under instructions advised the Soviet
                        Foreign Minister thereof in accordance with the Russo-Turkish Protocol of
                        1929 and on that occasion Molotov took a very menacing tone. There were no
                        formal representations, however, and the question was not raised by the
                        Soviet Embassy here.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The only concession which the Turkish Minister for Foreign Affairs would
                        make to the importunities of the Allied Ambassadors was that by way of
                        allaying the impression of Turkish indifference to the situation he would
                        make public reference to the fact that the Turkish Army is calling up
                        several classes of reserves. The Minister presented for the approval of the
                        Ambassadors the draft of a proposed public statement to the effect that in
                        full agreement with its Allies the Government had decided not to act at this
                        time under the <pb facs="0489" n="477" xml:id="pg_477"/> Tripartite Treaty;
                        but they refused to permit such an assertion and the question of the nature
                        of the statement to be made is now under consideration.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>When taxed with resorting to the protocol as a mere subterfuge to evade
                        the obligations of the alliance and reminded that he had all along insisted
                        that the Soviet Government was neither able nor willing to undertake any
                        serious military involvement, the Minister maintained that since the Finnish
                        campaign the Red Army had considerably increased its fighting capacity and
                        that the Kremlin had become much bolder in its policy towards the war. But
                        he appears to have admitted that in any case this Government did not feel
                        able to commit itself in the present military and political situation in
                        Europe to action which would almost necessarily draw it into the war.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Repeated to Moscow, Rome.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
