<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-09T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-09T17:00:00-05:00" n="68" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d68">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/2035:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Sterling</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-09T23:00:00+01:00">April 9,
                                    1940—11 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received April 9—9 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>182 [<hi rend="italic">bis</hi>]. Department’s No. 55, April 9, 10
                                a.m.<note n="17" xml:id="d68fn17">Not printed.</note> Impossible to
                            reach either Legation at Oslo or Mrs. Harriman at Hamar this evening as
                            all telephone communication with Norway is cut off at least
                            temporarily.</p>
                        <p>At my request Consul General Johnson succeeded in seeing Prime Minister
                            tonight who made the following remarks: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“A state of war exists between Germany and Norway just as a state
                                    of war existed between Russia and Finland. This is all I can say
                                    as to the exact juridical status since Germany has not declared
                                    war on Norway and as far as I know Norway has not declared war
                                    on Germany. I do not believe the fighting can last long in
                                    Norway.</p>
                                <p>Germany has exerted no pressure upon Sweden but has asked Sweden
                                    whether it intends to remain neutral as between Germany and
                                    Norway. The Swedish Government has replied that it intends to
                                    pursue the same policy of strict neutrality which has been
                                    followed since the beginning of the Great War.</p>
                                <p>As regards the passage of troops through Sweden my attitude
                                    remains the same as that outlined in my speech in the Rigsdag in
                                        [<hi rend="italic">on</hi>] January 17 when I said that no
                                    foreign troops would be allowed to pass through Sweden.</p>
                                <p>Regarding the freedom of movement of Swedish shipping and the
                                    possible dependency of Sweden for supplies on Germany I am
                                    unable to say anything pending further developments.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The above is undoubtedly the Government’s attitude today but it is very
                            possible that it may change at any moment depending on developments,
                            such as the success of the British movements in Norway and German
                            pressure on Sweden. Despite Swedish assertions of her intention to
                            defend her neutrality at all costs it must be realized that Sweden is
                            now cut off from essential necessities on the west such as oil and coal
                            and she may, as has apparently Norway, put up only a nominal resistance
                            to German aggression.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sterling</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>