<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Steinhardt) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d699</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">699</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-09-30T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-09-30T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recJqlMttIxR5nnOr" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Nonaggression</term>
                    <term ref="receKRNx87Ug7K5bW" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-09-30T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-09-30T05:00:00-05:00" n="699"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d699">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762.9411/65: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-09-30T13:00:00+03:00"
                            >September 30, 1940—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 1—12:22 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1251. Embassy’s 1249, September 28 [<hi rend="italic">30</hi>], 2 p.m. The
                    editorial reported in my telegram under reference appears to reflect the public
                    position which the Soviet Government has elected at the moment to adopt in
                    regard to the German-Italian-Japanese agreement in that it accepts at its face
                    value the reservation contained in the pact concerning the Soviet Union and even
                    interprets the inclusion of this reservation as proof of the efficacy of the
                    nonaggression pacts between the Soviet Union and Germany and Italy. In regard to
                    the general outline of the pact the most interesting feature is the blunt
                    statement in the <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> editorial that the United States
                    is now making common cause in a military sense with Great Britain and that the
                    pact presages the development of the war on a world-wide stage between Germany,
                    Italy and Japan on the one hand and England and the United States on the
                    [other], a development which, as the Embassy has previously reported, would not
                    be displeasing to the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Despite, however, the public acceptance through the medium of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Pravda</hi> editorial of the view that the tripartite pact
                    will not affect the Soviet Union it must be assumed that the similarity of the
                    present agreement between Germany, Italy and Japan and the anti-Comintern Pact
                    has not passed unnoticed in Moscow. It will be recalled in this connection that
                    one of the chief advantages which the Soviet Union obtained through the
                    nonaggression pact with Germany last August was the elimination of
                    German-Japanese cooperation directed against the Soviet Union. It is furthermore
                    significant that while the editorial refers somewhat pointedly to the existence
                    of nonaggression pacts between the U. S. S. R. and Germany and Italy, no mention
                    is <pb facs="0667" n="655" xml:id="pg_655"/> made of the effect of the
                    German-Italian-Japanese military alliance on Soviet-Japanese relations.</p>
                <p>In this connection the Secretary of the Japanese Embassy, while professing to be
                    unaware of the exact nature of the instructions which the new Japanese
                    Ambassador will bring him from Tokyo, was quite frank in stating that the
                    general position in view of Japanese preoccupation in the south was more
                    favorable for an improvement in Soviet-Japanese relations than at any time in
                    the past. As the Embassy has reported since Molotov’s speech on October 31, 1939
                    (Embassy’s 847, November 1, 10 p.m.<note n="62" xml:id="d699fn62">Not
                        printed.</note>) the Soviet Government has given certain indication of a
                    disposition to reach some political agreement between Germany [<hi rend="italic"
                        >the Soviet Union?</hi>] and Japan. The failure of this event to materialize
                    appears to have been primarily due to hesitancy on the part of Tokyo. The
                    general tone of the editorial under reference would seem to indicate that the
                    Soviet attitude in this respect has undergone no change and that the possibility
                    of a Japanese-Soviet political agreement has been enhanced rather than
                    diminished by the German-Italian-Japanese alliance. Indeed, since as a result of
                    this alliance the Soviet Union is now precluded from taking advantage by hostile
                    action of any difficulties which Japan might encounter in the Far East, without
                    running the risk of becoming involved in war with Germany and Italy at the same
                    time, it is possible that the Soviet Government may be prepared to make greater
                    concessions than heretofore particularly in respect of its assistance to China
                    in an endeavor to reach an agreement with the Japanese.</p>
                <p>Not repeated to Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
