<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-12-27T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-12-27T08:00:00-05:00" n="727" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d727">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">761.94/1249: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-12-27T16:00:00+03:00">December 27,
                                1940—4 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received 9 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1786. In the course of a conversation with the Japanese Ambassador this
                        morning, he told me that his negotiations with the Soviet Government looking
                        towards a political convention were “at a standstill”. He said that
                        Molotov’s suggestion (see my 1638, November 28, 7 p.m.) that Japan cede the
                        lower half of Sakhalin had made Matsuoka “very angry” and that Matsuoka had
                        instructed him to tell Molotov that Japan was prepared “to purchase” the
                        northern half of Sakhalin, which Molotov had described as “rude”. He said
                        that notwithstanding the impasse which had caused a “temporary suspension”
                        of the negotiations for a political agreement, he was in daily contact with
                        the Soviet authorities on the subject of the fisheries convention and that
                        Molotov had suggested to him yesterday an 8-year fisheries convention to
                        take the place of the customary annual <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>
                        which expires in January. He said he was also endeavoring to negotiate an
                        agreement concerning trans-Siberian freight rates, as in the absence of a
                        commercial convention with the Soviet Union the rates assessed against
                        Japanese merchandise in transit to Germany were “grossly excessive”.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion the Ambassador observed that Matsuoka had decided to take a
                        “strong stand” in his political negotiations with the Soviet Government, as
                        he considered it inadvisable at the present time to exhibit any
                        “weakness”.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>