<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-03-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="757" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d757">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">862.857/139</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Armour</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 536</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-03-12">March 12,
                                1940</date>.<lb/>[Received March 19.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Department’s
                            circular telegram of March 2, 4 p.m., transmitting the text suggested by
                            the Brazilian Government of a note of protest to be delivered to the
                            British Government <pb facs="0720" n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/> by the
                            President of Panama on behalf of the twenty-one American Republics in
                            connection with the <hi rend="italic">Wakama</hi> incident, I have the
                            honor to report that upon receipt of the above telegram I called on the
                            Foreign Minister and handed to him a note embodying the contents of the
                            Department’s telegram under reference.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Cantilo, after reading the note, informed me that he had been in
                            touch with the Brazilian Foreign Minister on this matter adding that his
                            Government was in accord with the text of the note as proposed and would
                            take the necessary action in so informing the Government of Panama. At
                            the same time, however, Dr. Cantilo indicated considerable scepticism as
                            to whether action as proposed would have any real effect along the lines
                            desired, namely, that the war be kept away from the waters which the
                            Declaration of Panama contemplated preserving for the specific use of
                            intercontinental commerce.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Minister added that in talks with the British Ambassador<note n="34" xml:id="d757fn34">Sir Esmond Ovey.</note> the latter had
                            insisted that adherence by the British Government to the proposals laid
                            down by the twenty-one American Republics would give a great advantage
                            to the Germans and enable their merchant ships to navigate without risk
                            within the zone to say nothing of offering a haven for German submarines
                            from which they could prey on British shipping.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Cantilo was, however, of the opinion that as a matter of record in
                            establishing the position of neutral countries for the future, protests
                            of this sort would perhaps serve a useful purpose and possibly lead,
                            after the termination of hostilities, to the extension of the limited
                            area of territorial waters as now generally accepted under international
                            law.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Minister referred in passing to the procedure proposed by his
                                Government<note n="35" xml:id="d757fn35">See telegram No. 291,
                                December 16, 1939, 4 p.m., from the Ambassador in Argentina, <ref target="frus1939v05#pg_100">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1939, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 100</ref>.</note> to be followed
                            in the event of violation of the security zone as later embodied in the
                            protest subscribed to by the American Republics and embodied in the note
                            to the belligerent powers of December last.<note n="36" xml:id="d757fn36">For text of note as released on December 23, 1939,
                                see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, December
                                23, 1939, p. 723.</note> In doing so, however, the Foreign Minister
                            did not make clear that he felt that action such as that envisaged in
                            that note should be invoked in connection with the <hi rend="italic">Wakama</hi> incident.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Norman Armour</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>