<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Argentina ( (Armour) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d819</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">819</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recXuFW8WO1tqBrVK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="819"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d819">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00111 A.R./1022</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Armour</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 624</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-22">April 22,
                            1940</date>.<lb/>[Received April 30.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Embassy’s confidential
                    telegram No. 112 of April 19, 6 p.m., “For the Secretary”, I have the honor to
                    transmit herewith a memorandum of my conversation with the Minister for Foreign
                    Affairs on April 19 last, of which the telegram mentioned above was a
                    summary.</p>
                <p>As pointed out in the memorandum, Dr. Cantilo did not appear to have worked out
                    the details of his somewhat startling proposal. He explained that he had only
                    just come from the President with whom he had apparently discussed the matter
                    for the first time, but whose enthusiastic endorsement of the idea he assured me
                    he had secured. In fact, as will be noted, the President felt that if our
                    Government approved the idea, he would favor having us both go on with it, even
                    in the event the Brazilian Government should not be disposed to fall into
                    line.</p>
                <p>What prompted Dr. Cantilo to advance the suggestion at this time does not appear
                    clear. In discussing the advantages which he felt would result from the
                    abandonment of the present position of neutrality in favor of a non-belligerent
                    status, the Minister mentioned several times the difficulties of the present
                    situation from an internal point of view. (While he did not elaborate on this
                    point or cite any instances, it seems reasonable to believe that he had in mind
                    the problem presented by the internment of the officers and sailors of the <pb
                        facs="0761" n="749" xml:id="pg_749"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Graf Spee</hi>
                    <note n="82" xml:id="d819fn82">See telegram No. 147, December 18, 1939, 5 p.m.,
                        from the Minister in Uruguay, <ref target="frus1939v05#pg_106">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1939, Vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 106</ref>.</note> as well, possibly, as
                    the difficulties presented by a large German colony in Argentina, the presence
                    of the several German ships, etc.)</p>
                <p>As the Department is aware, Dr. Cantilo has for some time been doubtful as to the
                    practicability of effectively maintaining the 300-mile security zone. Both in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Wakama</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hannover</hi>
                        incidents,<note n="83" xml:id="d819fn83">See section entitled “Violations by
                        the Belligerents of the Security Zone Established by the Declaration of
                        Panama,” <ref target="#pg_681">pp. 681</ref> ff.</note> he has somewhat
                    reluctantly agreed to his Government joining in the protests to the belligerent
                    powers, expressing scepticism as to the probability of any useful results being
                    accomplished by such protests.</p>
                <p>The Minister appeared to be equally sceptical as to the Neutrality
                        Commission<note n="84" xml:id="d819fn84">See <ref target="frus1940v05">Vol.
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>
                        </ref>, section under General entitled “The Inter-American Neutrality
                        Committee.”</note> in Rio de Janeiro being able to formulate any plan of
                    procedure which would result in strengthening the neutral position of the
                    American Republics. As he pointed out in one of my talks with him regarding the
                        <hi rend="italic">Hannover</hi> incident, even if the Rio Commission were to
                    reach an agreement on proposals in the nature of sanctions, any attempt to
                    enforce these might even result in bringing us into the war.</p>
                <p>It seems entirely possible therefore that Dr. Cantilo’s somewhat sudden proposal
                    to abandon our neutral status may have arisen out of his attempt, or the
                    attempts of his Government, to find some substitute for the security zone as a
                    method of keeping the war away from the American continent.</p>
                <p>I must frankly admit that it was not clear to me just what Dr. Cantilo means by
                    “non-belligerence” as contrasted with, or distinguished from neutrality. The
                    most definite answer he could give me when I asked him was to point to the case
                    of Italy as an example of non-belligerence, as distinguished from
                    neutrality.</p>
                <p>While I was careful not to express any opinion which might have been taken to
                    indicate approval on the part of our Government of his proposal, after
                    expressing interest in the suggestion, I ventured to point out what, even
                    admitting our willingness to consider the idea, I felt would be the difficulties
                    confronting our Government from a mechanical viewpoint (so to speak), e. g., the
                    necessity for congressional action, in view of the revised neutrality law passed
                    by Congress under which we are now functioning.</p>
                <p>My personal feeling is that perhaps the greatest importance to be attached to Dr.
                    Cantilo’s suggestion is the indication it affords of the lines along which he
                    and his Government are thinking at the present time. As I have pointed out in
                    previous despatches, Dr. Cantilo has several times referred to a suggestion
                    which he states was made <pb facs="0762" n="750" xml:id="pg_750"/> in 1916 (at
                    which time he was Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs) by the Argentine Minister
                    for Foreign Affairs through their Ambassador at Washington for a conference of
                    the American Republics to discuss the situation created at that time by
                    Germany’s unrestricted submarine warfare. (See Embassy’s despatch No. 136 of
                    September 19, 1939).<note n="85" xml:id="d819fn85">See <ref
                            target="frus1939v05#pg_27">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1939, Vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 27</ref>, footnote 21.</note> In these
                    references Dr. Cantilo pointed to the rejection of the Argentine Government’s
                    proposal by the then Secretary of State as justifying the Argentine Government’s
                    decision a year later not to follow our lead in declaring war on Germany in
                    contrast with the course adopted later by other of the American Republics.</p>
                <p>On one or two occasions recently, the Foreign Minister has expressed to me the
                    opinion that, with the evolution which the war is now taking in Europe, while
                    admitting the natural desire of our Government to avoid being drawn in, he
                    cannot see how it will be possible eventually for us to keep out, particularly
                    if things should come to a point where a defeat for the democracies would seem
                    to be a possibility.</p>
                <p>Read in this light and in the background of his previous statements, Dr.
                    Cantilo’s proposal, it would seem, can logically be interpreted as favoring a
                    procedure which would have the effect of keeping the American Republics in step
                    with us to the end that in the event of our being drawn into the war, this final
                    step would for them also be a natural and logical consequence to those which had
                    preceded it.</p>
                <p>If this assumption is correct, it is suggested that whatever decision may be
                    reached by our Government with regard to Dr. Cantilo’s proposal, in the wording
                    of the reply due consideration be given to this apparently cooperative attitude
                    on the part of the Argentine Government. In the event that our Government should
                    not consider the proposal practicable, I feel sure the Department will consider
                    it important to make it clear to Dr. Cantilo that we welcome—as I feel sure we
                    do—all suggestions which indicate a desire to see a common front preserved by
                    the American Governments in meeting the increasingly difficult situation created
                    by the evolution of the war in Europe.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Norman Armour</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Ambassador in
                            Argentina</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Armour</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-19">April 19,
                                1940</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>[The first part of this memorandum, here omitted, is in substance the same as
                        telegram No. 112, April 19, 6 p.m., from the Ambassador in Argentina,
                        printed on <ref target="#pg_743">page 743</ref>.]</p>
                    <pb facs="0763" n="751" xml:id="pg_751"/>
                    <p>Dr. Cantilo asked me my opinion with regard to the proposal. I said that of
                        course it was impossible for me to express an opinion on a matter of such
                        importance until my Government had had an opportunity to study it. Speaking
                        entirely personally, however, while I felt the suggestion was an extremely
                        interesting one, I was afraid so far as we were concerned, regardless of the
                        merits of the suggestion, the machinery by which such a change could be put
                        into effect in the United States would, I felt, present certain
                        difficulties. As he knew, we had a Neutrality Law<note n="86"
                            xml:id="d819fn86">Approved November 4, 1939; 54 Stat. 4.</note> which
                        had been voted by Congress and any such action as that proposed, would
                        presumably require congressional action or approval. As to his observations
                        with regard to our neutrality, I pointed out that our neutrality law
                        permitted the sale of supplies to any belligerents who could come and get
                        them, and the fact that the Germans were not in a position to avail
                        themselves of this did not alter the situation, even though the practical
                        result, as he had stated, was that the Allies were the only ones able to
                        purchase from us. Nor was I clear in my own mind as to what particular
                        advantages a change from our present neutral status to one of
                        non-belligerence would bring the situation.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Cantilo mentioned once or twice in the course of the conversation that
                        the freeing of the Governments from the obligations—duties—automatically
                        enforced by neutrality would be of considerable assistance in the internal
                        situation, at least so far as Argentina was concerned. (While he did not
                        explain what he had in mind, I presume he referred to incidents such as the
                        internment of the officers and sailors of the <hi rend="italic">Graf
                            Spee</hi>—the handling of the large German colony in
                        Argentina—Patagonian incident<note n="87" xml:id="d819fn87">
                            <p>The Habana <hi rend="italic">Avance</hi> of April 10, 1939, gave
                                publicity to a note allegedly sent to the Cuban Secretary of State
                                by the German Minister in Cuba stating that Germany had no interest
                                whatsoever in Patagonia. The newspaper said that the Minister had
                                stated: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“According to notices from abroad reproduced in the Cuban
                                        press, it is alleged that Germany, according to a document
                                        placed at the disposition of the Government of Argentina,
                                        has the intention to annex Patagonia. On behalf of my
                                        Government I have the honor to inform Your Excellency’s
                                        Government that insofar as the said document is concerned it
                                        is completely false.… So far as Germany is concerned there
                                        is no Patagonian question.” (835.00N/15)</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                        </note>—German ships, etc.)</p>
                    <p>Dr. Cantilo had obviously not worked out his ideas in any detail; in fact he
                        told me that he hoped later to put his plan in more definite form. He
                        explained that it was only that morning that he had discussed the matter
                        with the President and had not wished to lose any time in putting the matter
                        up to our Government for consideration. I told him that in order to present
                        his ideas as accurately as possible, I would suggest his outlining the
                        essence of what he had told me, for presentation to Washington, and in his
                        presence I made notes for use in the telegram which I later despatched to
                        the Secretary.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">orman</hi>] A[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >rmour</hi>]</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
