<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Argentina ( (Armour) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">893</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-07-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recb140a4efc2e771d" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Warships</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="western-hemisphere" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="western-hemisphere-relations">Western Hemisphere</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monroe Doctrine</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-07-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="893"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d893">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">710.Consultation (2)/457</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Armour</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 955</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-07-17">July 17,
                            1940</date>.<lb/>[Received July 27.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Embassy’s telegram no. 294
                    of July 13, 1 p.m. and its despatch no. 951 of July 16,<note n="62"
                        xml:id="d893fn62">Latter not printed.</note> as well as previous despatches,
                    reporting German propaganda in Argentina hostile to the <pb facs="0817" n="805"
                        xml:id="pg_805"/> United States, I have the honor to enclose a translation
                    of the first page of the daily news bulletin of the German Embassy here for July
                    10 last, which criticizes the Monroe Doctrine. As the Embassy has noted in
                    previous communications, these bulletins appear under German Embassy
                    letter-heads and purport to be “official news received by cable from
                    Berlin”.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Norman Armour</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Press Release by the German Embassy in Argentina, July 10,
                            1940</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Monroe Doctrine</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In connection with the military preparations of British warships against the
                        French island Martinique<note n="63" xml:id="d893fn63">See <ref
                                target="frus1940v02#pg_505">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp.
                                505</ref> ff.</note> in Central America [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]
                        and with the publication of the reply of the Government of the Reich to the
                        note of the United States regarding the interpretation of the Monroe
                            Doctrine,<note n="64" xml:id="d893fn64">See telegram No. 1652, June 17,
                            11 a.m., to the Chargé in Germany, and reply No. 2293, July 2, 5 p.m.,
                                <ref target="frus1940v02#pg_494">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                                pp. 494</ref> and <ref target="frus1940v02#pg_495">495</ref>,
                            respectively.</note> statements were made in Washington<note n="65"
                            xml:id="d893fn65">See statement by the Secretary of State released July
                            5, Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, July 6, 1940, p.
                            3.</note> and Hyde Park which could not be understood even by those who
                        are well acquainted with American opinions. It is now being pointed out that
                        the occupation of French colonies in America by British forces does not
                        necessarily imply a change of sovereignty. A difference is also being made
                        now between the real transfer of territorial property and political
                        intervention. It is finally declared that all the American nations should
                        gather information relative to British measures against Martinique since the
                        United States does not wish to assume responsibility regarding those
                        possessions. For the first time there arises in Washington in this respect
                        the idea of allocating American possessions of European powers in the form
                        of mandates.</p>
                    <p>On top of this, the statements made by competent American sources also refer
                        to the possibility of a new territorial order in Asia. Roosevelt’s secretary
                        said that this matter in the sense of an Asiatic Monroe Doctrine should be
                        discussed exclusively by Asiatic countries. It is not easy to form an
                        accurate idea of the present trend of the American policy based on this
                        number of new and disconcerting versions. Is this supposed to be a new
                        generous distribution of the world, for which Washington accepts as a “fait
                        accompli” the defeat of the British Empire and the future status of France?
                        Do the governments of Australia, The Netherland Indies and French Indo-China
                        react against that attitude? Has approval from London been obtained or is
                        this an independent act of American policy? Or do the speakers <pb
                            facs="0818" n="806" xml:id="pg_806"/> consider themselves as
                        interpreters of the President’s personal opinion? Is it a non-transparent
                        electoral maneuver? As long as these questions remain unanswered, the
                        countries directly affected by the statements referred to will continue to
                        feel confused and in doubt. At present all that can be said with certainty
                        is that the reply of the Government of the Reich has created a great
                        impression in the United States, and it shows that in addressing its note to
                        Berlin the American Government did not consider the possibility that
                        territorial changes in the Western Hemisphere might turn into serious
                        problems, particularly between France and England.</p>
                    <p>Finally, the indecision with which Washington observes the British
                        greediness, allowing the Martinique problem to approach a state which every
                        day can assume the nature of the butchery which took place in Oran,<note
                            n="66" xml:id="d893fn66">For correspondence regarding the attack by a
                            British fleet upon French warships at Mers-el-Kebir near Oran, Algeria,
                            July 3, 1940, see <ref target="frus1940v02#pg_469">Vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 469</ref>–<ref
                                target="frus1940v02#pg_474">474</ref>.</note> has caused uneasiness
                        in Latin American countries. Evidently at the latter’s initiative the
                        problem of the transfer of possessions assumes in Washington the importance
                        of a question of Pan American significance. The future development of this
                        question awakens all the more interest, inasmuch as the spirit of a doctrine
                        lies in the unalterability of principles once they are adopted.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
