<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Germany ( (Kirk) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-02-14T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-02-14T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-02-14T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-02-14T07:00:00-05:00" n="9"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">121.840 Welles, Sumner/32: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Germany</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-02-14T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >February 14, 1940—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 5:26 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>388. For the Secretary and Under Secretary. My 363, February 11, noon.<note
                        n="11" xml:id="d9fn11">Not printed.</note> Although the official reserve on
                    the matter of the visit to Europe of the Under Secretary still continues there
                    is reason to believe from information received up to the present that his
                    impending arrival in Berlin has aroused the greatest interest in the highest
                    governmental circles here and it is said that particularly close contact with
                    Rome is being maintained in regard to the significance and possible consequences
                    of his mission. I have received no indication from authoritative sources as to
                    the reception which may be contemplated but I have received an indirect
                    intimation to the effect that there is the present intention that he be received
                    by the highest authorities. There is furthermore the definite impression that if
                    the Under Secretary proceeds directly from Rome to Berlin and concludes his
                    journey in Europe by visits to England and France the purpose of his visit will
                    be colored in the minds of the German authorities.</p>
                <p>In the absence of instructions I have made no representations or inquiries at the
                    German Foreign Office in regard to the visit. I have merely communicated to
                    State Secretary Weizsäcker in a personal <pb facs="0021" n="9" xml:id="pg_9"/>
                    and informal letter the substance of the Department’s circular telegram February
                    9, 4 p.m., and have received a courteous acknowledgment thereof.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
