<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Sweden ( (Sterling) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d90</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">90</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-05-15T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-05-15T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZobsyHhwdJPklD" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085246"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Occupied territory</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-05-15T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-05-15T10:00:00-05:00" n="90"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/3046: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sterling</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-05-15T16:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 15, 1940—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 5:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>512. Following received from Cox by courier:</p>
                <p>May 12, 10 a.m. Continuing my April 23, 5 p.m.,<note n="27" xml:id="d90fn27">Not
                        printed.</note> German control over occupied territory in Norway has been
                    and continues to be effectively strengthened by the continuous arrival of
                    transport and supply ships during the past 2 weeks. The arrival of Reichs
                    Commissioner Terboven reported in my 249, April 28<note n="27" xml:id="d90fn28"
                        >Not printed.</note> has been followed by that of many German officials to
                    assume posts in the German civil administration as well as officials and members
                    of German safety and secret police under whom the Norwegian police authorities
                    now function.</p>
                <pb facs="0176" n="164" xml:id="pg_164"/>
                <p>The Storthing Building is now the Commissioner’s headquarters and the Foreign
                    Office has been taken over as the German police headquarters. Germans occupy
                    advisory positions in Government Ministries such as Finance and Supplies, the
                    Bank of Norway, and other key offices. Press and telecommunications are under
                    absolute German control and censorship. Strict control is exercised over
                    finance, prices, firearms, movements of individuals, et cetera. The German
                    Legation is nonexistent. Its senior officers are now attached as
                    “representatives of the Foreign Office” to the Commissioner’s staff. There is
                    still considerable confusion as between civil and military authorities in the
                    exercise of duties. The above, however, indicates the general lines of the
                    present setup.</p>
                <p>The Commissioner’s first proclamation indicates that while the Norwegian
                    Administrative Council appointed April 15 continues its functions under him, it
                    is entirely subordinated to German decisions on all important questions.
                    Terboven proclaimed that among his principal duties were the maintenance of
                    safety and order and the utilization of all the occupied area’s
                    “potentialities”, the supply [of] military necessities. So far, only strict
                    rationing of food, fuel, and lubricants has been enforced and to some extent
                    grain reserves are being utilized for the German troops. Some apprehension
                    exists that if transport facilities break down, or for other reasons, the
                    Germans may requisition reserve stocks of foodstuffs and raw materials required
                    by military forces or for shipment to Germany.</p>
                <p>The Norwegian reaction in Oslo area to the withdrawal of British forces from
                    southern Norway has been one of complete disillusionment. This, coupled with the
                    strong undercurrent of defeatism evident here since the beginning of the
                    occupation, indicates that except possibly for isolated localities Norwegian
                    resistance in southern Norway will terminate shortly.</p>
                <p>I am confidentially informed that important groups of Norwegian industrialists
                    and some members of Storthing are endeavoring to reach [the] King, said to be at
                    Tromso, and persuade him that his continued refusal to accept the fact of German
                    control may force his abdication. Many who know the English sympathies of both
                    King and Crown Prince believe that both will refuse possibly in favor of a
                    regency for Crown Princess. [Cox.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sterling</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
