<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 136.Mr. Kasson
                            to Mr. Frelinghuysen.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1884</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d136</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">136</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1884-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1884-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274" lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004" lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907" lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1884-11-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1884-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="136" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d136">
                <head>No. 136.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kasson</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    The United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-11-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 17, 1884</date>.
                            (Received December 1.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 74.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Among the many legal questions arising under
                        our naturalization laws ‘and treaty upon Which I am required to give
                        opinions at this legation there is one case that of Augustus Reichard, which
                        had previously been submitted to the Department of State. Its reply,(March
                        19, 1884), as he claimed, still left him in doubt touching his rights, and
                        now he appeals to this legation.</p>
                <p>After an examination of the text of the German law of naturalization, I sent
                        him a reply as full and explicit as possible. I should be glad to know that
                        the opinion of his rights and liabilities, and those of his family, under
                        the treaty of 1868, as expressed in my reply to his letter, is concurred in
                        by the Department.</p>
                <p>Copies of his letter and of my answer are herewith inclosed.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOHN A. KASSON.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 74.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Reichard</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Kasson</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dresden</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-11-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 10,
                                    1884</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As a citizen of the United States, I take
                            the liberty to transmit under cover a letter to the minister of foreign
                            affairs of the Kingdom of Prussia, Berlin, and respectfully to request
                            that the same be forwarded through your kind offices, as in this way
                            said communication will naturally receive a more attentive
                            consideration.</p>
                    <pb facs="0311" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/>
                    <p>The object of my addressing the Prussian ministry is to ascertain whether
                            the authorities here might possibly look upon my prolonged stay in
                            Germany, on account of ill health, as being in conflict with the
                            Bancroft treaty of 22d February, 1868, so far as my claims to the
                            preservation of my prerogatives as an American citizen are concerned. In
                            said letter I state that I was born in 1820, in the then Kingdom of
                            Hanover, now a Prussian province; that I fulfilled my military
                            obligations in 1840, emigrated to New Orleans in 1844, made my
                            declaration to become an American citizen on 21th January, 1850, and
                            received the certificate of my American citizenship on 4th November,
                            1853, which certificate is now in my possession. I further state that in
                            1881 my health became so deplorable that my physicians declared that the
                            only means of saving my life were a radical change of climate, free from
                            the excessive heat of American summers, and a prolonged, use of the
                            mineral waters of Germany. Consequently I settled here in Dresden in the
                            summer of 1881; returned to New Orleans last winter for six months,
                            partly to attend to my business there, partly to ascertain whether my
                            somewhat improved health would withstand the climate. This, as soon as
                            the heat recommenced, was by no means the case, and my physicians
                            declared most emphatically that I must stay away fox several years more.
                            In obtaining my new passport at Washington my attention for the first
                            time was called to the details of the Bancroft treaty, by our Louisiana
                            Senators, Hon. B. F. Jonas and General Randall be Gibson, who advised me
                            to be very careful not to omit anything which might be necessary to
                            avoid being mixed up with the stipulations of Article IV of said treaty,
                            Under these circumstances I thought it advisable to address the Hon.
                            Frederick T. Frelinghuysen and to request to be enlightened on, the
                            following three points, viz: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>On my return to Germany I intend to place on record, with the
                                    United States legation at Berlin my, declaration that although
                                    the state of my health may necessitate a stay in Germany for
                                    more than two years, it is my intention to preserve for myself
                                    and children all the prerogatives of citizens of the United
                                    States, to which country I shall return as soon as circumstances
                                    may permit. Will such proceedings prevent the German,
                                    authorities from calling in question nay rights as a citizen of
                                    the United States, and those of my children?</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>Suppose the above declaration should not have the desired,
                                    effect as far as I am personally concerned, could this possibly
                                    affect the status of my children (now all minors) as citizens of
                                    the United States, where they were all born, the father being a
                                    naturalized citizen, the mother a native American; in other
                                    words, would the altered state of citizenship of the father
                                    forcibly bring about a change of citizenship of his minor
                                    children and his native American wife?</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>If none of the above joints could be decided in a positive
                                    manner, would my return to this country (United States) every
                                    two years, for a limited period, remove all doubts and his
                                    difficulties.?</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>In reply I received a letter from the Hon. Frederick T. Frelinghuysen
                            dated 19th March, 1884, which I beg to inclose for perusal; it leaves my
                            position still clouded with doubt. Perhaps the honorable Secretary of
                            State might have been more positive in his reply if I had stated to him,
                            the positive fact that, with the exception of my villa here, which I
                            bought at a very low price from a returning American, my whole fortune
                            is in vested in real estate in Louisiana, which I intend to retain
                            intact, and that, besides, I still own my dwelling-house in New Orleans,
                            with the intention of reoccupying it with my family on our return, I
                            really believe no stronger proof could be given of any intention to
                            return to the United States, and as a matter of course to retain my
                            American citizenship of nearly one-third of a century’s standing.</p>
                    <p>On my return here I had several conversations on the subject with the
                            United States consul and vice-consul, who are both of the opinion that
                            inasmuch as I had fulfilled my military obligation before emigrating,
                            having been for more than thirty-one years an American citizen, my wife
                            and children being native Americans, and, moreover, my means being all
                            invested in the United, States, from where alone I draw all my income,
                            the Bancroft treaty could find no application to my particular case; and
                            they further state that they know of many similar cases where the
                            individuals have never been troubled by the authorities here. They are
                            decidedly of the opinion that all that is necessary would be to have
                            every two years my passport renewed at the United States legation in
                            Berlin, and they think that perhaps, in order to observe even the very,
                            wording of Article IV of the Bancroft treaty., it might be well every
                            two year to spend a certain time abroad.</p>
                    <p>This may probably be your opinion likewise, and you may perhaps consider
                            my steps to ascertain the opinion of the Prussian ministry of foreign
                            affairs as altogether unnecessary; yet I thought it might serve to
                            remove all possibility of future difficulties with the authorities here,
                            as also in such cases to avoid a necessitated intervention of the United
                            States legation in the future. I should feel under great obligations if,
                            at a convenient time, you Would kindly do me the favor of transmitting
                            to me the views you entertain respecting my particular case, and</p>
                    <p>Remain, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>AUGUSTUS REICHARD,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bergstrasse</hi>
                                16.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0312" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 74.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kasson</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Reichard</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-11-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 14,
                                    1884</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your letter of the 10th instant is
                            received. With it you inclose a communication addressed to the German
                            ministry for foreign affairs, and request that the same he transmitted
                            to its destination by this legation, in order, as you state, that it may
                            receive more attentive consideration. In the communication to this
                            legation, as well as in that to the German ministry, you present facts
                            relating to your compliance before emigration with the obligation of
                            military service in your native country, your acquisition of citizenship
                            in the United States, and your places of residence since, and conclude
                            by soliciting both from this legation and the German ministry
                            expressions of their views upon your case.</p>
                    <p>The essential facts stated appear to be the following: You were born in
                            Germany in 1820; emigrated in 1844, at the age of twenty-four years, to
                            the United States, where you were naturalized January 21, 1850, as shown
                            by a certificate of naturalization now in your possession; that in the
                            summer of 1881 you returned to Germany in pursuit of health, and settled
                            at Dresden; that, after a residence in Germany of more than two years,
                            you returned last winter for business and other purposes to the United
                            States, where you spent six months; that, finding the American climate
                            still injurious to your health, and being advised by your physicians to
                            absent yourself for several years more, you returned to Germany, after
                            obtaining a new passport from the Department of State, and after making
                            yourself acquainted with the details of the Bancroft treaty, with the
                            special view of guarding yourself against the stipulation of Article IV
                            of said treaty. You also state that you addressed a communication to the
                            honorable Secretary of State on the subject of your case, and received,
                            under date of March 19, 1884, a reply thereto which left your position
                            still clouded with doubt.</p>
                    <p>You quote the three questions submitted in your communication to the
                            Department of State, and request this legation to answer them,
                            substantially repeating the same inquiries in your inclosure addressed
                            to the German Government.</p>
                    <p>Briefly stated, you wish to know (1) whether, in view of the state of
                            your health, you may again stay in Germany for more than two years
                            without forfeiting for yourself or children, now all minors and born in
                            the United States, the rights of American citizenship; (2) whether a
                            possible forcible alteration of your citizenship would bring about a
                            change in the citizenship of your minor children and your native
                            American wife; (3) would your return to the United States every two
                            years for a limited period remove all doubts and difficulties?</p>
                    <p>Replying to your first inquiry, you are informed that Atrticle IV of the
                            treaty referred to leaves it optional with the German authorities to
                            hold that the renunciation of American citizenship exists, as to these
                            authorities, after your residence in Germany shall have been prolonged
                            beyond the period of two years. This legation cannot anticipate the
                            action thereon of the German Government. But if they should so hold,
                            that would not make you a German subject without voluntary proceedings
                            taken by yourself therefor. As we read the German naturalization law,
                            after being once a citizen of another country you can again become a
                            German subject only by applying for naturalization under their forms of
                            law. They might expel you from Germany, but cannot make you a subject
                            against your will.</p>
                    <p>In reply to your second inquiry, your children were all born in
                            America—we so understand it—after you became a citizen. They are,
                            therefore, native-born American citizens, and can become liable as
                            German subjects in only one of two ways—(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) by
                            their father becoming a German subject during their minority and while
                            they remain under paternal control, or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) by
                            they themselves voluntarily becoming naturalized under German laws. We
                            know of no case of an American-born citizen being put into the army as a
                            German subject, without the father’s consent, either by naturalization
                            or expressly. Your own naturalization as a German subject would abandon
                            for your wife and for your minor children, at least till they attain
                            their majority, their rights as American citizens, as their condition
                            always follows yours.</p>
                    <p>In reply to your third inquiry, the legation is of opinion that recurring
                            visits to Germany, not prolonged beyond two years, are permissible under
                            the treaty, <hi rend="italic">if preceded by bona fide resumptions of
                                residence in the United States</hi>, and that the residence of six
                            months which preceded your recent return to Germany should be regarded
                            as such a residence.</p>
                    <p>In the opinion of this legation, the German Government reserved the right
                            in question in order to act or decline to act upon each case as it
                            should be presented at the time for action, without interference by the
                            United States. We do not, therefore, believe that you would now obtain
                            from them a satisfactory reply, and do not think it <pb facs="0313" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> advisable to transmit your application to
                            them, thus calling special attention to your case and that of your
                            children. The only effect, in our view of the case, of your overstaying
                            two years would, be to give the German authorities the right to say
                            (without our interference) that you or your children, or both, must
                            become naturalized or leave the country. As long as you hold to the <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> intention to return to the United
                            States to reside there as a citizen, <hi rend="italic">we</hi> hold you
                            and your minor children to be still American citizens.</p>
                    <p>Your inclosures are herewith returned.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN A. KASSON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
