<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1884-05-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1884-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="249" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d249">
                    <head>No. 248.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Frelinghuysen</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Morgan</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-05-17"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 17,
                            1884</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 570.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatches Nos. 775 and 776, both of the
                        25th ultimo, have been received. Your No. 775 is in relation to the claim of
                        the owners of the American schooner Daylight, of Bath, Me., which vessel
                        while at anchor outside of the bar near the harbor of Tampico, being then on
                        her voyage from Key West, Fla., with a cargo of lumber for Tampico, was, on
                        the 21st of March, 1882, at night, run into by the Mexican gunboat
                        Independencia, the vessel and cargo becoming a total loss; with that
                        dispatch you inclose a copy and translation of a note of the 23d of the same
                        month on the subject, addressed to you by Mr. Fernandez, the secretary for
                        foreign relations of Mexico.</p>
                    <p>I have given to the suggestions of that minister’s note such consideration as
                        its importance and the high source from which these suggestions emanate
                        demand. Mr. Fernandez, conceiving that the views of his Government as
                        heretofore presented by him had not been fully understood by this
                        Department, reiterates the essential points of his previous arguments,
                        stating, in a categorical form, the grounds upon which they rest. These, for
                        convenience, I briefly restate. They are: “That the owners of the Daylight
                        can make their direct demand on the Mexican Government before the Mexican
                        tribunals without previous permission. That the Mexican Government is
                        considered as a person, and as such can sue and be sued before the proper
                        tribunals.”</p>
                    <p>From these grounds Mr. Fernandez concludes that should the Government deem it
                        best that the matter of the Daylight be settled between the two Governments,
                        the United States minister and the Mexican department of foreign affairs
                        will be the medium through which the settlement <pb facs="0459" n="359" xml:id="pg_359"/> will be made, the department of war and navy acting as
                        witnesses only of the facts. “But,” says Mr. Fernandez, “it having been a
                        practice constantly sustained by the Government that a diplomatic course
                        cannot be taken when it interferes in favor of persons, except in case of a
                        denial of justice, Señor Mariscal and I had the honor to notify your
                        excellency that the complainant (or complainants) must himself appear before
                        the department of war and navy, regretting that such a course is
                        necessary.”</p>
                    <p>Mr. Fernandez’s sixth and last conclusion is that “the disaster of the
                        Daylight having occurred in Mexican waters the Mexican tribunals are the
                        proper ones to hear this case, as well as any other which treats of the
                        defining of civil or criminal responsibility, and decide what grade or form
                        of responsibility must be laid upon the delinquents in the deplorable
                        case.”</p>
                    <p>Upon a careful examination of these several propositions of the distinguished
                        secretary for foreign relations of Mexico, I find myself wholly unable to
                        agree with him in the conclusion that the doctrine embraced in them can,
                        with any legal propriety, be considered applicable to the case of the
                        Daylight. In his note to you of the same date regarding the case of the
                        Sidbury, a copy of which accompanies your 776, referring to this same
                        jurisdictional contention, Mr. Fernandez says: “This opinion does not merely
                        rest upon the principle that the courts are called upon to redress injuries
                        which are suffered by the inhabitants of the country or those who are
                        transiently therein, for the purpose for which they are established is to
                        administer justice.” Giving to this proposition the interpretation which it
                        has received from all writers on public law, and hitherto accepted by all
                        civilized governments, that is, that the municipal civil laws can only be
                        held applicable to and operative on the rights, property, and persons of the
                        citizens of the country and foreigners who may be either permanently or
                        temporarily residing in the country, I find no difficulty in acceding to it.
                        This, however, is all that can be claimed for it—all, as it is believed,
                        that is claimed for it by the governments of Christian nations—and all that
                        is allowed to it by the uniform declaration of writers on public law.
                        “Considered,” says Halleck, “in an international point of view, either the
                        thing or the person made the subject of the jurisdiction must be within the
                        territory, for no sovereignty can extend its process beyond its own
                        territorial limits so as to subject either persons or property to its
                        judicial decisions, and every exertion of authority of its sort beyond its
                        limits is a mere nullity and incapable of binding such persons or property
                        in any other tribunals.”</p>
                    <p>The same doctrine is found stated in different forms of expression in
                        Phillimore, in Wheaton, in Westlake, and in Woolsey. I am not aware that it
                        has ever been questioned.</p>
                    <p>The owners of the Daylight were never residents of Mexico, either permanent
                        or temporary. They are not known to have ever been in that country. The
                        master of the vessel was not a resident of Mexico, either permanent or
                        temporary, and was never in the country beyond the port at which his vessel
                        might touch. At the time of the occurrence which gave rise to the claim the
                        vessel could scarcely be said, with strict propriety, to have been in
                        Mexican waters. She was anchored outside the bar, near the harbor of
                        Tampico, in an exceptionally rough sea, at the close of a severe storm,
                        which rendered it unsafe for her to attempt to cross the bar or enter the
                        harbor. To insist that those claimants shall go from Maine to Tampico to
                        seek redress in the Mexican tribunals for a grievous wrong suffered at the
                        hands of a high <pb facs="0460" n="360" xml:id="pg_360"/> officer of the
                        navy of that Republic, and in such proceedings to be met by the evidence
                        which the commander of the Independencia would readily be able to elicit
                        from the ship’s crew, would, in the estimation of this Government, be a
                        practical denial of justice. The Mexican Government is conceived to be
                        justly responsible to this for the act of that officer, and consequently the
                        views put forth by Mr. Fernandez in behalf of his Government cannot be
                        accepted or acceded to by this.</p>
                    <p>Guided by the suggestions of my former instructions in regard to the matter,
                        you will again, in the light of the observations made in this, bring the
                        subject to the attention of the minister for foreign affairs, and you will
                        say at the same time that the President hopes and expects that so just a
                        claim as this is deemed to be will receive early consideration, followed by
                        prompt and speedy adjustment at the hands of the Government of Mexico.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>FRED’K T. FRELINGHUYSEN.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>