<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1884-04-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1884-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="354" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                    <head>No. 354.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-04-04"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4, 1884</date>.
                            (Received April 21.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 201.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It will be seen by the inclosures herewith
                        that steps have at last been taken by the Spanish Government to carry out
                        the long-promised reform in its consular tariff. A commission has been
                        appointed by royal decree to revise the existing consular tariffs with a
                        view to the submission of the projected reform to the Cortes for its
                        approbation.</p>
                    <p>The minister of state in his “exposition” refers, among other reasons for the
                        revision, to the international engagements recently contracted, doubtless
                        having in mind the additional article of our agreement of February 13 last,
                        respecting the abolition of consular tonnage dues for the West India
                        Islands. I have not omitted the opportunity, afforded by the publication of
                        the royal decree nominating the commission, to bring to his attention the
                        remonstrances of our Government against these tonnage dues. In my note of
                        the 2d instant, of which a copy is inclosed, I have recited the
                        correspondence of this legation on the subject, and have asked the Minister
                        of State to bring this correspondence to the notice of the commission with
                        such favorable recommendation as will secure the abolition of the
                        objectionable dues for the entire commerce between the United States and
                        Spain.</p>
                    <p>I propose, also, as far as I can, to secure the co-operation of my diplomatic
                            <pb facs="0589" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/> colleagues of the leading
                        commercial nations by notes of similar purport as the one I have sent to the
                        Minister of State. The representatives of Great Britain and of other
                        Governments have already signified to me their intention to follow my
                        action.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                201.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head>[From the Gaceta de Madrid, March 28, 1884.]</head>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">ministry of state exposition.</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Señor</hi>: On the 15th June, 1874, the consular
                            tariffs were revised with an object to regulate and make uniform on
                            equitable bases the collection of the obventional fees received by the
                            agents of Spain in foreign countries on account of the numerous acts of
                            their official duties, providing at the same time that the special
                            services which they render may be justly recompensed by the persons
                            soliciting them.</p>
                        <p>The well known and constant spread which mercantile transactions have
                            acquired since then, the reforms introduced in the public
                            administration, and even the indications of opinion, now advise that all
                            possible facility be given to trade, modifying the orders and the
                            application of regulations little justified, and harmonizing the
                            consular tariff with the international compromises recently contracted,
                            without on this account leaving unprovided for the legitimate
                            remuneration of the guarantee which the intervention of consular agents
                            offers to commerce in its lucrative operations.</p>
                        <p>In order to prepare this work with indispensable care and attention, so
                            as to present it to the approbation of the Cortes, the undersigned
                            minister believes the nomination of a commission composed of
                            functionaries of recognized competency is necessary, which may in a
                            brief time carefully examine the points which ought to be reformed, fix
                            with clearness the articles of the tariff, with the object of preventing
                            doubtful interpretations, and draw up the project of the new consular
                            tariff, endeavoring to satisfy the legitimate aspirations of commerce
                            without impairing the interests of the state.</p>
                        <p>Founded on these reasons the undersigned minister has the honor to submit
                            to the approbation of Your Majesty the following project of decree.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName>Madrid</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-03-27">March 27,
                                1884</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>JOSÉ ELDUAYEN.</signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">royal decree.</hi></head>
                            <p>Taking into consideration the reasons exposed to me by my Minister of
                                State, in accord with the opinion of the council of ministers, I
                                decree the following: <list>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1. The nomination of a
                                        commission composed of the chiefs of the section of
                                        administration and commerce, of the ministry of state, of
                                        the directors-general of customs and of taxes (“impuestos”),
                                        of the ministry of finance, and of two officials of the
                                        consular corps, the most recent appointee performing the
                                        duties of secretary, is approved, in order to proceed to the
                                        revision of the present consular tariffs.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. The Minister of State is
                                        authorized to attach to said commission one or more
                                        merchants, or persons who may possess recognized competency
                                        in the matter, in order that they may illustrate, with their
                                        practical knowledge, the resolutions adopted.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 3. The commission will
                                        endeavor to report its work within a brief time, and will
                                        conform itself in the fulfillment of its charge to the
                                        regulations, which will be previously dictated for the
                                        arrangement of this question.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Given at the palace on <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-03-27">the 27th of March,
                                        1884</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>ALFONSO.</item>
                                        <item>The Minister of State,<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">José
                                                Elduayen.</hi></item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of State, Office of
                                        Undersecretary.</hi></p>
                                <p>In compliance with the provisions of the royal decree of the 27th
                                    March, 1884, creating a commission for the revision of the
                                    present consular tariffs, His Majesty the King (whom God guard)
                                    has been pleased to nominate on the same date, to form part of
                                    the said commission Don Jacobo Prendergast y Gordon, Don Isidore
                                    Millas, Don Placido de José y Hevia, Viscount de Campo Grande,
                                    Don Rafael Atard, Don Balbino Cortes y Morales, consul-general,
                                    pensioned, and Don Antonio Vazquez y Lopez, consul of the second
                                    class, retired, who will perform the duties of secretary.</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0590" n="490" xml:id="pg_490"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 201.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Elduayen</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-04-02"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 2,
                                1884</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have been greatly gratified to
                            notice the enlightened exposition which your excellency addressed to His
                            Catholic Majesty on the 27th ultimo and the royal decree of the same
                            date, providing for the appointment of a commission to revise the
                            existing Spanish consular tariff and to have it conform to existing
                            international compromises and the freedom of commercial intercourse with
                            other nations. I trust I am not mistaken in the conviction I entertain
                            that in the appointment of this commission your excellency had in view,
                            among other reforms, the abolition of the tonnage dues levied and
                            collected by Spanish consuls on cargoes of vessels in the ports of the
                            United States and other nations.</p>
                        <p>I need not remind your excellency of the attitude assumed by my
                            Government on this subject, but I beg to suggest that the attention of
                            said commission may be directed to the correspondence which has passed
                            between this legation and your excellency’s department, and especially
                            to the notes of this legation of January 7, 1882, July 16, 1883, and
                            January 22 of the present year. The last of these notes contains a
                            recapitulation of the views of my Government, showing that it is
                            virtually an <hi rend="italic">export</hi> to, levied and collected by
                            Spanish consuls in the ports of the United States, and that as all
                            export taxes are prohibited by the Constitution of the United States, it
                            is an exaction of duties in which it is not possible for my Government
                            to acquiesce. In view of the fact that your excellency, with a
                            commendable spirit of commercial freedom, has already agreed with me, by
                            virtue of the agreement of February 13 last, to ask the Cortes to
                            authorize the abolition of this duty so far as trade with Cuba and Porto
                            Rico is concerned, I do not doubt that it will be decided by said
                            commission to extend the abolition to the entire commerce between the
                            United States and Spain.</p>
                        <p>Confident that your excellency will submit this subject with such
                            favorable recommendation to the attention of the commission referred to
                            as will secure an entire abolition of these objectionable dues,</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.</p>
                        <closer><signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>