<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-06-07T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-06-07T15:00:00-05:00" n="110" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d110">
                        <head>110. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation to the Conference
                                on Laos</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d110fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 751J.00/6–761. Secret; Niact;
                                Limited Distribution. Also sent to Moscow and Vientiane and repeated
                                to London and Paris.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-06-07T21:00:00+01:00">June 7,
                                    1961, 9 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>Confe 144. For Secretary from <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>.</p>
                        <p>I called on <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> at 5:00
                            accompanied by <persName corresp="#p_SJM1">Steeves</persName> and
                            Crawford. I began with statement along following lines:</p>
                        <p>I had heard from our Ambassador in Vientiane of attacks that took place
                            yesterday at Padong. Heavy artillery fire occurred throughout entire day
                            as well as infantry attacks by <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>,
                            Vietnamese and <persName corresp="#p_KL1">Kong Le</persName> troops. As
                            result Col <persName corresp="#p_VP1">Vang Pao</persName> commanding RLG
                            forces withdrew from Padong to prepared positions. This constitutes most
                            ruthless attack since cease-fire declaration and press reports today
                            show world aroused by these actions of <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>
                            which can no longer be concealed. They obviously underline immediate
                            need <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> investigation.</p>
                        <pb facs="0264" n="240" xml:id="pg_240"/>
                        <p>Moreover we cannot help but hold Soviet Government responsible because of
                            its role in supplying <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> by air with
                            military supplies and equipment. In light of Vienna discussions and
                            communique I assumed <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                            will want to take action. (I read to <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> what President said on Vienna discussions re
                            Laos in his address last night.)<note n="1" xml:id="d110fn2">For text of
                                the communique issued after the meeting at Vienna, June 4, see <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current Documents,
                                    1961</hi>, p. 574. <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s address to the Nation, June 6, is ibid.,
                                pp. 574–578; for the portion on Laos, see <ref target="#pg_576">p.
                                    576</ref>.</note> I was sure <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> would have same feelings as President on
                            question since <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> had said today that Vienna
                            talks could be prelude to breakdown of cold war barriers and pledged
                            Soviet Union will do all it can to improve Soviet-American
                            relations.</p>
                        <p>I told <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> I would be grateful
                            if he would call foregoing to attention his government and expressed
                            confidence <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> would take
                            immediate action to instruct <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>
                            investigation on ground and to see to it that criminal attacks of <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> cease. I added that he of course
                            understood that effective cease-fire was prerequisite to our
                            negotiations here. However, I did not want to take a negative attitude
                            as I felt sure <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> would
                            want to take positive action.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> said he had no information
                            on recent events in Padong. However, he regarded our information as
                            one-sided. <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>’s
                            representative had recounted history of Padong and pointed out that area
                            had been fully under <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> control and
                            opposing paratroopers had been sent in by air only after cease-fire
                            established. Therefore cease-fire is two-sided matter and this was what
                            they had in mind when referring to effective cease-fire in Vienna.
                            Furthermore he could not accept my statement that Soviet Union
                            responsible. If Soviet Union responsible for anything in Laos, it was
                            for effective cease-fire established since May 3. He personally knew how
                            much effort had gone into putting stop to hostilities in face of many
                            obstacles since he had dealt directly with these problems in Foreign
                            Ministry. If US had shown same degree of patience it would have had
                            great effect. He was sure my remark that Soviet Union responsible must
                            result from misunderstanding since he was firmly convinced Soviet Union
                            was doing everything to make cease-fire effective. He stressed in this
                            regard they didn’t want Vienna communique to be “just a piece of paper”
                            but something to be put into execution. Reiterating that this was
                            two-sided question he said effective cease-fire requires end to
                            unauthorized flights over territory of <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>
                            and <persName corresp="#p_KL1">Kong Le</persName>. Otherwise bad results
                            could ensue.</p>
                        <p>I agreed this was two-way matter and this was why we were urging that
                                <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> investigate facts. There had
                            been allegations on both sides. Therefore, our joint instrument should
                            be sent to investigate. We felt that this was way to settle matter
                            between forces of <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> and RLG.</p>
                        <pb facs="0265" n="241" xml:id="pg_241"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> argued we can’t give to
                            this instrument such powers that do not flow from task which faces us.
                            Draft reply to <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> message of May
                                20<note n="2" xml:id="d110fn3">The <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> Report of May 20, calling for establishment of a
                                machinery to deal with the maintenance of the cease-fire, was <ref target="#d6">Document 6</ref> of the International Conference on
                                the Settlement of the Laotian Question. (Laos/Doc/6; Department of
                                State, L/EA Files: Lot 70 D 453)</note> is now being considered in
                            Moscow and they are “sure agreement will be reached.” As for
                            developments in Laos, these will be clearer tomorrow when two Princes
                            arrive at 3:40 p.m.</p>
                        <p>I agreed was good to have them come and said <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> was going to Nice. <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> said Princes might go to Nice too. I told him
                                <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> had agreed with <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> to abandon air supply if <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> would stop their attacks. <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> said this was good but there
                            should be no reasons for any provocative actions. I said I knew too much
                            as we had first hand information from US officers on ground that <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> had been attacking for some time.
                            Therefore <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> must go and confirm facts.
                            I was sure <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> had so
                            agreed with President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>.
                                <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> agreed to report my
                            statement.</p>
                        <p>We were told <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> due Geneva
                            about 8 p.m. Thursday, June 8.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>