<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-07-12T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-07-12T15:00:00-05:00" n="135" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d135">
                        <head>135. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation to the Conference
                                on Laos</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d135fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 751J.00/7–1261. Secret;
                                Priority. Repeated priority to London, Paris, Vientiane, and
                                Moscow.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-07-12T21:00:00+01:00">July 12,
                                    1961, 9 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_Confe1">Confe</gloss> 365. From <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>. In an informal meeting today
                            which we agreed would be considered unofficial and personal I discussed
                            with <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> conference
                            procedure. <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> remained
                            adamantly opposed to MacDonald compromise proposal<note n="1" xml:id="d135fn2">The MacDonald compromise was described in Confe 353
                                from Geneva, July 8. With the concurrence of the U.S., French,
                                Canadian, and British Delegations, MacDonald suggested to Puskin
                                either simultaneous discussion of “neutrality” and “controls” on
                                every other day or as the basis of separate committees of the whole.
                                Puskin refused to accept any departure from the Soviet-Chinese
                                procedure of discussing only neutrality. (Ibid.,
                                751.J.00/7–861)</note> but offered in answer to my arguments
                            following proposal: First, that Declaration on Neutrality and Protocol
                            on Controls, taken together, should be considered a “single entity.”
                            Second, they would be considered in order in which they appeared in both
                            currently tabled drafts, i.e., neutrality first, on understanding that
                            if there is disagreement on any provision after one day debate, this
                            provision will be set aside and discussion will proceed to next
                            provision. After discussion of neutrality on this basis, and without
                            attempting further to resolve points of disagreement, conference would
                            proceed with discussion of protocol on controls on same basis.
                            Thereafter, we would then consider how the unresolved provisions of both
                            declaration and protocol could be dealt with by the conference.
                                <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> said he had not
                            obtained approval this proposal other bloc countries. He hoped we would
                            give the matter serious consideration and felt that this compromise
                            proposal met all our objections. I told him I would study this proposal,
                            consult my government and let him know. I request urgently the
                            Department’s reaction. I recommend its acceptance in principle, and that
                            I be authorized reach detailed agreement with him and with non-Communist
                            delegations along these lines. There are a number of details which would
                            have to be satisfactorily resolved. For example, the idea of a single
                            day’s debate on provisions in dispute should probably be interpreted as
                            applicable only after we have reached an acknowledged deadlock on a
                            particular provision. It is patent that many provisions would require
                            more than a single day to negotiate. <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> agrees, of course, that discussions on general
                            subjects, such as equipment for <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>,
                            access or cease-fire can be taken up in conference any day at the
                            instance of the US or any other delegation.</p>
                        <pb facs="0320" n="296" xml:id="pg_296"/>
                        <p>I feel this compromise gives us the main points for which we were
                            pressing and in some ways is better than the British alternate day
                            proposal as all unresolved matters of both declaration and protocol
                            would be held for consideration at one time.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Martin</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>