<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>156. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Rostow) to the President’s Military Representative () to the
                    President’s Military Representative (Taylor))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d156</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">156</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-08-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-08-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="rece0CacX1xkHTAHw" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="covert-actions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139574"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Covert operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-08-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-08-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="156"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d156">
                <head>156. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="from">Rostow</persName>) to
                    the President’s Military Representative (<persName corresp="#p_TGMD1" type="to"
                        >Taylor</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d156fn1">Source:
                        National Defense University, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>
                        Papers, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, T–624–71. Secret. An unsigned file copy
                        indicates that copies of this paper were also sent to <persName
                            corresp="#p_JRH1">Robert Johnson</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis Johnson</persName>. (Kennedy Library,
                        National Security Files, Laos: General, 8/1/61–8/10/61) In a memorandum of
                        August 4, <persName corresp="#p_JRH1">Robert Johnson</persName> provided
                        comments on a draft of this paper to the effect that the pro-Western and
                        neutralist positions were so weak in Laos that it would be almost impossible
                        to prevent by diplomatic negotiations a Communist take-over. (Ibid.) A note
                        on the memorandum indicates <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>
                        “noted” it.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-08-08">August 8, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>A Split vs. A Unified Laos</item>
                </list>
                <p>As we come closer to the crisis in the Geneva negotiations about Laos it is clear
                    that on our side—and probably on the other side—there will be increasing thought
                    about a split Laos. It is evidently a situation where all the alternatives
                    involve risk; and none of the alternatives is particularly pleasant.</p>
                <pb facs="0379" n="355" xml:id="pg_355"/>
                <p>It is possible that the other side will confront us with a situation where a
                    split Laos will be the most we can hope to achieve short of fighting a war to
                    clean the Communist element out of the North.</p>
                <p>If we continue on our present course without change, it is even possible that
                    both the alternatives of a unified neutral Laos achieved by negotiation and a
                    split Laos will be denied to us and that we will be faced by the alternatives
                    either of undertaking a substantial military effort in Laos to hold the South or
                    of permitting Laos to slip away wholly to the Communists. In Geneva we seem to
                    be making no progress toward an agreement; on the ground in Laos, though
                    non-Communist forces are by no means lacking in assets, their position in the
                    north is very weak and in the south is gradually eroding away.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d156fn2">In a memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_RWW1"
                            >Rostow</persName>, August 4, <persName corresp="#p_JRH1">Robert
                            Johnson</persName> reported the views of a staff analyst responsible for
                        Southeast Asia at the Office of National Estimates of the Central
                        Intelligence Agency. It was that staffer’s personal conclusion that the
                        Pathet Lao had developed a political organization and consolidated their
                        hold on the villages in the countryside to the extent that <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>’s independent political
                        base was seriously undermined. Militarily, the Pathet Lao had the neutralist
                        forces in a squeeze. The result, according to the staffer, was that a de
                        facto partition of Laos would be very difficult. In a memorandum of August 5
                        to <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>, Johnson reported that he
                        had talked to Jenkins of <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> who confirmed this view and responded, when
                        asked by Johnson, that <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> and
                        the other negotiators at Geneva were shutting their eyes to the real
                        situation in Laos. (Both ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Thus, we face a choice as to how hard we press at the conference, in possible
                    bilateral talks with the Russians, and conceivably at the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> itself for a unified Laos with a tolerably effective <gloss
                        target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> as opposed to resigning ourselves to a split
                    and taking the action necessary to achieve one. Even if we press very hard, it
                    is by no means certain that agreement will be achieved. It may be useful,
                    therefore, to lay out dispassionately the pros and cons of a unified as opposed
                    to a split Laos.</p>
                <p>As far as a unified Laos in concerned, the most we can hope for is a unified Laos
                    with a considerable Communist element in the government, which would give
                    relatively free play to the further political development of the Pathet Lao
                    party within Laos and which would exert on the government a strong Communist
                    influence. If there were to be an <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> with
                    adequate powers, including reasonable independence of the Lao government there
                    is some hope that those political elements within Laos which are anxious to
                    maintain the independence of the country would gain strength. But as the weeks
                    go by without agreement this result is becoming increasingly difficult (and
                    perhaps impossible) to achieve; for the Pathet Lao is strengthening its
                    village-level political apparatus in all of the areas that it holds and has
                    apparently gained complete control of the <persName corresp="#p_KL1">Kong
                        Le</persName> neutralist military forces. <persName corresp="#p_SPP1"
                        >Souvanna</persName> and the neutralists may rally their forces, and if all
                    the non-Communists could make common cause the situation may not be lost. But
                    without an effective, <pb facs="0380" n="356" xml:id="pg_356"/> independent
                    international presence, it seems most unlikely under the most favorable
                    assumptions, that a neutralist Lao government could successfully resist
                    pressures from Hanoi. To simplify the problem, therefore, we should compare the
                    most favorable case we can envisage—a neutral government with a tolerably
                    effective <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> with a split Laos.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The case for a neutral unified government is as follows.</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>There will be considerable Lao and international resistance to splitting
                        another country. There will also be great resistance to taking—or
                        supporting—the paramilitary or military moves that probably will be
                        necessary to achieve a split Laos. In short, the weight of opinion in areas
                        not directly involved or responsible will bear on us to accept a political
                        settlement, even if the government and the <gloss target="#t_ICC1"
                            >ICC</gloss> controls are ambiguous.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>We would leave open the possibility that a gradual gathering of impulses
                        in Laos for independence might reduce the Communist strength in Laos,
                        notably if the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> could force the removal
                        of the Vietminh cadres from the army and protect the country from Vietminh
                        penetration. The Meos and other non-Communist military units could meanwhile
                        be a deterrent to drastic Communist action.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>A unified country would permit the U.S. to disengage from direct
                        involvement in a military-political situation that is extremely awkward and
                        to concentrate in Southeast Asia on Thailand and Viet-Nam.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The argument against a unified neutralist government may be
                        stated as follows.</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Basically the argument against a neutralist Laos with an <gloss
                            target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> is that once the American presence were
                        withdrawn, it might be very difficult, whatever the diplomatic agreement may
                        be, to prevent a subtle or progressive takeover by Communist elements. The
                        continued prolongation of the negotiations in Geneva is likely to result in
                        a further deterioration of the already very weak position of the
                        non-Communists in North and Central Laos and to erode further their position
                        in the South. As a consequence, the non-Communist base from which the
                        non-military struggle in a unified Laos is resumed is likely to be quite
                        weak.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>We do not know how successful the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>
                        would be in protecting Lao-Viet-Nam and Lao-Thai borders, but, in view of
                        the inherent difficulties involved, we should not be too optimistic.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The argument for a split is that:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>As a practical matter, short of U.S. military intervention in Laos, it
                            is the most we can hope to achieve. Even in a supposedly unified neutral
                            Laos, the Communists will control the North.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>It would provide a political base on which Thai and Vietnamese troops
                            could be introduced into Southern Laos and would provide the <pb
                                facs="0381" n="357" xml:id="pg_357"/> possibility of a continued
                            American military presence in the strategic southern part of the
                            country.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>It would give us time to build a more effective Laos government in the
                            South than we now have.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>It would put friendly forces along the Laos-Viet-Nam and along a part
                            of the Thai border, south of the seventeenth parallel. Holding southern
                            Laos may be the minimum condition necessary to keeping Thailand and
                            South Viet-Nam non-Communist.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The argument against a split is that:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Under present circumstances it would be difficult, and might be
                            impossible, to achieve an effective split without some U.S. military
                            involvement. At a minimum, such involvement would be likely to entail a
                            commitment to send U.S. troops into the South if effective control of
                            that area cannot be achieved by the <gloss target="#t_FAL1">FAL</gloss>
                            with the support of the Vietnamese and the Thai.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>It would virtually guarantee an extension of full-scale Vietminh
                            control down to the southern border of northern Laos.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>It is uncertain whether infiltration could be effectively checked from
                            northern into southern Laos and thence into Viet-Nam. A split would also
                            leave a long section of the Thai border quite open to infiltration. (For
                            this reason the Thai would probably be unenthusiastic about providing
                            military support to an operation designed only to secure southern
                            Laos.)</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Political and military viability of a southern Laos government under
                                <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> is questionable.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Interim Conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—It is too soon to decide. We are committed to accept a neutral unified
                        Laos if a tolerable <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> is created. The
                        first job is to see what kind of deal is possible on the Lao government and
                        the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>.</item>
                    <item>—If we get a tolerable settlement our job is to maximize the chance that
                        we get its advantages and minimize the chance that it fails. Contingency
                        planning to this end should be begun, including the following: how all the
                        non-Communists could be brought closer together; how aid could be used to
                        strengthen their hand; what covert operations we would envisage, including
                        role of Meos; how the Viet-Nam and Thai borders could be protected against
                        the weaknesses of the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>; how more vigorous
                        non-Communist political figures could be sought out and developed,
                        etc.</item>
                    <item>—If a split emerges—or turns out to be our best option—we must plan not
                        only military measures to clean out the panhandle, but also political
                        measures to make a southern government more effective in maintaining links
                        of sympathy and support with its people.</item>
                    <pb facs="0382" n="358" xml:id="pg_358"/>
                    <item>—In any case it is clear that, if we are to hold Southeast Asia, it must
                        be held via Viet-Nam and Thailand. Laos will remain a can of worms.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
