<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-09-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="177" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d177">
                        <head>177. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of
                            State (<persName corresp="#p_BLD1" type="from">Battle</persName>) to the
                            President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG1" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d177fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, National
                                Security Files, Countries Series, Laos: General, 9/61. Secret. No
                                drafting information appears on the source text.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-09-08">September 8,
                                    1961</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Weekly Summary, Geneva Conference, August 28–September 3,
                                1961</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><p>In the face of Souvanna’s unsatisfactory response to Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_FPL1">Falaize</persName> on August 27,
                                    we decided it was imperative that we ourselves frankly discuss
                                    with the Prince the conditions he must be prepared to fulfill to
                                    warrant our support of a national union government under his
                                        leadership.<note n="1" xml:id="d177fn2">Instructions for
                                            <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s
                                        discussions with <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> are in telegram 1094 to London,
                                        August 31. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                        751J.00/8–228)</note> Therefore, despite expressed
                                    misgivings of the French and British, we have asked <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> to meet with
                                    Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BWG1">Brown</persName> in Paris, or
                                    secondarily in Phnom Penh. No reply has thus far been received.
                                    Over the weekend, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> engaged in talks with the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Government on all aspects of the
                                    Lao problem and returns to Geneva this week.<note n="2" xml:id="d177fn3">Instructions for <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s discussions with
                                        the British in London are in telegram 1093 to London, August
                                        31. (Ibid.) An account of <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s discussions in London, September
                                        3, are in telegram 956 from London, September 5. (Ibid.,
                                        751J.00/9–561)</note> In the meantime, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Addis</persName> is also seeking a
                                    rendezvous with <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName>
                                    at Phnom Penh, but has indicated he will go to Xieng Khouang if
                                    necessary.</p>
                                <p>We have instructed our Ambassadors in Bangkok and Saigon to set
                                    forth to <persName corresp="#p_STM1">Sarit</persName> and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_Diem1">Diem</persName> respectively
                                    our purpose in approaching <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> and the steps we are taking to bolster
                                    the RLG’s military posture.<note n="3" xml:id="d177fn4">In
                                        telegram 283 to Bangkok, sent also to Saigon as 269,
                                        September 2. (Ibid., 751J.00/9–261)</note> In addition, Mr.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> is consulting
                                    with the representatives of the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> powers on contingency plans in the event that
                                    all efforts at a peaceful settlement fail and the Communists
                                    renew the offensive. These plans essentially call for an
                                    extension of <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Plan 5,
                                    i.e., military operations to clear Southern Laos of Pathet Lao
                                    elements.</p></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><p>At Geneva, the majority of the draft texts pertaining to the
                                    powers of the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> have been
                                    debated and either sent to the Drafting Committee or held in
                                    suspense. The remaining items may require one more week of
                                    discussion.</p>
                                <p>Since no united Lao government can now be expected before the
                                    negotiating phase begins, the Conference may well reach a
                                    stalemate. In <pb facs="0432" n="408" xml:id="pg_408"/> that
                                    event, rather than risk a definite breakdown, we would prefer a
                                    recess so that the negotiating channels may remain open. The
                                    atmosphere at Geneva, however, is now considerably less
                                    optimistic than it had recently been, partly as a result of the
                                    Soviet posture on Berlin and resumption of nuclear testing,<note n="4" xml:id="d177fn5">On August 30, the Soviet Union
                                        announced that because of the aggressiveness of the United
                                        States and NATO, especially over Germany, it was resuming
                                        atmospheric nuclear tests notwithstanding their harmful
                                        effects. Text of the statement is in Documents on
                                        Disarmament, 1961, pp. 337–348.</note> partly because of the
                                    danger of renewed hostilities in Laos with the forthcoming
                                    advent of the dry season.</p></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BLD1">L.D. Battle</persName><note n="5" xml:id="d177fn6">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                                    signature. Melvin S. Manfull signed for <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Battle</persName>.</note>
                            </signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>