<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-09-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="182" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                        <head>182. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of
                            State (<persName corresp="#p_BLD1" type="from">Battle</persName>) to the
                            President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG1" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d182fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, National
                                Security Files, Countries Series, Laos: General, 9/61. Secret. No
                                drafting information appears on the source text.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-09-15">September 15,
                                    1961</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Weekly Summary, Geneva Conference September 4–11, 1961</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><p>Souvanna Phouma responded on September 6 to our invitation to
                                    meet with Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BWG1">Brown</persName> by offering several alternatives. Plans
                                    are now set for them to meet at Rangoon on September 15, and the
                                    British are making a plane available to Souvanna. The Burmese
                                    Government has reacted favorably to serving as the host country
                                    and, while Marshal <persName corresp="#p_CLGMS1">Sarit</persName>, President <persName corresp="#p_Diem1">Diem</persName>, and General <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> have doubts as to any fruitful outcome of
                                    such an encounter, they appreciate the motivation underlying
                                    this approach. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_STM1">Sarit</persName> are informed of
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s plans to
                                    see them after his talks with Souvanna; he may also stop in New
                                    Delhi for discussions on Laos with the Indian Government and
                                    possibly return to Geneva via Washington.</p>
                                <p>Under instructions from his government, British Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Addis</persName> saw <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> in Xieng Khouang
                                    September 11, but we have not yet heard the details of their
                                        conversation.<note n="1" xml:id="d182fn2">The results were
                                        reported in telegram 444 from Vientiane and commented on in
                                        telegram 445 from Vientiane, both September 12. In telegram
                                        445, <persName corresp="#p_BWG1">Brown</persName> commented
                                        that the <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Addis</persName>-Souvanna conversation revealed that
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> was
                                        still reluctant to accept the fact that he needed strong
                                        moderate candidates in the center group to contain the
                                        Pathet Lao. To persuade him otherwise would be one of
                                            <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>’s “most
                                        important and delicate tasks.” (Both Department of State,
                                        Central Files, 751J.00/9–1261)</note> We know, however, that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Addis</persName>
                                    <pb facs="0440" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> was to stress the same
                                    points of the August 7 Paris Agreement, which Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> will raise
                                    this weekend with the Prince, i.e., the need for a strong center
                                    group in any government of national union, an <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> endowed with adequate
                                    authority, a formula agreed to in advance by the three factions
                                    for the integration of the Pathet Lao forces into a new national
                                    army. (According to Indian Ambassador Ratnam there is some
                                    indication that <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName>
                                    is already prepared to include some of the Vientiane moderates
                                    in his Cabinet should he become Prime Minister.)</p></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The French and British governments have voiced concern that our
                                contingency planning for Laos may encourage <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> to rely on a military
                                solution rather than on a negotiated settlement and may also
                                adversely affect the attitude of the Communist bloc with respect to
                                the Geneva Conference.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>There has been a definite slow down at Ban Namone and <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> has stated that he intends to
                                take a harder position in those negotiations.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>At Geneva only three restricted sessions were held last week and
                                discussions on <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> terms of
                                reference all ended in disagreement with belligerent statements made
                                by bloc representatives, especially by the Chinese. Consultations
                                among the Free World delegates and subsequently between <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, MacDonald and <persName corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> resulted in a decision to
                                string out the Conference by holding only two restricted sessions
                                each week supplemented by smaller group discussions on the more
                                thorny <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> issues, which might thus
                                more easily be resolved and then submitted to the restricted session
                                for approval. This group would include the U.S., <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> representatives, plus others, in particular the
                                Chinese, depending on the topics under debate.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BLD1">L.D. Battle</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d182fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                                    signature.</note>
                            </signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>