<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>286. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-01-02T11:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-12-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec0tfPbYHg7imwab" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067175"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Intelligence community</term>
                    <term ref="recyb5QQsNI4WeVPs" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military capabilities</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-02T11:15:00-05:00" n="286" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d286">
                <head>286. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On January 31, 1962, the intelligence community released <gloss target="#t_SNIE1"
                        >SNIE</gloss> 58/1–62, “Relative Military Capabilities of Opposing Forces in
                    Laos.” The estimate summarized <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> 58–62; see
                        <ref target="#d268">Document 268</ref>. It then described recent military
                    clashes between <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> and anti-government forces
                    in which <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> was forced to retreat every time.
                    The <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> stated that although its estimate of
                    actual numbers was inconclusive, North Vietnamese cadres and combat troops
                    played an important part in these operations. The estimate continued: <list>
                        <item>“3. We now estimate that there are about 9,000 North Vietnamese troops
                            in Laos (6,000 combat; 3,000 cadre and support) as compared with about
                            5,000 estimated in <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> 58–62. Two
                            battalions of North Vietnamese (as many as 1,000 men) may have entered
                            Laos in recent weeks; the balance is attributable to a reassessment of
                            indications previously available, and to new evidence. Our estimates of
                            the numbers of North Vietnamese in Laos are highly tenuous because of
                            the various possible interpretations of the available evidence.
                            Moreover, the numbers may change quickly; the North Vietnamese are well
                            organized and prepared to move units easily to and fro across the
                            Laotian-North Vietnamese border.</item>
                        <item>“4. The performance of <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> units in
                            recent skirmishes was not as unsatisfactory as it generally was
                            immediately before the cease-fire. It is clear, however, that problems
                            of morale and leadership are still critical. We now believe it was too
                            optimistic to estimate in <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> 58–62
                            ‘that the government forces would have a slight edge if fighting were
                            resumed on a pattern comparable to that prior to the cease-fire but
                            intensified as a consequence of the strengthening of both sides over the
                            past several months.’ In particular, we believe that the <gloss
                                target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> is unable to deal with any substantial
                            number of North Vietnamese forces, whom they greatly fear. The
                            Communists are able to bring these forces into play where they wish or
                            need to do so.</item>
                        <item>“5. Although outnumbered by the Lao armed forces, the antigovernment
                            forces now in Laos have a superiority in artillery and armor. They are
                            generally capable of maintaining their main forward positions and of
                            conducting local operations to counter aggressive actions by the
                            government forces. Without further external reinforcements, they could,
                            by concentrating their forces, seize and hold certain key positions now
                            held by government troops. If reinforced by additional combat units from
                            North Vietnam, they could quickly overrun the remainder of Laos.”
                            (Kennedy Library, National Security Files, Countries Series, Laos:
                            General, 1/1/62–1/15/62; full text in <hi rend="italic">Declassified
                                Documents, 1978</hi>, 16D)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
