<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>3. Memorandum of Discussion at the 473d Meeting of the National Security
                    Council</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-01-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recuSPZDcCd8RkSsx" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002736"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Aircraft carrier</term>
                    <term ref="recJwYAJf2vdRiALq" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039539"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Mobility</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="reciuru9i20NCuS5s" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recu0jAoErrAESV42" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002775"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Airlift</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-01-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="3"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d3">
                <head>3. Memorandum of Discussion at the 473d Meeting of the National Security
                        Council<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d3fn1">Source: Eisenhower Library,
                        Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records. Top Secret; Eyes
                        Only. Drafted by Boggs on January 5.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-01-05">January 5, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follow a paragraph listing the participants and items 1–2. The following
                    discussion is taken from item 3, “Significant World Developments Affecting U.S.
                    Security.”]</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> reported that there was little
                    change in the military situation in Laos. The pro-Communist forces claim that
                    they still hold Xieng Khouang and that near Paksane they have cut the road
                    running south <pb facs="0031" n="7" xml:id="pg_7"/> and east of Vientiane.
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> said the <persName
                        corresp="#p_BOP1">Boun Oum</persName> government had been legalized by the
                    Laotian Parliament by a vote of 41 to 0 with only eleven abstentions. In reply
                    to a question by the President, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> said that no reaction to this development had been
                    received from India.</p>
                <p>[Here follow the remainder of item 3 and item 4. The following discussion is
                    taken from item 5, “Possible Deficiencies in the U.S. Posture for Limited
                    Military Operations.”]</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">General Lemnitzer</persName> then summarized the
                        <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> comments on Southeast Asia. Limited
                    operations there, he said, were handicapped by logistical limitations stemming
                    from lack of communications, lack of transportation, and lack of port and
                    terminal facilities. Furthermore, the existing facilities were extremely
                    vulnerable to disruption and are inadequate to support sustained operations.
                    These limitations, however, have been offset to some degree by countermeasures.
                    The Pacific Command has recently been augmented by an airborne battle group and
                    an aircraft carrier. Equipment has been pre-stocked in the Pacific area.
                    Periodic mobility training exercises are planned. The Air Force modernization
                    program will improve our limited war capability in the Pacific. We now have
                    authority for overflights in the Pacific area. Other corrective action which is,
                    or could be, taken will enable us to use additional bases and improve strategic
                    signal communications and strengthen over-the-beach supply methods.</p>
                <p>In concluding, <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">General Lemnitzer</persName> said
                    that most of the problems adverted to in the limited war study were not
                        new.<note n="1" xml:id="d3fn2">The study referred to was a <gloss
                            target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> report entitled “Possible Deficiencies in
                        U.S. Posture for Limited Military Operations,” dated December 28 and
                        transmitted to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> on December 30, 1960.
                        (Eisenhower Library, Records of the Office of the President’s Assistant for
                        National Security Affairs) This report was an outgrowth of an earlier study,
                        “U.S. and Allied Capabilities for Limited Military Operations,” September
                        28, 1960. (Ibid.) For texts, see <ref target="frus1958-60v03#d134">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1958–1960, vol. III, Documents
                            134</ref> and <ref target="frus1958-60v03#d121">121</ref>.</note>
                    Additional funding would alleviate many of the deficiencies pointed out in the
                    study but in the light of total requirements, not all of the deficiencies could
                    be remedied at once.</p>
                <p>The President said this was the kind of report he could understand. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> said the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> report was very encouraging, especially as
                    regards airlift. However, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> felt he must take exception to Paragraph 9 on Page 6 of
                    the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> report. This paragraph indicated that
                    indecision and lack of clear-cut policies could contribute to starting a
                    conflict we desired to avoid and then went on to say “a pertinent example is the
                    recent conflict of judgment between the Department of Defense and the Department
                    of State concerning the proper implementation of U.S. policy in Laos.” <persName
                        corresp="#p_LGLL1">General Lemnitzer</persName> said this <pb facs="0032"
                        n="8" xml:id="pg_8"/> paragraph appeared in the <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                        >JCS</gloss> report because the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> thought
                    that last August when <persName corresp="#p_KL1">Kong Le</persName> rebelled,
                    the U.S. should have built up the <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                    forces. At that time the State Department embarked on a course of building up
                        <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>. This issue was not
                    settled and as a result <persName corresp="#p_KL1">Kong Le</persName> had
                    several months in which to build up his forces. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> replied that the Phouma government
                    became the recognized government of Laos and therefore the government with which
                    the U.S. had to deal. Moreover, our allies supported <persName corresp="#p_SPP1"
                        >Souvanna Phouma</persName> and were opposed to <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                        >Phoumi</persName>. We had been successful in continuing military assistance
                    to <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> even when he was a rebel against
                    the recognized government. Moreover, we had worked constantly to shift power
                    from <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> to <persName
                        corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> and had finally succeeded. If the U.S.
                    had armed <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> last August, it would
                    have been arming rebels against the recognized government.</p>
                <p>The President said the word “indecision” must be eliminated from the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> report. No agency of the government had the
                    right to say that another agency was indecisive and did not know what it was
                    doing. It was proper to say that the problems were such that decisions could not
                    be made immediately but dereliction of duty should not be imputed to another
                    agency. The President said that even now we did not know what we could do about
                    Laos because of the attitude of our allies. The Joint Chiefs of Staff were
                    correct from the military point of view in stating that it was better to use
                    small forces promptly than to use larger forces later but the question of when
                    small forces can be used involved a political judgment.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">General Lemnitzer</persName> said the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> had experienced for some time a feeling of
                    frustration about Laos. The President asked to whom the <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                        >JCS</gloss> report was made. Secretary Gates said the report was made to
                    him and would be a part of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files. The
                    President said the criticism in the report of another government department must
                    be removed.</p>
                <p>[Here follows the remainder of item 5, a more general discussion of U.S. limited
                    warfare capabilities.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Marion W. Boggs</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
