<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>304. Telegram From Vientiane to to Washington</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d304</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">304</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recoco7SW1Tkt0mwM" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007735"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sports</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="304"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d304">
                <head>304. Telegram From <gloss type="from">Vientiane</gloss> to <gloss type="to"
                        >Washington</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d304fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, National
                        Security Files, Countries Series, Laos: General, 3/62. Secret. A note by
                            <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> on the covering memorandum
                        from <persName corresp="#p_HR1">Richard Helms</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> indicated that the President saw this
                        telegram.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Vientiane</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-03-06">March 6, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">2½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>] We found
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> in much better physical
                        condition and apparently ready to come back to work March 7, and we informed
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> to his satisfaction of the
                        welfare of his children.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>We told <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> that we had heard
                        that both <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_SP1">Souphanouvong</persName> had rejected the
                        idea of a government of the King’s Council and how it was apparently at
                        present an untenable position. However, before <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> made up his mind we would like him to have a clear
                        picture of U.S. policy.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                        delivered President’s message transmitted on 23 February<note n="1"
                            xml:id="d304fn2">Apparent reference to <ref target="#d298">Document
                                298</ref>.</note> prefacing it with short statement that President
                        most anxious <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> play useful role
                        in new govt [<hi rend="italic">2½ lines of source text not
                        declassified</hi>] added that not only was U.S. not prepared to support
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> militarily in the event he
                        refused to participate in coalition govt or negotiations collapsed as result
                        his unwillingness to enter into such a govt, but that it now further clear
                        that U.S. Govt also determined not come to his assistance militarily even in
                        event other side attacked, whether as result Russian inability any longer
                        control <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> and <pb facs="0669" n="645"
                            xml:id="pg_645"/> VM, or as result other side’s impatience with slow
                        progress of negotiations, etc. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                        appeared listen intently, then said this exactly what <persName
                            corresp="#p_FAHD1">Admiral Felt</persName> had just told him a few
                        minutes earlier.<note n="2" xml:id="d304fn3">See <ref target="#d305"
                                >Document 305</ref>.</note> (Portion garbled) that the only solution
                        would be a <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> coalition
                        government. At the very start we wanted to impress on <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> that in any coalition govt the U.S.
                        was very desirous of his participation. We realized, however, that in a
                            <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> coalition
                        government he could not have the Ministries of Defense or Interior. However,
                        whatever position he could get, we wanted him to know that we realized that
                        it would be very difficult for him to operate because Souvanna, being Prime
                        Minister, would control a great deal of his finances. For example, if
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> could get Ministries of
                        Information and Youth and Sports, keep the Secretary Generalship of the
                        Veterans Association, and Leuam could have the Ministry of Education, there
                        would be then great possibilities in these positions for useful work, and we
                        were prepared under such circumstances to make available funds to support
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> in his undertakings to
                        strengthen anti-Communist elements and support his supporters. We strongly
                        urged <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> to consider this because,
                        as far as we could see, this is about the only way out.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                        then reinforced above by saying to <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> that [<hi rend="italic">5½ lines of source text not
                            declassified</hi>] <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> should
                        realize that the U.S. holds him largely responsible for the failure to
                        establish a <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> coalition
                        government. Also the U.S. believes, rightly or wrongly, that the untenable
                        and dangerous position in Laos today is due in large part to Phoumi’s
                        actions. As <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> has been told in
                        the past, the U.S. will not support him if he initiates military attack.
                        Phoumi, we believe, already understands this position. Recently there has
                        been a further clarification of policy which <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> must understand, namely, that if the Soviets are
                        unable to hold back the Pathet Lao from attacking, the U.S. will not, even
                        under these circumstances, come to the support of Phoumi.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Phoumi was told that the U.S., and indeed world opinion, demands a
                        peaceful solution to the Lao crisis and, in the opinion of the majority, the
                        only peaceful solution is a <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName>
                        coalition govt. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> was told that
                        in our honest opinion the only way out was for <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> to accept a position of importance in the new govt.
                        We repeated that we wanted <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> to
                        continue to head anti-Communist elements and we were ready to make funds
                        available to support him in this work. We urged <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> to give this his deepest consideration. It was of the
                        utmost importance to him and his country, and we believed for the U.S. <pb
                            facs="0670" n="646" xml:id="pg_646"/> also, that he continue to be one
                        of the leaders of Laos. We could not urge him too strongly to give us an
                        affirmative answer.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Phoumi then again said that <persName corresp="#p_FAHD1">Admiral
                            Felt</persName> had earlier in the morning delivered a message from the
                        President which was similar [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source
                            text not declassified</hi>]. <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> said that he wanted to tell us the same things he had
                        told <persName corresp="#p_FAHD1">Admiral Felt</persName>. It would be very
                        “difficult” to accept <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>
                        as a leader. The biggest error the U.S. had made was to put so much
                        confidence in the word of Souvanna. <persName corresp="#p_SPP1"
                            >Souvanna</persName> is not the leader, the strong man, that the U.S.
                        believes him to be. He is no more than the front man for <persName
                            corresp="#p_SP1">Souphanouvong</persName> and the <gloss target="#t_PL1"
                            >PL</gloss>, just like <persName corresp="#p_BOP1">Boun Oum</persName>
                        is the front man for Phoumi.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Phoumi said he spent three hours with Marshal <persName corresp="#p_STM1"
                            >Sarit</persName> March 4 discussing the Lao problem. <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> said that a great deal of their
                        conversation was on the Thai radio broadcast morning of 6 (we had not yet
                        seen the transcript of this broadcast as of time this conversation with
                        Phoumi). <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> went on to say that
                            <persName corresp="#p_STM1">Sarit</persName> had agreed to try to
                        persuade the U.S. to see the errors of its ways in putting so much
                        confidence in <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> before it was
                        too late.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Phoumi did say, however, that if he could have Ministry of Defense which
                        would assure him of army support he would enter a <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> coalition govt, but without
                        army support he would have no power and would be reduced to nothing. When we
                        said that logically the command structure of the army would remain intact
                        until integration took place, <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                        replied that this was American logic, not Lao. <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> then asked, “What would happen to us if <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> as Prime Minister and Minister of
                        Defense released General Amkha from prison and made him Commander in Chief?”
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> went on to say the U.S. did
                        not understand the realities of internal Lao politics.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>When we referred to the hard times in the past when difficult decisions
                        had to be made, especially during Savannakhet days, <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> said that at the time <persName
                            corresp="#p_KL1">Kong Le</persName> had control of only Vientiane and
                        that was easy to get back because he knew where his enemy was. Now, if
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> gives in, it would be
                        complete capitulation, and the enemy would be everywhere, even behind his
                        back. It would be giving all Laos to the enemy and there would be no way of
                        getting it back later.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Phoumi also said that he would no longer have control of the army because
                        whoever pays, controls, and it would be <persName corresp="#p_SPP1"
                            >Souvanna</persName> who paid. When asked if he did not think that the
                        post of Minister of Finance, in this case might prove powerful enough,
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> replied that it was
                        completely unacceptable and no good. At this point referring to the Ministry
                        of Information, <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> remarked that
                        most of trained propagandists and organizers are Pathet Lao, and we would
                        not have time to organize his own men.</item>
                    <pb facs="0671" n="647" xml:id="pg_647"/>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Phoumi said that he is now stronger than the other side and that with just
                        a little more backing he could win. <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> was told that this was one of the major differences
                        of opinion and that the U.S. did not believe <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> was stronger now and consequently a solution must
                        come in the shortest possible time. <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> said that he realized that without U.S. support he
                        could not go on and that the U.S. should realize that by withholding support
                        from him they are only playing the Communist game.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>Again we urged <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> to consider
                        our proposition because the alternative would only mean the U.S. completely
                        withdrawing its support which would have disastrous results. <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> said that if he went to a Cabinet
                        meeting and asked his fellow ministers to go along with this, they and even
                        the King would laugh at him, and accuse him of being the slave of the
                        Americans. At this point we asked if it would help any for us to talk to
                        other members of the Cabinet. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                        said, “perhaps—do it if you want to.”</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>Phoumi went back to the King’s Council concept and asked if the U.S. would
                        support it. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> was reminded that
                        he had been told in the past that the U.S. would support it if all parties
                        concerned agreed, but now <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_SP1">Souphanouvong</persName> had rejected this
                        concept and it must be considered a closed subject. <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> argued for time. It is only a
                        question of time and he could convince the others of the merits of a
                        government by King’s Council. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                        was told that time was of the essence and that we cannot wait. <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> pointed out that patience is a virtue
                        and should be practiced.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>Phoumi said that he would be willing to work with <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> but he is now an enemy and that
                        before <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> could work with him
                            <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> must prove himself.
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> said he is convinced he
                        could win over <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> and his
                        supporters to Phoumi’s side. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                        again mentioned the fundamental error in U.S. judgment in having too much
                        confidence in <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>Before leaving we again urged <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName>
                        to think over the advantages of going into a <persName corresp="#p_SPP1"
                            >Souvanna Phouma</persName> government and thereby gaining our financial
                        support. We asked <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> to keep this
                        strictly to himself, adding however, that if he wished to mention it to
                            <persName corresp="#p_STM1">Marshal Sarit</persName>, we would have no
                        objections. <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> said he would talk
                        to <persName corresp="#p_STM1">Sarit</persName> but not about our support.
                            <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> took us to the door and
                        said that maybe we should try this on someone else. “I don’t think I can go
                        along with a <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>
                        government and I may retire to Thailand.” <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> was urged to give utmost consideration to our talks.
                        We said that after his return to Vientiane, we would ask him for his answer.
                        If necessary we would talk later about retiring.</item>
                    <pb facs="0672" n="648" xml:id="pg_648"/>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>Comments: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>During the whole conversation <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                                    >Phoumi</persName> seemed somewhat subdued, but was courteous
                                and friendly.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>The only indication that the above conversation, or perhaps
                                    <persName corresp="#p_FAHD1">Admiral Felt</persName>’s earlier
                                conversation, had made any impression on <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                                    >Phoumi</persName> was his frequent reference to the very
                                difficult or severe predicament in which he found himself, his
                                recurrent observation that the American position is very difficult
                                to understand, and finally, his reference to possible retirement.
                                However, [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>] for what it may be worth, [<hi rend="italic"
                                    >1½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>] <persName
                                    corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> rarely accepts any suggestion
                                the first time.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>We will make approach to <persName corresp="#p_BOP1">Boun Oum</persName>,
                        along already approved lines, 7 Mar.<note n="3" xml:id="d304fn4">[<hi
                                rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] another message, March 7,
                                [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] reported that [<hi
                                rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] <persName
                                corresp="#p_BOP1">Boun Oum</persName> was briefed on the discussion
                            with <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> and was given advice
                            similar to that offered Phoumi. <persName corresp="#p_BOP1">Boun
                                Oum</persName> was also given a promise for financial help for
                            anti-Communist activities after he joined the coalition. [<hi
                                rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] a special appeal was made
                            to the Prince as a “leading Lao personality” to bring about a peaceful
                            solution to the Lao crisis. <persName corresp="#p_BOP1">Boun
                                Oum</persName> promised to try to convince <persName
                                corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> to follow American advice.
                            (Kennedy Library, National Security Files, Countries Series, Laos:
                            General, 3/62)</note> We were unable see him evening 6 Mar.</item>
                    <label>18.</label>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BWG1">Brown</persName> has seen this
                        msg.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
