<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-06-12T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-06-12T11:00:00-05:00" n="396" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d396">
                        <head>396. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d396fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                751J.00/6–1262. Top Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> on June 12 and approved in <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss> on June 26. The meeting was held in the
                                Secretary’s conference room. The Secretary left at 12:50 p.m. for
                                the White House for lunch with the President of Panama. (Johnson
                                Library, <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> Appointment
                                Book)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1962-06-12T12:00:00-04:00">June 12, 1962,
                                noon</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Contingency Planning for Laos</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">For State</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName>Bell</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>
                                        (G)</item>
                                    <item>Gov. <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">For <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss></hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Gen. <persName corresp="#p_CLGMS1">Carter</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CCL1">Cooper</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">For White House</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bowles</persName></item>
                                    <item>Gen. <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName>Forrestal</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">For Defense</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Gilpatric</persName></item>
                                    <item>Adm. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName></item>
                                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName></item>
                                    <item>Gen. <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName></item>
                                    <item>Adm. <persName>Heinz</persName></item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_FBGP1">Gen.
                                        Fontana</persName></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Secretary opened the meeting by noting that the recent agreement on
                            the formation of a government of national union in Laos had changed the
                            politics of the situation in that country.<note n="1" xml:id="d396fn2"><persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>’s Naval Aide
                                    <persName corresp="#p_Bagley1">Bagley</persName>, who is not
                                listed as a participant but apparently accompanied <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>, wrote an account of this
                                meeting. He stated that <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>
                                and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> met privately
                                in <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s office prior to the
                                meeting. At the outset, <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>
                                announced that there were two political objectives in Southeast
                                Asia: a stable situation in Laos conducive to negotiations and U.S.
                                action to provide psychological evidence that the United States
                                intended to draw the line against Communist aggression. (Memorandum
                                for the record by <persName corresp="#p_Bagley1">Bagley</persName>,
                                June 12; National Defense University, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> Papers, <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>
                                National Planning, T–019–69)</note> Therefore, the political side of
                            the contingency planning for Laos would probably have to undergo some
                            changes. However, these factors did not appear to alter the military
                            shape of the problem and it seemed reasonable that military contingency
                            planning should proceed on the same basis as previously
                            contemplated.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary felt there was some difference between State and Defense
                            concerning one aspect of the planning which had been done to date. The
                            State Department placed considerable emphasis on the need to hold the
                            Mekong River Valley. Such an objective was important not <pb facs="0867" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/> only to support the political settlement
                            in Laos, but particularly to be consistent with our obligations in the
                            rest of Southeast Asia. It was especially important to the Thai that the
                            U.S. contemplate its defense of Thailand east of the Mekong rather than
                            upon Thai soil.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that the
                            Joint Chiefs of Staff and the Defense Department shared the Department
                            of State’s concern for the retention of the Mekong River Valley, but
                            felt it was unwise militarily to introduce U.S. forces for the sole
                            purpose of occupying that valley. They thought such forces might find
                            themselves immobilized in the valley and unable to control the movement
                            of enemy personnel and equipment infiltrating into South Viet-Nam
                            through the unoccupied portions of Laos. Despite this feeling, however,
                            the Defense Department was prepared to go ahead with contingency
                            planning which would take into account the sort of military and
                            political objective which the State Department contemplated with respect
                            to the Mekong River Valley. Having such planning in hand would be
                            helpful to the President if and when he had to make a decision. However,
                            there appears to be no need to request the President to make a decision
                            at this stage.</p>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said there was
                            a decision which he would like to have made, affecting the lead time
                            involved in any of these contingency plans for Laos. He felt strongly
                            that it was necessary to build up logistical capabilities in Thailand
                            which would reduce the lead time problem. He had in mind POL facilities,
                            pipelines, railway equipment and other improvements which would assist
                            the logistical base. He thought that a military construction battalion
                            and a pipeline company could be assigned to Thailand to install some of
                            this infra-structure. The costs would run somewhere upward of
                            $25,000,000 to carry out the projects that he had in mind. He could
                            finance $20,000,000 of it from 1962 contingency reserves and needed a
                            decision rapidly to be able to put such a program into effect. He felt
                            it would be effective in three areas: (a) support for contingent
                            military operations in Laos, (b) support for the defense of Thailand
                            itself and (c) the economic development of northeast Thailand.</p>
                        <p>In response to questions from the Secretary and from Governor <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that the program he had
                            in mind could be termed “civic action” or “economic aid” if that made it
                            politically more palatable. None of the funds involved would be taken
                            away from any other projects or problems in Southeast Asia. The
                            personnel involved would not be drawn from current reserves assigned to
                            Southeast Asia, but would be additional to those reserves.</p>
                        <p>There then followed considerable discussion about the immediate future in
                            Laos, the political risks involved, the prospects for <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>’s role, the behavior of
                            the Viet Minh and the Pathet Lao, and the integration of Laotian
                            military forces. Additionally, the form and nature <pb facs="0868" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/> of U.S. aid was touched upon as well as
                            the responsibilities which the French would be assuming in this new
                                period.<note n="2" xml:id="d396fn3">At this point, <persName corresp="#p_Bagley1">Bagley</persName> recorded a discussion of
                                the desirability of making a prompt $3 million payment to <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> in response to his positive
                                and cooperative attitude. When the present RLG resigned, payments
                                would be switched to the <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> government. <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> also announced his intention to use his
                                forthcoming visit to France to remind the French of their
                                responsibility to support <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> and assure his neutralism.</note></p>
                        <p>The Secretary then returned to a discussion of the contingency planning
                            currently being studied with respect to Laos. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that the military were
                            working on four plans: (1) air strikes in response to a Communist
                            rupture of the cease-fire, (2) an occupation of the Mekong River Valley
                            which would not advance beyond that point but which would have a back-up
                            capacity in Thailand to do so, (3) an occupation of the Mekong River
                            Valley and an advance to take over the rest of the panhandle, and (4) an
                            occupation with an advance to take over a lesser portion of the
                            panhandle.</p>
                        <p>In response to a question, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that the Defense Department was not
                            currently pursuing the plan for an amphibious operation at Vinh.</p>
                        <p>The meeting then turned to a discussion of the role which the <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> would play during the interim period
                            before integration of the Lao forces and particularly the attitude of
                            the U.S. Government and especially <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>
                            toward the <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss>.<note n="3" xml:id="d396fn4"><persName corresp="#p_Bagley1">Bagley</persName>
                                quoted <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> as inquiring
                                as to plans to maintain the readiness of <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> and it was agreed it should be supported at its
                                current levels up to the point of integration. As for support after
                                integration and <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> equipment
                                stocks, the consensus was that the issue should be reviewed by
                                Defense. <persName corresp="#p_Bagley1">Bagley</persName> also
                                recorded an understanding that the United States should seek an
                                agreement with <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> for
                                support of a new national army when it was formed.</note> This
                            discussion touched on the role of the Meo tribesmen in relation to the
                                <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss> and on the attitude of <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> toward the <gloss target="#t_FAR1">FAR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>In closing, the meeting discussed the possibility of limited bilateral
                            discussions with the British concerning contingency planning. It was
                            agreed that these could be continued in much the same frame-work as they
                            had previously been conducted. It was decided, however, that no
                            discussion should be had with other <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> members at this stage.<note n="4" xml:id="d396fn5">Bagley noted that the meeting ended with an agreement that there
                                was no item for the President to make a decision on at the meeting
                                scheduled for the next day (see <ref target="#d398">Document
                                    398</ref>), but <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                                proposed to describe the logistics buildup in Thailand, and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> suggested looking
                                over existing contingency plans to make sure they were compatible
                                with the new situation evolving in Laos.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>