<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>450. Telegram From Secretary of State Rusk to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d450</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">450</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-04-09T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-04-09T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-04-09T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-04-09T17:00:00-05:00" n="450"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d450">
                <head>450. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="from"
                        >Rusk</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d450fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL 27 Laos. Secret; Operational Immediate; No Other
                        Distribution.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-04-09T23:00:00+01:00">April 9, 1963, 11 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 17. Eyes only for Acting Secretary from
                    Secretary. Following suggestions are based upon somewhat limited information
                    available in <pb facs="0981" n="957" xml:id="pg_957"/> Paris and presumably in
                    Washington about actual situation in Plaine des Jarres and series of group and
                    personal discussions with <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Foreign
                    Ministers.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> is key to present
                        situation in Laos. He is custodian of governmental legitimacy and has had
                        public commitment from all signatories of Geneva agreements. It seems to me
                        that we should take steps to encourage <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna
                            Phouma</persName> to commit himself publicly to integrity of Geneva
                        agreements and to insist that Pathet Lao and Viet-Minh (according to
                            <persName corresp="#p_KL1">Kong Le</persName>) action against neutralist
                        forces is direct violation those agreements. I would suggest therefore that
                            <persName corresp="#p_ULS1">Unger</persName> be directed to present
                        issues to <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> in
                        consultation with British and French colleagues Vientiane.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Further, there is one potential asset in Laos which we have never
                        succeeded in mobilizing behind a genuinely independent and neutral country.
                        This is the attitude of the King and the tradition of royalty in that
                        country. The King must do something about the views he expressed to the
                        President in Washington<note n="1" xml:id="d450fn2">See <ref target="#d444"
                                >Documents 444</ref> and <ref target="#d445">445</ref>.</note> and
                        risk the throne if he expects anyone else to risk anything for Laos. I would
                        suggest therefore that <persName corresp="#p_ULS1">Unger</persName> see the
                        King and emphasize necessity for King to give full public support to
                            <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> and the concept
                        of an independent and neutral Laos and that he be prepared to take this
                        issue to the country with a complete commitment of his own person and royal
                        institutions at this juncture. It should be made obvious to him that there
                        is no room in communism for royalty and that he has nothing to lose and
                        everything to gain by a maximum effort to insure the independence of his
                            country.<note n="2" xml:id="d450fn3">In telegram 953 to Vientiane, April
                            10, the Department suggested that “another effort to engage King
                            personally in present crisis would be in order.” If <persName
                                corresp="#p_ULS1">Unger</persName> was able to spare the time during
                            the crisis, he was to seek an audience with <persName corresp="#p_SV1"
                                >Savang</persName> and persuade him to appeal to the contending
                            factions and make a dramatic gesture, like a tour of the contested
                            provinces or, at least, issue a public statement. (Department of State,
                            Central Files, POL 27 Laos)</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>A further asset which should be pressed to the limit is <persName
                            corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s own personal commitment to
                        President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> that an independent
                        and neutral Laos is his own objective. Admitting there may be some
                        limitations on Soviet ability to guarantee a particular result with Hanoi or
                        Peiping, nevertheless we should press upon <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                            >Khrushchev</persName> the fact that his own good faith is at stake and
                        that we expect compliance with his solemn pledges on this subject. Lord
                            <persName corresp="#p_HAFD1">Home</persName> has instructed British
                        Ambassador Moscow to press this matter with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                            >Gromyko</persName> personally. I believe that it would not be wise for
                        the President to press <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> on
                        Laos in a personal message until after the message which we were discussing
                        just before I left Washington. If that message has not already gone, a
                        direct and simple message on Laos might be included but I <pb facs="0982"
                            n="958" xml:id="pg_958"/> would not send a special message on Laos until
                        that communication has gone forward.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I further believe we should give whatever practical assistance we can to
                            <persName corresp="#p_KL1">Kong Le</persName> and the Meo and <persName
                            corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> forces in the general vicinity of
                        Plaines des Jarres. This should be done with <persName corresp="#p_SPP1"
                            >Souvanna Phouma</persName>’s knowledge. In fact, I can see some
                        advantage in having <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>
                        request the two co-chairmen to insure that the neutralist forces are
                        adequately supplied with the resources needed to conform to the
                        understandings of the Geneva agreements.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>I do believe that it is important for us to try to achieve and maintain a
                        situation in which any action which we might subsequently be forced to take
                        would be in support of the Geneva agreements. I do not rule out the
                        possibility that several signatories of the Geneva agreements might take
                        military action to establish a position in Laos on the basis that such
                        action is designed to permit the Geneva agreements to be executed as
                        originally intended. Apart from maintaining general character of cease-fire
                        line, it is not inconceivable to me that South Viet-Nam, Cambodia, Thailand,
                        as well as the US and certain other Allies might occupy certain positions in
                        Laos pending a determination as to whether or not the Geneva agreements are
                        to be executed. However, from available information I would think it
                        premature to move in the military field beyond supplies to <persName
                            corresp="#p_KL1">Kong Le</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PN1"
                            >Phoumi</persName> forces but this contingency might arise if Pathet
                        Laos in fact attempt to press in the Plaines des Jarres.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>I should like to re-emphasize the importance of <persName
                            corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName>’s position and attitude. We
                        would be in a very strong position in supporting him against treacherous
                        Pathet Lao opposition to Geneva arrangements but would be in very difficult
                        position were he to quit or equivocate on issues raised by recent events in
                        Plaines des Jarres.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>It is my impression that the United Kingdom, France, Australia, New
                        Zealand, and Philippines are seriously concerned and would support above
                        program. Pakistan can be eliminated from any serious participation or
                        attention to Laotian question. Thailand would hope that strong action would
                        be taken to prevent Communist takeover of Laos but may be somewhat careful
                        after disillusionment previous efforts on Laotian question. However,
                            <persName corresp="#p_TK1">Thanat</persName> appears to have much more
                        confidence in basic intentions of <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna
                            Phouma</persName> than was confessed a year ago, but he is obviously
                        worried about whether we shall march uphill and then down again as he felt
                        we did earlier.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Looking ahead and not for immediate decision is question of possible
                        military action in face of threatened takeover of Laos by Pathet Lao and
                        Viet-Minh. After experience of past two years and extraordinary effort we
                        have made to find peaceful solution with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                            >Khrushchev</persName> and through Geneva agreements, I do not believe
                        we are obligated to <pb facs="0983" n="959" xml:id="pg_959"/> attempt
                        military action under conditions of greatest disadvantage by restricting our
                        forces to landlocked area of Laos. I would urge serious contingency planning
                        aimed at a clear warning to Hanoi that continued military action in Laos
                        would lead to direct action against North Viet-Nam. Our reluctance to
                        escalate should not require us to commit doughboys to a frustrating and
                        unrewarding effort if we can shoot at the Viet-Minh from the air and sea at
                        less cost to us and maximum cost to them. In other words it seems to me that
                        Geneva agreements must succeed or we must take the handcuffs off ourselves
                        in deciding what we think about the security of Southeast Asia.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
