<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-04-29T08:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-04-29T08:05:00-05:00" n="67" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                        <head>67. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d67fn1">Source: Department of State, Secretary’s Memoranda
                                of Conversation: Lot 65 D 330. Top Secret; Limit Distribution.
                                Drafted by <persName>G. Edward Reynolds</persName> and approved by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">McConaughy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName>, and in <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s office on June 6. The time is
                                taken from <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s Appointment
                                Book. (Johnson Library) Also printed in <hi rend="italic">United
                                    States-Vietnam Relations, 1945–1967</hi>, Book 11, pp.
                                62–66.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" from="1961-04-29T09:05:00-04:00" to="1961-04-29T09:50:00-04:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">April 29, 1961, 9:05–9:50
                                    a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Laos</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName></item>
                            <item>Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName></item>
                            <item>The Under Secretary</item>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">General Geo. H.
                                Decker</persName></item>
                            <item>General <persName corresp="#p_LMGCE1">C.E. Le
                                May</persName></item>
                            <item>General <persName corresp="#p_SGDM1">David M.
                                Shoup</persName></item>
                            <item>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Arleigh
                                Burke</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName></item>
                            <item>Deputy Under Secy <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName></item>
                            <item>Assistant Secy <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">McConaughy</persName></item>
                            <item>Deputy Asst. Secy Steeves</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Charles E.
                                Bohlen</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ADV1">Daniel V.
                                Anderson</persName></item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Kenneth
                                Young</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>G. Edward Reynolds</persName>, Lao Desk
                                Officer</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Secretary observed that the principal change on the ground had been
                            that forces had moved from such points as Muong Kassy and Tha Thom.
                            However, there had been no major change that would in itself make the
                            difference between our carrying out Plan 5 today and three weeks
                            ago.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that the real
                            question was whether we could land forces in Vientiane because of the
                            danger of Chinese air retaliation, local sabotage and the action by
                                <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> guerrillas who could move into
                            Vientiane at any time. The Secretary observed that the presence of these
                            guerrillas had been noted for weeks.</p>
                        <p>General Le May observed that there had been a large build-up of supplies
                            on the Pathet Lao side.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName> said that we were
                            faced with the “folding” of the <gloss target="#t_FAL1">FAL</gloss>,
                            which was not fighting.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary asked to what extent we were influenced by the movement of
                            Chinese Communist fighter bombers and pointed out that this capability
                            certainly existed three weeks ago.</p>
                        <p>General Le May said that these aircraft could always be moved in to scare
                            us off.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary next asked to what extent the Defense Department had been
                            influenced by the danger of escalation. Had this made any <pb facs="0175" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/> considerable difference? Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> replied that it
                            would be easy for the <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> or Chinese
                            Communists to prevent successful landings at Vientiane or Seno.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName> said that the
                            situation had deteriorated quite a bit but he still thought it possible
                            to go in. War is dangerous, he said. If pushed we could retreat across
                            the river, reinforce from Udorn and go back and fight.</p>
                        <p>When the Secretary asked whether we could send in troops to secure the
                            airfield, <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName> said
                            that would be a first task. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said it would be easy for the enemy to deny us
                            the airfield as we would need thirty-six sorties a day to get US troops
                            into Vientiane.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName> said that if we took
                            this action we would be doing something which most countries would not
                            appreciate.</p>
                        <p>The Attorney General asked where would be the best place to stand and
                            fight in Southeast Asia, where to draw the line. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said he thought we would take
                            a stand in Thailand and South Viet-Nam. The Attorney General asked
                            whether we would save any of Laos, but the major question was whether we
                            would stand up and fight.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName> said that we could
                            hold Tourane, and General Le May observed that we could use our air
                            power back as far as necessary, letting the enemy have all of the
                            countryside but that the <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> could be
                            stopped by air power.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that we would
                            have to attack the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> if we gave up
                            Laos.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary suggested that the part of Laos from the 17th Parallel
                            across to the Mekong might be easier to hold than the entire
                            country.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">General Decker</persName> thought that there
                            was no good place to fight in Southeast Asia but we must hold as much as
                            we can of Viet-Nam, Cambodia and Laos. At this point the Secretary said
                            that we had missed having government troops who were willing to
                            fight.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJM1">Steeves</persName> pointed out that we
                            had always argued that we would not give up Laos and that it was on the
                            pleas of our military that we had supported Phoumi; that we had
                            reiterated in the press and to the public what Laos meant to us. If this
                            problem is unsolvable then the problem of Viet-Nam would be unsolvable.
                            If we decided that this was untenable then we were writing the first
                            chapter in the defeat of Southeast Asia. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said the situation was not as
                            bad five weeks ago as it was now.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName> pointed out that
                            each time you give ground it is harder to stand next time. If we give up
                            Laos we would have to put US forces into Viet-Nam and Thailand. We would
                            have to throw enough in to win—perhaps the “works”. It would be easier
                            to hold now than later. The thing to do was to land now and hold as much
                            as we can and make <pb facs="0176" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/> clear that
                            we were not going to be pushed out of Southeast Asia. We were fighting
                            for the rest of Asia.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> wondered whether
                            more Viet Cong would necessarily enter South Viet-Nam if Laos went down
                            the drain. He mentioned that some 12, 000 Viet Cong had entered South
                            Viet-Nam under present conditions and that the Communists held the area
                            south of the 17th Parallel to a depth of twenty-five miles with a
                            supposedly friendly government in South Viet-Nam. (Several of those
                            present questioned the accuracy of the figure of 12,000.)</p>
                        <p>Turning to the question of the morale of the Southeast Asians, the
                            Secretary recalled that the Thai Foreign Minister had told him during
                            the recent <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> conference that
                            Thailand was like a “golden bell” which had to be protected from
                            outside. The Secretary said he was not sure the Foreign Minister was
                            wrong. He added that he was less worried about escalation than he was
                            about infectious slackness. He said he would not give a cent for what
                            the Persians would think of us if we did not defend Laos.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">General Decker</persName> thought that we
                            should have stood last August and wondered what would happen if we got
                            “licked”. The Secretary suggested that Thai and US troops might be
                            placed together in Vientiane and, if they could not hold, be removed by
                            helicopter. Even if they were defeated they would be defeated together
                            and this would be better than sitting back and doing nothing. <persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">General Decker</persName> said we cannot win a
                            conventional war in Southeast Asia; if we go in, we should go in to win,
                            and that means bombing Hanoi, China, and maybe even using nuclear bombs.
                            He pointed out that all the advantage we have in heavy equipment would
                            be lost in the difficult terrain of Laos where we would be at the mercy
                            of the guerrillas. The Secretary pointed out that this fact was also
                            true at the time of the Bangkok Resolution<note n="1" xml:id="d67fn2">The resolution passed at the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Council Meeting at Bangkok; see <ref target="#d42fn4">footnote 4, Document 42</ref>.</note> but that
                            we had gone ahead with the resolution anyway and had issued statements
                            indicating that we would back up our words with deeds. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> repeated that the situation
                            is now worse than it was five weeks ago. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJM1">Steeves</persName> pointed out that the same problems existed in
                            South Viet-Nam, but <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral
                                Burke</persName> thought that South Viet-Nam could be more easily
                            controlled.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">General Decker</persName> then suggested
                            that troops be moved into Thailand and South Viet-Nam to see whether
                            such action would not produce a cease-fire. <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName> asked what happens if there is still no
                            cease-fire. <persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">General Decker</persName> said
                            then we would be ready to go ahead.</p>
                        <pb facs="0177" n="153" xml:id="pg_153"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> said we would look
                            sillier than we do now if we got troops in there and then backed down.
                            He reiterated the question whether we are ready to go the distance.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that we would want to get the United Nations “mixed
                            up” in this.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> said he saw no need for
                            a fixation on the possibility of a reaction by the Chinese Communists.
                            He said we had no evidence that they want to face the brink of nuclear
                            war. He said that he was more concerned about the objectives we would
                            seek if we took military action.</p>
                        <p>There followed a discussion about the possibility of restoring the
                            kingdom of Champassak where <persName corresp="#p_BOP1">Boun
                                Oum</persName> relinquished the throne and where he is popular. It
                            was thought that <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName> would
                            support a partition of Laos. <persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">General
                                Decker</persName> thought that if a cease-fire could be effected
                            now, it would be possible to secure southern Laos.</p>
                        <p>General Le May did not believe that it would be possible to get a
                            cease-fire without military action. He admitted that he did not know
                            what US policy is in Laos. He knew what the President had said but he
                            also pointed out that the military had been unable to back up the
                            President’s statements. He then enumerated a number of possibilities: 1)
                            do nothing and lose Laos; 2) use B–26’s and slow up the enemy; 3) use
                            more sophisticated bombers and stop supplies and then perhaps Phoumi’s
                            forces could be brought up to where they could fight; 4) implement Plan
                            5, backing up troops with air. General Le May did not think the Chinese
                            would escalate but believed on the contrary that a cease-fire could then
                            be brought about. He added that he believed we should go to work on
                            China itself and let Chiang take Hainan Island. He thought Chiang had a
                            good air force.</p>
                        <p>General <persName corresp="#p_SGDM1">Shoup</persName> suggested that
                            B–26’s should be used before troops are landed. He felt that it might
                            then be possible to obtain a cease-fire and get the panhandle of Laos.
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> asked if any
                            appreciable dent could be made on the guerrillas with B–26’s. General Le
                            May said it would be possible to knock out a big wad of supplies with
                            B–26’s and 100’s. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>
                            asked what would be the next step. The Secretary said it would be
                            necessary to get the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in quickly. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> asked what the others
                            would do then. General Le May said the worst that could happen would be
                            that the Chinese Communists would come in. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> asked if it could all be done
                            by air. General Le May said it could. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said you would have to use nuclear weapons. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> asked if South
                            Viet-Nam and Thailand could be held if Laos were lost. The Secretary and
                                <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName> agreed that it
                            would take a greater effort to hold them after Laos had been lost and
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName> pointed out that
                            Thailand had to be defended from the other bank.</p>
                        <pb facs="0178" n="154" xml:id="pg_154"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJM1">Steeves</persName> felt that the prize to
                            be focused on was Southeast Asia. The question to be faced, he thought,
                            was whether we could afford to lose Southeast Asia.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary thought if a cease-fire is not brought about quickly, then
                            it would be necessary to get the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> to
                            come in with the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> forces
                            committed in a Plan 5 action. He thought that a majority could be found
                            in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> for such action if the cost is
                            not distributed. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                            and <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName> thought that
                            more than two weeks would be required for <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action. <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral
                                Burke</persName> said that only the United States could pull its own
                            chestnuts out of the fire. (There followed a general discussion on the
                            extent to which others would support us. It was agreed that the
                            Pakistani could be relied upon if we paid for them and that a few
                            Malays, New Zealanders and others would help.)</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName> suggested the
                            possibility of training 50 to 60,000 Vietnamese. He pointed to the ready
                            access to ports in the area of the Lao border and to the fact that the
                            terrain in the area is not too bad.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bowles</persName> said he thought the
                            main question to be faced was the fact that we were going to have to
                            fight the Chinese anyway in 2, 3, 5, or 10 years and that it was just a
                            question of where, when and how. He thought that a major war would be
                            difficult to avoid. General Le May said that, in that case, we should
                            fight soon since the Chinese would have nuclear weapons within one or
                            two years.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that the
                            situation was worsening by the hour and that if we were going to commit
                            ourselves, then we must do so sooner rather than later.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary then adjourned the meeting saying he would like to consider
                            the matter further.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>