<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-02T11:15:00-05:00" n="76" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                        <head>76. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>Attached to Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">Robert
                                McNamara</persName>’s and Deputy Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Roswell Gilpatric</persName>’s memorandum to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>, May 2 (<ref target="#d75">Document 75</ref>), were five memoranda and one
                            telegram from the Chiefs of Staff and two of the three Service
                            Secretaries. The memoranda were addressed to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, but a note on one of them
                            reads: “Returned by <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">M[axwell] D[.]
                                T[aylor]</persName> (these were sent over for the Atty Gen’l).” In a
                            memorandum, May 2, Chief of Staff of the Army, <persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">General George H. Decker</persName>, recommended
                            presenting the “Communists” with an ultimatum for a cease-fire within 48
                            hours and concurrently moving <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                            troops into Thailand along the Lao border opposite key communications
                            centers such as Vientiane, Paksane, and Savannakhet, and into South
                            Vietnam through Tourane. In addition, <persName corresp="#p_DGGH1">Decker</persName> suggested deployment of air forces into Thailand
                            and South Vietnam, and a carrier strike force near Laos so that if the
                            initial actions failed to produce a cease-fire, direct intervention into
                            Laos by <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> ground forces could be
                            possible.</p>
                        <p>Air Force Chief of Staff, General <persName corresp="#p_WGTD1">Thomas D.
                                White</persName>, stated that the best that could be hoped for was
                            to force a cease-fire. Intervention by ground forces in Laos on mainland
                            Southeast Asia would be a “maldeployment.” Therefore, if a 48-hour
                            deadline failed to produce a cease-fire, he recommended deploying U.S.
                            air power against Pathet Lao supply centers and military concentrations
                            in Laos. Should these <pb facs="0194" n="170" xml:id="pg_170"/> actions
                            still fail to achieve a cease-fire, White recommended threatening Hanoi
                            and South China with air and naval action. It these threats failed,
                            White recommended striking Hanoi even though he considered it would mean
                            war with China, which White considered “inevitable” if the United States
                            was determined to take decisive action in Southeast Asia and avoid the
                            mistakes of the Korean War.</p>
                        <p>In telegram 021215Z from Saigon, May 2, to <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName>, Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
                            General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lyman L. Lemnitzer</persName>
                            doubted that a cease-fire could be obtained in Laos without direct
                            intervention by <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> forces into Laos
                            to secure territory held by the <gloss target="#t_FAL1">FAL</gloss>.
                                <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName>, who was on a tour
                            of Southeast Asia, concluded from his talks there that the Armed Forces
                            of the Royal Lao Government were “falling apart.” <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> recommended that such <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> intervention occur as soon as
                            possible even if not all members agreed. Although <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> forces would not initially attack
                            Pathet Lao or North Vietnamese forces, if attacked themselves they
                            should be permitted to counterattack strongly.</p>
                        <p>Chief of Naval Operations <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Arleigh
                                Burke</persName>, in his memorandum of May 2 to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, recommended landing U.S.
                            troops in Thailand and South Vietnam immediately and within 48 hours
                            moving them into Laos to protect key population centers. U.S. forces
                            could counterattack if attacked, but not in such a way “as to pose
                            direct threat to North Vietnam or Red China.” If a cease-fire was not
                            obtained, <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Burke</persName> recommended air
                            attacks on the Pathet Lao. If North Vietnamese or Chinese forces
                            retaliated, the United States should escalate to defeat their
                            action.</p>
                        <p>Commandant of the Marine Corps General <persName corresp="#p_SGDM1">David
                                M. Shoup</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> in a memorandum of May 2 that he favored the
                            nonintervention course, but if it failed to achieve a cease-fire, he
                            then recommended bombardment by U.S. aircraft and the movement of
                                U.S./<gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> forces into given areas
                            of Laos.</p>
                        <p>In a May 2 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, Secretary of the Air Force <persName corresp="#p_ZEM1">Eugene M. Zuckert</persName> favored the air
                            strike strategy and opposed sending ground troops into Laos. Secretary
                            of the Army <persName corresp="#p_SEJJ1">Elvis J. Stahr</persName> sent
                            undated comments to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> in
                            which he recommended sending U.S. forces along with other <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> troops into Thailand and South
                            Vietnam, and if a cease-fire was not forthcoming, moving them into Laos
                            with air and naval support if they were attacked. (All in the Kennedy
                            Library, National Security Files, Countries Series, Laos: General,
                            Defense Papers, 5/61)</p>
                        <p>There was no memorandum found from the Secretary of the Navy. For
                            additional background on these memoranda and the meeting at which they
                            were considered, see <persName corresp="#p_SAMJ1">Arthur M. Schlesinger,
                                Jr.</persName>, <hi rend="italic">A Thousand Days</hi>, page 337,
                            and <persName>Theodore C. Sorenson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KJF1"><hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi></persName>, pages
                            644–645.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>