<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>88. Telegram From Secretary of State Rusk to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d88</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">88</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-05-13T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-05-13T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-05-13T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-05-13T12:00:00-05:00" n="88"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d88">
                <head>88. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD1" type="from"
                        >Rusk</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d88fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 751J.00/5–1361. Secret; Priority. Repeated to Moscow, Vientiane, and
                        Bangkok.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-05-13T18:00:00+01:00">May 13, 1961, 6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 94. I made one hour call on <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> this morning with <persName
                        corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PGM1"
                        >Pushkin</persName> present.<note n="1" xml:id="d88fn2">A memorandum of
                        conversation of this meeting between <persName corresp="#p_RD1"
                            >Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> is
                        ibid., Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 65 D 330 and Conference
                        Files: Lot 65 D 366, CF 1868.</note> I started by asking <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> how he envisaged Laotian representation
                    at conference. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said he saw two
                    possible solutions. First was seating of coalition government if one “acceptable
                    to all sides in Laos” could be formed prior to conference. If this not possible,
                    alternative was seat representatives of “three existing forces” in Laos. These
                    he described as <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> government,
                    Pathet Lao and “rebels”. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> added if
                    we had any doubts about reality of Pathet Lao movement we had only to look at
                    map.</p>
                <p>I pointed out our understanding this was to be conference of governments. I
                    observed Pathet Lao was merely military arm of a political party. I said we had
                    no objection political parties themselves being heard if conference so desired.
                    However, I was unaware of any invitation to Pathet Lao. I asked him to clarify
                    this point.</p>
                <pb facs="0216" n="192" xml:id="pg_192"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said that from outset of talks
                    between co-chairmen he had made his position clear that unless coalition
                    government formed before conference the “three existing forces” must be
                    represented. He said we did not like Pathet Lao because we apparently considered
                    left wing or Communist-oriented. However, “there can be no step forward” so long
                    as we adhere to such ideological considerations. In response to my repeated
                    questioning whether Pathet Lao had been invited to conference and if so by whom,
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> asserted there had been
                    “understanding” among co-chairmen that “efforts should be made to ensure that
                    representatives of existing forces be physically available in Geneva.” He had
                    assumed each co-chairman would see to this. Soviets for their part had done so
                    in arranging for <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> and Pathet Lao
                    representatives to come. Question of neutral and independent Laos to which
                    principle we all subscribed was political one to be resolved on tripartite basis
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>I said we stood firmly for Laotian neutrality and independence but believed
                    conference should not prejudice or instruct Lao on how to form government. We
                    disagreed all Laos divided into three parts. Moreover it was not for us to
                    decide or to intervene at conference in processes of forming government.
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> agreed conference should not
                    interfere in internal affairs of Laos but insisted that understanding of
                    Co-chairmen as to measures for providing Laotian representation was not
                    interference. I said proposal for including Pathet Lao representation offered
                    entirely new basis and we were not prepared to start conference on that basis. I
                    reminded <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> Pathet Lao had not been
                    seated at Geneva in 1954 but had been represented by Hanoi. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PGM1">Pushkin</persName> observed Pathet Lao were included in
                    1957 Vientiane agreements at which I noted that under those agreements they were
                    supposed to disappear.</p>
                <p>At this point <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> stated <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> wants to safeguard peace as he supposes does
                    U.S. However, he had impression we were creating artificial difficulties on what
                    Soviets regard as trifling matters since Pathet Lao after all were real Lao
                    force, repeating again “as any glance at map will show”. I asked him why he was
                    so insistent if matter was so unimportant and noted again this was first time we
                    had heard of any invitation to Pathet Lao. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> said we were evidently intimidated by Pathet Lao and
                    asked whether we did not want to hear them. I said we had no objection to
                    hearing them but they should not be regarded on same level as governments. I
                    asked <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> whether <persName
                        corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> himself did not claim to speak for
                    Pathet Lao. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> replied <persName
                        corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> and Pathet Lao agree on many things
                    but not on question of speaking for Pathet Lao at conference.</p>
                <p>I then asked <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> how in absence of
                    agreement on Pathet Lao he thought we might get conference started since we were
                    all eager to begin. He did not see how this could be done without Pathet Lao. As
                        <pb facs="0217" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/> final thought I suggested as
                    possible solution that Laos not be seated but that individual Lao might state
                    their views in any way co-chairmen agreed. For example they could be seated in
                    balconies and be called upon if they wished to speak. Under some such
                    arrangement any formal agreement on Laos seating would be unnecessary and
                    conference could proceed.</p>
                <p>However, <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> held flatly to position
                    that conference could not begin without Laos representation. He said in absence
                    of coalition government he was prepared open conference today without seating
                    any Lao at table (since <persName corresp="#p_PN1">Phoumi</persName> group
                    absent) on condition tripartite seating be adopted Monday. I said we ready to
                    begin today only under conditions I had outlined. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> refused to envisage anything but tripartite
                    representation, and we closed on this point. I said we would consult further
                    with others.</p>
                <p>I communicated foregoing to Lord <persName corresp="#p_HAFD1">Home</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve</persName> before lunch. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CMM1">Couve</persName> will see <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> at three p.m. and sound him out in particular on how he
                    envisages coalition government. Lord <persName corresp="#p_HAFD1"
                        >Home</persName> seeing <persName corresp="#p_CY1">Chen Yi</persName> at
                    five.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
