<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Clay to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-09-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-09-02T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664" lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-09-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-09-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="193" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Clay</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 19, official.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburgh, Russia</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-09-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 2, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I am in the regular receipt of your late
                            despatches, including the lost No. 30. The late responses of the three
                            powers to Prince Gortchacow have <pb facs="0198" n="876" xml:id="pg_876"/> not yet been made public, but it is generally admitted that no war
                            will be the result, at least this year. In the mean time Russia does not
                            relax her defences by land and sea, and the Emperor has made himself
                            popular anew with the disaffected nobles, by the spirit with which he
                            defends the integrity of the empire.</p>
                <p>All Americans with whom I have conversed agree that it is more important
                            to carry out the conscription ordered by Congress and the President than
                            to put down the southern rebellion. The power of the national government
                            “to raise and support armies,” so clearly given to Congress by the
                            Constitution, is all-important to our national existence, without which
                            we would relapse into the impotency of the “old confederation,” and
                            weakness of the Germanic confederation.</p>
                <p>It is the part of the southern rebels, their northern and foreign allies,
                            to strip us of this essential national vitality, which would ultimately
                            insure disunion, and reduce us to Mexican imbecility before foreign
                            subjugation. With intense interest, then, have we watched the action of
                            the President; and much do we rejoice to believe that he will go on with
                            the conscription, without fear or compromise. It will settle the fatal
                            heresy of state rights forever, and make our nationality a fixed fact
                            before the world. * * * * *</p>
                <p>I am, truly, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C. M. CLAY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c.,
                                    &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
