<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Pike to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d218</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">218</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-04-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-04-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="218"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d218">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Pike</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 82.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Hague</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-04-08">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 8, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi>* * * * *</p>
                <p>The speculation in American government stocks goes on at Amsterdam with unabated
                    activity. Yesterday, news of an armi <pb facs="0214" n="892" xml:id="pg_892"/>
                    been brought by the Australasian and telegraphed from Queenstown, was reported
                    on the bourse, and our bonds rose five per cent. instantly. It appears now to
                    have been a ruse of the operators. But the announcement produced extraordinary
                    excitement, and sales went on at the rise. So much are stock operators absorbed
                    by the movement that complaints are made that everything not American is
                    neglected. For example: a canal has long been projected to unite Amsterdam in a
                    direct line with the sea-coast. This winter, government has approved the project
                    and voted a guarantee of four per cent. on the capital necessary to construct
                    the work. It has been expected that Amsterdam would earnestly contend for the
                    privilege of subscribing for the whole capital. It turns out, however, that the
                    subscription there, just completed, is not a third part of the sum needed. The
                    King is indignant, and announces that Amsterdam must reform or he will not make
                    his annual visit to that city, the period for which has now arrived. It is to be
                    seen if the more inviting investments in American 6’s at 65 are to be overlooked
                    by reason of this evidence of the royal displeasure. It is likely to be found
                    that Holland has money enough for both enterprises. I have communicated with Mr.
                    Van der Mæser in respect to the non-intervention resolutions of Congress, and,
                    as such was his preference, I have left with him a copy of them.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with great respect, your most obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JAMES S. PIKE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Seward</hi>,
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
