<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Koerner to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d289</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">289</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-04-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="289"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d289">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Koerner</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 32.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Madrid</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-04-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> On the 1st of April I addressed a note to the
                    minister of foreign affairs, of which I enclose a copy, (marked A,) and which
                    will explain itself.</p>
                <p>I also sent him, on the same day, another one covering the resolutions of
                    Congress concerning foreign intervention, in which I informed him that, having
                    received no answer to my request for a personal interview, made on the 28th of
                    March, for the purpose of reading to him said resolutions, I felt constrained to
                    transmit the same to him, as it was desirable that a document of such importance
                    should be brought at an early period to the knowledge of her Majesty’s
                    government.</p>
                <p>An hour or two after I had sent the notes, I received a communication that the
                    minister would see me on the 7th of April, and also a note dated the 1st of
                    April, in reply to mine directed to the minister’s predecessor, General Serrano,
                    (Duke de la Torre,) on the 23d February last, and which treats of the events
                    which lately happened in and near the island of Cuba. I enclose a translation of
                    said note, (marked B.)</p>
                <p>You will perceive by its tenor that, with the exception of the complaint as to
                    the discrimination made against us in admitting vessels at unusual hours into
                    the port of Havana, and in regard to which the government here has asked
                    information from the Spanish authorities there, to ascertain the facts, all the
                    other grievances are considered by the Marquis of Miraflores as not well
                    founded.</p>
                <p>I have not yet replied to this last note, principally for the reason that on the
                    2d of April the high church festivities commenced, and that before Tuesday next
                    no secular business is expected to be transacted. Without anticipating the final
                    decision of the President on the question raised by our complaints, and the
                    manner in which they are viewed by the government here, I shall certainly,
                    either by note or verbally, state to the Marquis of Miraflores that I cannot
                    share his belief that the President will be satisfied with the reasoning of the
                    Spanish Department of State, suggesting to him my objections, and preparing him
                    for similar ones, as likely to be expected from the President.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, with very great respect, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GUSTAVUS KOERNER</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Seward</hi>,
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <pb facs="0295" n="973" xml:id="pg_973"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>A.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Madrid</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-04-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1, 1863.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">ir</hi>: On the 23d day of February last I had the
                        honor to address a note to General Serrano, your excellency’s predecessor,
                        according to his request, on the subject of certain important events which
                        had happened in and near the island of Cuba, and on account of which I had
                        been instructed by the President of the United States to make proper
                        representations to her Majesty’s government, and to expect explanations
                        which should prove satisfactory to the government of the United States. To
                        this communication, as well as to others of less importance upon divers
                        subjects, I have thus far received no reply.</p>
                    <p>I am not unmindful of what you remarked to me on the occasion of the two
                        brief interviews which I had the honor to hold with your excellency on the
                        8th and 22d of March last, respecting the very large amount of business
                        devolving upon you at your recent entrance into office as president of her
                        Majesty’s council and first secretary of state, and the consequent delay
                        which naturally would arise in the transaction of business, owing to the
                        circumstances surrounding your excellency.</p>
                    <p>But your excellency having been pleased, in our last interview, to promise me
                        an answer by note in a few days, and the questions pending being of such a
                        character that my government has certainly expected me to report upon them a
                        long time ago, I feel myself constrained to proceed according to my
                        instructions, and to transmit to your excellency, enclosed, a copy of a
                        despatch from the Secretary of State of the United States of the 30th of
                        January last, relating to the events at and near the island of Cuba, with
                        the urgent request that your excellency take the subjects therein mentioned
                        into serious consideration, and act upon them as promptly as possible.</p>
                    <p>I beg to repeat here what I have stated in my note to General Serrano, viz:
                        that the question as to the misdeed alleged to have been committed by her
                        Majesty’s vessel-of-war the Princesa de Asturias, in firing upon and
                        detaining the United States <hi rend="italic">aviso</hi> W. B. Reaney on the
                        open sea, is one which can be disposed of at once, since her Majesty’s
                        government, as I have understood from General Serrano, is in possession of
                        the facts of the case, as reported by the authorities of Spain at the
                        Havana.</p>
                    <p>I embrace this opportunity of assuring your excellency of my most
                        distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>GUSTAVUS KOERNER.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency the <hi rend="smallcaps">Marquis of Miraflores</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">First Secretary of State of her Catholic Majesty.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>B.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Palace</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-04-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1, 1863.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Being informed of the confidential note
                        which, on the 23d of February last, your excellency was pleased to direct to
                        my predecessor, the Duke de la Torre, bringing to his knowledge various
                        complaints brought by the honorable Secretary of State of the United States
                        against the authorities of Cuba, and against the commander of her Majesty’s
                        cruiser Princesa de Asturias, your excellency will permit me to observe
                        that, in my opinion, among the events to <pb facs="0296" n="974"
                            xml:id="pg_974"/> which Mr. Seward refers, the only one that might give
                        occasion for reclamations, if it should prove true, is the giving permission
                        to the confederate vessel Florida to enter the port of Havana, where it
                        arrived at 8 o’clock in the evening of the 20th of January, while it was
                        denied to the federal vessel Wachusett, which arrived at 6½ o’clock p. m. on
                        the 22d, on account of the lateness of the hour.</p>
                    <p>The government of the Queen my lady, which has undertaken to guard the
                        strictest neutrality in the war through which the United States are now
                        passing, could not tolerate the partiality which the denounced act would
                        indicate on the part of the authorities of Cuba; and not believing them
                        capable of deviating from the instructions they have received, asks them,
                        tinder this date, to give information, in the shortest possible time, of
                        what occurred concerning this subject. This same neutrality, of which so
                        many proofs have been given, imposes upon the government of her Majesty the
                        obligation to admit the vessels of the south into all Spanish ports; and in
                        nowise has it wanted in faith towards the government of the Union, by
                        permitting the Florida to enter Havana after having destroyed a ship of her
                        enemy. And if the Florida was permitted to sail from that port before the
                        twenty-four hours after the United States despatch steamer Reaney had put to
                        sea had expired, it is because in the nineteen hours that transpired between
                        the departure of both, the latter, which directed its course towards Cayo
                        Hueso, was able to gain a much greater distance than sufficient to escape
                        capture by the Florida; and in this manner the obligation which the law of
                        nations lays upon neutral powers was complied with. Your excellency will
                        easily understand that in that time the Reaney could not only arrive at her
                        destination, but almost to return to Havana.</p>
                    <p>As far as regards the detention of the Reaney by the Princesa de Asturias,
                        arising in the jurisdictional waters of Cuba, it is justified by the right
                        belonging to every vessel-of-war to detain, and even to search, within the
                        limits under the jurisdiction of its country, any merchant vessel,
                        particularly when the latter pays no attention to its signal. And that this
                        detention took place in the waters of Cuba is evident, not only from the
                        declaration of the commander of the Princesa de Asturias, but also from what
                        may be deduced from the fact that the Reaney returned to Havana,
                        notwithstanding that she was carrying the official correspondence.</p>
                    <p>In respect to the answer given by the captain general of Cuba to the consul
                        of the United States, the government of her Majesty finds nothing censurable
                        in it, since the terms in which it is held are not less courteous than could
                        be expected from that authority, and its laconic brevity may be attributed
                        to the fact that the consul engaged himself to judge of questions of law,
                        and of dispositions of her Majesty’s government which are beyond his power,
                        and into the discussion of which General Dulce was not allowed to enter with
                        him.</p>
                    <p>I believe that the government of the Union will be satisfied with the
                        explanations I herewith give to your excellency, and that it will be
                        convinced that that of the Queen my lady, which is anxious to preserve the
                        truly friendly relations uniting the two countries, cannot disapprove of the
                        conduct of the authorities of Cuba, which are in every respect in conformity
                        with the requirements of law, and with the royal decree of neutrality,
                        unless it should prove true that the entry into the Havana was refused to
                        the Wachusett after it had been conceded to a confederate vessel under like
                        circumstances, concerning which, as I assure your excellency, information
                        has been requested of the captain general of that island.</p>
                    <p>I improve this opportunity to renew to your excellency the assurances of my
                        most distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>EL MARQUES DE MIRAFLORES.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister Plenipotentiary of the</hi> U. S.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
