<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-09-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="301" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Perry</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 7.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-09-03"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 3, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your several despatches of July 29, (No.
                            103,) July 31, (No. 104,) and August 2, (No. 105,) have been received.
                            The President is pleased with the assurance you have received from the
                            Marquis Miraflores that the government of Spain still adheres to its
                            policy of withholding recognition from the insurgents. It is not
                            surprising that all the statesmen of Spain do not fully understand or
                            always bear in mind the divisions of parties in the United States, and
                            their relative policies in regard to the Spanish possessions of Cuba and
                            Porto Rico. Still less does it surprise us that the Marquis Miraflores
                            should have failed to fully the unswerving policy, exclusively American,
                            which determines ted States to decline alliances for purposes of offence
                            or guarantee with tions. Nor is it generally wise or expedient for the
                            government, under <pb facs="0307" n="985" xml:id="pg_985"/> any
                            administration, to open its questions of domestic policy in its
                            controversies with foreign states. Nevertheless, you have not erred in
                            bringing to the knowledge of the Marquis of Miraflores the bearing of
                            the present civil war upon the question of slavery at home as well as
                            abroad. The Spanish government can easily determine for itself whether
                            the continued enjoyment of Cuba with slavery is more likely to be
                            secured by a recognition of the insurgents, which would be an act
                            hostile to the United States, than it will be secured by the policy of
                            cordial friendship towards the United States which has induced them for
                            sixty years to respect that occupation themselves, and to insist upon
                            its being respected by all other nations. The United States do not want
                            any more territories, certainly they do not want anymore slaveholding
                            territories. The United States government is not a forcible propagandist
                            of emancipation even at home, although it does not hesitate to strike
                            slavery down when it rises in resistance to the government. Much less is
                            this government an armed propagandist of emancipation or any other
                            policy in foreign countries. But it certainly could not, if assailed by
                            any foreign slaveholding power, show any greater forbearance towards the
                            slavery maintained by a foreign army than it shows to domestic slavery
                            when employed against the government by the insurgents.</p>
                        <p>If you think it proper that these thoughts should be brought to the
                            attention of her Catholic Majesty’s government, your own discretion must
                            be exercised as to the way of making them known informally to the
                            Marquis of Miraflores.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Horatio</hi> J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Perry</hi>,
                                Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c</hi>., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                                    Madrid.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>