<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-12-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="446" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d446">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Morris</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 37.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States of
                                        America</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-12-04"><hi rend="italic">December</hi> 4, 1862.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to enclose a printed
                            translation of the answer of the minister of foreign affairs to the note
                            of the ambassadors of the Great Powers, on the subject of the rights of
                            foreigners to own real property in Turkey. This note confirms the
                            observations which I had the honor to submit on this question in
                            despatch No. 36.</p>
                        <p>I also enclose a correspondence with the consul at Beirut, on a case
                            which is connected with this question. The “helpers” of the missionaries
                            are native <pb facs="0500" n="1178" xml:id="pg_1178"/> preachers,
                            converted by them to protestantism, and for the most part, originally
                            Americans. The Porte is daily growing more jealous of the interference
                            of foreign legations in the affairs of Ottoman subjects, and it requires
                            great prudence not to offend its sensibilities on this subject. By the
                            existing treaties the United States agents in Turkey are expressly
                            restrained from protecting Ottoman subjects not in the employment of the
                            legation or consulates.</p>
                        <p>The native protestants are recognized as a distinct religious fraternity
                            in the empire, and as such choose, by authority of the Porte, an Agha,
                            or chief, who is the organ through whom they communicate with the
                            Turkish government. The Porte acts with the same deference and regard to
                            the representative of this, the smallest religious fraternity in the
                            empire, as towards the millions of Greeks represented by their patriarch
                            at Constantinople.</p>
                        <p>For some time the Turkish government has had under consideration the
                            question of the creation of a government bank. The utility of such an
                            institution, in aiding the financial operations of the government, in
                            regulating the exchanges, and in furnishing a paper currency of equal
                            value in all parts of the empire, has become so apparent of late that
                            the Porte has resolved to create a national bank. The plan is matured,
                            but not yet published.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, with great respect, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>E. JOY MORRIS.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>P. S.—As an example of the insecurity of life and property on the
                                roads of the interior of the empire, and to show that others, as
                                well as Americans, suffer from this cause, I beg to mention the fact
                                of the robbery of Baghir Bey, an agent of the Persian minister, on
                                his way from this place to Teheran, with jewelry to the value of
                                1,500,000 piastres, purchased for the Schah of Persia by the
                                minister, on a recent visit to Paris. The Bey was assailed by
                                robbers near the frontier beyond Erzeroum, robbed of his despatches
                                and jewels, and killed. The robbers have escaped.</p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Morris</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Johnson</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States of
                                            America</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-11-26"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 26, 1862.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have had the honor to receive your
                                letter of the 14th instant, reporting the conduct of his excellency
                                Achir Pacha, governor of Marash, in relation to a house possessed by
                                Messrs. Goodale &amp; White, in the name of an Ottoman subject, for
                                the use of their helper, who, I suppose, is also a subject of the
                                Sultan, and have brought the case before the minister of foreign
                                affairs for his consideration.</p>
                            <p>The present incident, which I greatly regret, furnishes me with an
                                occasion to inform you that the Ottoman government firmly refuses to
                                all foreigners the rights of possessing real estate in their own
                                names, and is as strongly indisposed to allow any privileges or
                                distinctions in favor of property which they may acquire in a
                                fictitious manner. The interference of the legation in such cases
                                must therefore be entirely officious, and great discretion is
                                required, so as not to excite the sensibilities of the Porte.</p>
                            <p>I must also add, that the Ottoman government does not admit that the
                                employment of its subjects by private foreigners in Turkey gives to
                                the former any foreign protection, or in any manner releases them
                                from their proper subjection. It is only when temporarily in the
                                employ of the foreign legations and consulates that they enjoy their
                                protection.</p>
                            <p>The house in question is officially owned and occupied by an Ottoman
                                subject, and is therefore wholly within the jurisdiction of the
                                local authorities. I hope <pb facs="0501" n="1179" xml:id="pg_1179"/> that the friendly intercession of the legation will, however,
                                induce the Porte to address such an order to his excellency Achir
                                Pacha as will cause him to release, under the circumstances, the
                                American gentlemen from the inconvenience complained of.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>E. JOY MORRIS.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>J <hi rend="smallcaps">Aug. Johnson</hi>, <hi rend="italic">United States Consul, Beirut.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Johnson</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Morris</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate</hi>,
                                            <hi rend="italic">Beirut, Syria</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-11-14"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 14, 1862.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to inform you that I
                                have this morning received a communication from the American
                                missionaries in Marash, relative to an outrage committed upon them
                                personally, and in the person of their employé, by the new governor
                                of Marash, Achir Pacha, of which the following is an extract:</p>
                            <p>“Three years ago, at a cost of one hundred pounds, we purchased a
                                house for the use of our helper, the acting pastor of a large
                                protestant church here. Yesterday morning, without any previous
                                warning, the helper and his wife were ejected forcibly from the
                                house, that it might be made a hospital for the soldiers. Dr.
                                Goodale immediately waited on Achir Pacha, but, without suffering a
                                word of explanation, with anger and rage he ordered him from his
                                presence. This morning Mr. White called, represented that the house
                                was our own, bought with our own money, and for a specific purpose,
                                and that there was an abundance of as good houses in the vicinity.
                                Achir Pacha replied that the deed of the house was in the name of a
                                native. For this reason he had a right to take it, and for this same
                                reason he could take the houses in which we live, and would do so if
                                necessary; and he threatened to make us smart in future for not
                                having considered it a high privilege to receive the King’s
                                soldiers.</p>
                            <p>“The Pacha’s whole deportment is tyrannical and insulting in the
                                extreme, and, according to his own words, we may any day be ejected
                                from our homes. Has the Pacha a right to seize the house of a
                                foreigner when there is an abundance of eligible houses in the
                                vicinity? Has he the right to drive from his presence a peaceful
                                American resident, without even hearing his petition?”</p>
                            <p>The letter, of which the above is an extract, is dated Marash,
                                October 11, 1862, and concludes with the prayer that an order may be
                                obtained commanding that their house be restored to them, and that
                                the Pacha be made to apologize to Messrs. White and Goodale, the
                                signers of the letter, for his unwarrantable and insulting conduct
                                towards them.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>J. AUG. JOHNSON.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Joy Morris</hi>, Esq., <hi rend="italic">United States Minister Resident, Constantinople.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Foreigners and the rights of property in
                                    Turkey.</hi></head>
                            <p>A French journal publishes the following as the reply of Ali Pacha to
                                the recent note of the foreign representatives on the subject of the
                                rights of foreigners to own real property in the empire. We shall
                                take early occasion to review some of the arguments employed by his
                                highness in defence of the existing disabilities:</p>
                            <pb facs="0502" n="1180" xml:id="pg_1180"/>
                            <p rend="right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Sublime Porte</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-10-03"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 3, 1862.</date></p>
                            <p>The undersigned, minister for foreign affairs to his Majesty the
                                Sultan, has had the honor to receive and to submit to his august
                                master the collective note which their excellencies the
                                representatives of the Great Powers have addressed him in reference
                                to the question of foreign subjects holding real property in the
                                Ottoman empire. The undersigned, by order of his Imperial Majesty
                                the Sultan, hereby declares to their excellencies, that the imperial
                                government does not hesitate to recognize its proclamation some time
                                ago on the subject; and will also add, that even issued without the
                                existence of such a circumstance, he would consider himself happy to
                                be able to solve a question which appears to be destined to produce
                                great benefit for Turkey, as well as to increase its relations with
                                Europe. But the representatives are not ignorant of the motives
                                which have, up to the present, delayed this result. They are also
                                aware that the Sublime Porte has always affirmed that it will only
                                grant to foreign subjects the right of possessing real property,
                                under certain conditions.</p>
                            <p>The government of the Sultan desires to act towards other nations
                                according to the principles of the most civilized people. In return,
                                it considers it its right, and as due to its dignity and
                                preservation, to invoke the same principles on its own behalf. It is
                                well known in what a situation Turkey was, when its relations with
                                Europe commenced. A few foreign merchants, completely separated from
                                the rest of the population, resided in the seaports of the Levant.
                                They had hardly anything to do with the natives, and were entirely
                                devoted to wholesale trade. The Ottoman government granted them
                                privileges which the state of society in which they lived, and the
                                customs and habits of that time, had rendered necessary; but, what
                                existed then has given place to a state of things completely
                                different. Europe has changed, and Turkey is no more what she was.
                                The relations between her and Europe are no longer the same.
                                Everything, then, is changed, except those antiquated capitulations
                                which are often put forward in order to justify pretensions
                                incompatible with the present system, and of such a nature as to
                                render impossible the regular course of the government.</p>
                            <p>Foreign subjects are, in virtue of the said capitulations, only
                                subject to their own authorities. It follows, then, that in the
                                provinces of the empire there are as many police administrations, as
                                many tribunals governed by different laws, as there are consulates.
                                Consequently, in any police matter, as well as everything relating
                                to judicial, financial and other administrations, the hand of the
                                government is paralyzed in the name of this irregularity. The great
                                inconvenience arising from such an extraordinary state of things,
                                the insurmountable obstacles opposed to the accomplishment of the
                                wishes of the Sultan to have order and regularity in all branches of
                                the administration, are too evident to require enumeration here, and
                                the extent of which cannot be more fully appreciated by any one than
                                by those on whom the responsibility of the government of the empire
                                rests. The undersigned is persuaded that if the representatives who
                                signed the collective note would take into consideration the
                                preceding observations, they will admit that, as long as such a
                                state of things exists, it must be impossible for the Sublime Porte
                                to adopt the course on which they advise it to enter. In fact, how
                                can it grant the right of establishing themselves as proprietors to
                                populations who do not recognize its authority or its laws, and who
                                do not submit to the obligations to which the subjects of his
                                Imperial Majesty, the Sultan, are themselves subordinated, but to
                                their own foreign tribunals? Everywhere else, where strangers enjoy
                                the privilege of possessing property, they are subjected to the
                                police, to the laws and tribunals of the nation amongst which they
                                reside; they pay the same taxes as the people of that nation, and
                                they do not expect to be treated more favorably than its own
                                subjects.</p>
                            <pb facs="0503" n="1181" xml:id="pg_1181"/>
                            <p>The necessity and legitimacy of modifying the capitulations has been
                                solemnly recognized by the Great Powers who signed the treaty of the
                                30th March, 1856, and has been solemnly expressed in one of the
                                protocols of the Congress of Paris. In consequence, the undersigned
                                feels himself justified in repeating that the government remains
                                faithful to the promise made at the conclusion of that treaty, to
                                deal with this question as soon as the legislation which governs
                                foreign subjects in Turkey shall have undergone such changes as are
                                required by present circumstances. According to the opinion of the
                                Sublime Porte, the following three points must form the basis of the
                                revision for that end:</p>
                            <p>1st. The integral payment, by strangers resident in Turkey, of all
                                taxes and imposts to which Ottoman subjects are subjected.</p>
                            <p>2d. What authority should the Sublime Porte exercise over them?</p>
                            <p>3d. Are there any advantages that could be granted them in return for
                                the obligations they will have to accept?</p>
                            <p>The undersigned cannot omit to say, at the same time, that the
                                government will neglect nothing in order that the laws to which
                                strangers will be subjected shall offer all the most desirable
                                guarantees. It is equally to be observed that the obtainment of all
                                the immunities (to be) accorded to foreign subjects, and which would
                                not be in direct opposition to their new position, would not be an
                                affair of a stroke of the pen, nor of immediate accomplishment,
                                since it would be out of the question to grant them all the
                                privileges enjoyed by native subjects of the Porte. The undersigned
                                avails himself of this occasion to repeat to his excellency the
                                assurance of his high consideration.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>ALI.</signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>