<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-11-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="472" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d472">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Thayer</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No 24.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate
                                    General</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Alexandria</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-11-12"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 12, 1862.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am informed by an intelligent
                            proprietor, who claims to have made a careful and accurate reckoning,
                            that the yield of cotton in Egypt next year, if the command of the
                            Viceroy to plant one-fourth of the cultivated land with that product is
                            carried out, cannot be less than two-thirds greater than in any previous
                            season, and that it will amount to three million cantars, or about six
                            hundred thousand American bales. It is commonly asserted that Egypt
                            could supply a million bales a year, if its capacity were fully tested,
                            and that, too, without serious displacement of the grain and other <pb facs="0517" n="1195" xml:id="pg_1195"/> staple crops. The governor
                            (mayor) of Alexandria, himself a large cotton-planter, tells me that a
                            few Americans, experienced in the raising and preparation of cotton,
                            would be of signal service in teaching the native cultivators here.</p>
                        <p>The telegraph news, which came on the 10th, of the President’s order to
                            facilitate the export of cotton from New Orleans, caused an immediate
                            fall in the Egyptian article of two cents on the pound. A few
                            speculators on the exchange expressed themselves highly incensed at the
                            order, as well as at the proclamation of emancipation. Both of these
                            measures, though cordially approved by the less interested classes, they
                            consider as tending towards the end of the war, which, however
                            calamitous elsewhere, has not been without its compensations to them.
                            There is scarcely one of them, it is believed, who has not doubled or
                            tripled his capital during the past summer, and the sudden influx of
                            wealth in the community is apparent, as it was at the time of the
                            Crimean war, in the unusual number of new buildings, and in other signs
                            of enterprise and prosperity.</p>
                        <p>The principal difficulty in fulfilling the Viceroy’s command is said to
                            be the withdrawal, by the government’s direction, of labor to the works
                            on the canal of the isthmus of Suez, which have lately required an
                            average of from 20,000 to 30,000 hands. The places of those who are
                            taken from the plantations may, it is true, be supplied by those who
                            have served their time on the canal, but, unhappily, the latter are by
                            no means so efficient on the cotton field as their more skilled
                            predecessors.</p>
                        <p>This drain, however, on the already insufficient labor of the country is
                            not likely to be long continued. The canal company are now importing
                            from Europe twenty steam excavating machines of immense power, which it
                            is expected will finish the great ship canal between the seas in three
                            or four years, with the employment of but from one thousand to two
                            thousand men. This estimate is derived from the surveys and measurements
                            of engineers. The proposed canal will have a width of 65 metres (213½
                            feet,) and a depth of 8 metres, (about 26¼ feet.) The entire length from
                            Port Said, on the Mediterranean, to Suez, on the Red sea, will be 931/5
                            miles.</p>
                        <p>Thus far, besides their ample canals of Nile water for the fertilization
                            of their lands, the company have been engaged in digging a small canal,
                            called <hi rend="italic">la rigole de service</hi>, on the route of the
                            proposed large one. It is now more than half finished, extending from
                            the Mediterranean to Lake Tirasah, with a width of twelve metres (about
                            391/3 feet) and a depth of one metre and three-fifths, (about 5¼ feet.)
                            The remainder will be built in ten months. The waters of the
                            Mediterranean, to the completed portion of the canal of service, in a
                            few days, and it is expected the occasion will be marked by a festive
                            commemoration, in presence of the Viceroy, Mr. de Lesseps, (the
                            energetic projector,) Sir Henry Bulwer, British ambassador at
                            Constantinople, and other official guests.</p>
                        <p>One advantage of the small canal will consist in the facilities it will
                            afford in bringing from the quarries on the isthmus the stone needed for
                            building the pier at Port Said, a material heretofore brought from the
                            distant and inferior quarries of Alexandria. Returning from Port Said
                            the boats can be reloaded with coal for the steam-engines employed in
                            excavation. When this small canal shall have been finished to Suez, it
                            will be useful in supplying coals to the numerous steamers of the
                            Peninsular and Oriental and French Messageries companies which ply
                            between that port and India. At present these companies have all their
                            coals brought from England, in sailing vessels, around the Cape of Good
                            Hope, or else by railway across Egypt, at an expense of 27 shillings a
                            ton. The estimated expense of transportation from the Mediterranean over
                            the canal is but eleven shillings a ton, a very material saving.</p>
                        <pb facs="0518" n="1196" xml:id="pg_1196"/>
                        <p>During the period of favorable winds, it is hoped by this route to ship
                            cotton from India, thus avoiding the passage of the Cape of Good Hope,
                            and saving at least 5,000 miles. But since, even at the best season, the
                            rocky and narrow channel of the Red sea is a dangerous one for sailing
                            vessels, Mr. de Lesseps relies greatly on the increased use of the screw
                            as an adjunct to the sail in vessels designed for the India trade. With
                            the existing demand for cotton, and at existing high prices; a
                            practicable canal across the Isthmus would certainly be of vast utility
                            in expediting the great staple to the markets of the world.</p>
                        <p>The practicability of building a sufficient harbor at Port Said, and of
                            resisting the encroachments of the desert sands on the channel of the
                            canal, appears to be generally conceded. Even the most unfriendly
                            critics do not deny it so unhesitatingly as formerly. The panic of
                            danger to British possessions in India, from the increased proximity of
                            France, has subsided. The objection most often repeated is implied in
                            the question, will it pay? The shareholders, it is stated, are the
                            Viceroy and a multitude of small capitalists in Europe, principally
                            French. With his Highness, who has been interested in the project from
                            the beginning, it is a matter of personal pride that it should succeed,
                            and it will not probably fail from any want of support on his part. The
                            works on the isthmus have now almost become one of the regular and
                            necessary sights for the tourist in Egypt.</p>
                        <p>The Viceroy is building three naval steamers in England; one of them is a
                            large iron-clad frigate, intended as a present to the Sultan, who has
                            ordered three more frigates of the same kind on his own account. I may
                            mention here that the news of the achievments of the <hi rend="italic">Monitor</hi> is alleged (I cannot say how truly) to have occasioned
                            the breaking up of a business house which was founded here for the
                            purpose of fulfilling orders for Sicilian oak for the dock-yards of the
                            British navy; whether its contracts were cancelled in prospect of the
                            new age of iron, I am not informed.</p>
                        <p>About two weeks ago the annual pilgrimage of foreign tourists in Egypt
                            began. Five dahabeahs, or travellers’ boats, went up the Nile, the first
                            of the season. But four Americans have as yet arrived.</p>
                        <p>I have neglected to mention that the oldest protégé of the United States
                            in Egypt died at Cairo on the 9th of July of this year. His name was
                            Mohammed Habbat. He was nephew of Hamet Caramalli, ex-Pacha of Tripoli,
                            whom he accompanied on the famous joint expedition of Arabs and American
                            marines under General Eaton, which, in 1805, marched from Egypt across
                            the desert of Barca and captured Derna, (see American State Papers, vol.
                            II, also Life of General Eaton.) In recognition of the services of Hamet
                            Pacha, he and his family and suite, numbering about 50 persons, received
                            at the time papers of American protection, but, notwithstanding his
                            urgent petition, Congress was never induced to reward him in any other
                            way; and 50 years later this Mohammed Habat, then an old man in great
                            poverty, came from Cairo to Washington to supplicate in vain for what he
                            considered our debt to the remnant of his uncle’s descendants. The
                            venerable mussulman, though he left but little property, thought it
                            necessary to leave a will, “in accordance,” (so says the concluding
                            sentence) “with the word of the Prophet which declares, he who makes his
                            will dies in the grace of God.” A wife and one child, a son of about
                            forty, survive him.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your obedient
                            servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM S. THAYER.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>