<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-03-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="521" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d521">
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Webb</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#left">No. 42.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Petropolis</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-03-09"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 9, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The British steam packet Magdalena arrived
                            on the evening of the 5th, bringing despatches Nos. 46, 41, 48, 49, and
                            50; and circulars Nos. 14 and 29.</p>
                        <p>I immediately enclosed to the secretary of foreign affairs a copy of
                            despatch No. 49, and took occasion to cancel so much of my despatch to
                            the Marquis d’Abrantes, in relation to the President’s proclamation of
                            the 22d of September, as conflicted with the spirit of that
                            all-important document, and of which I most cordially and unreservedly
                            approve.</p>
                        <pb facs="0581" n="1259" xml:id="pg_1259"/>
                        <p>The copy of my despatch enclosed herewith will, I trust, prove
                            satisfactory, as it certainly is intended to demonstrate that all that
                            has been done in the way of manumission is in strict compliance with the
                            Constitution and the law.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>J. WATSON WEBB.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Webb</persName> to <persName type="to">the Marquis d’Abrantes</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Petropolis</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-03-07"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 7, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>The undersigned, envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary
                                from the United States, has the honor to enclose to his Excellency
                                the Marquis d’Abrantes, counsellor to his Majesty the Emperor,
                                minister and secretary of state for foreign affairs, a copy of a
                                circular from the Secretary of State of the United States, bearing
                                date the 3d January, 1863, enclosing a proclamation, issued by the
                                President of the United States on the 1st of January, 1863, giving
                                freedom to the slaves held in bondage by the States, and parts of
                                States, in insurrection against the United States on that day. This
                                proclamation was issued in conformity to the pledge contained in the
                                proclamation from the same high source bearing date the 22d of
                                September last, and was resorted to by the Executive as a military
                                necessity. The Constitution gives the President of the United States
                                no right to abolish slavery in those States where it exists under
                                the local law; but both the Constitution and the law invest him with
                                extraordinary powers to put down insurrection, punish traitors, and
                                suppress rebellion; and it was in the legitimate exercise of this
                                necessary war power that the proclamations of the 22d of September
                                and 3d of January were issued, and will produce such mighty results
                                upon the future destinies of the United States. <hi rend="italic">Slavery</hi> can only be abolished under the war power with
                                which the President is clothed, in those districts of the country in
                                open rebellion against the United States. Consequently, it is not
                                abolished in the more northern slave States of Delaware, Maryland,
                                Missouri, Kentucky, and Tennessee, and in certain portions of
                                Virginia and Louisiana. Therefore, the attention of the undersigned
                                has been called to the fact that he committed an error, or wrote
                                hastily, when he said, as he did in the copy sent to Washington, of
                                his note to your excellency of the 3d of November last, that the
                                proclamation of the 22d of September “<hi rend="italic">manumits on
                                    the first of January next all the slaves in the United
                                    States.</hi>”</p>
                            <p>The phrase should have read, “<hi rend="italic">virtually</hi>
                                manumits on the first day of January next all the slaves in the
                                United States;” and if the word “<hi rend="italic">virtually”</hi>
                                is engrossed in the copy of the despatch sent to your excellency, it
                                is well; if not, it should be substituted; because the Executive of
                                the United States never claimed, and has never attempted to
                                exercise, the power of manumitting slaves, except where their
                                masters were in open insurrection, and their property thereby had,
                                under the law and the Constitution, become forfeited to the
                                government of the United States.</p>
                            <p>The slave population of the United States, by the census of 1860, was
                                3,953,760; and in round numbers may be put down at <hi rend="italic">four millions.</hi> The circular from the State Department,
                                herewith enclosed, communicates the pleasing intelligence, that by
                                the proclamation of the 1st of January, 1863, “the number of slaves
                                thus restored to freedom is about three and one-half <pb facs="0582" n="1260" xml:id="pg_1260"/> millions,” or <hi rend="italic">seven-eighths</hi> of the whole number. And thus, that
                                proclamation “virtual” gives freedom to all; because the moral
                                effect of thus confiscating, and, as a war measure, emancipating <hi rend="italic">seven-eighths</hi> of our slave population,
                                secures the freedom of the remaining <hi rend="italic">one-eighth</hi> by purchase from their owners.</p>
                            <p>I have, also, the honor to enclose a circular from the Postmaster
                                General of the United States, naming the 2d Monday in May next as a
                                convenient day for the meeting <hi rend="italic">at Paris</hi> of
                                the International Postal Convention, and I am instructed to invite
                                the special attention of the Brazilian government to this
                                interesting subject.</p>
                            <p>The undersigned avails himself of this occasion to reiterate to your
                                excellency his sentiments of respect and most distinguished
                                consideration.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>J. WATSON WEBB.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency the <hi rend="smallcaps">Marquis d’Abrantes</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Councillor to his Imperial Majesty,
                                        &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>