<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-09-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="553" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d553">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Fogg.</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 26.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-09-26"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 26, 1862,</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your despatch of September 4 (No. 22) has
                            been received. Doubtless you are right in supposing that it is difficult
                            for the truth in relation to the social condition of this country to
                            make its way to the people <pb facs="0630" n="1308" xml:id="pg_1308"/>
                            of Europe against the statements of an interested or prejudiced press.
                            But the great facts, of millions of acres of unoccupied and fertile
                            lands awaiting cultivators, and increasing demands for bread for our own
                            growing armies, manufacturing towns, and mining districts, while there
                            is a diversion by the hundreds of thousands of our industrial population
                            into the occupations of war, must in the end overcome all
                            misrepresentations and reach classes in Europe who are suffering for
                            want of employment. It is not practically true that there is a
                            deficiency of soldiers in the country. All the early requisitions were
                            promptly filled. Four hundred thousand have volunteered within two
                            months under the two last calls for an aggregate of six hundred
                            thousand, and one month more will bring in the remainder almost without
                            a doubt. On the other hand, those who immigrate can choose peaceful
                            labor or military service when they arrive, as the armies are always
                            ready for recruits to fill vacancies. I trust, therefore, that
                            immigration will prove more rapid than you have apprehended.</p>
                        <p>The subject of favoring military immigration by offering special
                            inducements in Europe has been often submitted to the War Department,
                            but it has not yet thought it necessary or expedient to adopt any means
                            of that kind.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi> G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Fogg</hi>,
                                Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., Berne.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>