<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Coffey to to Mr. Seward.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d601</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">601</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-07-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-07-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="601"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d601">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Coffey</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward.</persName>
                </head>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">CONSTRUCTION OF THE SECOND SECTION OF THE ACT OF
                    JULY 17, 1862, CHAP. 195, AND ITS BEARING ON AMERICAN VESSELS DESPATCHED TO A
                    NEUTRAL PORT IN BALLAST.</note>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <hi rend="italic">Opinion of the Attorney General.</hi>
                </note>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General’s Office</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-07-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 27, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your letter of the 14th instant, enclosing certain correspondence with the
                    Secretary of the Treasury and the United States consul at Nassau with the
                    Department of State, and <pb facs="0669" n="1347" xml:id="pg_1347"/> submitting
                    for my opinion the question suggested by the consul at Nassau, viz: Whether the
                    act of despatching an American vessel to a neutral port in ballast, though its
                    ultimate destination as a blockade runner is all but certain, is an offence
                    against the laws of the United States, and for which arrests may be made, and
                    parties concerned in such enterprises may be prosecuted, and, if convicted,
                    punished.</p>
                <p>The 2d section of the act of July 17, 1862, chapter 195, to suppress
                    insurrection, to punish treason and rebellion, to seize and confiscate the
                    property of rebels, and for other purposes, enacts that if any person shall
                    hereafter incite, set on foot, <hi rend="italic">assist</hi>, or engage in any
                    rebellion or insurrection against the authority of the United States, or the
                    laws thereof, <hi rend="italic">or shall give aid or comfort thereto</hi>, or
                    shall engage in, <hi rend="italic">or give aid and comfort to, any such existing
                        rebellion or insurrection</hi>, and be convicted thereof, such persons shall
                    be punished by imprisonment for a period not exceeding ten years, or by a fine
                    not exceeding ten thousand dollars, and by the liberation of all his slaves, if
                    any he have, or by both of said punishments, at the discretion of the court.</p>
                <p>The act of despatching an American vessel from any port of the United States to a
                    neutral port in ballast, with the purpose of taking in cargo at that port, and
                    running the blockade therefrom, would, in my opinion, bring the person or
                    persons so despatching her within the penalties of the above cited section, if
                    the vessel, in the execution of that purpose, actually ran the blockade. This
                    would be an overt act of assistance, or aid and comfort to the rebellion, such
                    as the law prohibits. To secure the conviction of the person or persons who
                    despatched the vessel, it would, of course, be essential to prove the existence
                    of the guilty purpose in so doing.</p>
                <p>I am also of opinion that the act of despatching an American vessel to a neutral
                    port in ballast, with the ascertained purpose of taking in cargo at that port,
                    and running the blockade therefrom, would subject the person or persons so
                    despatching her to the penalties of this law, if, in pursuance and in execution
                    of that purpose, the vessel actually attempted to run the blockade, but in the
                    attempt was captured, or otherwise prevented from so doing by a blockading
                    vessel.</p>
                <p>The question whether the mere act of despatching an American vessel to a neutral
                    port in ballast, for the purpose of running the blockade therefrom, not followed
                    by an actual running, or attempt to run, the blockade, would, of itself,
                    constitute an offence within and punishable by our criminal statutes, deserves
                    careful consideration. The 2d section of the act of July 17, 1862, provides
                    comprehensively enough for the punishment of the offence of actually inciting,
                    setting on foot, assisting or engaging in rebellion or insurrection, or of
                    giving aid or comfort thereto, or of engaging in, or giving aid or comfort to,
                    an existing rebellion or insurrection; but it fails to include the class of acts
                    which, whilst done with the <hi rend="italic">intent</hi> to do these things, do
                    not of themselves amount to actual assistance, or aid and comfort to the
                    rebellion or insurrection.</p>
                <p>The question, then, is, whether the act of despatching an American vessel from a
                    port of the United States to a neutral port in ballast, with the ascertained
                    purpose of there taking in cargo to run the blockade, of itself amounts to
                    actual assistance, or aid and comfort to the rebellion, within the statute. I
                    think it does, for this reason: Such a vessel started from an American port with
                    intent to run the blockade, would, in my opinion, be subject to lawful capture
                    as prize of war from the moment she left that port. It is a well-settled
                    principle in the law of blockade that the act of sailing with an intent to break
                    a blockade is deemed a sufficient breach to authorize confiscation. From that
                    moment the blockade is fraudulently invaded, and the vessel is liable to
                    capture, without reference to the distance between the port of departure and the
                    blockaded port, or to the extent of the voyage performed.—(3 Phil., 390–406, and
                    cases cited; 5 Cranch, 343–’9; ib., 440, Story, J.) Whether a neutral vessel <pb
                        facs="0670" n="1348" xml:id="pg_1348"/> proceeding from one neutral port to
                    another neutral port, with the intent there to take in cargo, and from thence to
                    run the blockade, is liable to capture and condemnation before she reaches the
                    port at which she is to receive her cargo, it is not necessary now to decide,
                    although, from the language of Lord Stowell, in <hi rend="italic">The Jonge
                        Pieter</hi>, (4 Rob., 89,) I infer that such was his opinion. But however
                    this may be, he distinctly asserts, in that case, that if a subject of the
                    blockading country ship goods to go to the enemy <hi rend="italic">through a
                        neutral country</hi>, they are liable to capture and condemnation. For, as
                    he says, “without the license of government no communication, direct or
                    indirect, can be carried on with the enemy. * * * * * <hi rend="italic">The
                        interposition of a prior port makes no difference; all trade with the enemy
                        is illegal, and the circumstances that the goods are to go first to a
                        neutral port will not make it lawful.</hi>” Of course, if the goods shipped
                    on such a venture nay be condemned, a vessel started from a port of the
                    blockading country with the intent to take in cargo at a neutral port, and from
                    thence run the blockade, and thus to hold illicit intercourse with the enemy, is
                    equally guilty and liable to capture and condemnation.</p>
                <p>If, then, an American vessel starting from an American port in ballast, with such
                    a purpose, be a lawful prize of war, it follows, that, from the time of her
                    departure for the neutral port, it is as much the duty of our cruisers to
                    capture her as if she were actually entering a blockaded port with full cargo.
                    And the moment she is placed in this predicament the persons who despatched her
                    on her guilty errand became liable to the penalties of the 2d section of the act
                    of July 17, 1862. For, whenever the vessel they have started is in such a
                    position as to impose on our cruisers the duty of arresting her voyage by her
                    capture, then these persons have actually and materially assisted the rebellion
                    by adding to the duties of our cruisers that of pursuing and capturing her,
                    which involves, necessarily, their withdrawal, for the time, from other service.
                    If necessary, it would be easy to illustrate, in a variety of ways, the
                    effective assistance which might be rendered to the rebellion by the mere act of
                    despatching vessels in ballast to neutral ports, with the ultimate purpose of
                    running the blockade. The right, and consequent duty, of capturing such vessels
                    off our coast, before they reach the intermediate neutral ports, might well give
                    so much employment to our navy as to diminish its effectiveness elsewhere, or
                    require a considerable addition to its force. To create this necessity would, in
                    contemplation of law, be to assist and give aid and comfort to the rebellion in
                    a form only less aggravated than the actual fitting out of vessels of war for
                    rebel use. And of this offence, within the terms of the statute I have cited,
                    are those persons guilty, in my opinion, who despatch American vessels in
                    ballast from our own ports, with intent to stop at neutral ports, and, after
                    there taking in cargo, from thence to run the blockade. The unlawful purpose
                    being established, the offence is committed whenever the vessel shall have
                    started on her voyage, whether it be consummated at the blockaded port or be
                    arrested after she has left, or before she has reached the intermediate neutral
                    port.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>TITIAN J. COFFEY, <hi rend="italic">Attorney General ad interim.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Wm.</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Seward</hi>, <hi
                            rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
