<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Embassy in Venezuela</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-01-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="124"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">831.01/1–1349: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Venezuela</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-13">January 13,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>12. Dept feels exchange of views with other <gloss target="#t_AmReps1">Amer
                        Reps</gloss> and its press release Dec 21<note n="1" xml:id="d124fn1">For
                        text, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, January 2,
                        1949, p. 30.</note> have made clear our belief use of force as instrument
                    political change of duly elected Govts inconsistent ideals <gloss
                        target="#t_AmReps1">Amer Reps</gloss>. Dept also convinced non-recognition
                    not suitable approach to problem and concludes no useful purpose would be served
                    in further delaying resumption normal relations with Ven Govt.</p>
                <p>You shld therefore on Jan 21 send or in ur discretion deliver in person to <gloss
                        target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> note replying his note Nov 25. Subject
                    any changes you deem advisable, which shld be approved in advance by Dept, text
                    reply shld be as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have the honor to ack receipt of Your Excellency’s note dated Nov 25,
                            1948 informing me that a Military Junta of Govt has been constituted
                            under the Presidency of Lt. Colonel Carlos Delgado Chalbaud in which
                            Your Excellency has been designated to serve as Minister of Foreign
                            Relations.</p>
                        <p>“My Govt has noted Your Excellency’s statement that the new
                            administration will strictly fulfill its international obligations. It
                            has also noted a passage in an address delivered on Nov. 26, 1948 by His
                            Excellency the President of the Junta in which it is stated that the
                            Junta will prepare for elections in which all citizens will participate
                            under conditions of equality.</p>
                        <p>“My Govt attaches importance to this statement particularly in view of a
                            cardinal principle found in the Charter of the Organization of Amer
                            States, namely: <pb facs="0168" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>‘The solidarity of the Amer States and the high aims which are
                                    sought through it require the political organization of those
                                    States on the basis of the effective exercise of representative
                                    democracy’.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>“Under instructions from my Govt, I have the honor to express to Your
                            Excellency the hope that the cordial relations which have long existed
                            between Ven and the US will continue unimpaired.</p>
                        <p>“Accept, Excellency, the assurances of my highest consideration.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Upon receipt advice ur note has been delivered Dept will issue press release
                    including texts two notes.<note n="2" xml:id="d124fn2">Department of State <hi
                            rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, February 6, 1949, pp. 172–173.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Govts <gloss target="#t_OAR1">OAR</gloss> and Canada being informed our proposed
                    action.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
