<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Charles C. Hauch of the
                        Division of Caribbean Affairs</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d129</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">129</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="mediation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846" lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-01-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="129" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">731.39/1–2148</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Charles C. Hauch of the
                        Division of Caribbean Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-21">January 21,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Dominican-Venezuelan-Haitian Relations; Dominican
                    requests for planes and ships.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Ambassador Luis F. Thomen—Dominican Republic</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Daniels—Director, <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Hauch—<gloss target="#t_CRB1">CRB</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The Dominican Ambassador called by appointment to discuss general matters of
                    interest. He presented a note (copy in translation attached<note n="1" xml:id="d129fn1">Not printed.</note>) and then outlined its contents. He
                    stated that the Dominican Government in advising the Department of Venezuelan
                    activities against his country had not intended to seek our good offices as a
                    mediator in the affair, but had merely desired to inform us of events. He went
                    on to say that nevertheless the Dominican Government while not seeking mediation
                    would be disposed to accept mediation spontaneously offered by one or more other
                    governments or by some qualified organ of the inter-American system. He added
                    that it would be especially satisfying to the Dominican Government if any such
                    mediation could obtain from the Cuban and Venezuelan Governments an official and
                    public statement that they will not permit on their territory the formation of
                    revolutionary expeditions against the Dominican Republic. (<hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> In his remarks the Ambassador stated that this mediation might
                    be through the American Government, or a combination of several governments, or
                    through an organ of the inter-American system, whereas the note he presented
                    referred simply to good offices or mediation by the American Government or any
                    other government.)</p>
                <p>Mr. Daniels stated the Dominican suggestion was an interesting one and without
                    agreeing to the tendering of good offices or mediation by this Government
                    indicated that he would informally sound out the Venezuelan Ambassador with
                    regard to the Dominican proposal of an official public statement. Mr. Daniels
                    said that the Venezuelan Ambassador might inquire whether the Dominican
                    Government would likewise issue such a statement regarding activities on
                    Dominican soil against Venezuela. The Ambassador said he had no instructions on
                    this point, but would make inquiry. He said that personally he thought this
                    might be possible. (<hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> Despatch No. 17 of January 6
                    from Ciudad Trujillo<note n="1" xml:id="d129fn2">Not printed.</note> transmitted
                    an official Dominican Foreign Office press release denying that the Dominican
                    Government is aiding or tolerating a conspiracy against the Venezuelan
                    Government. This was <pb facs="0176" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/> published in the
                    Ciudad Trujillo newspaper <hi rend="italic">La Nacion</hi>. It is intemperate in
                    language and would probably serve to keep the pot boiling rather than to calm it
                    down.)</p>
                <p>The Ambassador inferred that Haiti’s participation in any revolutionary activity
                    depended upon the existence of such activity in other countries and that by
                    itself Haiti would not be used as a base of operations. As for Guatemala, he
                    said that country is too far away to serve as a jumping off place for an attack
                    on the Dominican Republic.</p>
                <p>Mr. Daniels then informed the Ambassador of the circular telegram of January 17
                    sent to our diplomatic missions in the other American republics advising them
                    regarding our intention to comply with our international obligations on
                    revolutionary activities and expressing our confidence that other governments
                    would do likewise.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador stated that he had received information that Juan Bosch and a
                    brother of President Arévalo of Guatemala had very recently arrived in Venezuela
                    and were conferring with one another. Mr. Daniels said that we understood
                    certain Venezuelan exiles were residing in the Dominican Republic and that
                    several such Venezuelans upon arriving at Ciudad Trujillo had been received by
                    General Fiallo.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then referred to the Dominican desire for planes and ships. He
                    observed that Cuba had obtained warships from the United States. He added that
                    we had, of course, indicated our willingness to license the export of certain
                    vessels into the Dominican Republic, but that the vessels available from surplus
                    stocks were in poor condition. …</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
