<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            Embassy in the Dominican Republic
                    
                    Copies were sent to the Embassies in Cuba and
                        Haiti.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d155</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">155</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-09-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-09-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="155" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d155">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">737.39/9–1648: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in the Dominican Republic</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d155fn1">Copies were sent to the Embassies in Cuba and
                        Haiti.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-16">September 16,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–126. With reference to the consideration of Dominican charges against Cuba
                    before the Inter-American Commission on Methods for the Peaceful Solution of
                    Conflicts (Committee of Five), the following is the text of a press release
                    issued by the Commission on September 9: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Inter-American Commission on Methods for the Peaceful Solution of
                            Conflicts met at 4 p. m. on Thursday, September 9, 1948 to consider the
                            matter submitted on August 13, 1948 by the Special Delegation of the
                            Dominican Republic now in Washington.</p>
                        <p>“The following members of the Commission attended the meeting: Ambassador
                            Luis Quintanilla, Representative of Mexico and Chairman of the
                            Commission; Ambassador Enrique V. Corominas, Representative of
                            Argentina; Ambassador Paul 0. Daniels, Representative of the United
                            States; Doctor Sergio Correa da Costa, Representative of Brazil; Dr.
                            Ricardo Sarabasa, Representative of Cuba.</p>
                        <p>“The following members of the Special Delegation of the Dominican
                            Republic were present: Ambassador Julio Ortega Frier, Chairman;
                            Ambassador Joaquín Salazar; Ambassador Arturo Despradel and Minister
                            José Ramón Rodríguez.</p>
                        <p>“The Commission has already given careful consideration to the Note and
                            accompanying documents delivered by the Dominican Delegation.</p>
                        <p>“As soon as the Commission was requested to intervene, its Chairman and
                            members immediately proceeded to exchange views with the Representatives
                            of the interested Parties for the purpose of finding a friendly manner
                            of resolving their differences of opinion.</p>
                        <p>“As a result of the good services of the Commission, and of the special
                            session held today, the Commission is pleased to announce that the
                            Representatives of Cuba and the Representatives of the Dominican
                            Republic have willingly accepted the suggestion of the Commission that
                            direct negotiations be carried out through the usual official channels
                                <pb facs="0204" n="188" xml:id="pg_188"/> for the purpose of
                            settling the matter in a way satisfactory to both. This, the Commission
                            feels, can be accomplished without difficulty.</p>
                        <p>“The Commission is pleased to state that the happy results attained in
                            this case—a notable instance of fair international behavior—is due
                            principally to the good will manifested by the Commission and in the
                            exchange of friendly conversations between themselves, were always
                            motivated by the highest feeling of American fraternity, and by the
                            spirit of unshakeable solidarity characteristic of inter-American
                            relations.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
