<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-01-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="167" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d167">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">810.20 Defense/1–648</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of
                                State</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-06">January 6, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                <cell>Mr. George C. Marshall, Secretary of State</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Señor Dr. Antonio Parra Velasco, Ecuadoran Foreign
                                    Minister</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Señor Augusto Dillon, Ecuadoran Ambassador in
                                    Washington</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. George H. Owen, <gloss target="#t_NWC1">NWC</gloss><note n="2" xml:id="d167fn1">Foreign Affairs Specialist, Division
                                        of North and West Coast Affairs.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>After a while of pleasant conversation about politically indifferent
                            subjects, I mentioned a plan I had favored immediately after the war,
                            but which it was impossible to carry out, for the rapid development of
                            air transport systems in Latin America with the use of surplus U.S.
                            bombers and transports, concerning which Dr. Parra indicated
                            considerable interest.</p>
                        <p>I then spoke at some length of certain aspects of hemispheric defense. I
                            recalled the critical times preceding and during American participation
                            in the last war, when I was confronted with the repeated appeals of
                            several Latin American countries, gravely concerned about the inadequacy
                            of their coastal defenses. I pointed out that during the war, Japanese
                            submarines, properly directed, could easily have shelled important
                            industrial installations on the shores of certain West Coast
                            countries.</p>
                        <p>I mentioned the difficulties which were then and have now to be met in
                            planning adequate continental defense, in particular the political
                            repercussions in the several countries of any negotiations for the
                            installation of needed defense sites. I remarked on the propensity of
                            political factions everywhere to make political capital of defense site
                            agreements on the basis of vaunting “national sovereignty”. I recalled
                            how during the war negotiations for vital defense installations in the
                            Dutch West Indies against submarine attacks were prolonged by the Dutch
                            Government and imperiled the whole continent. <pb facs="0224" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/> I made particular reference to the current
                            situation with respect to the defense sites in Panama,<note n="3" xml:id="d167fn2">For documentation on this subject, see <ref target="#pg_664">pp. 664</ref> ff.</note> pointing to the
                            imperative need for adequate defense of the Canal, which the Republic of
                            Panama is utterly unable to insure by itself and the importance of which
                            to the whole continent may not be fully realized in Latin American
                            countries.</p>
                        <p>I then turned to the need for developing the natural resources of the
                            continent, in particular oil resources and remarked that the growing
                            requirements and consumption of petroleum products render the
                            development of Latin American oil resources imperative.<note n="4" xml:id="d167fn3">For documentation on this subject, see <ref target="#pg_243">pp. 243</ref> ff.</note> I indicated that,
                            while I entertained no preference as to the manner under which
                            arrangements for such development should be made, my principal desire
                            was that the development be undertaken as rapidly as possible, since the
                            question of oil supply was a critical defense problem and our resources
                            have been heavily drawn upon.</p>
                        <p>More than once I invited Dr. Parra to speak about any matter he might
                            wish to discuss. The Foreign Minister merely repeated that he had
                            listened with immeasurable interest to everything I had said and then
                            discussed briefly the matter of his government’s boundary dispute with
                            Peru in the Lagartococha area,<note n="5" xml:id="d167fn4">Documentation
                                on this subject not published.</note> which he had already taken up
                            at length with Mr. Armour<note n="6" xml:id="d167fn5">Norman Armour,
                                Assistant Secretary of State for Political Affairs.</note>
                            yesterday. I indicated that I knew the principal question at issue in
                            this dispute and that I would have the matter studied.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>