<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        North and West Coast Affairs (Espy)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d240</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">240</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-17T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="240" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d240">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">824.154/5–1748</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        North and West Coast Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Espy</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-17">May 17,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Bolivian Ambassador, Sr. Don Ricardo Martinez
                            Vargas</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Assistant Secretary of State, Norman
                            Armour</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">
                            <gloss target="#t_NWC1">NWC</gloss>, James Espy</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>During his call on Mr. Armour this morning Ambassador Martinez Vargas brought up
                    the question of the delay in the reinitiation of work on the Cochabamba–Santa
                    Cruz Highway, suspended since December, 1947.<note n="2" xml:id="d240fn1">For
                        documentation on the cancellation of the highway construction contract
                        between the Bolivian Development Corporation (an agency of the Bolivian
                        Government) and the McGraw-Warren Company, see despatch 1959 of December 19,
                        1947 and other documentation on this subject, <ref target="frus1947v08#pg_359">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 359</ref>–<ref target="frus1947v08#pg_363">363</ref>.</note> The Ambassador said that
                    five months had now passed and that although negotiations have been held with
                    the Export-Import Bank since the beginning of the year for reorganization of the
                    highway project, no final arrangements had yet been made to get the construction
                    of the road again underway. In the meantime the Bolivian Development Corporation
                    with the limited funds at its disposal was trying to keep a minimum of work
                    going on. However, its funds would soon be exhausted and unless arrangements
                    were made for repair of the equipment, final engineering plans and a new
                    contract, financed by further credits from the Export-Import Bank, the whole
                    project would come to a dead stop. In that event, it would be very costly to the
                    Corporation because of the large discharge payments which the Corporation would
                    have to make to the highway laborers. Besides this consideration there was, the
                    Ambassador stated, much dissatisfaction in his country over the length of time
                    it was taking to build the highway. In this latter connection he referred to the
                    Brazilian and Argentine efforts to push through railroads from the <pb facs="0346" n="330" xml:id="pg_330"/> respective borders of their countries
                    to the city of Santa Cruz and he stressed that it was of paramount importance
                    both politically and economically to Bolivia and from an international point of
                    view to South America that the highway, forming the communication link between
                    Santa Cruz and the rest of Bolivia, be completed before the railroads are
                    finished from Brazil and Argentina.</p>
                <p>Mr. Epsy informed the Ambassador that the Bolivian exasperation over the slowness
                    in the completion of the highway was understandable, but that he, the
                    Ambassador, would realize the number of necessary steps which had to be taken to
                    reorganize the work and put it this time on a sound basis. Such steps took time.
                    However, the Export-Import Bank was actively engaged in assisting the
                    Corporation to this end and was at the moment endeavoring to engage the services
                    of a competent engineer to study and review the plans and specifications of the
                    highway, consider the best way of repairing the equipment and make an estimate
                    of the final cost to complete the highway preparatory to concluding a new
                    construction contract.</p>
                <p>At the close of the conversation Ambassador Martinez Vargas informed Mr. Armour
                    that he would prepare a memorandum<note n="3" xml:id="d240fn2">Not
                        printed.</note> on the subject and present it to the Department.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
