<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Telephone Conversations, by the Assistant Chief of the Division
                    of Brazilian Affairs ( (Clark) ) With the Ambassador in Brazil (
                    (Pawley))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d274</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">274</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-03-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="274"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d274">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.51/3–2448</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversations, by the Assistant Chief
                        of the Division of Brazilian Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clark</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">With the Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pawley</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-24">March 24,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>On Tuesday, March 23, I telephoned the Ambassador in Rio de Janeiro and discussed
                    with him, among other matters, the problem of the renewal of the Brazilian
                    Stabilization Agreement with the U.S. Treasury. I advised him that arrangements
                    apparently had progressed in a satisfactory manner between the Brazilian
                    authorities and the Federal Reserve Bank in New York City and that the Federal
                    Reserve <pb facs="0395" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> Bank was willing to take over
                    the $80,000,000 from the U.S. Treasury. Presumably this credit, which is backed
                    by Brazilian gold, would be repayable in the amount of $40,000,000 in nine
                    months and the balance of $40,000,000 at the conclusion of the annual
                    period.</p>
                <p>Reports have been received that the Federal Reserve Bank in New York City on
                    March 12 sent a telegram to the Bank of Brazil in Rio de Janeiro outlining its
                    tentative acceptance of the Brazilian credit and requesting certain information.
                    No reply has so far been received to this telegram from the Bank of Brazil and I
                    mentioned this to the Ambassador in the hope that he or some one else in the
                    Embassy might be able to discuss this subject with possibly Vieira Machado in
                    the Bank of Brazil and encourage the Bank of Brazil to reply to the Federal
                    Reserve Bank in New York without further delay. In the course of our
                    conversation, the Ambassador mentioned that shortly before his departure from
                    Washington he had discussed this subject with the President and the President
                    had indicated his desire that the Treasury continue its arrangement for Brazil
                    rather than have the Brazilians go to the Federal Reserve Bank in New York City.
                    The Ambassador suggested, therefore, that before any mention was made of the
                    Federal Reserve Bank telegram to the Bank of Brazil authorities it would be best
                    to query the appropriate authorities in the U.S. Treasury Department as to
                    whether or not a final definite decision had been taken on this matter.</p>
                <p>I subsequently talked with both Mr. Wiggins<note n="1" xml:id="d274fn1">Under
                        Secretary of the Treasury.</note> and Mr. Southard of the Treasury
                    Department. Both stated that it had been decided that it would be preferable for
                    the Brazilians to deal with the Federal Reserve Bank in New York City. Mr.
                    Southard stated that he personally had handled the matter at the request of
                    Secretary Snyder and that the Secretary had assured him that he was quite
                    confident that the President would be satisfied if the arrangement with the
                    Federal Reserve Bank in New York gave the Brazilians the same facilities as
                    those afforded heretofore by the Treasury Department.</p>
                <p>Mr. Southard explained that, while the Treasury has no desire to close the door
                    definitely on the Brazilian request for a renewal of the Agreement, the Treasury
                    is desirous of mobilizing those funds which are available in anticipation of a
                    drain from European sources. Mr. Southard stated that he had the assurances of
                    the Federal Reserve Bank in New York City that an advantageous deal could be
                    worked out with the Brazilians and that the cost, in actual fact, would be less
                    than if the Agreement was to be renewed by the Treasury. Mr. Southard also added
                    a confidential mention of the fact that the Treasury finds itself in a rather
                    anomalous position with Brazil, that is, carrying <pb facs="0396" n="380"
                        xml:id="pg_380"/> such a credit while at the same time Brazil has made no
                    attempt whatsoever to participate in the International Fund. Mr. Southard
                    implied that Brazil’s position was inconsistent, to say the least, and that
                    while no one wished to force Brazil into joining <gloss target="#t_TheFund1">the
                        Fund</gloss>, he did feel that the Brazilians could maintain independence of
                    action much better if the Stabilization Agreement was transferred to the Federal
                    Reserve Bank in New York City on a more or less strictly commercial basis.</p>
                <p>On Wednesday, March 24, at approximately 2:15 p. m., I again telephoned the
                    Ambassador at Rio de Janeiro and informed him of the results of my conversations
                    with Mr. Wiggins and Mr. Southard of the Treasury Department. He seemed
                    perfectly satisfied and stated that, after all, it was a decision which would
                    have to be made by the Treasury. At my request, he indicated that some one from
                    the Embassy would immediately get in touch with the people at the Bank of Brazil
                    to attempt to see that a reply to the March 12 telegram from the Federal Reserve
                    Bank in New York City is despatched without further delay.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">DuWayne</hi> G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Clark</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
