<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            Embassy in Chile</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d309</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">309</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-08-20T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-08-20T16:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-20T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-20T16:00:00-05:00" n="309" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d309">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.516 Export-Import Bank/8–2048: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in Chile</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-20T17:00:00-04:00">August 20, 1948—5 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>317. Board Directors <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss> Aug 18
                    considered application Fabrica Victoria de Puente Alto for credit $2 million to
                    finance purchases US equipment services for expansion of its plant in Chile for
                    production and spinning rayon filament yarn and staple fibers. <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss> concluded that credit $1.2 million
                    would be ample to meet company’s needs and be a loan which company could repay
                    without undue burden. Board approved credit this amount to be repaid in 5 years
                    with interest 4½ percent. Credit to be covered by unconditional guarantee <pb facs="0446" n="430" xml:id="pg_430"/> Bank Chile as to repayment principal
                    and interest with satisfactory exchange assurances to be given by appropriate
                    Chile Govt agency.</p>
                <p>Board also approved request by Machine Affiliates Inc on behalf of group Amer
                    machine tool and other manufacturers for credit to assist financing sale
                    $650,000 worth machine tools cranes and foundry equipment to Manufacturera de
                    Metales (Mademsa). Purchasers to pay 25 percent cash and Amer exporters to
                    participate in financing to extent another 25 percent. <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss> to finance balance about $375,000 to
                    be repaid in about 3½ years with interest 4½ percent. Credit to be guaranteed by
                    Bank Chile and dollar exchange to be assured by Govt Chile.</p>
                <p>Dept refers to statement <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 545 Aug 12<note n="1" xml:id="d309fn1">Not printed.</note> that “apparent past policy not
                    make govt loans to private enterprises”. This has never been policy <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss>. Bank prepared at all times to
                    consider on their merits applications from private enterprises. The facilities
                    of <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1">Eximbank</gloss> are open to US exporters to US
                    importers and to foreign govts the agencies of foreign govts and foreign firms
                    and nationals.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
