<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Costa Rica (
                        Davis
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d353</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">353</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-03-25T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-25T14:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-25T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-25T14:00:00-05:00" n="353" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d353">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">818.00/3–2548: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Costa Rica</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">San José</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-25T13:00:00-06:00">March 25, 1948—1 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>116. On instructions from President and with specific request it be considered
                    confidential between me and my government, Foreign Minister last night told me
                    former changed position of regarding question of selection first designate as
                    purely a matter between two major parties and now has taken active role in
                    endeavor work out satisfactory compromise. Appointed Bonilla Lara and Minister
                    Government <pb facs="0517" n="501" xml:id="pg_501"/> Quesada to endeavor obtain
                    agreement on competent person. Actual negotiations and detailed conversations
                    carried out by Fernando Palau, former journalist on <hi rend="italic">Prensa
                        Libre</hi>. Thus far conversations not far advanced due insistence Ulate on
                    selection person not previously connected with public life while President
                    insists necessity figure having certain Parliamentary support and experience
                    management political affairs.</p>
                <p>Bonilla Lara said every effort being made push matters through this weekend when
                    business banks et cetera closed for Holy Week. Said majority Congress favorable
                    and considered once candidate agreed upon deputies would give President written
                    pledge ratify selection May first. Foreign Minister appeared neither optimistic
                    nor unduly pessimistic. However names he mentioned have all already been
                    considered in earlier discussions under auspices Bankers Association without
                    success. Nevertheless possible agreement be reached due urgency arising present
                    political military situation.</p>
                <p>Sent Department only.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
