<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="408" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d408">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/3–248</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Norweb</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                <lb/> No. 165</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-02">March 2,
                                1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to forward the following
                            comments regarding the political implications in Cuba of the recent
                            purchase by the United States of one million tons of Cuban sugar outside
                            the United States quota.<note n="1" xml:id="d408fn1">Translation of
                                Decree no. 586 providing for the segregation of 1,250,000 long tons
                                of Cuban sugar of the 1948 crop, was published in the <hi rend="italic">Gaceta Oficial</hi> of February 26 and effective
                                on that date; before the Decree was drawn up in final form,
                                agreement had already been reached on the sale of 1,000,000 short
                                tons of this segregated quantity for the use of the United States
                                Army in Occupied Areas. This sale left Cuba with an estimated
                                “surplus” of only about 420,000 short tons (370,000 long), according
                                to despatch 190, March 9, 1948 from Habana, not printed
                                (837.61351/3–948).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The recent agreement by which the United States purchased one million
                            tons of Cuban sugar outside of the United States quota has special
                            political implications coming as it has only three months before general
                            elections in Cuba. It will claim a leading place among the chief
                            accomplishments of the Auténtico Administration and thus contribute
                            immeasurably to its prospects of success at the polls. This transaction
                            has afforded additional political leverage from the fact that publicity,
                            chiefly of Cuban origin, has created the widespread impression that the
                            Administration not only initiated the negotiations but by exceptionally
                            astute effort concluded the contract, so advantageous to Cuba’s
                            principal source of national wealth and employment. This distortion of
                            the facts was made possible because the Cuban Ambassador in Washington,
                            Ghillermo Belt, was afforded an unprecedented opportunity for that
                            purpose by the inept manner in which publicity was handled by our news
                            agencies in Washington. Practically no publicity emphasizing the fact
                            that the United States initiated the negotiations <pb facs="0567" n="551" xml:id="pg_551"/> and that most of this sugar would probably
                            be given away has appeared in Cuba.</p>
                        <p>In the last two or three months one of the most critical questions in
                            Cuba has been the disposal of the 1948 sugar crop. It could have been a
                            tremendous factor against the Administration in the June 1948 elections.
                            The shortage of dollar exchange throughout the world and the inability
                            of Cuba to deal in any other currency made it seem very likely that a
                            huge surplus would remain unsold this year. Despite this, however, in
                            answer to labor pressure the Administration went ahead in December and
                            decreed that the high 1947 wages should be paid during the 1948
                            crop—thus apparently going way out “on a limb”. Now, however, the Grau
                            Administration is able to say that it took the necessary steps for the
                            sale of one million tons of sugar outside the United States quota, that
                            it refused the first offer of the United States of 3 and ½ cents as too
                            low, and that it forced the price up to 4 cents a pound (a price above
                            the average which might have been anticipated if any effort to dispose
                            of a large amount of sugar on the world market had been necessary).
                            Although the internal difficulties in the Auténtico Party continue
                            unsolved and although the events of the last two months would not
                            normally have enhanced the prestige of the Administration, the
                            completion of the sugar deal has given the Grau Government a most
                            powerful political card.</p>
                        <p>This coup was accomplished by Belt and President Grau despite the fact
                            that when Belt was negotiating in Washington he had no sugar to sell and
                            when he and Grau were negotiating in Cuba with the mill owners and cane
                            growers they had no definite purchaser. By the use of clever maneuvering
                            they have managed, however, to bring the deal off, a triumph for which
                            the Cuban Government has not been obliged to give any <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> whatsoever.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Norweb</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>