<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1985-11-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1985-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="142" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                        <head>142. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SPR_1">Peter
                                Sommer</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d142fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_CT_1">Tyrus Cobb</persName> Files, Country File, <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> 1985 (12); NLR–98–5–20–7–9.
                                Secret. Sent for action. <persName corresp="#p_MJF_1">Matlock</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LRE_1">Linhard</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_CT_1">Cobb</persName> concurred, with <persName corresp="#p_SPR_1">Sommer</persName> initialing for <persName corresp="#p_MJF_1">Matlock</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_LRE_1">Linhard</persName>. An unknown hand wrote “Copy for Ty” in the
                                upper right-hand corner.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1985-11-12">November 12, 1985</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>SWM Breakfast, Wednesday, November 13: Meeting with <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d142fn2">SWM: <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WCW_1">Weinberger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>.</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>My understanding is that tomorrow’s weekly breakfast agenda will have
                            only one topic: the President’s meetings with General Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>. Defense
                            reportedly has asked that Geneva be the sole topic because of a general
                            feeling that they have been left out of the non-arms control side of the
                            process. Thus, my further understanding is that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCW_1">Weinberger</persName> does not plan on raising
                            any specific arms control items. As you know, tomorrow’s <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meeting will also cover the non-arms
                            control aspects of the Geneva agenda.</p>
                        <p>State is well aware of Defense’s complaints and is positioning Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> to take the lead in
                            going over in detail all aspects of the Geneva meeting. In blunt terms,
                            State sees tomorrow’s breakfast as a hand-holding session.</p>
                        <p>The two items that apparently have caused Defense specific heartburn are
                            the nuclear fusion reactor project and certain aspects of the
                            U.S.-Soviet exchange agreement. In both instances, I am told that
                            Defense’s problem is technology transfer. However, I understand that any
                            relevant exchanges would have to be approved by the Technology Transfer
                            Committee.</p>
                        <pb facs="0653" n="622" xml:id="pg_622"/>
                        <p>Beyond these points, the overall subject of a joint communique is a sore
                            point with Defense.<note n="3" xml:id="d142fn3">In his memoir, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> recalled: “The mere thought
                                of a joint communiqué with the Soviets alarmed <persName corresp="#p_WCW_1">Cap Weinberger</persName> and others in the
                                Defense Department. They were driving <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">Bud McFarlane</persName> wild with charges that he had to ‘stop
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>’ from doing any
                                such thing.” He continued: “The president did not like the acrimony
                                and decided that we should put ‘on hold’ efforts with the Soviets to
                                develop what they described as a possible joint communiqué. But he
                                did agree with me on the importance of developing language for what
                                we called an ‘agreed statement’ privately so that I would have some
                                ideas and language ‘in my pocket’ should we have the opportunity for
                                something constructive in Geneva. We would just skip over this
                                interagency squabbling.” Of the breakfast with <persName corresp="#p_WCW_1">Weinberger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> wrote: “On November 13, I
                                went over to the Defense Department for breakfast with Cap. I
                                reviewed for him the twenty-six items that we planned to take up
                                with the Soviets. I was on top of my brief and felt confident. The
                                breakfast went well, to my surprise.” (<persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Turmoil and Triumph,</hi>
                                pp. 596–597) A list of 26 issues for discussion in Geneva is in
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>’s preparatory
                                materials for a November 6 meeting with <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>. (Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George Shultz</persName> Papers, Secretary’s
                                Meetings with <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                                (09/24/1987) (2); NLR–775–21–40–1–3)</note> This is basically
                            because Defense did not see the original draft communique language
                            before it was handed to the Soviets. Defense also reportedly believes
                            that the current communique language is vague in a way that papers over
                            differences. Furthermore, Defense is convinced, despite assurances to
                            the contrary, that State is continuing to work with the Soviets on a
                            joint communique. I do not believe that Defense is aware that the
                            Soviets have provided us a revised draft communique.</p>
                        <p>I believe you are aware that all the specific arms control questions, to
                            include not only <gloss target="#t_NST_1">NST</gloss> but also <gloss target="#t_CDE_1">CDE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss>, are all being
                            worked in the arms control support group, with Defense
                            participation.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation</p>
                        <p>That you draw on the above for tomorrow’s breakfast.<note n="4" xml:id="d142fn4"><persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>
                                did not approve or disapprove the recommendation</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>