<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1985-12-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1985-12-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="173" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                        <head>173. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> to Soviet General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d173fn1">Source: Reagan Library, Executive Secretariat,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Head of State File,
                                U.S.S.R.: General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> (8591241, 8591243). No classification
                                marking. This letter is in response to <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>’s December 5 letter, not the handwritten
                                letter of December 24. In a December 18 covering memorandum to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MJF_1">Matlock</persName> explained: “A letter from
                                the President to <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>
                                on regional issues is at Tab A. It would follow up, in greater
                                detail and on a more formal basis, some of the suggestions he made
                                in his handwritten letter.” A December 13 covering memorandum from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PN_1">Platt</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> indicates the letter was
                                drafted and revised in the Department of State then sent to the
                                White House. <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>’s
                                December 5 letter is <ref target="#d166">Document
                            166</ref>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1985-12-26">December 26, 1985</date></dateline>
                            <salute>Dear Mr. General Secretary:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>I have already written to you informally to express some of my thoughts
                            on the issues facing us in the wake of our meeting in Geneva.<note n="2" xml:id="d173fn2">See <ref target="#d163">Document 163</ref>.</note>
                            I would like in this letter to deal with some of the particularly
                            pressing regional issues which I believe we must address in the months
                            ahead.</p>
                        <pb facs="0793" n="762" xml:id="pg_762"/>
                        <p>I mentioned Afghanistan in my earlier letter, but I would like to share
                            with you some further thoughts. Afghanistan was, after all, the regional
                            question on which we spent the most time in Geneva. You expressed Soviet
                            readiness to see an agreement emerge from the United Nations negotiating
                            process which would entail a ceasefire, withdrawal of troops, return of
                            the refugees and international guarantees. The discussion recalled the
                            suggestion in your June 10 letter that my government had “opportunities
                            to confirm by its actions” our readiness to reach a political settlement
                            in Afghanistan.<note n="3" xml:id="d173fn3">See <ref target="#d41">Document 41</ref>.</note> As I explained in my October speech
                            to the <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss>, we are prepared to
                            cooperate with others on practical steps. Three elements could form the
                            basis for a lasting solution: A process of negotiations among the
                            warring parties including the Soviet Union; verified elimination of the
                            foreign military presence and restraint on the flow of outside arms; and
                            movement toward political self-determination and economic
                            reconstruction.</p>
                        <p>As you know, we have been disappointed with the results of the proximity
                            talks conducted by the U.N. Secretary General’s Special Representative.
                            Five rounds in Geneva have not addressed the real issue on which a
                            resolution of this problem depends—withdrawal of your forces. No other
                            element of the problem presents real difficulty.</p>
                        <p>To underscore this, we have formally notified the Secretary General that
                            we accept the agreed formulation on guarantees. For your part, I believe
                            that the talks would gain a real impetus from Soviet action to permit
                            discussion of a timetable for withdrawal at Geneva and a public
                            announcement to that effect. Were such action taken by the time of our
                            Ministers’ next meeting, it would enable them to have a more focussed
                            and productive discussion.</p>
                        <p>Another area where I believe movement is possible is Southern Africa.
                            Because we have covered this ground often in the past, the point I need
                            to make is a simple one.</p>
                        <p>As I am sure you are aware, I am reviewing our policy in Southern Africa,
                            specifically with respect to the war in Angola. This review might not be
                            necessary if there were real evidence that the outside forces in that
                            country could be reduced, and then withdrawn, making possible the
                            reconciliation of the indigenous parties to the war. Such an outcome, of
                            course, would dramatically improve prospects for the establishment of an
                            independent Namibia in accordance with <gloss target="#t_UNSC_1">UNSC</gloss> Resolution 435—an objective we share with the
                                U.S.S.R.<note n="4" xml:id="d173fn4">See <ref target="#d28fn17">footnote 17, Document 28</ref>.</note> Unfortunately, the
                            evidence is clear that your own involvement in Angola is deepening.</p>
                        <pb facs="0794" n="763" xml:id="pg_763"/>
                        <p>As I said at the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> in October, our aim
                            is to reduce, not increase, military involvement by the superpowers in
                            local disputes like that in Angola.</p>
                        <p>I was pleased to learn from Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> that the Soviet Union had expressed an interest
                            in calming tensions between Libya and Egypt. At the same time, it
                            appears that Libya is preparing at least two sites for the emplacement
                            of SA–5 Air Defense Missiles to be supplied by the Soviet Union.<note n="5" xml:id="d173fn5">See <ref target="#d167fn6">footnote 6,
                                    Document 167</ref>.</note> It is hard to reconcile Soviet
                            interest in restraint in this region with the provision of advanced
                            weapons to a leader whose reckless behavior is a major danger to
                            regional stability. Because we view this development with utmost
                            seriousness, I was disappointed to see that the Soviet response to our
                            presentation failed to address the transfer of these weapons to Libya.
                            Our Ministers and experts should address this vital matter, since it
                            raises the prospect of dangerous incidents that I hope you want to avoid
                            as much as we do.</p>
                        <p>If you agree, both Angola and Libya are additional subjects which
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> and Foreign
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> might take
                            up in their next meeting.</p>
                        <p>In closing, let me underline my satisfaction with our agreement in Geneva
                            to put our regional experts’ talks on a regular basis. When we met in
                            Geneva we agreed that it was important for both of us to avoid a
                            U.S.-Soviet clash over regional conflicts and to work for solutions. I
                            believe that we must move forward on some of these issues before we meet
                            again. In that regard, I was pleased to note that in your remarks to
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BHM_1">Baldrige</persName> you referred
                            to the importance of dealing with regional trouble spots.<note n="6" xml:id="d173fn6">See <ref target="#d169">Document
                            169</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"><hi rend="strong">Ronald
                                        Reagan</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>