<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1986-01-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1986-01-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="182" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                        <head>182. Information Memorandum From the Director of the Policy Planning
                            Staff (<persName corresp="#p_RPW_1">Rodman</persName>) to Secretary of
                            State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d182fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George Shultz</persName> Papers, Executive
                                Secretariat Sensitive (01/18/1986–01/21/1986). Secret; Sensitive.
                                Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BAT_1">Bohlen</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LN_1">Ledsky</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_LN_1">Ledsky</persName> initialed the memorandum for
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RPW_1">Rodman</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1986-01-18">January 18, 1986</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Responding to the <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> Proposal: Possible Pitfalls Ahead</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">SUMMARY:</hi> On Friday, I expressed various
                            reservations about accepting the basic framework of the new Soviet
                                proposal.<note n="2" xml:id="d182fn2">January 17. In his memoir,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> wrote: “How
                                should we proceed diplomatically? The naysayers were hard at work,
                                even in my own building. <persName corresp="#p_RPW_1">Peter
                                    Rodman</persName> said that the elimination of nuclear weapons
                                meant a neutralist Europe, the end of our <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> strategy, a disaster for the West. No one could
                                accept the thought of a world moving toward the elimination of
                                nuclear weapons.” (<persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Turmoil and Triumph,</hi> p. 701)</note> I
                            will not repeat what I said then, and I acknowledge that the approach
                            outlined by <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Paul Nitze</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_HHA_1">Allen Holmes</persName> in their
                            respective memos deflects some of the more objectionable elements in the
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> proposal by
                            frontloading <hi rend="italic">our</hi> objectives into Phase I and
                            making subsequent phases as fuzzy as possible.<note n="3" xml:id="d182fn3">See <ref target="#d180">Document 180</ref> and <ref target="#d180fn3">footnote 3 thereto</ref>.</note> Nevertheless
                            I still see some serious problems—particularly of Alliance
                            management—coming down the road, sooner than some may think. The new
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> proposal is a
                            regression from where we stood after the Geneva Summit in the sense that
                            it shifts the focus from the areas of common ground to a number of
                            propagandistic themes; by engaging a negotiation in this new framework,
                            we are committing ourselves to further battles on a more slippery
                            terrain. In this memorandum, I will try to point out some of the larger
                            pitfalls I see ahead. <hi rend="italic">END SUMMARY</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Of the specific issues raised by the new <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> proposal, the two most important are Alliance
                            issues: the question of British and French forces presented in a new
                            form, and European perceptions about the role of nuclear weapons in
                            their security—a particular concern in West Germany. Thus we may be
                            touching some raw nerves very broadly in Europe.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">British and French systems:</hi> The new Soviet
                            proposal drops the long-standing Soviet demand for numerical
                            compensation for French and British forces—a potentially important
                            concession which we will want to pocket quickly—but is guaranteed to
                            remain divisive. Because reduced, the new Soviet demands—a ban on <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> and French modernization in Phase I, a
                            commitment to participate in negotiations and <pb facs="0821" n="790" xml:id="pg_790"/> reductions at a future stage—will appear more
                            reasonable to some publics in Europe. Moreover, the Soviet proposal
                            purports to address all the French and British preconditions for
                            participating in reductions: deep <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and
                            Soviet cuts, conventional balance through <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>, ban on <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> and no
                            upgrading of strategic defenses.</p>
                        <p>More seriously, if we sign on to a formal scheme to eliminate all nuclear
                            weapons, we must now acknowledge the logic of including British and
                            French forces and their participation in multilateral negotiations at
                            some stage—as we have never had to do for any arms control or reduction
                            proposal before. Buying onto this framework in a U.S.-Soviet context
                            will thus put us inescapably in the position of implicity pressuring the
                            French and British to agree to this—or of being at odds publicly with
                            their position, which is likely to be negative. This plays into the
                            hands of the antinuclear movement just when both countries are
                            undertaking major (and controversial) modernization programs. I agree
                            with <persName corresp="#p_HHA_1">Allen Holmes</persName> that we should
                            avoid emphasizing this issue or giving the appearance that we are
                            speaking for the French and British. But I’m not sure we will get off so
                            lightly: We cannot, for example, avoid telling the Soviets something of
                            what we have in mind for Phase 2 and 3.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Nuclear weapons and the conventional balance in
                                Europe:</hi> As you know, the Europeans are uncomfortable with our
                            antinuclear rhetoric and will be extremely reserved about a <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> commitment to abolish nuclear weapons in
                            fifteen years. This is already evident from the cautious reaction to the
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> proposal in
                            London, Paris, and Bonn.</p>
                        <p>I take only momentary pleasure from the fact that the Europeans will have
                            been hoist on their own petard and will now act as a brake on our
                            negotiations instead of constantly badgering us to do more. European
                            nervousness about nuclear issues is deep-seated and reflects the
                            precariousness of European opinion on the whole question of being
                            “caught in the middle” between East and West. The belief that a Western
                            nuclear deterrent is essential to maintain the balance in Europe is
                            deeply held by all European governments and large sectors of the
                            public—and they have defended this doctrine courageously against decades
                            of Soviet and neutralist pressures.</p>
                        <p>Moreover, what they mean by maintaining the balance is not merely
                            offsetting the huge Soviet conventional superiority in Europe but in
                            effect protecting Western Europe against the inherent and <hi rend="italic">uncorrectable</hi> weakness that flows from its lesser
                            size and military power, its geographic location under the shadow of the
                            Soviet Union, and its long distance from its main protector, the United
                            States, with its isolationist history and volatile domestic politics.
                            Any <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> action which tends to deemphasize
                            the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> nuclear element is therefore seen
                            as decoupling—i.e., as a form of U.S. withdrawal. This is especially
                            true <pb facs="0822" n="791" xml:id="pg_791"/> in West Germany.
                            Conceivably this prospect could have the healthy effect of stimulating
                            more intra-European defense cooperation, but it could also stimulate
                            resignation and a drift toward accommodation with the Soviet Union.
                            Unlike Central America or certain other arms control issues, the issue
                            of our nuclear presence in Europe is central to the European perception
                            of their own security.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, two recommendations seem to me to be in order:</p>
                        <p>We should avoid defining at this stage our requirements for the
                            conventional balance—that is, under what conditions we would be prepared
                            to give up nuclear weapons altogether. In particular, we should avoid
                            encouraging the notion that an <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>
                            agreement even on our terms will create a conventional balance or that
                            the conventional imbalance can be “fixed” through arms control
                            agreements. I agree with Allen on this point but would go further and
                            argue that even <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CDE_1">CDE</gloss> plus conventional defense improvements
                            are probably not enough. In any event, we should remain vague on this
                            point for now.</p>
                        <p>Because our nuclear weapons in Europe are central to our European
                            strategy and to the <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>
                            proposal, our consultations with key Allies on a response to <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> must be more than
                            perfunctory. Before the President responds to <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>, we should be prepared to
                            meet with them—at the Foreign Minister level if necessary—and discuss
                            the problems posed by the <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> proposal frankly, while both listening to
                            their views and making clear in which direction we want to go. This
                            makes sense on the merits and would be good public diplomacy in Europe.
                            Some profound issues are being raised here and should not be treated
                            casually.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>