<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>292. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d292</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">292</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1986-09-28T19:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1986-09-28T22:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="rec7XCpI38AIhVpLJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional issues</term>
                    <term ref="recMRN6sXmJwGNbiO" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">ABM Treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007171"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Summit meeting</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85019949"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Death penalty</term>
                    <term ref="recHEnRX74raOryAY" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044893"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Espionage</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general">Fishing rights</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86002124"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Hostage</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1986-09-28T22:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1986-09-28T19:30:00-05:00" n="292"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d292">
                <head>292. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d292fn1">
                        <p>Source: Department of State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss
                                target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss> Records, Memorandum of Conversations,
                            1981–1990, Lot 93D188, September 19 &amp; 23, 1986, <persName
                                corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                                >Shevardnadze</persName> at the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>.
                            Secret; Sensitive. There is no drafting information. The meeting took
                            place at the Soviet Mission to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>.
                            In his memoir, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> recalled:
                            “I arrived at the Soviet mission in New York at 8:30 P.M. on Sunday and
                            did not leave until well after 11:00. After some very hard dealing,
                                <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> and I
                            agreed:</p>
                        <p>“• Day 1: the Soviets permit <persName corresp="#p_DN_1"
                                >Daniloff</persName> to leave the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                                >USSR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>“• Day 2: twenty-four hours after <persName corresp="#p_DN_1"
                                >Daniloff</persName>’s departure, Zakharov pleads <hi rend="italic"
                                >nolo contendere</hi> (no contest), a legal equivalent of guilty,
                            and the United States expels him.</p>
                        <p>“• Day 3: as soon as Zakharov departs, the U.S. announces that <persName
                                corresp="#p_OY_1">Yuri Orlov</persName> and his wife will be allowed
                            to leave the Soviet Union by October 7.</p>
                        <p>“• The Soviets acquiesce in our reduction of the number of personnel at
                            the Soviet mission to the United Nations.</p>
                        <p>“• On Tuesday, September 30, we announce that <persName
                                corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> and <persName
                                corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> will meet in Reykjavik on
                            October 10–12, 1986.</p>
                        <p>“<persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> also gave me his
                            commitment to work on getting other dissidents and refuseniks released.
                            I trusted him to do this.” (<persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                                >Shultz</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Turmoil and Triumph</hi>, p.
                            745)</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1986-09-28T20:30:00-04:00" to="1986-09-28T23:20:00-04:00"
                            >September 28, 1986, 8:30–11:20 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">U.S.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>D. Zarechnak, Interpreter</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <list>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                                    >Shevardnadze</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DY_1">Dubinin</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PP_1">P. Palazhchenko</persName>,
                                Interpreter</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>After some preliminary conversation about tennis, the Secretary told <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> that he had been to Washington and
                    had talked at length with the President.<note n="2" xml:id="d292fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d290">Document 290</ref>.</note> He wished to tell <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> the President’s reaction to what
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had proposed. He had
                    told the President what <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had
                    said about the Soviet <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Mission personnel, and
                    that this was an especially important issue. He had indicated to the President
                    what the Foreign Minister had told him, i.e., that the number of <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Mission personnel was already below the number
                    that the U.S. had indicated, and that this was correct in accordance with U.S.
                    information. He had told the President that <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> had said that approximately ten of the people on
                    the list had either already returned to Moscow or were in the process of
                    returning in the normal course of rotation. He also had told the President that,
                    recognizing the U.S. reply to the Soviet request that the deadline be extended
                    past October 1 by 14 days on condition that the present problems would be
                    resolved, <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had proposed that
                    he and the Secretary discuss the situation in Reykjavik, where <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> would have more information on the
                    people on the list, i.e., on those <pb facs="1253" n="1222" xml:id="pg_1222"/>
                    people who will have been rotated at the Mission. The Secretary had also told
                    the President that he had felt in his meeting with the Foreign Minister that
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had been especially
                    concerned about two or three people on the list whom he felt had not been
                    properly identified. He had indicated that <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> had proposed that he and the Secretary discuss the
                    situation in Reykjavik and resolve it there, bearing in mind the background
                    indicated.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> interjected that it wasn’t
                    so much a case of improper identification, as the fact that he personally knew
                    several of the people, whereas he did not know the others.</p>
                <p>The Secretary confirmed that he had indicated to the President that <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had a special concern about two or
                    three of the people whom he knew personally. The Secretary asked if this was a
                    proper description of the current state of affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> nodded.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that the President had said that if the other aspects of
                    the problem could be resolved, he would go along with the Soviet side’s
                    proposal, which for now would make that issue one which could be dealt with.
                    With regard to the other category of issues, he had passed on to the President
                    the respective positions of the two sides, i.e., that <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> would be released and Zakharov would
                    be released 24 hours later, both without trial. The U.S. could say what it
                    wished publicly about Zakharov, and if it did so, the Soviet side would publicly
                    say what it wished about <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that he had told the President that the U.S. position was
                    that <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> and his wife, along with four
                    or five of the people on the list submitted, should be released simultaneously
                    with Zakharov, and that the Soviet position was that <persName corresp="#p_OY_1"
                        >Orlov</persName> and his wife should be released ten or fifteen days after
                    Zakharov. The other names on the list would be personally reviewed by <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>, and he personally would make a
                    judgment on them on the basis of their particular cases, appropriate Soviet law,
                    and the circumstances involved, and indicate a decision to the U.S. side at a
                    later date.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that the President had indicated that we could not live
                    with a time gap between the release of Zakharov and <persName corresp="#p_OY_1"
                        >Orlov</persName>. The President felt that if this were not done
                    simultaneously, it would be difficult for him to go on to deal with other
                    issues. Therefore, he asked the Secretary to tell <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> that he was ready to go along with the Foreign
                    Minister’s proposal concerning the four or five other people. The Secretary
                    indicated that he had told the President that he had gotten to know <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> during their meetings, and that
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had looked him in the
                    eye and had told him in good faith that he would look at the list, and the
                    Secretary believed him. The President had accepted these assurances, provided
                    that the <pb facs="1254" n="1223" xml:id="pg_1223"/> Soviet side would release
                        <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> at the same time as Zakharov
                    was released. But the question of simultaneous release was of key importance to
                    the President, and the Secretary wished to say that he could appreciate this and
                    shared this view.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked that this was what
                    the <hi rend="italic">President</hi> thought.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he wanted to repeat that the President had gone along
                    with several suggestions of the Soviet side, except for one.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> asked if there had been any
                    change on the Presidential decision to meet with the General Secretary on
                    October 11 and 12.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that there had been no change, assuming that the present
                    issues were resolved. It would not be wise to meet in Iceland otherwise. He
                    added that the two sides had agreed that that meeting would be described as a
                    preparatory meeting for the summit in the U.S., which would hopefully take place
                    in 1986.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> replied that out of this
                    package, he felt that the preparatory meeting of the two leaders should be put
                    on the top of the list. The General Secretary viewed this as the most important
                    thing, where the two leaders would give instructions to their assistants and
                    delegations about the main issues, i.e., in area of arms control, which they
                    thought would be the most promising for resolution. Other issues could also be
                    discussed, of course, such as bilateral issues and regional issues, and the
                    General Secretary indicated this in his letter.<note n="3" xml:id="d292fn3">See
                            <ref target="#d280">Document 280</ref>.</note> After this preparatory
                    meeting, and on the basis of the instructions given, agreements could then be
                    signed during the Washington visit.</p>
                <p>The Secretary indicated that this was the U.S. view as well. Moreover, he felt
                    that between the present time and the meeting in Reykjavik, the people on both
                    sides in Geneva should be pushed as much as possible to make the most of the
                    time available. For example, a lot of progress had been made in the area of
                        <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>. With respect to the outstanding
                    issues, e.g., the question of duration, the U.S. had proposed a phrase from an
                    earlier Soviet draft. With regard to Asia, <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> had indicated that the General Secretary had had
                    some ideas, but nothing specific had yet been laid out. So it would be useful if
                    these specific ideas were presented in Geneva, so that the delegations could
                    work on them and prepare them for examination in Reykjavik.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that the U.S. had put many proposals on the table
                    concerning verification, and the Soviet side had said many things which were
                    encouraging. The U.S. and the Soviet side had reached agreement on the question
                    of verification in Stockholm, and <pb facs="1255" n="1224" xml:id="pg_1224"/>
                    this had been very encouraging. So a big push ought to be made in this area,
                    since it was one of the very important ones.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that he and the Foreign Minister had not come to grips
                    with the question of shorter range <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> systems
                    during their meeting in Washington. As the Secretary had indicated, the U.S.
                    felt that these weapons ought to be frozen until further decisions had been
                    made.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that these were the types of areas where progress could
                    be made. So the delegations in Geneva should work hard at these things during
                    this week and the coming week in order to have this in hand for the leaders to
                    resolve at their meeting.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed with what <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> had said about the importance of the Reykjavik
                    meeting, and he hoped that <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                    could see that the U.S. side wanted to do as much as possible in order to get
                    ready for the preparatory meeting as well as it could. In this, the Secretary
                    was following the results of the process which <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> had proposed, i.e., that the two sides work hard
                    during the summer. This work had produced a more fruitful meeting between the
                    two of them. And just as this work had helped their meeting, he thought that the
                    work in Geneva could help the meeting of the two leaders in Iceland.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked that he did not
                    think that he and the Secretary should speak of the instructions which the
                    leaders would give to their delegations. In principle, the two of them had had a
                    dialogue and had touched on questions which they agreed were promising, such as
                    the issue about the duration of the <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>
                    agreement, the duration of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> treaty, etc.
                    These things had been indicated in the letter of the General Secretary, and
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> did not think that he
                    and the Secretary ought to decide these things at present. Each of the sides
                    would come to the meeting with its own thoughts and ideas. The two leaders would
                    give the Foreign Ministers and the delegations a push, and <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> believed that progress would be
                    possible in at least two or three areas.</p>
                <p>The Secretary indicated that he agreed with the Foreign Minister, but his thought
                    was that the delegations should not sleep in Geneva, excusing themselves by
                    saying that the meeting was only two weeks away.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that it was his personal hope, and he had heard the
                    General Secretary speak of this, as had <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> and the President, that the world would be much
                    better off without nuclear weapons. So if the two leaders felt this to be so
                    important, a way ought to be found to achieve this (he indicated that he was
                    aware of the General Secretary’s statement of January 15), i.e., to take
                    practical steps to move more rapidly to achieve this aim.</p>
                <pb facs="1256" n="1225" xml:id="pg_1225"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> replied that he agreed that
                    a great deal of work needed to be done in Geneva. Despite the fact that
                    agreement had not been reached, and deep differences remained between the
                    positions of the two sides, both sides had produced various proposals, and
                    compromises were possible. A push needed to be given, the type of push which
                    neither he nor the Secretary could give, but which demanded a higher level
                    political will, that is, a decision of the two leaders. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> repeated that he considered that
                    the main achievement of his meeting with the Secretary had been the decision on
                    the meeting between the two leaders.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that in all of his
                    meetings in New York, the main question which had been raised was whether or not
                    there would be a meeting between the President and the General Secretary.</p>
                <p>The Secretary confirmed that this had also been a major topic at his meetings,
                    but he felt that it was a question which was deeper than simply a question of a
                    meeting. It was a desire to see a lessening of tension and a more constructive
                    relationship between the two countries, which would have a rippling effect in
                    many ways. It was also a question of nuclear weapons hanging over the heads of
                    these nations. Even if a country did not possess any nuclear weapons and was not
                    geographically near the Soviet Union or the U.S., it could see that if there
                    were a nuclear exchange between the U.S. and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss>, the entire world would be hurt, if not decimated.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said that if shortly after
                    the Geneva summit, there had been arguments about the fruitfulness of the
                    meeting, now the two countries, as well as everyone else, thought that the
                    upcoming meeting should produce concrete results.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that he felt that
                    the preparatory meeting between the principals would lead to areas of accord
                    culminating in the signature of important agreements, at least in some areas, in
                    Washington, and this would be an historic event. It would open the way for the
                    future visit of the President to the Soviet Union, where additional achievements
                    could be recorded. So it would be a step-by-step process, and progress would be
                    made all along the way.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that he agreed with the Foreign Minister’s concept. He
                    thought that before the beginning of both the summit in the U.S. and in the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, agreements should be achieved on
                    important issues, so that the summits themselves would ratify these agreements.
                    However, he also felt that questions which had not been resolved should be
                    discussed at the summits which would give additional leadership and push to the
                    negotiators, so that important things could be resolved at subsequent
                    meetings.</p>
                <pb facs="1257" n="1226" xml:id="pg_1226"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> replied that the negotiating
                    process was this kind of a process, i.e., this was what agencies such as the
                    Foreign Ministries existed for.</p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that he was glad there was something for them to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> wanted to ask a question,
                    i.e., if there were no agreement on the other issues, did this mean that there
                    would be no meeting between the leaders?</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that he thought that it would be difficult for the meeting
                    to be a fruitful one unless these issues were resolved first.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed that these matters
                    needed to be resolved in order that the leaders could concentrate on the main
                    issues.</p>
                <p>The Secretary recalled that the Foreign Minister had said that the two of them
                    would not be worth their salt if they would not be able to resolve this issue,
                    so that their leaders could go on from there.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> confirmed this and added
                    that their leaders might even say that, seeing that the Foreign Ministers could
                    not agree on nuclear arms, space weapons or on <persName corresp="#p_DN_1"
                        >Daniloff</persName> and Zakharov, who needed them?</p>
                <p>The Secretary confirmed that this was a danger, and that he could perhaps return
                    in that case to California, and the Foreign Minister could return to Georgia.
                    And perhaps they might even be happier there.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> confirmed that he did have a
                    residence which belonged to his father in Georgia.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he had forgotten the melody, but by the next meeting he
                    would recall the tune to “Georgia on My Mind” and sing it to the Foreign
                    Minister.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked that he wished to
                    repeat that the question of the Soviet <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                    Mission personnel had been artificially created. In the first place, these
                    people were not spies. First of all, there had been no proof of this, and there
                    would be none. Secondly, even if they were all spies, why was this move made on
                    the day before the scheduled meeting between the Foreign Ministers, which was to
                    prepare a summit? So both in its essence and in its form, this issue was a
                    contrived one. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> did not
                    believe that the State Department had been involved in this decision. He
                    believed that the State Department truly wanted an improvement of
                    Soviet-American relations. But someone who was not interested in this had
                    thought of it.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that to now make
                    the conclusion out of all of this that the U.S. is making concessions and that
                    the President is being magnanimous in meeting the interests of the Soviet side
                    was naive. It was the Soviet side that was making concessions. A scenario of
                    retaliatory steps had been prepared, a very serious one. All that was <pb
                        facs="1258" n="1227" xml:id="pg_1227"/> needed to put it into force would be
                    a signal from <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>. But the
                    General Secretary had indicated that the Soviet side should wait until the heads
                    of government would meet.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> realized that there were
                    people in the U.S. who were sincerely interested in improving Soviet-American
                    relations, and that we ought to make it easier for them. The General Secretary
                    did not wish to disrupt the summit meeting. Perhaps the Foreign Minister did not
                    have to indicate to the U.S. side how many people on the list had left, and how
                    many would leave and the fact that some would leave due to normal rotation.
                    Other issues could be decided at the meeting of the heads of state or at the
                    level of Foreign Ministers. So there had been no compromises on the U.S. side.
                    The U.S. actions were illegal. But it was good that a mutually acceptable
                    solution was found. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> felt
                    that the Secretary’s personal involvement had been very important.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that the Soviet
                    side had said that the cases of <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>
                    and Zakharov were similar. The U.S. side said that it had proof that Zakharov
                    was a spy, but the Soviet side was not convinced of this, and said that he was
                    an honest citizen. On the other hand, the Soviet side had indicated that it had
                    proof about <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>, and it was not
                    coincidental that the President had referred to a possible death penalty for
                        <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> in his <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> speech.<note n="4" xml:id="d292fn4">See <ref
                            target="#d288fn2">footnote 2, Document 288</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary interjected that this was said in reference to the penalty given
                    for espionage in accordance with Soviet law.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> replied that the President
                    must realize that such things were not done without appropriate proof in
                    civilized countries, and although the President did not like the Soviet Union,
                    he must consider it civilized. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> again referred to the President’s phrase as
                    indicative of the realization of the strict punishment which could be given on
                    the basis of Soviet law.</p>
                <p>The Secretary again interjected that what the President did know was that the
                    U.S. Government did not have <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>
                    working for it, had not given him any tasks, and was not using him in any way.
                    So, regardless of what he had or had not done, he was not an agent and was not
                    engaged in gathering information for the U.S. Government, which was the U.S.
                    definition of espionage.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> replied that this was a
                    different matter. The Soviet side had different evidence. He repeated that
                    although the two sides were in a similar situation, the Soviet side had made
                    concessions. Zakharov would be released 24 hours after <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> felt that this was not a big issue, but this was
                    not easy from the point of <pb facs="1259" n="1228" xml:id="pg_1228"/> view of
                    government prestige. He mentioned the Secretary’s reference to the fact that it
                    was important what people would say about the President’s decision. But it was
                    also important what the Soviet people would say. The Soviet Government had said
                    that the U.S. had taken illegal steps with regard to Soviet <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Mission personnel.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that although some
                    Soviet citizens had returned to the Soviet Union, no retaliatory steps had been
                    taken. People would ask why this was so. They would ask the General Secretary
                    and others. They would ask why Zakharov was released 24 hours after <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>. Why had the Soviet side made all the
                    concessions?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that the main
                    thing was that all of this had been agreed to, and of primary importance was the
                    fact that a meeting between the two leaders had been arranged. Then, suddenly a
                    new ultimatum had been given, i.e., the release of <persName corresp="#p_OY_1"
                        >Orlov</persName> and five others. This was artificial. Someone wished to
                    show that the U.S. side had won, that it had brought the Soviets to their knees.
                    But in order to achieve the main goal and to comply with the wishes of the
                    Soviet, the American and the other nations of the world, the Soviet side had
                    gone along with all of this.</p>
                <p>The Secretary interjected that the U.S. side did not wish to bring the Soviet
                    side to its knees. This would not be good for either the U.S. or the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. He had listened very carefully in Geneva to
                    the General Secretary, and he thought that the General Secretary had shown a
                    great deal of wisdom when he had said, in speaking of arms control, that it
                    would not be good for either side to make a deal that would be unfair, since
                    such a deal would tend to quickly unravel. The Secretary also knew from his
                    experience in business that if in working with a customer or a supplier, too
                    hard a bargain was driven, one would come to regret it later. So there was no
                    desire to do that in the present situation.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that he and the President wished to resolve the present
                    situation in order to move on to other issues. The President had accepted the
                    Soviet side’s proposals with one exception. Unfortunately, there were news
                    people who only thought in concepts of who won and who lost.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> interjected that it was not
                    only news people who thought that way.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that he felt that the world was inhabited by people who
                    wanted to solve problems and those that wanted to create them. He felt that he
                    and the Foreign Minister were among those who wished to solve problems.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed. But he indicated
                    that he did not want to deviate from the discussion of this problem. Why was the
                    question of <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> introduced? From the
                    beginning, the two sides had agreed that <pb facs="1260" n="1229"
                        xml:id="pg_1229"/> the issue of the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                    Mission personnel was a separate issue, as were the issues of <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> and Zakharov. This applied to
                        <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> as well. But if the release of
                        <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> and Zakharov was to be
                    simultaneous, then these actions would not be independent. The Secretary must
                    understand that this was a question of national prestige. If the two issues were
                    separate, then the question of releasing <persName corresp="#p_OY_1"
                        >Orlov</persName> after ten or twelve days would be no problem. The issue of
                    national prestige would not arise.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that among the
                    options which had been considered on the Soviet was to leave all of these issues
                    unresolved until the meeting between the President and the General Secretary,
                    but he agreed with the Secretary that this ought not to be done. In this case,
                    both of them would be viewed as helpless since they had not been able to resolve
                    the issue in the 22 or 24 hours that they had discussed it. He felt that it was
                    not important whether it was a matter of ten or eight days (or perhaps twelve),
                    compared to the major decision about a meeting between the two heads of
                    state.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that the Soviet
                    side had made a significant concession on the first issue. It had also made a
                    concession on the second issue. On the third issue, it had added <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>, which was more than a major concession.
                    With regard to the additional five or seven names, he had promised that if there
                    was a basis for their release, it would be done.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> continued that agreement had
                    been reached on the main thing, and that he would regret it if the timing for
                        <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>’s release would stand in the
                    way. For example, what if <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> had a
                    fever? The Secretary had indicated that he had no flexibility on this matter.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> might be able to shorten
                    the time period by two or three days, but could not do any more. He had given
                    the Secretary all of the options.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he wished to make one proposal. Perhaps the Foreign
                    Minister had no flexibility on this, but he wanted to say the following. At the
                    present time, the situation was that there was agreement that <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> would be released and that Zakharov
                    would be released 24 hours later. The timing of <persName corresp="#p_OY_1"
                        >Orlov</persName>’s release was unresolved.</p>
                <p>The Secretary wished to make the following operational proposal. He knew that
                    there was an Aeroflot flight from Moscow to Dulles Tuesday morning.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d292fn5">September 30.</note> The Soviet side could put Mr. &amp;
                    Mrs. Daniloff, together with Mr. &amp; Mrs. Orlov, on that flight. When the
                    flight would arrive at Dulles, Zakharov could be waiting in a lounge to board
                    that plane, and there could be a trade. Zakharov could board the Aeroflot
                    flight, and <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> could get off of it. In this way, there
                        <pb facs="1261" n="1230" xml:id="pg_1230"/> would be no time gap between the
                    release of <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> and Zakharov, and
                    there would be no time gap between the release of <persName corresp="#p_OY_1"
                        >Orlov</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> replied that this would not
                    change anything. The main problem was still the timing of <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>’s release.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that it would change the sequence of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>/Zakharov release, which he thought
                    might be helpful to the Soviet side, just as the change in the <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> release would be helpful to the U.S.
                    side.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> replied that this would not
                    change anything. The main thing was that <persName corresp="#p_OY_1"
                        >Orlov</persName> would not be released at the same time as Zakharov. If
                    these things were independent issues, they should be resolved independently. The
                    two sides should not add anything to the resolution of the Zakharov and
                        <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> cases. The Secretary had
                    agreed this with the President, and <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> had agreed this with Moscow. The 24-hour time gap
                    had been agreed to. If the two sides agreed in principle that <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> would be released subsequently, tomorrow
                    or the day after the U.S. could hold a press conference and could say that a
                    decision had been taken to release <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>
                    at a later date. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked
                    parenthetically that the American public apparently would be very happy to
                    receive <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that he might actually become a problem for the U.S.</p>
                <p>The Secretary then said that he wished to describe the current situation as he
                    saw it, and also add something. On day one, i.e., on Monday, <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> would be released. On Tuesday,
                    Zakharov would be released and the U.S. could say what it wished about <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>. It would say that a date had been agreed
                    on <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>’s release, as well as the
                    procedure for it. Obviously, this should be a few days before the meeting in
                    Reykjavik, to have this out of the way by then. The Secretary asked <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> if this was a reasonable
                    interpretation of <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s
                    proposal, with the addition of an indication of a specific date.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> repeated the Secretary’s
                    suggestion about announcing a date, for clarification.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had
                    indicated that it was important for the Soviet side that <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> depart later, and that the U.S. could
                    then announce at a press conference that it was agreed that <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> would be released and that the U.S. would
                    welcome him.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed.</p>
                <p>The Secretary repeated that he had added mention of a specific date to what
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had proposed. He thought
                    that the question of <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>, and Zakharov ought to be resolved at
                    least two or three days before the meeting at Reykjavik. The question of the
                    Soviet <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> personnel would still need to be
                    discussed between <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                    <pb facs="1262" n="1231" xml:id="pg_1231"/> and the Secretary, but the other
                    issues would need to be resolved by then. Additionally, <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had given his word that he would
                    look at the list of Soviet citizens in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> presented by the U.S. side, but the Secretary would not say
                    anything about this publicly. The U.S. side would wait for <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s decision.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> confirmed that such an
                    approach would be acceptable, and could now say that all issues had been
                    resolved satisfactorily before the meeting of the heads of state.</p>
                <p>The Secretary started to look at specific dates. He suggested that <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> could be released tomorrow, i.e., the
                    29th, and then Zakharov would be released on the following day. When the U.S.
                    released Zakharov, it would also make a public statement about <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> and say that <persName corresp="#p_OY_1"
                        >Orlov</persName> would be released on October 7, i.e., one week after
                    Zakharov. This would be two days before the President’s departure for Iceland.
                    He added that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> had
                    just indicated to him that there was an Aeroflot flight leaving Moscow for
                    Washington on September 30, and perhaps Zakharov could be put on that plane. The
                    Secretary wasn’t sure about what flights were leaving on Monday from Moscow.
                    Perhaps the U.S. could send in a military plane.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> mentioned the problem of the
                    time difference between New York and Moscow, but indicated that what the
                    Secretary had proposed was basically acceptable.</p>
                <p>The Secretary confirmed that there were eight hours difference, and suggested
                    that the two sides begin work immediately. The U.S. would begin to process
                    Zakharov’s release the following day.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that in order to have an announcement of this during
                    working hours in the two countries, this could be accomplished if the
                    announcement were made at 9:00 a.m. Washington time and 5:00 p.m. Moscow time.
                    This would leave one day for going through the procedure for releasing <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> in Moscow. On Tuesday, Zakharov would
                    be released, and the U.S. would make a statement about <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>. This would be at 5:00 p.m. Moscow time,
                    and the Soviet side could say what it wished about this, and could put Zakharov
                    on the Aeroflot flight if it wished to do so. There would be no interference
                    from the U.S. side.<note n="6" xml:id="d292fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> continued in his memoir:
                            “<persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> and I had met on
                        the <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> problem three times in
                        Washington and four times in New York. These meetings had been intense and
                        personal. Most of the time only our interpreters and one other person on
                        each side were present. <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Roz Ridgway</persName>
                        was with me and her Soviet counterpart, <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1"
                            >Aleksandr Bessmertnykh</persName>, joined <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                            >Shevardnadze</persName>. No papers were exchanged for signature. At the
                        moment of agreement, we went over the points carefully with each other. I
                        was within my instructions, which President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"
                            >Reagan</persName> had signed off on personally. At the end, <persName
                            corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> and I sealed our agreement
                        with a handshake. We had been through a tense and extended effort together.
                        The experience built personal confidence in each other, and trust.”
                            (<persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Turmoil and Triumph</hi>, p. 747)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1263" n="1232" xml:id="pg_1232"/>
                <p>The Secretary thought that one other thing should be done, i.e., by Monday
                    afternoon or Tuesday morning, each of the sides should approach the Government
                    of Iceland independently about hosting the meeting between the heads of state.
                    Then on Wednesday, October 1, there could be a simultaneous announcement at 9:00
                    a.m. Washington time and 5:00 p.m. Moscow time about a preparatory meeting in
                    Reykjavik.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DY_1">Dubinin</persName> interjected that the
                    news program “Vremya” comes on at 9:00 p.m.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he felt that it would be useful to have a short common
                    statement, along the lines that President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"
                        >Reagan</persName> and General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1"
                        >Gorbachev</persName> agreed to meet on October 11 and 12 in Reykjavik, and
                    that the meeting would be a preparatory one to plan for the summit in the U.S.
                    He handed the U.S. draft to <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1"
                    >Bessmertnykh</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> indicated that he could
                    agree in principle to the indication of a date.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName> remarked that 9:00 a.m. was
                    too early.</p>
                <p>The Secretary thought that the details could be left to Ambassadors <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1"
                        >Bessmertnykh</persName>, including the details of <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>’s release. But these were technical
                    matters, and could be resolved.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed, but there was one
                    issue which he wanted to agree in principle. He and the Secretary would be
                    meeting with the press either on Monday or on Tuesday, depending on how they had
                    agreed, like it had been done in Washington where both of them had given a press
                    conference at 6:00 p.m. The content of their remarks would be different, but the
                    basic facts would be the same.</p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that the Minister had a good point, and this also argued
                    for a Monday/Tuesday release schedule, because if it were done this way, an
                    announcement could be made before <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName>’s departure from the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that the meeting at Reykjavik would be the next thing
                    announced, but this was a different matter.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said that he could not
                    refrain from mentioning the meeting. Since the dates had not yet been agreed
                    with Iceland, but the fact of the meeting had been agreed, the two sides could
                    say that the President and the General Secretary had agreed to meet in the near
                    future, without specifying a date, and the Soviet side had a draft statement on
                    this which was similar to the one the Secretary had read from.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> when he
                    was planning to leave the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> replied that it was 5:00
                    p.m. on Tuesday. But their principal news program came on at 9:00 p.m. Moscow
                    time, i.e., 1:00 <pb facs="1264" n="1233" xml:id="pg_1233"/> p.m. New York time.
                    Therefore, his press conference would need to be held at noon New York time at
                    the latest. The place for the meeting between the heads of state could be
                    announced later. This might even be better. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> was concerned about security if this were announced
                    two weeks in advance. The main thing was that agreement had been reached about a
                    meeting. The U.S. formulation was basically satisfactory.</p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that if the place was not indicated, speculation would be
                    rampant. Also, two weeks was not such a long time to make preparations. Both
                    sides had advance teams which worked well together in Geneva, but they would
                    still need to look around, find the most suitable facility, and so on. The
                    Government of Iceland would need to clear some hotels and do similar things. So
                    the more time there was to prepare for the meeting, the better. So the Secretary
                    felt that the place of the meeting should be announced. He could not see that
                    the Icelandic authorities would not agree to it, but they should be asked.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> indicated that the Soviet
                    side would approach the Government of Iceland tomorrow morning, and would ask
                    them for a quick reply. In all likelihood, the Icelandic Government would reply
                    quickly, and this would permit an announcement on Tuesday in the morning about
                    all of the things which had been agreed to. This would sound serious and
                    convincing.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed that the two sides should try to do this. He would need to
                    get the President’s agreement, but he believed that he would be able to do this.
                    Then sometime on Monday the two countries could approach Iceland about the
                    meeting and hopefully receive a reply by Tuesday. He felt that there was 90
                    percent certainty of this.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> felt it was 99 percent
                    certain.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed. He then indicated that the U.S. side would like to see
                    three events. On Monday at 9:00 or 11:00 a.m., it would be announced in
                    Washington that <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> was being
                    released, and he would leave the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. On
                    Tuesday at 9:00 a.m. or so, the U.S. would announce the release of Zakharov and
                    would say that <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> would be released
                    one week later. The U.S. and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> could
                    say whatever it wished on that score. At 11:00 a.m., the Foreign Minister would
                    have a press conference at which he would describe everything that had been
                    agreed to, and the meeting between the heads of state would also be announced in
                    Washington and Moscow. The Foreign Minister could mention it at his press
                    conference, and the Secretary could as well. Then all of this could be
                    accomplished before the Foreign Minister left the U.S.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said that he envisioned a
                    scenario where there would be a meeting with the press tomorrow at which it
                    would be announced that agreement had been reached on <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> and Zakharov. It was <pb facs="1265"
                        n="1234" xml:id="pg_1234"/> agreed that the U.S. could say what it wished on
                        <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>. It was agreed what the two
                    sides would do about the Soviet <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> contingents.
                    In principle, agreement had been reached on the meeting of heads of state. All
                    this could be said tomorrow. The place of the meeting could be indicated the day
                    after tomorrow or at another time as a separate item. Then all of the events,
                    including the release of <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>,
                    Zakharov, and <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> and everything else,
                    would take place after these announcements. <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> did not see anything inconvenient for either side
                    in such an approach. This kind of approach had been agreed with Moscow with the
                    General Secretary. For any other approach, <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> would need to cable Moscow tonight, and this would
                    delay things.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he did not think that he could agree with such an
                    approach. There were three or maybe four independent events. The U.S. felt that
                    these things should occur one by one and not all at once. The first event would
                    be that <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> would be released and
                    would come home. The second event would be that 24 hours later Zakharov would be
                    released and would go home, and the U.S. would indicate what would happen with
                        <persName corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>, i.e., that he would be
                    released one week later. The U.S. side felt that it would be desirable to handle
                    these personal issues separately, even if there were only a one or two hour lag.
                    Then the announcement about Iceland, if it had been pinned down by then, could
                    be made at the time of the Minister’s press conference on Tuesday, at which time
                    the Minister could say all that he wished.</p>
                <p>The Secretary wished to say that he still needed to clear <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>’s proposal on <persName
                        corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> with the President, but he felt that it
                    was a sensible one, and that he would have no problem in doing this. He would
                    call the President tonight, and meanwhile, Ambassadors <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1"
                        >Bessmertnykh</persName> could work on a text so that everything would be
                    clear and there would be no misunderstandings.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName> asked what would happen if
                    the U.S. side announced the release of <persName corresp="#p_DN_1"
                        >Daniloff</persName>, and the press would ask about Zakharov.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DY_1">Dubinin</persName> also asked what the
                    U.S. would reply to any questions about a summit.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he would say that the information being presented
                    concerned <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>, and the press should
                    hang around.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> indicated that he had not
                    thought that any difficulties would arise in connection with the Soviet
                    scenario, which he had cleared with Moscow the previous day. Perhaps both sides
                    could wait an extra day. It was important to decide how to present the case
                    publicly.</p>
                <pb facs="1266" n="1235" xml:id="pg_1235"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName> added there would be no
                    time to get this accomplished by 9:00 a.m. the following day.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> indicated that if he were
                    not to mention the summit, he needed time to get agreement on this course of
                    action, and this might put things off by one or two days. He repeated that he
                    had thought that the Soviet approach would be acceptable, indicating solution of
                    all issues, including the question of the meeting of heads of state, and
                    everyone in the U.S. and in the Soviet Union would welcome it. The Soviet side
                    had thought of all possible options, including those it believed would not be
                    acceptable to the President, but had not expected that there would be any
                    objection to the one <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> had
                    described. Perhaps things could be put off until Tuesday. Then agreement could
                    be obtained from Iceland, and <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> could address at least the Soviet press, possibly
                    without the U.S. press if the U.S. side so desired. He would then relate
                    everything that had happened. The U.S. side could then announce <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> separately as it wished.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> indicated that perhaps the
                    following option might be used. Agreement could be announced about a meeting
                    without an indication of place. This was often done in international practice,
                    and would not offend anyone. Otherwise, the decision might have to be put off.
                    He was not saying that there would be no decision. But it would be difficult to
                    delay his visit to Canada. As it was, he would probably have to cut back his
                    stay in Canada and Mexico to return more quickly to the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that his Africa trip would have to go down the drain, but
                    this might be for the good.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked that when people
                    heard of the meeting between the President and the General Secretary, everything
                    else would take second place.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he would like to propose the following. The two sides had
                    agreed on the content and sequence of the events and on the preparatory meeting
                    in Iceland. They were struggling over how to announce this and were not sure how
                    fast it could be done, i.e., Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1"
                        >Bessmertnykh</persName> did not think <persName corresp="#p_DN_1"
                        >Daniloff</persName> could be processed by 9:00 a.m. So the two sides should
                    work at this, and he would have to clear it with the President, which he felt he
                    could do. The Secretary realized that the Foreign Minister wished to mention
                    Iceland before leaving the U.S. The U.S., on the other hand, wished to mention
                    the meeting in Iceland separately, after the decisions on the individuals. The
                    U.S. did not want to mix these things. Therefore, the staff people should work
                    hard to try to arrive at a sequence that would fit both the Minister’s schedule
                    and the desires of the U.S. side. Perhaps in Moscow it would not be important to
                    announce <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>’s departure. <pb
                        facs="1267" n="1236" xml:id="pg_1236"/> So perhaps the announcement could be
                    made in late afternoon in Washington. It would be night in Moscow then, and
                    would pose no difficulty. The following day the release of Zakharov would be
                    announced in the morning and a few hours after that, the meeting in Iceland. If
                    the Soviet side approached Iceland tomorrow, they would probably quickly agree
                    to the meeting, and then <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>
                    could go to Canada and talk about Soviet-Canadian fishing rights, although the
                    Canadians would probably only want to talk about the meeting in Iceland.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed and said that he had
                    not studied the question of fishing rights in very great detail in anticipation
                    of this.</p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1"
                        >Ridgway</persName> had cut her teeth negotiating about fishing rights. This
                    was one of the most difficult subjects there was. Fish had no regard for
                    territorial waters, they just swam where they wanted. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked that he did not want to
                    talk about any difficult issues with the Canadians. It had been difficult enough
                    in the U.S.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that things had been difficult, but the two sides were very
                    close to a final solution, and this was very good.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> suggested that the two sides
                    might instruct their Ambassadors in Iceland to approach the Icelandic
                    Government.</p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that this should be done in secrecy so that it was not
                    leaked in Iceland.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed. He also indicated
                    that he would need to agree on all of this with Moscow, and a statement would
                    not be possible tomorrow. The technical details about timing and procedures
                    needed to be worked out, but the Soviet side was very interested in resolving
                    this very quickly. This might take a couple or more hours. He would not exclude
                    Iceland giving the reply tomorrow, and then everything could be wrapped up
                    tomorrow. Then perhaps on Tuesday morning, there could be a press conference or
                    announcement on <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>. Or perhaps this
                    could happen in the afternoon. And <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName> could make an announcement before he departed.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that we should not rule out an announcement on <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> tomorrow, even if this would be done
                    late in the day in the U.S. The Soviet side’s deadline was pushing events, and
                    the Secretary could understand <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName>’s desire to do this.</p>
                <p>And the Secretary continued that since the two sides were working without factual
                    information, he would first want to ask his government for approval, and then
                    set Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName> to work, making decisions on
                    facts and sequences, starting immediately, bearing in mind the Minister’s
                    schedule.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said that since such an
                    approach was different from the one which had been approved for him, he could
                    not agree to it at <pb facs="1268" n="1237" xml:id="pg_1237"/> the moment. He
                    joked that if he had to change his document, he might be told not to come back,
                    and would become a hostage in the U.S.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that the U.S. would welcome <persName corresp="#p_SE_1"
                        >Shevardnadze</persName>. He continued that both sides had their
                    requirements and would work within that framework to wrap everything up by the
                    time of the preparatory meeting. He repeated that Ambassadors <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1"
                        >Bessmertnykh</persName> had a lot of work to do and perhaps the <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> announcement could be made tomorrow
                    afternoon in order for the sequence to go through.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked that the Secretary
                    was looking for a statement, but agreement had not yet been reached. So
                    Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName> should work on it. They usually
                    did good work.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that the question of the content of the issues had been
                    resolved. Now the two sides should use this solution to advance further
                    prospects. He understood the Minister’s desire to announce this at the press
                    conference. And the U.S. needed to put things in a row—one, two, three. So there
                    was need to work hard to fit all this in.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed and asked when
                        <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName> should meet.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName> suggested tomorrow.</p>
                <p>The Secretary indicated that he would need to call the President tonight, and he
                    would wake him up, but things needed to get moving, and <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1"
                        >Bessmertnykh</persName> could consult in a few hours.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that he would not say anything about the Soviet <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> contingent. If questions were asked about this,
                    he would say that the issue had been discussed and that the Minister had told
                    him that the number of representatives at the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                    Mission was already below the framework that the U.S. had indicated, and the
                    U.S. had no difficulty with this. With regard to the 25 names (which have never
                    been published)—they were discussed, and the U.S. was informed that in the
                    process of personnel management a significant fraction of those on the list were
                    already in Moscow due to rotation. The Soviet side had requested an extension of
                    time, and the U.S. had agreed. The Secretary and the Minister had also agreed to
                    further discuss this issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said that he wanted to make
                    one correction. He had said that six or seven of the people on the list had
                    departed the U.S. before the U.S. demand. As for the rest, this could be
                    indicated as the Secretary desired.</p>
                <p>The Secretary repeated that he was not planning to raise this issue on his
                    own.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> said that if he were asked,
                    he would confirm that the action was illegal, but that the Soviet side would not
                    take retaliatory <pb facs="1269" n="1238" xml:id="pg_1238"/> steps since this
                    could hinder the resolution of the main thing, i.e., the meeting between the
                    heads of state.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that, obviously, the Minister should say what he wished, and
                    the U.S. would say what it wished to describe the situation and what would
                    follow. The Secretary would say this in a voice which was not contentious and
                    would not fan the flames. He would simply describe the results. But the two
                    sides needed to get down to work.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> agreed and said that the
                    Soviet side was seeking a reasonable solution.<note n="7" xml:id="d292fn7">At 10
                        a.m. on Tuesday, September 30, in Washington, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                            >Shultz</persName> announced the release of Zakharov and <persName
                            corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName>. He was joined by <persName
                            corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> who declared that he would meet
                        with <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> in Reykjavik October
                        11–12. For the text of <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>’s
                        statement and <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>’s exchanges with the press
                        concerning the meeting, <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>’s
                        release, and the expulsion of the Soviet <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                        employees, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"
                                >Reagan</persName>, 1986</hi>, Book II, pp. 1292–1299. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName>, in his September 30 news
                        conference in New York, discussed the expulsion order and <persName
                            corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> and Zakharov’s release. He said he
                        believed a “reasonable solution” would be found at the Reykjavik meeting.
                        (Elaine Sciolino, “Soviet Warning on Expulsion Order,” <hi rend="italic">New
                            York Times,</hi> October 1, 1986, p. A10)</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that there would be a million press people waiting outside
                    the Soviet Mission. His preference would be not to say anything and to tell his
                    press spokesman, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KB_1">Kalb</persName>, that they had
                    discussed <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName> and Zakharov and other
                    issues, and could say nothing else about it. The press would note that this was
                    different from what had been said before. After the last meeting, it was said
                    that the issue had not been resolved. But now, it would be said that nothing
                    could be said. At this point, the Secretary remarked that Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> had suggested that it might be better
                    to say that the two sides were still working on resolving the matter. This might
                    be better.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked that he probably
                    would not go outside.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that his cars might not be able to move because of the
                    press.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> remarked that in that case,
                    the Secretary could spend the night at the Soviet Mission.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that that would really be a sensation. He would be held
                    hostage.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE_1">Shevardnadze</persName> indicated that he would,
                    after all, say good-bye to the Secretary outside.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that after he consulted with the President, Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName> would call Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_BAA_1">Bessmertnykh</persName>. If necessary, he could
                    meet again with the Minister to work things out. However, if they did not meet
                    again in New York, he wished the Minister <pb facs="1270" n="1239"
                        xml:id="pg_1239"/> a good stay in Canada and Mexico and would look forward
                    to meeting him in Reykjavik.<note n="8" xml:id="d292fn8">On September 29,
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> wrote in his diary:
                        “George S. has won the day. Mr. &amp; Mrs. Daniloff will be on their way
                        home before the morning is over. That will be announced. Then tomorrow
                        George will announce that Zakharov will be found guilty &amp; sent to Russia
                        on probation so long as he never returns to the U.S. and <persName
                            corresp="#p_OY_1">Orlov</persName> &amp; his wife will be freed to leave
                        Soviet Union within one week. Then I’ll announce a meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> in Iceland October 10, 11, &amp;
                        12.” (Brinkley, ed., <hi rend="italic">The <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"
                                >Reagan</persName> Diaries,</hi> vol. II: November 1985–January
                        1989, p. 643) <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> first announced
                            <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Daniloff</persName>’s release at 12:24 p.m.
                        on Monday, September 29, at a Senate campaign rally in Kansas City,
                        Missouri. (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"
                                >Reagan</persName>, 1986</hi>, Book II, p. 1284)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
