<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1985-05-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1985-05-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="35" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                        <head>35. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d35fn1">Source:
                                Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George
                                    Shultz</persName> Papers, 1985 Soviet Union May. Secret;
                                Sensitive. A typed note in the top margin reads: “5/25 Orig +1 via
                                Special Courier 1310 p.m. per <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>.”
                                Under a June 1 covering memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName> forwarded the memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>. (Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_MJF_1">Jack Matlock</persName> Files, Chronological
                                File, 1980–1986, <persName corresp="#p_MJF_1">Matlock</persName>
                                Chron June 1985 (1/4))</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1985-05-25">May 25, 1985</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Conversation with <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>—May 24th</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At a reception last night, I had the opportunity to take Soviet
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> aside to
                            discuss the question of a Summit. I told him first that I wanted him to
                            pass on to <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> that, should
                            the Foreign Minister come to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                            General Assembly this late September as usual, he would be welcome to
                            come to Washington and meet with you in the Oval Office at that
                            time.</p>
                        <p>Second, I told <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> that I had
                            passed to you <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>’s
                            proposed time frame for a meeting between the two of you, and that you
                            were agreeable, preferring sometime in the week beginning Monday,
                            November 18.<note n="2" xml:id="d35fn2">See <ref target="#d30fn3">footnote 3, Document 30</ref>.</note> I stated that you felt a
                            one-day meeting would probably not be sufficient and that a two-day
                            meeting with three substantive sessions would perhaps be best.
                            Concerning the venue, I reiterated your invitation for <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> to come to Washington,
                            observing that for protocol reasons, Washington would be most
                            appropriate since it was our turn to host such an affair. I added,
                            however, that in any follow-on meeting after such a Washington summit,
                            you would be quite prepared to visit Moscow. I noted to <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> your view that it would be
                            better for the leaders of the world’s two most powerful countries to
                            meet in each other’s capitals than in some third country.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> promised to convey back
                            to Moscow both the invitation for <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> to visit Washington in late September and your
                            proposed time frame for a meeting with <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>. On the question of venue, he stated that
                                <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> wanted you to
                            visit Moscow because he thought it would be good for you “to look
                            around” and see the Soviet people and society. I reminded <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> that you would be prepared to
                            visit, but that it was the turn of a Soviet leader to come to the U.S. I
                            noted that in any joint announcement of a Washington meeting, we would
                            willing to add that the next meeting would be in Moscow.</p>
                        <pb facs="0162" n="131" xml:id="pg_131"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> said that he would report
                            this to <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName>, but mused
                            whether our interest in a Washington venue was solely a matter of
                            protocol. I told him it was. We both agreed that if such a meeting were
                            to take place, it would best if it could accomplish something tangible.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> added that from his
                            own experience, once agreement on a Summit was reached, the respective
                            bureaucracies “begin to move” to produce progress.</p>
                        <p>I concluded by reminding <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                            of the need for the Soviets to take special care in the weeks and months
                            to come not to take any unfortunate action, deliberate or otherwise,
                            which might have the effect of derailing this process. (I took this
                            moment to pass to <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> a
                            non-paper noting our strong concerns over the plight of Soviet
                            hunger-striker Balovlenkov).<note n="3" xml:id="d35fn3">The non-paper
                                was not found. In telegram 6822 from Moscow, May 23, the Embassy
                                reported that Yuri Balovlenkov, “who is married to an American
                                citizen, for six years has sought permission to emigrate from the
                                Soviet Union to the United States in order to be reunited with his
                                wife and two children.” It continues: “On March 25 Balovlenkov began
                                a hunger strike in support of his demand to be permitted to join his
                                family in the United States.” (Department of State, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, Electronic Telegrams, D850365–0050)</note> I also
                            stated that, while the other <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                            Foreign Ministers might not decide until the Lisbon <gloss target="#t_NAC_1">NAC</gloss>, it was likely I would be going to the
                            Helsinki commemoration in late July where I meet with <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> again. I suggested that the two
                            sides should soon begin work on an agenda for that meeting.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>