<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-09-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="250" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d250">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01 Manchuria/491</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far
                                Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_HSK1">Hornbeck</persName>) of a Conversation With the Former Chinese
                                Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs (<persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LCFW1">Lee</persName>)</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-09-08">September 8, 1932</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>After discussion of other matters, Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LCFW1">Lee</persName> said that Dr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_KHH1">Kung</persName> had informed him of the
                            substance of the conversation between Dr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_KHH1">Kung</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_HSK1">Hornbeck</persName> of September 7. He
                            said that the Chinese Government would be under additional pressure from
                            opposition factions in China and from the public when Japan recognizes
                            “Manchoukuo”. It would undoubtedly be necessary for the Chinese
                            Government to do something. They had in mind both the possibility of
                            asking for a conference under the Nine-Power Treaty and that of making
                            on their own account a definite and vigorous protest against Japan’s
                            action of recognition. He wanted to get the benefit of Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_HSK1">Hornbeck</persName>’s advice.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_HSK1">Hornbeck</persName> inquired
                            by what process they would go about asking for a conference. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LCFW1">Lee</persName> said that
                            they would probably ask the <pb facs="0331" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/>
                            American Government to call a conference under the Nine-Power Treaty and
                            he would like to know whether such a request by the Chinese Government
                            would be embarrassing to the American Government: the Chinese Government
                            had tried and would continue to try not to take steps which would
                            embarrass the American Government. Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_HSK1">Hornbeck</persName> said that, as he
                            had said to Dr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_KHH1">Kung</persName>,
                            he could not undertake to answer such inquiries authoritatively or to
                            speak for the American Government, but that, viewing the question
                            unofficially and attempting to view it objectively, it would seem that,
                            if such a request came from the Chinese Government at this time, the
                            American Government would have to defer any action with regard to it
                            and, if it became known, as it doubtless would, that the Chinese
                            Government had made such a request and that the American Government was
                            taking no action in reply, that would have a bad effect. Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_HSK1">Hornbeck</persName> would therefore
                            suggest that Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LCFW1">Lee</persName>,
                            in any communication with the Chinese Legation or with the Chinese
                            Government direct, should suggest, on his own responsibility and not as
                            coming from this Department or any official thereof, that the present
                            would not be an opportune time for the Chinese Government to make such a
                            proposal and that the Chinese Government should have in mind the fact
                            that the world is at present awaiting receipt of the report of the
                            League Commission and that it is not likely that the American Government
                            would give any serious thought to the suggestion that it call a
                            conference until sometime after that report has been made public and
                            probably not until after the election in November. Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LCFW1">Lee</persName> said that that all
                            seemed very logical to him and that in any communications which he might
                            make he would not bring the State Department into the question.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LCFW1">Lee</persName> then reverted
                            to the subject of the necessity for the Chinese Government’s taking some
                            action if and when Japanese recognition of “Manchoukuo” takes place. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_HSK1">Hornbeck</persName> said that
                            the problem which confronts other governments in that connection is that
                            of relative advantage as between taking notice of or taking no notice of
                            Japanese recognition, if and when; but that, of course, the Chinese
                            Government had the domestic situation to consider. He said that there
                            occurred to him a suggestion, which he would make, it being understood
                            that he was speaking “not for attribution”. It occurred to him that the
                            Chinese Government might well make this the occasion and take advantage
                            of it as an opportunity to make a carefully wrought, noncontroversial
                            and noncontrovertible statement in support and in defense of the thesis
                            that Manchuria is an integral part of China. There followed some
                            discussion of this point and Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LCFW1">Lee</persName> expressed thanks for the suggestion, said that he
                            would consider it, <pb facs="0332" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/> and that in
                            any communication which he might make he would not bring the Department
                            into the matter.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_HSK1">S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ornbeck</hi>]</persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>