<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-11-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="348" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d348">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/746</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State
                                    (<persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_CWR1">Castle</persName>) of a
                                Conversation With the Japanese Chargé (<persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SH1">Saito</persName>) on November 14,
                                1932</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-11-15">November 15, 1932</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SH1">Saito</persName> said that he
                            had nothing particular to say, but that he wanted to tell me about a
                            letter he had had from a man high up in the Japanese Government who is a
                            good friend of my friends <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_MCS1">Count
                                Makino</persName>, <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SBK1">Baron
                                Shidehara</persName> and others. (I am sorry to say that I doubt the
                            existence of a letter.)</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SH1">Saito</persName> began by
                            saying how much all the Japanese liked Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_GJC1">Grew</persName>. I said that this
                            seemed to me perfectly natural, since Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_GJC1">Grew</persName> was not only a very
                            able man, but a very friendly man who liked people and was quick to see
                            their good points. Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SH1">Saito</persName> said that he felt Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_GJC1">Grew</persName>
                            <pb facs="0443" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/> was doing fine work in Japan
                            to calm down the feeling there against this country; that his
                            correspondent had informed him that the Government had ordered the
                            newspapers to stop their anti-American agitation, that as a result of
                            this the feeling toward the United States was growing rapidly better; he
                            said that the Japanese appreciated the fact that the Department of
                            State, since the publication of the <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LERB1">Lytton</persName> Report, had not made
                            any public statements critical of Japan. I pointed out to Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SH1">Saito</persName> that, after all, the
                                <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LERB1">Lytton</persName> Report was
                            made to the League, that although we were very interested in it, we,
                            nevertheless, felt that it was a matter for the League to act upon and
                            that it was not in our province to say anything about it until the
                            League should act; that we were, of course, through our silence,
                            avoiding any possible implication that we were trying to influence the
                            League. Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SH1">Saito</persName> said
                            he was very glad to know this and that his Government would be glad to
                            know that we were not directing the League as to what it might do. I
                            told him it was nonsense to think any such thing because we were not in
                            the habit of interfering with the internal workings of an organization
                            of which we were not a member.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SH1">Saito</persName> then came to
                            the purpose of his call, which purpose he had intended to hide under
                            talk about other things. This was, of course, that the presence of the
                            fleet in the Pacific was a continual irritation to the Japanese; he said
                            that his correspondent failed to understand why a great nation like the
                            United States should find it necessary to keep the fleet in the Pacific
                            as a threat to Japan. I told him that his correspondent had no right to
                            use the last phrase in the statement, that there was no reason whatever
                            to think that the fleet was threatening Japan and that it seemed
                            childish on the part of Japan to make anything out of it. Mr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_SH1">Saito</persName> hastened to say that
                            his correspondent had said that it was childish of Japan to take this
                            attitude, but that, nevertheless, he felt it would be very quietening to
                            the childish minds in Japan if the Atlantic fleet were sent to the
                            Atlantic or, even if two or three ships were sent; that it would
                            immediately improve the situation in Japan. I told him that the
                            disposition of the fleet was a matter for this Government to decide,
                            that if the Navy preferred to keep it in the Pacific, which was
                            incidentally a very great saving of money, I did not see where Japan had
                            any right to complain. He said he entirely realized this, that he was
                            merely mentioning the fact because his correspondent had mentioned it as
                            something that would improve the atmosphere if some of the ships came to
                            the Atlantic.</p>
                        <p>We parted on amicable terms.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_CWR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">W. R. Castle, Jr.</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>