<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China (Johnson) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-05-23T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-05-23T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-05-23T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-05-23T02:00:00-05:00" n="39"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d39">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01 Manchuria/221: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China (<persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_JNT1"
                            type="from">Johnson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-05-23T15:00:00+08:00"
                            >May 23, 1932—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 23—8:30 a.m.<note n="25" xml:id="d39fn25">Telegram in
                            three sections.</note>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>558. Following from American Consul General at Harbin: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“May 20, 4 p.m. The local Japanese Consulate General has stated that
                            sporadic fighting between the Japanese defence forces near Sungpu and
                            about 1200 of General Ma’s troops is still continuing; that there is
                            fear that some of General Ma’s soldiers disguised as civilians have made
                            their way into Fuchiatien with refugees who have fled across the river
                            to Harbin; that Japanese troops are coming from Sansing and possibly
                            from <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_CC7">Changchun</persName> to
                            reenforce the islands near Sungpu; that old Kirin troops have arrived at
                            Pinghsien with the object of making an advance on Harbin; and that
                            Japanese patrols had been increased at Harbin and Fuchiatien to avoid
                            local disturbances.”</p>
                        <p>“May 21, noon. League Commission left Harbin by special train for Mukden
                            at 7:10 this morning, leaving behind <persName
                                corresp="frus1932v03#p_BLWS1">Biddle</persName>, <persName
                                corresp="frus1932v03#p_MGS1">Moss</persName>, <persName
                                corresp="frus1932v03#p_KBHUv1">Kotze</persName> and <persName
                                corresp="frus1932v03#p_AWW1">Astor</persName> who are to proceed
                            tomorrow to Tsitsihar by aeroplane, thence by train via Taonan to
                            Nanking.</p>
                        <p>Commission abandoned idea of proceeding to Tsitsihar because Japanese
                            military stated that they could not afford protection.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Manchukuo refused to assist Commission to meet General Ma who was
                                accused of being an enemy of the new state. Soviet Government
                                refused permission to enter Siberia to four persons mentioned above
                                who were desirous of meeting Ma at Taheiho on the ground that <pb
                                    facs="0129" n="31" xml:id="pg_31"/> granting such permission
                                would be departure from the neutral position which Soviet Russia has
                                consistently maintained throughout the present conflict.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center"> . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Harbin is closely surrounded on all sides by anti-Japanese and
                                anti-Manchukuo troops. Chinese forces estimated to be about 10,000
                                at Pinghsien have stopped their advance south according to a
                                Japanese report. Japanese troops are being withdrawn from Sansing on
                                steamers, which are constantly being fired upon, to reinforce those
                                now engaged in fighting Ma’s forces near Sungpu.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>It is not believed danger threatens Harbin but the situation is annoying
                            to Japanese military who are obliged to scatter their limited forces on
                            so many fronts. Anti-Manchukuo forces continue to make raids along the
                            railway east of Imienpo. It is reliably reported that Sansing was
                            evacuated by Chinese troops before arrival of Japanese forces there.
                            Chinese tactics appear to be to refuse to engage large bodies of
                            Japanese troops but to attack isolated groups. New Kirin troops
                            continually going over to other side. Chinese crews of gunboats
                            allegedly assisting Japanese operations on Sungari River reported
                            unwilling to fire on own people.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_JNT1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
