<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-05-08T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-05-08T23:00:00-05:00" n="6" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d6">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/5174: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China (<persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_JNT1" type="from">Johnson</persName>) to
                                the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-05-09T12:00:00+08:00">May 9,
                                1932—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received May 9—6:25 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>511. Following from Kuo Wen, Nanking, May 6th: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Dr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LW1">Lo Wen-kan</persName>
                                    issued a statement this afternoon with regards to the
                                    Sino-Japanese peace agreement signed at Shanghai last
                                    Thursday.</p>
                                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LW1">Lo</persName> expressed
                                    his confidence that the Japanese troops will be <pb facs="0104" n="6" xml:id="pg_6"/> withdrawn to their defense position as
                                    before January 28 last, and that there will be no necessity for
                                    the Mixed Commission to exercise its function of reporting
                                    whether normal conditions have been reestablished in Shanghai or
                                    not.</p>
                                <p>The Foreign Minister defined the peace agreement in a press
                                    interview at 10 o’clock tonight. He said that since the
                                    conference began, Japan had brought up many unreasonable
                                    demands, which were successfully resisted by the Chinese
                                    delegates. For example, the Japanese first proposed a
                                    round-table conference to settle the Shanghai question. Then
                                    they suggested the establishment of a free port in Shanghai and
                                    the extension of the Settlement. They also brought up the demand
                                    for the suppression of the anti-Japanese boycott. All these
                                    demands were eventually withdrawn as a result of the efforts of
                                    the Chinese delegates.</p>
                                <p>Referring to the question of Japanese withdrawal, Dr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LW1">Lo</persName> said that the
                                    Japanese originally demanded an extensive area for their troops
                                    to withdraw to, but as the result of a prolonged argument on the
                                    part of the Chinese delegates, they agreed to the area
                                    designated in the peace agreement. The Japanese also brought up
                                    the question of the stationing of Chinese troops along the
                                    southern bank of the Soochow Creek and at Pootung, but the
                                    demand was withdrawn upon the opposition of the Chinese. Dr.
                                        <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LW1">Lo</persName> added
                                    that although the present agreement fails to provide for the
                                    immediate withdrawal of all the Japanese troops from Shanghai,
                                    it represents the best bargain which China can get under the
                                    existing international situation as well as the circumstances
                                    prevailing in China today. With the Shanghai affair settled, the
                                    Ministry of Foreign Affairs will turn its attention to the
                                    Manchurian question, which is the root of the Sino-Japanese
                                    controversy.</p>
                                <p>Concerning the Sino-Russian situation, Dr. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_LW1">Lo</persName> said that the
                                    Chinese Government had long been considering the question of
                                    resuming diplomatic relations with Soviet Russia, but recent
                                    events such as the failure of the Soviet Government to accord
                                    adequate treatment to the Chinese delegation at the Sino-Russian
                                    conference, coupled with reports that the Soviet authorities
                                    were treating with the puppet government in Manchuria, are
                                    likely to hinder the speedy restoration of friendly relations
                                    between the two countries.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer>For the Minister:<lb/><signed><persName><hi rend="smallcaps">Perkins</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>