<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-06-13T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-06-13T06:00:00-05:00" n="88" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d88">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01 Manchuria/252: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan (<persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_GJC1" type="from">Grew</persName>) to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-06-13T20:00:00+09:00">June 13, 1932—8
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received June 13—10:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>155. The movement for recognition of Manchukuo seems to be gaining
                            headway in the past few days. Both major political parties are reported
                            as preparing a joint resolution in favor of recognition, for
                            presentation to the Diet tomorrow. <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_UCY1">Count Uchida</persName>, whose
                            appointment as Foreign Minister seems to be imminent, is reported as
                            strongly in favor of immediate recognition. According to several press
                            interviews, General <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_ALGS1">Araki</persName>, Minister for War, is, curiously, reported as
                            opposed to immediate recognition because he desires the settlement of
                            the question of Manchurian administration (Sanshomondai) before granting
                            recognition.</p>
                        <p>The influential <hi rend="italic">Nichi Nichi</hi> suggests that Chinese
                            in Manchuria fear that the delay in recognition by Japan is due to
                            Japan’s desire to annex that country—a belief growing out of the present
                            Japanese plan to combine the Japanese authorities in Manchuria under one
                            head. The above paper, the <hi rend="italic">Chugai</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Yomiuri</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Osaka
                                Mainichi</hi>
                            <pb facs="0174" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/> have all published editorials in
                            the past 3 days advocating immediate recognition.</p>
                        <p>Replying to interpellations in the Diet the Government has stated that
                            the time is still premature for recognition although the Government is
                            prepared to grant recognition when the time arrives. Public opinion
                            seems to be split, some advocating immediate recognition—others advising
                            a watchful waiting policy. The press tonight reports that <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_UCY1">Uchida</persName> and <persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_ALGS1">Araki</persName> are meeting to
                            discuss this question.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="frus1932v03#p_GJC1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>