<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[166] *Part X: Remarks in conclusion. *Part X: Remarks in conclusion.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1872p2v1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1871-12-31T23:56:00-05:00" notAfter="1872-12-01T23:55:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1872-12-01T23:55:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-12-31T23:56:00-05:00" n="16" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d16">
                <head>
                    <seg type="margin">[166]</seg> *Part X: Remarks in conclusion.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-volume-rules" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1872-12-01T23:59:59-04:56" notBefore="1872-01-01T00:00:00-04:56">undated</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <seg type="margin">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Part X.</hi>—Concluding
                            remarks.</seg> Her Britannic Majesty’s government has now stated, for
                        the information of the arbitrators, the principal facts which it believes to
                        be material to a just adjudication on the claims urged on the part of the
                        United States. In so doing, Her Majesty’s government has been under the
                        unavoidable disadvantage of having to meet a case which has not yet been
                        presented. When that shall have, been done, and the claims of the United
                        States shall have been clearly ascertained, Her Majesty’s government will
                        avail itself of the opportunity which it will have, under Article IV of the
                        treaty, to submit to the tribunal such additional or more ample statement of
                        facts as may then appear to be necessary. It forbears, also, until a
                        comparison of the cases submitted on both sides shall have shown what points
                        are really in dispute between the two governments, to enter into argument in
                        support of its own position, and will, for the present, content itself with
                        placing before the tribunal the considerations which follow.</p>
                <p>That vessels should, under whatever circumstances, have been procured from
                        British ports for warlike use, and employed as belligerent cruisers against
                        the United States, Great Britain herself being neutral, has been a subject
                        of displeasure and regret to Her Britannic Majesty’s government. This regret
                        is not removed by the facts, material as they undoubtedly are to a just
                        appreciation of the question, that the vessels were obtained by means of
                        artifice and concealment, which defeated the vigilance of the officers of
                        the government; that all of them, when they respectively departed from Her
                        Majesty’s dominions were wholly unarmed, and some of them constructed as
                        mere merchant-ships, without any special adaptation for war; that they were
                        few in number; and that the persons who gained possession, and control of
                        them, and by whom they were used for war, were themselves, as the Government
                        of the United States has never, ceased to maintain, American citizens.
                        Circumstances such as these must greatly affect, in the judgment of any
                        impartial person, the question as to the responsibility of the neutral
                        government. Yet it is nevertheless true that the “acts themselves, being
                        such as, if done or authorized by the neutral government, would have
                        compromised its neutrality, had an inevitable tendency to disturb its
                        relations with the belligerent against whom they were directed. Her
                        Majesty’s government, therefore, has not hesitated to express its regret,
                        frankly and publicly, to the Government of the United States, and has
                        permitted the expression of it to be placed on record in the treaty which
                        has been concluded between the two powers.</p>
                <p>But the Government of the United States insists that it is entitled to
                        satisfaction in money for claims which it asserts have arisen out of acts of
                        these vessels—that is, out of operations of war carried on, by means of
                        them, by the persons in possession of them for the time being. It is <pb facs="0426" n="412" xml:id="pg_412"/> manifest that this contention is
                        one which Her Britannic Majesty’s government, although animated by the most
                        friendly feelings toward the United States, could not, with due regard for
                        its own rights and those of neutral nations in general, consent to
                        acknowledge, not believing it to be just. It is a claim of strict right, and
                        can be supported only by clearly establishing that an international duty,
                        owed by Great Britain to the United States, has been violated by Great
                        Britain, and by showing further that an appreciable injury has accrued
                        directly from this cause to the United States, for which Great Britain
                        ought, in justice, to make reparation in money. It is for the Government of
                        the United States, then, to substantiate these positions, to specify clearly
                        the international duty or duties on which it relies, and to prove the
                        violation of which it complains.</p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="margin">[167]</seg> A charge of injurious negligence on the part
                        of a sovereign government, in the exercise of any of the powers of
                        sovereignty, needs to be sustained on strong and solid grounds. Every
                        sovereign government claims the right to be independent of external scrutiny
                        or interference in its exercise of these powers; and the general assumption
                        that they are exercised with good faith and reasonable care, and that laws
                        are fairly and properly administered, (an assumption without which peace and
                        friendly intercourse could not exist among nations,) ought to subsist until
                        it has been displaced by proof to the contrary. It is not enough to suggest
                        or prove that a government, in the exercise of a reasonable judgment on some
                        question of fact or law, and using the means of information, at its
                        *command, has formed and acted on an opinion from which another government
                        dissents or can induce an arbitrator to dissent. Still less is it sufficient
                        to show that a judgment pronounced by a court of competent jurisdiction, and
                        acted upon by the executive, was tainted with error. An administrative act
                        founded on error, or an erroneous judgment of a court, may, indeed, under
                        some circumstances, found a claim to compensation on behalf of a person or
                        government injured by the act or judgment. But a charge of negligence
                        brought against a government cannot be supported on such grounds. Nor is it
                        enough to suggest or prove some defect of judgment or penetration, or
                        somewhat less than the utmost possible promptitude and celerity of action on
                        the part of an officer of the government in the execution of his official
                        duties. To found on this alone a claim to compensation, as for a breach of
                        international duty, would be to exact, in international affairs, a
                        perfection of administration which few governments or none attain in fact,
                        or could reasonably hope to attain, in their domestic concerns; it would set
                        up an impracticable, and therefore an unjust and fallacious standard, would
                        give occasion to incessant and unreasonable complaints, and render the
                        situation of neutrals intolerable. Nor, again, is a nation to be held
                        responsible for a delay or omission occasioned by mere accident, and not by
                        the want of reasonable foresight or care. Lastly, it is not sufficient to
                        show that an act has been done which it was the duty of the government to
                        endeavor to prevent. It is necessary to allege and to prove that there has
                        been a failure to use for the prevention of an act which the government was
                        bound to endeavor to prevent, such care as governments ordinarily employ in
                        their domestic concerns, and may reasonably be expected to exert in matters
                        of international interest and obligation. These considerations apply with
                        especial force to nations which are in the enjoyment of free institutions,
                        and in which the government is bound to obey, and cannot dispense with the
                        laws.</p>
                <p>
                    <seg type="margin">[168]</seg> If the tribunal should come to the conclusion
                        that Great Britain has <pb facs="0427" n="413" xml:id="pg_413"/> incurred
                        any liability to the United States, the question will then arise what should
                        be deemed the just measure and extent of that liability. Her Britannic
                        Majesty’s government abstains at present from entering into that question,
                        and will reserve such observations as may be fitly offered in relation to it
                        on the part of Great Britain to a later stage of the proceedings. Here it is
                        sufficient to remark that a claim on the part of a belligerent to be
                        indemnified at the expense of a neutral for losses inflicted or occasioned
                        by any of the ordinary operations of war, on the plea that those operations
                        were assisted or facilitated by negligence on the part of the neutral
                        government, is one which involves grave considerations and requires to be
                        weighed with the utmost care. Losses of which such negligence is the direct
                        and proximate cause, (and it is in respect of such only that compensation
                        could justly be awarded,) are commonly not easy to separate from those
                        springing from other causes. Success in warlike operations is generally due
                        not only to the force possessed, but to the skill and courage exerted by the
                        successful combatant. If claims of this nature were to be freely admitted, a
                        belligerent might demand to be indemnified by the neutral against
                        consequences fairly attributable, in part or altogether, not to the fault of
                        the latter but to his own want of capacity and enterprise. Her Majesty’s
                        government has been compelled to point out that in respect of the vessels to
                        which the foregoing statement relates there was, on the part of the
                        Government of the United States or its officers, an extraordinary remissness
                        in using the naval forces at their disposal, and that if ordinary activity
                        had been exerted in the endeavor to intercept and capture these vessels, the
                        losses of which the United States now complain would probably have been in
                        great measure averted. It cannot be consistent with any reasonable view of
                        international obligations that a belligerent state, alleging itself to be
                        aggrieved by some imputed negligence of a neutral government, should on that
                        account claim indemnity from the neutral for losses in the course of warlike
                        operations which it has not actively and diligently exerted itself to
                        prevent or arrest.</p>
                <p>It was the constant aim of Her Britannic Majesty’s government throughout the
                        war to observe with fidelity and exactness the obligations, and to maintain
                        unimpaired the rights, which the law and practice of nations have assigned
                        to neutral powers. In upholding those rights all the nations of the world
                        are interested and it was the duty of Great Britain, as a maritime power of
                        the first order, brought by circumstances, into closer contact with the war
                        than any other state, to resist on the one hand any encroachment on them,
                        and to abstain on the other from any attempt to extend them beyond the just
                        and expedient limits traced out by international law. Her Majesty’s
                        government has given the best proof of its sincerity in these respects, as
                        well as its earnest desire to promote the pacific and amicable settlement of
                        international differences, by proposing and agreeing to refer to the
                        judgment of impartial arbitrators the question whether, in the matters
                        complained of by the United States, it has failed to discharge any
                        international duty. In deciding on the questions submitted to it, the
                        tribunal will be called upon to apply to *them principles and considerations
                        of wide application, not confined to maritime neutrality, nor to the acts
                        and conduct of maritime nations alone. Great Britain is prepared to accept
                        the award, whether favorable or unfavorable to her. She desires only that it
                        shall be just. She claims only that it shall be founded on a true and
                        equitable interpretation of the law of nations, and on principles which she
                        herself and all other powers may be satisfied, whether as neutral or as
                        belligerent, to acknowledge and abide by in time to come.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
