<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1869-07-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1869-07-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="413" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d413">
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hoar</persName>,
                                    Attorney-General, to Mr. <persName type="to">Pierrepont</persName>, district attorney.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <dateline><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1869-07-06"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 6, 1869</date>.</dateline>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am instructed by the President to
                                say to you that your course in prosecuting with energy and vigor the
                                violations of the neutrality laws of the United States meets his
                                full approbation.</p>
                            <p><seg type="margin">[93]</seg> Whatever may be the sympathies felt by
                                the Government or people of the United States with the inhabitants
                                of other countries seeking to vindicate their liberty, or acquire
                                national independence, a *violation of the laws of the United
                                States, by their agents or sympathizers, cannot be tolerated. It is
                                the duty of every executive officer faithfully and fearlessly to
                                administer the law; and the United States will never permit, or
                                connive at, the fitting out of military expeditions, within our
                                territory, against any country with whom we are at peace. The nation
                                will conduct and control its own wars, and will not allow private
                                citizens, or foreigners who enjoy our hospitality and protection, to
                                make, with impunity, this country the base of hostile
                                operations.</p>
                            <p>The President also directs me to to say to you that he desires that
                                you will use every means in your power to arrest and punish the
                                lawless men who have assaulted and obstructed the deputies of the
                                marshal in the discharge of their official duties.</p>
                            <p><seg type="margin">[94]</seg> It has been represented to me that
                                threatening letters have been addressed to the members of the grand
                                jury in attendance upon the district court, for the purpose of
                                deterring them from finding indictments. It would be disgraceful to
                                the Government if such an outrage should be successful in its
                                object, or the perpetrators of it escape with impunity. You will,
                                therefore, use every exertion to detect and punish them, and the
                                whole power of the Government will be used to support you in [94]
                                your efforts to insure a steady administration *of law, and a firm
                                administration of justice.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully, yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>B. R. HOAR,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Attorney-General.</hi></signed>
                            </closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Edwards Pierrepont</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Attorney, New York
                                    City.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>