<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-03-11T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-03-11T13:00:00-05:00" n="232" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d232">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94 Commission/882: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland (<persName type="from">Wilson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-03-11T19:00:00+01:00">March 11, 1933—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received March 11—3:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>145. My 142, March 8, 9 p.m.<note n="58" xml:id="d232fn58">It read:
                                “British delegation had just made an appointment with me to see Sir
                                John Simon on Saturday morning. Simon telegraphed that he desired to
                                talk about embargo on arms to the Far East” (783.91
                                Commission/869)</note> Simon asked me whether I had any information
                            as to my Government’s views on the matter of an embargo to the Far East
                            and I replied that I had not. He stated that he understood from
                            Washington that action by our Government could only be taken after
                            special legislation passed Congress. I replied that this was my
                            understanding of the matter. He stated that since he arrived here he had
                            ascertained that a number of states would require such legislation
                            before taking action. He added that Great Britain had laws by which the
                            Government could stop shipments at the ports by Executive Act but that
                            he had been unable to find any other producing states in the same
                            situation. Therefore his present thought was that common action would
                            necessarily have to be delayed for an indefinite period; that the
                            British Government had taken its action in order to draw attention to
                            the matter; that he was now about to report to the Cabinet what the
                            situation was, and was under the impression that the Cabinet would
                            decide to lift the embargo.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>