<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-05-12T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-05-12T16:00:00-05:00" n="350" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d350">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94 Advisory Committee/41:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Switzerland (<persName type="to">Wilson</persName>),
                                at Geneva</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-05-12T17:00:00-04:00">May 12, 1933—5
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>101. Your 177, May 10, 5 p.m., third paragraph.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Department does not understand why the question of the status of
                                consuls in Manchukuo in reference to the principle of
                                non-recognition is “pressing”. American consular officers are, as
                                you know, continuing to function in Manchuria and to look after
                                American interests in their respective districts in the same manner
                                as consular officers of other nations.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>As, in the Department’s opinion, the question of the status of
                                consuls in Manchuria is more delicate than certain other questions
                                connected with the principle of non-recognition, the Department
                                would deprecate especial stress or publicity in regard to the status
                                of consuls. It appears distinctly inadvisable to do anything which
                                would precipitate any action by the Manchuria regime which would
                                make the position of foreign consuls in Manchuria more difficult
                                than it now is.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Although the Department would not object to you, if you consider
                                such action advisable, informing the Secretary-General now along the
                                lines of the second sentence of paragraph 1, it suggests that you
                                defer communicating that information until you ascertain the nature
                                of the information furnished by other governments. In case other
                                governments are communicating more detailed information, please
                                inform the Department of the nature of that information, whereupon
                                the Department will give further consideration to the matter.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>