<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-12-30T14:27:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-01-20T12:15:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                    <head>180. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry Kissinger</persName> met in the Oval Office of
                        the White House on the morning of November 5, 1971, to discuss <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>ʼs conversation with Prime Minister
                            <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName> on the previous day.
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>ʼs overall assessment
                        was that “the Indians are bastards anyway. They are starting a war there.…
                        To them East Pakistan is no longer the issue. Now, I found it very
                        interesting how she carried on to you yesterday about West Pakistan.” He
                        felt, however, that <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> had
                        achieved his objective in the conversation: “While she was a bitch, we got
                        what we wanted too&amp;. She will not be able to go home and say that the
                        United States didnʼt give her a warm reception and therefore in despair
                        sheʼs got to go to war.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        judged that <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName> had been thwarted
                        in her objective: “She would rather have had you give her a cool reception
                        so that she could say that she was really put upon.” <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> agreed: “We really slobbered over the
                        old witch.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> felt that on
                        matters of substance, nothing of importance had <pb facs="0529" n="500" xml:id="pg_500"/> been conceded: “You slobbered over her in things that
                        did not matter, but in things that did matter, you didnʼt give her an inch.”
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> agreed that in the upcoming
                        conversation with <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName> the approach
                        to take was to be “a shade cooler” and allow her to do more to carry the
                        conversation than had been the case in the initial conversation. (National
                        Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, White House Tapes, Recording of conversation between <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, November 5, 1971, 8:51–9:00 a.m., Oval Office,
                        Conversation No. 615–4) A transcript of this conversation is published in
                            <ref target="frus1969-76ve07#d150">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume E–7,
                            Documents on South Asia, 1969–1972, Document 150</ref>.</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and Prime Minister
                            <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName> met in the Oval Office at
                        11:20 a.m. on November 5. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_HPN1">Haksar</persName> were also present.
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> opened the conversation by
                        discussing the objectives of his planned trip to China. Thereafter the
                        conversation, which lasted an hour, became a diplomatic tour dʼhorizon,
                        touching on many of the trouble spots of the world, but with scant reference
                        to South Asia. <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName> did not respond
                        to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>ʼs proposal of the previous
                        day to consider a withdrawal of forces from the borders of India and
                        Pakistan. (Ibid., Recording of conversation between President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName>, November 5, 1971, 11:20 a.m.–12:20
                        p.m., Oval Office, Conversation No. 615–23) <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> prepared a memorandum of the conversation (ibid.,
                        White House Special Files, Presidentʼs Office Files, Box 2, Memoranda for
                        the President, Beginning October 31, 1971) which is published in <ref target="frus1969-76ve07#d151">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume E–7,
                            Documents on South Asia, 1969–1972, Document 151</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>