<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-12-30T14:27:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-01-20T12:15:00-05:00" n="199" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d199">
                    <head>199. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, Secretary of State
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>, and National Security
                        Assistant <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> met in the Oval
                        Office of the White House at 12:30 p.m. on November 24, 1971, to discuss
                        developments in South Asia in light of the expanding conflict in East
                        Pakistan. <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> began the
                        conversation by denying that there was any difference in perspective on
                        South Asia between the White House and the Department of State and offering
                        his assessment of how the United States should respond to the crisis.
                        “First, it seems to me we should engage in the maximum diplomatic efforts to
                        do everything we can to caution restraint on both sides at the highest level
                        always so that everyone can look at the record and see that we have done
                        everything that we can diplomatically. Secondly, I think that our relations
                        with <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> are good and should
                        continue to be good and we should continue to keep very close to him. Three,
                        I donʼt think we should try to mastermind a political solution. I never
                        thought so. I donʼt think it is possible and I think he [<persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName>] is coming to the conclusion that
                        something has to be done politically.” <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> went on: “He is going to have to do it on his own.”
                        He added: “I think he is going to be forced to do something, either that or
                        he is going to get out. There is the possibility that he will turn over to
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName>, which would not be a good
                        development…. I think the thing we have to face up to, and not make any
                        decisions so this is not to ask you to decide anything, but I think, I want
                        to express my view that I think it is probably going to get worse. I donʼt
                        see any solution for—so I think our principal objective should be to do what
                        we can to prevent fighting from breaking out.”</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> referred to news reports on the
                        fighting in East Pakistan and asked if the Indians were still denying that
                        they had divisions fighting there. <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> responded that they were denying it and that while
                        they did not have divisions involved, India was in East Pakistan in brigade
                        strength. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> noted that the
                        Indian brigades were supported by artillery, air, and armor. <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> concluded that India would “get more
                        involved” in the fighting in East Pakistan and that Pakistanʼs position
                        would progressively deteriorate. “I think we have to face the fact that
                            <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName>ʼs position militarily is
                        extremely weak. Heʼs got 60–80 thousand men in East Pakistan.” <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> interjected: “Heʼll be demolished
                        there.” <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> pointed to the
                        logistical problems confronted by Pakistan. “It is a 2500 mile flight” to
                        resupply the troops in East Pakistan. “The logistics, you know, are
                        impossible…. My own judgment is that probably it will get worse, and
                        probably we will have to face up to the fact that it will get worse.” He
                        added: “Our ability to affect the course of events is quite limited.”
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> noted that he had
                        instructed Department of State officials to delay processing export licenses
                        to <pb facs="0585" n="556" xml:id="pg_556"/> India and not to make any
                        commitments on economic assistance to India. But he felt that these were
                        effectively symbolic gestures that would not serve to deter India: “The
                        leverage we have on India is very minimal. If we take some action against
                        them, which you might decide to do, it would be symbolic rather than
                        substantive.”</p>
                    <p>There was inconclusive discussion about whether anything would be gained by
                        submitting the crisis to the United Nations Security Council. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> then reverted to <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>ʼ observation that the United States
                        appeared to be limited to symbolic gestures in attempting to restrain India.
                        “I know it can be said that it wonʼt do any good, and we donʼt have any
                        leverage, and itʼs only symbolic and the rest. But on the other hand, I want
                        you to look into what we could do that is symbolic because “I think we need
                        some symbolism.” He recognized the realities of the situation: “Looking at
                        the balance there, the Indians are going to win…. Pakistan will
                        disintegrate.” It was therefore “very much in our interest to get the damned
                        thing cooled if we can…. Under those circumstances, it seems to me that,
                        clearly apart from the fact that <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> has been more decent to us than she has, clearly apart
                        from that, I think that our policy wherever we can should definitely be
                        tilted toward Pakistan, and not toward India. I think India is more at
                        fault…. Having said that, it seems to me that our whole game has got to be
                        played—if you could find something symbolic to do I think it really has to
                        be … [He did not complete this thought.] She knows that we did not shoot
                        blanks when she was here. Maybe it doesnʼt mean anything…. In terms of the
                        merits of the situation, to the extent that we can tilt it toward Pakistan,
                        I would prefer to play that. Thatʼs where the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> game comes in.” <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> felt that if the issue was taken up by the United
                        Nations “Pakistan will come off better than India.”</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> “agreed fully” that the United
                        States should tilt toward Pakistan. The question was how to do it. He felt
                        there were several possibilities. “One would be right now weʼd just announce
                        that weʼre not going to grant any more export licenses…. We actually could
                        embargo everything in the pipeline…. We may have $10 or $15 million worth in
                        the pipeline…. military equipment…. We could say that weʼre not going to
                        permit economic assistance [to be] committed, itʼs about $11 million worth.
                        Itʼs insignificant. I think that would be probably not a wise thing to do
                        because weʼre going to have to provide help for them for the refugees
                        anyway.” <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> added that “300 and
                        some odd million is done in irrevocable letters of credit, so we canʼt get
                        out of that.” <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> said “I just may
                        want to take a hard line on that.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> agreed with <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> that it would be hard to finesse the letters of
                        credit that had been issued.</p>
                    <p>Whatever the constraints, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> was
                        determined to do something that might serve to restrain India: “I feel that
                        we ought to do something <pb facs="0586" n="557" xml:id="pg_557"/> symbolic,
                        I really … feel that something symbolic might have an effect on restraining
                        India.” <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> suggested an
                        announcement on November 26 of a suspension of any further export licenses.
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> indicated that he wanted to
                        review his policy options before meeting again on November 26. He was wary
                        of economic sanctions that might prove “useless.” He said he was looking for
                        an approach that was “very firm.” “In anything that we say,” he added,
                        “there should be a very positive statement that the United States commitment
                        to help refugees, to help hungry people, et cetera remains.” He felt that
                        military assistance, on the other hand, should be halted.</p>
                    <p>The conversation continued with <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>ʼs interpretation of Indiaʼs objectives in the
                        crisis. He saw India as striving to split the two wings of Pakistan, with
                        West Pakistan ultimately reduced to the status of Afghanistan, and East
                        Pakistan similarly reduced to the status of Bhutan. <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> viewed the conflict as growing out
                        of the deeply ingrained sectarian animosity that had animated the initial
                        division of the subcontinent. There was general agreement with <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>ʼs assessment of <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya Khan</persName> as a “decent and reasonable man”
                        if “not always smart politically.” All three viewed the prospect of
                            <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> stepping aside in favor of
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> with trepidation.
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>ʼs assessment of <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Bhutto</persName> was that he was “a total demagogue.”
                        In a concluding admonition to <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> said: “I donʼt want to get caught in
                        the business where we take the heat for a miserable war that we had nothing
                        to do with.” (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White House Tapes, Recording
                        of conversation among <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, November 24, 971, 12:27–1:12
                        p.m., Oval Office, Conversation No. 624–21) A transcript of this
                        conversation is published in <ref target="frus1969-76ve07#d156">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume E–7,
                            Documents on South Asia, 1969–1972, Document 156</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>