<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-12-30T14:27:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-01-20T12:15:00-05:00" n="244" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d244">
                    <head>244. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>On December 7, 1971, Secretary of Commerce <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Maurice
                            Stans</persName> reported to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> at the White House on his 11-day trip to the Soviet
                        Union. He was upbeat about the prospects for improved relations. Premier
                            <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName> had told him: “Mr.
                        Secretary, we have high hopes for your mission.” <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Stans</persName> and his party had been feted in such a way as to
                        reinforce that impression. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Stans</persName> left
                        after 20 minutes.</p>
                    <p>After <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Stans</persName> left the conversation
                        turned to the situation on the subcontinent. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                        began by discussing the backgrounder <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> intended to provide for the press on the crisis.
                        Framed in general statements about United States concern for the success of
                        Indiaʼs democracy and <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>ʼs
                        long-standing interest in the country, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> said he could “make in a very low key way an
                        enormously damning case against the Indians.” In sketching his indictment of
                        India, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> said: “I can show a
                        real pattern of Indian deceit. For example on November 19 I saw the Indian
                        Ambassador. On November 15 I saw the Pakistan Foreign Secretary. And I told
                        him we needed a maximum program because it would be very difficult to
                        prevent hostilities from breaking out. He said he would let me know after he
                        came back on the 22nd. And on the 19th I told this to the Indian Ambassador.
                        He said let me know as soon as you know when that will be. I said around the
                        28th. On the 22nd they attacked.”</p>
                    <pb facs="0712" n="683" xml:id="pg_683"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> outlined the case he wanted to
                        see made to the press: “The purpose is to show that weʼve done the best we
                        can. And incidentally, I would also—I think you should also get across
                        [that] we have no influence, we have no responsibility for either. Itʼs not
                        our job. The Russians have an interest in India. The Chinese have a hell of
                        an interest in Pakistan. We only have an interest in peace. Weʼre not
                        anti-Indian, weʼre not anti-Pakistan. We are anti-aggression.” (National
                        Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, White House Tapes, Recording of conversation among President
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Stans</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HGAMJ1">Haig</persName>,
                        and <persName corresp="#p_ZRL1">Ziegler</persName>, December 7, 1971,
                        3:55–4:29 p.m., Oval Office, Conversation No. 631–4) The editors transcribed
                        the portions of the tape recording printed here specifically for this
                        volume. A transcript of this conversation is published in <ref target="frus1969-76ve07#d163">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume E–7,
                            Documents on South Asia, 1969–1972, Document 163</ref>.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>