<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-12-17T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-12-17T10:00:00-05:00" n="324" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d324">
                    <head>324. Transcript of Telephone Conversation Between President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and His Assistant for National
                        Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d324fn1">Source: Library of Congress,
                            Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                            Papers, Box 370, Telephone Conversations, Chronological File. No
                            classification marking.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-12-17T10:00:00-05:00">December 17, 1971, 10
                            a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Mr. President.</p>
                    <p>P: Hello, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry</persName>, whatʼs the topic
                        today?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: It looks like we are in business.
                        The Paks have accepted it [the Indian cease-fire offer].</p>
                    <p>P: Does that mean she (Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName>)
                        wonʼt break it?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, she has no pretext to break
                        it. Oh, they are bringing me in a flash cable.<note n="2" xml:id="d324fn2">Reference is to telegram 3516 from Colombo, December 17. (National
                            Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, DEF 6–3 <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>)</note> The Celanese want us to put some of our ships in
                        the Indian Ocean into Colombo.</p>
                    <pb facs="0880" n="851" xml:id="pg_851"/>
                    <p>P: Why do they want them?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: They would like to show our
                        presence.</p>
                    <p>P: I see.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: But at any rate, <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> has accepted it now. The Security
                        Council in essence killed the Soviet resolution last night. What we did
                        after you and I talked—the British were horsing around with this
                        nonpermanent residents resolution and the Soviets were running around with
                        one. We just took the resolution of the others as ours.<note n="3" xml:id="d324fn3">In a conversation with <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> the evening of December 16, <persName corresp="#p_BGHW1">Bush</persName> described the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> draft resolution as “the Italian draft
                            with just a slight change.” He said it was the text that Pakistan wanted
                            and that China was prepared to accept. (Transcript of a telephone
                            conversation; Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box 370, Telephone
                            Conversations, Chronological File)</note> We had to because the Soviets
                        were going to.… As it was the Soviet one was killed—never got to a vote.
                        They adjourned and this was better for us. It means both sides have accepted
                        the ceasefire.</p>
                    <p>P: As far as the Security Council is concerned, what will they do?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, my view is that if the
                        fighting flares up again the attacker will be violating a <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> order—this is the only advantage. The
                        disadvantage is that it legitimizes aggression. Our position is if anyone
                        wants to vote for our resolution we will be delighted to let it pass.</p>
                    <p>P: Yes, I think that is a good point. Now at the present time the Paks are
                        satisfied, the Chinese are satisfied and the Russians. That is fine.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: We have come out of this amazingly
                        well and we scared the pants off the Russians. One shouldnʼt give somebody
                        who drops a match into a fire credit for calling the fire department.</p>
                    <p>P: Are you going to do a background thing?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: I talked to <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Scali</persName>. I will have a backgrounder with two
                        or three groups of two each and in a general way explain our strategy. I
                        think it is too early to put out the details.</p>
                    <p>P: Yes, I think that is very important. What will we get out of it?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, Henry Hubbard called me
                        yesterday and he said the President did it again. We were all screaming at
                        him and he was vindicated by events. And Kleiman was in from the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> this morning, but I didnʼt do too much
                        with him.</p>
                    <p>P: He must be pretty pleased with the Azores trip.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: The Azores he was delighted with
                        but the Post had a grudging position.</p>
                    <p>P: I see. [<hi rend="italic">1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                    <pb facs="0881" n="852" xml:id="pg_852"/>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                            line of source text not declassified</hi>] What we can get out is that
                        they were planning to attack but not say how.</p>
                    <p>P: Well, now if the question is raised about aid to India, I would be just
                        completely … I wouldnʼt tell them anything. The thing to do is to do it but
                        donʼt tell them anything. But on the other hand, it is what we do not what
                        we say.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GI1">Gandhi</persName> has written a letter<note n="4" xml:id="d324fn4">See
                                <ref target="#d314">Document 314</ref>.</note> which has been leaked
                        to the press.</p>
                    <p>P: That is outrageous.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: We are drafting a reply and I
                        think we ought to release it.</p>
                    <p>P: Release it before she gets it.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Right, because that gives us
                        another chance to make our case.</p>
                    <p>P: Now, what points … Does <persName corresp="#p_SJ1">Scali</persName> think
                        it is important for you to do the background thing?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Yes, he thinks it is
                        essential.</p>
                    <p>P: What points are you going to get across basically?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: The point that I want to get
                        across …</p>
                    <p>P: What I mean is to bring on the details.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: We have to let them know this was
                        not a war just between India and Pakistan, but whatever are the initial
                        reasons.</p>
                    <p>P: I think you ought to make the point very strongly that if we hadnʼt used
                        our influence as strongly as possible, it never would have come out the way
                        it did. The word would have been carried on from one <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> member to another. I think that is the point.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Well, that is a good point and
                        also that it would have had a very serious impact if the Soviet Union
                        had…</p>
                    <p>P: And in other parts of the world it would have been resisted.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Your whole strategy from the
                        beginning was to bring about what in fact we did. There are many who heard
                        me talk about this last week.</p>
                    <p>P: That is right so they are prepared for it.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: Even Henry Hubbard said for a few
                        days we thought we had to change our evaluation a little bit, but you have
                        come out right again. But what I will not do is put out all the exchanges.
                        That is premature.</p>
                    <p>P: Yes, and I suppose we should stay away from any interagency bickering and
                        all of that. I should think everyone is happy.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName>: No, now they (State) want to take
                        credit for it.</p>
                    <p>[Omitted here is discussion unrelated to South Asia.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>