<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>39. Telegram From the Embassy in India to to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-05-04T00:41:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-05-04T00:41:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-05-04T00:41:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-05-04T00:41:00-05:00" n="39"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d39">
                <head>39. Telegram From <gloss type="from">the Embassy in India</gloss> to <gloss
                        type="to">the Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d39fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 23–9 <gloss
                            target="#t_PAK1">PAK</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_EXDIS1"
                            >Exdis</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New Delhi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-05-04T05:41:00+00:00">May 4, 1971, 0541Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6741. Subj: Alleged Indian Support to Freedom Fighters and Other
                    Observations.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>During my meeting with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Swaran
                            Singh</persName> May 3 on refugees reported <gloss target="#t_SEPTEL1"
                            >septel</gloss>,<note n="2" xml:id="d39fn2">Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_KKB1">Keating</persName> told the Foreign Minister that
                            the United States would support the refugee relief efforts the <gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> High Commissioner for Refugees planned to
                            undertake in India. He also indicated that he had authorized the release
                            to various <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> volunteer agencies in
                            India of sufficient food to feed 175,000 refugees for a period of up to
                            3 months. (Telegram 6720 from New Delhi, May 3; ibid., REF <gloss
                                target="#t_PAK1">PAK</gloss>)</note> I told him that a number of my
                        colleagues in the diplomatic corps had come to me with what they claimed to
                        be first-hand information regarding the training and equipping of freedom
                        fighters on Indian territory.<note n="3" xml:id="d39fn3">In telegram 75390
                            to New Delhi, April 30, the Department referred to press stories
                            speculating that India intended to train refugees for guerrilla
                            operations in East Pakistan. The Department felt that such training
                            would call into question humanitarian support for the refugees.
                            (Ibid.)</note> I told him that I, of course, recognized the sensitivity
                        of this matter. On a personal basis I asked him to give me the justification
                        for Indian activities in support of the Bangla Desh forces.</item>
                    <pb facs="0131" n="102" xml:id="pg_102"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The Foreign Minister replied that the information to which I referred was
                        “absolutely incorrect.” Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KTN1"
                            >Kaul</persName> referred me to the reports of Frank Moraes in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Indian Express</hi> as well as to those of British and
                        American journalists regarding the organization and training of the
                        liberation forces inside East Pakistan. <persName corresp="#p_KTN1"
                            >Kaul</persName> said the refugees were in no state to fight. They were
                        hungry, sick and at times almost naked.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KTN1">Kaul</persName> insisted
                        that the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> had prevented the organizing of
                        volunteers to fight in East Pakistan. They had not retaliated against
                        fighting that had occurred on Indian territory or the more recent strafing
                        of Agartala Airport by Pakistan air force planes.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Swaran Singh</persName> said
                        he had a very uncomfortable feeling that without making a careful assessment
                        of what had actually transpired in East Pakistan an attempt was now being
                        made by people who were close to Pakistan to allege that Indiaʼs actions
                        were politically motivated against Pakistan. The Foreign Minister said, “I
                        stoutly refute these allegations.” He went on, as he put it, to “make a
                        special request to you” that the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                        Government should be the last to put India on the defensive in a situation
                        like this. He expressed concern if this was the type of international
                        recognition that India would get for all the restraint that they had shown.
                        Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KTN1">Kaul</persName> commented that
                        we were politicizing our relief.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The Foreign Minister said he felt extremely unhappy that there should be
                        any such feeling. He said in a very basic way, the sense of justice of the
                        international community would be shaken. Whether India received help or not
                        was a relatively minor matter. If the international community was prepared
                        to come to Indiaʼs assistance they would be most welcome.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>At this point the Foreign Minister referred to J.P. Narayan,<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d39fn4">Jayaprakash Narayan, senior member of the Congress
                            Party.</note> who has historically been the principal exponent of
                        Indo-Pak reconciliation and who has now publicly condemned developments in
                        East Pakistan. He said these were factors which should not be lightly
                        ignored.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>I told the Foreign Minister that I thought he was misstating some of my
                        remarks. I was conscious of the situation which he faced and that I would
                        prefer to leave the matter at that.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Later on in the conversation, Foreign Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_KTN1">Kaul</persName> asserted that the <gloss
                            target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> did not wish to provoke war with Pakistan.
                        The Pakistanis, on the other hand, were now deliberately killing Hindus in
                        East Pakistan in order to provoke India. The <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                            >GOI</gloss> had suppressed this news.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>In closing, I told the Foreign Minister that I was pleased with the
                        increased consultation that had been going on between the Ministry <pb
                            facs="0132" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/> of External Affairs and the
                        Embassy on a wide range of issues of mutual interest. I told him I would
                        like to see this continued in even greater depth. The Foreign Minister said
                        he was happy to hear this from me. He said he had already had a report from
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JLK1">Jha</persName> following his
                        conveying the suggested dates for our next round of bilateral talks.<note
                            n="5" xml:id="d39fn5">The annual bilateral talks to review relations
                            between the United States and India had initially been scheduled for
                            January 27–28. The talks were postponed several times, most recently in
                            a meeting on April 19 between Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JLK1"
                                >Jha</persName> and Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_IJN1"
                                >Irwin</persName>. (Telegrams 209080 and 66318 to New Delhi,
                            December 17, 1970, and April 20, 1971, respectively; National Archives,
                            RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, ORG 7 <gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss> and
                                <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> INDIA–<gloss target="#t_US1"
                                >US</gloss>)</note> The Foreign Minister said it had been his desire
                        that relations with my country should be as close or closer than those with
                        any other country in the world. That, he said, was the policy of his
                        government. It was their desire that a close exchange of views take place.
                        The <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> was anxious that our relations be
                        one of mutual confidence and understanding.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>The Foreign Minister said that the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> was
                        “not keen for leadership in the area” but they were prepared to face their
                        responsibilities and they appreciated the increased understanding of the
                            <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> in this regard.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>The Foreign Minister then referred to my pre-election article in which I
                        stated that Americaʼs candidate was not any one political party but rather
                        the Republic of India and he said that my candidate had won and that he
                        wanted to congratulate me on that.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>Referring to the suggested dates of our bilateral talks the Foreign
                        Minister explained that by September 1 parliament would no longer be in
                        session. The United Nations General Assembly was scheduled to resume about
                        September 17 or 18. He said he wanted a clear ten days before that time to
                        prepare himself. It was these factors that had influenced him. He said he
                        also understood that the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> was in the
                        process of making a reassessment of its policy in this area and he realized
                        we would want to have our reassessment completed before undertaking
                        bilateral talks.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGL1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Stone</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
