<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>44. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-05-10T15:54:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-05-10T16:25:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004010601"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Rural</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="receYZXmZSuptfeyg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">PL 480</term>
                    <term ref="recez5uVgqvmr6Nwm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006268"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Irrigation</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Development aid</term>
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="south-and-central-asia">South Asia</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-05-10T16:25:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-05-10T15:54:00-05:00" n="44"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                <head>44. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d44fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 625,
                        Country Files, Middle East, Pakistan, Vol. IV, 1 Mar 71–15 May 71. Secret;
                            <gloss target="#t_NODIS1">Nodis</gloss>. The meeting was held in the
                        Oval Office. The time given of the meeting is from the Presidentʼs Daily
                        Diary. (Ibid., White House Central Files) The time given on the memorandum
                        is 4:45–5:20 p.m. The conversation was tape-recorded, but the sound quality
                        of the tape is poor. (Ibid., White House Tapes, Recording of conversation
                        among President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_AMM1">M.M. Ahmad</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_HA1"
                            >Agha Hilaly</persName>, May 10, 1971, 4:54–5:25 p.m., Oval Office,
                        Conversation No. 496–14)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1971-05-10T16:54:00-04:00" to="1971-05-10T17:25:00-04:00">May 10,
                            1971, 4:54–5:25 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AMM1">M.M. Ahmad</persName>, Economic Advisor to the
                        President of Pakistan</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Agha Hilaly</persName>, Ambassador of
                        Pakistan</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Harold H. Saunders</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff</item>
                </list>
                <p>The President opened the conversation by expressing sympathy for all that
                    Pakistan had been through in recent days. He noted that President <persName
                        corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> is a good friend and he could understand
                    the anguish of the decisions which he had had to make.</p>
                <pb facs="0142" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> replied with President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1"
                        >Yahya</persName>ʼs appreciation for the stance that the President had
                        taken.<note n="2" xml:id="d44fn2">At this meeting,
                            <persName>Ahmad</persName> presented President <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> with the April 17 letter from
                        President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName>. (Telegram 83947 to
                        Islamabad, May 14; ibid., RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15–1 <gloss target="#t_US1"
                            >US</gloss>/<persName corresp="#p_NRM1">NIXON</persName>) For text of
                        the letter, See <ref target="#d29">Document 29</ref>.</note> He realized the
                    fact that the President had been surrounded by a “hostile press.” He also
                    understood the pressures that had built up in the Congress.</p>
                <p>The President smiled and acknowledged that there were a number of critics who
                    felt that the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> should become heavily involved
                    in telling Pakistan how to work out its political difficulties. He said that the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> is not going to become involved in that
                    way. It is wrong, he concluded, to assume that the <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss> should go around telling other countries how to arrange their
                    political affairs.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> then launched into a brief discussion of how
                    recent developments in East Pakistan had come about, what the situation is now
                    and how President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> plans to proceed.
                    He said that President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> wanted very
                    much to have President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> know what
                    his plans were before they were made public.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> said that President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1"
                        >Yahya</persName> had made every effort to negotiate a political arrangement
                    with East Pakistani leaders. He had made it clear from the start that he was
                    willing to grant virtual autonomy within the framework of “one country.” He had
                    told <persName corresp="#p_RSM1">Mujibur Rahman</persName> that he should not
                    come to a soldier—<persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName>—and ask him to
                    split the country, that if he wanted to do that he should try to do it through
                    the constituent assembly. President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName>
                    had granted the virtual autonomy described in the “six points” of the Awami
                    League, but it became apparent that <persName corresp="#p_RSM1">Mujib</persName>
                    was negotiating for independence and not just for autonomy.</p>
                <p>Now, President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> planned to create a
                    provincial assembly around the representatives elected last December. He did not
                    intend to hold fresh elections; he would consider the December elections valid.
                    He would be prepared to proclaim an interim constitution which would contain
                    almost all that had been asked for in the Awami Leagueʼs “six points.”</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> noted that the objectives of President <persName
                        corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> were first to restore law and order—a
                    process which has now almost been completed. His next objective was to restore
                    civil administration. Then it would be necessary for the Indians to cease
                    assisting insurgents so that the border areas might be quieted. Pakistan would
                    welcome anything the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> could do to influence the
                    Indians in that direction.</p>
                <p>If that kind of framework could be established, Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName>
                    continued, then it would be possible to begin the rural works programs <pb
                        facs="0143" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> again to put enough money into
                    peoplesʼ hands to buy food. The food problem is not one of supply, however,
                    since there is enough food for the moment in East Pakistan. Pakistan will need
                    more later in the year, but that is not the problem now. The problem is that the
                    communications system—the roads and railroads—had been disrupted.</p>
                <p>Speaking of the food situation, Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> said that Pakistan
                    is quite willing to accept contributions from the international relief
                    organizations and would welcome the support of the United Nations in collecting
                    contributions. President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName>, however,
                    wanted their participation to stop at that point. President <persName
                        corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> felt that since the army had been forced
                    to take firm measures in restoring law and order, it should now be involved in
                    the duty of distributing food. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1"
                        >Hilaly</persName> added that President <persName corresp="#p_YKA1"
                        >Yahya</persName> did not want all the voluntary agencies “flocking in” with
                    all of the unfavorable publicity and criticism that had followed the cyclone
                    disaster last fall.</p>
                <p>The President acknowledged the Ambassadorʼs point and then asked about the rural
                    works program. Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> explained that this was a program
                    that had been developed using <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> counterpart
                    funds. When the President looked puzzled, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHH1"
                        >Saunders</persName> stated that the proceeds from past <gloss
                        target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> 480 food sale programs had been devoted to a
                    program of rural works to enable the East Pakistani government to develop
                    irrigation, roads and other rural programs, using the currency that came from
                    the sale of the food. The President said that he wanted to be sure that
                    everything was done in this regard that was possible.</p>
                <p>The President then came back to the question of the critics who wanted the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> to have some policy other than supporting the
                    present government of Pakistan. He said the question he always asks himself is
                    what the alternative is. He implied that he did not see any alternative to
                    working with the present government to help it do the best it could with the
                    situation. Then he asked Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> and Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_HA1">Hilaly</persName> what they felt the alternative to the
                    present government was. They stated that, if the present government were to
                    fall, there would be chaos. In East Pakistan, for example, the army can not even
                    be pulled out without the expectation of large number of killings by Bengalis
                    directed at the non-Bengali population. Moreover, the economic problems of East
                    Pakistan—the high ratio of population to land—left East Pakistan with tremendous
                    problems which it was not prepared to attack by itself.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hilaly</persName> noted that it was
                    essential for the army to remain in the wings. Moreover, he felt that in a
                    united country, East and West balanced each other. The moderates in West
                    Pakistan would offset the extremists in the East and vice versa. He thought it
                    unlikely that the radicals in both West and East would come together and form a
                    majority.</p>
                <pb facs="0144" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/>
                <p>The President said that we wanted to stay out of the political negotiations and
                    to do what we could to help within the limits of our law. He noted that
                    attitudes in Congress had to be taken into account and could restrict our
                    ability to help. He also stated that he was not familiar with the intricacies of
                    all of the economic programs we have in Pakistan, with the implication that he
                    was not addressing any particular solution or proposal in making this statement.
                    But, he said, we would not do anything to complicate the situation for President
                        <persName corresp="#p_YKA1">Yahya</persName> or to embarrass him. He asked
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Saunders</persName> to be sure those who would
                    be talking to Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> understood his views.</p>
                <p>The President then asked about the ability of the World Bank to help. He
                    understood that the Bank itself did not have a great deal of money to devote to
                    Pakistan. He asked how helpful it could be. Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName>
                    explained that the Bank problem was partly the problem of other aid donors in
                    the World Bank consortium. In response to a question from the President, Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Saunders</persName> noted that other
                    governments— to varying degrees—are subject to pressures not to provide further
                    development aid until they judge there is a viable political framework.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d44fn3">In a May 9 memorandum to President <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, Acting Secretary of State <persName
                            corresp="#p_IJN1">Irwin</persName> noted that most members of the
                        Pakistan consortium had decided to delay or suspend new economic assistance
                        to Pakistan. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 <gloss target="#t_PAK1"
                        >PAK</gloss>)</note> The President asked who the principal members were and
                    was told that the British, Germans and Japanese were—along with the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss>—the leading members. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_HA1">Hilaly</persName> noted from his days as Ambassador in
                    London that <persName corresp="#p_DS2">Sir Alec Douglas-Home</persName>
                    understood the background in South Asia better than Prime Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_HE1">Heath</persName>. The President said he wanted to be sure
                    the Bank understood that we feel strongly that it and the other aid donors
                    should do what they could to be helpful. He said to Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SHH1">Saunders</persName> that he thought “we had done this
                    yesterday.” The President asked that a paper be given to him on this
                    subject.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> mentioned briefly the programs which he had been
                    working on with the World Bank for the rescheduling of debt and the need for
                    some support in the current situation, but he did not go into detail about the
                    specific programs he would be discussing. Nor did he present any specific
                    proposals to the President.</p>
                <p>The President then asked whom Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName> would be meeting
                    during his stay in Washington and was told that Mr. <persName>Ahmad</persName>
                    would see Mr. Schweitzer of the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>, Mr. Cargill
                    and perhaps Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRS1">McNamara</persName> of the World
                    Bank, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_HJA1">Hannah</persName>, Secretary Hardin. He
                    was told that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> had not
                    had a chance to sort out his schedule for the <pb facs="0145" n="116"
                        xml:id="pg_116"/> week since returning from the Middle East but that Mr.
                        <persName>Ahmad</persName> would certainly be seeing someone in the State
                    Department as well.<note n="4" xml:id="d44fn4">
                        <persName>Ahmad</persName> met with Secretary of State <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> on May 12, with Secretary of
                        Agriculture Hardin on May 13, and with <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>
                        Administrator <persName corresp="#p_HJA1">Hannah</persName> on May 14. These
                        conversations were summarized in telegrams 83022, May 12; 83948, May 14; and
                        85267, May 17; all to Islamabad. Telegrams 83022 and 83948 are ibid.;
                        telegram 85267 is ibid., SOC 10 <gloss target="#t_PAK1">PAK</gloss>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In parting, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA1">Hilaly</persName> noted that
                    former President Ayub of Pakistan had been operated on in open heart surgery
                    earlier in the day and the report was of a successful operation. The President
                    concluded, as he was seeing his guests out the door, that he wished that some of
                    the marvelous things that were done by modern surgery could be performed on
                    nations as well.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">
                            <hi rend="strong">H.S.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
