<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-02-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-02-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="138" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d138">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">441.11 W 892/18</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-02-04"><hi rend="italic">February 4,
                                1926</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The British Ambassador called today and left an <hi rend="italic">aide
                                memoire</hi> which is attached.<note n="6" xml:id="d138fn6"><hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> He explained that what he meant
                            was that we would first take up the inter-governmental claims. I
                            suggested to him that all claims ought to be taken up. He thought this
                            might be <pb facs="0314" n="218" xml:id="pg_218"/> embarrassing to the
                            Government to appoint commissioners to negotiate the settlement of all
                            claims but would be willing to do it first as to inter-departmental
                            claims.</p>
                        <p>It seems to me that we should insist that all claims be taken up by the
                            joint commission or representatives to examine them and, if possible, to
                            obtain an agreement to arbitrate any of those where the two
                            representatives do not agree.</p>
                        <p>I said that I did not know how many claims the Government of the United
                            States had against Great Britain or Great Britain against the United
                            States but that there were a large number of private claims by citizens
                            which necessarily the Government must present; that about many of these
                            claims there could be no question. The Ambassador answered in the
                            affirmative saying that some of the claims were for properties taken by
                            the prize courts and which had not been paid for and undoubtedly should
                            be. I told him that many of the claims filed were in the form of letters
                            without stating the amount or circumstances or details sufficient to
                            present; that it seemed to me the only possible way was for experienced
                            men to sit down and take them up one by one and see if some adjustment
                            could not be made.</p>
                        <p>The Department should make some reply to this <hi rend="italic">aide
                                memoire</hi>. I do not remember the exact terms of the reply in
                            relation to the governmental claims referred to.</p>
                        <p>I suggest that this would be an opportune time to remind the British
                            Ambassador that we have never had a reply to the various notes about the
                            Romano-Americana Oil Company in Rumania.<note n="7" xml:id="d138fn7">See
                                    <ref target="#pg_308">pp. 308</ref> ff.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>