<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Great Britain ( (Houghton) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1926v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1926-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1926-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="173"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">441.11 St 23/46</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Houghton</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-09-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 10, 1926</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received September 20 (?).]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1340</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to previous correspondence on the claim
                    of the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey for compensation for the destruction
                    of oil properties of its subsidiary in Rumania, the Romano-Americana, against
                    the British Government, I have the honor to enclose copy in triplicate of Sir
                    Austen Chamberlain’s reply, dated April 15, 1926, to my representations of
                    February 16, 1925, when I communicated to him a memorandum based on the
                    memorandum prepared by the then Secretary of State, Mr. Hughes,<note n="74"
                        xml:id="d173fn74">The reference is to the memorandum drafted by Mr. Charles
                        C. Hyde, Solicitor of the Department of State, <hi rend="italic"
                        >supra</hi>.</note> and transmitted by him to the then American Ambassador,
                    Mr. Kellogg, with a personal letter dated January 31, 1925. Greatly to the
                    Embassy’s regret Sir Austen’s reply had been mislaid in the Embassy and is only
                    now forwarded to the Department.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">F. A. Sterling</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Counselor of Embassy</hi>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Chamberlain</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Ambassador</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Houghton</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-04-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">15 April, 1926</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. C 4421/1310/37</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: In a memorandum communicated by
                        Your Excellency’s predecessor on February 16th last year, the United States
                        Government renewed the claim put forward on behalf of the <pb facs="0419"
                            n="323" xml:id="pg_323"/> Standard Oil Company of New Jersey in respect
                        of loss and damage done to the property in Roumania of the Romano-Americana
                        Company (a Roumanian corporation in which the Standard Oil Company is a
                        large share-holder) by belligerent operations during the war. The claim is
                        put forward against the Government of this country on the ground of the
                        destruction of the properties of the company caused by or directly resulting
                        from the acts of British authorities, and it is upon this ground maintained
                        that the Government of His Britannic Majesty are burdened with an obligation
                        under international law to make full compensation. It is stated in the
                        earlier part of the memorandum that the claim is framed upon a legal basis
                        and it is there made clear that the Standard Oil Company does not rest its
                        claim upon a moral liability on the part of the Allied Governments to make
                        compensation for the war losses of which the oil properties in Roumania were
                        the victims. At the close of the memorandum a reference of the dispute to
                        arbitration is proposed.</p>
                    <p>2. As the claim is put forward on a strictly legal basis, it has been
                        necessary for His Majesty’s Government to consider the claim in all its
                        bearings upon that basis and to arrive at their conclusions under the advice
                        of the highest legal authorities of the country. It is to this cause that
                        the delay in returning an answer to the memorandum of February 16th 1925 is
                        due.</p>
                    <p>3. His Majesty’s Government do not admit that any international
                        responsibility for the destruction of this property rests upon or can be
                        undertaken by this country. The memorandum based the claim on the
                        destruction of property by a belligerent and maintained that the belligerent
                        is under an obligation, imposed by the law of nations, to make reparation.
                        His Majesty’s Government agree that the destruction was an act of war. It
                        arose out of acts of war committed in Roumania when Roumania was an active
                        belligerent. The question of the nationality of the individuals who carried
                        out the acts complained of is immaterial. The acts were carried out on
                        Roumanian soil by individuals acting on behalf of and in co-operation with
                        the military authorities of the country, and by the authority of the
                        Roumanian Government. That Government approved of the steps which were taken
                        and if and so far as there was need for them to do so they have ratified the
                        acts in question in the most unequivocal manner. It follows, ‘therefore,
                        that if the acts complained of give rise to any claim for compensation on
                        the part of those whose property was injured or destroyed, the party
                        responsible is the Roumanian Government and it is against that Government
                        that the claim must be brought.</p>
                    <p>4. There can be no doubt that this is also the view of the Roumanian
                        Government. Roumania has openly proclaimed her responsibility <pb
                            facs="0420" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/> in this matter. In this connection
                        I venture to quote an extract from a speech of the Roumanian Minister of
                        Finance before the Chamber of Deputies, delivered on February 11th,
                        1925.</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="center">[Translation]</p>
                        <p>“From the very beginning we laid down the rule that we did the
                            destruction in our territory and that we make compensation. We pledged
                            ourselves to those who suffered damages and hence, the sums that become
                            due under that head you must deliver to us.</p>
                        <p>“We cannot admit that those compensations be made directly as some States
                            tried to do with their people.</p>
                        <p>“We have taken a pledge with the whole petroleum industry, and what is
                            due to it must be given to us and it will be distributed by us to the
                            sufferers”.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p rend="flushleft">and a further extract from an official Roumanian Government
                        memorandum published in the Official Press of September 24th, 1925:— <quote
                            rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="center">[Translation]</p>
                            <p>“As a result of the pressure exerted and steps taken by the Allied
                                Powers in November 1916, the Roumanian Government ordered the
                                destruction of all plants for the extraction, transformation and
                                transportation of petroleum, and also the destruction by fire of all
                                the stores of crude oil and derivatives found in the yards,
                                refineries and warehouses throughout the Muntenia and Dobrudja
                                territory.</p>
                            <p>“The sole purpose of the destruction was to deprive the enemy of one
                                of its best implements of war. It turns out that it was fully
                                accomplished”.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Your Excellency will note from these declarations that not
                        only did the Roumanian Government declare that the work of destruction was
                        undertaken by the orders of the Roumanian Government, but also that Roumania
                        cannot admit the right of Great Britain or France or any other Power to
                        negotiate directly with respect to compensation with the persons or
                        companies whose properties were injured, and that they would regard any such
                        action as a violation of Roumania’s sovereign rights.</p>
                    <p>5. As such responsibility rests solely with Roumania, it is unnecessary for
                        me to set out at length the other considerations upon which His Majesty’s
                        Government would be in a position to rely if a legal claim could properly be
                        formulated against them. Nevertheless, I would invite Your Excellency’s
                        attention to a brief enumeration of some of the considerations of this
                        character, though in so doing it must not be assumed that I waive any other
                        objections which His Majesty’s Government would be in a position to put
                        forward.</p>
                    <p>6. In the first place, the destruction of this property, being, as your
                        memorandum admits, an act of war, gives rise to no legal right to
                        compensation. The principle that “war losses” do not give rise to a legal
                        right to compensation is not limited to war losses in the sense <pb
                            facs="0421" n="325" xml:id="pg_325"/> of loss or damage inflicted by the
                        enemy, but covers also loss and damage which the commander in the field is
                        himself obliged to inflict upon the owners of property in the area under his
                        authority: see the decision of the Tribunal in the “Hardman” case in the
                        arbitration between the British and United States Governments (<hi
                            rend="italic">American Journal of International Law</hi>, Vol. 7, p.
                        879). Secondly, His Majesty’s Government would, if necessary, maintain that
                        the claim, being in respect of damage to the property of a company
                        incorporated in and still carrying on business in Roumania, must be regarded
                        as a claim on behalf of a company which is a Roumanian national. The
                        ownership of the shares, even if it extended to the totality of the shares,
                        by an American corporation would not in the opinion of this Government
                        justify the diplomatic protection of the Roumanian company by the Government
                        of the United States on the footing that it was an American national.</p>
                    <p>7. The view of His Majesty’s Government being that it is the Roumanian
                        Government alone which can deal with a claim for compensation for the
                        destruction of the property of the Romano-Americana Company, I would repeat
                        what I think is already known to your government that the British, French
                        and Russian Governments when inviting the Roumanian authorities to destroy
                        the oil properties in Roumania to prevent them from falling into the hands
                        of the enemy, agreed to compensate that Government for any loss which the
                        latter might sustain as the result of their destruction and they have always
                        been and still are willing to reduce their claims in respect of sums due to
                        them by the Roumanian Government on this account. So far as His Majesty’s
                        Government are concerned the above arrangement has been carried out by a
                        reduction of the Roumanian debt to this country. I would add, however, that
                        the question of compensation is one to be arranged between the Roumanian
                        Government and the various owners of the oil properties concerned, and the
                        conclusion of any agreement between the Roumanian and the Allied Governments
                        on the question cannot, in my view, be taken to prejudice the right of the
                        Roumanian Government to maintain that if compensation is claimed on a
                        strictly legal basis, the belligerent acts of destruction were not such as
                        to give rise to any claims for compensation as of right.</p>
                    <p>8. If for one moment I may depart from the strictly legal considerations
                        applicable to the case, I would ask you also to reflect how impossible it is
                        for His Majesty’s Government to admit that a claim can rightly be brought
                        against them alone in respect of the destruction of these oil properties in
                        Roumania, when their sole interest in the case is the undertaking which they
                        gave jointly with France and Russia, and which is certainly, so far as
                        France is concerned, a subsisting undertaking, to reimburse to the Roumanian
                        Government any compensation which might be given to the owners of the oil
                        properties.</p>
                    <pb facs="0422" n="326" xml:id="pg_326"/>
                    <p>9. In view of the preceding considerations, I trust that Your Excellency will
                        agree with me that the claim of the Standard Oil Company is not one which
                        lends itself to arbitration between the British and United States
                        Governments.</p>
                    <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Austen Chamberlain</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
