<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Japanese Chargé ( (Yoshida))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1926v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d278</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">278</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1924-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1924-10-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOAfZ9FRSJKK76a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Income tax</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1924-10-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1924-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="278"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d278">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.512394Shipping/11</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Japanese Chargé</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Yoshida</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1924-10-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 14, 1924</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to your notes No. 73 of
                    August 4, and No. 81 of September 13, 1924,<note n="6" xml:id="d278fn6">Latter
                        not printed.</note> regarding the establishment of reciprocity between the
                    United States and Japan concerning the exemption from income tax of earnings
                    derived from the operation of merchant vessels documented under the laws of the
                    respective countries. You enclosed with your note of September 13 a translation
                    of a law No. 6 promulgated by your Government on July 17, 1924, regarding the
                    exemption from income tax of earnings derived from the operation of vessels of
                    foreign registry and requested that it be substituted for the translation quoted
                    in your note of August 4. In the last mentioned note you inquired whether the
                    law satisfies the provisions of Section 213 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) (8) of
                    the United States Revenue Act of 1924.</p>
                <p>The law of July 17, 1924, as transmitted with your note of September 13, reads as
                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“A” Foreigners or foreign juridical persons who have no domicile in Japan
                            shall be exempted from income tax in respect of the income derived from
                            vessels of foreign nationality, except in cases where a country whose
                            nationality is possessed by the said vessels does not grant similar
                            exemption in regard to the income of Japanese vessels.</p>
                        <pb facs="0550" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">“Annex.</p>
                        <p>“The present law shall come into operation on the day of its
                            promulgation, (July 17, 1924.)”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The Treasury Department, to which copies of your notes were referred for
                    consideration, calls attention to a statement in its letter of June 18,
                        1924,<note n="7" xml:id="d278fn7">Not printed.</note> which was quoted in my
                    note of June 26, 1924, to the Japanese Ambassador<note n="8" xml:id="d278fn8">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_451">p. 451</ref>.</note> in
                    reply to the inquiries contained in his note of May 27, 1924,<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d278fn9">Not printed.</note> regarding the establishment of
                    reciprocity between the United States and Japan concerning income derived from
                    the operation of merchant vessels. This statement, which appears at the end of
                    the first paragraph of page 4 of the note of June 26, reads as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“It is deemed advisable to point out that the exemption granted by the
                            Japanese law to the United States corporations must be absolute, that
                            is, the exemption must apply to all United States corporations even
                            though such corporations have a branch office, a place of business or an
                            agent in Japan.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The Treasury Department observes that under the term “Foreigners or foreign
                    juridical persons who have no domicile in Japan”, as used in the law promulgated
                    by the Japanese Government, the exemption of a citizen of the United States
                    non-resident in Japan or of a United States corporation upon income derived from
                    the operation of ships documented under the laws of the United States might be
                    destroyed by the citizen or corporation having an office or place of business or
                    an agent in Japan; that if such should be the case, it would follow that the
                    Japanese law of July 17, 1924, does not satisfy the equivalent exemption
                    provision of Section 213 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) (8) of the Revenue Act of
                    1924.</p>
                <p>In view of the doubt as to the construction which may properly be placed on the
                    provisions of the law, the Treasury Department desires a statement from the
                    Japanese Government concerning the interpretation which that Government places
                    upon the provisions in question. It also desires to be furnished with a
                    statement from the Japanese Government <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">“whether a citizen of the United States, a non-resident
                            in Japan, or a corporation organized in the United States, under the
                            Japanese law promulgated on July 17, 1924, would be subject to Japanese
                            taxes upon so much of their income as consists exclusively of earnings
                            derived from the operation of a ship or ships documented under the laws
                            of the United States if such citizen or corporation were engaged in
                            business in Japan or had an office, place of business or an agent in
                            Japan.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>If you will be good enough to furnish me with a statement from your Government on
                    these points, I shall be glad to transmit it to the <pb facs="0551" n="455"
                        xml:id="pg_455"/> Treasury Department for the purpose of determining whether
                    the reciprocal exemption provided for in Section 213 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                    (8) of the Revenue Act has been established.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph C. Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
