<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-10-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-10-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="356" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d356">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">882.51/1893: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">National City Bank of New
                                    York</gloss> to the Financial Adviser of Liberia</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">De la Rue</hi></persName>)<note n="58" xml:id="d356fn58">Received by the Department as an enclosure to a
                                letter dated Oct. 29, 1926, from Guy Cary of Shearman &amp;
                                Sterling.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-10-28"><hi rend="italic">October 28,
                                1926</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Following from Finance Corporation of America: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Replying to your cable 26th through National City Bank, we will
                                    accept wish of the Government of Liberia regarding assignment of
                                    revenues and accordingly you are authorized to strike out lines
                                    13 and 14, article 7, page 7, of Loan Agreement signed by
                                        us,<note n="59" xml:id="d356fn59">The words “On all other
                                        revenues or moneys received for the account of the
                                        Government from any source whatever.”</note> and substitute
                                    the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>‘On all the revenues receivable on and after said date
                                            from headmoneys and</p>
                                        <p>‘The Government further agrees that in the event that the
                                            above revenues should prove insufficient for the service
                                            of the loan, the Government shall first allocate from
                                            its other revenues such sums as shall be sufficient to
                                            make up the deficiency.’</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>And to strike out the last 5 lines, page 12 and the first 9
                                    lines, page 13,<note n="60" xml:id="d356fn60">In art. X from the
                                        words “If the Government shall desire to issue the
                                        additional $2,500,000 face amount of Bonds …” through the
                                        end of that article.</note> and substitute the following:
                                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>‘It is understood by the parties hereto that the
                                            Government may offer for sale in such amounts as it may
                                            decide the bonds covering the remaining $2,500,000
                                            authorized under this agreement when the total annual
                                            amount of the assigned custom duties and headmoneys have
                                            exceeded the sum of $800,000 for 2 consecutive years.
                                            Such additional bonds shall only be sold in the American
                                            financial market, and to or through the Finance
                                            Corporation of America, or other American financial
                                            concerns, bank or banks doing business in the United
                                            States, and the Finance Corporation of America shall be
                                            given the first opportunity to purchase such bonds.’</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p rend="right">Finance Corporation of America”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer><hi rend="smallcaps">National City Bank of New York</hi></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>