<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-11-10T15:44:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-11-10T15:44:00-05:00" n="359" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d359">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">382.1121 Dr. Shattuck and Cheek:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Liberia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Clark</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Monrovia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-11-10T20:00:00-00:44"><hi rend="italic">November 10,
                                        1926—8 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received November 11—10:15
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>42. … The planting agreements have now passed both Houses in the form
                            agreed upon. As regards the loan agreement the President has formulated
                            the remaining points of difference which De la Rue is now transmitting.
                            Articles 15 and 25 of the last-named appear to be the only ones at all
                            difficult of adjustment. I am convinced that the Finance Corporation can
                            accept no material weakening of the first without impairing Firestone’s
                            security while the suggested amendment of the arbitration clause may not
                            be acceptable to the Department.</p>
                        <p>The Department is not a party to the loan agreement but in view of
                            present conditions considered as a whole, perhaps the Department could
                            reexpress its friendly interest in a manner peculiarly effective.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Clark</hi></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0657" n="561" xml:id="pg_561"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">An Act Passed by the Liberian Legislature
                                    November 10, 1926, Approving the Agreement Between the
                                    Government of Liberia and the Firestone Plantations
                                    Company</hi><note n="61" xml:id="d359fn61">Printed from <hi rend="italic">Acts Passed by the Legislature of the Republic
                                        of Liberia During the Session 1926</hi> (Monrovia,
                                    Government Printing Office, 1926), ch. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 3.</note></head>
                            <p>It is enacted by the Senate and House of Representatives of the
                                Republic of Liberia in Legislature assembled:—</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Section</hi> 1. That from and after the passage
                                of this Act the Agreement between the Government of Liberia and the
                                Firestone Plantations Company hereinunder recited, be and the same
                                is hereby approved. <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum of Agreement</hi> made and
                                        entered into at the City of Monrovia this 2nd day of October
                                        in the year of our Lord Nineteen Hundred and Twenty-six by
                                        and between <hi rend="smallcaps">The Government of the
                                            Republic of Liberia</hi> hereinafter styled the
                                        Government and <hi rend="smallcaps">Firestone Plantations
                                            Company</hi>, a Corporation organized and existing under
                                        and by virtue of the laws of the State of Delaware, with
                                        principal office in the City of Akron, State of Ohio, United
                                        States of America, hereinafter styled the Lessee <hi rend="smallcaps">Witnesseth</hi>:—</p>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi></p>
                                    <p>That the Government hath agreed and by these presents doth
                                        agree to grant, demise and to farmlet unto the Lessee for
                                        the period of Ninety-nine years from this date an area of
                                        land within the boundaries of the Republic of Liberia of one
                                        million acres or any lesser area that may be selected by the
                                        Lessee from time to time within said period of Ninety-nine
                                        years; such land to be suitable for the production of rubber
                                        or other agricultural products.</p>
                                    <p>But should the Lessee fail <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>To notify the Government of its acceptance of the
                                                conditions herein contained and stipulated within
                                                six months after the execution of this Agreement by
                                                the Government of Liberia;</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Or within one year thereafter to commence the
                                                selection of lands hereunder;</item>
                                        </list></p>
                                    <p>Then in such case the obligation of the Government under this
                                        Agreement shall be discharged and ended.</p>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi></p>
                                    <p>The Government further agrees the Lessee shall during the
                                        life of this Agreement have and enjoy the following
                                        additional rights and exemptions: <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>All products of Lessee’s plantations and all
                                                machinery, tools, supplies and buildings
                                                established, constructed or placed upon the leased
                                                land or elsewhere for the operation and development
                                                of the Lessee’s land holdings and all leasehold
                                                interests, improvements and other property,
                                                franchises rights and income shall be free of and
                                                exempt from any internal revenue or other tax,
                                                charge, or impost except <pb facs="0658" n="562" xml:id="pg_562"/> the revenue tax provided for in
                                                Article III, Paragraph (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>),
                                                provided, however that the exemption herein granted
                                                shall not affect the liability of the Lessee for the
                                                payment of the Emergency Relief Fund nor for the
                                                payment of the tax leviable on vehicles.</item>
                                            <label/>
                                            <item>It is understood and agreed that this exemption
                                                shall not apply to Lessee’s employees, labourers or
                                                servants.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>All machinery, tools and supplies of all kinds
                                                purchased and imported by Lessee for the operation
                                                and development of the lands held by Lessee under
                                                this Agreement and for the welfare of the employees
                                                of Lessee’s enterprise shall be exempt from all
                                                customs dues or other import duties. But such import
                                                duties, if any, as are now required by the
                                                “Agreement for Refunding Loan, 1912”, or any
                                                modification thereof, shall be paid by the Lessee
                                                until such Agreement shall be so modified as to
                                                reduce or abrogate such duties required on such
                                                imports by Lessee; in which event, Lessee shall be
                                                required to pay only such import duties as are
                                                demanded by such Agreement as modified. It is
                                                understood and agreed that the word “welfare” used
                                                in this paragraph shall connote only hospital
                                                supplies and games and that any articles which may
                                                be used by the Lessee in trade or barter or in
                                                payment for labour shall not be deemed “supplies”
                                                within the meaning of this section.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Lessee shall have the exclusive right and
                                                privilege upon the lands which shall be selected
                                                under this Agreement to construct highways, railways
                                                and waterways for the efficient operation and
                                                development of the properties. It is agreed that all
                                                trails across such lands used immemorially by the
                                                population shall be subject and open to free use by
                                                the public.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Lessee shall have the right to construct and
                                                establish at its own expenses lines of communication
                                                such as highways, roadways, waterways and railways
                                                outside the lands selected under this Agreement.
                                                Such routes may be so located by the Lessee as to
                                                best serve the purpose of efficient operation of its
                                                plantations and enterprises but the Lessee agrees to
                                                consult the Government in the matter of such
                                                location. All highways and roadways in this
                                                paragraph mentioned shall upon completion become
                                                public property. But the Government in any event
                                                shall not be required to refund to the Lessee any
                                                sums of money expended by it in the construction and
                                                maintenance of such highways, roadways, waterways or
                                                railways.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The Lessee shall have the right to construct and
                                                establish lines of communication for the purpose of
                                                more efficiently operating its plantations and
                                                enterprises such as telegraph lines, telephone lines
                                                and wireless stations outside of the confines of the
                                                lands selected under this Agreement, subject to the
                                                provisions of paragraph (<hi rend="italic">h</hi>),
                                                Article IV of this Agreement; and to the extent
                                                necessary for such purpose may use, without the
                                                payment of rent for such land, any Government lands
                                                not already devoted to some other use. The
                                                Government in case of war or other emergency shall
                                                have the right to use such lines of
                                                communication.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The Lessee shall have the right to cut and use all
                                                timber upon the lands covered by this Agreement but
                                                if it shall engage in the sale of lumber to be
                                                removed from such lands for export it shall pay the
                                                Government royalty of two (2) cents per cubic foot
                                                for the lumber so sold, in gold coin of the United
                                                States of the present standard of weight and
                                                fineness.</item>
                                            <pb facs="0659" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The Lessee shall have the right to engage in any
                                                operations other than agricultural upon the lands
                                                held under this Agreement and to utilize any product
                                                or materials of or upon said lands; but any mining
                                                or other similar operations shall be subject to the
                                                laws of the Republic of Liberia unless the parties
                                                hereto shall agree upon special terms
                                                therefor.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The Government warrants to the Lessee the title to
                                                all lands selected by it upon which the Government
                                                shall accept the rental or compensation as herein
                                                provided and will defend and protect such title for
                                                the benefit of the Lessee.</item>
                                        </list></p>
                                    <p>The Government further agrees that it will encourage, support
                                        and assist the efforts of the Lessee to secure and maintain
                                        an adequate labour supply.</p>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi></p>
                                    <p>The Lessee in consideration of the Agreements herein by the
                                        Government hath agreed and by these presents doth agree as
                                        follows: <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>To notify the Government within a period of six
                                                (6) months after the execution of this Agreement by
                                                the Government of Liberia of its acceptance or
                                                rejection of the conditions and stipulations of this
                                                Agreement.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Beginning one year after the acceptance by the
                                                Lessee of this Agreement it shall select from year
                                                to year land suitable for the production of rubber
                                                and other agricultural products in such areas or
                                                quantities within the maximum limit of one million
                                                acres of land as may be convenient to it and in
                                                accordance with the economical and progressive
                                                development of its holding and said Lessee shall
                                                upon the selection or location of any tract or
                                                tracts of land notify the Government of such
                                                selection and the boundaries thereof. But the Lessee
                                                shall within five years of the final execution of
                                                this Agreement select and begin the payment of rent
                                                upon a total of not less than twenty thousand
                                                acres.</item>
                                            <label/>
                                            <item>Upon written notice by the Lessee to the
                                                Government of Liberia of Lessee’s intention to make
                                                a selection of land hereunder within a named
                                                territory Lessee shall have six (6) months
                                                thereafter to select land within such territory and
                                                upon the filing by Lessee with the Government within
                                                such six (6) months or written notice of the
                                                selection of land within such designated territory
                                                the title of such selected land shall vest in Lessee
                                                for the purpose named in this Agreement.</item>
                                            <label/>
                                            <item>It is not intended hereby to deny Lessee the right
                                                to make selection of lands hereunder without such
                                                previous notification of intention to select within
                                                six (6) months; but if such last named notification
                                                is filed the same shall have the effect of
                                                preventing others from acquiring title within such
                                                territory during such six (6) months.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>As and when the Lessee takes possession of lands
                                                selected by it under this Agreement Lessee shall pay
                                                to the Government rental at the rate of six (6)
                                                cents per acre yearly and every year in advance in
                                                gold coin of the United States of the present
                                                standard of weight and fineness. Such payments shall
                                                be made to the Secretary of the Treasury of Liberia
                                                or to such other officer as may be by law provided,
                                                it being understood and agreed that the rent herein
                                                provided to be paid by the Lessee shall be due to be
                                                paid by it to the Government upon all areas of land
                                                selected by it as and when such areas are
                                                selected.</item>
                                            <pb facs="0660" n="564" xml:id="pg_564"/>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Six (6) years after the acceptance by the Lessee
                                                of this Agreement and annually thereafter, the
                                                Lessee shall pay to the Government a revenue tax
                                                equivalent to one per centum of the value of all
                                                rubber and other commercial products of its
                                                plantation shipped from Lessee’s plantations
                                                calculated on the price of such products prevailing
                                                in New York market at the time of the arrival of the
                                                shipment in New York.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Any taxes which may become payable by virtue of
                                                the laws of the Republic by any person or persons
                                                carried on the payroll of the Lessee, if the Lessee
                                                so desires, shall be collected as follows:—The
                                                Lessee may come to an arrangement with the Treasury
                                                Department of the Republic of Liberia which shall
                                                regulate the method of collection and payment of
                                                such taxes. But the Lessee shall in no event be held
                                                to collect in any year the tax for a greater number
                                                of employees than the average employed during the
                                                year.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Should the rent reserved on any piece or parcel of
                                                ground selected by the Lessee be behind or unpaid on
                                                any day of payment whereon the same ought to be paid
                                                as herein provided, or if default should be made in
                                                any of the covenants hereinbefore contained on the
                                                part of Lessee to be paid, kept and performed, and
                                                if such default in the payment of rent or otherwise
                                                shall continue after six months written notice of
                                                the existence of such default served by the
                                                Government upon the Lessee, then it shall be lawful
                                                for the Government to cancel this lease as to that
                                                piece or parcel of ground, the rent for which is in
                                                default or in respect of which piece or parcel any
                                                other default exists as specified in such notice,
                                                and to re-enter into and upon the said demised
                                                premises and to again repossess and enjoy the same.
                                                But if the Lessee shall, within said period of six
                                                (6) months after written notice as aforesaid, make
                                                good the default complained of in said notice, no
                                                right of cancellation shall thereafter exist because
                                                of such default. The notice required by this
                                                paragraph to be served on the Lessee shall be
                                                delivered to the representative of the Lessee in the
                                                Republic of Liberia and a duplicate thereof shall be
                                                simultanously sent by registered mail to the
                                                President of the Lessee at its head office in the
                                                City of Akron, State of Ohio, United States of
                                                America. The Lessee shall promptly notify the
                                                Government of any change in the location of its head
                                                office and thereafter any such notice shall be
                                                addressed accordingly.</item>
                                        </list></p>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi></p>
                                    <p>It is further agreed between the parties hereto as follows:— <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The Lessee will not import unskilled foreign
                                                labour for the carrying out of any operations or
                                                development undertaken by virtue of this or any
                                                other grant except in the event the local labour
                                                supply should prove inadequate to the lessee’s
                                                needs. In the event that the local labour supply
                                                should prove inadequate as aforesaid Lessee
                                                undertakes to import only such foreign unskilled
                                                labour as shall be acceptable to the Government of
                                                Liberia. It is understood and agreed that Lessee
                                                shall not have in its employ in Liberia more than
                                                1500 white employees at any one time.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Should the operations of the Lessee under this
                                                Agreement cease for a period of three consecutive
                                                years then all and singular <pb facs="0661" n="565" xml:id="pg_565"/> of the rights of the Lessee
                                                hereunder shall become extinguished and void and
                                                this Agreement shall become of no effect but such
                                                cancellation of this Agreement shall not affect any
                                                rights granted by the Government to the Lessee under
                                                any other Agreement.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The rights by this Agreement granted to the Lessee
                                                shall not be sold, transferred or otherwise assigned
                                                by the Lessee to any person, firm, group or trust
                                                without the written consent thereto of the Liberian
                                                Government previously had and obtained.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The Government reserves the right to construct
                                                roads, highways, railroads, telegraph and telephone
                                                lines and other lines of communication through any
                                                and all plantations owned and operated by Lessee;
                                                but the Government shall pay to Lessee all damage
                                                which will be caused to Lessee’s property by the
                                                construction and operation of such roads or other
                                                lines of communication; such damage to be
                                                ascertained in accordance with the General law of
                                                the Republic of Liberia.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The Lessee shall have the right to develop for its
                                                own use such natural water power and hydroelectric
                                                power as may be capable of development upon any of
                                                the tracts of land selected by the Lessee under this
                                                Agreement and Lessee shall have the right to
                                                construct and maintain power lines over any
                                                Government lands in order to convey power so
                                                developed from one tract of land selected by Lessee
                                                to any other tract.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Tribal reserves of lands set aside for the
                                                communal use of any tribe within the Republic of
                                                Liberia are excluded from the operation of this
                                                Agreement. Should any question arise as to the
                                                limits and extent of such reserves such question
                                                shall be finally determined by the Secretary of
                                                Interior of Liberia on a reference by the
                                                Lessee.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Lines of communication such as telegraph,
                                                telephone lines, railroads and canals constructed
                                                and established by Lessee outside the confines of
                                                the Lessee’s tracts selected hereunder shall during
                                                the life of this Agreement be exempted from all
                                                taxation so long as they be used only for the
                                                purposes of the operations of Lessee upon lands held
                                                under this Agreement. In the event that such lines
                                                of communication shall be used by Lessee for general
                                                commercial purposes to serve others for hire then
                                                while so used they shall be subject to taxation
                                                under the general laws of Liberia.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>It is further agreed that at the expiration of the
                                                term of this lease hereinabove provided or of any
                                                extension thereof or: upon the cancellation of this
                                                Agreement at any earlier time such buildings and
                                                improvements erected by the Lessee upon the land
                                                selected hereunder as shall not have been removed
                                                before the expiration or cancellation of the lease
                                                shall become the property of the Government of
                                                Liberia without charge or condition.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">i</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>It is further agreed that if hereafter the
                                                Government shall grant to any other person, firm or
                                                corporation any rights in connection with the
                                                production of rubber in Liberia upon more favourable
                                                terms and conditions in any respect than those
                                                granted in this Agreement such more favourable terms
                                                and conditions shall inure to the benefit of the
                                                Lessee herein the same as if such more favourable
                                                terms and conditions were incorporated
                                                herein.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">j</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>It is further agreed that the Lessee shall use its
                                                best efforts to secure either from the Government of
                                                the United States or with <pb facs="0662" n="566" xml:id="pg_566"/> the approval of the Secretary of
                                                State of the United States from some other person or
                                                persons a loan of not less than five million dollars
                                                to establish a credit for public developments in the
                                                Republic of Liberia to the end that the credit may
                                                be a revolving credit set up through reserves so as
                                                to meet the future requirement of funds for such
                                                developments. Such loan shall be upon terms and
                                                conditions to be negotiated by a Commission
                                                appointed by the President of Liberia who shall
                                                proceed promptly to the United States for this
                                                purpose. It is understood that such terms and
                                                conditions as may be agreed upon shall be subject to
                                                the approval of the Legislature of the Republic of
                                                Liberia.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">k</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Wherever in this Agreement the Government grants
                                                to the Lessee the right to build and operate a
                                                railroad or to use the highways and waterways, it is
                                                understood that the Lessee is not seeking and is not
                                                granted public utility or common carrier privileges
                                                and that the same are not intended to be conveyed to
                                                it.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">l</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Wherever in said Agreements the Lessee is granted
                                                the right to construct and maintain telephone or
                                                telegraph lines or wireless stations it is
                                                understood that the rights intended to be conveyed
                                                permit the establishment of such lines of means of
                                                communication for the private use of the Lessee in
                                                the operation of its business and that the Lessee
                                                does not seek and is not granted the right to
                                                establish and maintain any public services.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">m</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>During the life of this Agreement the Lessee shall
                                                at all times have access to the port and harbour
                                                facilities at Monrovia, or in any other district of
                                                the Republic where it may be carrying on operations,
                                                upon not less favourable terms than is accorded
                                                others under existing treaties and the laws of the
                                                Republic of Liberia. It shall be privileged to lease
                                                available lands in all ports of entry from the
                                                Government upon favourable terms.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">n</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>All or any questions in dispute arising out of
                                                this Agreement between the Government and the Lessee
                                                which cannot be harmonized or adjusted by the Lessee
                                                and the Government shall be referred to the Liberian
                                                Supreme Court or any one of the Justices thereof for
                                                arbitration on application of either party; and said
                                                Court shall make appointment of three arbitrators
                                                (one of whom shall be nominated for such purpose to
                                                said Court by the President of Liberia, and one of
                                                whom shall be nominated for such purpose to said
                                                Court by the representative of the Lessee in charge
                                                of Lessee’s affairs in the Republic of Liberia, the
                                                third arbitrator being the Court’s selection without
                                                nomination) to hear and determine such dispute
                                                within five days after application being filed, upon
                                                first being satisfied of the service of notice of
                                                such application at least five days previous to the
                                                filing of the application by (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), by delivery of a copy of the application
                                                to the Attorney General of Liberia, or in his
                                                absence, to the officer in charge of his office when
                                                said application is made by the Lessee, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), by delivery of a copy of
                                                the application to the representative of the Lessee
                                                in charge of Lessee’s affairs in the Republic of
                                                Liberia and by mailing a duplicate thereof on the
                                                same date by registered mail to the President of the
                                                Lessee at its head office in the City of Akron,
                                                State of Ohio, United States of America, when said
                                                application is made by the Government.</item>
                                        </list></p>
                                    <pb facs="0663" n="567" xml:id="pg_567"/>
                                    <p>That the arbitrators so appointed as aforesaid shall render
                                        their decision of the question or questions in dispute in
                                        writing and file same with the Clerk of the Supreme Court,
                                        together with copy of testimony taken and statement of
                                        proceedings had within fifteen days after their appointment
                                        as aforesaid, unless an application for further arbitration,
                                        as hereinafter provided, be made by either party within a
                                        period of four months after said decision is given, said
                                        decision shall be a definitive settlement of the question or
                                        questions in dispute and shall be binding upon both parties,
                                        their agents or assigns, and the Government of Liberia
                                        agrees to make said decision operative. Should however,
                                        either party feel aggrieved at the decision of the
                                        arbitrators then the Government agrees to arrange with the
                                        United States Department of State for a further arbitration
                                        of the question or questions submitted by either or both
                                        parties; provided, however, that in the case of such further
                                        arbitration each party shall bear its own respective costs;
                                        and provided further that the procedure for such further
                                        arbitration shall be as follows:</p>
                                    <p>Written notice of desire for further arbitration shall be
                                        given by either party to the other within four months after
                                        the written decision of the arbitrators in the first
                                        instance has been filed with the Clerk of the Supreme Court;
                                        thereupon both parties shall prepare and file with the Clerk
                                        of the Supreme Court within sixty days after service of the
                                        notice written statements of the questions in disputes, and
                                        these statements together with a copy of the testimony and
                                        proceedings of the arbitrators together with a copy of their
                                        decision, shall be certified by the Clerk of the Supreme
                                        Court and delivered within five days after receipt of said
                                        papers in his office to the Secretary of State of Liberia
                                        who will thereupon promptly arrange with the United States
                                        Department of State for further arbitration of the questions
                                        in dispute, the decision of which arbitration shall be final
                                        and binding upon both parties to this Agreement.</p>
                                    <p>It is understood and agreed that the final decision shall
                                        become effective thirty days after such final decision has
                                        been rendered and shall not be retroactive. It is also
                                        understood and agreed that during the period of arbitration,
                                        the Lessee shall be permitted by the Government to carry on
                                        without interference, all operations under this Agreement,
                                        including the operations involved in the subject matter of
                                        dispute, which the Lessee had undertaken, and, being
                                        undertaken, had not been objected to by the Government prior
                                        to the dispute arising. It is understood, however, that the
                                        fact there was no objection on the part of the Government
                                        shall not prejudice its rights in the subject matter of
                                        dispute.</p>
                                    <p>It is hereby expressly understood and agreed that the
                                        arbitration procedure provided for herein does not apply to
                                        civil or criminal proceedings to be brought by or against
                                        employees of Lessee in Liberia.</p>
                                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">In Witness Whereof</hi> the parties
                                        hereto have hereunto set their hands and seals the day and
                                        year first above written.</p>
                                    <table cols="3" rend="width: 95%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="3">
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>Witness:</cell>
                                            <cell/>
                                            <cell>For the Government of Liberia<lb/>. . . . . .
                                                .<lb/>Secretary of State.</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell>Attest:</cell>
                                            <cell/>
                                            <cell>Firestone Plantations Company<lb/>By . . . . . .
                                                .</cell>
                                        </row>
                                        <row>
                                            <cell/>
                                            <cell>Secretary.</cell>
                                            <cell>President.</cell>
                                        </row>
                                    </table>
                                </quote></p>
                            <pb facs="0664" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Section</hi> 2. This Act shall take effect
                                immediately and be published in hand bills.</p>
                            <p>Any law to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
                            <closer><dateline rendition="#left">Approved <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-11-18">November 18,
                                1926</date>.</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>