<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Mexico ( (Sheffield) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1926v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1926-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1926-07-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039557"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Drilling</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-07-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="397"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d397">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.6363/1908</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sheffield</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-07-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 23, 1926</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received July 30.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2568</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer further to the
                    Department’s telegram No. 241, received on July 20, 1926, regarding oil drilling
                    permits, and to state that the British Minister called on me on July 21 in
                    company with Mr. J. A. Assheton, legal counsel for the Aguila Company, a
                    British-owned organization, for the purpose of discussing the steps which were
                    to be taken in connection with this matter.</p>
                <p>I informed Mr. Ovey and Mr. Assheton in confidence of the steps which the Embassy
                    had already taken and which were apparently already known to both. Mr. Assheton
                    stated that his Company, while not wishing to make an issue of the question of
                    unlimited bond, would not accept the conditions of the order as it now stood,
                    particularly the third and fourth paragraphs. The Department will recall from my
                    despatch number 2554 of July 20, 1926,<note n="67" xml:id="d397fn67">Not
                        printed.</note> that this corresponds with the attitude as expressed to me
                    of the Standard Oil and Huasteca companies. I was glad to be assured by Mr.
                    Assheton that his Company would not, as erroneously reported in my telegram No.
                    317 of July 19, 1926, 2 p.m., agree to the conditions of the administrative
                    order of June 8th. The British Minister stated that he intended, at a meeting
                    with the President which would shortly take place, to present a memorandum
                    prepared by the Aguila Company, protesting against the provisions of the order.
                    I am transmitting a copy of this memorandum in a separate despatch.<note n="67"
                        xml:id="d397fn68">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>As reported in my telegram No. 319 of today, 12 noon, all of the oil producing
                    companies in Mexico appear to be taking a firm attitude <pb facs="0778" n="682"
                        xml:id="pg_682"/> in opposition to the administrative order of June 8, 1926.
                    The only difference of opinion among the companies at the present time seems to
                    be as to the advisability of applying for concessions under the recently enacted
                    petroleum law and regulations, thereby tacitly admitting the weakness of their
                    position with respect to pre-constitutional rights. It is my understanding that
                    both the Aguila and Corona companies, respectively British and Dutch owned, have
                    applied for concessions to drill under the existing law.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James R. Sheffield</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
