<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-05-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="410" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d410">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">312.1124 Caruana, George J.
                            (Archbishop)</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the General Secretary of the National Catholic Welfare
                                Conference</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Burke</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-05-18"><hi rend="italic">May 18,
                                1926</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Father Burke</hi>: I am in receipt of your
                            letter of May 14, 1926,<note n="87" xml:id="d410fn87">Not
                                printed.</note> stating that information has reached you that His
                            Excellency, the Most Reverend George Caruana, Apostolic Delegate to
                            Mexico, an American citizen, has been notified by the Secret Police of
                            the Mexican Government that he must leave Mexico within a period of six
                            days. You add that you have been advised by the Chief of the Division of
                            Mexican Affairs that the American Ambassador at Mexico City had
                            interceded on behalf of Archbishop Caruana.</p>
                        <p>In reply I desire to inform you that Ambassador Sheffield telegraphed
                            under date of May 12<note n="87" xml:id="d410fn88">Not printed.</note>
                            that Archbishop Caruana had informed him that he received notice on the
                            afternoon of the 12th instant that he must leave Mexico within six days.
                            The Ambassador further reported that, in accordance with telegraphic
                            instructions from the Department sent to him on April 30,<note n="87" xml:id="d410fn89">Not printed.</note> he would intercede on behalf
                            of the Archbishop. Under date of May 13, the Ambassador telegraphed<note n="87" xml:id="d410fn90">Not printed.</note> that he had interceded
                            with the Mexican Minister of Foreign Affairs on behalf of the Archbishop
                            and that the Minister <pb facs="0801" n="705" xml:id="pg_705"/> had
                            promised to make an investigation and advise the Ambassador as to the
                            reasons for the proceedings.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador has now reported in a telegram dated May 15, noon,<note n="88" xml:id="d410fn91">Not printed.</note> that he had just
                            received a memorandum dated the 13th instant, from the Foreign Office,
                            stating that the Archbishop had been invited to leave the country. A
                            further telegram received from the Ambassador, dated May 17, 10
                                A.M.,<note n="88" xml:id="d410fn92">Not printed.</note> stated that
                            Archbishop Caruana left Mexico City for Washington via Laredo on the
                            night of the 16th instant.</p>
                        <p>The Department has taken a deep interest in this case and, as you know,
                            while Ambassador Sheffield was interceding with the Mexican Foreign
                            Minister I made appropriate representations on behalf of the Archbishop
                            through the Mexican Ambassador at this capital. I regret the outcome of
                            these efforts but I feel that everything has been done that this
                            Government could consistently do in the circumstances.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Frank B. Kellogg</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>