<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-07-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="415" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d415">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.12151a/99</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Sheffield</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-07-16"><hi rend="italic">July 16,
                                1926</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received July 23.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 2534</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my telegram No. 309 of July
                            13, 1926, 1 p.m.,<note n="98" xml:id="d415fn98">Not printed.</note> with
                            respect to the Rio Grande Boundary matter, I have the honor to transmit
                            herewith a copy and translation of the note from the Foreign Office on
                            which my telegram was based.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James R.
                            Sheffield</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation<note n="99" xml:id="d415fn99">File translation
                                revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Mexican Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Sáenz</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the American Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sheffield</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-07-10"><hi rend="italic">July 10,
                                        1926</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 8959</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Ambassador</hi>: I have noted Your
                                Excellency’s courteous note No. 1319 of June 14, last,<note n="1" xml:id="d415fn1">Note sent on basis of Department’s telegram No.
                                    197, June 12, 4 p.m., <ref target="#pg_708">p. 708</ref>.</note>
                                in which and in connection with my recent note of May 28, you state
                                that an agreement between the two Governments for rectifying the
                                entire channel of the Rio Grande and for determining in advance the
                                sovereignty over lands to be segregated, would necessitate much
                                preliminary work involving a delay prejudicial to the project
                                approved by the International Boundary Commission <pb facs="0806" n="710" xml:id="pg_710"/> for averting floods in the vicinity of
                                El Paso and Juarez; but that the Government of the United States,
                                being disposed to listen to any proposal tending to the settlement
                                of the other issues involved, asks if my Government is willing to
                                approve Minute No. 61, in which case instructions will be issued to
                                the American Boundary Commissioner to proceed to dispose of the
                                pending banco cases.</p>
                            <p>In reply, I beg leave to state to Your Excellency that I agree with
                                you, that the completion of the rectification plan for the entire
                                Rio Grande channel, determining in advance the location of the
                                cut-offs and the sovereignty of the lands segregated, would delay
                                the works, the urgent necessity of which I realize.</p>
                            <p>My Government, in note No. 11089 of August 18, 1925,<note n="2" xml:id="d415fn2"><ref target="frus1925v02#pg_579"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1925, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 579</ref>.</note> desirous
                                of avoiding the creation of new difficulties before the settlement
                                of pending cases, decided, without rejecting them, to postpone the
                                carrying out of the recommendations contained in Minute No. 61, but
                                subsequently waived, in view of the urgency of the case, in note No.
                                6416 of May 28 of the present year, all the pending questions
                                relating thereto. However, in the recommendations of said Minute,
                                even in connection with cut-offs for a distance of eight miles below
                                El Paso and Juarez and the stipulation that the jurisdiction over
                                lands segregated should continue the same as prior to the
                                segregation, it was not borne in mind that the proposed works would
                                cut lands on which bancos have formed and that the carrying out of
                                such works would completely obliterate traces of abandoned channels
                                and the exact location of these presumptive bancos, which would
                                justify a previous survey and delimitation thereof before
                                obliterating these natural marks or traces.</p>
                            <p>However, since maps of the presumptive bancos of the valley of El
                                Paso have been completed and presented to the International Boundary
                                Commission, I take pleasure in stating that my Government is
                                disposed to carry out the recommendations of said Minute No. 61,
                                counting on the promise of Your Excellency’s Government contained in
                                the note under acknowledgment, to discuss the elimination of the
                                bancos mentioned, thus ending the delay which the Government of the
                                United States has continued with regard to this matter since
                                1911.</p>
                            <p>I should add that the willingness of my Government to carry out the
                                recommendations of Minute No. 61 is based on the understanding that
                                efforts will be made to carry out, within the shortest time
                                possible, the general plan for the rectification of the Rio Grande
                                channel from El Paso to Fort Quitman, upon the basis, in general
                                terms, of superficial compensation, stipulating in a special
                                convention the exchange of nationality of these parcels according to
                                a standard similar to that adopted for the elimination of
                                bancos.</p>
                            <p>1 avail myself [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Aarón Sáenz</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>