<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-09-01T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-09-01T12:00:00-05:00" n="438" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d438">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">881.00/1289: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hammond</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">San
                                        Sebastián</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-09-01T18:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">September 1,
                                        1926—6 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received 8:33
                            p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>66. Department’s 44, August 31, 6 p.m. Upon my handing a note in the
                            sense of the instruction above-mentioned to the Minister of State, the
                            latter stated that he as well as the Spanish Government deeply
                            appreciated the attitude of the American Government in the premises and
                            that he felt that the presence of the United States (a power
                            disinterested politically) at a conference of this nature would be of
                            the greatest help as an influence toward a fair settlement of <pb facs="0836" n="740" xml:id="pg_740"/> an extremely difficult
                            problem. He said that Spain would continue her efforts to bring about a
                            conference of the signatories of the Treaty of Algeciras although the
                            connection between this question and that of a permanent seat for Spain
                            in the Council of the League had ceased to exist. Both questions would
                            be decided separately on their merits and there was therefore no longer
                            any real special haste in calling a conference.</p>
                        <p rend="center">[Paraphrase]</p>
                        <p>When I asked him about the attitude of the other great powers interested
                            in the Moroccan question he said that Italy was openly favorable to a
                            conference, that the attitude of Great Britain was reserved, but that
                            the British admitted in principle the validity of the reasons offered
                            for proposing changes in the Statute of Tangier in Spain’s favor, while
                            the French, although they admitted the justification of Spain’s call for
                            a conference of the signatories of the Act of Algeciras, wished to
                            postpone it for some time and possibly to nullify its benefits by
                            calling for a previous arrangement between France, Spain, and Great
                            Britain which should deal with the question on the basis of the treaty
                            of 1912 and the Statute of Tangier of 1923, with this agreement to be
                            placed before the conference for acceptance.</p>
                        <p>On the subject of the League of Nations, Yanguas said that Spain would
                            dissociate herself from the League by a note which would be presented
                            when the Assembly convened on September 6th.</p>
                        <p>He went on to say that this action made it more desirable than ever for
                            Spain to strengthen the ties of friendship which united her to the
                            United States and to the Latin American countries.</p>
                        <p>Copies have been forwarded by mail to Paris, London, Rome, and
                            Tangier.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hammond</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>