<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the American Missions in Costa Rica, Guatemala,
                    Honduras, and Salvador</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1926v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d468</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">468</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1926-01-07T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1926-01-07T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-01-07T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-01-07T19:00:00-05:00" n="468"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d468">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">817.00/3383a: Circular telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">American Missions in Costa Rica, Guatemala, Honduras,
                            and Salvador</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-01-07T19:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 7, 1926—7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>On October 25, General Chamorro seized the fortress dominating Managua and
                    informed the American Minister that it was his express purpose to drive the
                    Liberals from the cabinet and restore the Conservative Party to the power which
                    it enjoyed before the last election. He stated that he wished Solorzano to
                    remain President and himself to be appointed Minister of War and to have
                    complete control of all arms. The American Minister immediately informed him
                    that any Government assuming power by force would not be recognized by the
                    Government of the United States. Chamorro forced Solorzano to sign a joint
                    document agreeing (1) that the coalition pacts should be broken and be
                    considered as of no value henceforth; (2) that the Government be entirely
                    Conservative; (3) that full amnesty be granted to all participants in his
                    military operations; (4) that the Government pay Chamorro 10,000 cordobas for
                    the expenses of his uprising besides paying the troops; (5) that Chamorro be
                    made General in Chief of the Army. Chamorro thus gained complete control. The
                    middle of November he sent 1200 men to Leon and stated that they would be held
                    there until Vice President Sacasa who was then in hiding should resign and he
                    intimated that if milder means could not produce Sacasa’s resignation sterner
                    measures might be adopted toward relatives and friends of the Vice President.
                    Sacasa escaped and is now in the United States.</p>
                <p>Chamorro was elected Senator on January 3, and states his intention of being
                    elected first <hi rend="italic">designado</hi> on January 11, whereupon he will
                    cause Solorzano to resign and through intimidation will keep Sacasa from
                    returning to the country and he will thus be President.</p>
                <p>The Legation in Managua has been instructed to inform Chamorro that the United
                    States would not recognize any Government headed by him since such a government
                    would be founded on a <hi rend="italic">coup d’etat</hi>
                    <pb facs="0877" n="781" xml:id="pg_781"/> and hence is debarred of recognition
                    under the General Treaty of Peace and Amity of 1923.<note n="2" xml:id="d468fn2"
                        >See <hi rend="italic">Conference on Central American Affairs, Washington,
                            December 4, 1922–February 7, 1923</hi> (Washington, Government Printing
                        Office, 1923), p. 287.</note> The Nicaraguan Minister in Washington has also
                    been definitely told that Chamorro will not be recognized if he assumes the
                    presidency and it is hoped that this categoric statement made both here and in
                    Managua may prove effective in preventing his taking this step. The Department
                    feels that the signatories of the 1923 Treaty should make clear to Chamorro
                    their position in the matter and it hopes that the Government to which you are
                    accredited will instruct its representative in Managua by telegraph to tell
                    Chamorro immediately that he will not be recognized by it should he assume the
                    presidency during the present presidential term of office. This statement should
                    be made before January 11, and should also be made public. The Legation at
                    Managua reports on January 5,<note n="3" xml:id="d468fn3">Telegram not
                        printed.</note> that Chamorro maintains that he can obtain recognition from
                    the other Central American States.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
