<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-03-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="97" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">890d.00/377</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Damascus</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Keeley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Damascus</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-03-03"><hi rend="italic">March 3,
                                1926</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received April 28.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 329</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my despatches
                            Nos. 285 and 296 of October 26 and December 4, 1925, respectively,<note n="69" xml:id="d97fn69">Neither printed.</note> in so far as they
                            deal with representations to the French Authorities respecting the
                            protection of foreigners in general and Americans in particular residing
                            in Damascus, and to report the following additional developments along
                            this line.</p>
                        <p>On February 9, 1926, at the instigation of this office, the Consular
                            Corps addressed a note to M. Pierre Alype, Envoy Extraordinary in
                            Damascus of the French High Commissioner, inviting his attention to the
                            ease with which the rebels had recently been circulating in Damascus
                            where they had kidnapped various persons and possessed themselves of
                            their belongings. It was pointed out that there appeared to be nothing
                            to prevent the same thing being done to foreigners, and he was requested
                            to inform the Consuls whether or not he thought the condition of
                            security in the city warranted any modification in the opinion expressed
                            by General Soulé, the predecessor of General Andréa, and communicated to
                            the Consuls on December 1, 1925, (see Enclosure No. 5 with despatch No.
                            296 of December 4, 1925) to see effect that the situation did not then
                            seem to warrant advising foreigners to evacuate the city. A copy of the
                            Consular Corps’ note, in French and in translation, is transmitted
                            herewith.</p>
                        <pb facs="0233" n="137" xml:id="pg_137"/>
                        <p>On February 19, 1926, M. Alype transmitted to the Dean of the Consular
                            Corps a copy of General Andréa’s reply, dated February 13, 1926, to the
                            questions raised in the Consular Corps’ note. Copies of each of these
                            communications are transmitted herewith. They are self-explanatory.</p>
                        <p>Being unable to share General Andréa’s optimistic view of the situation
                            as expressed in his letter, and the potential danger to Americans having
                            been subsequently increased by the anti-Christian and anti-foreign
                            feeling aroused by the action of Armenian irregulars who were sent into
                            the Meidan Quarter on February 15th ostensibly against the rebels
                            occupying that quarter … this Consulate on February 22, 1926, addressed
                            a further note to M. Alype. A copy of the note, in English and in
                            translation, is transmitted herewith.</p>
                        <p>It is believed that the Department will find my note of February 22nd
                            self-explanatory. In order to avoid a possible misinterpretation of my
                            motive in referring to the use of Armenian irregulars, however, it may
                            be well to point out that it was from their use that Moslem feeling had
                            become aroused to such an extent that a massacre of all Christians was
                            not beyond probability and was thwarted not so much by any preventive
                            action of the French Authorities as by the attitude of the more
                            enlightened Moslems who, some because they realized the inexpediency of
                            a massacre, others because they were really opposed to it on ethical
                            grounds, counseled moderation to their coreligionists.</p>
                        <p>On February 25, 1926, not having received any response to my
                            communication of the 22nd to the French Authorities, I addressed all
                            Americans in Damascus individually, advising them to leave the city and
                            district. A copy of one of these letters is transmitted herewith.<note n="70" xml:id="d97fn70">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <p>Certain of the more loquacious members of the American colony upon
                            receiving my letter proceeded to divulge its contents to their native
                            friends with the result that within a few hours my advice to my
                            nationals was quite generally known in the city and was being
                            exaggerated by repetition.</p>
                        <p>Saturday morning, February 27, 1926, I received a personal note from
                            General Andréa asking me whether I would be good enough to call upon him
                            to discuss the matter of protecting my nationals. I called at three in
                            the afternoon and passed an hour with the General who took up my letter
                            of February 22nd point by point with me. He went into great detail in
                            explaining the military measures taken for the defense of the city and
                            assured me that he was prepared to guarantee foreigners in general and
                            Americans in particular from the danger of any important attack from
                            without and from serious disorders within the city.</p>
                        <pb facs="0234" n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/>
                        <p>General Andréa made no reference to the letter advising Americans to
                            leave the city, but being certain that he either then knew of it or
                            would soon learn of it and perhaps misconstrue its intent, I broached
                            the subject, showed him a copy of the letter and translated its
                            contents. His previous cordial manner changed to a formal reserve as he
                            pointed out that, diplomatically speaking, the letter was really a
                            reflection upon his administration in that it declared the city to be
                            unsafe, whereas he had just shown me that it was safe. I pointed out his
                            admitted inability to guarantee Americans against the danger of stray
                            shots which have recently killed a number of innocent pedestrians, and
                            for that reason alone, if for no other, the warning to Americans was
                            justified.</p>
                        <p>After a further exchange of opinions and friendly discussion of the
                            rebellion, he became more cordial again, and as we parted he assured me
                            that the safety of my nationals would be one of his chief concerns, that
                            he would notify me immediately of impending danger, and that in the
                            event of serious disorder within the city he would send a special guard
                            to the Consulate for its protection and for that of any Americans who
                            might take refuge there.</p>
                        <p>Yesterday I received from M. Alype his reply, dated March 1, 1926, to my
                            note of February 22, 1926. A copy of M. Alype’s letter, in French and in
                            translation, is transmitted herewith. It is self-explanatory.</p>
                        <p>I agree with M. Alype’s admission in the fifth [<hi rend="italic">fourth</hi>] paragraph of his letter of March 1, 1926, to the
                            effect that the situation in Damascus is still serious and must be
                            followed with attention. I am pleased to report, however, that the
                            situation within the city has ameliorated since my note of February 22,
                            1926, was written, but I cannot conscientiously grant that there is as
                            complete security for foreign nationals established in Damascus as M.
                            Alype would have me believe. I have no intention, however, of pursuing
                            the discussion further with the Authorities along abstract lines, and I
                            have therefore merely thanked M. Alype and General Andréa for their
                            detailed exposition of the case, assuring them at the same time of my
                            sincere desire to cooperate with them fully in this part of their
                            difficult task.</p>
                        <p>I trust that the Department will approve the course pursued by me as
                            outlined herein, since I am of the opinion that it, together with Mr.
                            Knabenshue’s representations direct to the High Commissioner, has
                            aroused the French Authorities locally to a better appreciation of their
                            responsibility with respect to our nationals, a responsibility for which
                            they have not on all occasions shown due regard.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. H. Keeley</hi>,
                            Jr.</signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0235" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure
                                1—Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Dean of the Consular Corps at Damascus</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Smart</hi></persName>)<note n="71" xml:id="d97fn71">British
                                    consul at Damascus.</note>
                                <hi rend="italic">to the Envoy Extraordinary at Damascus</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Alype</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">of the French High Commissioner to the States
                                    of Syria and the Lebanon</hi> (<persName><hi rend="italic">De
                                        Jouvenel</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Damascus</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-02-09"><hi rend="italic">February 9,
                                        1926</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Envoy Extraordinary</hi>: I am charged by
                                the Consular Corps to make known to you its anxiety on the subject
                                of the actual situation in the city of Damascus. While fully
                                considering the momentary difficulties confronting the Authorities,
                                the Consular Corps believes it necessary to point out the
                                possibility of danger for the foreign colonies.</p>
                            <p>The foreigners are very much scattered in the city, and, for the most
                                part, are not found in the limited zone that is covered by the
                                troops. Recently, bands have circulated quite frequently in many
                                quarters of the city, where they have carried away various persons
                                and their belongings. It seems that nothing prevents these bands
                                from doing the same with respect to the foreigners.</p>
                            <p>General Soulé in his letter No. 9335/1 of November 30 addressed to
                                the Delegate, who communicated it to me as Dean under cover of his
                                letter No. 9335 bis of the same date, expressed the opinion that the
                                situation did not indicate that foreigners should be advised to
                                leave the city. The Consular Corps would be grateful to you to be
                                good enough to let it know if this advice should be modified in view
                                of the present situation.</p>
                            <p>Meanwhile, the Consular Corps hopes that the Mandatory Authorities
                                will take the necessary measures to assure the foreigners against
                                the dangers, above-mentioned.</p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. A. Smart</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure
                                2—Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Envoy Extraordinary at Damascus</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Alype</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">of the French High Commissioner to the States
                                    of Syria and the Lebanon</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">De Jouvenel</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Dean of the Consular Corps at Damascus</hi>
                                        (<persName><hi rend="italic">Smart</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Damascus</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-02-19"><hi rend="italic">February 19,
                                        1926</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 2924/C</seg></opener>
                            <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean</hi>: The 9th of February last, you
                                were good enough to call my attention to the anxiety of the Consular
                                Corps on the present situation in Damascus.</p>
                            <p>I hastened to bring this matter to the attention of General Andréa,
                                and I have the honor to transmit to you herewith a copy of his
                                answer.</p>
                            <p>I add that the fate of the foreign colonies is the object of all the
                                solicitude of the Mandatory Power in Syria, and I beg you to accept,
                                Mr. Dean, the assurance of my high consideration.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre Alype</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0236" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure—Translation<note n="72" xml:id="d97fn72">File translation
                                revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The General Commanding the Troops of the Region
                                    of Damascus and of the Djebel Druse</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Andréa</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Envoy Extraordinary at Damascus</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Alype</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">of the French High Commissioner to the States of
                                    Syria and the Lebanon</hi> (<persName><hi rend="italic">De
                                        Jouvenel</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Damascus</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-02-13"><hi rend="italic">February 13,
                                        1926</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. /2</seg></opener>
                            <p>The kidnapping of persons to which the Dean of the Consular Corps
                                refers has not failed to attract every attention of the Command.</p>
                            <p>The works of defense now in progress will make it possible within two
                                weeks to prevent bands from entering the inner quarters which
                                represent, after all, the most important part of the city. The
                                elimination of the troublesome elements will follow.</p>
                            <p>Only the Meidan-Akrad and Mohajrin quarters will be left outside the
                                barbed wire entanglements. Their defense will be entrusted to three
                                groups of 50 partisans each.</p>
                            <p>I consider that, under these circumstances, the security of the
                                foreign nationals will be adequately assured, and I cannot in
                                consequence modify the advice previously expressed by General
                                Soulé.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Andréa</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure
                                3—Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The American Consul at Damascus</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Keeley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Envoy Extraordinary at Damascus</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Alype</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">of the French High Commissioner to the States
                                    of Syria and the Lebanon</hi> (<persName><hi rend="italic">De
                                        Jouvenel</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Damascus</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-02-22"><hi rend="italic">February 22,
                                        1926</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to your
                                letter No. 2924/C of February 19, 1926, addressed to the Dean of the
                                Consular Corps, transmitting a copy of General Andréa’s reply to the
                                Consular Corps’ note of February 9, 1926, respecting the anxiety of
                                the Consuls for the safety of their nationals because of the
                                condition of public security in Damascus.</p>
                            <p>The danger from the activities of the bands which prompted the
                                Consular Corps’ note of February 9, 1926, has now been added to by
                                the natural reaction against foreigners and Christians as a result
                                of the recent activities of the Circassian and Armenian partisans in
                                certain sections of the city.</p>
                            <p>Despite the optimistic tone of General Andréa’s communication, I feel
                                sure that neither he nor you can now be unaware of the gravity of
                                the present situation in Damascus or of the fact that further
                                religious animosity and hatred of foreigners cannot fail to result
                                from a continued use of Armenian partisans against the Moslems.</p>
                            <pb facs="0237" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/>
                            <p>While being sincerely appreciative of the solicitude for the safety
                                of foreigners expressed by yourself and taking into account the
                                measures of defense which General Andréa believes will eventually
                                assure the security of foreigners, I regret to record that I am yet
                                unable to view the situation with optimism. From information which I
                                can no longer ignore I am forced to conclude that the present
                                situation in Damascus is more serious than at any previous time. I
                                must request, therefore, that adequate measures be taken immediately
                                to safeguard the lives and property of American citizens, for the
                                protection of which the Mandatory Government will be held strictly
                                accountable.</p>
                            <p>In order to assist the Mandatory Authorities in this difficult task
                                should grave disorders break out in the city an effort will be made
                                to gather as many Americans as possible under the shelter of this
                                Consulate.</p>
                            <p>I shall be grateful, therefore, to you and to General Andréa if you
                                will advise me immediately of the start of any serious
                                disorders.</p>
                            <p>A similar request addressed to your predecessor prior to the outbreak
                                in October<note n="73" xml:id="d97fn73">See telegram of Oct. 28,
                                    1925, 4 p.m., from the consul at Beirut, and subsequent papers,
                                        <ref target="frus1925v02#pg_112"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1925, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                                        pp. 112</ref> ff.</note> elicited assurances that Americans
                                would be fully protected and that this Consulate would be promptly
                                informed of the least sign of danger … I trust that you will
                                understand, therefore, that this letter is prompted by solicitude
                                for my nationals and by a sincere desire to cooperate fully with the
                                French Authorities with the difficulty of whose task I am fully
                                sympathetic.</p>
                            <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. H. Keeley</hi>,
                                Jr.</signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 4—Translation<note n="74" xml:id="d97fn74">File translation
                                revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Envoy Extraordinary at Damascus</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Alype</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">of the French High Commissioner to the States
                                    of Syria and the Lebanon</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">De Jouvenel</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Consul at Damascus</hi> (<persName><hi rend="italic">Keeley</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Damascus</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-03-01"><hi rend="italic">March 1,
                                        1926</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 5080/SP</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Consul</hi>: You were good enough to invite
                                my attention to the apprehension which the political situation in
                                Damascus has caused you, and to the dangers that seemed to you would
                                result to the Christian elements of this city, whether of Syrian
                                origin or of foreign nationality.</p>
                            <p>Already, in a note which was transmitted to me by the Consular Corps
                                on February 9, you made known to me your anxiety. I answered
                                assuring you that General Andréa had taken sufficient military
                                measures so that no threats could be put into execution in respect
                                to your nationals dwelling in town and so that they would <pb facs="0238" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/> suffer no more from the
                                repercussions of acts of banditry in the interior of Damascus.</p>
                            <p>General Andréa, to whom I communicated your letter of February 22,
                                informs me that the apprehensions of which you make yourself the
                                interpreter do not seem to him to correspond any longer to the
                                present situation. After the clearing operations in the Meidan
                                Quarter where a great number of bandits were killed, a certain
                                agitation had, in fact, manifested itself among the Moslems against
                                the Armenians and the Christians in general, but the measures taken
                                immediately by the responsible authorities, as well as the advice to
                                be calm which was given to the delegation of the notables, have
                                greatly abated this feeling. You have yourself been able to note a
                                conspicuous resumption of commercial activity.</p>
                            <p>I do not pretend that the situation in Damascus must not be followed
                                with attention. It is still serious. General Andréa carries on very
                                actively the work for the defense of the outskirts of the city. The
                                barbed wire entanglement is completed and will be further
                                strengthened.</p>
                            <p>This wirework, perfectly commanded at all points by the machine-gun
                                fire from the barrage posts, is already a very effective guarantee
                                against the incursions of bands into the interior of the city.</p>
                            <p>To prevent any insurrectionary movement in the city itself, strong
                                patrols composed of French soldiers, commanded by officers of our
                                army and aided by gendarmes, policemen and partisans, patrol, night
                                and day, the different quarters.</p>
                            <p>General Andréa considers, under these circumstances, that he will be
                                kept accurately in touch with the state of mind of the population,
                                and will be able, in case of necessity, to take immediate measures
                                which will enable him to maintain order and peace.</p>
                            <p>I am glad to bring this information to your knowledge, and I hope it
                                will allay the apprehension which you have manifested. The French
                                Authority assumes at this moment the responsibility of maintaining
                                order in Syria, and its first care is to see that a security as
                                complete as possible, in view of events, be given to the foreign
                                nationals settled in Damascus.</p>
                            <p>You will be good enough to grant that it is not lacking.</p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre Alype</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>