<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="104" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d104">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">690B.9321/9–2653: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 104<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Republic of China
                                    (<persName type="from">Jones</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Taipei</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-09-26T14:00:00+09:00">September 26, 1953—2
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>195. Reference <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 253<note n="1" xml:id="d104fn1"><ref target="#d103"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note> and <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 189.<note n="2" xml:id="d104fn2">Dated Sept. 24; it
                                reported that Yeh told Jones that the Ministry of National Defense
                                had taken steps to ensure that no supplies were sent to the troops
                                in Burma. (690B.9321/9–2453)</note> President Chiang returned from
                            south last night and I was given appointment to see him this morning. I
                            conveyed substance of reference telegram almost verbatim and left strong
                            paraphrase as informal reference. President replied that he was
                            instructing Foreign Minister to communicate with me on this matter
                            immediately and indicated his conviction reply would be satisfactory to
                            US Government.</p>
                        <p>Inwardness of situation here is that Foreign Minister, Prime Minister,
                            Secretary-General and Chief of Staff (real OSP Ministry of National
                            Defense and Military Forces) are united in bringing pressure to bear on
                            President to accept American proposals. He has been yielding, inch by
                            inch, but it has been hard work accompanied by violent argument and
                            Generalissimo is irritable now whenever subject is brought up.
                            Nevertheless, he received me courteously, listened with patience but
                            obviously did not wish to enter into discussion of matter himself.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, Cabinet met this morning and approved statement of a draft
                            prepared by the Foreign Minister for presentation to the President
                            immediately following my interview with him.</p>
                        <p>I have appointment with Foreign Minister at 4:30 today to receive
                            statement and will inform Department soonest.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Jones</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>