<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-10-14T04:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-10-14T04:30:00-05:00" n="225" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d225">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">756D.00/10–1452: Telegram</note>
                        <head>No. 225<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Indonesia (<persName type="from">Cochran</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Djakarta</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-10-14T17:00:00+07:30">October 14, 1952—5
                                    p.m.</date><note n="1" xml:id="d225fn1">The file copy indicates
                                    that this telegram was received at 11:50 a.m. on Oct. 14. A
                                    notation by Coerr, however, indicates it was received after
                                    telegram 562 (<ref target="#d226"><hi rend="italic">infra</hi></ref>) was sent.</note></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>688. Re <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 536.<note n="2" xml:id="d225fn2"><ref target="#d224"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note> Asst Secy Allison and Amb were recd by
                                <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> Mukarto 10 a.m. Oct 14
                            with Darmasetiawan, Rasjid, Sudjono, and Ismael present.</p>
                        <p>Conversation was only general in character on <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> matters until toward close. <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> then asked Amb whether it wld be possible consummate
                            exchange of ltrs on aid program before Mukarto leaves for UNGA Oct
                            17.</p>
                        <p>Amb replied he had reported promptly to Dept unwillingness <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> Govt meet technical terms of US
                            drafts and had been informed US Govt was studying this question.</p>
                        <p>Mukarto had stated earlier in mtg that immed danger of Cab crisis had
                            subsided and that this development wld allow his attend UNGA. Amb asked
                            whether this easing of polit situation wld permit <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> Wilopo submit <gloss target="#t_TCA1">TCA</gloss> agreement containing US technical
                            provisions to Parl. Mukarto said this wld be impossible. Amb replied he
                            did not want to urge <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> Govt do
                            anything which might endanger it. Mukarto said really no urgency in
                            getting matter settled before his departure. Amb pointed out that
                            inability consummate agreement delays consideration of 1953 program. Amb
                            made point, however, that <gloss target="#t_TCA1">TCA</gloss> organ
                            carrying out aid projects already under way. Mukarto’s attitude
                            indicated unlikely <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss> Govt take any
                            new decision on aid question prior his US visit.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Cochran</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>