<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 256The Ambassador in Indonesia (Cumming) to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d256</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">256</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-11-23T22:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-11-23T22:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recLolgZHy7viyqKU" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068390"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="recrT0TBgNbKJyC3W" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006005376"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Extremist</term>
                    <term ref="recfab616ca717a635" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="decolonization" subject="colonialism">Colonialism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-11-23T22:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-11-23T22:30:00-05:00" n="256"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d256">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">756D.00/11–2453: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 256<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Indonesia (<persName type="from"
                            >Cumming</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Djakarta</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-11-24T11:00:00+07:30"
                            >November 24, 1953—11 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>525. Foreign Minister said he wished take advantage my call on him this morning
                    on other matter to clarify what he called “misconceptions” on part of number of
                    foreign governments and especially their diplomatic representatives in Djakarta
                    of attitude of Indonesian Government towards Communism. His manner was earnest
                    and frank although I could detect a certain defensiveness on his part which
                    showed itself in a repetition of a number of statements as if he were most
                    anxious that I believe what he said.</p>
                <p>He commenced by saying that while some Moslems could for reasons unknown to him
                    reconcile their religious faith with the anti-God dogma of Communists, he
                    himself was unable to do so; he wanted me to know that although he might not at
                    all times be as devout a Moslem as he should be, his faith in God was complete
                    and a guarantee against any personal leaning on his part toward Communism.</p>
                <p>He said it was true that government was willing accept Communist Party support in
                    Parliament: “No parliamentarian could refuse to accept a vote from any source;”
                    but that government had sufficient votes to carry its measure without addition
                    of Communist votes (note discrepancy between this statement and that of Prime
                    Minister Ali last paragraph my telegram 453, November 2).<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d256fn1">
                        <p>Not printed. The paragraph in question reads as follows:</p>
                        <p>“Ali comments to me on the subject of his government’s association with
                            Commies might be summarized: ‘We are not Communists but they have the
                            votes we need.’ I think he realizes he playing with fire; whether all of
                            his associates are as sophisticated is doubtful.” (756D.13/11–253)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>He said he could assure me that government of the <gloss target="#t_PNI1"
                        >PNI</gloss> was well aware through intelligence sources of strategy of
                    Communist Party to infiltrate government and to maneuver government if possible
                    into position where Communist vote was essential to continue in office; that
                    government was equally aware of strategy of <gloss target="#t_Masjumi1"
                        >Masjumi</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_PSI1">PSI</gloss> to do everything
                    including, if necessary, participation in Communist plots to bring about
                    government’s downfall. But he said government of <gloss target="#t_PNI1"
                        >PNI</gloss> had its own strategy designed circumvent these plans. He did
                    not elucidate.</p>
                <p>To illustrate government’s preoccupation with Communist danger he said that
                    conversations had already taken place with <pb facs="0422" n="402"
                        xml:id="pg_402"/> British officials in Sarawak to prevent Communists
                    crossing border between Kalimantan (Borneo) and Sarawak; that conversations had
                    already taken place with Malayan authorities with regard to similar
                    arrangements, and he had raised question again with Malcolm MacDonald<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d256fn2">British Commissioner General in Southeast Asia.</note>
                    during his recent visit to Djakarta. He also mentioned Australia but I did not
                    understand whether he said similar conversations had taken place or were
                    contemplated with Australian authorities on same subject. (I have no
                    confirmation of foregoing statements from any other source and will not attempt
                    verify locally. Would appreciate any information Department has on
                        subject.)<note n="3" xml:id="d256fn3">On Dec. 1 the Department informed the
                        Embassy of talks in August 1952 between Indonesian and Sarawak officials
                        concerning agreed joint measures to combat Communist terrorism. It also
                        referred to a statement made in April 1953 by Sunario concerning Indonesia’s
                        interest in political developments, including the increasing strength of the
                        Communist movement, in Malaya. (Telegram 443; 756D.00/11–2453)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sunario said government was also concerned with Chinese problem; Chinese even
                    though long resident in Indonesia and in former Dutch East Indies had never been
                    truly loyal to local government. He said that while government especially
                    concerned with Communist infiltration and trying formulate plans to meet this
                    situation, its principal concern was not with whether Chinese were Communists or
                    Nationalists, but whether they were subversive of government of the country in
                    which they resided.</p>
                <p>With regard to Indochina he said that Indonesian Government had naturally
                    disliked French colonialism and French “delays” in promising real independence
                    to Associated States but that his government equally understood French and
                    Associated States were fighting Communism; that if Communists were successful in
                    Indochina, Malaya would be next and “Indonesia soon after.”</p>
                <p>Sunario concluded by reference to President Sukarno’s recent speech (<gloss
                        target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 487, November 11)<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d256fn4">Telegram 487 reported on a speech made on Nov. 10 by
                        President Sukarno in Solo in which he called for national discipline and
                        criticized the extremists in Darul Islam and the Indonesian Communist
                        movement. The speech was characterized as the President’s most forthright
                        anti-Communist statement in some time and his first since the Ali government
                        came into office. (756D.00/11–1153)</note> and anticipated a question I had
                    in mind to put to him by saying that the President’s reference to “extreme
                    Communists” meant Communists who were actively attempting overthrow government
                    as contrasted with rank and file of party followers. He reverted to government
                    evidence of Dutch support of Darul Islam and criticized his fellow Moslems of
                    the <gloss target="#t_Masjumi1">Masjumi</gloss> party which he said was slowly
                    drifting towards extremist position of the Darul Islam. “The Government”, he
                    said, “will prevent any extremists taking over under an Indonesian
                    Mossadeq.”</p>
                <pb facs="0423" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/>
                <p>I am reporting this conversation at length because it is first time the Foreign
                    Minister has so fully unburdened himself to me and because he gave me to
                    understand that what he was saying had been discussed with and approved by Prime
                    Minister and President.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cumming</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
