<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 287The Ambassador in Indonesia (Cumming) to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d287</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">287</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-28T01:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-28T01:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-28T01:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-28T01:30:00-05:00" n="287"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d287">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">756D.11/7–2854: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 287<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Indonesia (<persName type="from"
                            >Cumming</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Djakarta</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-28T14:00:00+07:30"
                            >July 28, 1954—2 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>183. <gloss target="#t_mytel1">Mytel</gloss> 161.<note n="1" xml:id="d287fn1">In
                        telegram 161, July 26, Cumming informed the Department of State that
                        Sukarno, recently returned from a trip to the North Moluccas, had sent word
                        that he wished to see the Ambassador on July 28. (756D.11/7–2654)</note>
                    President received me very cordially this morning. Said he had heard I was going
                    to US on leave and wanted to be sure of seeing me before I went. He was pleased
                    that I had planned to stay Djakarta until after Independence Day celebrations
                    August 17, remarking that my absence would have been noted by anti-American
                    press, and adding “I personally am very sorry your British colleague is going on
                    leave before August 17”.</p>
                <p>Sukarno said he could not order American Ambassadors around but if I had been
                    called home on consultation about this time, he would have found some means to
                    suggest to me the advisability of trying to explain the Indonesian scene in
                    person. He said that his job and he thought mine also was complicated by such
                    items as appeared in the July 19 issue of <hi rend="italic">Newsweek</hi> saying
                    that Indonesia would be the next target of Communist aggression. He said that
                    only foolish people or Communists could believe that the cease-fire in Indochina
                    meant an end to Communist aggression in Southeast Asia or even more than a
                    temporary halt in the development of such plans as the Communists might have for
                    further advances in Asia. He said “We [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] have now lost
                    Indochina” but that it was not yet Indonesia which was in direct danger but
                    rather all Southeast Asia, more especially Thailand.”</p>
                <p>Sukarno said he felt that it was now more important than ever that US find some
                    way to appeal to the bulk of Indonesian people and restore high regard
                    Indonesian people had for US until past two or three years. Sukarno said he felt
                    US and American people could be best and most influential friends that Indonesia
                    could have. He wanted to assure me that he was doing all he could consistent
                    with Indonesian independent policy and requirements of his office not only to
                    combat tendencies to regard Communist countries as the real friends of Indonesia
                    but also to explain in private conversations his understanding apparent
                    inconsistencies between American action or rather as he put it, inaction with
                    regard to Irian and American stated anti-imperialism and anti-colonialism.
                    Accordingly he very sincerely hoped that we could make some gesture <pb
                        facs="0477" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/> to recognize legitimacy of
                    Indonesians’ claim in Irian. He said he thought he understood thoroughly,
                    although yet he did not agree, the dilemma posed by our alliance with
                    Netherlands and our friendly feelings toward Indonesia but his people,
                    particularly in the rest of the country, did not understand and the Communists
                    were carrying on most active campaign to prevent them from understanding.
                    (Courtesy forbade me observing his own part in whipping-up of Irian
                    campaign.)</p>
                <p>He asked me bluntly whether we of US Government had ever given the Dutch any form
                    of assurance our support of Dutch claims in Irian and also whether any
                    individuals in American Government as distinguished from government itself
                    advocated Dutch claims to Irian. To the first question I replied in the sense of
                    first paragraph <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 846:<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d287fn2">Dated Apr. 10, not printed.</note> That while our neutral
                    or hands-off attitude re Irian dispute certainly implied recognition of <hi
                        rend="italic">de facto</hi> Dutch administrative control of Irian, we had
                    never so far as I knew ever informed either Dutch or Indonesians that we
                    recognized Dutch sovereignty. To his second question I replied that obviously I
                    could not give a comprehensive reply but that I could say that while both sides
                    of question naturally were discussed from time to time in light of American
                    interests, I had not heard any responsible person come out flatly with advocacy
                    of Dutch or Indonesian sovereignty claims; that any persons with whom I talked
                    over the problem felt that, properly handled, a settlement could be finally
                    reached which would be satisfactory.</p>
                <p>Referring to Communism in Indonesia, Sukarno said very much what Vice President
                    Hatta said to me a week ago: That he was encouraged by the progress which was
                    being slowly made toward countering the growth of domestic Communist influence;
                    that for example whereas a year or two ago <gloss target="#t_SOBSI1"
                        >SOBSI</gloss> was without question “the crowned king of Indonesian labor”
                    he felt that <gloss target="#t_SOBSI1">SOBSI</gloss> influence was now somewhat
                    on the wane and that <gloss target="#t_Masjumi1">Masjumi</gloss> and other
                    non-Communist labor organizations had reason to be more hopeful now than
                    formerly. (<hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> I think the President’s statement is
                    overly optimistic but I think it worth noting that Hatta should in this respect
                    make same assertion as Sukarno, Prime Minister Ali, Foreign Minister Sunario and
                    some other <gloss target="#t_PNI1">PNI</gloss> leaders.)</p>
                <p>The conversation lasted nearly an hour and was friendly and calm, the President
                    convincingly expressing his real friendship for US. He especially requested that
                    the President and Vice President be informed of the essence of conversation<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d287fn3">The substance of this telegram was transmitted to
                        Vice President Nixon in a letter from Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Congressional Relations Thruston B. Morton, dated Aug. 6.
                        (611.56D/8–654)</note> which he summed up <pb facs="0478" n="458"
                        xml:id="pg_458"/> as an appeal to US to find some way—and he thought
                    recognition of Indo-Irian claims the best way—to strike a response from the
                    heart of Indonesian people and thus help him to combat Communist influence and
                    promote understanding and friendship for US.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cumming</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
