<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 348Memorandum by the Secretary of State to the President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d348</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">348</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-12-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-12-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="348"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d348">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.56396/12–2453</note>
                <head>No. 348<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                            State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-12-23">December 23,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Modification of Presidential policy of July 14, 1948 regarding release of
                        bases to the Philippines.<note n="1" xml:id="d348fn1">
                            <p>For text of President Truman’s memorandum of July 14, 1948, to
                                Secretary of State George C. Marshall, see <ref
                                    target="frus1948v06#pg_627">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi
                                        rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 627</ref>. The concluding
                                paragraph reads:</p>
                            <p>“I am in complete agreement with you that the bases we do not need
                                should be returned to the Philippines without compensation and if
                                title is not clear we should make it clear by the proper transfer. I
                                am sure that in case of necessity we would have no trouble getting
                                whatever Military and Naval Bases where necessary anywhere in the
                                Philippines. I am in agreement with you that we should not negotiate
                                on a trading basis.”</p>
                        </note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I refer to the Department’s memorandum, dated July 15, 1953, entitled “Special
                    Mission to the Philippines (1) to negotiate for land required for military base
                    expansion and (2) to reach an overall settlement on property and related
                    questions arising under the Military Bases Agreement”. (Enclosure 1.)<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d348fn2">Not printed. On July 15, President Eisenhower sent a letter
                        to President Quirino requesting discussion of the enumerated topics by
                        representatives of the two countries. President Quirino responded in a
                        letter of Sept. 16 expressing his willingness to cooperate and suggesting
                        that the talks be expanded to include several matters pending since World
                        War II. On Nov. 4, Eisenhower replied stating his, unwillingness to expand
                        the talks beyond property rights and the Military Bases Agreement. (<gloss
                            target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> files, lot 55 D 388, box 388, “Philippine
                        Military Bases”; 711.56396/1–1554) For text of the Military Bases Agreement
                        of 1947, see <gloss target="#t_TIAS1">TIAS</gloss> No. 1775; printed in 61
                        Stat. (pt. 4) 4019.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In a memorandum to former Secretary Marshall of July 14, 1948 former President
                    Truman directed a policy concerning these matters.</p>
                <p>The Attorney General’s opinion, mentioned in the second paragraph of my
                    memorandum under reference, was received on August 28, 1953.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d348fn3">The opinion by Attorney General Herbert S. Brownell is not
                        printed. (711.56396/8–2853)</note> The Attorney General holds that (1)
                    except for properties already conveyed to the Philippines, the United States now
                    has whatever title it had prior to July 4, 1946 in the land comprising
                    pre-Philippine independence military and naval reservations; (2) the President
                    has complete discretion to transfer, with or without compensation, title to such
                    reservations to the Philippines; (3) there is no obligation on the part of the
                    United States to transfer at this time title to any property; and (4) there has
                    been no adjustment <pb facs="0590" n="570" xml:id="pg_570"/> and settlement of
                    United States property rights within the meaning of the Tydings–McDuffie
                        Act.<note n="4" xml:id="d348fn4">Approved Mar. 24, 1934; 48 Stat. 456. It
                        was the legislation which provided for the independence of the
                        Philippines.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The situation in the Far East has changed drastically since 1948. China has
                    fallen into the Communist orbit; the hostilities in Korea have pointed up the
                    urgency of improving our defense in the Pacific; the United States and the
                    Philippines have entered into a Mutual Defense Treaty; and the Philippines has
                    not proved to be as cooperative as anticipated with respect to our military and
                    strategic needs.</p>
                <p>As its contribution toward its own defense under the Mutual Defense Treaty, and
                    in consideration of the value of such of the U.S.-held surplus lands as it may
                    be decided should be transferred to the Philippine Government, the Philippine
                    Government should, I believe, grant to us all other lands we need for our
                    military and diplomatic purposes.</p>
                <p>I therefore recommend that the policy enunciated in 1948 be modified so that the
                    United States shall be free in the forthcoming negotiations to consider and
                    utilize those assets to which we retain title without limitation or restriction
                    in order to accomplish successfully the main objectives of the mission, namely:
                    (1) the acquisition of land required for base expansion and diplomatic purposes,
                    and (2) the over-all settlement of property and related questions arising out of
                    the Military Bases Agreement.</p>
                <p>The Department of Defense, Navy, Air Force and Justice and the Bureau of the
                    Budget concur.<note n="5" xml:id="d348fn5">
                        <p>A note on the source text, initialed by President Eisenhower and dated
                            Dec. 24, indicates his approval of the memorandum.</p>
                        <p>Also on Dec. 24, Secretary Dulles sent a message to Ambassador Spruance
                            stating that the President had emphasized to him his strong desire to
                            deal liberally on the bases question and to give incoming President
                            Magsaysay an encouraging start. (Telegram 1653; 611.96/12–2453)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John Foster Dulles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
