<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-01-15T19:11:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-01-15T19:11:00-05:00" n="786" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d786">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">663.001/1–1552: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 786<lb/><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United
                                        Kingdom</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d786fn1">Drafted by
                                        <persName corresp="#p_AEP1">E. P. Allen</persName>,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_WFT1">Williamson</persName>, and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RP1">Rutter</persName> and cleared by
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BJCH1">Bonbright</persName> and (in
                                    draft) <persName corresp="#p_PGW1">Perkins</persName>. Repeated
                                    to Vienna, Moscow, Paris, and Bonn.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-01-15T19:11:00-05:00">January 15 1952—7:11
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3360. In resuming negots Aust Treaty US objective shld be to seek
                                definite Sov position on present draft treaty, to ascertain on what
                                terms Sov wld conclude treaty, and, in event of anticipated,
                                obstructionism, to prepare way for proposing new basis of
                                negots.</p>
                            <p>Believe Sovs will follow one of three courses of action (1) Sov
                                Deputy may issue propaganda blast against Aust and West Powers, thus
                                blocking conclusion present draft and making more certain Aust
                                settlement dependent on gen Eur settlement or at least settlement
                                Ger problems. (2) Sovs may make new proposal of their own for
                                neutralization Aust, for a Four Power conference, or some other <pb facs="0526" n="1726" xml:id="pg_1726"/> proposal not heretofore
                                considered. Any such Sov proposal shld be referred to West Govts for
                                consideration on its merits unless it is so obviously a propaganda
                                move that such reference is not warranted. (3) Unlikely alternative
                                is that Sov Deputy may indicate he is prepared to discuss present
                                draft with view to its conclusion.</p>
                            <p>Dept considers that in gen terms you shld seek to ascertain Sov
                                position by inquiring whether they are prepared to conclude present
                                draft and, if so, on what terms. This inquiry shld be prefaced by
                                review of previous mtgs and summary of reasons why agreement has
                                been impossible. We are willing if necessary to indicate we are
                                prepared to examine any proposals they wish to make for conclusion
                                of treaty, but extreme care must be exercised to avoid making
                                concessions or involve West in any commitment of any nature to make
                                concessions. Dept considers this question can be handled by skillful
                                negots provided West Powers agree that our objective is to obtain
                                definitive Sov statement on treaty, which if negative can justify
                                intro abbreviated treaty.</p>
                            <p>In event, Sov Deputy indicates willingness to conclude treaty and
                                does not raise extraneous issues, the US will examine his proposals
                                in manner consistent with Secy’s talks with <persName corresp="#p_EASA1">Eden</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d786fn2">Reference to <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName>’s
                                    meeting with <persName corresp="#p_EASA1">Eden</persName> on
                                    Jan. 10; see <ref target="#d782">Document 782</ref>.</note> No
                                commitment can be made concerning concessions on specific articles
                                or extent we wld move to obtain conclusion treaty without instrus
                                from Dept. Action of this nature wld require Congressional
                                consultation and decisions at highest level in Washington.</p>
                            <p>Dept considers that in ur negots you can find acceptable compromise
                                in initial approach to Sovs which does not involve us in any
                                commitment and which satisfies Brit wish to clear field for new
                                basis of negots. We believe Sov Deputy can be maneuvered into
                                position which implies that they wld not accept treaty even on their
                                own terms without making West commitment. It is quite likely that
                                Sov Deputy himself will resolve this problem by refusing to proceed
                                with Aust settlement. Therefore, every effort shld be made to draw
                                out Sov Deputy to propose his program for Aust settlement without
                                directly offering to accept his terms. Dept also considers that if
                                record of negots is published in White Paper and contents and
                                purpose of abbreviated treaty made known, Brit opinion wld endorse
                                this move to obtain an equitable Aust settlement.</p>
                            <p>In summary, US policy in negots shld be guided by fol principles: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>US shld refuse discuss extraneous issues or change agreed
                                        arts.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>US shld not offer further concessions to Sov but shld be
                                        willing to indicate we are prepared to consider
                                        sympathetically any Sov <pb facs="0527" n="1727" xml:id="pg_1727"/> proposals re text of treaty,
                                        providing they offer hope of concluding treaty.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Continuity of negots shld be preserved in order ultimate
                                        objective of settlement containing minimum requirements for
                                        Aust independence can be obtained.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Avoid any situation wherein West Powers can justifiedly be
                                        blamed by Austs for blocking settlement.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AD1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>