<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-09-30T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-09-30T06:00:00-05:00" n="821" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d821">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">663.001/9–3052: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 821<lb/><hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner
                                    for Austria (<persName corresp="#p_TLE1" type="from">Thompson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the
                                        United Kingdom</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d821fn1">Repeated to Paris, Bonn, and Washington. The source text is the
                                    copy in Department of State files.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-09-30T12:00:00+01:00">September 30,
                                        1952—noon.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>41. In discussion with <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber</persName>
                                last evening (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 39, Sept
                                    29<note n="2" xml:id="d821fn2"><ref target="#d820"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note>) fol views were
                                expressed which were, of course, personal on part of all except
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber. Gruber</persName> and Fr rep
                                felt every effort shld be made to get Sovs to conf table. First Fr
                                suggestion was that our reply shld state we had been unable reach
                                agreement through exchange <pb facs="0587" n="1787" xml:id="pg_1787"/> of notes and were therefore inviting Sovs to meet in order that
                                they might explain their point of view. I pointed out that this was
                                tantamount to accepting Sov note as basis for discussion which wld
                                get us nowhere. All agreed that abbreviated draft had pushed Sovs
                                toward acceptance long draft but Fr rep wanted go very far toward
                                disavowing abbreviated draft. Brit rep supported my position that
                                since all agreed little possibility of Sovs agreeing to meet and
                                conclude a treaty at this time we should not throw away this means
                                of pressure. It was clear, however, that <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber</persName> and French and to lesser extent Brit wld be
                                prepared accept long draft, the assumption being that US wld
                                shoulder financial burden. <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber</persName> said it was important make Sovs state their
                                terms then it wld be for the US, UK, Fr and Aust Parliaments to
                                decide whether they could be accepted.</p>
                            <p>I stressed importance of not allowing the Sovs to confuse issue
                                before <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and said that even if we
                                could get Sovs to meet on basis suggested by Fr rep it was unlikely
                                that we could obtain a more clear statement of their position than
                                that contained in their latest note.</p>
                            <p>We were all agreed on importance of removing confusion in mind of
                                Aust public, many of whom now think that negots are blocked by our
                                insistence on abbreviated draft. <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber</persName> also pointed out that if frightened Aust man
                                in the street gave up hope of treaty he wld feel strong pull toward
                                Ger or Sov Union.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber</persName> said that he did not
                                believe he wld have to make any immediate public comment but wld be
                                grateful for any guidance we could give him as soon as possible.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_TLE1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Thompson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>