<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-03-17T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-03-17T13:00:00-05:00" n="856" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d856">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">763.00/3–1753: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 856<lb/><hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner
                                    for Austria (<persName corresp="#p_TLE1" type="from">Thompson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                        State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d856fn1">Repeated to
                                    Paris.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-03-17T19:00:00+01:00">March 17, 1953—7
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2716. British, French and US <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss>s
                                have been in almost daily touch regarding Austrian Government
                                negotiations. At meeting today, following receipt <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 2713 March 16,<note n="2" xml:id="d856fn2">Telegram 2713 instructed <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> to continue his
                                    informal efforts, in coordination with the British and French,
                                    to hasten the early establishment of a coalition government in
                                    Austria. It also noted that a French Embassy official visited
                                    the Department of State and expressed the desire of the French
                                    Government to exert tripartite pressure in Vienna on both
                                    parties to reach a prompt agreement. (763.00/3–1353)</note>
                                there was agreement that our current informal efforts to hasten
                                formation two-party government should be continued, but that no
                                wider action, such as is apparently contemplated by French Embassy
                                Washington, should be undertaken.</p>
                            <p>Talks between two parties are approaching critical stage, and it
                                seems likely that <persName corresp="#p_FL1">Figl</persName> will
                                give up attempt to form government unless he succeeds this week.
                                Federal President would then have to decide whether to call upon
                                another <gloss target="#t_PP1">PP</gloss> representative (<persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Raab</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber</persName> have been mentioned) or Socialist
                                representative (presumably <persName corresp="#p_SA1">Schaerf</persName>) to attempt form government. <gloss target="#t_PP1">PP</gloss> leaders are now saying that if effort
                                to form two-party government fails, <gloss target="#t_PP1">PP</gloss> will probably propose minority government of <gloss target="#t_PP1">PP</gloss> only with expectation it could
                                survive until autumn, when new elections would be held.</p>
                            <p>Although situation is unclear, owing to reluctance of either <gloss target="#t_PP1">PP</gloss> or Socialists to put all their cards
                                on table, only issue on Cabinet now seems to be whether <gloss target="#t_PP1">PP</gloss> will agree to another Socialist State
                                Secretary post, perhaps in Foreign Office, in addition to
                                appointment of Socialist as President of General Accounting Office
                                (Oberrechnungshof), which <gloss target="#t_PP1">PP</gloss> is
                                apparently prepared to concede. <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Raab</persName> seems adamant on maintenance of <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in actual Cabinet posts;
                                Socialists have asked for Minister of Education, but have implied
                                they would settle for State Secretary as set forth above. There is
                                some suspicion that <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Raab</persName>
                                wishes to eliminate <persName corresp="#p_FL1">Figl</persName>, and
                                that his strategy is to allow latter to fail in his attempt to form
                                government as best means of accomplishing this.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_TLE1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Thompson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>