<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-26T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-26T05:00:00-05:00" n="862" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d862">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.5 MSP/4–2653: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 862<lb/><hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner
                                    for Austria (<persName corresp="#p_TLE1" type="from">Thompson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-26T11:00:00+01:00">April 26, 1953—11
                                        a.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3038. Joint Embassy/<gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> message.
                                Cotel. Attention: Arth, IMS. Reference Vienna 3038.<note n="1" xml:id="d862fn1">Telegram 3038 to Vienna, Apr. 16, requested
                                    information from the Embassy for the fiscal year 1954
                                    Congressional presentation on U.S. objectives concerning
                                    European defense production. (740.5 MSP/4–1653)</note> Subject:
                                Austrian contribution west defense.</p>
                            <pb facs="0653" n="1853" xml:id="pg_1853"/>
                            <p>Lettered paragraphs correspond <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Austria physically capable making substantial contribution
                                    west defense program in materials, components, and end-items not
                                    having specific military character although supply strictly
                                    military items precluded by occupation control agreement. Such
                                    contribution would greatly facilitate <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Battle</persName> Act enforcement, as well
                                    as strengthen Austrian <gloss target="#t_BP1">B/P</gloss>.
                                    However, factors described paragraph h below and danger
                                    provoking adverse Soviet reactions possibly impeding resumption
                                    state treaty negotiations dictates development of special type
                                    of limited program minimizing these risks. Therefore mission
                                    believes such program should: (1) not attempt direct procurement
                                    from Soviet zone or Vienna, but limit program to west zones; (2)
                                    possibly establish new office under auspices business
                                    cooperative export agency to channel information, contacts,
                                    negotiation between Austrian businesses and <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> or US prime contractors or
                                    procurement centers, thus minimizing dangers Soviet
                                    retaliation.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Mission aware only one Austrian company (Boehler
                                    Brothers-Steel) which controls subsidiary in Germany. Controls
                                    do not affect subsidiary’s eventual defense production
                                    program.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>Austria has filled army procurement contracts for lumber,
                                    paper, prefabs, steel for railroad car repairs.</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>Attitude of Austrian Government towards acceleration
                                    participation Austrian firms in <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDAP</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_OSP1">OSP</gloss> programs
                                    remains cautious. Various Austrian Government agencies concerned
                                    refuse open support program fearing possible Soviet reprisal
                                    against officials responsible policy. Interest Austrian business
                                    considerable and growing. Need find new export outlets major
                                    problem Austrian business now. Increasing number firms seeking
                                    establish contact with military procurement agencies with
                                    mission as intermediary.</item>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item>Austrian experience supplying US Forces Austria limited to
                                    contracting jobs for construction military housing.</item>
                                <label>f.</label>
                                <item>Uncertainties Austrian situations do not permit adequate
                                    predictions.</item>
                                <label>g.</label>
                                <item>Austria can furnish the following items on sub-contracting
                                    basis to holders <gloss target="#t_OSP1">OSP</gloss>-financed
                                    prime contracts: aluminum-pig and sheet, extruded shapes and
                                    wires; steel-sheet and plates, hot and cold rolled, hot coiled
                                    strips; forgings—large and small; castings—up to 70 tons; ball
                                    bearings—all types; magnesite—sinter bricks and caustic powdered
                                    metallurgy items; lumber and lumber products including prefabs;
                                    machine tools—nuts, screws, and bolts; electro power machinery
                                    and transformers; railroad cars and locomotives; diesel engines;
                                    trucks; pneumatic drills; textile materials or end items.
                                    Mission will forward despatch estimate available quantities.
                                    Quality items listed above recognized good by international <pb facs="0654" n="1854" xml:id="pg_1854"/> standards. Prices
                                    competitive, delivery terms reasonable and adjustable in
                                    accordance requirement.</item>
                                <label>h.</label>
                                <item>Terms control agreement constitute most significant legal
                                    restriction imposed on full Austrian participation <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDAP</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_OSP1">OSP</gloss> program. Allied mail censorship greatly hampers
                                    effective communications potential Austrian suppliers, military
                                    procurement agencies. Soviet-imposed travel restrictions (Enns,
                                    Semmering checkpoints) considered further serious deterrents.
                                    Opinion prevails among businessmen steady contact military
                                    procurement agencies abroad could lead to Soviet kidnapping at
                                    above indicated points.</item>
                                <label>i.</label>
                                <item>Mission attaches greatest importance program as one of few
                                    concrete possibilities for badly needed outlets. Export
                                    situation numerous firms seriously deteriorating in view imposed
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BLD1">Battle</persName> Act
                                    restrictions (Gebus, Steyr, Plansee; reference Embassy despatch
                                    809, November 12,<note n="2" xml:id="d862fn2">Not printed.
                                        (764.00/10–3152)</note> Embassy despatch 1391, February
                                        10<note n="3" xml:id="d862fn3">Despatch 1391 reported on the
                                        capacity and delivery possibilities of the
                                        Steyr–Daimler–Puch Ball Bearing Works, which was seeking new
                                        markets in the West and other non-Soviet bloc countries.
                                        (863.3313/2–1253)</note>). Situation considered particularly
                                    bad in view business pressure on Austrian Government to expand
                                    East European trade. In light Austrian potential contribution
                                    west defense program, on one hand, and probability, on other
                                    hand, serious consequences if US element unable to indicate
                                    alternate outlets in nearest future for blocked eastward
                                    exports, mission would highly appreciate <gloss target="#t_MSAW1">MSA/W</gloss> close consideration
                                    establishment procurement policy facilitating Austrian
                                    participation more extensive scale than heretofore.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_TLE1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Thompson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>