<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 878The United States High Commissioner for Austria (Thompson) to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v07p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d878</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">878</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-07-30T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-07-30T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec26FVg4SV48wXxH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124118"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Socialism</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                    <term ref="recJFd5tAUUdqBj9H" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">East-West relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-30T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-30T14:00:00-05:00" n="878"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d878">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.63/7–3053: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 878<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Austria (<persName
                            corresp="#p_TLE1" type="from">Thompson</persName>) to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-07-30T20:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 30, 1953—8 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>270. Limit distribution. Department circular 53.<note n="1" xml:id="d878fn1"
                        >Circular telegram 53 asked the Ambassadors in 11 <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss> countries and Austria and Germany for their frank
                        confidential estimate and views on how the United States was regarded by the
                        public and government in the countries to which they were accredited.
                        (611.00/7–2353) For the reply to this circular telegram from Bonn, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v07p1#d208">Document 208</ref>.</note> Unquestionably
                    confidence of Austrian Government and people in US leadership was shaken by
                    developments early part this year. Principal causes were following: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Exaggerated reports both US and Austrian press of such matters as
                            Congressional investigations, purge USIS<note n="2" xml:id="d878fn2"
                                >U.S. Information Service.</note> libraries, etc.
                                <persName>Kaghan</persName> case<note n="3" xml:id="d878fn3">
                                <persName>Theodore Kaghan</persName>, Deputy Chief of the Public
                                Affairs Office, <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>, was accused
                                of being soft on communism in April 1953. After appearances before
                                the Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations of the Senate
                                Government Operations Committee, in which he denied the accusations,
                                    <persName>Kaghan</persName> resigned in May 1953.</note> had
                            particularly unfortunate repercussions in Austria where he was
                            well-known by virtually all top officials government as vigorous and
                            effective anti-Communist. Socialists particularly sensitive these
                            developments as tending confirm their fears new US administration would
                            follow policies opposed to liberal concepts Austrian socialism. Both
                            Austrian political parties tend interpret foreign events in terms sharp
                            class and occupational divisions prevailing in Austrian politics. State
                            Secretary for Foreign Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_KB1"
                                >Kreisky</persName> recently informed me there had been serious
                            discussions in top social circles as to whether party could continue
                            follow US leadership in view these developments. Believe situation now
                            seen at least in government circles in more true perspective.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Scepticism with which our official announcements and propaganda
                            greeted each move Soviet peace offensive caused many of less politically
                            sophisticated to doubt whether US genuinely wished arrive at settlement
                            with Soviet Union. This feeling reinforced by <persName
                                corresp="#p_ACR1">Attlee</persName>’s outburst,<note n="4"
                                xml:id="d878fn4">Presumably a reference to former Prime Minister
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ACR1">Attlee</persName>’s speech before
                                the House of Commons on May 12, 1953, in which he criticized the
                                United States and its foreign policy. For text, see <hi
                                    rend="italic">H. C. Deb 5s</hi>, vol. 515, cols.
                                1061–1071.</note> reluctance agree four power talks, etc. Many
                            Austrian officials on other hand more concerned lest US deceived by
                            Soviet moves and make deal at Europe’s expense. To the extent domestic
                            and other considerations allow, I am convinced our propaganda <pb
                                facs="0676" n="1876" xml:id="pg_1876"/> and official statements
                            should place more emphasis on welcoming and encouraging further Soviet
                            moves toward detente in East-West relations. <persName corresp="#p_GK1"
                                >Gruber</persName> recently remarked that we should be careful not
                            to provide the excuse for a reversal of Soviet policy, which he believes
                            will eventually occur. Effect on public opinion would be serious if
                            Communists could successfully maintain that Soviet efforts to reach
                            accommodation had been rebuffed.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>There is in Austria underlying doubt of our ability maintain
                            continuity in our basic international policies. This based more on
                            historical than recent events, although emphasis on foreign affairs in
                            election campaign stimulated these misgivings. These are being allayed
                            as the outlines of the policies of the new administration are becoming
                            clear.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Strain of long occupation and accumulated resentment at what some
                            Austrians regard as undue interference in their economic affairs without
                            sufficient regard for political consequences of our actions have made
                            Austrians fretful. This exacerbated by extent of our East-West trade
                            controls. The increasing intensity of these controls has been cause for
                            serious concern among agricultural, industrial and organized labor
                            groups as well as Austrian Government. Diminished Austrian trade with
                            East and simultaneous difficulties finding West markets in country
                            heavily dependent upon international trade is subject of continued
                            Communist press attacks but also of thoughtful analyses in non-Communist
                            press. While Austrian Government cooperation on East-West controls has
                            been remarkably good in past, I believe simplification and reduction in
                            number of items subject to quantitative control essential for the
                            accomplishment of basic objectives of program.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Closely related to growing resentment at overly rigid and broad scope
                            East-West controls is question repeatedly put to us by Austrians as why
                            US simultaneously continues adhere to restrictive import policy that
                            handicaps Austrian ability to earn needed dollars. Reduction in
                            East-West trade has forced Austria to find import supplies and export
                            outlets elsewhere with greatly increased dependence upon dollar area for
                            imports of commodities formerly obtained in East Europe. The problem
                            becomes increasingly acute as <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> dollar
                            grants to Austria diminish. US is criticized for advocating and even
                            pressing Europeans for liberalization of trade while not practicing that
                            philosophy itself.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>While factors listed have caused us serious preoccupation, basic confidence in US
                    democracy and leadership is intact, Austria would be one of last countries in
                    Europe to be deceived by Soviet tactics and while Soviet peace offensive has
                    doubtless caused much soul searching and while they will understandably endeavor
                    to exploit situation to their advantage, net effect in my opinion has <pb
                        facs="0677" n="1877" xml:id="pg_1877"/> been to increase Austrian
                    determination remain firmly attached to West.</p>
                <p>I have received categoric assurances to this effect from President
                        <persName>Koerner</persName> as well as the Chancellor and Vice
                    Chancellor.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Thompson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
