<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 894Memorandum of Discussion at the 166th Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Tuesday, October 13, 1953</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v07p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d894</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">894</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States policy</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="894"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d894">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_EGADD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_EGADD1">Eisenhower</persName> papers,
                        <persName>Whitman</persName> file</note>
                <head>No. 894<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Discussion at the 166th Meeting of the National
                        Security Council, Tuesday, October 13, 1953</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d894fn1">Drafted on Oct. 14.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>eyes only</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-10-13">October 13,
                            1953</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Present at the 166th meeting of the Council were: The President of the United
                    States, presiding; the Secretary of State; the Secretary of Defense; the
                    Director, Foreign Operations Administration; the Director, Office of Defense
                    Mobilization. Also present were the Secretary of the Treasury; the Attorney
                    General (for Item 3); the Director, Bureau of the Budget; the Chairman, Atomic
                    Energy Commission (for Item 3); the Secretaries of the Navy and the Air Force
                    (for Item 3); the Deputy Secretary of Defense, Assistant Secretary <pb
                        facs="0710" n="1910" xml:id="pg_1910"/> of Defense
                        <persName>McNeil</persName>, and <persName>Francis J. McCarthy</persName>,
                    of the Atomic Energy Commission (for Item 3); the Chairman, Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff; General <persName corresp="#p_RGAMB1">Ridgway</persName>, Admiral Carney,
                    General <persName corresp="#p_TLGNF1">Twining</persName>, and Lt. Gen.
                        <persName>Thomas</persName>, USMC (for Item 3); the Director of Central
                    Intelligence; the Assistant to the President (for Item 3); the Deputy Assistant
                    to the President; <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Robert Cutler</persName>, Special
                    Assistant to the President; <persName>James C. Hagerty</persName>, Secretary to
                    the President (for Item 3); Brig. Gen. <persName>Paul T. Carroll</persName>,
                    Acting White House Staff Secretary; the Executive Secretary, <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>; and the Deputy Executive Secretary, <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>There follows a summary of the discussion at the meeting and the chief points
                    taken.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of items 1–4, the concept of the National Security
                    Council and its advisory and subordinate groups, significant world developments
                    affecting United States security, fiscal year 1955 budget considerations, and
                    United States policy toward Germany. Following the discussion of these agenda
                    items, the President, the Attorney General, and the Chairman of the Atomic
                    Energy Commission left the meeting.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">5. U.S. Objectives and Policies With Respect to Austria</hi>
                        (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164;<note n="2" xml:id="d894fn2">Not
                        printed, but see the amendments under paragraph b. below and <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164/1, <ref target="#d895">
                            <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> Memo for <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> from Executive
                    Secretary, same subject, dated October 12, 1953<note n="3" xml:id="d894fn3">Not
                        printed. This was the covering memorandum attached to <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164 indicating that it would be considered
                        by the Council at its meeting on Oct. 13. (<gloss target="#t_SS1"
                            >S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files, lot 63 D 351,
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164 Series)</note>)</p>
                <p>In presenting the background of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164, Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> called attention to the
                    principal differences between the Departments of State and Defense with regard
                    to U.S. policy on Austria. The first of these, in paragraph 16–d, related to the
                    degree of neutralization of Austria which would be acceptable to the United
                    States. The second concerned the wisdom of accepting Article 35 of the long
                    draft treaty concerning Soviet assets in Austria.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> stated that it was his
                    view that while we should of course oppose the neutralization of Austria just as
                    far as possible in any negotiations, the decision in the long run would depend
                    on the Austrians themselves. If, in order to induce the Russians to get out of
                    Austria, the Austrian Government refused to align itself with <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, there was very little, said Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, that the United States could
                    do about it, even though we should refuse to sign the treaty. We can, of course,
                    explain our position to the Austrians, but we could not impose our will upon
                    them, nor could we carry the British and French along if they agreed with the
                    Austrian <pb facs="0711" n="1911" xml:id="pg_1911"/> viewpoint. In any case, an
                    embittered Austria would never prove a reliable ally of the United States.</p>
                <p>In response, Admiral <persName>Radford</persName> said that the Joint Chiefs
                    realized the validity of Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                    >Dulles</persName>’ points, but they insisted that a neutralized Austria would
                    greatly weaken us in Europe.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> then proposed certain
                    changes in the language of paragraph 16 which he thought might make this
                    statement less objectionable to the Joint Chiefs. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1"
                        >Cutler</persName> suggested further revisions in order to achieve
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>Admiral <persName>Radford</persName> stated, however, that these changes were not
                    sufficient to meet the anxiety of the Joint Chiefs about the proposal ultimately
                    to accept a neutralized Austria.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> replied that while he
                    recognized the force of the statement in the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                    comment which Admiral <persName>Radford</persName> had read, it remained true
                    that Austria was in the last analysis master of its own destiny. We had never
                    had any legal control over the Austrian Government, and since our economic aid
                    was about to be terminated, we would shortly be unable to use that as a means of
                    influencing the Austrian Government.</p>
                <p>Admiral <persName>Radford</persName> said that he was not only concerned about a
                    neutralized Austria, but even more worried that we might face a similar
                    situation in Germany itself. A neutralized Germany would be much more
                    serious.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> replied that indeed it
                    would, but that in Germany, at least, we still had a measure of sovereignty and
                    certain legal controls. Accordingly, Germany was easier to manage than Austria.
                    To sum up his position, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                    said that the State Department simply did not wish us to get into a situation
                    where we are opposing something that is inevitable.</p>
                <p>Admiral <persName>Radford</persName> recommended that the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                    undertake a study of the results if the inevitable happened.</p>
                <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> observed that to his mind
                    the status of neutralization did not necessarily imply disarmament. What we want
                    to avoid above all else, especially in Germany, is the combination of
                    neutralization with disarmament. It was for this reason that he has been so
                    anxious to see the German units come into existence.</p>
                <p>After the Council had agreed to accept the views of the Secretary of State on the
                    neutralization issue, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> turned to
                    the question of Article 35, and pointed out that on this issue, likewise, the
                    Joint Chiefs were very concerned.</p>
                <p>After Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> had explained the
                    content of Article 35, Admiral <persName>Radford</persName> read the comments of
                    the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> on this issue, pointing out that the
                    matter was so serious that we should all take a stand on insisting that the
                    article be eliminated or revised. Even <pb facs="0712" n="1912" xml:id="pg_1912"
                    /> the Austrians, he thought, should be willing to take a stand on this.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> corrected Admiral
                        <persName>Radford</persName>, and explained that the Austrians were already
                    engaged in under-the-table conversations with the Russians which would accept
                    the latters’ position on Article 35. As in the case of the neutralization
                    problem, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> said that we
                    could not let this one stand in the way of final agreement on an Austrian
                    treaty, though here too he was prepared to fight to the last ditch for revision
                    of the article.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> pointed out the previous Council
                    decision in favor of the point of view taken by Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, who thereafter recommended that the
                    Council now adhere to its previous decision.</p>
                <p>Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName> said that what he was
                    most afraid of was complete Soviet control of Austria if (1) Austria were
                    disarmed, and (2) if Austria were put at the economic mercy of the USSR by
                    virtue of accepting Article 35 of the long draft treaty.</p>
                <p>Expressing agreement with Governor <persName corresp="#p_SHE1"
                    >Stassen</persName>, Admiral <persName>Radford</persName> insisted that Austria
                    would not in fact be really neutralized if the Soviets secured the rights
                    accorded them under Article 35. This would enable them to stay in Austria and
                    ultimately to subvert it.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> answered that although
                    they have much greater power now than they would after a treaty, the Soviets had
                    not yet succeeded in subverting Austria. Indeed, there was no country in the
                    world with less indigenous Communist strength. The issue with respect to Article
                    35, he continued, was much the same as the neutralization issue. We would end by
                    making an enemy of Austria if we insisted on revising Article 35 and thus
                    prevented the achievement of a treaty. Communist influence would certainly then
                    increase in Austria, and it would be best for the Council to reiterate its
                    previous stand.</p>
                <p>Admiral <persName>Radford</persName> then said that the Joint Chiefs would
                    reappraise the effect of accepting Article 35, and would bring before the
                    Council any significant conclusions they reached.</p>
                <p>The discussion then turned to various other suggested revisions of the paper by
                    the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and agreement was reached on each of these
                    points.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Cutler</persName> also called the attention of the
                    Council to the Financial Appendix, and pointed out that the estimated costs
                    therein would increase if we transferred our forces now in Trieste to
                    Austria.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_RGAMB1">Ridgway</persName> commented that the Joint
                    Chiefs were now in the process of examining the courses of military action open
                    to us in Trieste, but were not yet ready to state what they were.</p>
                <pb facs="0713" n="1913" xml:id="pg_1913"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>a. Discussed the reference report on the subject in the light of the views of the
                    Joint Chiefs of Staff contained in the enclosure to the reference
                    memorandum.</p>
                <p>b. Adopted the statement of policy contained in <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 164, subject to the following amendments:</p>
                <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Page 9, paragraph 16–d, first sentence:</hi> Delete
                    “particularly as a possible precedent for a German settlement.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Third sentence:</hi> Revise to read as follows: “Nevertheless,
                    the United States should refuse to sign a treaty which would preclude Austria’s
                    association with the economic community of Western Europe, which would prejudice
                    Austria’s capacity to preserve internal order, or which would restrict the
                    Western Powers in giving aid to Austria in the establishment of adequate
                    internal security forces.”</p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Page 13, paragraph 17-h:</hi> Delete the word
                    “interim”.</p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">Page 13, paragraph 19:</hi> In the first sentence, change
                    the word “concerning” to “supporting”; delete the second sentence.</p>
                <p>(4) <hi rend="italic">Page 13:</hi> Add a new paragraph 20 to read as follows:
                    “20. Seek to obtain, in addition to the tripartite declaration, an Austrian
                    commitment to raise and maintain forces adequate for the internal security and
                    integrity of the Austrian state and the acceptance of Western assistance in the
                    formation of these forces.”</p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                <p>(6) <hi rend="italic">Page 14, Annex to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164,
                        subparagraph a:</hi> Delete the words “under the command of the Commanding
                    General of the United States Forces”.</p>
                <p>(7) <hi rend="italic">Page 15, Annex to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164,
                        paragraph h:</hi> Delete the first, second and fourth sentences and, in the
                    last sentence, change the word “You” to “U.S. authorities”.</p>
                <p>c. Noted that the Joint Chiefs of Staff would study the military implications of
                    the degree of neutralization of Austria which might ultimately be accepted by
                    the United States under paragraph 16–d of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    164, and would report back to the Council if, in their opinion, reconsideration
                    of this subparagraph was necessary.<note n="4" xml:id="d894fn4">See <ref
                            target="#d904">Document 904</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164 as amended, and approved by the
                    President, subquently issued as <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 164/1 and
                    referred to <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> as the coordinating agency. The
                    action in c above subsequently transmitted to the Secretary of Defense for
                    reference to the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</p>
                <p>[Here follows a notation indicating that the Council noted the proposed amendment
                    of Executive Order 10450 submitted by the Attorney General.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
