<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 944The Secretary of State to the Embassy in France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v07p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d944</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">944</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-11-30T20:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-11-30T20:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-30T20:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-30T20:15:00-05:00" n="944"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d944">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">663.001/11–3054: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 944<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d944fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MLT1"
                            >Merchant</persName> and cleared in substance by Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>. Repeated for action to London and
                        for information to Vienna, Bonn, and Moscow.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-11-30T20:15:00-05:00"
                            >November 30, 1954—8:15 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1996. <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> called on Secretary Nov
                        30<note n="2" xml:id="d944fn2">A brief memorandum of this conversation is in
                        file 663.001/11–3054.</note> expressing London’s concern reported in
                    London’s 2459<note n="3" xml:id="d944fn3">Apparently an incorrect citation.
                        Telegram 2459 from London does not concern the subject under
                        discussion.</note> over project unilateral French approach in Moscow on
                    Austria. Such concern gains support from Mendes’ conversation with <persName
                        corresp="#p_JSHMG1">Jebb</persName> reported Paris’ 2264.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d944fn4">Telegram 2264 summarized
                        <persName>Mendès-France</persName>’s conversation with <persName
                            corresp="#p_JSHMG1">Jebb</persName> on Nov. 29 as described by British
                        Embassy officials that same afternoon. It reported
                            <persName>Mendès-France</persName>’s statement that U.S. officials had
                        suggested “diplomatic channels” as the best means for any discussion of his
                        proposal but that he had not liked this idea and preferred the medium of the
                        Ambassadors at Vienna and therefore wished a <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi>
                        to this effect at Moscow. (663.001/11–3054)</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> suggested and Secretary agreed to
                    holding tripartite consultation in London Dec 1 or 2 to concert tripartitely
                    French follow-up if any in Moscow. We are opposed to quadripartite conference
                    ambassadors in Vienna which would almost surely become involved discussion
                    substance treaty. This was proposal we rejected at Berlin Conference.</p>
                <p>Upon reflection we are opposed to unilateral French approach in Moscow on this
                    matter and you should make every effort dissuade French from such action.
                    Tactically it seems poor since subject to misinterpretation by Soviets. Moreover
                    we consider it important to maintain solid tripartite front as in past on
                    Austria in dealing with Soviets. Unilateral approach re Austria would also have
                    undesirable implications with respect to Germany.<note n="5" xml:id="d944fn5">In
                        telegram 2288 from Paris, Dec. 1, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                            >Dillon</persName> reported that the French Foreign Ministry had been
                        informed of the Department of State’s views as requested in this telegram.
                        (663.001/12–154)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
