<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-10-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="25" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d25">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">611.4231/1318</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Counselor of Legation in
                                    Canada</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Boal</hi>)<note n="19" xml:id="d25fn19">Transmitted to the Department by the Minister
                                    in Canada in his despatch No. 214, November 8; received November
                                    12.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ottawa</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-10-31">October 31, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>At the Minister’s request I called today upon Dr. Skelton, and after
                                discussing one or two other matters turned the conversation to the
                                recent talks which had taken place between Mr. Armour and the Prime
                                Minister, in particular to the latter’s projected visit to
                                Washington and to his suggestion that some announcement regarding
                                Canadian-American relations be made on Armistice Day.<note n="20" xml:id="d25fn20">The Canadian Prime Minister arrived in
                                    Washington, November 7, 1935. For text of joint statement dated
                                    November 9, 1935, by the President of the United States and the
                                    Canadian Prime Minister, see Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Press Releases</hi>, November 9, 1935, p.
                                    366.</note> I asked Dr. Skelton in this connection if he
                                understood, as we did, that the trade agreement negotiations had
                                remained exactly in the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> existing
                                before the elections. Dr. Skelton said that he did so understand and
                                that while a good deal of progress had been made up to that time
                                they were still, in his view, a considerable distance from an
                                agreement, particularly because of the five principal products on
                                which we apparently could not make the concessions the Canadians
                                wanted (cod, lumber other than Douglas fir, cream, seed potatoes and
                                live cattle). Dr. Skelton did not enumerate these as the products,
                                but merely mentioned the “five products”. He said that in his own
                                personal view, whatever might be the view of Mr. King at the moment,
                                he thought that an agreement which did not cover these would be so
                                narrow as not to be worth concluding. However, he emphasized that
                                that was merely his own personal opinion.</p>
                            <p>I said that the Minister felt that he wanted to obviate any
                                possibility of any misunderstanding, although he thought that he had
                                been quite clear on the subject, that of course the pleasure of the
                                President and of the Secretary, the Under Secretary and other
                                officials of the Department at having Mr. King come to Washington
                                should not be interpreted as in any way affecting the present status
                                of the negotiations which, as we understood it, would have to be
                                taken up on their own merits. In other words, there was really no
                                more assurance of the likelihood of the conclusion of an agreement
                                at the time Mr. King came to Washington than there had been before,
                                and if it should develop that an agreement couldn’t be reached at
                                that time certainly <pb facs="0107" n="31" xml:id="pg_31"/> he hoped
                                the Prime Minister would not feel he had been put in an awkward
                                position because an agreement had not been provided for him to bring
                                back with him.</p>
                            <p>I remarked that the Prime Minister, in talking with the Minister,
                                said that he had wanted to go to Washington if it seemed likely that
                                an agreement could be reached, and that one of his purposes in going
                                there was to further the conclusion of such an agreement. I said
                                that these two thoughts might not fit very well together, as
                                certainly no assurances could be given now that an agreement would
                                be reached, and therefore Mr. King, in making the trip, would be
                                taking something of a chance if he felt that not to reach an
                                agreement while he was there would leave him in a difficult
                                position.</p>
                            <p>Dr. Skelton said that he had expressed exactly the same view to the
                                Prime Minister and would do so again, but he thought that the Prime
                                Minister fully understood that the suggestion of the visit had not
                                made any change in the status of the negotiations.</p>
                            <p>I then referred to the enclosed clipping<note n="21" xml:id="d25fn21">Not reprinted.</note> on the embargo question and said quite
                                personally that I supposed this subject might be one which it would
                                be useful to discuss informally before any statements were made on
                                one side or the other if Canada were to embargo nickel and other
                                exports to Italy. Dr. Skelton said he felt that that was his view,
                                that this subject might indeed be usefully discussed. I then said
                                that if matters did so develop that it seemed desirable to present
                                some kind of a picture of Canadian-American relations at the time of
                                the Prime Minister’s visit to Washington, there were some pending
                                matters which might conceivably be useful to include in that
                                discussion to broaden the picture. There was, for instance, an
                                extradition treaty in negotiation, and I understand that at the
                                moment consideration was being given it primarily in Ottawa. Dr.
                                Skelton said that this was correct, but that he did not know whether
                                they were close enough to final adjustment to permit of conclusion
                                of this treaty by the time of the visit. However, he made note to
                                look into it with either conclusion or an announcement in mind.</p>
                            <p>I mentioned also the possibility, which we have discussed before, of
                                a treaty of consular rights. He said at once that he thought it
                                would be advisable to await the appointment of consuls for Canada in
                                the United States before dealing with this subject, and that
                                therefore it would not be possible to conclude a treaty very
                                rapidly. I said I did not have in mind the conclusion of a treaty at
                                this moment, but thought that perhaps it might be useful to be able
                                to announce an intention or a hope in this regard at the time of the
                                visit. He immediately said that that seemed to him a good suggestion
                                and that he would talk it over. I said that no doubt other subjects
                                would suggest themselves to him as he considered the matter.</p>
                            <pb facs="0108" n="32" xml:id="pg_32"/>
                            <p>Dr. Skelton said that they hoped to get the experts down to
                                Washington on Monday or Tuesday, that in the meantime Mr. Euler,
                                Minister of Trade and Commerce, and Mr. Dunning were working on the
                                question with the Prime Minister and with Mr. Wilgress and Mr.
                                McKinnon.</p>
                            <p>Later I saw Mr. Wilgress who confirmed that they were working
                                intensively on the questions, that the Prime Minister, while not yet
                                fully informed regarding details, was now acquainted with the broad
                                lines of the negotiations. He added that he and Mr. McKinnon expect
                                to leave Saturday for Washington so that they might be on hand to
                                begin work there Monday morning, November 4th. He also said that
                                there was a delegation representing the lumber interests in town who
                                were urging that lumber, especially Douglas fir, have a place in the
                                agreement and were at the same time presenting their objections to
                                any lowering of Canadian duties on doors. He remarked that one of
                                the problems which remained to be solved in connection with the
                                agreement was that of shingles.</p>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>[For text of the reciprocal trade agreement between the United
                                    States and Canada, signed November 15, 1935, and related notes,
                                    signed November 15, 1935, see Department of State Executive
                                    Agreement Series No. 91 or 49 Stat. 3960. For other documents
                                    issued at the time of the signature of the agreement or
                                    immediately thereafter, see Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Press Releases</hi>, November 16, 1935, pages
                                    379–381; December 7, 1935, pages 477–486; and December 14, 1935,
                                    pages 526–534.]</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>