<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-03-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-03-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="253" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d253">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">862.20/824</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of
                                    Western European Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-03-25">March 25,
                                    1935</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Dr. Leitner<note n="63" xml:id="d253fn63">Rudolf Leitner, Counselor
                                    of the German Embassy.</note> asked me to lunch with him today
                                and naturally brought up the subject of Germany’s recently announced
                                intention to re-establish conscription, to create armed air force,
                                et cetera. He said that as he diagnosed it, this move was an answer
                                    (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) to recent increases by France and
                                Britain of the military establishments, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) to the reproaches which had been leveled against
                                Germany for the past year that she was rearming in spite of the
                                treaty. Leitner pointed out (somewhat inexactly) that what Germany
                                was doing followed in large measure the tenor of her note of March
                                    1934.<note n="64" xml:id="d253fn64">See British Cmd. 4559
                                    (1934): <hi rend="italic">Further Memoranda on Disarmament,
                                        February 14 to April 17, 1934</hi>, p. 7.</note> This note,
                                he said, had never been controverted by either the British or the
                                Italians, which he felt gave it a certain moral force.</p>
                            <p>Dr. Leitner then reverted to the usual German thesis and said that
                                Germany could not remain disarmed while all her neighbors were
                                heavily armed. I asked whether Germany felt that any of her
                                neighbors had aggressive tendencies. He replied “why else should
                                they be armed?” I told him that I had lived enough in Europe to know
                                that there was real fear of Germany’s intentions to expand or at
                                least to alter the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi>. He answered
                                that there was no official pronouncement to that effect on record. I
                                told him that the failure of the German Government to accept the
                                Eastern Frontiers or the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in
                                Austria, coupled with some of the chapters in Hitler’s book <hi rend="italic">Mein Kampf</hi>, had been responsible for this
                                feeling. <pb facs="0391" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> It was not my
                                business to argue with him the rights or the wrongs of Germany’s
                                action but I wished I could feel that it would ease the situation
                                rather than make it more complicated. Dr. Leitner replied that he
                                could not see it in that light and felt that it would certainly ease
                                the situation. As far as Austria was concerned, Germany considered
                                it an internal problem and he remarked that if a group within
                                Austria should develop the same philosophy as Germany’s, it should
                                concern nobody but Austria and Germany.</p>
                            <p>Dr. Leitner again complained of the American press which he felt was
                                far from objective. He thought that the Associated Press despatches
                                were fair as well as one or two papers such as the <hi rend="italic">Christian Science Monitor</hi>. On the whole, he felt that the
                                American press was biased and gave the anti-German point of view
                                whenever possible.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Pierrepont
                                Moffat</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>