<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-03-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-03-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="27" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d27">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.4215 Air Pollution/600</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in Canada</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Robbins</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1151</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ottawa</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-03-21">March 21, 1935</date>.<lb/>[Received March
                                    25.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of the Department’s telegraphic instruction No. 20 of March
                                20, 6 p.m.,<note n="25" xml:id="d27fn25">Not printed.</note>
                                authorizing me to sign on behalf of the United States a convention
                                dealing with the Trail Smelter problem and conforming to the draft
                                transmitted as an enclosure to a note dated December 31, 1934, from
                                the Canadian Secretary of State for External Affairs, copies of
                                which were forwarded to the Department with my despatch No. 989 of
                                January 1, 1935.<note n="26" xml:id="d27fn26">Despatch not
                                    printed.</note></p>
                            <p>I am enclosing, for the Department’s information, copy of the note
                                which I have today addressed to the Secretary of State for External
                                Affairs on this subject.<note n="25" xml:id="d27fn27">Not
                                    printed.</note></p>
                            <p>I may add for the Department’s information that prior to the delivery
                                of my note, Dr. O. D. Skelton, Under-Secretary of State for External
                                Affairs, was informally notified of the Department’s acceptance of
                                the draft submitted, including the verbal changes indicated in
                                Article 3. Dr. Skelton expressed great satisfaction that the two
                                Governments have at last been able to reach an agreement on this
                                question. Upon being asked whether he could give an informal
                                indication as to a possible date for signing the convention, Dr.
                                Skelton stated that it depended largely upon the health of the Prime
                                Minister. If the latter is unable to sign on behalf of Canada, this
                                task will probably fall to the Acting Prime Minister, Sir George
                                Perley. Dr. Skelton promised to look into the matter at once and to
                                notify me as soon as possible.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Warren</hi> D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Robbins</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>