<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-10-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-10-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="320" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d320">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">548.D1/251</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Bingham</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 979</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-10-03">October 3, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has received the
                                Embassy’s despatch No. 1616 of August 6, 1935,<note n="78" xml:id="d320fn78">Not printed.</note> with its enclosure, a
                                communication dated August 3, 1935,<note n="78" xml:id="d320fn81">Not printed.</note> addressed to the Secretary of State by the
                                Secretary General of the High Commission for Refugees (Jewish and
                                Other) coming from Germany, in which information was requested
                                concerning the documentation of refugees, their permits to work in
                                the countries to which they proceed, and other related
                                questions.</p>
                            <p>You are requested to transmit to the Secretary General the attached
                                memorandum, which has been prepared by the Visa Division of the
                                Department.</p>
                            <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                            <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William Phillips</hi></signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                            State</gloss> to the Secretary General of the High
                                        Commission for Refugees</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Jewish and Other</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">Coming From Germany</hi> (<persName><hi rend="italic">Wurfbain</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <p>The Secretary of State of the United States of America refers to
                                    the note of August 3, 1935,<note n="78" xml:id="d320fn82">Not
                                        printed.</note> transmitting three Resolutions adopted at
                                    the Fourth Session of the Governing Body of the High Commission
                                    for Refugees (Jewish and Other) coming from Germany, held at
                                    London on July 17, 1935, concerning the documentation of
                                    refugees, their permits to work in the countries to which they
                                    proceed, and other related questions.</p>
                                <p>With regard to Resolution No. 1, concerning passports and visas,
                                    it may be stated that in the case of refugees who are outside
                                    the country to which they owe allegiance, American consular
                                    officers are authorized to accept a substitute travel document,
                                    such as a Nansen certificate, or even an affidavit executed by
                                    the alien himself, if for any reason a valid passport or
                                    document in the nature of a passport can not be obtained. With
                                    regard, however, to refugees who are still residing in the
                                    country to which they owe allegiance, that is, if an alien is in
                                    his own country and if travel documents are required for exit,
                                    the consular officer could not waive the passport requirements,
                                    but would have to inform the alien that he should obtain
                                    permission from his government to leave the country.</p>
                                <pb facs="0501" n="425" xml:id="pg_425"/>
                                <p>Although the documents mentioned above would be acceptable for
                                    entry into the United States, it may be observed, with respect
                                    to Resolution No. 1, that there is no provision under the law
                                    for the issuance by United States authorities of documents of
                                    identity and travel to aliens. Aliens, however, whether refugees
                                    or not, who have been admitted into the United States for
                                    permanent residence, may receive from the Department of Labor
                                    reentry permits which are sufficient for return to the United
                                    States without a passport or other travel document. These
                                    reentry permits, for which a fee of $3.00 is charged, are valid
                                    for one year in the first instance, and their validity may be
                                    extended for further periods of six months on adequate
                                    cause.</p>
                                <p>All aliens, whether refugees or not, are required by the
                                    Immigration Act of 1924<note n="79" xml:id="d320fn79">43 Stat.
                                        153.</note> to pay a fee of $10.00 for an immigration visa
                                    and application therefor. Aliens coming on temporary visits to
                                    the United States, who are nationals of countries with which
                                    agreements have been concluded for the waiver or reduction of
                                    passport visa fees either are exempted from the payment of the
                                    usual $10.00 passport visa fee or such fee has been reduced on a
                                    reciprocal basis. Nationals of other countries are required by
                                    law to pay the usual $10.00 fee for passport visas obtained for
                                    the purpose of visiting the United States temporarily. The
                                    Government of the United States has invited the governments of
                                    all foreign governments to enter into bilateral agreements for
                                    the waiver or reduction of passport visa fees.</p>
                                <p>As regards Resolution No. 2, concerning permits to work, it may
                                    be stated that aliens with or without nationality, whether
                                    refugees or not, who are able to qualify under the immigration
                                    laws of the United States and who are admitted for permanent
                                    residence, are not prohibited from accepting employment. It
                                    would be difficult, however, under present circumstances for
                                    aliens to find work in the United States. Moreover, aliens
                                    coming to the United States for prearranged employment would be
                                    subject to the contract labor provisions of the Immigration Act
                                    of 1917<note n="80" xml:id="d320fn80">39 Stat. 874.</note> which
                                    provides generally that, with certain stated, exceptions, aliens
                                    are excluded from entry into the United States if they are
                                    induced, assisted, encouraged, or solicited to migrate to the
                                    United States by offers or promises of employment. The Secretary
                                    of Labor has authority to waive the contract labor clause, upon
                                    suitable application by the importing person or firm, in the
                                    case of skilled labor where labor of like kind unemployed can
                                    not be found in the United States.</p>
                                <p>With reference to Resolution No. 3, concerning the expulsion of
                                    refugees, it may be stated that the practice of the Department
                                    of Labor is that deportation orders against aliens who are found
                                    to be in the United States in contravention of its laws are
                                    carried into <pb facs="0502" n="426" xml:id="pg_426"/> effect
                                    only if the consent of the government of another country to
                                    receive such aliens has been obtained in advance.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>