<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="35" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">842.801/126</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Secretary of Commerce</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Roper</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-06">May 6, 1935</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: The Department has
                                given consideration to your letter of March 9, 1935,<note n="46" xml:id="d35fn46">Not printed.</note> your reference WE:
                                842.801/120, regarding the possibility of entering into an agreement
                                with Canada whereby on the Great Lakes and St. Lawrence River
                                Canadian vessels may transport goods for export between ports and
                                places in the United States, American vessels to have the same
                                privilege as regards Canadian ports.</p>
                            <p>The proposal does not meet with the approval of this Department. The
                                effect of the section 663 (1) of the Canadian Shipping Act will be
                                felt by American ship owners and grain elevators only to the extent
                                that Canadian grain is shipped to Buffalo for the purpose of later
                                reshipment to Canadian points—principally Montreal. It has been
                                found that the movement from Buffalo to Montreal has decreased
                                markedly in the past year and that the size of this movement has no
                                perceptible relation to the movement of Canadian grain into Buffalo.
                                Further, because of other factors such as the imperial preference on
                                Canadian wheat exported to the United Kingdom and extended use of
                                the Welland Canal, Buffalo has lost considerable importance as one
                                of the principal transshipment points for Canadian grain destined to
                                Canadian ports. However, there is good reason to believe that
                                Buffalo will retain its position as a transshipment point for
                                Canadian grain principally for export through United States North
                                Atlantic ports. If such is the case, neither the American vessels
                                carrying Canadian grain to Buffalo nor the elevators at Buffalo in
                                which said grain is stored will suffer to a serious degree from the
                                Canadian Act.</p>
                            <p>The relaxation of the coastwise laws of the United States is viewed
                                as a dangerous precedent coming at a time when such pressure is
                                being <pb facs="0123" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/> exerted for a similar
                                purpose as respects other aspects of our coastwise restrictions.
                                Should the Great Lakes trade change so that a large amount of
                                American goods would move for export, American vessels, because of
                                much larger operating costs, would be unable to meet the competition
                                of Canadian carriers. The concessions which such a relaxation would
                                procure for citizens of the United States seem illusory and
                                incommensurate with the potential danger to our coastwise trade
                                which such a step entails.</p>
                            <p>For your further information a memorandum submitted by the Director
                                of the United States Shipping Board Bureau, this Department, is
                                    enclosed.<note n="47" xml:id="d35fn47">Not printed.</note> If
                                this Department may be of any assistance in the matter, you are
                                assured of its cooperation.</p>
                            <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Daniel</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Roper</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>