<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d368</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">368</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="368"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d368">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.015311/26</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-09-07">September 7,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The German Ambassador came in and said that it was his duty to make earnest
                    complaint about the violent and offensive utterances of a New York City
                        judge<note n="47" xml:id="d368fn47">Judge Louis Brodsky.</note> relative to
                    the German flag, and to request this Government in suitable language to deal
                    with that situation in accordance with the comity existing between nations. The
                    Ambassador reiterated the very offensive and serious nature of the utterances of
                    this judge and the importance to satisfactory relations between our two
                    Governments of utterances by this Government showing more concern than
                    heretofore in similar circumstances.</p>
                <p>I replied that it was, of course, very unfortunate for these publications to
                    occur, such as the one he referred to, whatever might be the actual facts; that,
                    of course, I had not had a chance to assemble officially the full and accurate
                    facts of the reported occurrence, but that I would be glad to proceed at once to
                    do so through the Governor of New York; that counties and municipalities and
                    their officials were, of course, creatures of the state and I could only seek
                    through the Governor the full and official facts pertaining to the incident. I
                    said that, of course, we had many millions of Catholics and many millions of
                    Jews in this country, together with their friendly and other relationships
                    extending into still other millions; that we had all races here, including many
                    violent and ultra-radical persons, entertaining every shade of social,
                    political, religious, and other views; that they thrived on controversy and
                    newspaper notoriety and desired above all else to figure in international
                    controversy and in <pb facs="0564" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/> great headlines in
                    the press growing out of such controversy, and that the problem was how to deal
                    with these large numbers of violent, extreme, controversial persons, thus
                    seeking publicity and strife, without increasing such utterances and actions
                    rather than quieting and decreasing them. I further stated that these persons
                    relish bitter exchanges of epithets and denunciations back and forth and,
                    therefore, it was a problem as to how to deal most effectively with a given
                    case, for this and the additional reason that when one such person so offending
                    was given a castigation by the Government, probably fifty others of similar mind
                    and disposition proceeded at once to find ways also to give offense and to get
                    their names in the press conspicuously in connection with international
                    exchanges with reference thereto, I then very earnestly said to the Ambassador
                    that without reference to their truth or falsity the awful news reports coming
                    out of his country about racial and other conditions and controversies were the
                    basis on which these violent utterances, such as he was now complaining of in
                    this country, were inspired and that it was absolutely necessary, if the seat of
                    the trouble was to be dealt with, that those reports be diminished or
                    discontinued. I then emphasized the view that I would be so gratified if some
                    cooperative efforts thus dealing with the fundamentals of the situation could be
                    brought about, adding that myself and the German Ambassador would be worried
                    half to distraction by a chronic state of incidents such as the one he now
                    complained of, unless some cessation of these inflammable reports coming out of
                    his country could be accomplished. I said that we had talked this phase over
                    more than once in the past, but that I could only keep this view alive in the
                    hope that it might be carried into effect to a more or less extent. The
                    Ambassador parried this statement and view by making some reference to the
                    interference by one country with the internal affairs of another, to which I
                    replied that, of course, I was not raising that question in any sense but was
                    only making a concrete statement to the effect that so long as these combustible
                    reports came out of his country we were liable to have a succession of just such
                    unfortunate incidents as the one he was now complaining about.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then said that he was especially concerned about this Government
                    showing more concern and more feelings in the nature of regret than it had
                    shown. I again emphasized to him the unusual type of persons we were dealing
                    with and that I must first secure the official facts and study them with the
                    view to carefully approaching and dealing with the problem presented so as not
                    to inflame and aggravate this type of violent-minded person which existed in
                    large numbers in our big cities, so that we would have numerous repetitions of
                    such utterances as he now complained of.</p>
                <pb facs="0565" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/>
                <p>The Ambassador urged me to say something rather definite now, which I inferred
                    meant to express regret, even reminding me that this Government expressed regret
                    to Japan about the publication of a cartoon.<note n="48" xml:id="d368fn48">See
                        memorandum by the Secretary of State, August 5, 1935, <ref
                            target="frus1935v03#pg_863">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p.
                            863</ref>.</note> I reminded him that I had expressed regret that Japan
                    felt constrained to take exception to the matter, or words to that effect. He
                    then inquired what he should say to the press, seeking still further to draw
                    from me some expression of regret right now. I gave him no satisfaction and he
                    then said he would say nothing to the press. I finally repeated that I would
                    give the matter attention just as soon as the official facts could be
                    assembled.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
