<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Poland ( (Nielsen) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d519</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">519</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="519"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d519">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">660C.116/174</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Poland</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Nielsen</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 750</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Warsaw</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-07-01">July 1,
                            1935</date>.<lb/>[Received July 16.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the Embassy’s despatch No. 726,
                    June 5, 1935, and to previous correspondence with regard to the treatment
                    accorded in Poland to American trade, I have the honor to report that, having in
                    mind the desire expressed in the penultimate paragraph of instruction No. 185,
                    May 12, 1935, that the Embassy endeavor to arrange discussions on this subject
                    with officials of the Ministry of Industry and Commerce, the Embassy last week
                    communicated with the secretary to Mr. Franciszek Doleżal, Under Secretary of
                    State in that Ministry, and informed him that in the event that the
                    Undersecretary should desire to discuss with me our note to the Foreign Office
                    No. 173, June 5, 1935, I would be glad to call on him at any time at his
                    convenience. An appointment thereupon was arranged for July 1.</p>
                <p>Mr. Doleżal’s secretary was approached by the Embassy with the knowledge and
                    approval of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, and after Mr. Wiktor Podoski, Chief
                    of the Anglo-Saxon Section of that Ministry, had stated that in his opinion the
                    Embassy would be well advised to discuss the trade situation with none of the
                    “smaller fry” in the Ministry of Industry and Commerce. Mr. Podoski suggested
                    that either the Undersecretary or the Minister (Mr. Henryk Floyar-Rajchman) be
                    approached by the Embassy.</p>
                <p>A memorandum of the conversation with Mr. Doleżal is enclosed.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Orsen</hi> N. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nielsen</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0725" n="649" xml:id="pg_649"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the American Chargé</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Nielsen</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conversation With the Polish Under
                            Secretary of State in the Ministry of Industry and Commerce</hi> (<hi
                            rend="italic">Doleżal</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Warsaw</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-07-01">July 1,
                                1935</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Within the first few minutes of my conversation with Mr. Doleżal it became
                        quite apparent that his secretary had not informed him that it was the
                        purpose of my visit to discuss any points in our note of June 5, 1935, that
                        he might care to take up with me, and to give him any additional information
                        that he might desire to obtain with respect to the policy of the American
                        Government. Until I stated the purpose of the visit the Undersecretary was
                        under the impression that the Embassy was about to press for a reply to the
                        note under reference, and he explained that because the summer holiday
                        season has greatly reduced the personnel in his Ministry and because a
                        number of his assistants who remain on duty have been engaged in trade
                        negotiations with Germany, Italy, and other countries, the Embassy’s note of
                        June 5 has not as yet received the careful study that the Polish Government
                        desires to give to it. He said that his Government desires to make a well
                        considered and adequate reply to the note and that in the course of a few
                        weeks he contemplated requesting an officer of the Embassy to discuss the
                        matter with him before the drafting of his Government’s reply should take
                        place. I said that I had received no instructions to press for an answer;
                        that the American Government would not desire the Polish Government to reply
                        until the latter had given the matter careful study; and that the Embassy
                        would be prepared any time that might be convenient to the Undersecretary to
                        supply him with further information and to attempt to clarify any points
                        that might require clarification.</p>
                    <p>He thereupon said that he was familiar with the general outline of the trade
                        policy of the Government of the United States and he remarked that at
                        various times at Geneva he had discussed with American representatives
                        clearing agreements and allied subjects.</p>
                    <p>He then went into a general statement of the necessity that confronts the
                        Polish Government to maintain over a long period an excess of exports, or at
                        least to insure that imports are balanced by exports. He spoke of the great
                        volume of raw cotton that Poland buys from the United States and of what an
                        important part these imports of raw cotton play in the adverse balance of
                        Poland’s foreign trade with that country. He remarked that imports of raw
                        cotton are subject to no restrictions and he added that Poland always has
                        been well disposed toward trade with the United States and that he could not
                        admit that there has been in Poland any discrimination against American
                        trade.</p>
                    <pb facs="0726" n="650" xml:id="pg_650"/>
                    <p>To this I remarked that I felt certain that he would not desire to contend
                        that merchandise entering Poland from the United States, a country with
                        which Poland has an excess of imports, is accorded in this country the same
                        treatment that is accorded to merchandise from Great Britain for example, a
                        country with which Poland has an excess of exports. I referred to the
                        compensation export requirement to which certain merchandise of American
                        origin is subject, and I mentioned the fees which are imposed on such
                        merchandise from the United States, although no like fees are imposed on
                        imports from Great Britain. Whereupon he revised his original statement and
                        said that he could not officially admit that any discrimination exists in
                        Poland against imports from the United States.</p>
                    <p>Since Mr. Doleżal did not seem to be entirely familiar with our note of June
                        5, 1935, I took occasion to outline for him in some detail the provisions of
                        the Trade Agreements Act of June 12, 1934; to point out that it is the view
                        of the Government of the United States that a return to world prosperity can
                        best be attained not by a policy of imposing further restrictions upon
                        international trade but by liberalizing or abolishing existing restrictions,
                        and to state that the American Government desires to generalize fully to all
                        countries the tariff reductions that it grants in its bilateral trade
                        agreements, but that extension of these reduced duties to countries which
                        discriminate against American trade may be withheld. I said that one purpose
                        of our note is to ascertain the precise policy of the Polish Government
                        toward trade with the United States, with a view to making it possible for
                        the American Government to determine whether Poland should be assured
                        continued enjoyment of the benefits of duties proclaimed under our trade
                        agreements. I remarked that although the Government of the United States
                        desires to continue to accord to Poland most-favored-nation treatment under
                        the provisions of the treaty of friendship, commerce and consular rights
                        between Poland and the United States, and although Poland is listed in a
                        letter from the President to the Secretary of the Treasury under date of
                        April 1, 1935, among the countries designated as entitled to the application
                        of reduced duties as long as such duties remain in effect and as long as the
                        instructions of the President are not modified, whether, or not my
                        Government would find it possible to continue to list Poland among such
                        countries would largely be determined, in my opinion, by the reply that the
                        Polish Government makes to the note under reference.</p>
                    <p>I stated that the American Government has invited the Polish Government to
                        cooperate at once, or as soon as it is in a position to do so, with the
                        United States and other countries in pursuit of a broad commercial policy
                        calculated to bring about a world-wide increase in international trade. I
                        said that judging by Minister Floyar-Rajchman’s <pb facs="0727" n="651"
                            xml:id="pg_651"/> address at Poznań on April 28, 1935 (despatch No. 725
                            [<hi rend="italic">723</hi>], June 3 [<hi rend="italic">5</hi>],
                            1935<note n="18" xml:id="d519fn18">Not printed.</note>), and by the
                        interview which he granted to the Iskra news agency on June 13, 1935
                        (despatch No. 739, June 18, 1935<note n="18" xml:id="d519fn20">Not
                            printed.</note>), the views of the Polish Government are substantially
                        in accord with those of the American Government. To this Mr. Doleżal replied
                        with a smile that the views of the two Governments are “parallel”.<note
                            n="*" xml:id="d519fn21">I do not take this statement to mean that the
                            Polish Government will necessarily find it possible to accept <hi
                                rend="italic">in practice</hi> our views. [Footnote in the
                            original.]</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>I stressed that the foreign trade policy of the United States is not designed
                        to benefit the United States alone, but to bring benefits to the second
                        party to each trade agreement and to the world at large. As concrete
                        evidence of the benefits that flow from that policy I thereupon quoted from
                        Assistant Secretary Sayre’s address on April 30, 1935,<note n="19"
                            xml:id="d519fn19">Department of State, Commercial Policy Series No. 8,
                                <hi rend="italic">Bargaining America’s Way to Export Markets:</hi>
                            Address by the Honorable Francis B. Sayre, Assistant Secretary of State,
                            Before the Chamber of Commerce of the United States, Washington, April
                            30, 1935 (Washington, Government Printing Office, 1935).</note> before
                        the annual meeting of the Chamber of Commerce of the United States, in which
                        he gave statistics showing that during the first six months of the life of
                        our trade agreement with Cuba, imports into the United States from that
                        country increased from $30,000,000 in the same six-months period of 1933–34
                        to $50,000,000, and that exports from the United States to Cuba increased
                        from $13,000,000 to $27,000,000 in the same periods. I added in connection
                        with the attitude of the American Government toward increased imports into
                        the United States that, as was stated in our note of June 5, it views with
                        favor an increase in imports of Polish merchandise. Mr. Doleżal remarked
                        that he had noticed that Poland’s exports to the United States recently have
                        somewhat increased.</p>
                    <p>At the conclusion of the conversation the Undersecretary said that he expects
                        to remain in Warsaw the entire summer, or at least for the greater part of
                        the summer; that the Ministry would give careful study to our
                        representations at the earliest possible date; and that in the course of
                        three or four weeks he hoped to be able to ask me to call on him again so
                        that further discussion might take place.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
