<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Spain ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d575</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">575</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-05-28T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-05-28T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectaC46Ncpjf3NEb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011129"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Trade balance</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-05-28T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-05-28T06:00:00-05:00" n="575"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d575">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5231/976: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-05-28T11:00:00+00:00"
                            >May 28, 1935—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 4 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>37. My telegram No. 33, May 21, 10 a.m. Following up Ambassador’s interview I
                    have had long conversations with Sub-Secretary and Chief of Overseas Division,
                    Ministry of Foreign Affairs, and dwelt upon situation described in Department’s
                    telegram 28, May 17, noon.</p>
                <p>Aguinaga stated that England and France are both demanding approximation of
                    equalization trade balance with Spain thus demanding just what Spain is asking
                    of us. If no agreement is come to with France and England, Spain will have no
                    foreign exchange with which to pay for her imports and the peseta would fall
                    dangerously.</p>
                <p>Spain disapproves of all quotas but has been forced into her present position. It
                    is impossible for Spain to base our automobile contingent on the years 1927 to
                    1929 as, if she did so, commercial agreement would be impossible with France and
                    England and Italy and Germany as well. I pointed out, giving exact figures, the
                    enormous difference in the number of our automobiles imported ‘27 to ‘29 and in
                    the annual importations since the Spanish tariff has discriminated against us
                    and stated that a contingent based on the latter period would be impossible for
                    us to accept. Aguinaga said that Calderón had already been instructed to make a
                    slightly better offer. I replied that this would be <pb facs="0787" n="711"
                        xml:id="pg_711"/> useless and that we must have at the very least a
                    contingent based approximately upon our percentage of participation during
                    representative years when tariff discrimination did not exist. Aguinaga promised
                    to instruct Calderón further in the sense that he should increase the offer
                    already made.</p>
                <p>As to tariffs, I inferred from Sub-Secretary’s remarks that most-favored-nation
                    tariffs will, subject to negotiations, be accorded automobiles and other
                    products of special interest to us. Some slight reductions below such tariffs
                    possible in rare instances.</p>
                <p>According to best information available Minister of Finance has decided to let
                    exchange problem alone, hoping that it will solve itself as, Owing to present
                    long delay in securing exchange, imports will probably decrease and as
                    commercial treaties under negotiation should rectify balance of trade. He is
                    said, however, to be considering possibility of seeking foreign credits.</p>
                <p>Former head of Inter-Ministerial Committee on Foreign Trade who is now economist,
                    Cortes Committee on Trade and Commerce, has stated treaty must at least appear
                    to favor Spain or it will have small chance of ratification by Cortes.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, desire invite attention cotton situation. Cortes ratified
                    commercial agreement with the Argentine yesterday which guarantees annual
                    purchase of 13,500 metric tons Argentine raw cotton. Understand similar
                    provision for purchase of even larger quantity may appear in the treaty now in
                    negotiation with Brazil. These concessions will decrease already diminishing
                    participation our cotton Spanish market.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
