<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Trade Agreements Section ( (Grady))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1935v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d616</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">616</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1935-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1935-04-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1935-04-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1935-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="616"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d616">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.5431/158</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Trade Agreements Section</hi>
                        (<hi rend="italic">Grady</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1935-04-13">April 13,
                            1935</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Swiss Minister<note n="3" xml:id="d616fn3">Marc Peter.</note> called upon me
                    at the suggestion of the Secretary to inquire why Switzerland was put on the
                    list of countries which discriminate against American trade.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d616fn4">See letter from President Roosevelt to the Secretary of the
                        Treasury, April 1, 1935, Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Press
                            Releases</hi>, April 6, 1935, p. 216.</note> He was under the impression
                    that his country was not discriminating and he asked me for something specific
                    as to the nature of Switzerland’s discriminations. I pointed out that these were
                    largely the result of the use of bargaining quotas by Switzerland and that these
                    were discriminatory in a number of instances. He stated that his Government was
                    operating on a different system from ours and so the criteria of discrimination
                    might be hard to determine. I pointed out that where quotas result in a
                    diversion of business from one country to another, the case is clear for
                    discrimination. I said that it was our aim in the trade agreements to have
                    quotas extended to us on the basis of a representative period. While a
                    representative period may be subjected to differences of opinion, it is possible
                    to arrive at a definition of a representative period which is fair to the
                    various suppliers in a particular market. I said that we were not attempting to
                    change the system of any country in connection with trade agreements with them,
                    but simply to get agreement on certain principles that would insure the
                    non-diversion of a fair share of the other countries’ trade—fair share to be
                    determined on the basis of a representative period rather than on bargaining
                    quotas. We had already given to the Minister a set of our general provisions
                    which he has sent to his Government and which I feel sure they will
                    understand.</p>
                <p>The Minister said that he felt that he understood our position and our policies
                    and that his Government was looking forward to the consummation of a
                    satisfactory trade agreement with us.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry F. Grady</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
