<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-11-23T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-11-23T12:00:00-05:00" n="151" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d151">
                        <head>151. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in
                                Yugoslavia</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d151fn0">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 768.00/11–2359. Confidential.
                                Repeated to Ankara, Athens, Moscow, London, Paris, Bucharest,
                                Zagreb, Sarajevo, and Rome.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Belgrade</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-11-23T18:00:00+01:00">November
                                    23, 1959, 6 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>486. Rome for Lister. <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName> at Nis
                            November 22 expounded Yugoslav view that greater emphasis must be given
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in achieving world relaxation
                            tensions. Summit meetings which conducive East-West rapprochement he
                            said are highly desirable if they not indeed precondition any general
                            relaxation. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> visit and
                            forthcoming meetings other high government officials<note n="1" xml:id="d151fn1">During November and early December, British Foreign
                                Secretary Lloyd, German Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>, Italian Prime Minister Segni, Foreign
                                Minister Pella, and President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> made visits to other Western capitals to
                                discuss plans for a summit meeting. These meetings culminated when
                                the four Western heads of state met in Paris on December 19.</note>
                            thus welcomed, he asserted but benefits active coexistence can only be
                            finally realized with elimination bloc concepts and development
                            coexistence on universal basis.</p>
                        <p>Turning to immediate problems within Balkans <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName> declared Yugoslavia had always favored any positive
                            approach to general rapprochement and had only resorted to Yugoslav
                            Greek Turkish agreement when broader understanding proved impossible.
                            Under this agreement he said Greek Yugoslav relations had prospered. Now
                            with elimination Cyprus issue<note n="2" xml:id="d151fn2">Accords signed
                                in London on February 19 by the Greek, Turkish, and British Prime
                                Ministers established a Republic of Cyprus on February 19,
                                1960.</note> there are no reasons why similar improvement should not
                            take place with Turkey and he had recently said as much to Turkish
                            Ambassador. With respect Bulgaria, Rumania and particularly Albania,
                            however, situation is such “there are not realistic foundations for a
                            meeting” (presumably along lines recent Rumanian proposals).<note n="3" xml:id="d151fn3">On June 8 the Romanian Government proposed a
                                meeting of Balkan Prime Ministers with the objective of completing a
                                collective security treaty and establishing a nuclear-free zone in
                                the Balkans with a great power guarentee for both agreements.</note>
                            Unless bilateral relations improved <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName> said “this meeting would be pure propaganda and it
                            would bring more harm than benefit”.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> In discussions <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName> speech at Nis with senior Foreign
                            Secretariat officials Rukavina and Primozic both agreed today that
                            statements regarding desire improve relations with Turkey rather than
                            engage in “propagandists” general Balkan conference represented
                            important expression current Yugoslav attitude. Rukavina moreover
                            volunteered additional remark that some suggestion has been made (he <pb facs="0430" n="398" xml:id="pg_398"/> failed specify by whom) that
                            Albania might be simply ignored as way around difficulty posed by
                            strained Yugoslav-Albanian relations<note n="4" xml:id="d151fn4">Yugoslav-Albanian relations deteriorated during 1958 as Albania
                                joined in the Communist bloc campaign against Tito’s “revisionism.”
                                In addition, Albania accused Yugoslavia of mistreating its Albanian
                                minorities and renewed its territorial claims against Yugoslavia.
                                The Albanian Minister to Yugoslavia was recalled in August 1958 and
                                returned only in the fall of 1959.</note> thus enabling other Balkan
                            countries achieve harmonious settlement their differences. According
                            Rukavina <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName> speech at Nis
                            should make clear that any such suggestion completely unacceptable to
                            Yugoslavs who adhere firmly to their now established position that
                            substantial improvement bilateral relations must precede any generalized
                            “settlement” (for further discussion this point see <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 416).<note n="5" xml:id="d151fn5">Telegram 416, November 3, reported on an editorial in the Belgrade
                                daily <hi rend="italic">Politika</hi> that indicated Yugoslav
                                interest in improving its relations with other Balkan governments.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, 033.6166/11–359)</note> Any
                            Balkan rapprochement without Albania Rukavina added would only free that
                            country to continue its disruptive activities thus rendering
                            rapprochement meaningless.</p>
                        <p>Judging from Rukavina, Primozic further remarks as well as other official
                            comment heard recently <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName>
                            references to necessity eliminate blocs in order realize benefits
                            coexistence also represented something more than mere repetition
                            familiar Yugoslav positions. Thus in separate conversations both men
                            asserted East-West rapprochement without assurance of progress toward
                            elimination blocs would only lead to kind of partition of world along
                            lines at one time favored by Stalin. Such partition they said could only
                            be harmful to interests uncommitted countries in manner certain to
                            provoke rather than eliminate further tensions.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RK1"><hi rend="strong">Rankin</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>