<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-11-21T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-11-21T14:00:00-05:00" n="274" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d274">
                        <head>274. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Greece</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d274fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 781.00/11–2159. Secret; Limited Distribution. Transmitted in
                                two sections.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Athens</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-11-21T21:00:00+02:00">November
                                    21, 1959, 9 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1412. Reference: Embtels 1337 and 1338, November 16.<note n="1" xml:id="d274fn1">In telegram 1337 from Athens, Briggs reported on a
                                conversation with Averoff in which Averoff outlined a “three front”
                                Soviet effort to undercut the pro-Western stance of the <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName> government. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 661.81/11–1659) In telegram 1338 from
                                Athens, Briggs outlined courses of action available to the United
                                States to support <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName>
                                against external and internal Communist challenges. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 781.00/11–1659)</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>At Prime Minister’s request I spent nearly two hours with him this
                                morning, net of which was that his government approaching critical
                                situation and will fall at very early date unless assistance
                                forthcoming. By assistance, as developed during conversation, it
                                appears that he means aid from US and action by Western European
                                Governments to absorb agricultural surpluses. “A little assistance
                                now, before it is too late, can tide us over, whereas if assistance
                                not forthcoming, we are undone.”</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName> began by
                                referring to his satisfaction at arrangements for President’s visit,
                                including his call on President on December 15.<note n="2" xml:id="d274fn2">On November 4, the White House announced that
                                        <persName>Eisenhower</persName> would visit 11 nations,
                                    including Greece, in a December tour. See <ref target="#d276">Document 276</ref>.</note> He said would much prefer not to
                                expose his troubles at time when he and entire Greek nation would be
                                wishing to express affection and esteem for Chief Executive of
                                nation which has already done so much <pb facs="0718" n="686" xml:id="pg_686"/> for Greece. He hoped therefore by my conveying
                                his estimate of situation in advance, he would be spared need to
                                speak at length about Greece’s troubles. His outline followed lines
                                already forecast in Embassy reports as a result conversations with
                                Foreign Minister Averoff and others, and our own assessment of
                                deteriorating situation.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName> spoke of his
                                government’s difficulties in arranging Cyprus settlement, adding
                                with bitterness that <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies
                                had done little to show sympathy or understanding. Cyprus settlement
                                was unpalatable to large segments Greek public and government
                                correspondingly vulnerable. On top of this has come decline of the
                                economy, particularly production and employment, accompanied by
                                falling national and government revenues, and now problem of
                                agricultural surpluses. Although government has heretofore
                                maintained brave public posture, extent of economic difficulty can
                                no longer be obscured since government increasingly hard pressed to
                                meet its commitments (<gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> Prime
                                Minister has ordered ten percent expenditures cut in all
                                ministries), farm surpluses are real, and thousands of individual
                                farm families are affected.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In these circumstances Greece’s allies have not been helpful. He
                                spoke of discouraging report from Greek common market negotiators in
                                Brussels, which indicates little prospect of early relief from that
                                    quarter.<note n="3" xml:id="d274fn3">Greece applied for
                                    associate membership in the <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>
                                    on June 8.</note> It seemed incomprehensible to him that allies
                                of Western Europe, whose imports from Greece almost microscopic in
                                terms their total imports, would not be willing to come to rescue at
                                this critical time.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Turning to US and conceding its economic difficulties,
                                nevertheless, he said, annually decreased US aid has marked his
                                tenure of office, and proposals for current year, insofar as known
                                to his government, meant that Greece now can not count on aid from
                                that source in amounts Greece considers necessary.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Prime Minister concluded with description of Greece’s
                                vulnerability to Soviet pressures, along line statements of Foreign
                                Minister of November 16 (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>
                                1337). While he himself will never deal with <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> on their terms, he said, Soviet
                                offers can not but appear attractive when country so deeply in
                                trouble. Soviet aim, as he sees it, is detach Greece from <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, and Greece at present time is
                                wide open target.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>There was more along same line but net of his representation, as
                                stated paragraph 1, is that Greece must have help from her allies,
                                and have it soon, or economy will collapse and political stability
                                with it, with incalculable effects on Greece’s alliance with
                                West.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>I told Prime Minister I would of course immediately report
                                substance grave picture he had described. On my departure <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName><pb facs="0719" n="687" xml:id="pg_687"/>said he hoped we could have further
                                conversation between now and Presidential visit which I interpret as
                                hope there may be some response from Washington to this appeal,
                                prior to December 14.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Comment</hi>: Prime Minister account reaffirms
                                and emphasizes picture recently drawn by Averoff (reference
                                telegrams). Even partially discounting some of <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName> pessimism, his picture of
                                Greece’s politico-economic fragility and vulnerability corresponds
                                by and large with our own and, in our opinion, calls for action
                                along lines commented on in Embattle 1338. Primary stress laid by
                                Prime Minister was on need for quick assistance to buy time (which
                                would involve less effort and money than that required to collect
                                and reassemble the pieces after a collapse). So far as we can see,
                                only practical source of such emergency assistance is US grant aid.
                                What Greeks would do with time thus gained and what long-term
                                assistance allies could muster are questions which would later
                                follow. <list>
                                    <label>(A)</label>
                                    <item>Immediate step we recommend is earliest possible
                                        Washington decision on pending aid items–i.e., additional $5
                                        million for defense support; and <gloss target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss> loan applications, if bond negotiations
                                        have cleared way. While this may not meet <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName> time-buying
                                        objective, it will be helpful not only financially but also
                                        in clearing air and enabling useful public announcement of
                                        an aid level comparing favorably with last year’s.</item>
                                    <label>(B)</label>
                                    <item>Next step would be to provide Greece with some additional
                                        grant aid. <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName>
                                        mentioned ten million dollars, which he associated with need
                                        for increased investment spending on top of heavy defense
                                        load.</item>
                                    <label>(C)</label>
                                    <item>As follow-up attention should be directed at basic
                                        underlying problems–especially problem of Greece’s
                                        agricultural policies and its expanding unmarketable
                                        surpluses. Dealing effectively with that problem may well
                                        require several steps, including corrective Greek action as
                                        far as possible, common market action on Greece’s
                                        association, and possibly even modifications US policies on
                                        aid in the agricultural sector (if Greek situation accepted
                                        as being of demanding importance).</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>While impossible to predict with exactitude political and economic
                                consequences of economic collapse, it can certainly be said they
                                Would bode little good for US and Western cause. <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName> would be repudiated and
                                his party break up, and Grivas (a dubious Messiah) enabled to emerge
                                as important political force. No party would have safe or stable
                                majority, and we might be confronted with succession of weak
                                governments pillow fighting with economic problems, not least of <pb facs="0720" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/> which would be feather
                                weight drachma, with all its collapse would entail. [<hi rend="italic">6½ lines of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>]<note n="4" xml:id="d274fn4">In telegram 1683,
                                    December 12, the Department of State instructed Briggs to inform
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName> that, in
                                    view of Greek cooperation on bond issues, the United States
                                    would extend up to $31 million in <gloss target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss> funds. No defense support funds were, however,
                                    available for Greece. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                        781.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/12–1159)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Briggs</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>