<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-10-04T08:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-10-04T08:45:00-05:00" n="299" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d299">
                        <head>299. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d299fn0">Source: Department of State, Greek Desk Files: Lot
                                61 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 456, United Nations.
                                Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HAG1">Hope</persName>
                                on October 5. The meeting was held at the Waldorf
                            Towers.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1960-10-04T09:45:00-04:00">October 4, 1960, 9:45
                                    a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">SECRETARY’S DELEGATION TO THE FIFTEENTH SESSION OF THE
                            UNITED NATIONS GENERAL ASSEMBLY New York, October 3–7, 1960</p>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">U.S.</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_JGL1">G. Lewis Jones</persName>,
                                        Assistant Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss></item>
                                    <item><persName corresp="#p_HAG1">A. Guy Hope</persName>,
                                        Advisor, USDel, <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss></item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">Greece</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>H.E. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ATE1">Evangelos</persName></item>
                                    <item>Averoff-Tossizza, Greek Foreign Minister</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Call on the Secretary by the Foreign Minister of Greece</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Foreign Minister Averoff had asked to call on the Secretary following his
                            luncheon with Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_JGL1">Lewis
                                Jones</persName> on October 3.<note n="1" xml:id="d299fn1"><persName>Jones</persName> and Averoff discussed the bond
                                issue, Greek problems with the <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>,
                                and Greek relations with the United Arab Republic. A memorandum of
                                their conversation is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Conference
                                Files: Lot 64 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 559, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 1767.</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0760" n="728" xml:id="pg_728"/>
                        <p>The Secretary thanked Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> for his excellent
                            short talk on October 3 in seconding the postponement of the five–power
                            resolution on <persName>Eisenhower</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> talks.<note n="2" xml:id="d299fn2">On September 29, the leaders of Yugoslavia, India,
                                the United Arab Republic, Ghana, and Indonesia introduced a
                                resolution in the General Assembly calling for a meeting between
                                President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> and
                                Premier <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>. For text,
                                see U.N. doc. A/4522.</note> The Foreign Minister said that the
                            Yugoslavs were very upset with him and Popovic had spoken to him quite
                            sharply, saying he had compromised their effort to obtain a meaningful
                            resolution. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> had explained that he had
                            stressed the open-door characteristic of President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>’s reply<note n="3" xml:id="d299fn3">For text of <persName>Eisenhower</persName>’s
                                reply, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                                October 17, 1960, pp. 595–596.</note> and did not believe that he
                            should be held to account by the neutrals for his reasonable action. He
                            commented that the Yugoslavs were most anxious to get something nailed
                            down before <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName> left New York
                            today and that this probably explained their upset. Mr.
                                <persName>Averoff</persName> said <persName corresp="#p_PK1">Popovic</persName> had not made this point to him but had said that
                            the situation was too serious for delay. Mr.
                                <persName>Averoff</persName> was inclined to believe that it was not
                            a good thing to be slapping the faces of the “five personalities”
                            involved in the resolution since they enjoyed a considerable following
                            among the neutrals. As Popovic had pointed out to Ambassador Wadsworth,
                            the Australian resolution<note n="4" xml:id="d299fn4">U.N. doc.
                                A/L.316.</note> gave <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> a good excuse for some new propaganda
                            explosions over the U–2 incident. The Yugoslavs had assumed, according
                            to Averoff, that the U.S. had put the Australians up to introducing
                            their resolution.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he was inclined to agree that the Australian action
                            did give <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> a propaganda
                            opportunity. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> suggested that the best
                            thing would be to amend the five–power resolution in order to save face
                            for the personalities who had introduced it. The Secretary agreed but
                            hoped the resolution would not emerge with a request for an
                                <persName>Eisenhower</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> meeting. Averoff thought this would be
                            difficult for the Yugoslavs and the other sponsors but said he would be
                            talking with Popovic about it.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> remarked that the President’s reply to
                            the letter from the five was clear and dignified and was very helpful
                            since it did not close the door to a future meeting. The Secretary said
                            that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s reply<note n="5" xml:id="d299fn5">U.N. doc. A/4532.</note> was not at all
                            helpful or flexible and seemed to close the door to any negotiations
                            under acceptable terms. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> said the
                            problem was how to handle the exchanges so that the West seemed to be in
                            the right. The Secretary said that we would be doing a lot of thinking
                            about <pb facs="0761" n="729" xml:id="pg_729"/> the matter during the
                            day and would be in touch with Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> and our
                            other friends about it. Averoff stressed that if the door to talks would
                            be kept open it would help immensely. He thought the five could go along
                            with a change of dates if there were no other substantial
                            alterations.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that, apart from the present incident, he was
                            concerned about the precedent involved. If the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> establishes a custom of attempting to persuade leaders
                            to get together on issues, there is no telling where such a course might
                            lead. He mentioned, for example, the complications which could arise in
                            the case of a <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> mandate for Nasser to
                            talk to Ben-Gurion or Hussein.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> commented, and the Secretary agreed,
                            that King Hussein’s speech<note n="6" xml:id="d299fn6">In his October 3
                                speech, Hussein rejected neutralism, condemned the Soviet Union’s
                                intervention in Arab affairs, and attacked the United Arab Republic
                                for its interference in Jordanian affairs.</note> was very
                            courageous and timely. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> thought that the
                            courage demonstrated in his appearance would be helpful in inspiring
                            courage on the part of some of his auditors about other matters before
                            the Assembly.</p>
                        <p>Turning to the Chinese representation issue, Mr.
                                <persName>Averoff</persName> said that he did not expect an answer
                            from the Secretary but wanted to report frankly that many of our friends
                            in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> are not happy about the Chinese
                            question and followed the US position only for reasons of decency and
                            loyalty to the US. The Secretary said he realized the problem and knew
                            that it became more difficult each year. Mr.
                                <persName>Averoff</persName> said that he did not believe we could
                            maintain the present position much longer. The Secretary commented that
                            perhaps there had been some wishful thinking about Chiang dying or other
                            changes in the situation in Formosa. He noted that Mr.
                                <persName>Nash</persName> of New Zealand and some others had been
                            advocating a scheme for a separate Formosa idea in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> but the Chinese Communists had shown no
                            interest in such a plan nor was it acceptable to the Government of the
                            Republic of China. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> said that he thought
                            something could be worked out on a “two Chinas” scheme. He said that the
                            friends of the US had no arguments with which to counter the attacks on
                            the Chinese representation issue. The Secretary pointed out that
                            Communist China has been declared by the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> as an aggressor in Korea and is still continuing to
                            remain there in defiance of the resolution, that the Chinese Communists
                            have declared their intention of taking Formosa by force, and that
                            perhaps even more significantly from the US point of view, the Chinese
                            Communists had repudiated their signed agreement with us on the
                            repatriation of nationals. We still have five Americans who are held by
                            the Chinese Communists in violation of their signed undertaking. The
                            Secretary said that <pb facs="0762" n="730" xml:id="pg_730"/> when he
                            was Governor of Massachusetts, he had agreed to pardon a Chinese who was
                            serving a sentence for murder in order that the man could be repatriated
                            to China in order to live up to our agreement on this matter. He thought
                            there was some significance to the fact that the Chinese prisoner had
                            preferred to continue serving his sentence rather than return to the
                            China mainland. The Secretary said that we had scrupulously lived up to
                            our side of the repatriation agreement. He realized fully that there
                            existed an unnatural situation with 600 million people not recognized in
                            the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> but that the Chinese Communists
                            should declare their intention to stand by the provisions of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter if admitted. They had not made
                            any such statement. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> agreed that such a
                            statement was a condition precedent to <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> membership and in addition he believed the Chinese
                            Communists should agree to guarantee the independence of Formosa.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> referred to the report which he had made
                            available to the Department through Ambassador Briggs (relating to the
                            Bucharest meeting).<note n="7" xml:id="d299fn7">Reference is to the June
                                20–25 conference of Communist Parties in Bucharest at which the
                                Soviet and People’s Republic of China Delegations publicly disagreed
                                about <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s policy of
                                “peaceful coexistence” with capitalist states.</note> He was
                            absolutely certain of the veracity of the report of difficulties in the
                            Communist camp, as certain as if he had been present. While he found the
                            evidences of Sino-Soviet difficulties very interesting, he did not feel
                            we should base our policy on an expectation of a major blow-up between
                            the two Communist powers. He felt that the Communist leaders would never
                            allow an open break if they could possibly help it. He felt that a real
                            clash could come only if material considerations conflicted, for
                            example, if the Chinese found they needed more land and pressed against
                            Russian borders. The Secretary said he could visualize a real conflict
                            if the Chinese Communists should decide unilaterally to attack Formosa
                            under the present circumstances. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName>
                            responded that perhaps this would be another instance because
                            unquestionably the Chinese are very bellicose and the Soviets are
                            not.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary and the Foreign Minister agreed that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is a most curious
                            personality whose behavior at the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                            had been deplorable. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> commented that the
                            Africans had behaved very well. While two or three of the delegations
                            had joined the claque for <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>, it was a fine thing that the others
                            refrained from such behavior. The Secretary agreed.</p>
                        <p>Queried by the Secretary as to his travel plans, Mr.
                                <persName>Averoff</persName> said that he could not remain in New
                            York long. He had to go to Paris to try to help along the Common Market
                            talks which were not going too well. Then it was necessary for him to
                            return to Greece where there were bothersome internal problems. The
                            Secretary inquired whether the <pb facs="0763" n="731" xml:id="pg_731"/>
                            Greek parliament is in session. Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName>
                            responded that it was not, but it might be necessary to call up
                            parliament because of a scandal which is brewing. He explained that a
                            war criminal who had been tried in Greece, then turned over to the
                            Germans, who had released him, had accused high Greek officials,
                            including the Prime Minister, Minister of War and Minister of Interior
                            of collaborating with the Nazis. As far as <persName corresp="#p_KK1">Karamanlis</persName> is concerned, it would not be difficult to
                            disprove charges which were being made by this war criminal and
                            exploited by the Communists, but it was apparently going to be necessary
                            to provoke the Communists to an open fight before parliament in order to
                            have an opportunity to produce evidence to disprove the charges.</p>
                        <p>In response to Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> inquiry the Secretary
                            said he planned to stay in New York until Friday. His further movements
                            would depend on developments.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> turned briefly to the situation in
                            Turkey, which he said disturbed him a little. His good friend Foreign
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sarper</persName> had told him of
                            his meetings with <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName> and
                            Nasser in New York but had not given him any report on his hour and
                            fifteen minute meeting with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>. The Secretary explained that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sarper</persName> had left for Turkey yesterday.
                            Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> said that he was sure that <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sarper</persName> had not made significant
                            commitments to any of the three. [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines of source
                                text not declassified</hi>] He also expressed support for General
                                <persName corresp="#p_GC1">Gursel</persName> whom he felt was
                            determined to live up to his <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            commitments but understandably was attempting to improve Turkish
                            relations with the Arabs which had deteriorated considerably under the
                            previous administration. What worried Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName>
                            was that we do not know where the Turks are going in their internal
                            situation. He deplored the trials saying “blood is always bad”.<note n="8" xml:id="d299fn8">Following the military coup of May 27, the
                                Turkish military government placed 15 top leaders of the Democratic
                                Party, including former President <persName corresp="#p_BC1">Bayar</persName> and former Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Menderes</persName>, on trial for
                                corruption.</note></p>
                        <p>The Secretary commented that <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Menderes</persName> must still have many friends. The Foreign
                            Minister said that his information indicated there was more support
                            among the peasants for <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Menderes</persName>
                            than ever before and that he was informed <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Menderes</persName> would not be harmed. If the court should
                            sentence him to death, Mr. <persName>Averoff</persName> felt confident
                            that he would receive “grace” but he felt that some leaders would be
                            executed.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Minister suggested that the Secretary should ask his Eastern
                            European specialists to make a comparison between the Albanian speech at
                            the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> last year and in the present
                            session. He found it interesting that the tune had changed considerably.
                            Last year the Albanians were licking the feet of the Russians but now
                            were much less <pb facs="0764" n="732" xml:id="pg_732"/> enthusiastic
                            and were fawning on Peiping instead. The Secretary said we had noticed
                            that the Russians did not speak to the Albanians in the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> for several days. Mr.
                                <persName>Averoff</persName> said that this development had been
                            noted in the report on the Bucharest Conference which he had sent to the
                            Secretary.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>