<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>310. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v10p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="310"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                <head>310. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d310fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 64
                            <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 199. Secret. Drafted by
                            <persName>Dulles</persName>. Heuss and Brentano were in Washington June
                        4–7 on a State visit. The meeting was held at the German Embassy.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1958-06-06">June 6,
                            1958</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>President Heuss</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName>Von Brentano</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Secretary <persName>Dulles</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>After dinner when I was talking alone with President Heuss, he recalled the visit
                    of President <persName corresp="#p_BC1">Bayar</persName> to Germany<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d310fn1">May 7–15.</note> and his (Heuss’) feeling that Turkey was
                    in a desperate financial position and that something should be done to help
                    Turkey. I asked that Foreign Minister Von Brentano join us because Von Brentano,
                    whom I sat next to at dinner, had referred to the fact that he had seen the
                    Turkish Ambassador that day here in Washington.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName>Von Brentano</persName> joined us. He, too, expressed the view that
                    Turkey’s situation was very bad and that she should not be pushed over the
                    brink. I said we agreed with that and that the United States was giving a very
                    substantial amount of assistance in one way or another to Turkey, but that we
                    felt that it was imperative that Turkey should take more positive measures to
                    put its own house in order. I said I felt that it would be a mistake if Germany
                    should, on a bilateral basis, extend financial assistance to Turkey without
                    regard to the views of the International Monetary Fund or the <gloss
                        target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> as to the over-all financial and economic
                    position. Dr. <persName>Von Brentano</persName> said that he quite agreed that
                    there should be no bilateral assistance to Turkey by the Federal Republic, and
                    that anything that was done should be coordinated with the Monetary Fund or with
                        <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss>. He seemed to have in his mind the
                        <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> rather than the Monetary Fund.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
