<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-28T10:00:00-05:00" n="357" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d357">
                        <head>357. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>The political situation in Turkey was the subject of discussion at the
                            meeting of the Operations Coordinating Board on April 27. During the
                            meeting: “Mr. <persName>Hare</persName> gave a short briefing on the
                            present political situation in Turkey noting that the approaching
                            national elections make the domestic activity fairly typical. He cited
                            the need to exercise care to avoid US involvement with either side. Mr.
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> (<gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>)
                            outlined certain developments which, if elections were to be held
                            immediately, the opposition could be able to use effectively to come out
                            on top.</p>
                        <p>“Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gray</persName> thought it was generally
                            understood that the present situation is not serene, neither is it at a
                            spark-producing stage. All agreed on the desirability of close
                            observation of the scene.” A copy of <pb facs="0865" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/> the preliminary notes on the meeting, from which
                            this quotation is taken, is in Department of State, <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> Files: Lot 61 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 385, <gloss target="#t_M1">M</gloss>/OP Informal Notes. A
                            copy of the briefing paper from which Hare spoke is <hi rend="italic">ibid.:</hi> Lot 62 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 430, <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> Luncheon Items.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> commented on the
                            instability in Turkey during his briefing at the 442d meeting of the
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> on April 28: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Turning to Turkey, Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> reported that
                                    that country might find itself in a critical situation sometime
                                    during the next few years. Since early 1960 the opposition party
                                    in Turkey, the Republican People’s Party of ex-President
                                        <persName corresp="#p_II1">Ismet Inonu</persName>, has been
                                    increasingly oppressed by the government. Some questions have
                                    arisen as to the validity of the last election in Turkey,
                                    although the situation is not as bad as it was in Korea. The
                                    Turkish Government has now appointed a committee to investigate
                                    subversive activities. This committee, exercising wide powers,
                                    has been moving against <persName corresp="#p_II1">Inonu</persName> and his party. Mr.
                                        <persName>Dulles</persName> felt this problem required
                                    careful consideration by the U.S. Government in the future. The
                                    Turkish Army was probably behind the government; however, there
                                    was a strong popular feeling in favor of <persName corresp="#p_II1">Inonu</persName>. Unless constitutional
                                    procedures are more carefully followed in Turkey, a situation
                                    similar to that now existing in Korea might develop. The
                                        <persName corresp="#p_II1">Inonu</persName> Party may
                                    attempt demonstrations at the time or the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Council Meeting in Istanbul.”
                                    (Memorandum of discussion; Eisenhower Library, <persName corresp="#p_WA2">Whitman</persName> File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records)</p>
                            </quote></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>