<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>83. Operations Coordinating Board Report</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v10p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-09-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-09-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec0YzQ4Y7ayjLsvS" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="decolonization"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008006757"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">National independence</term>
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Information programs</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="83"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                <head>83. Operations Coordinating Board Report<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d83fn0">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_OCB1"
                            >OCB</gloss> Files: Lot 61 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 385, Poland
                        Documents. Secret. A cover sheet and a statement entitled “Purpose and Use
                        of the Operations Plan” are not printed. This plan, originally drafted on
                        August 6, 1958, was revised on September 23, 1959. In an undated memorandum,
                        which was revised October 8 and attached to the plan, <persName
                            corresp="#p_SBK1">Bromley Smith</persName>, Executive Officer of the
                            <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss>, summarized the actions taken by the
                            <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> at its meeting of August 26; see
                            <ref target="#d80">Document 80</ref>. A footnote in
                            <persName>Smith</persName>’s memorandum states that revisions of
                        paragraphs 9 and 40 developed by the Departments of State and the Treasury
                        were concurred in by the agencies on September 21 and that the Board noted
                        this concurrence at its meeting on September 23; see <ref target="#d80fn2"
                            >footnote 2, Document 80</ref>. A handwritten note on the cover sheet
                        states that this Operations Plan for Poland was superseded by the Operations
                        Plan of February 26, 1960; see <ref target="#d95">Document 95</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1959-09-23">September 23, 1959</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">OPERATIONS PLAN FOR POLAND</p>
                <p rend="center">I. Introduction</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">A. Special Operating Guidance</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Short-Term Objectives</hi>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Conditions in Poland enabling, through Western influence, the
                                promotion of peaceful evolution toward internal freedom and national
                                independence, the reduction of the Polish contribution to Soviet
                                strength, and the weakening of the monolithic front and internal
                                cohesiveness of the Soviet bloc.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Greater political, economic and social orientation of Poland
                                toward the West, and diminution of Soviet influence in
                                Poland.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Long-Term Objectives</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Eventual fulfillment of the right of the Polish people to live under a
                            government of their own choosing, which maintains peaceful and stable
                            relations with neighboring states, and participates fully in the Free
                            World community.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Interest in Poland</hi>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>The Communist nature of the <persName corresp="#p_GW1"
                                    >Gomulka</persName> regime, and its close association with the
                                    <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> for ideological and
                                geopolitical reasons (including membership in the Warsaw Pact),
                                prevent achievement of a really independent Poland in the
                                foreseeable future. Nevertheless, the limited independence gained by
                                Poland since the establishment of the <persName corresp="#p_GW1"
                                    >Gomulka</persName> regime in October, 1956, serves U.S.
                                interests by tending to weaken the monolithic character of the
                                Soviet Bloc; impugning the alleged universality of certain aspects
                                of Soviet Communism, contributing to ferment in Eastern Europe; and
                                providing new opportunities to project Western influences in
                                Poland.</item>
                            <pb facs="0265" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Because of the influence which its example exerts on other
                                Communist countries in Eastern Europe, Poland’s ability to maintain
                                its present semi-independence will be a key factor affecting future
                                political developments in that area.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>The United States wishes to avoid any situation which might lead
                                to retrogression in Poland, harsher Soviet policies in the
                                Soviet-dominated countries of Eastern Europe, or serious risk of
                                general war. Consequently, U.S. interests currently are best served
                                by a semi-independent Poland with a potential for evolving toward
                                full independence by gradual means not jeopardizing the gains
                                already made.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Experience has shown that U.S. policy toward Poland can be pursued
                                effectively through the Polish government, as well as directly with
                                the Polish people, through such means as aid, trade, and information
                                programs. The Polish bureaucracy still contains numerous
                                non-Communists.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Special Treatment for Poland</hi>. All government agencies
                        should recognize that U.S. interests require a distinction in certain cases
                        between the treatment accorded Poland and that accorded Czechoslovakia,
                        Hungary, Albania, Rumania, and Bulgaria. Poland is considered as having
                        gained limited independence, whereas the other countries mentioned are
                        regarded as Soviet-dominated.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Attitude Toward <persName corresp="#p_GW1"
                                >Gomulka</persName> Regime</hi>. All feasible steps should be taken
                        to promote and encourage in Poland an evolution toward greater internal
                        freedoms and national independence. [<hi rend="italic">3½ lines of source
                            text not declassified</hi>] Actions should be avoided which might be
                        interpreted as encouraging attempts to overthrow the regime by violence or
                        which would be likely to provoke retrogression within Poland or the use of
                        force by the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Actions should also be
                        avoided which could be interpreted as unreserved endorsement of the
                            <persName corresp="#p_GW1">Gomulka</persName> regime. Good working
                        relations with Polish officials should be cultivated, and Polish Government
                        channels should be exploited to the maximum extent feasible when taking U.S.
                        actions designed to benefit the Polish people.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Delicate Balance of the Polish International
                        Position</hi>. Because of the delicate balance of the Polish international
                        position, care should be taken both in action and publicity to avoid placing
                        the Polish Government in positions where it would feel compelled to affirm
                        solidarity with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. This is
                        particularly true regarding the objective of reducing Soviet influence in
                        Poland, as present circumstances prohibit the Polish Government from
                        accepting without comment public statements to the effect that U.S. policies
                        are designed to wean Poland away from the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss>. At the same time, it must be recognized that the Polish
                        Government, in order to maintain its delicate balance vis-à-vis the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, and influenced by ideological prejudice
                        as well as genuine fears of a resurgent Germany supported by the United
                        States, will make critical <pb facs="0266" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/>
                        statements about the United States and its policies. Reasoned refutation of
                        Polish statements and unpublicized representations against extravagant
                        language will advance U.S. interests without the likelihood of prejudice to
                        Poland’s relations with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S. Aid</hi>. The United States should be prepared, at
                        Polish request, to furnish economic and technical aid to Poland at
                        approximately current program levels for the purpose of encouraging Poland
                        to pursue policies which would contribute to the attainment of U.S.
                        objectives. During the course of the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1959
                        economic discussions, the Polish representatives formally submitted a
                        request for expanded technical cooperation between the United States and
                        Poland as part of any dollar loan program which might be agreed upon.<note
                            n="1" xml:id="d83fn1">This Polish request for expanded technical
                            cooperation was made on March 4; see <ref target="#d67">Document
                                67</ref>.</note> The Poles have been assured that their request is
                        being given careful consideration, and the United States has now started
                        preliminary discussions with the Poles on the possibility of a technical
                        cooperation program involving both Polish participants and U.S. technicians.
                        A United States position is currently being developed in consultations among
                        the agencies represented in the economic negotiations with Poland. The
                        United States should also be prepared to increase the level of aid to Poland
                        should significant opportunities arise which would move Poland toward
                        internal freedom and national independence. To the extent possible, without
                        prejudicing the primary purposes outlined above, U.S. aid to Poland should
                        be designed to: (a) reduce Polish economic dependence on the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and other countries of the Soviet bloc;
                        (b) reach those sectors of the Polish economy where it is likely to be of
                        the greatest benefit to the Polish people; (c) contribute to the development
                        of free economic forces within Poland; and (d) provide to the Polish people
                        the maximum visible evidence of the source of the aid.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Increased Trade</hi>. Trade with Poland in non-strategic
                        goods should be encouraged to the maximum extent consistent with the
                        established policy of maintaining a distinction between the treatment
                        accorded Poland and that accorded other Eastern European countries.
                        Strategically-rated goods, including embargo-type items, may be made
                        available to Poland from Western countries on a case-by-case basis as such
                        goods are shown to be reasonable and necessary to the Polish civilian
                        economy (as determined in each case by reference to the stated civilian
                        uses, and with due consideration to the strategic risk involved).</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Possible Polish Membership in <gloss target="#t_IMF1"
                                >IMF</gloss> and World Bank</hi>. The United States should oppose
                        Polish membership in the International Bank and International Monetary Fund.
                        The Poles are being advised that the <pb facs="0267" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"
                        /> United States will not support any application from them for readmission
                        to the Bank or Fund.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Increased Contacts and Exchanges</hi>. Subject to security
                        safeguards, an especial effort should be made through official and
                        non-official channels to increase scientific, economic, academic, and
                        cultural contacts and exchanges between the United States and Poland. In
                        some instances it will be desirable to include known Polish Communists in
                        the exchange program in cases of individuals known to be influential and
                        whose exposure to life here would be in the best interests of the United
                        States. In view of the favorable trend under present informal arrangements,
                        initiation by the United States of negotiations leading to an overall formal
                        exchange agreement with Poland is not recommended at this time. As part of
                        the official exchange program, Polish leaders should be invited to the
                        United States and the United States should be prepared to send U.S. leaders
                        to Poland. Invitations to Polish leaders should be extended in such a manner
                        that they may be refused without publicity or embarrassment.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy</hi>. Opportunities should
                        be utilized for cooperation in the unclassified, peaceful uses of atomic
                        energy, including, under appropriate safeguards, the training in the United
                        States of Polish scientists in non-sensitive fields.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Information Program</hi>. The goals of the U.S.
                        information and cultural program in Poland are to provide Poles with
                        information useful to them, over a period of time, in their efforts to
                        achieve a greater degree of independent authority and popular control in the
                        direction of their own affairs, and to give the Polish people a sound and
                        sympathetic understanding of United States policy and the American people.
                        The official U.S. information and cultural program in Poland (currently
                        conducted largely on an informal basis) should be strengthened to the extent
                        feasible. The activities of private U.S. individuals and organizations
                        should also be encouraged to the extent that the activities contribute to
                        the achievement of the goals set forth above. It is important to plan and
                        conduct information activities so that the above objectives are furthered
                        without incurring the suppression of these activities either because of
                        Soviet pressure or because of the Polish regime’s concern that <gloss
                            target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> activities, because of their nature or
                        scope, would tend to frustrate the attainment of the regime’s internal
                        goals. It must be recognized that the number of personnel that can be
                        assigned the Embassy in Warsaw for the information and cultural work is
                        limited, while the demand among the Poles for more information materials
                        about the United States is practically unlimited.</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Defectors and Escapees</hi>. In general, current policy on
                        defectors, escapees, and refugees continues to apply to Polish nationals.
                            [<hi rend="italic">3 lines of source text not declassified</hi>]
                        Publicity concerning Polish defectors, escapees, <pb facs="0268" n="236"
                            xml:id="pg_236"/> and refugees should be avoided unless it is the view
                        of the Department of State and other agencies concerned that such publicity
                        would produce a net advantage to the United States.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Oder-Neisse Line</hi>. The Western Allies have taken the
                        position that the Oder-Neisse line is temporary and that the final
                        boundaries of Germany should be fixed in a peace settlement with the
                        agreement of an all-German government. They have taken no position on where
                        the boundary should be. The German Federal Republic has from time to time
                        hinted at the desirability of finding some compromise solution of the border
                        question. However, it would be unwise for the United States to take a
                        position on the boundary, at least until prospects for a settlement are more
                        promising, because to do so would incur the ill will of either the Poles or
                        the Germans, or both.</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follow Section B, “Selected U.S. Agreements With or Pertaining to Poland,”
                    and Part II, “Current and Projected Programs and Courses of Action.”]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
