<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1986-12-16T10:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1986-12-16T09:45:00-05:00" n="172" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                    <head>172. Minutes of a National Security Council Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d172fn1">Source: National Security Council,
                            National Security Council Institutional Files, Box SR–094, <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> 252. Secret. The meeting took place
                            in the Cabinet Room. No drafting information appears on the
                            minutes.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1986-12-16T09:45:00-05:00" to="1986-12-16T10:45:00-05:00">December 16, 1986, 9:45–10:45 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> Modernization</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>The President</item>
                        <item>The Vice President</item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>The Vice President’s Office:</head>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_WS_1">Sam Watson</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>State:</head>
                                <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George P.
                                        Shultz</persName></item>
                                <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Paul
                                    Nitze</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_HHA_1">Allen Holmes</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>Treasury:</head>
                                <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BJAIII_1">James
                                        Baker</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head><gloss target="#t_OSD_1">OSD</gloss>:</head>
                                <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Caspar W.
                                        Weinberger</persName></item>
                                <item>Edward C. Aldridge</item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_GR_3">Richard Godwin</persName></item>
                                <item>General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Larry D.
                                    Welch</persName></item>
                                <item>General Charles A. May, Jr.</item>
                                <item>LtCol Michael Elliott</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>Justice:</head>
                                <item>Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_MEIII_1">Edwin
                                        Meese</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>Transportation:</head>
                                <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DE_1">Elizabeth
                                        Dole</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head><gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss>:</head>
                                <item>Director <persName corresp="#p_MJ_2">James
                                    Miller</persName></item>
                                <item>Wayne Arny</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head><gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>:</head>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_GR_2">Robert Gates</persName></item>
                                <item>Lawrence Gershwin</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head><gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss>:</head>
                                <item>General <persName corresp="#p_KPXPX_1">P.X.
                                    Kelley</persName></item>
                                <item>Lt. General <persName corresp="#p_MJH_1">John
                                        Moellering</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head><gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss>:</head>
                                <item>Director <persName corresp="#p_AKL_1">Kenneth
                                        Adelman</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Michael Mobbs</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head><gloss target="#t_OSTP_1">OSTP</gloss>:</head>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_GW_1">William R.
                                    Graham</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head>White House:</head>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_RDT_1">Donald Regan</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_KAGA_1">Alton Keel</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_BWL_1">William Ball</persName></item>
                                <item>Dan Howard</item>
                                <item>David Chew</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><list>
                                <head><gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>:</head>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_CW_1">William Cockell</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_MDR_1">Rod McDaniel</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_DJ_1">John Douglass</persName></item>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_SR_1">Ron Sable</persName></item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KAGA_1">Keel</persName></hi>
                        introduced the subject and set the context of the meeting. He noted the long
                        history of several Administrations’ attempts to find an acceptable basing
                        mode for the Peacekeeper missile and summarized the events leading to the
                            <persName corresp="#p_SBA_1">Scowcroft</persName> Commission. He
                        reminded the participants of the <persName corresp="#p_SBA_1">Scowcroft</persName> recommendations, to place 100 Peacekeepers in
                        Minuteman silos, to start development of a small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>, to pursue arms control, and to seek a new survivable
                        basing mode for the <pb facs="0616" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/> Peacekeeper
                        missile. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KAGA_1">Keel</persName> noted that the
                            <persName corresp="#p_SBA_1">Scowcroft</persName> recommendations
                        attracted bipartisan support at first, but that the support faded and the
                        Congress limited deployment of the Peacekeeper to 50 missiles in Minuteman
                        silos.</p>
                    <p>He further noted that the Secretary of Defense would be reporting during the
                        meeting on the results of the basing work to date.</p>
                    <p>Changing the tone slightly, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KAGA_1">Keel</persName>
                        noted the great importance of the Peacekeeper and the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> to our arms control negotiations. He
                        spoke of the need to maintain and demonstrate our resolve to protect our
                        national security absent the arms control process and the need to develop
                        leverage as we negotiate.</p>
                    <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KAGA_1">Keel</persName> concluded his introduction
                        by speaking of the need to resolve the apparent contradictions between our
                        arms control proposals to ban mobile missiles and our plans to develop
                        mobile missiles for our deterrent force, and cautioned that we must not stop
                        our development programs in anticipation of an arms control agreement.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName></hi> followed with a short introduction of
                        the Garrison Rail Mobile basing concept and a discussion of the high cost of
                        the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> in relation to the
                        Peacekeeper garrison rail mobile system.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName></hi>
                        then presented the briefing at Tab A.<note n="2" xml:id="d172fn2">Attached
                            but not printed is a slide deck prepared in the Department of
                            Defense.</note></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName></hi> asked General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName> if garrison rail mobile basing required warning of a
                        Soviet attack.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName></hi>
                        replied that it required about four hours of warning to be highly
                        survivable.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BJAIII_1">Baker</persName></hi> asked if garrison rail mobile basing was the same
                        as the old racetrack system in the <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> Administration.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName></hi>
                        replied that it was not the same. He noted that the shallow trench system is
                        more similar to the old racetrack system.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The President</hi> asked if there were problems in finding
                        locations for the basing sites.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName></hi>
                        explained the Air Force’s initial thinking about basing the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> and noted that there had been few
                        objections to the locations of the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> bases. He also explained the garrison rail concept and
                        further noted that these sites had not been discussed in detail or their
                        planned locations announced.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The President</hi> noted that the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> was strongly supported by members of
                        Congress and that its continued development was essential to national
                        security and to winning further support from the Democrats for the
                        Peacekeeper garrison rail basing concept. He further <pb facs="0617" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/> remarked that he felt a low-key announcement of his
                        decisions on <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> Modernization was the
                        best approach for now. He concluded his remarks by asking General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName> if the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> would be deployed on the highways.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName></hi>
                        explained to the President that the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> may use some local roads, but does not depend on them for
                        survivability. General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName> also
                        noted that we have been transporting Minuteman missiles to and from their
                        silos over these same roads for years and have had few if any problems.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_KPXPX_1">Kelley</persName></hi> joined the conversation by noting that the
                        Peacekeeper basing is a political hostage to the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> program on the <persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Hill</persName>. He further noted, however, that the
                        small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> has strong military value to
                        the country and is fully supported by the Joint Chiefs of Staff. He
                        recommended to the President that we move forward with both the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> and Peacekeeper garrison rail basing as
                        soon as possible.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The President</hi> explained that he had approved a low-key
                        announcement on Friday, the 19th of December.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName></hi> responded to the President by noting his strong
                        support for the <persName corresp="#p_SBA_1">Scowcroft</persName>
                        Commission’s recommendations and expressing his view that the recommended
                        development of the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> and
                        Peacekeeper garrison rail basing was in full agreement with the Commission’s
                        recommendations. The Secretary noted that the two programs are linked and
                        should be considered as a package. He expressed the view that some critics
                        may try to exploit the idea that garrison basing depends on warning and
                        noted the need to deal with that issue carefully and with tact. He explained
                        to the President that having both programs in development would help with
                        our objectives of getting an equitable arms control treaty. The Secretary
                        further noted that in the past the Peacekeeper program had been plagued by
                        less than full support from within the Department of Defense. He noted that
                        the Chiefs did not support the plan for Closely Spaced Basing for
                        Peacekeeper and asked for everyone to express their views on the present
                        program so that the President would know where everyone stood. He closed by
                        noting that we will need everyone’s support this time or the program will
                        not be approved by the Congress.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">General <persName corresp="#p_KPXPX_1">Kelley</persName></hi> replied that the Chiefs fully support the
                        recommendation to proceed with development of both the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> and the Peacekeeper garrison rail
                        basing.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName></hi> noted that there were concerns within
                        the Department of Defense over the cost of the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>, but explained that the Department would
                        fully support the President’s decisions.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_MEIII_1">Meese</persName></hi> joined in by noting that Congressional
                        support is the real issue. The Attorney General then recommended that the
                        President invite the Congressional leadership down to the White <pb facs="0618" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/> House to be briefed and to discuss
                        the issue with the President. He noted that this would give them the feeling
                        they are participating in this important decision and generate considerable
                        goodwill.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName></hi> agreed that such a meeting was a good
                        idea.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KAGA_1">Keel</persName></hi>
                        explained to the President that General <persName corresp="#p_WLL_1">Welch</persName> and Dick Godwin had been prebriefing Congressional
                        leaders and that their reaction had been favorable so far.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Director <persName corresp="#p_AKL_1">Adelman</persName></hi> noted the need to support the small <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss> in such meetings.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DR_2">Dole</persName></hi>
                        expressed the strong support of the Department of Transportation for
                        garrison rail basing for the Peacekeeper missile.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName></hi> again raised the issue of whether or not
                        we should try to have a leadership meeting before the Friday<note n="3" xml:id="d172fn3">December 19.</note> announcement.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The President</hi> asked if there was time to organize such
                        a meeting.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName></hi> said that the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> is ready to announce on Friday, but expressed concern that
                        there was not enough time to organize a leadership meeting, especially since
                        the Congress was not in session.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KAGA_1">Keel</persName></hi>
                        noted the need to go ahead with the announcement on Friday and told the
                        President that we would see what was possible with the Congress.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The President</hi> concluded the meeting with a humorous
                        story and thanked everyone for their recommendations.<note n="4" xml:id="d172fn4"><persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> wrote in
                            his personal diary for December 16: “An N.S.C. meeting on the Midget
                            Missile. I’m afraid we’re stuck with a $40 Bil. program the military
                            doesn’t want &amp; I dont want. Congress tied the small missile (mobile)
                            to the 2nd 50 <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> missiles. We couldn’t
                            have the <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss>’s unless we agreed to go
                            forward with the Midget.” (Brinkley, ed., <hi rend="italic">The
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> Diaries</hi>,
                            vol. II: November 1985– January 1989, p. 668)</note></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>