<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1987-03-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1987-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="221" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d221">
                    <head>221. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Robert Linhard</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_TW_1">William Tobey</persName> of the National
                        Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d221fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_TW_1">William Tobey</persName> Files, Subject File, Arms
                            Control Proposals. Secret; Sensitive. Sent for action. All brackets are
                            in the original. A stamped notation indicates <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName> saw the
                        memorandum.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1987-03-05">March 5, 1987</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName> Memo on D&amp;S
                            Developments</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>At <hi rend="italic">Tab A</hi> is a memo to you from <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Cap Weinberger</persName>, expressing his concern
                        about hints from <persName corresp="#p_KMM_1">Max Kampelman</persName> that
                        the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> might be willing to accept a period
                        of additional negotiations on permitted and prohibited <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> activities. There is some basis for Cap’s
                        concern. A case can be made that Max has pushed his instructions to the
                        limit—or (some feel) perhaps beyond. These actions include: <list>
                            <label>○</label>
                            <item>Tabling in December a side-by-side paper comparing <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and Soviet views of permitted and
                                prohibited activities under the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss>
                                Treaty.</item>
                            <pb facs="0837" n="806" xml:id="pg_806"/>
                            <label>○</label>
                            <item>Proposing working groups in January and accepting the Soviet
                                position that one of two working groups should be on permitted and
                                prohibited activities under the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss>
                                Treaty.</item>
                            <label>○</label>
                            <item>Suggesting to <persName corresp="#p_VY_1">Vorontsov</persName> in
                                January a seven year period of non-deployment, to be followed by an
                                unspecified period of negotiations. [This is not one of two
                                authorized <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> proposals.]</item>
                            <label>○</label>
                            <item>To our surprise, briefing the Soviets on the details of the
                                ongoing consultations under <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss>
                                    261.<note n="2" xml:id="d221fn2">See <ref target="#d218">Document 218</ref>.</note> In this context he told the
                                Soviets on February 24th that “None of this [i.e. the contemplation
                                in Washington of restructuring the <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> program to take advantage of the LCI] should
                                interfere with our negotiations since what the sides negotiate, with
                                the advice and consent of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                                Senate, would become the supreme law of the United States.” This may
                                have led the Soviets to believe that the negotiations in Geneva
                                could somehow supersede the President’s decision on this issue,
                                despite <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> 261’s caution that,
                                “it is essential that we avoid giving the Soviet Union the mistaken
                                impression that we are willing to accept additional restrictions on
                                the conduct of the <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> program . .
                                .”</item>
                            <label>○</label>
                            <item>With <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Paul Nitze</persName>, proposing
                                to visiting Senate Arms Control Observers a plan whereby the
                                Executive Branch would not move to take advantage of the <gloss target="#t_LCI_1">LCI</gloss> for a specified period of time, in
                                return for a commitment by those senators to support an <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> funding level of $4 billion. [The
                                President’s <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 88 budget request for
                                    <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> is $5. 2 billion.]</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>While Max can explain his rationale and his view of his authority to do each
                        of the above, we need to remember that his standing instructions since
                        September state that, “It is not in the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        interest to accept any changes in the understanding of key terms and
                        definitions associated with the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty
                        which alter that which has already been negotiated and agreed. The
                        negotiating group should counter and reject Soviet attempts indirectly to
                        amend the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty and to narrow that
                        which is permitted by the Treaty.” These instructions were reinforced in
                            <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> 261.</p>
                    <p>The issue of negotiations with the Soviets about permitted and prohibited
                        activities under the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty reaches
                        back to the start of the negotiations, with Max resisting instructions that
                        would limit his flexibility. Thus, instructions, private conversations
                        (including one here), backchannel messages (including ones from Cap and
                        you), and now an <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> have not really
                        prevented Max from discussing with the Soviets and senators how the
                        President’s authority to implement the broad interpretation of the <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> Treaty might be circumscribed.</p>
                    <p>Only intervention from the highest levels will dampen Max’s activity and help
                        us to keep peace in the interagency community. You may wish to discuss these
                        issues with the President, and if he concurs, take Max aside and stress to
                        him privately the nature and level of concern about these issues. If you
                        wish, we will provide talking points for such a conversation.</p>
                    <pb facs="0838" n="807" xml:id="pg_807"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation</p>
                    <p>That you raise these issues with Max at an appropriate moment.<note n="3" xml:id="d221fn3">Neither <persName corresp="#p_PCL_1">Powell</persName>
                            nor <persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName> approved or
                            disapproved the recommendation.</note></p>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline"><hi rend="strong">Tab A</hi></note>
                        <head>Memorandum From Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName> to the President’s Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CFCIII_1">Carlucci</persName>)<note n="4" xml:id="d221fn4">Secret. <persName corresp="#p_WCWC_1">Weinberger</persName> wrote “Frank” above
                                the recipient line.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1987-02-27">February 27, 1987</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>DST Joint Working Paper Paragraph on “Right to Deploy” (U)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_S_1">S</gloss>) I am concerned about the direction
                            discussions within the DST Delegation may take regarding the deployment
                            of strategic defenses. The Soviets recently suggested it might be
                            possible to move their proposal for 3–5 years of subsequent negotiations
                            on the entire issue of <gloss target="#t_ABM_1">ABM</gloss> defenses
                            within the 10-year period of non-withdrawal. As currently drafted,
                            paragraph 5 of the joint working paper contains Soviet language
                            proposing the sides “begin negotiations on subject of advanced strategic
                            defenses,” juxtaposed with <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> language
                            that the sides “shall be free to deploy.”</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_S_1">S</gloss>) Although the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> language contains the phrase “unless the sides agree
                            otherwise,” the focus of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                            position <hi rend="italic">must</hi> remain on the right to deploy
                            strategic defenses at the end of whatever delay interval is suggested.
                            As you know, I think a 10-year delay is much too long. I recommend no
                            more than a 5-year period, as I have before. But our Delegation should
                                <hi rend="italic">not</hi> imply to the Soviets that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> side is willing to accept <hi rend="italic">additional</hi> restrictions on the <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> program. Indeed, placing restrictions
                            on <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> has been the long term objective
                            of the Soviets in these talks. I believe, therefore, that any further
                            effort by the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> side to accept the
                            Soviet notion of negotiations within any interval must not forsake that
                                <hi rend="italic">right</hi> to deploy and must be carefully
                            coordinated with Washington.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>