<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1985-03-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1985-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="23" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                    <head>23. Memorandum From the Special Assistant to the Under Secretary of State
                        for Political Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CWH_1">Courtney</persName>) to
                        the Special Advisor to the President and Secretary of State on Arms Control
                        Matters (<persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d23fn1">Source: Department of State, Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName>’s Personal Files 1953,
                            1972–1989, Lot 90D397, March and April 1985. Secret. Copies were sent to
                                <persName corresp="#p_TJ_1">Timbie</persName> and John Gordon
                                (<gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss>). A handwritten note at the
                            bottom of the first page of the memorandum indicates that copies were
                            also sent to <persName corresp="#p_BR_1">Burt</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_AKL_1">Adelman</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_CJTJ_1">Chain</persName> on March 28.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-editorial-annotation" calendar="gregorian" when="1985-03-28">undated</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_TRW_1">TRW</gloss> Briefings on Superhardening,
                            SICBM, and <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss></hi></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Following are my notes on the February 28 briefings at <gloss target="#t_TRW_1">TRW</gloss> in Los Angeles.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Superhardening</p>
                    <p>MX. [<hi rend="italic">5½ lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> in a Minuteman (<gloss target="#t_MM_1">MM</gloss>) silo will have the same rattlespace on the
                        side and top-to-bottom as the smaller <gloss target="#t_MM_1">MM</gloss>
                        missile, because the <gloss target="#t_MM_1">MM</gloss> cage is absent.</p>
                    <p>Ten launch control centers (LCCs) will control 100 <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> missiles, as compared with <gloss target="#t_MM_1">MM</gloss>, for which 5 LCCs control 50 missiles. The 10/100
                        arrangement is a better hedge against an <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss> attack.</p>
                    <p>In 1983 the President approved an <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> program
                        costing $16.6 billion (in 1982 dollars). The estimated actual cost at
                        present is a shade lower, $16.5 billion.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Superhardening</hi>. Following is the silo damage radius
                        for each of several silo hardnesses, assuming a one megaton burst:</p>
                    <table xml:id="table002">
                        <row>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Type of Silo</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Hardness (psi)</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Silo Damage Radius</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><gloss target="#t_MM_1">MM</gloss></cell>
                            <cell rows="3">[<hi rend="italic">column not declassified</hi>]</cell>
                            <cell rows="3">[<hi rend="italic">column not declassified</hi>]</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Superhard</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Enhanced superhard</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>A useful measure of the value of alternative levels of hardening, in relation
                        to warhead accuracies, is the “attack price,” the number of SS–18 equivalent
                        missiles (assuming ten warheads per missile) required to attack and damage a
                        silo with 90% confidence. The following chart summarizes the attack price
                        estimates for varying levels of hardness and missile CEP.</p>
                    <pb facs="0104" n="73" xml:id="pg_73"/>
                    <table xml:id="table003">
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell cols="3">[<hi rend="italic">column header not
                                declassified</hi>]</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">CEP</hi></cell>
                            <cell>[<hi rend="italic">number not declassified</hi>]</cell>
                            <cell>[<hi rend="italic">number not declassified</hi>]</cell>
                            <cell>[<hi rend="italic">number not declassified</hi>]</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>450′</cell>
                            <cell>0.1</cell>
                            <cell>0.6</cell>
                            <cell>0.9</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>300′</cell>
                            <cell>0.1</cell>
                            <cell>0.3</cell>
                            <cell>0.4</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>200′</cell>
                            <cell>0.1</cell>
                            <cell>0.1</cell>
                            <cell>0.2</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Thus, for example, for an SS–18 having a CEP of 450′, only one <gloss target="#t_RV_1">RV</gloss> would be needed to destroy an existing silo
                        with 90% confidence, but nine RVs would be required to damage an enhanced
                        superhard silo with 90% confidence. The estimates in the table above exclude
                        any survivability gains that would accrue from fratricide caused by closely
                        spaced basing of silos. Calculations of fratricide effects for superhard
                        silos arrayed in CSB will be completed in 6–9 months. (Comment: These will
                        be the interesting calculations: if they show strong symbiosis between CSB
                        and superhardening, it may be useful to reevaluate the concepts for SICBM
                        basing, and indeed the marginal utility of the deploying SICBM versus more
                            <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>Past DNA estimates of crater size (never measured precisely in the past
                        because potential hardness increases were not expected), so new estimates
                        are being undertaken. A one megaton detonation might create a crater having
                        a lip hard to 200–300,000 psi.</p>
                    <p>Superhard silos should be located in dry soil, but not rock or wet soil. Dry
                        soil craters are smaller than wet soil craters. Craters in rock would be
                        even smaller, but seismologists think rock would shear, destroying the silo.
                        This hypothesis cannot be tested without using nuclear detonations, but
                        scientists believe it is valid.</p>
                    <p>In small-scale tests engineers are trying to figure out where to put the
                        steel. Radial steel appears to be better than hoop steel. Tests of the 24′
                        scale silo model had a 7–8% steel content.</p>
                    <p>Tests show that motions and stresses on a silo from a second detonation are
                        less than those from the first, because the first one compacts the earth
                        around the silo. But to compact earth as a construction technique in
                        building silos would be too expensive.</p>
                    <p>Silos built at ground level tend to be pushed partially out of the ground by
                        the first shot, thus making them vulnerable to a second. But this can be
                        solved by building silos slightly underground, which will also help protect
                        them against thermal and radiation effects.</p>
                    <p>The problem of source regioning <gloss target="#t_EMP_1">EMP</gloss> effects
                        is also being examined.</p>
                    <p>Superhard silos are doing well in tests against motion effects. The <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> is capable of withstanding [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>], and the SICBM can
                        be designed without much difficulty to withstand [<hi rend="italic">less
                            than 1 line not declassified</hi>]<hi rend="italic">.</hi> While fiber
                        optic communications is adequate for peacetime communications with silos,
                        antennae will be needed for wartime launch from airplanes and mobile
                        LCCs.</p>
                    <pb facs="0105" n="74" xml:id="pg_74"/>
                    <p>Missile egress is a problem from surface bursts. Recently a successful test
                        took place in which a multistage actuator pushed up a sleeve through debris,
                        enabling the gas-driven cannister to surface into launch position.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">SICBM</p>
                    <p>Gorman said the <persName corresp="#p_SBA_1">Scowcroft</persName> Commission
                        timetable is what paces the SICBM program, not technology. If the <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> were defeated today, an SICBM with modified
                        AIRS guidance could be ready in about four-and- one-half years. But the
                        current SICBM program has decelerators built into it. If the SICBM had to
                        meet only the specifications of the Trident C–4 missile, it could be built
                        for 25–30% less cost, but this wouldn’t be salable. At present the Air Force
                        is looking at a stellar inertial and two ring laser guidance systems as
                        possibilities for the SICBM. Guidance is one-half the cost of the SICBM.</p>
                    <p>A mobile launcher hardened to 30–50 psi deployed in an area of 2.5–4.0 sq.
                        mi. would exact an attack price of one SS–18 warhead. A soft truck hardened
                        to three psi deployed over an area of 100 sq. mi. would exact the same
                        attack price. We learned from the <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss>
                        experience that we cannot get public lands, or military bases being used for
                        something else, as basing locales for a new <gloss target="#t_ICBM_1">ICBM</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>A hard mobile SICBM, mounted on a vehicle capable of doing 30 mi/hr and based
                        along a 1,000 mile perimeter enclosing a square could move up to 4 miles
                        inside the perimeter to protect against a short-warning <gloss target="#t_SLBM_1">SLBM</gloss> attack. This potential deployment area
                        of 4,000 sq. mi. could be doubled if missiles could move either inside or
                        outside the perimeter.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Cost Comparisons for Missiles and Basing Modes</p>
                    <p>Assuming that $16 billion has already been spent on the <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> program, following are incremental costs
                        (1982 dollars) for alternative 1989 basing options for both <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> and SICBM:</p>
                    <table xml:id="table004">
                        <row>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Missile/Basing Mode</hi></cell>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Incremental Cost</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>100 MX/100 Super/CSB</cell>
                            <cell>$16 billion</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>100 MX/100 Super/MM</cell>
                            <cell>16</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>100 MX/500 Super</cell>
                            <cell>30</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>500 SICBM/500 Super/CSB</cell>
                            <cell>49</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>450 SICBM/450 Super/MM II</cell>
                            <cell>44</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>500 SICBM/Hard Mobile</cell>
                            <cell>44</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>500 SICBM/Continuous Road Mobile</cell>
                            <cell>43</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <pb facs="0106" n="75" xml:id="pg_75"/>
                    <p>Procurement of an additional 100 <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss> missiles,
                        beyond the first 100, would cost $3 billion (excluding basing costs).</p>
                    <p>The incremental cost for construction alone of 100 superhardened silos is
                        about $35 million per silo, but total incremental cost (including, for
                        example, electronics and communications hookup) is $150–200 million per
                        silo.</p>
                    <p>The cost of an SICBM is one-half the cost of an <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss>, making the cost per warhead of the SICBM five times greater
                        than for the <gloss target="#t_MX_1">MX</gloss>.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital"><gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss></p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Technologies</hi>. <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss>
                        requires advances in a number of technologies: microelectronics, advanced
                        computers and netting, advanced radars and optical sensors, improved
                        discrimination techniques, non-nuclear kill mechanisms, directed energy
                        weapons, and improved space launch capabilities. Non-nuclear kill mechanisms
                        are desirable both for political reasons and because they do not disrupt the
                        battlefield environment.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Discrimination</hi>. Below 300,000 feet the Army has
                        responsibility, and it has made a lot of progress. We have reasonable
                        confidence also for boost phase discrimination technologies. In the last ten
                        years, great gains have been made in optical sensors, especially for the
                        terminal phase. We are now collecting optical data at Kwajalein on all
                        missile flights.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Astrodome Defense</hi>s. What “miracles” are needed for us
                        to be able to deploy an astrodome defense?</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>○</label>
                        <item>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] a feat
                            especially difficult for kinetic energy weapons;</item>
                        <label>○</label>
                        <item>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] a difficult
                            task, but one perhaps not so difficult as some believe since we [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]</item>
                        <label>○</label>
                        <item>low-leakage mid-course discrimination (we have little data on
                            mid-course flight, and almost none on false targets in
                            mid-course).</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (9 lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                    <p>We need an aggressive program to collect data for <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> research, [<hi rend="italic">1 line not
                        declassified</hi>]</p>
                    <p>It will be hard to develop lasers for target kill.</p>
                    <p>Deployment of sensors for <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> could, by
                        itself, enhance deterrence. For example, non-continuously mobile ICBMs need
                        warning to be survivable.</p>
                    <p>[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (4 lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                    <p>The nearest-term <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> layers are terminal and
                        midcourse technologies being developed by the Army. It is quickest to deploy
                            <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> “from the ground up.”</p>
                    <pb facs="0107" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/>
                    <p>The concept of ground-based, blue-green lasers using mirrors in space is
                        being considered for communications with submerged submarines.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_SDIO_1">SDIO</gloss> very much wants to keep the <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> program focused on long-term research, and
                        not on a specific mission. But a very modest defense could be valuable
                        against a highly-stylized Soviet attack.</p>
                    <p>At the end of the session, <persName corresp="#p_FJS_1">John
                            Foster</persName> made a case for hard target terminal defense. He
                        commented also that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> may need a
                        nuclear system in order to get an effective defense.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>