<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1985-04-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1985-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="29" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d29">
                    <head>29. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d29fn1">Source: Department of State, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName>’s Personal Files 1953, 1972–1989, Lot 90D397,
                            March and April 1985. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PS_1">Pifer</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1985-04-05">April 5, 1985</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Nitze–Linhard Meeting, April 5, 1985</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> gave <persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Linhard</persName> a paper<note n="2" xml:id="d29fn2">See <ref target="#d30fn6">footnote 6, Document 30</ref>.</note> with
                        themes the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> should use when addressing
                            <gloss target="#t_SDI_1">SDI</gloss> and a memo noting his problems with
                        the President’s March 29 speech.<note n="3" xml:id="d29fn3">For <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName>’s memorandum, see <ref target="#d30">Document 30</ref>; for <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>’s March 29 speech, see <ref target="#d27">Document 27</ref>.</note>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Linhard</persName> scanned the themes and said
                        they looked fine; he would undertake to turn them into “policy” from the
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>. Regarding the President’s speech,
                            <persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Linhard</persName> understood <persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName>’s concerns but there were strongly
                        held views in the White House; he had done what he could to improve on the
                        original draft.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the transition paper, <persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Linhard</persName> said he had some basic problems. While he wanted to
                        reflect further on the paper, he offered three preliminary comments: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>the paper’s focus on terminal defense was inconsistent with recent
                                NSDDs which focused on “high-leverage” defenses, i.e., <pb facs="0120" n="89" xml:id="pg_89"/> space-based systems that
                                would attack ballistic missiles in the boost and mid-course
                                phases;</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>he was unsure about the paper’s focus on doing away with hard
                                target kill systems; and</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>the offensive force levels needed to be considered in light of
                                    <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> targeting
                                requirements.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_NPH_1">Nitze</persName> emphasized that the paper was a
                        first cut and was premised on a cooperative transition between the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.
                        The <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> would have to think about the
                        uncooperative scenario, which was the more likely case.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Linhard</persName> doubted that ground-based
                        terminal defenses were politically doable in the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>, e.g., “the dump trucks full of environmental impact
                        statements.” He was concerned the Soviets might agree to a cooperative
                        transition but restrict it to terminal defenses (in which he felt they might
                        have a competitive advantage). Moreover, terminal defenses were more
                        appropriate for a hardened target set, an area where the Soviets were
                        clearly ahead.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Linhard</persName> promised to send over his
                        detailed comments on the transition paper. In the meantime, he strongly
                        urged that the paper not be sent to the <gloss target="#t_IG_1">IG</gloss>.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>