<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Nelson to  to Mr.
                            Fish</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1871</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d306</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">306</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1871-04-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1871-04-12T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131" lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884" lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-04-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-04-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="306" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d306">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 286.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Nelson</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Fish</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 377.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-04-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi>
                                12, 1871</date>. (Received May 22.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In fulfillment of the promise contained in my
                        dispatch No. 365, of March 23, I now proceed to furnish some data concerning
                        the railroad now in process of construction between this city and the port
                        of Vera Cruz. I went carefully over the completed as well as much of the
                        unfinished work on this line, accompanied by several officers of the railway
                        company, who supplied me with every facility for thorough observation.</p>
                <p>The total length of this railway, when completed, will be two hundred <pb facs="0846" n="632" xml:id="pg_632"/> and sixty-one miles. A branch,
                        thirty miles long, now connects the main line with the city of Puebla; it
                        leaves the main line at the station of Apizaco, eighty-six and a half miles
                        from the city of Mexico. In 1864 a contract was entered into for the
                        construction of this line, a small portion of it being then in operation for
                        traffic, though in a very imperfect condition. The contract by an English
                        company (Smith, Knight &amp; Co.) included the purchase of the open
                        sections, and the putting them into a thoroughly satisfactory condition. In
                        October, 1864, the engineers of the company, Colonel Talcott and Mr. Samuel,
                        were both in Mexico, and the contractors’ agent commenced work, and carried
                        it on vigorously, until the month of May, 1866, when the works were
                        suspended in consequence of the non-payment of the subvention by the
                        so-called government of the empire.</p>
                <p>In November, 1866, Colonel Talcott resigned, and Mr. Alister Fraser was
                        appointed to act as resident engineer in Mexico. A new arrangement was
                        entered into, by which the works were to be carried out by Mr. George B.
                        Crawley as contractor, in place of Smith, Knight &amp; Co. After a series of
                        interruptions and difficulties, during the siege of Mexico, a new
                        commencement was made, and the company’s resident engineer, Mr. Fraser,
                        became engineer for the contractor. Mr. Samuel was made consulting engineer
                        to the board in London, and Mr. William Cross Buchanan was appointed the
                        company’s chief engineer, in direct charge of all the works. Unfortunately,
                        Mr. Fraser was shortly taken ill, and was obliged to go home. As soon as Mr.
                        Crawley, the contractor, became aware of this, he appointed Mr. Thomas
                        Braniff as his agent in Mexico, and the works have been steadily pushed on
                        for the last two years in a very satisfactory manner. Mr. Braniff is a
                        citizen of the United States, a man of great energy and administrative
                        ability, and has achieved an honorable reputation in connection with the
                        construction of railways in the republic of Chili. The branch to Puebla was
                        finished and opened to the public on the 16th day of September, 1869, and
                        the works in the Tierra Caliente were started afresh on a new survey in
                        November, 1869, and on the 1st of January of the present year some seven and
                        a half miles of the most difficult work on the line were completed and
                        opened to the public.</p>
                <p>Several large works have been successfully erected on the lower section just
                        opened; and the line has been completed from Vera Cruz inland for a distance
                        of fifty-five miles.</p>
                <p>Mr. Braniff has the work well in hand, and expects to have the line finished
                        by July as far as a place called Fortin, about seventy miles from Vera,
                        Cruz. Several bridges have been erected of iron and stone, three of them
                        over 100 feet in height, and in spans of from 140 to 66 feet. At the Fortin
                        mentioned above a very large barranca or gully occurs. Various designs were
                        submitted for a bridge over this, and the last one, designed by Mr. William
                        Cross Buchanan, was a suspension-bridge of 900 feet span, to be principally
                        of steel. These designs were, however, all abandoned, and a new line was
                        surveyed which will pass down on one side of the barranca, cross the Metlac
                        River on a comparatively small bridge, and, rising on the opposite side,
                        join the original line at a convenient point. This line will cost much less,
                        and be a solid road throughout, with gradients of 1 in 40, or 2½ per cent.,
                        and 1 in 33, or 3 per cent., and no curve less than 350 feet radius. A very
                        great saving to the company will be effected by this new line, and at least
                        twelve months will be gained in time.</p>
                <p>The total distance at present open to the public (including the branch) is
                        one hundred and sixty-three miles, leaving one hundred and twenty-eight <pb facs="0847" n="633" xml:id="pg_633"/> miles to complete. A very large
                        portion of these one hundred and twenty-eight miles is partially completed
                        already. In one portion, a distance of over seventy miles, 90 per cent. is
                        finished of the earthworks; and over the portion called the <hi rend="italic">Cumbres</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Maltrata</hi>, where
                        there are curves of 350 feet radius, and a continuous grade for twenty-two
                        miles of 4 percent., or one in twenty-five, over 60 per cent. of the
                        earth-works are finished.</p>
                <p>Two years’ steady work would complete the whole line, and when opened to the
                        public will, in my opinion, be one of the best paying lines in the world.
                        There could be no competition, and every pound of traffic that now is
                        carried over the roads on mules or in wagons would go by rail. To the
                        traveling public diligence journeys would become a dream of the past, and
                        Mexico would advance, as all nations do where railways exist.</p>
                <p>The management of this railway is in the hands of a board of directors in
                        London, and in Mexico there is a local board composed of five directors. The
                        opened sections are managed by a traffic manager appointed by the
                        company.</p>
                <p>When completed, the Mexican Bailway will be, in an engineering point of view,
                        one of the exceptional railways of the world, and in a commercial view I
                        believe it will be a most perfect success. From the present returns of
                        traffic it is impossible to calculate what the future returns may be.
                        Railways in most countries have created a traffic for themselves, and Mexico
                        will not be behind in this respect. Wars and <hi rend="italic">pronunciamentos</hi> will gradually cease, and peace and prosperity
                        will follow in the track of the locomotive.</p>
                <p>The obliging superintendent of traffic, Mr. W. H. Mills, has furnished me the
                        following:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of the receipts and expenditures on the two
                            opened sections of the line:</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">MEXICO AND PUEBLA SECTION.</p>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Length, 115¾ miles.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total receipts for the six months ending December 31, 1870</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">$332,233 95 <hi rend="superscript">6</hi>/8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total working expenses for the six months ending December 31,
                                1870</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">166,989 22⅞</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Balance</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">165,244 72⅞</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total receipts for the two months, January and February,
                                1871</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">$107,473 29⅞</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total working expenses</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">53,089 48½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Balance</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">54,383 81⅜</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="center">VERA CRUZ SECTION.</p>
                <table cols="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell>Length, 47¼ miles.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total receipts for the six months ending December 31, 1871</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">$96,937 25¼</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total working expenses.</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">92,147 28½</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Balance</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">4,789 96¾</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total receipts for the two months, January and February,
                                1871</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap" role="num">$46,902 26⅜</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Total working expenses</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">35,277 86¾</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Balance</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #border-bottom" role="num">11,624 39⅝</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The amount of money that is annually paid to this company by the federal
                        government of Mexico amounts to about $1,000,000, viz, $560,000 as
                        subvention, and 15 per cent. of the importation duties on all the
                        custom-houses.</p>
                <pb facs="0848" n="634" xml:id="pg_634"/>
                <p>Upon my return to the capital I addressed a brief note to the department for
                        foreign affairs, announcing my arrival, and returning thanks for official
                        courtesies, (A,) to which Mr. Aspiroz replied on the 28th ultimo, (B.)</p>
                <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>THOMAS H. NELSON.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">A.</note>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Nelson</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Aspiroz</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Mexico,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-03-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 27, 1871.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to advise you of my
                            return to the capital, and to express to the department over which you
                            preside, and also through you to the governors of the States of Puebla
                            and Vera Cruz, and the military commandant of that division, my grateful
                            acknowledgments for the official courtesies and honors that were
                            extended to me during my journey and residence in those States.</p>
                    <p>I beg leave to renew the assurances of my high consideration, and to
                            subscribe myself your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>THOMAS H. NELSON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">B.</note>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Aspiroz</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Nelson</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Mexico,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-03-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 28, 1871.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have had the honor to receive your
                            excellency’s polite note of yesterday, in which you inform me of your
                            return to this capital from Vera Cruz.</p>
                    <p>The supreme government is pleased to learn that your excellency made your
                            journey without accident, as well because it takes an interest in your
                            excellency’s personal prosperity as because your presence near the
                            government of Mexico is a valued guarantee of the friendship and cordial
                            relations which ought to bind the Mexican republic to that of the United
                            States of America.</p>
                    <p>With this occasion I have the honor to reiterate the high and
                            distinguished consideration with which I am your excellency’s very
                            obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>MANUEL ASPIROZ.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
