<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Low to to Mr. Fish</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1871</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1871-05-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1871-05-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-05-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-05-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="43"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 30.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Low</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Fish</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 68.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">On board Flag-ship Colorado</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Harbor of Nagasaki,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-05-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 13, 1871.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> By the last mail I received a dispatch from H. M.
                    Brent, esq., United States chargé d’ affaires in Peru, inclosing a document
                    written in the Chinese language, which he supposed was a petition from the <pb
                        facs="0327" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/> Chinese laborers in Peru to their
                    government, and asking me to forward it to Prince Kung, if, after examination, I
                    found it a proper communication. I have the honor to send herewith copy of Mr.
                    Brent’s dispatch, and a translation of its inclosure; the original of the letter
                    has been sent to Mr. Williams, with instructions to present it to the prince, as
                    requested. This document furnishes additional proof of the barbarities and
                    miseries inseparable from the coolie trade; and although it may not produce such
                    a profound impression upon the Chinese government as it would upon that of any
                    western nation, it will prove one of the many lessons by means of which the
                    officials of China will be made to realize their international obligations, and
                    induce the government to conform its action to the rule recognized as binding
                    upon all other countries. The fact of these people appealing to be placed under
                    the protection of the representative of the United States, in order that their
                    hardships and sufferings may be ameliorated, cannot fail to impress upon the
                    Chinese that there is a clear line of distinction to be drawn between foreign
                    nations and the principles of honesty and humanity by which they are governed,
                    of which the Chinese people generally have a very faint idea.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>FREDERICK F. LOW.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Brent</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Low</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States, Lima</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Peru,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-01-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 27, 1871.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to inclose herewith a
                        document in Chinese, with its envelope, that has been handed me by the
                        Chinese resident in this capital. It is directed to his excellency Prince
                        Kung; and if you, after having become acquainted with its contents, see fit
                        to deliver it to the Chinese Foreign Office, you will confer a favor upon
                        its authors. I am entirely ignorant of its tenor.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>H. M. BRENT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">Translation of the Chinese document inclosed in the
                                dispatch of the United States chargé d’affaires at Lima, of date
                                27th January,</hi> 1871, <hi rend="italic">to the minister of the
                                United States at Peking.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Note</hi>.—The document is a petition by the
                            representatives of certain Chinese societies in Lima, setting forth the
                            distress of coolie emigrants in Peru, and praying that a Chinese envoy
                            may be appointed to inquire into their condition; or, failing in this,
                            that the United States minister to Peru may be invested with authority
                            to act as such envoy. The date of the petition is 26th January, 1871.
                            The cover is dated 10th year of Tung-Chih, first moon, 26th day, and is
                            stamped with the name of the Fukeên and Swatow Guild, the Kwang Tung
                            Guild, and the Tung Shêng club, of Lima.</p>
                        <p>The petition is in very good literary style; the person to whom it is
                            addressed is probably the United States minister at Lima, though no name
                            or title excepting “your excellency” appears in it.</p>
                        <p rend="center">[Translation.]</p>
                        <p>Chêng Chuan, Wen Têh-lin, Chêng Chun-ta, and Lin Hu-shih, representing
                            the Kwang Tung and Fu-Keên Guilds, all being Chinese subjects lost
                            abroad, with their foreheads to the ground, present a petition to your
                            excellency. They cast themselves upon your heaven-like intelligence,
                            that the insolent deception and cruelly oppressive treatment, suffered
                            by Chinese subjects at the hands of wicked barbarians, may be inquired
                            into. Petitioners would humbly set forth that the reason why, though
                            born and bred in China, they took service abroad is because they were
                            unable to gain a livelihood at home, owing to the swarm [like bees] of
                            rebels and robbers from the fourth year of Heen Fêng, (1854.) Later, in
                            the eighth year of Heen Fêng, (1858,) there appeared a joint
                            notification by his excellency Hwang, governor general of the two Kwang
                            provinces, and his excellency Pih, governor of Kwang Tung, to the effect
                                <pb facs="0328" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> that rules of agreement
                            had been entered into with England and France, with reference to the
                            engagement of laborers to go to Peru, the period of service to be eighth
                            years, on the expiry of which term those thus engaged to be sent home,
                            etc., etc.; and consequently the number of emigrants who have come to
                            Peru since that year is no less than several myriads. But, far from what
                            was expected, the barbarians have shown themselves treacherous in many
                            ways. In China, when they were seeking men, they spoke of our taking
                            service as laborers, and designated us “guests,” [<hi rend="italic">i
                                e</hi>., <hi rend="italic">visitors</hi> abroad;] on landing in
                            their country, however, they said we had “sold ourselves,” and called us
                            “slaves.” Furthermore, they beat and swear at us with great violence,
                            and feed and clothe us insufficiently; they brand two characters on the
                            side of the face as is done in China in cases of banishment; they fasten
                            shackles on the ankles, just as if we were captured prisoners. We have
                            to till the soil or dig canals, day and night; with dogging and beating
                            to death, one cannot reckon the number of resentful ghosts.
                            Notwithstanding rules of agreement were drawn up, in how many instances
                            have they been regarded? While it was stated that we should be sent
                            home, yet, who, we ask, has been so sent on the expiry of the term of
                            service? Alas! Alas! Your suppliants went forth from a land of reason
                            and justice to one where no sense of right prevails; from being the
                            faithful subjects of a great country we have unwittingly fallen into the
                            poisonous clutch of barbarian slaves. We humbly submit that having [in
                            going abroad] shown ourselves disloyal to our sovereign and unfilial to
                            our ancestors, the indiction upon us of insult and oppression does not
                            indeed merit commiseration; still, the treatment we, his subjects,
                            receive gives our Emperor cause to blush, and is a stain upon our
                            ancestors. How very painful it is to speak or think of this! In the
                            first moon of the ninth year of Tûng Chih, a petition was forwarded
                            through the United States magistrate [? consul] to the minister, praying
                            him to intercede. On the 21st day of the 4th moon a reply [from the
                            consul] was received to the effect that he hoped the United States
                            minister would examine the circumstances with compassion, and devise
                            means of relief, so that those desiring to remain should no longer be
                            subjected to oppression, and those desiring to return home might do so
                            at an early day. This the consul earnestly hoped; and further, this
                            matter had been fully communicated to their excellencies, the envoys
                            from China to the different powers, Mr. Burlingame, Chih, and Sun, for
                            their information, &amp;c.; such was the reply to the position. But
                            although we have been favored with the sympathy of these high officials,
                            still our extreme distress has been too great to be relieved, and from
                            day to day the oppression grows worse. The avarice and cruelty of the
                            wealthy merchants is wolf-like, and the vexatious treatment of the
                            foreign [Peruvian] officials is like a tiger. Our countrymen cannot make
                            a motion without its being construed into a fault. What is the
                            explanation of all this? England, France, and the United States, and the
                            various nations great and small, whose people are engaged in commerce
                            here, and go to and fro, have each established an official called
                            “consul,” a man sent out from his own country; again, there are ships of
                            war every year visiting and looking about, and each nation has its
                            resident minister to exercise control. Hence the officials and people of
                            Peru do not dare to commit such acts as they pleas-with the people of
                            other nationalities, and the reason why all kinds of tyranny is visited
                            upon Chinese alone is verily that our heavenly dynasty has no ships of
                            war to visit and inspect, and no minister to exercise control on the
                            spot. With the majesty of the Emperor extending to the four seas, and
                            his goodness pervading every place, we humbly venture to ask why this
                            hateful tribe should be permitted to give the rein to their violence and
                            audacity, to the grievous affliction of his subjects?</p>
                        <p>Your petitioners, in sore distress at the cruelties inflicted, and with a
                            sense of resentment for the living and the dead, have prepared a
                            petition in common, supplicating your favor to save and lift them up;
                            they would beg your excellency to have the Emperor memorialized to
                            exercise his special grace, and commission an envoy to proceed to Peru
                            to make an investigation, when the wicked barbarians must certainly put
                            a stop to their cruel conduct; or, failing this, to commission the
                            minister of the United States to act for him. Then the restoration of
                            your humble petitioners from death to life will be the gift of your
                            excellency. On our knees we present this petition, praying that your
                            excellency’s posterity may be ennobled for all generations.</p>
                        <p>The humble members of the Kwang Tung Guild, and of the Fukeen Guild,
                            prostrate themselves.</p>
                        <p>Petition presented on the 26th day of January, (according to the
                            occidental date.)</p>
                        <p>True translation:</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>EDWD. B. DREW.</signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-05-11">
                                    <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 11, 1871</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
