<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Bailey to to Mr. Davis.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1871</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1871-04-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1871-04-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recfIX2Uumy8inHEq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85144526"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wages</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107622"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prostitutes</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1871-04-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1871-04-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="56"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 43.</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Bailey</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Davis.</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 35.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate, Hong Kong</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1871-04-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 25, 1871</date>. (Received June
                        20.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The subject of Chinese emigration from this port
                    to the United States has claimed my careful thought and patient investigation
                    for the last four months, with a view to get at the facts, and to understand it
                    in its surroundings and bearings. The whole subject is an anomaly. Rules that
                    will do elsewhere in the world, when applied in considering questions of
                    immigration, have no application to Chinese immigration to the United States.
                    Immigrants to America from other parts of the world go of their own volition,
                    free and voluntary. Emigration from China to all parts of the world is an
                    organized business or trade, in which men of large capital, and hongs of great
                    wealth, engage as a regular traffic, by which men are bought and sold for so
                    much per head, precisely as a piece of merchandise is handled, at its market
                    value. The poor laborer of Europe applies his own scanty means to get to the
                    land of promise, or is assisted by his friends, charitable societies, or
                    benevolent institutions, to reach a place where he hopes to have his toil
                    properly requited, where his labor will inure to his own benefit. The cooly of
                    China is bought by the rich trader to serve his purchaser at low wages for a
                    series of years in a foreign country, under contract for the faithful
                    performance of which in many instances he gives a mortgage on his wife and
                    children, with a stipulation that at the end of his term of service he is to be
                    brought back to China by his purchaser. This contract is sold by the dealer
                    through his agents in the United States and elsewhere at a large advance, and is
                    a source of great profit to capitalists who have the means to buy and sell large
                    numbers of men. This contract, in the United States, is no doubt null and void,
                        <pb facs="0422" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/> but nevertheless the cooly will
                    comply strictly with all its terms, a copy of which in Chinese characters is
                    always in his possession, and this he will do because his purchaser holds his
                    household <hi rend="italic">lares</hi> in the land to which he always hopes and
                    expects to return, in pledge for the faithful performance of his bonds. The
                    central idea of a Chinaman’s religion, if he has any religion at all, is that of
                    the worship of the tombs of his ancestors. The superstitions of Fung-Shusy
                    dominate him wherever he may be in the world. The subtile mysticisms of China so
                    strangely govern all its people in their social, political, and quasi religious
                    life, are as a hook in his nose, by which his purchaser controls him at all
                    times and in all places; and thus this relation of master and quasi slave, no
                    matter how many miles apart, is welded by the mystical links of religious
                    superstitions, family ties, and rights of ancestral tombs, which control and
                    regulate the reciprocal duties of trader and coolie in the home land.</p>
                <p>The means of obtaining coolies are as various as the ingenuity of man can devise,
                    and are as corrupt as the incentive to large gains can stimulate and invent. Men
                    and boys are decoyed by all sorts of tricks, opiates, and illusory promises,
                    info the haunts of the traders. Once in the clutches of these men-dealers, by a
                    system of treachery and terrorism, connived at by the local Chinese authorities,
                    whose chief business in life is to “squeeze” the people, the stupefied cooly is
                    overawed into making a contract under such Chinese influences and surroundings
                    as give it a sacredness of character nowhere else known in the world. From that
                    moment he is the mere tool of the rich dealer wherever he may go. It is
                    difficult for persons accustomed to western civilization to understand the depth
                    and extent of this relationship, but Chinese civilization is unique, perhaps
                    opaque, and cannot be measured by that of any other.</p>
                <p>The above is a mere outline of the system, and is the general rule that controls
                    Chinese emigration. Contact with American ideas and the spirit of American law
                    has, in some measure, modified the rule as applied to Chinese emigrants going to
                    the United States, so that there is in reality free and voluntary emigration;
                    but it is so surrounded, mixed up, and tainted with the virus of the coolie
                    trade, as to require the utmost vigilance and scrutiny to separate the
                    legitimate from the illegitimate emigration.</p>
                <p>I am charged under the law with the duty of giving to every American vessel
                    leaving this port with Chinese emigrants, a permit or certificate, setting forth
                    the fact that each person is a free and voluntary emigrant, but that the same
                    shall not be given until I am first personally satisfied, by evidence produced,
                    of the truth of the facts therein contained. I find among my consular duties,
                    prescribed by the consular regulations of 1868, that I am—</p>
                <p>“To repress and discourage, by all proper means, the traffic in laborers, usually
                    called the cooly trade.” It is fully expected that they (consular officers) will
                    carefully see that its provisions (act of February 19, 1862) are strictly
                    observed. The Secretary of State, in his circular of January 17, 1867, says:
                    “You are consequently directed to make use of all the authority, power, and
                    influence at your command, towards preventing and discouraging the carrying on
                    of the traffic referred to in any way.”</p>
                <p>In the consular regulations of 1870, concerning the act of February 19, 1862, I
                    find the following instructions:</p>
                <p>Consuls will be rigid in exacting a compliance with these provisions.</p>
                <p>I have made the above recapitulation to show the Secretary of State the stand
                    point from which I am viewing the subject, and the lights that are guiding me in
                    the course I am pursuing; and to ask, if I am taking too serious a view of the
                    matter, for such further instructions as the better judgment of the Secretary
                    may think proper and advisable.</p>
                <pb facs="0423" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/>
                <p>In consideration of the foregoing the first question that arises is, how shall I
                    perform the duties devolving upon me in this matter? The number of emigrants is
                    so large as to make it impossible for me to examine each person, and in addition
                    attend to the various and arduous duties of this consulate. I must, therefore,
                    either abandon the execution of the law as an idle form, or I must appoint a
                    corps of assistants, sufficient in number, in integrity and sagacity, to make
                    the examination a rigid and faithful compliance with the letter and spirit of
                    the law. Heretofore, I am free to say, from all I have been able to learn, the
                    whole proceeding in this regard has been a complete farce.</p>
                <p>I have not the means to pay for these assistants, for my salary is hardly
                    sufficient to support me in the plainest and most economical manner possible for
                    me to adopt. Therefore I must allow these assistants to charge a fee such as
                    will make reasonable compensation for their services, labor, and expenses in and
                    about the matter. I can procure men of small capacity and less integrity to
                    undertake the task for a mere trifle; but this would make an expense without any
                    good in return, for such an examination would be neither thorough nor reliable.
                    The only safe rule is to put the matter in charge of first-class men, and allow
                    them to collect such fees as shall be reasonable compensation for their
                    services. Even this plan, which seems to me at present to be the best, is not
                    satisfactory to my mind, for the reason that it will necessarily involve an
                    expense that may be the subject of irritation; but I do not know what better to
                    do than to try it, and by carefully watching reduce it, as experience may
                    suggest, to the lowest possible cost.</p>
                <p>While the law, my instructions, and the condition of affairs here are as at
                    present, I deem this examination by assistants as indispensable, and the
                    necessary expense must follow it, unless the law and the facts are to be ignored
                    and investigation abandoned.</p>
                <p>Perhaps it will oocur to the mind of the Secretary that a thorough investigation
                    here as to the character of the emigrants going to the United States, and a
                    check to prevent the now world-famed atrocities at Macao being practiced or
                    winked at here, will largely negative the clamor of a growing public opinion in
                    the United States hostile to the introduction of Chinese or servile labor, to
                    compete with the great free-labor interests of our own country. Chinese
                    emigration to the United States brings the opposite civilizations of the East
                    and the West face to face, and it occurs to me that Congress is wise in throwing
                    all the safeguards possible around the introduction of heathen labor, to prevent
                    its bringing harm to our institutions. I am convinced that China is on the verge
                    of a great cataclysm of some kind, and I believe it will result in sending
                    immense numbers of Chinese, with the good and bad that is in them, to the United
                    States. The facilities of ships and steamers will do it easily and cheaply, and
                    they will go to escape unbearable evils here; whether to introduce unbearable
                    evils there remains to be seen.</p>
                <p>I have said that this traffic in laborers is exceedingly profitable; therefore I
                    cannot expect that anything that will hamper it, by investigation or otherwise,
                    will be popular with the men-dealers or with the great interests interlocked
                    with it. It prostitutes everybody here, and thus far has prostrated every one
                    who has stood up against it.</p>
                <p>It will be asserted that I am putting obstacles in the way of commerce. I will
                    endeavor to do my duty, let the consequences care for themselves. Well, so far
                    as concerns that commerce which has for its object the buying and selling of
                    men, I propose to put obstacles in its way. Legitimate emigration and legitimate
                    commerce shall have my active co-operation and encouragement in every possible
                    lawful way; but if commerce <pb facs="0424" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/> demands at
                    my hands assistance in a new mode of enslaving men, differing from the African
                    slave-trade “in little else than the employment of fraud instead of force to
                    make its victims captive,” will not lend my aid to build up its nefarious
                    traffic, nor bow to the behests of the great houses that are interested in
                    forcing this great wrong.</p>
                <p>I have the honor, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>D. H. BAILEY.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
