<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-08-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="204" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d204">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">751G.94/165</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>)</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-08-07">August 7, 1940</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>This afternoon I called on the Foreign Minister and after calling his
                        attention to the reports that France has received secret demands from Japan
                        in regard to Indochina, I addressed to the Minister the substance of
                        paragraph 2 of the Department’s telegram No. 293, August 6, 1 p.m., and
                        conveyed to him, as instructed, the concern with which the Government of the
                        United States regarded the developments reported.</p>
                    <p>In replying to my opening remarks, the Minister said that (1) he wished to
                        withhold his comment; (2) that admitting certain demands had been made on
                        Indochina, still he could not reveal their precise character; and (3) that
                        in regard to a recent article in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>,
                        a cabled report of which he had with him, he considered its various points
                        as either grossly exaggerated or completely unfounded. The Minister declined
                        to comment on the two demands listed in the Department’s telegram.</p>
                    <pb facs="0357" n="291" xml:id="pg_291"/>
                    <p>In departing, I presented the Minister with copies of the Secretary’s
                        statements of April 17 and May 11, and stressed the attitude of the American
                        Government towards maintaining the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> with
                        regard to the entire Pacific area, including both French Indochina and the
                        Netherlands East Indies.</p>
                    <p>I was told by the Minister and authorized to inform the Department in strict
                        confidence that the Japanese demands had been already accepted in principle
                        by the French Government.</p>
                    <p>An official of the Information Bureau, sent by the Foreign Minister, arrived
                        later in the afternoon with the message that it was the wish of the Japanese
                        Government not to disclose the object of my call and therefore the press
                        would be told that I had called about the Gendarmerie case in Shanghai.<note n="6b" xml:id="d204fn6b">See telegram No. 671, July 22, 1940, 1 p.m.,
                            from the Consul at Shanghai, <ref target="#pg_101">p. 101</ref>.</note>
                        I sent back the reply that whereas I was convinced that the Department would
                        not betray any confidence, it might deem it necessary to release to the
                        American public that I had called in connection with alleged Japanese
                        demands concerning Indochina, and that hence it would be understood that in
                        no way could I have committed my Government on this point. Further, to say
                        that I had called in connection with the Shanghai Gendarmerie case would not
                        be true, and therefore I suggested that it be reported that I called for
                        “various routine matters”. The Foreign Office informed us, after further
                        telephone conversation that the press release would say that I had called to
                        inquire about press reports published abroad regarding late developments in
                        relations between French Indochina and Japan, and that the reports were
                        declared to be inaccurate by the Foreign Minister.</p>
                    <closer><signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">oseph</hi>] C. G[<hi rend="smallcaps">rew</hi>]</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>