<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-02-26T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-02-26T12:00:00-05:00" n="222" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Pacific War/134: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-02-27T02:00:00+09:00">February 27, 1941—2
                            a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 4:55 p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                    <p>317. In the course of my conversation today with the Foreign Minister he went
                        out of his way to accuse the British Government of taking measures in the
                        Far East which were a direct incitement to Japan and which rendered very
                        difficult an improvement in the situation. He referred in this connection to
                        the reported mining of Singapore and the sending of Australian troops to the
                        Malaya-Thailand border.</p>
                    <pb facs="0375" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/>
                    <p>I said that it seemed to me extraordinary that the Japanese should interpret
                        and characterize obviously defensive measures as measures of offense. As I
                        had said to the Minister at the American-Japan Society luncheon,<note n="21" xml:id="d222fn21">See <ref target="#pg_129">p. 129</ref>.</note> we must
                        inevitably be guided by “facts and actions” and that certainly the facts and
                        actions relating to Japan’s southward advance were concrete causes for
                        serious anxiety not only on the part of Great Britain but of ourselves.
                        Having occupied in succession Waichow, Hainan, the Spratly Islands, and
                        other areas, the Japanese military were now pouring troops into Indo-China
                        and, according to our informer, had occupied the airport in Saigon, quite
                        apart from naval activities in those regions, and that these steps, taken in
                        conjunction with the public utterances of many Japanese statesmen, generals
                        and admirals concerning Japanese intentions to the southward, had created a
                        situation which could hardly be regarded with equanimity either by the
                        United States or Great Britain since they threatened not only our interests
                        but our possessions.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Matsuoka replied that Japan was not the only country where inflammatory
                        utterances occurred and in this connection he mentioned the names of certain
                        Americans. He denied the truth of the report that the airfield at Saigon had
                        been occupied, merely murmuring something about Tongking, and he said that
                        the Japanese troops in Indo-China were there in strict accordance with the
                        terms of the official agreement with the Vichy Government. I said that
                        according to our own information these troops were very much in excess of
                        the number originally stipulated, but the Minister replied that this was
                        merely a question of replacement.</p>
                    <p>The conversation then turned into other channels.</p>
                    <p>Sent to the Department. Repeated to Hong Kong. Hong Kong please repeat to
                        Bangkok and Hanoi.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>