<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931-41v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d29</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">29</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-03-23T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-03-23T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-03-23T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-03-23T05:00:00-05:00" n="29"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d29">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/1454: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-03-23T19:00:00+09:00"
                            >March 23, 1940—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received March 23—10:40 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>199. The press reports that the Foreign Minister made the following reply to an
                    interpellation in regard to Japanese-American relations in the Budget Committee
                    of the Lower House this morning: <pb facs="0124" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“With respect to Japanese-American relations, we have been concerned that
                            they have not been satisfactory of late. However, we by no means think
                            that improvement is impossible. We are making and are determined to
                            continue to make every effort toward improvement. The fundamental cause
                            of Japanese-American relations reaching their present state, the focal
                            point of which is the China incident, lies in the failure of the
                            American Government and people fully to understand Japanese thought and
                            action relating to the incident. The Government has exerted every effort
                            in this connection but has not succeeded in having the United States
                            recognize our real intentions or the new world situation. Each country
                            has its own viewpoint and interests, and in some instances these cannot
                            be understood no matter how they are explained. Present day
                            Japanese-American relations are in a stage, I think, where the United
                            States because of its relations with China or because of traditional
                            habits of thought is not yet able to understand the Imperial
                            Government’s thought and actions. Nevertheless, the Imperial Government
                            will exert every effort towards such understanding. It is of greater
                            importance that not only should the Government and its representatives
                            make every endeavor to explain in order that American public opinion may
                            receive a correct understanding of the situation but that the Japanese
                            people from all classes and quarters should discuss the problem from
                            every angle in order that they too may convey correct understanding. In
                            short, the Government does not think that Japanese-American relations
                            are stalemated and that nothing can be done. We intend to make every
                            possible effort to change the conception prevailing in public and
                            private circles in the United States.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Shanghai please repeat to Peiping and Chungking.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
