<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Counselor of Embassy in Japan ( (Dooman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931-41v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d365</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">365</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="365"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d365">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/2624</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Counselor of Embassy in Japan</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Dooman</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-10-09">October 9,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I called this morning on Mr. Terasaki at his request.</p>
                <p>Mr. Terasaki said that he was very anxious to obtain “off the record” my
                    impressions of the memorandum handed by the Secretary of State to Admiral Nomura
                    on October 2. I said that the Ambassador told me that Mr. Terasaki had already
                    called on the Ambassador and had received the latter’s private and informal
                    observations on the memorandum, and that I did not see that I was in a <pb
                        facs="0734" n="668" xml:id="pg_668"/> position to add anything. Mr. Terasaki
                    then briefly summarized his conversation of last night with the Ambassador,
                    laying special emphasis on the Ambassador’s observations that, in our view, the
                    memorandum was friendly in tone and helpful in substance. He went on to say that
                    he was especially interested in that portion of the memorandum which makes
                    mention of the need for Japan’s manifesting evidence of intention to withdraw
                    its forces from Indochina and China. He pointed out that the paragraph under
                    reference might be open to the interpretation that the American Government
                    expected that Japan should withdraw its forces from the areas mentioned before
                    the proposed meeting of the heads of Government could be held. After remarking
                    that possibly the passage which he had in mind was open to such interpretation,
                    I said that there was obviously another one. The Japanese military forces in
                    Indochina were acting as though they were in permanent occupation of French
                    Indochina and had converted that area into a Japanese colony. It stood to reason
                    that the American Government would hesitate to make the slightest move toward
                    agreeing to the opening of formal negotiations so long as the actions of the
                    Japanese forces in Indochina constitute a complete negation of the spirit and
                    letter of the undertakings which the Japanese Government expresses willingness
                    to assume.</p>
                <p>Mr. Terasaki said that he was not aware of the situation in French Indochina to
                    which I referred. I told him that it was extremely important that he should
                    bring himself completely up to date on recent developments, and I suggested that
                    he confer with the Director of the South Seas Bureau. I referred to the actions
                    of the Japanese military forces, such as the arrests of French and Chinese
                    nationals, seizure of private property, seizure of air fields and military
                    barracks, threats to seize the Customs, etc. I expressed the belief that he
                    would agree, in view of the extremely difficult position created in Indochina by
                    the Japanese forces, that there was sound reason for assuming that the American
                    Government would not want to have the conversations progress at this time.</p>
                <p>In reply to Mr. Terasaki’s question whether the Japanese formula with regard to
                    the application of the principle of equality of treatment in the southwestern
                    Pacific constituted a serious obstacle, I said that it was my opinion, based on
                    what he had said to me on various occasions, that the Japanese formula under
                    reference was not designed to be taken as an expression of intention on the part
                    of the Japanese Government to confine the application of the principle of
                    equality of opportunity to the southwestern Pacific—that it was intended as an
                    affirmation of a positive intention with regard to an area in part of which the
                    Japanese Government now exercise <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> control,
                    namely, French Indochina, but that it was not intended by <pb facs="0735"
                        n="669" xml:id="pg_669"/> implication to exclude the application of the
                    principle from other areas under which the Japanese exercised control. Mr.
                    Terasaki said that that was precisely the case, and that it was evident that the
                    intentions of the Japanese Government had not been clearly expressed. He thought
                    also that the Japanese explanation with regard to equality of opportunity in
                    China, particularly the reference to conditions created by geographical
                    propinquity, were open to implications the giving of which the Japanese
                    Government had especially desired to avoid.</p>
                <p>Mr. Terasaki reverted to the reference in the October 2 memorandum to the
                    question of withdrawal of troops from China. He said that it was impossible for
                    Japan to manifest evidence, by withdrawing its troops from China, of intention
                    to effect such withdrawal, until agreement had been reached between Japan and
                    China. How then was it possible for Japan to meet this requirement of the
                    American Government? I said that I could not pretend to interpret the passage
                    under reference, but there could be several ways in which the Japanese
                    Government could demonstrate the sincerity of its desire to evacuate China. It
                    might be possible, for example, to provide a time schedule of withdrawal of
                    troops; or, again, the Japanese Government might indicate willingness to
                    consider the establishment of a military police force by the Chinese Government,
                    possibly with the assistance of foreign military experts, as a satisfactory
                    substitute for the Japanese troops which Japan proposed to station in Inner
                    Mongolia and North China for the specific purpose of maintaining law and
                    order.</p>
                <p>Mr. Terasaki was summoned at this point by the Foreign Minister, and in bringing
                    our conversation to an end he expressed his appreciation for my courtesy in
                    calling on him this morning and giving him the benefit of my views.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>E[<hi rend="smallcaps">ugene</hi>] H. D[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ooman</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
