<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-12-01T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-12-01T01:00:00-05:00" n="90" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/17041: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-12-01T15:00:00+09:00">December 1, 1941—3
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received December 5—5:03 a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>1869. Extract from Premier Tojo’s message to rally held yesterday under
                            sponsorship Imperial Rule Assistance Association and Dai Nippon East
                            Asia League in commemoration first anniversary joint
                            Japan-China-”Manchukuo” declaration<note n="17" xml:id="d90fn17"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_122">p.
                                122</ref>.</note> follows (from Domei report in <hi rend="italic">Advertiser</hi>): <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“It is certainly the most fortunate lot of the three powers to
                                    have the privilege of collaborating together under this banner
                                    for cutting open the thorny way, and 1 year has already gone by
                                    since we started this honorable work together, and if it is not
                                    the greatest task of the present century what else can it
                                    be.</p>
                                <p>However if we look around we find that there are still many
                                    countries who are indulging in actions hostile to us. In fact
                                    they are trying to throw obstacles in the way of the
                                    construction of the East Asia co-prosperity sphere and are
                                    trying to enjoy the dream of exploitation of East Asia at the
                                    cost of the 1,000 million populace of the East Asiatic peoples
                                    to satisfy their greed of possession.</p>
                                <p>The fact that Chiang Kai-shek is dancing to the tune of Britain,
                                    America, and communism at the expense of able-bodied and
                                    promising young men in his futile resistance against Japan is
                                    only due to the desire of Britain and the United States to fish
                                    in the troubled waters of East Asia by putting [<hi rend="italic">pitting?</hi>] the East Asiatic peoples
                                    against each other and to grasp the hegemony of East Asia. This
                                    is a stock in trade of Britain and the United States.</p>
                                <pb facs="0215" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/>
                                <p>For the honor and pride of mankind we must purge this sort of
                                    practice from East Asia with a vengeance.”<note n="18" xml:id="d90fn18">For Japanese explanation of this speech,
                                        see statement of December 2, 1941, <ref target="#pg_778">p.
                                            778</ref>.</note></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Sent Department via Shanghai.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>