<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1903-08-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1903-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="158" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d158">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Beaupré</persName> to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-08-10"><hi rend="italic">August 10,
                                1903</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 101.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my No. 98 of the 7th instant,
                            I have the honor to inclose herewith a copy and translation of a note
                            from the minister for foreign affairs, together with a copy of my reply
                            thereto.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. M. Beaupré.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure
                                1.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName type="from">Rico</persName> to Mr.
                                        <persName type="to">Beaupré</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry for Foreign Relations</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-08-08"><hi rend="italic">August 8, 1903</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: One of your attentive
                                communications which your excellency had the pleasure to address to
                                me on the 5th of the present month, relative to the business of the
                                Interoceanic Canal of Panama, contained the part which I take the
                                liberty to quote as follows:</p>
                            <p>“I may say that the antecedent circumstances of the whole negotiation
                                of the canal treaty, from official information in the hands of my
                                Government, are of such a nature as to fully warrant the United
                                States in considering any modification of the terms of that treaty
                                as practically a breach of faith on the part of the Government of
                                Colombia, such as may involve the very greatest complications in the
                                friendly relations which have hitherto existed between the two
                                countries.”</p>
                            <pb facs="0262" n="178" xml:id="pg_178"/>
                            <p>Wishing to give to your excellency as soon as possible the required
                                answer to the two notes to which I refer in the present, I will
                                appreciate it if you will inform me that if among the circumstances
                                alluded to in the paragraph, a version of which I have transcribed,
                                there exist any others not mentioned in the notes which your
                                excellency has seen fit to address to me on this subject.</p>
                            <p>With this motive I renew to your excellency the assurance of my
                                highest consideration.</p>
                            <closer>(Signed) <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Luis Carlos
                                    Rico.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">A. M. Beaupré</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Envoy Extraordinary and Minister
                                        Plenipotentiary of the United States.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Beaupré</persName> to
                                    Doctor <persName type="to">Pico</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bogotá</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-08-08"><hi rend="italic">August 8, 1903</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">His Excellency Dr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Luis Carlos
                                    Rico</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs of
                                    the Republic of Colombia</hi>.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                                receipt of your excellency’s courteous note of to-day, quoting a
                                paragraph of my note of the 5th instant, and asking if the statement
                                therein contained is based upon information not mentioned in my
                                previous notes.</p>
                            <p>In reply I have the honor to inform your excellency that the
                                antecedent circumstances to which I made reference are fully
                                outlined in my previous notes, and particularly in the one of June
                                10, 1903.</p>
                            <p>If your excellency will permit me a few words more on this subject I
                                would like to refer to the extraordinary efforts made by my
                                Government to keep faith with Colombia after an agreement had been
                                reached between the executive Governments of the two nations.</p>
                            <p>As your excellency is aware, when the canal convention was presented
                                to the Senate of the United States it encountered the most violent
                                opposition. Not only were strenuous efforts made to defeat the
                                treaty in its entirety, but many amendments of varying degrees of
                                importance were presented and urged. During all that period the
                                friends of the Government were steadfast in their determination to
                                uphold the action of the Executive and to preserve intact the
                                agreement made with Colombia. It was a momentous struggle, and the
                                final and close victory was secured in the end only by the most
                                stupendous efforts on the part of the Administration, imbued as they
                                were with the idea that such a compact, made after mature and
                                careful consideration by the executive departments of the two
                                Governments, must be ratified as it stood.</p>
                            <p>In view of the foregoing, it is absolutely believed by my Government,
                                that any modification, as such, to the pending treaty could not be
                                safely submitted to the present Senate.</p>
                            <p>The intense feeling over large sections of the United States in favor
                                of the Nicaragua route on the one hand and interests on the other
                                hand hostile to any canal at all, and especially the Panama route,
                                are circumstances that, I fear, your excellency’s Government and the
                                people of Colombia have not weighed sufficiently to attach to them
                                the importance they deserve.</p>
                            <p>While my previous notes may have expressed an almost exaggerated
                                desire to impress upon your excellency the dangers of delay or
                                modification of any kind, they were inspired by a full knowledge of
                                conditions in my own country, which I feared would not be fully
                                appreciated in Colombia.</p>
                            <p>The condition which appears to me to be absolute, at least, is that
                                the proposed treaty should be ratified as it is, in good faith with
                                my Government, or the opportunity will be lost for any later
                                negotiations of any kind whatever.</p>
                            <p>In my own behalf, I most earnestly desire to assure your excellency
                                that, aside from fulfilling the instructions of my Government, I
                                have the deepest personal concern in the honor and glory of the
                                country to which I am accredited, and in which I have been extended
                                so much kindness and consideration. Every conviction of my mind
                                leads me to the belief that enormous aggrandizement must accrue to
                                Colombia if an interoceanic canal be constructed through her
                                territory, while the desire to bring the two countries into closer
                                and lasting friendship is ever present. Feeling <pb facs="0263" n="179" xml:id="pg_179"/> thus deeply every effort I may have
                                made, or shall make to this end, has or will have as its incentive
                                the ultimate good not only of the country which I represent but of
                                that in which I have the privilege and pleasure of residing.</p>
                            <p>I avail myself of this opportunity to renew, etc.</p>
                            <closer>(Signed) <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. M.
                                    Beaupré.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>