<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1902-12-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1902-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="34" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Conger</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-12-17"><hi rend="italic">December 17,
                                    1902</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1175.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to confirm my telegram of
                            the 16th instant concerning the proposed establishment of a customs
                            service under Russian control at Dalny (Talienwan) and other ports in
                            Manchuria.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>The completion of the Manchurian railway and the creation of an open
                            commercial port at Dalny, its terminus, make additional customs
                            facilities necessary in that corner of the Empire.</p>
                        <p>I have been unable to get exact details, because the arrangement is not
                            yet completed, but it will provide a principal custom-house at Dalny,
                            where goods to be used in Dalny and the Russian-leased territory
                            immediately surrounding will be free. Those to be consumed in Manchuria
                            will pay the regular Chinese import duties; those going into Russia the
                            Russian tariff, all being collected at one office. Another station will
                            be located where the railway crosses the border between Manchuria and
                            Siberia, and others where necessary.</p>
                        <p>It is proposed to establish post-offices where they have not yet been
                            established by the maritime customs, and I understand they are to await
                            the Russian evacuation of the second portion of the territory which
                            should take place April 8, next. The customs service, however, is to go
                            into effect as soon as an agreed arrangement can be arrived at.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">E. H. Conger.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>