<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Powell to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1903</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d349</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">349</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1903-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1903-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1903-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1903-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="349"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d349">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Powell</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Port au Prince</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-05-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 12, 1903</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 541, Santo Domingo series.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to state to the Department that
                    the steamer from Santo Domingo arrived after the mail had closed for the States.
                    I was therefore compelled to wait until the departure of this steamer to convey
                    to the Department information I had through private but trustworthy sources. I
                    am able through this medium to inform the Department of the political situation,
                    which I was not able to do when my last dispatch on this subject was written. By
                    letters received it is stated that General Vasquez had the city closely besieged
                    on all sides except its sea front. The revolutionists, on their part, were
                    strongly intrenched, and, besides, strong barricades had been erected in many of
                    the streets leading from the gates into the city. These barricades were well
                    supplied with rapid-firing guns. General Vasquez’s force numbered about 2,000
                    men; the revolutionists one-half this number. General Vasquez established his
                    headquarters at a village known as San Carlos, a place of about 800 houses and a
                    short distance from Santo Domingo. This place is entirely destroyed, not a house
                    standing. General Vasquez made several attempts to take the city by assault, but
                    was repulsed each time with heavy loss. His last attempt was partly successful,
                    as his troops had made a breach in the works of the revolutionists; but the
                    assaulting party not being supported at a critical moment by General Vasquez,
                    the revolutionists rallied and drove Vasquez’s force out of their intrenchments,
                    killing the general (Cordew) who led the assault. Vasquez failed to grasp the
                    situation in time. The sudden attack and the failure to receive reinforcements
                    caused a panic in his forces, which eventually ended in a rout, his force
                    scattering and fleeing in all directions, and Vasquez himself had to seek safety
                    in flight. At the time of his defeat the whole Republic was in his favor, with
                    the exception of the city of Santo Domingo. After his defeat he attempted to
                    establish his capital at Santiago. The revolutionists quickly realized their
                    victory, and followed closely after Vasquez to prevent him gathering another
                    force. Vasquez, finding it useless to continue the struggle, and also learning
                    that several provinces he had depended upon had espoused the cause of the
                    revolutionists, left with a chosen few (150) for Puerto Plata, and there
                    embarked on the <hi rend="italic">Presidente</hi> for Santiago, Cuba.</p>
                <p>Mr. Jimenez arrived at Puerto Plata three days after General Vasquez’s departure,
                    and at the time the mail left was at Santiago. <pb facs="0477" n="393"
                        xml:id="pg_393"/> General Deschamps, the former governor of Puerto Plata, on
                    the day the steamer departed had arrived in Santo Domingo, and General Rodrigues
                    was expected the following week. During the time the city was shelled several
                    shells struck our consulate, but no damage occurred. Several were killed in the
                    streets from flying or falling bullets, and one or two sailors from the vessels
                    of war in the harbor were injured. It is estimated the revolutionists lost in
                    killed and wounded about 400; Vasquez’s loss was very much greater. Great praise
                    is given by both sides for the active aid rendered by the medical corps from the
                        <hi rend="italic">Atlanta</hi>. The damage sustained will be another heavy
                    expense added to those that this country will have to pay. * * *</p>
                <p>The elections are supposed to take place in about two months, if there is not
                    another revolution. The leading candidates are Generals Gill, Deschamps,
                    Rodrigues, Richards, and Mr. Jimenez. There are others named, the principal
                    being ex-President Ignacio Gonzales, the present Dominican minister to this
                    country. While the revolution is over, the political situation is very grave. It
                    is stated Mr. Jimenez will make every effort to secure the Presidency, * * * The
                    other candidates fear that if he should succeed the friends of Gill and Vasquez
                    will unite to prevent it. This foreshadows another revolution.</p>
                <p>The financial condition of the Government is worse than bad, if such can be
                    accepted to express the present monetary condition of the Republic. It is
                    impossible for them to secure a loan, as they have nothing to guarantee it.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>At the time the mail closed the <hi rend="italic">San Francisco</hi> was in the
                    harbor.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. F. Powell.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
