<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1903-10-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1903-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="351" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d351">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Powell</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Santo Domingo City</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-10-01"><hi rend="italic">October
                                        1903</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 614, Santo Domingo Series.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to state to the
                            Department that according to instructions received I delivered to
                            President A. Woss y Gil, the letter of the President, Mr. Roosevelt.</p>
                        <p>I was very cordially received by the President. A guard of honor and the
                            palace band was placed at the entrance to receive me. Our interview
                            lasted about twenty minutes.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to inclose the remarks made on the occasion by the
                            President and myself.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. F. Powell.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0479" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Remarks to President.</hi></p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: I have a most pleasant
                                duty to perform, in being the bearer of a communication from Mr.
                                Roosevelt, the President of the United States of America, to Your
                                Excellency, extending to you his congratulations on your being
                                called to preside as the Chief Magistrate of this Republic.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to state to Your Excellency that it is the great
                                desire of Mr. Roosevelt, the President, that the closest friendship
                                shall exist between the two sister Republics, each being allied to
                                the other by strong commercial ties. I can also say to Your
                                Excellency that it is the desire of the President, Mr. Roosevelt,
                                that this country shall ever preserve its autonomy and its
                                independence, and that during the time that Your Excellency shall
                                exercise the functions of this office you will be able to bring to
                                this Republic the prosperity that it once attained. In order to do
                                this there must be a united people, whose only aim should be the
                                future prosperity of the Republic. This, Mr. President, with a just
                                regard to the fulfillment of all obligations entered into, will
                                bring to your Republic a future of hope, of prosperty, of peace, and
                                of happiness.</p>
                            <p>This, Your Excellency, I hope to see during the time you fill this
                                high and important office.</p>
                            <p>Allow me, sir, to extend my congratulations upon this happy
                                event.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure
                                4.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Galvan</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Powell</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Dominican Republic,<lb/>Department of Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Santo
                                        Domingo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-10-22"><hi rend="italic">October 22,
                                        1903</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Honorable Sir</hi>: I have the special order
                                from the President Woss y Gil to send your excellency the written
                                testimonial of the well-felt satisfaction with which he has received
                                the congratulations of His Excellency the President of the United
                                States of North America, expressed in his autograph letter, which
                                your excellency put in his hands yesterday, the 21st instant,
                                accompanied by the eloquent phrases of your excellency’s discourse,
                                manifesting the great desire which is felt by the illustrious
                                President Roosevelt that the closest friendship should exist between
                                the two sister Republics, the one being bound to the other by strong
                                commercial relations.</p>
                            <p>The President of the Dominican Republic, General Woss y Gil, and the
                                ministers who accompany him in the work of the Government, esteem in
                                a high degree and correspond loyally to this noble aspiration of the
                                First Magistrate of the Federal Union of the United States of
                                America, fully confident of the sincerity of these expressions which
                                conjointly your excellency has expressed in the name and by order of
                                the same Mr. President Roosevelt, that this Republic shall conserve
                                always its autonomy and its independence, and that it may reach
                                during the present administration the prosperity to which a united
                                people may aspire.</p>
                            <p>It is very grateful to me, honorable sir, to be the organ on this
                                occasion of the cordiality of sentiments with which President Woss Y
                                Gil and his Government receive such expressive manifestations of
                                friendship, which will find full correspondence in the way which the
                                Dominican Government proposes itself to encourage, by the rectitude
                                and the best will, in all its proceedings regarding the commercial
                                and political interests existing between both republics.</p>
                            <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Manuel de J.
                                Galvan.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Powell</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Galvan</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Santo Domingo City</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-10-23"><hi rend="italic">October 23, 1903</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge your
                                excellency’s note of October 22, 1903, conveying to me the kindly
                                expressions from His Excellency General Woss y Gil, President of
                                this Republic, in response to a congratulatory letter from Mr.
                                Roosevelt, the President of the United States of America.</p>
                            <pb facs="0480" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/>
                            <p>It will afford me great pleasure to communicate the contents of your
                                excellency’s very interesting letter to my Government.</p>
                            <p>Allow me to express to your excellency the great pleasure that Mr.
                                Roosevelt, the President, will feel in reading the kindly sentiments
                                that His Excellency the President, General Woss y Gil, and his
                                cabinet have for the Government and people of the United States.</p>
                            <p>I beg, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. F.
                                Powell.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>