<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1903-11-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1903-11-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="370" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d370">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hay</persName> to
                                    <persName type="to">Baron von dem
                                    Bussche-Haddenhausen</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-11-10"><hi rend="italic">November 10,
                                    1903</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 37.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to Baron von Sternburg’s note of
                            August 11 last, protesting against the intention of the United States
                            commissioner at San Francisco, as recently announced by him, in future
                            to examine into the question whether seamen brought before him by
                            foreign consular officers charged with desertion are deserters, I have
                            the honor, for your information, to quote the following from an opinion
                            of the Attorney-General, to whom I referred the matter: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Section 5280 of the Revised Statutes, upon which the commissioner
                                    rests his contention, reads as follows:</p>
                                <p>“On application of a consul or vice-consul of any foreign
                                    government having a treaty with the United States stipulating
                                    for the restoration of seamen deserting, made in writing,
                                    stating that the person therein named has deserted from a vessel
                                    of any such government while in any port of the United States,
                                    and on proof by the exhibition of the register of the vessel,
                                    ship’s roll, or other official document, that the person
                                    belonged at the time of desertion to the crew of such vessel, it
                                    shall be the duty of any court, judge, commissioner of any
                                    circuit court, justice, or other magistrate, having competent
                                    power, to issue warrants to cause such person to be arrested for
                                    examination. If, on examination, the facts stated are found to
                                    be true, the person arrested not being a citizen of the United
                                    States shall be delivered up to the consul or vice-consul to be
                                    sent back to the dominions of any such government or, on the
                                    request and at the expense of the consul or vice-consul, shall
                                    be detained until the consul or vice-consul finds an opportunity
                                    to send him back to the dominions of any such government.”</p>
                                <p>This section originated in an act of March 2, 1829 (4 Stats.,
                                    359), which, as amended by an act of February 24, 1855 (10
                                    Stats., 614), was, with a few immaterial changes in punctuation,
                                    incorporated into the revision of 1874 as section 5280.</p>
                                <p>Article 14 of the consular convention of 1871 with Germany is in
                                    the following language:</p>
                                <p>“Consuls-general, consuls, vice-consuls, or consular agents may
                                    arrest the officers, sailors, and all other persons making part
                                    of the crews of ships of war or merchant vessels of their nation
                                    who may be guilty or be accused of having deserted said ships
                                    and vessels, for the purpose of sending them back on board or
                                    back to their country.</p>
                                <p>“To that end the consuls of Germany in the United States shall
                                    apply to either the Federal, State, or municipal courts or
                                    authorities; and the consuls of the United States in Germany
                                    shall apply to any of the competent authorities and make a
                                    request, in writing, for the deserters, supporting it by an
                                    official extract of the register of the vessel and the list of
                                    the crew, or by other official documents, to show that the men
                                    whom they claim belong to said crew. Upon such request alone
                                    thus supported, and without exaction of any oath from the
                                    consuls, the deserters (not being citizens of the country where
                                    the demand is made, either at the time of their shipping or of
                                    their arrival in the port) shall be given up to the
                                    consuls.”</p>
                                <p>It will be observed that section 5280 applies in cases in which
                                    the United States have treaties providing for the restoration of
                                    deserting seamen. When it was enacted, the United States had
                                    five treaties on the subject, all of them employing
                                    substantially the language relied upon by the ambassador. One of
                                    them was with Prussia. It can not, then, be doubted that this
                                    statute, which was for the very purpose of carrying out those
                                    treaties, was regarded as consistent with their terms. It was
                                    followed by a long series of similar treaties, repeating
                                    substantially the same language relied upon by the ambassador,
                                    and the latest treaties with Great Britain, Japan, and other
                                    countries provide for the return of the seamen in the manner
                                    prescribed by law. Thus, for three-quarters of a century this
                                    statute, which provides for an examination in addition to an
                                    inquiry into the question whether a man belongs to the <pb facs="0501" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/> crew of the vessel,
                                    has stood and been enforced upon the theory that it was
                                    consistent with our numerous treaties on the subject of the
                                    restoration of seamen.</p>
                                <p>This would seem to raise a presumption in favor of the harmony of
                                    the statute with the treaties, and of the acquiescence of
                                    numerous foreign governments in the construction placed upon the
                                    treaties by Congress.</p>
                                <p>The treaty with Germany is certainly not clearly opposed to such
                                    a construction. The first sentence of article 14 provides that
                                    consuls may arrest officers, sailors, etc., who may be guilty,
                                    or be accused of having deserted ships, for the purpose of
                                    sending them on board, or back to their country. The next
                                    paragraph provides for the delivery up to the consuls of “the
                                    deserters.”</p>
                                <p>The treaty thus makes a distinction between persons belonging to
                                    the crew and away from the vessel in this country who are
                                    deserters and such persons who are accused of desertion. It
                                    provides, not that those accused, but that “the deserters” shall
                                    be delivered up. The ambassador reads this differently and says
                                    that the word “deserters,” in the second paragraph, includes
                                    those accused of desertion. The first paragraph provides for
                                    arresting, the other for delivering up to the consuls. Hence,
                                    there may well have been a difference of treatment intended, and
                                    only “the deserters” may have been intended to be delivered up.
                                    If so, an inquiry to distinguish the deserters from members of
                                    the crew away from the ship and accused of desertion, would be
                                    necessary. This inquiry is provided for by the law which has
                                    stood so long upon our statute books.</p>
                                <p>But this statute and treaty provide a method whereby the judicial
                                    authorities may determine this question. According to either the
                                    consul may apply to the proper court. If it should be held by
                                    the court that the statute is obligatory, notwithstanding
                                    differences which may be held to exist between it and the
                                    treaty, which the ambassador regards, and is probably right in
                                    regarding as of later date than the statute, then it will be
                                    necessary to modify the statute.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>In conclusion, the Attorney-General suggests that the question be fully
                            presented by the German consul-general to the proper court. Mr. Knox has
                            no doubt that should Baron von Sternberg’s contention be correct, the
                            court will so decide.</p>
                        <p>The two original inclosures with the ambassador’s note will be returned
                            to you in a few days.</p>
                        <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>