<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1903-11-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1903-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="667" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d667">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1903-11-15"><hi rend="italic">November 15,
                                    1903</hi>.</date></dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 63, Roumanian series.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to previous correspondence on
                            the Jewish question, I have the honor to inform you that I have received
                            a “Report of the Royal Commission on Alien Immigration.” This commission
                            was appointed by the King of England in March, 1902, to report upon “the
                            character and extent of the evils which are attributed to the
                            unrestricted immigration of aliens.”</p>
                        <p>In order to make a thorough study of the subject, one of the members of
                            the commission, Major Evans-Gordon, was sent to inquire into the causes
                            of immigration to England from the various countries.</p>
                        <p>For this purpose he visited Russia and Roumania to study the condition of
                            the Jews, and the part of the report dealing with the latter country has
                            caused a great deal of feeling there, as it has again stirred up the
                            already troublesome Jewish question.</p>
                        <pb facs="0793" n="707" xml:id="pg_707"/>
                        <p>In Russia, it seems, Major Evans-Gordon finds that Jewish emigration is
                            due partly to economic causes and partly to oppressive measures; in
                            Poland, mainly to economic causes, while in Roumania he states: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The expulsive force is undoubtedly the intolerant attitude of the
                                    Government toward the Jews and the series of oppressive measures
                                    which, contrary to treaty engagements, have appeared upon the
                                    statute books of that country.</p>
                                <p>The Jewish question has been a burning one ever since Roumanian
                                    independence was granted, and even long before. At the time of
                                    the Berlin conference, in 1878, an attempt was made to place the
                                    Jewish subjects of Roumania upon a footing of equality with the
                                    other classes of the population.</p>
                                <p>The evident intention of the powers throughout the negotiations
                                    was to establish a complete religious and civil equality for the
                                    Jews. The policy of the Roumanian Government was then and is
                                    still directly opposed to this intention. Rightly or wrongly,
                                    they have always asserted that such equality, if given to the
                                    Hebrew race, would end in the subjugation of their country by an
                                    alien people, and far from complying with the conditions laid
                                    down by the great powers, their policy tends toward the
                                    suppression, political extermination, and expulsion of the
                                    Jews.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>The value of the report of Major Evans-Gordon on the condition of the
                            Jews in Roumania seems to me not to be great, as he spent less than a
                            week in the country, principally in Sinaia, where there are no Jews, and
                            the rest of his time in Bucharest. He did not see the condition of the
                            Jews in the country districts, nor in the cities which are centers of
                            Jewish life. Neither did he attempt to see the King, nor Mr. Sturdza,
                            the prime minister, who from his long public service knows the country
                            and its conditions better than any man in the kingdom. On the contrary,
                            Major Evans-Gordon obtained all the information necessary for his report
                            from Mr. Take Jonesco, the leader of the opposition, and from others of
                            the same party. The opposition in Roumania always uses the Jewish
                            question as a means of attacking the party in power, but, in spite of
                            this fact, have never done anything to improve the condition of the Jews
                            when the opportunity has come to them.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>An official report of this nature has caused much indignation, not only
                            in Government circles, but in general, as the numerous newspaper
                            articles showed, for it is felt that this report will have great weight
                            abroad and that the country has been misrepresented. Objection is also
                            made, and very naturally, to the unfavorable comparison between the
                            condition of the Jews in Russia and Poland and those in Roumania. This
                            objection seems well founded, in view of the Jewish massacres in Russia,
                            while in Roumania the Jew is never in danger of personal violence of any
                            sort.</p>
                        <p>That the condition of the Roumanian Jew is not so bad as it would seem to
                            be from Major Evans-Gordon’s report, or as it is generally believed to
                            be, seems to be shown by the fact that, according to statistics, while a
                            certain number of Jews do emigrate from Roumania each year, yet the
                            number in the country is constantly increasing, due to immigration from
                            Russia and Austria.</p>
                        <p>The report does not take into consideration at all that, in the opinion
                            of Roumanians of all classes, as well as of most foreigners who
                            understand the conditions of the country, the restrictions placed upon
                            the Jew in Roumania are absolutely necessary for their national
                            preservation.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles S. Wilson</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires ad
                            interim.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>