<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Consul at Capetown ( (Denby))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">120</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-03-06T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-03-06T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-03-06T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-03-06T16:00:00-05:00" n="120"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d120">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">848A.24/188: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Consul at Capetown</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Denby</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-03-06T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >March 6, 1943—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>44. For the Minister. Your 186, February 19, from Capetown. Prime Minister’s
                    reception of President’s message seems to us encouraging, since main points of
                    our proposal have been accepted in principle. We do not agree, however, with his
                    suggestion that we make an advance commitment to provide gold mining supplies
                    before there has been a decision concerning the limits to be imposed on gold
                    mining operations. A similar proposal was made here by the South African
                        Minister<note n="23" xml:id="d120fn23">See telegram No. 28, February 13, 7
                        p.m., to the Consul at Capetown, <ref target="#pg_182">p. 182</ref>.</note>
                    on the day you delivered the President’s message. The South Africans evidently
                    prefer to treat the problem of gold mining separately, but they may not realize
                    that the supply authorities here are less likely to grant allocations for the
                    gold mines if their requirements are presented independently, than if they are
                    presented as part of the total requirements which are necessary for the Union
                    economy. We feel that it is essential to our proposal to consider the needs of
                    the gold mines in relation to the Union requirements as a whole. In that way we
                    should be in a position to know to what extent Union resources were devoted to
                    the war effort, and we should have some basis for determining what quantities of
                    materials we will endeavor to make available for gold mining and for other
                    purposes.</p>
                <pb facs="0197" n="185" xml:id="pg_185"/>
                <p>You are accordingly requested to make clear our view that the question of the
                    gold mines should not be considered separately or in advance, but must be
                    considered together with the other supply problems of South Africa. We shall not
                    be in a position to discuss further details until we have received an answer
                    from the British Embassy concerning the proposed council and supply program.
                    Meanwhile, please forward by telegram any further portions of the Prime
                    Minister’s memorandum which you think might be helpful to us.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
