<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-04-06T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-04-06T04:00:00-05:00" n="182" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 European War 1939/1381:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Standley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-04-06T12:00:00+03:00">April
                                        6, 1943—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received April 7—1:15
                                    p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>252. My 242, April 3, noon. I called on Molotov last evening at his
                                request. He presented me with <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                                which states in paraphrase translation as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Soviet Government is grateful to the American Government
                                        for information transmitted on April 2 by Ambassador
                                        Standley to Molotov regarding the conversations between the
                                        American Chargé d’Affaires at Helsinki and the Finnish
                                        Minister of Foreign Affairs concerning the proposal of the
                                        American Government to act as intermediary in establishing
                                        direct contact between the Soviet and Finnish Governments
                                        for discussing questions relative to the conclusion of a
                                        separate peace.</p>
                                    <p>The Soviet Government has also studied the memorandum of the
                                        American Government of April 2 and deems it necessary to
                                        state as follows. With reference to the proposal concerned
                                        in the memorandum to the effect that the American Government
                                        desired to be in a position to reply to the Finnish
                                        Government that if the Finnish Government were prepared to
                                        participate in a direct and confidential exchange of views
                                        with the Soviet Government the Soviet Government for its
                                        part would be similarly disposed, the Soviet Government
                                        wishes to refer to the statement made on March 20 by Mr.
                                        Molotov to Ambassador Standley to the effect that the Soviet
                                        Government had no reason to suppose that Finland could break
                                        away from Germany or was prepared to offer the Soviet Union
                                        peace terms which would be acceptable to it. The Soviet
                                        Government, therefore, has no reason to believe that direct
                                        contact between the Finnish and Soviet Governments will lead
                                        to positive results under present condition.</p>
                                    <p>The Soviet Government would be able to express its agreement
                                        to the desire of the American Government set forth above if
                                        the Soviet Government could receive information which would
                                        permit it to believe that the minimum conditions for the
                                        conclusion of peace with Finland, conveyed to the American
                                        Government on March 27, were acceptable to Finland.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>In the ensuing conversation I recalled that the Soviet terms were
                                given me exclusively for the information of my Government and
                                remarked that by implication the present Soviet memo might be
                                construed to mean that we should communicate these views to the
                                Finnish Government.</p>
                            <p>Molotov inquired whether my Government desired to do this. Referring
                                to my memo of April 2, I replied that this was obviously not the
                                case but added that in view of the nature of the Soviet reply my
                                Government might now consider the situation in a different light.
                                Molotov then [proceeded?] carefully and explained that since the
                                Soviet Government did not wish to show any indication of taking the
                                    <pb facs="0274" n="262" xml:id="pg_262"/> initiative in the
                                question of peace overtures and since it had no reason to believe
                                that the Finns desired peace, were prepared to accept the Soviet
                                conditions or to offer terms which would be acceptable to the Soviet
                                Government, it had communicated its terms for the exclusive
                                information of the American Government; however, if the Soviet
                                Government could obtain definite information to the effect that the
                                Finns were prepared to accept the Soviet minimum terms then there
                                would be no objection to their being communicated to the Finnish
                                Government.</p>
                            <p>It would seem to me that the Soviet reply, if accepted, would place
                                us in the position we wish to avoid, i.e., acting as an intermediary
                                so far as exchanging information with regard to peace terms.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Standley</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>