<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-03-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-03-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="257" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d257">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">760C.61/1018</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Polish Prime Minister</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Sikorski</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                                </hi><note n="68" xml:id="d257fn68">Sent to President Roosevelt by
                                    the Ambassador to the Polish Government in Exile, at London,
                                    with a covering letter dated March 17, 1943, which read in part:
                                    “As to Russian attitude towards him [General Sikorski], I doubt
                                    whether Moscow would press its campaign against him personally
                                    to the point of causing his political downfall—for Moscow would
                                    more than likely figure that it would result in his replacement
                                    by someone far less realistic and more violently anti-Moscow.”
                                    (760C. 61/1018)</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-03-16">March 16, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I am writing to
                                thank you, Mr. President, most sincerely for your message,<note n="69" xml:id="d257fn69">See the third paragraph of the Polish
                                    Ambassador’s letter of April 4, to President Roosevelt, <ref target="#pg_365">p. 365</ref>.</note> which I received
                                through our Ambassador in Washington.</p>
                            <p>Both the Polish Government and myself have the highest regard for
                                your viewpoint and we are prepared to do all in our power in order
                                to prevent the breaking off of Poland’s relations with Soviet Russia
                                if only we are met with good will and some response on the other
                                side. Meanwhile, however, as you know, the situation has
                                deteriorated still further since my return from the United
                                States.</p>
                            <p>I would like, therefore, on behalf of my Government to describe to
                                you, Mr. President, the difficult position in which the latest
                                Russian declarations have placed us. We are expected to fight side
                                by side with Russia at a time when the Soviet Government are making
                                claims to one half of our territory and to one third of the people
                                of Poland, and when in their note of January 16th, 1943,<note n="70" xml:id="d257fn70">See telegram Polish Series No. 3, January 28,
                                    midnight, from the Ambassador to the Polish Government in Exile,
                                        <ref target="#pg_323">p. 323</ref>.</note> they once more
                                insist on the Ribbentrop–Molotov line. The Soviet Government is
                                invoking for this policy the Atlantic Charter, which is to justify
                                their present imperialist designs. The denial to Poles, forcibly
                                deported to the U.S.S.R., of all rights, including the right to
                                live, completes the measure of their affliction. The men, women and
                                children concerned are on the verge of physical exhaustion. The
                                interruption of all humanitarian activities organised for the
                                benefit of the deportees with the generous help of the United States
                                would be tantamount to a condemnation to death.</p>
                            <p>Many of the Polish soldiers, airmen and sailors have relatives in the
                                U.S.S.R. or in that part of Poland to which Russia—our Ally—is
                                making her unprecedented claims, contrary to all the principles
                                proclaimed by the United Nations and it requires great efforts on my
                                part to keep their feelings under control.</p>
                            <p>On February 27th, the Polish Ambassador in Moscow had a three hour
                                conversation with M. Stalin, who appeared somewhat less exacting
                                than it might have been expected from previous semi-official Soviet
                                enunciations. I am afraid, however, that we cannot rely on <pb facs="0362" n="350" xml:id="pg_350"/> vague assurances that
                                there is no enmity in Russia towards Poland, but that we must take
                                into account the hostile manifestations of Soviet policy
                                consistently conducted by M. Molotov.</p>
                            <p>The Polish people suffered beyond measure in this war. It would be an
                                incomprehensible wrong, if at a time when the development of war is
                                taking a turn to the advantage of the Allies, the Polish people were
                                to realise, that the imperialist claims of Allied Russia are to be
                                met at the expense of Poland.</p>
                            <p>At this distressing time I find support in your friendship and your
                                understanding, Mr. President, which you expressed so often towards
                                my country and myself. I believe that the solid front of the United
                                Nations will be maintained and that acting together the British and
                                American Governments will find the means to confirm their solidarity
                                with us.</p>
                            <p>In this connection I take the liberty to make the suggestion that the
                                Governments of the United States and Great Britain may agree, either
                                publicly or by means of notes addressed to the Governments of the
                                United Nations, to reaffirm the principle of non-recognition by them
                                of any accomplished facts, effected after September the 1st, 1939,
                                on the occupied territories of States, belonging to the United
                                Nations.</p>
                            <p>The confirmation of this principle would strengthen the position of
                                Poland during the diplomatic negotiations, which the Polish
                                Government are conducting at the present time in Moscow. The
                                publication of such a declaration would, moreover, find a favourable
                                echo throughout the Continent of Europe, especially in the countries
                                adjoining the U.S.S.R., and supply a valuable counter-weight to
                                German propaganda and German agitation on behalf of the war effort
                                of the Axis Powers, which are exploiting Soviet territorial claims
                                against Poland for their own purposes.</p>
                            <p>Believe me,</p>
                            <p>Yours very sincerely,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sikorski</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>