<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="356" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d356">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">760C.61/11–1743</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Polish Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Ciechanowski</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Adviser on Political Relations</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Dunn</hi></persName>)<note n="47" xml:id="d356fn47">The letter
                                    was delivered to the Department by Michal Kwapiszewski, Minister
                                    Counselor of the Polish Embassy. As Mr. Dunn was temporarily
                                    absent from the Department, the letter was at Mr. Kwapiszewski’s
                                    request forwarded to the Secretary of State. In a memorandum of
                                    November 17, 1943, the Under Secretary of State. Edward R.
                                    Stettinius, recommended to Cecil W. Gray, of the office of the
                                    Secretary: “The matter is rather urgent. I have mentioned it to
                                    the Secretary and I think if you could squeeze the Ambassador in
                                    for a fifteen-minute appointment either Friday or Saturday it
                                    would be wise because of the pressing nature of the Polish
                                    matter at the moment.” In another note to Mr. Gray on November
                                    18, H. Freeman Matthews, Chief of the Division of European
                                    Affairs, stated: “This is pretty bitter stuff—and not one word
                                    of gratitude for Moscow Conf. or one word against the Nazis! I
                                    think the Secretary should look at this just before seeing the
                                    Pole.”</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-17">November 17,
                                        1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Jimmy</hi>: I deeply regret that the
                                Secretary of State has not yet found time to receive me in
                                connection with the results of the Moscow Conference and that,
                                according to your secretary, you are likewise too busy to see me. I
                                am especially anxious to have the opportunity of a frank talk with
                                you after reading the press reports of the Secretary’s two press
                                conferences of November 15th and 16th. I have no means of
                                ascertaining whether the Secretary’s statements have been accurately
                                reported by the press, but these press reports are causing me grave
                                apprehension regarding Poland.</p>
                            <p>While the Secretary’s statements, as reported by the press, to the
                                effect that the formula applied to Italy on geographical and
                                political self-determination is to be regarded as a pattern to be
                                applied to all liberated nations, gives me a feeling of relief, his
                                further comments, <pb facs="0491" n="479" xml:id="pg_479"/>
                                according to press reports, particularly those of the conference of
                                November 16th, have aroused my deep concern.</p>
                            <p>The interpretation of the vital and immediate problem of military
                                occupation of territories as they are being liberated, appears to
                                justify the anxieties of the Polish Government that the USA is
                                willing to admit the occupation of Polish territory <hi rend="italic">exclusively</hi> by Soviet forces, without the
                                participation, in some form at least, of American, British and
                                Polish forces.</p>
                            <p>You know the truth of the situation too well for me to have to stress
                                the fundamental difference between the disinterested occupation of
                                any territory by American or British forces, without Soviet
                                participation, and an occupation exclusively by the Soviets, of
                                Poland or part of Poland in view of clearly stated Soviet
                                annexationist claims on Poland. This matter is all the more serious
                                when one recalls the conduct of the Soviet authorities on Polish
                                territory after their invasion on September 17, 1939, and in the
                                course of their occupation until the German attack on Russia on June
                                22, 1941. At that time the Soviets partitioned Poland in agreement
                                with Germany and carried out a ruthless denationalization and
                                sovietization of that territory, applying methods of extermination
                                and deporting about a million and a half of leading and nationally
                                conscious Polish elements.</p>
                            <p>According to the Joint Four Nation Declaration signed in Moscow<note n="48" xml:id="d356fn48">For text, see <ref target="frus1943v01#pg_755">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 755</ref>.</note> (par. 6), as well as from the
                                press reports of the two last press conferences of the Secretary of
                                State,—no steps appear to have been taken to ensure the
                                reestablishment by the Polish Government of civil administration in
                                Poland as the liberation of Poland’s territory will proceed. On the
                                contrary, the press reports of the Secretary of State’s yesterday’s
                                press conference quote him as having expressed the opinion that the
                                administration of the occupied territory will be taken over by the
                                military authority of the Allied Power which will be the first to
                                enter such territory in the course of war operations. In Poland’s
                                case this would mean that the Soviet military command will be
                                empowered exclusively to take over the administration of occupied
                                Polish territory.</p>
                            <p>On the basis of past tragic experience, as well as of our intimate
                                knowledge of Soviet methods, this would be equivalent to delivering
                                Poland to the USSR for immediate and complete sovietization.</p>
                            <p>The press reports further state that after the termination of such
                                military occupation, the temporarily suspended application of the
                                principles of the Atlantic Charter would take place. One of the
                                expressions of this belated application of these principles would be
                                the right of the population freely to express by popular vote or
                                plebiscite its will regarding its national allegiance and form of
                                government.</p>
                            <pb facs="0492" n="480" xml:id="pg_480"/>
                            <p>In the case of Poland, after a considerable time of uncontrolled
                                Soviet occupation, such application of principles would remain but
                                an empty wish. One cannot hold a plebiscite on a cemetery and,
                                undoubtedly, by that time Poland would have virtually become a
                                cemetery. Moreover, free expression by popular vote in a sovietized
                                country is a contradiction in terms and totally out of the
                                question.</p>
                            <p>How can one persuade the Polish people,—whose splendid resistance,
                                unique of its kind, to enemy pressure in this war, and whose
                                behavior, has given to Poland the distinction of being the only
                                European country without a Quisling,—that they are to be treated
                                worse than Ethiopia and Italy. The Negus has already taken over his
                                liberated country and its administration, while in Italy, although
                                she was one of the leading Axis Powers, the local Italian civil
                                administration is already allowed to function.</p>
                            <p>I must return once more to the unfortunate wording of Paragraph 6 of
                                the Joint Four Nation Declaration of Moscow. In this Paragraph it is
                                said: “That after the termination of hostilities they (the
                                signatories) will not employ their military forces within the
                                territories of other states except for the purposes envisaged in
                                this declaration and after joint consultation.”</p>
                            <p>This wording clearly implies that while hostilities are still in
                                progress, the occupying power may use its forces for purposes not
                                envisaged in the Declaration and without any previous consultation
                                with the three remaining nations.</p>
                            <p>For Poland this creates a situation of the gravest peril when viewed
                                in the light of the occupation of Poland exclusively by the forces
                                of the USSR. The fact that the USSR Government refuses to resume
                                diplomatic relations with the Polish Government, further aggravates
                                this situation.</p>
                            <p>To sum up the apprehensions which I consider it my duty to
                                communicate to you without delay, I admit that I still lack your
                                official interpretation regarding the dangerous wording of Paragraph
                                6 of this Declaration, as well as your authoritative version of the
                                Secretary’s remarks at his press conferences. However, if my
                                interpretation, based on that of the press, is correct, I must
                                regretfully say that the situation of Poland and, for that matter,
                                of other European countries, must be regarded as extremely serious
                                inasmuch as it appears that they are being surrendered to the mercy
                                of the Soviets rather than encouraged to expect the liberation
                                repeatedly promised them in the Atlantic Charter, the Declaration of
                                the United Nations, and so many other more specific statements on
                                the part of the Governments of the United States and Great Britain,
                                guaranteeing the restoration of their independent existence.</p>
                            <pb facs="0493" n="481" xml:id="pg_481"/>
                            <p>I am sure that in view of the urgency of the situation which my
                                country faces at this moment, you will forgive my insistence on
                                trying to find the means of bringing these considerations to your
                                immediate attention. I should be most grateful if you would
                                communicate them to the Secretary of State and if I could be given
                                the earliest opportunity of discussing them with you and of being
                                received by the Secretary of State.</p>
                            <p>I am,</p>
                            <p>Yours ever</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Jan Ciechanowski</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>