<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="369" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">860C.515/111</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Polish Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Ciechanowski</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="64" xml:id="d369fn64">This note was acknowledged on
                                    January 19, 1944.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">819/SZ–10</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-28">December 28,
                                        1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: During the past three years I have
                                had the honor of informing you, on several occasions, with regard to
                                the Polish gold which had been shipped to French West Africa and had
                                been lost to the control of the Bank of Poland.</p>
                            <p>Lately, Mr. Michalski, Manager of the Bank of Poland, who, thanks to
                                the assistance of the Department of State, proceeded to Algiers at
                                the beginning of 1943, had the opportunity of negotiating with the
                                French authorities in Algiers. I have been informed that these
                                negotiations resulted in the signing of an agreement between the
                                Bank of Poland and the French National Liberation Committee on
                                December 17th, 1943. In accordance with the terms of this agreement,
                                the Polish gold in question is to be repossessed by the Bank of
                                Poland and concurrently the suit which has been instituted in New
                                York against the Bank of France is to be discontinued and the
                                attachment of Bank of France assets resulting from such suit
                                vacated.</p>
                            <p>In view of the sympathetic consideration which the Department of
                                State and the Treasury Department have given to the position of the
                                Bank of Poland in this matter, it gives me particular pleasure <pb facs="0508" n="496" xml:id="pg_496"/> to advise you of this
                                development and I would be grateful if you would inform the
                                Secretary of the Treasury thereof.</p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ciechanowski</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>