<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Standley) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d399</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">399</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receKRNx87Ug7K5bW" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="399"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d399">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.00B Communist International/243:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Standley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-05-23">May 23,
                            1943</date>.<lb/>[Received May 25—12:37 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>514. <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> for May 22 published resolution of Presidium
                    of Executive Committee of Communist International recommending dissolution that
                        organization<note n="91" xml:id="d399fn91">The Presidium took the decision
                        to dissolve the Communist International on May 15, and this resolution was
                        published in <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> on May 22.</note> and releasing
                    sections of Comintern from duties issuing from regulations and decisions of
                    Communist International.</p>
                <p>Resolution outlines briefly role of Comintern world affairs since 1919. Comintern
                    assisted in formation genuine workers’ parties and helped expose Fascist
                    preparations for present war.</p>
                <p>However, it points out it has been clear for years that historical and other
                    differences between different areas of world constitute insurmountable obstacles
                    to direction of working class movement of various countries by one international
                    center.</p>
                <p>War accentuated differences in situation of various countries. Workers and all
                    honorable people in countries of Hitlerite bloc must do all they can to
                    overthrow their government’s order to insure defeat of Hitler and prepare future
                    international friendship based on equality. These tasks can best be fulfilled by
                    the vanguard of the workers movement in each separate country. In support of
                    this position it recalls resolution to this general effect of Seventh Congress
                    of Comintern as well as decision of the United States Communist Party to leave
                    Comintern in November 1940.<note n="92" xml:id="d399fn92">The Communist Party
                        took action on November 16, 1940, to withdraw from the Communist
                        International to obviate the necessity of registering under the
                        Anti-Subversive Activities Act (Voorhis Act), approved October 17, 1940; 54
                        Stat. 1201. See the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, November 17,
                        1940, p. 9, col. 1.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Moreover, states resolution, Communists have ever [<hi rend="italic">never?</hi>]
                    been tradition bound. They hold that organizational forms must be <pb
                        facs="0544" n="532" xml:id="pg_532"/> abandoned when they have fulfilled
                    their historic functions. First International<note n="93" xml:id="d399fn93"
                        >Originally the International Working-Men’s Association founded in London in
                        1864, and dissolved at Philadelphia in 1876.</note> for example ceased to
                    exist after it had laid foundations of workers parties in Europe, America.</p>
                <p>In addition to the above considerations resolution cites growth in political
                    maturity of Communist Party and its cadres in various countries and requests
                    made during war by number of sections for dissolution of Comintern. It being
                    impossible under present conditions to call a Congress the Executive Committee
                    undertook to suggest resolution of dissolution for ratification by sections.</p>
                <p>Resolution concludes by appealing to supporters of Comintern to concentrate all
                    their strength for defeat German Fascists.</p>
                <p>[Here follows list of names of the members of the Presidium who signed the
                    resolution.]</p>
                <p>Complete text by mail.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Standley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
