<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-03-09T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-03-09T03:00:00-05:00" n="488" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d488">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/28388:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Standley</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-03-09T11:00:00+03:00">March
                                        9, 1943—11 a.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 1:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>131. Department’s 118, March 6, 5 p.m.<note n="94" xml:id="d488fn94">See footnote 87, <ref target="#pg_624">p. 624</ref>.</note> The
                                British Ambassador has shown me the full texts of the memoranda in
                                question as well as a recent note from Molotov<note n="95" xml:id="d488fn95">See telegram No. 1728, March 10, 9 p.m., from
                                    the Chargé in the United-Kingdom, <ref target="#pg_633">p.
                                        633</ref>.</note> in reply to certain British
                                representations in the premises. This note stated that the Soviet
                                Government adhered to its position in regard to the basing British
                                air squadrons in north Russia and the protection of convoys, and in
                                every instance accused the British of failing strictly to abide by
                                their original agreements with the Soviet Government.</p>
                            <p>From my observation of the situation, the British have probably
                                failed on various occasions strictly to live up to the letter of
                                their agreements, thus justifying to some extent the Soviet
                                grievances. However, it appears certain that the absence of a real
                                spirit of cooperation on the part of Soviet officialdom in the
                                north, and the presence of the obstructionist tactics and the petty
                                annoyances so common in this country are also contributing factors
                                in the present British-Soviet difficulties.</p>
                            <p>Clark Kerr appeared quite worried in regard to the situation and not
                                at all optimistic in regard to future British-Soviet relations.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Standley</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>