<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-09-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="552" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d552">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 European War
                                1939/1997</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 2244</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-09-29">September 29,
                                        1943</date>.<lb/>[Received October 30.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to submit herewith
                                the substance of a conversation which took place recently between
                                Mr. Konstantin Vinogradov, <pb facs="0711" n="699" xml:id="pg_699"/>
                                First Secretary of the Soviet Legation at Stockholm, and a member of
                                my staff.</p>
                            <p>During the course of the conversation, the subject of the rumored
                                peace negotiations between Germany and the U.S.S.R. was mentioned.
                                Reference was made to the numerous articles about this matter which
                                had appeared in the Swedish press. Rumors in circulation to the
                                effect that peace conversations between Germany and the U.S.S.R. had
                                taken place in Stockholm were also touched upon in the
                                conversation.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Vinogradov’s reaction to this matter was most interesting,
                                particularly in view of the repeated reports in the Swedish press
                                according to which the U.S.S.R. was alleged to be taking a somewhat
                                lenient attitude in respect to possible peace conditions for
                                Germany. While he did not say in so many words that German peace
                                feelers had reached the Soviet Legation at Stockholm, his remarks
                                implied that this had actually been the case. He referred vaguely to
                                individuals who had tried to act as “agents” and “intermediaries”
                                for Germany, and to efforts made by such persons to approach the
                                Soviet Legation in behalf of Germany. He also intimated that
                                attempts of this kind had been made by Axis Legations in Stockholm
                                with which the Soviet Legation was on friendly terms. In this
                                connection particular mention was made of the Bulgarian Legation in
                                Stockholm.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Vinogradov stated that in all of these instances the reply of the
                                Soviet Legation had been: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“No! No! And again No! We do not want to have anything to do
                                        with matters of this kind. The only thing that we will
                                        listen to from Germany is an offer of ‘complete
                                        capitulation’.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>He went on to say that it would not be in the interest of the
                                U.S.S.R. to make peace with Germany on any other terms. He referred
                                in particular to the tremendous efforts that were now being made by
                                the United Nations to bring Germany to its knees. The second front,
                                he said, would soon be an established fact whereupon Germany would
                                be brought into a much more difficult position. Moreover, there
                                would be absolutely no point in giving consideration to a separate
                                peace with Germany at this time when the victorious Soviet armies
                                were rapidly regaining the U.S.S.R. territory that had been overrun
                                by the Germans.</p>
                            <p>In view of the fact that Mr. Vinogradov in all previous conversations
                                has been evasive and that he usually is very close-mouthed, limiting
                                his replies to quotations from speeches by Stalin or Molotov, there
                                is reason to believe that the foregoing remarks may be the result of
                                instructions from Moscow. This question has probably been asked
                                members of the Soviet Legation so frequently of late that
                                instructions were necessary.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Herschel</hi> V. <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>