<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Elbridge Durbrow of the Division of European
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d648</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">648</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-12-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recFfX7HQw90Z0cuH" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112953"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Reproduction</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="648"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d648">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.24/1369</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Elbridge Durbrow of the Division of European
                        Affairs</hi>
                    <note n="60" xml:id="d648fn60">Addressed to H. Freeman Matthews, Chief of the
                        Division of European Affairs, and James C. Dunn, Adviser on Political
                        Relations.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-23">December 23,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Barkley<note n="61" xml:id="d648fn61">R. E. Barclay, First Secretary of the
                        British Embassy.</note> of the British Embassy called yesterday and handed
                    me the attached draft of a proposed agreement<note n="62" xml:id="d648fn62">Not
                        printed.</note> between the United States, Great Britain and the Soviet
                    Union covering the exchange of secret technical military information.</p>
                <p>As indicated in my previous memorandum on this subject the British are pressing
                    us to conclude such an agreement and have indicated that they feel that the
                    following advantages would ensue therefrom: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Under the present arrangement with us and their bi-lateral agreement
                            with the Soviet Union the British have to constantly consult the United
                            States prior to turning over to the Soviets secret information on
                            military devices of common development which causes considerable
                            delay.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>They feel that there are many secret military devices which a year ago
                            were not known to the enemy but which have since fallen into their hands
                            and therefore, since they are known to the enemy there should be no
                            reason why they should not be made known to our ally.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>In discussing this question with Mr. Blackett, a civilian technical
                            adviser with the British Admiralty now in the United States, he
                            indicated that British military experts were of the opinion that if we
                            should make available in time many of the secret military devices which
                            are not now available to the Soviet Government, they could be put into
                            production and installed in eastern Siberia and thus put the Soviet Army
                            in a better position to join in the fight against Japan and also make
                            them more willing to do so.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>As the British Government feels that even though we may not receive
                            full and equal information from the Soviet Government covering their
                            secret military devices, we will at least assist the Soviets in making
                            it easier to “kill more Germans” and also further convince them of our
                            sincerity in desiring to cooperate with them.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The Embassy has indicated that the British General Staff is taking up this
                    question through the Combined Chiefs of Staff in Washington but hopes that the
                    Department can indicate that it is favorably inclined to drawing up some such
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>It is not entirely clear why the British Government proposes the conclusion of a
                    tripartite agreement on this subject instead of encouraging the United States
                    Government to draw up a bi-lateral agreement similar to the one they have with
                    the Soviet Government. <pb facs="0807" n="795" xml:id="pg_795"/> I gained the
                    impression, however, that the British Government is pressing for the tripartite
                    agreement since they have found in actual practice that the escape clause in
                    their present agreement with the Soviet Government has proved somewhat
                    embarrassing. The escape clause now in effect between the two governments
                    provides that each shall furnish all secret information on military devices to
                    the other except in certain cases when reasons must be given for not disclosing
                    the information.</p>
                <p>In this connection, it will be noted in the attached draft agreement that the
                    escape clause in Article 2 provides three reasons for withholding information
                    from the other parties.<note n="63" xml:id="d648fn63">
                        <p>Article 2 specified the three reasons as follows: <list>
                                <item>“(i) because the weapon, process or device is of such
                                    particular secrecy that the Government concerned considers that
                                    it should only be employed under certain limited
                                    conditions;</item>
                                <item>(ii) because the existence, employment or effect of the
                                    weapon, process or device is unknown to the common enemy, and
                                    the Government concerned considers that in order to prevent
                                    premature disclosure to them the information should be withheld
                                    until it can be used with the greatest possible effect against
                                    them;</item>
                                <item>(iii) because the weapon, process or device is in such an
                                    early stage of development that its disclosure would not in the
                                    opinion of the Government concerned be of use to the other
                                    contracting Governments in the war against the common
                                    enemy.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </note> Mr. Barkley reading from a telegram discussing this question indicated
                    that the British Government thought that the proposed escape clause would be
                    more satisfactory than the one in the present British-Soviet agreement, since it
                    contains three exceptions and if a tripartite agreement is concluded the escape
                    clause could be invoked in certain instances without having to specify which one
                    of the three exceptions applied to a particular device in question. In this
                    manner the British Government apparently hopes to avoid having to give specific
                    reasons in each case when it is deemed imperative not to exchange technical
                    military information.</p>
                <p>There is a possibility that since many of the technical military devices being
                    used by the British and American forces are of common development the British
                    Government may feel that in cases where it is deemed inadvisable to exchange
                    information with Soviets, part if not all of the onus for this refusal can be
                    placed upon the American Government.</p>
                <p>Article 4 of the proposed agreement covers the use of technical information and
                    data after the termination of hostilities. The proposed article is very general
                    and, considering the completely different policy in regard to patents, royalties
                    and licenses in the Soviet Union, it does not, because of its general nature,
                    appear to give adequate protection to American firms against the use of trade
                    secrets and patented devices after the termination of hostilities.</p>
                <pb facs="0808" n="796" xml:id="pg_796"/>
                <p>Under present conditions many American firms have, despite the somewhat general
                    patent protection clause in the Master Lend-Lease Agreement, been reluctant to
                    turn over specific technical details for use by the Soviet Government since they
                    are apprehensive lest this information, which in many cases involves trade
                    secrets, will be used to produce goods commercially which will compete with
                    American goods in the world market after the war.</p>
                <p>In this connection under the present arrangement with the War and Navy
                    Departments requests by Soviet agencies for specific information regarding the
                    manufacture or operations of the devices developed by American firms, are passed
                    on from a military secret point of view by the War and Navy Departments and then
                    the Department of State has addressed a letter to the firm in question along the
                    lines of the attached letter to the Caterpillar Tractor Company, dated June 26,
                        1943.<note n="64" xml:id="d648fn64">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It will be noted from the enclosure to the attached letter that the firm is told
                    that in making available any such information “the Soviet Government must make
                    such arrangements as may be necessary with the patentees or the original
                    manufacturers of the given devices, for the reproduction or use of any features
                    of such given devices, guaranteeing to such manufacturers or patentees a right
                    to establish a claim against the Soviet Government for entire and reasonable
                    compensation for such reproduction …”<note n="65" xml:id="d648fn65">Omission
                        indicated in the original memorandum.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It is felt that the wording of this paragraph might mislead American firms into
                    the belief that the United States Government has some arrangements with the
                    Soviet Government assuring that patentees will be protected after the
                    termination of hostilities. There apparently is no such arrangement. It has been
                    the experience in the past that it is difficult if not impossible for foreign
                    firms to obtain adequate and complete protection for their patents used in the
                    Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>In view of the above it would seem advisable if an agreement for the exchange of
                    secret military information with the Soviet Union is concluded, it should
                    contain a more specific article giving greater assurance to American firms
                    regarding the use of their patents or trade secrets after the termination of
                    hostilities. If it should not be deemed advisable to incorporate this in the
                    specific military secret agreement, it is felt that this question should
                    nevertheless be covered simultaneously in a separate exchange of notes.</p>
                <p>If such an arrangement is made not only would the Department be in a better
                    position to give assurances to American firms that they <pb facs="0809" n="797"
                        xml:id="pg_797"/> would receive some patent protection in the Soviet Union
                    after the termination of hostilities but also American firms might, in the
                    interests of the war effort, be more willing during the war to make available to
                    the Soviet Government various trade secrets and patented devices which up until
                    the present time they have been reluctant to divulge.</p>
                <p>Recently the Soviet Purchasing Commission in Washington and Soviet organizations
                    in Moscow have asked for very specific information covering the manufacture of
                    American products which, although they might be used during the war, could also
                    be manufactured subsequent to the termination of hostilities for commercial use.
                    In view of the possibility that this type of request will increase it is felt
                    that this question should be considered most fully in connection with any
                    agreement we might make with the Soviet Government for the exchange of military
                    information during the war.</p>
                <p>As an indication of the type of detailed information requested by Soviet
                    organizations there is also attached a copy of a letter dated November 24, 1943
                    to the Caterpillar Tractor Company.<note n="66" xml:id="d648fn66">Not
                        printed.</note> An official of the company discussing this letter indicated
                    that the requests covered every possible detail regarding the manufacture of
                    Caterpillar Tractors including heat treatment processes, et cetera. This
                    official indicated that while his company was willing to assist the Red Army in
                    every way in its fight against our common enemy they could not make effective
                    use of this detailed information during the war but might be in a position to
                    use it in the manufacture of commercial tractors after the termination of
                    hostilities. Because of this possibility the Caterpillar official indicated that
                    he did not believe his company would feel free to comply fully with the Soviet
                    request.</p>
                <p>If it should be decided to conclude the proposed tripartite agreement and
                    incorporate therein an article giving further protection to American firms, this
                    might be done by making provision therein for licensing contracts to cover the
                    manufacture of the specific device after the war or the Soviet Government might
                    purchase the right to exploit the patent or trade secret for a lump sum rather
                    than to try to work out a royalty arrangement. It is understood that Amtorg in
                    New York has in recent years been willing to purchase such rights in order to
                    overcome the reluctance of American firms to “take their chances” with patent
                    arrangements in the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>While it is believed advisable to take all necessary steps to assure that the
                    Soviet authorities will receive information which they may need in the
                    prosecution of the war it is not clear, for the following <pb facs="0810"
                        n="798" xml:id="pg_798"/> reasons, whether the conclusion of the tripartite
                    agreement would in fact accomplish this end: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>It is understood that under Lend-Lease we are furnishing the Red Army
                            with all material and devices which it may require in its fight against
                            the Germans.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>If instead of furnishing the Red Army the various devices we should
                            give them detailed information regarding the manufacture of these
                            devices it is not certain that the necessary plant facilities could be
                            constructed during the war to make effective use of them against the
                            enemy.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>As far as is known, the Soviet Government has not indicated that it
                            desires to conclude an agreement for the exchange of secret military
                            information. It may, therefore, be assumed that they feel that they are
                            obtaining under present arrangements all important military devices
                            available in the United States.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The possibility cannot be excluded that the British have suggested the
                            conclusion of the tripartite agreement since they are not satisfied with
                            their present arrangements with the Soviet Government on this question
                            and hoped to effect a change by bringing us into the picture.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Elbridge Durbrow</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
