<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="823" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d823">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00114 Pacific War/125:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-16">February 16,
                                        1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>397. American interests Far East—prisoners of war camps. Your 410,
                                411, 413 and 417, all January 18th.<note n="7" xml:id="d823fn7">None
                                    printed.</note> While the Japanese Government has assumed the
                                obligation under Article 14 of the Geneva Prisoners of War
                                Convention to provide every kind of medical attention prisoners of
                                war need, it is possible that there is a limited supply in Japan of
                                the medicines used in the treatment of beriberi, dysentery,
                                diphtheria, bronchitis, rheumatism, and many of the other diseases
                                from which American prisoners of war in Japanese hands are
                                suffering. Although the Japanese Government is obligated to provide
                                such medicines the United States Government is prepared to ship them
                                by air to a convenient point where they may be picked up by the
                                Japanese provided that the Japanese Government will undertake that
                                obligation and arrange for the reception and distribution of the
                                medicines in accordance with the terms and spirit of the Geneva
                                Prisoners of War Convention. Several shipments might be made to <pb facs="0975" n="963" xml:id="pg_963"/> some point adjacent to
                                Japanese-occupied territory, there to be picked up by the Japanese
                                for distribution under the supervision of the International Red
                                Cross representatives in Japan and Japanese-controlled
                                territory.</p>
                            <p>The foregoing observations do not apply to furnishing quinine for the
                                treatment of malaria, chills, etc., as it is known that the Japanese
                                have large supplies of that drug. Request Swiss Minister Tokyo to
                                urge Japanese Government to make adequate quantities of quinine
                                available immediately for the treatment of American prisoners of war
                                in Japanese hands.</p>
                            <p>In addition to the responsibilities it has assumed under the Geneva
                                Convention, the following considerations might be pointed out to the
                                Japanese Government by the Swiss Minister: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Principles of humanity should prompt the detaining Power
                                        to make a special effort to provide the best care possible
                                        for sick prisoners of war.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Medical facilities provided by the United States
                                        Government for Japanese prisoners of war are excellent,
                                        being equivalent to those provided for personnel of the
                                        American armed forces.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>