<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-03T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-03T04:00:00-05:00" n="896" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d896">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00115 Pacific War/2028:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bern</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-03T10:00:00+01:00">December 3, 1943—10 a.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 7:27 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>7574. American interests, Far East, medical treatment internees.
                                Legation’s 5380, August 31. Following summary Swiss note November 30
                                conveying information telegraphed by Fontanel, Shanghai:</p>
                            <p>Prior “segregation” Swiss protégés, persons requiring medical
                                attention generally sent by Swiss representative and associations to
                                Allied doctors who content very low or nominal fees; patients signed
                                “special loan notes”. Upon internment all Allied doctors and owing
                                to certain abuses by other less scrupulous physicians Swiss
                                representative in consultation interned American, British doctors
                                prepared list recommended physicians largely neutrals who agreed
                                maintain fees reasonable level and prevent prolongation unnecessary.
                                These doctors treated all sick persons receiving financial
                                assistance namely, all <pb facs="1023" n="1011" xml:id="pg_1011"/>
                                those still exempt for reasons of health from segregation measures;
                                also sick persons in camps liberated for treatment Shanghai
                                hospitals.</p>
                            <p>Fontanel states Japanese authorities categorically refused assume
                                medical costs outside “assembly centers”. Special arrangements
                                accordingly made with Shanghai hospitals. This practice satisfactory
                                despite decision Japanese authorities not permit Swiss
                                representative visit patients thus hospitalized.</p>
                            <p>Japanese inspectors recently named Shanghai hospitals now insist,
                                contrary hospital regulations, camp patients henceforth be treated
                                by them or doctors they designate. Fontanel reports about 60%
                                available beds “Country Hospital” and “General Hospital” continually
                                occupied by camp patients (approximately 170 persons). Monthly
                                expenses these medical services charged against official funds
                                approximately 1,500,000 Shanghai dollars.</p>
                            <p>Owing to foregoing developments Fontanel informed Japanese Consulate
                                that, inasmuch as Japanese authorities refuse assume in accordance
                                with provision Geneva Convention these medical expenses which must
                                be paid from official funds represented government, he is unable
                                tolerate intervention Japanese inspectors. Japanese authorities
                                replied that henceforth camp patients, if liberated, undergo
                                treatment outside camps shall themselves pay these expenses.
                                Japanese added that necessary funds shall be deducted from those
                                paid by Swiss representative to assembly centers for relief.
                                Fontanel replied that relief funds paid not usable except for pocket
                                money disbursements which previously enabled internees procure at
                                canteen necessary items and supplementary food urgently needed
                                maintain health.</p>
                            <p>Fontanel adds that until Japanese authorities give assurance relief
                                funds not utilized cover hospitalization and for other purposes all
                                financial relief will be discontinued. According recent information
                                reaching Fontanel, relief funds partially used purchase stoves, fuel
                                for winter; also for various camp improvements, repairs and this use
                                of relief funds appears improper in view of Japanese responsibility
                                provide these articles.</p>
                            <p>Suspension relief greatly disturbs internees who are in great need.
                                Fontanel hopes conclude arrangement locally and with a view to
                                avoiding aggravation of situation requests that for the present no
                                intervention be made Tokyo. He desired learn urgently whether
                                Department approves his attitude.<note n="93" xml:id="d896fn93">In
                                    telegram No. 3089, December 11, to the Minister in Switzerland,
                                    the Department indicated approval of Mr. Fontanel’s action, and
                                    its desire “to be kept informed as his negotiations progress.”
                                    (740.00115 Pacific War/2028)</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Harrison</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>