<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="969" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d969">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">895.01/266</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far
                                    Eastern Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="2" xml:id="d969fn2">Marginal notation by the Secretary
                                    of State: “OK”.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-04-22">April 22,
                                    1943</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: On April 17 an officer of
                                the Chinese Embassy, at the instance of the Chinese Foreign Office,
                                approached an officer of FE<note n="3" xml:id="d969fn3">Division of
                                    Far Eastern Affairs.</note> to obtain in strict confidence the
                                view of this Government in regard to the question of recognition of
                                the “Provisional Government of the Republic of Korea” located at
                                Chungking, China.</p>
                            <p>You may recall that two reports have appeared recently in the press
                                in regard to the future status of Korea: Dr. T. V. Soong<note n="4" xml:id="d969fn4">Chinese Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note>
                                was quoted in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> of March 13
                                as having stated, in response to a question, that China wanted to
                                see Korea independent; and in a press report from London, dated
                                April 7 and written by Frederick Kuh of the <hi rend="italic">Chicago Sun</hi>, it was stated that the President and Mr.
                                    Eden<note n="5" xml:id="d969fn5">Anthony Eden, British Secretary
                                    of State for Foreign Affairs. For correspondence on his visit to
                                    Washington, March 12–30, see <ref target="#pg_1">pp. 1</ref>
                                    ff.</note> had “reportedly agreed that Korea is to be detached
                                from Japan and after being placed under international trusteeship
                                for a limited period will be proclaimed an independent state”. Also,
                                on March 29 Dr. Soong called on Mr. Welles<note n="6" xml:id="d969fn6">Sumner Welles, Under Secretary of State; for
                                    memorandum of his conversation with Dr. Soong, March 29, see
                                        <ref target="frus1943China#pg_845">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, China, p.
                                        845</ref>.</note> at Dr. Soong’s request, at which time Dr.
                                Soong made inquiry in regard to any general impressions relating to
                                Mr. Eden’s conversations in Washington. In reply, Mr. Welles,
                                referring to the question of Korea, commented to the general effect
                                that it seemed to him that the thought of the Chinese, the British,
                                and the United States Governments was moving along similar lines in
                                envisaging the setting up after the war of Korea as an independent
                                country under a temporary international trusteeship.</p>
                            <p>In view of the foregoing, it is suggested that Mr. Berle<note n="7" xml:id="d969fn7">Adolf A. Berle, Jr., Assistant Secretary of
                                    State.</note> ask the Chinese Ambassador<note n="8" xml:id="d969fn8">Wei Tao-ming.</note> to call on him and that
                                Mr. Berle inform the <pb facs="1103" n="1091" xml:id="pg_1091"/>
                                Ambassador of the substance of the preceding paragraph. It is
                                suggested further that Mr. Berle make further comment to the
                                Ambassador to the effect that it would seem best to us to let the
                                matter rest there; that, as the Ambassador knows, the question of
                                recognition of any regime as the Government of Korea involves a good
                                many complicated factors which relate not only to the situation in
                                the Far East but have a bearing also upon somewhat analogous
                                situations in other parts of the world; that this Government and, we
                                are sure, the other governments of the United Nations are giving
                                special attention at this time to questions which are associated
                                with prosecution of the war; that if the Chinese Government has
                                views or information which we do not have and which it believes
                                would be helpful to us, we should, of course, be very glad to be
                                informed thereof; that we appreciate the spirit of cooperation shown
                                by the Chinese Foreign Office in making this inquiry; and that we
                                hope that there will continue to be free and frank exchange between
                                our two Governments in regard to this question.</p>
                            <p>In this connection, it may be of interest that our Chargé d’Affaires
                                at Chungking<note n="9" xml:id="d969fn9">John Carter Vincent.</note>
                                has reported in a despatch dated March 17, 1943<note n="10" xml:id="d969fn10">No. 1004, not printed.</note> that, according
                                to the Director of the East Asiatic Affairs Department of the
                                Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs,<note n="11" xml:id="d969fn11">Yang Yun-chu.</note> the Chinese Government has always
                                encouraged unity between the two principal Korean factions in China,
                                namely, the “Provisional Government”, composed chiefly of
                                conservative Koreans, and the Korean Revolutionary Party, which is
                                “radical” and which has the support of the younger and more
                                aggressive Korean elements. The Chinese official informed Mr.
                                Vincent that if the two factions were able to attain unity he felt
                                that the Chinese Government would then wish again to consider the
                                question of recognition and consult with the United States
                                Government with regard to its attitude toward the question. Mr.
                                Vincent indicates in his despatch that the two factions are still a
                                long way from unity. Mr. Vincent adds that the “Foreign Minister of
                                the Provisional Government of Korea”<note n="12" xml:id="d969fn12">Tjo So-wang.</note> recently released a statement in Chungking
                                opposing proposals appearing in the American press that Korea be put
                                under international or mandated control.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>M[<hi rend="smallcaps">axwell</hi>] M. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">amilton</hi>]</signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>