<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>1. Memorandum From William Quandt and and Gary Sick of the National Security
                    Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of
                    the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Brzezinski))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec9ptkWICFUk7Mvu" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91001417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms transfers</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="rec7XCpI38AIhVpLJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recn8b1d7iCOsszeq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil production</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil prices</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119477"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Security assistance</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="rec3jq56tRRiAvPzT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85043147"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Energy policy</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-02-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-02-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="1"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1">
                <head>1. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_QWB_1">William Quandt</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_SG_1">Gary Sick</persName> of the National Security
                    Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d1fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Staff Material, Middle East, Chron File, Box 130, <persName
                            corresp="#p_QWB_1">Quandt</persName>: 2/1–2/77. Secret. Sent for
                        information. Brackets are in the original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-02-02">February 2, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Four-Year Goals in the Middle East</item>
                </list>
                <p>In the Middle East region, there are three broad areas in which to consider our
                    foreign policy objectives. Most critical is the Arab-Israeli conflict, which
                    will affect virtually all of the others in some fashion. But also important are
                    the development of cooperative relations with key Middle East countries and a
                    number of issues in the Persian Gulf/Indian Ocean area.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Arab-Israeli Conflict</p>
                <p>Peace in the Middle East is a goal to which the United States is deeply
                    committed. Our interests and our friendships require it. But a conflict which
                    has remained unresolved for over fifty years cannot be brought to a sudden end.
                    Our objective, therefore, over the next several years, should be to begin the
                    process of seeking a peaceful settlement.</p>
                <p>By the end of this year, we expect that a framework for negotiations will exist.
                    We could then urge the parties to develop a set of principles that would outline
                    the shape of a final peace agreement. For example, all parties to the
                    negotiations might be asked to agree that:</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="2" xml:id="pg_2"/>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item>—The purpose of the negotiations underway is to achieve a peace agreement
                        that will guarantee the sovereignty of all the states in the area. To this
                        end, the parties commit themselves to work toward a termination of all
                        hostile actions and to the eventual normalization of their relations.</item>
                    <item>—Peace must be based on mutual recognition and the establishment of agreed
                        and secure borders which do not constitute a source of future
                        conflicts.</item>
                    <item>—The parties are committed to work for a peace agreement that will meet
                        the legitimate concerns of the Palestinian people.</item>
                    <item>—The parties agree that a peace agreement should be implemented in stages
                        and that during the transition to full peace special security measures for
                        all sides will be essential.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The next step in negotiations, presumably during 1977, would be to work on
                    specific tradeoffs such as the end of belligerency for partial Israeli
                    withdrawal in Sinai and the Golan Heights. Next one might turn to the
                    Palestinian issue, perhaps seeking a solution within a confederal
                    Jordanian-Palestinian context.</p>
                <p>As Israel is asked to make concessions on territory and on the Palestinians as
                    part of the negotiating process, the United States will want to maintain a
                    continuing and close dialogue on security issues, on arms transfers, and on U.S.
                    guarantees of the various parts of the peace agreement. We will probably have to
                    accept the reality that very high levels of arms transfers to Israel will be
                    required throughout this phase. Only at a considerably later point in the
                    peacemaking process can we anticipate the possibility of reductions.</p>
                <p>To the degree possible, we will want to keep the Soviet Union out of the
                    substantive part of the negotiations. The one area in which the Soviets could be
                    tested as to their intentions would be in trying to induce the Palestinians to
                    moderate their position on Israel’s existence. We should make it clear that we
                    expect the Soviets to use their influence with the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> to bring about acceptance of the essential points of <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Resolutions 242 and 338.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Middle East Development Prospects</p>
                <p>Much of the Arab world is on the threshold of rapid socio-economic change.
                    Everywhere independence has been achieved, but only rarely has serious attention
                    been devoted to development. In the last part of this decade, however, we can
                    expect a more serious concentration on domestic issues. The United States will
                    therefore have an unusual opportunity to assist in the development of an
                    important part of the world. Since Arab capital is abundant, the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> contribution will be primarily through
                    technological assistance, our private sector activities, and some ideas that
                    will promote regional cooperation. To a large degree, the same is true for
                    Iran.</p>
                <p>More specifically, the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> should try at an early
                    date to revitalize our ongoing bilateral economic relations with key countries.
                    Joint com<pb facs="0046" n="3" xml:id="pg_3"/>missions that already exist in
                    Egypt, Saudi Arabia and Iran should be made to work more effectively.
                    Particularly in the case of Egypt, our efforts need a higher degree of
                    coordination for maximum political and economic impact.</p>
                <p>In the initial stages of our effort to promote development, we may have to take
                    initiatives and provide leadership. Our goal, however, should be to encourage
                    the countries of the area to assess their own needs and to do their own
                    planning. We should then try to improve our ability to be responsive to their
                    needs.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> Governmental efforts should appropriately be
                    directed at Egypt, Syria, <persName corresp="#p_JH_1">Jordan</persName> and
                    Lebanon. The private sector will remain active in Iran and Saudi Arabia, and
                    increasingly in Algeria and Iraq as well. By 1980, we should be able to count on
                    a very high volume of trade with the Middle East, relatively modest transfers of
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> aid, with the exceptions of Israel and
                    perhaps Egypt, a very large private sector involvement in development
                    activities, and ongoing government-to-government consultations on economic
                    issues.</p>
                <p>[This general issue should be raised during the staffing process with State,
                    Treasury and Commerce for suggestions on specific instrumentalities and courses
                    of action, which extend beyond our technical expertise.]</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Arabian Peninsula and Persian Gulf</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> interests in this area revolve almost
                    entirely around questions of oil production, price and supply, together with
                    protection and encouragement of the considerable <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> commercial investments in the region. From these interests, we
                    derive an immediate stake in the security and stability of the Persian Gulf
                    region, both in terms of the regional balance and in terms of our strategic
                    relationship with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. Our present
                    situation in the area, with the exception of oil prices, is basically favorable,
                    and realistically we would have no grounds to be dissatisfied if our position
                    four years from now was essentially the same. However, fundamental trends at
                    work in the area may tend to erode that position. By the mid-1980’s, these
                    trends could create a much more difficult situation for <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> policy as Iraq begins to replace Iran as the second largest oil
                    producer in the Gulf, as Soviet requirements for outside sources of oil possibly
                    become more acute, and as Soviet capability to project military influence into
                    remote areas comes to rival our own. Therefore, our policies over the next four
                    years must be designed to preserve our present advantages while establishing
                    policies designed to cope with foreseeable problems just over the horizon.</p>
                <p>We should attempt to expand the favorable climate for commercial exchange with
                    Iraq into other areas, with the objective of reestablishing diplomatic relations
                    at some point within the next four years. Barring <pb facs="0047" n="4"
                        xml:id="pg_4"/> major political disturbances, Iraq will emerge as a major
                    regional power in the Gulf area over the next 5–10 years, and it is in our
                    interests to be in a position to encourage them to adopt more moderate positions
                    and reduce their dependence on the Soviet Union. Our success will depend heavily
                    on internal developments in Iraq and on the progress toward a settlement of the
                    Arab-Israel dispute, which is the single greatest impediment to improved <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-Iraqi relations. We should, however, be alert
                    and responsive to even incremental shifts, demonstrating our willingness to meet
                    them at least half way. A realistic objective over the next four years would be
                    to establish a relationship with Iraq comparable to that which we now have with
                    Algeria or Syria.</p>
                <p>We should encourage the development of closer cooperation and coordination among
                    the nations of the Gulf on political, economic and security matters. Although
                    such initiatives must originate in the region, we can stress our support for
                    such an evolution in our normal diplomatic contacts and visits and by offering
                    preferential treatment to economic, technical and security assistance requests
                    which have a regional or multilateral dimension.</p>
                <p>We should begin to explore with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> the
                    possibility of establishing mutually acceptable limitations on military presence
                    in the Indian Ocean area. At the present time, neither superpower has a major
                    military capability in the area, but the basic support structure for a larger
                    permanent presence is being established. It is in our long-term interests to
                    develop meaningful limitations on <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-Soviet
                    military presence, whether by formal agreement or by the development of
                    unwritten norms of behavior, which will serve to inhibit a sizeable Soviet
                    buildup. Otherwise, the Soviet interest in protecting its sea lanes through the
                    area, its determination to establish itself as a global military power, and the
                    momentum of its rivalry with China for influence in the Third World may lead to
                    a continuing upward spiral of Soviet military presence which will directly
                    affect the security of our own oil supply and which would be difficult and
                    expensive for us to counter effectively.</p>
                <p>In terms of oil pricing and supply, our most direct and powerful influence lies
                    in our own domestic energy policy and our diplomatic influence with other energy
                    consumers. The more we can help to flatten the world demand curve for oil and
                    the more we can demonstrate our determination to explore vigorously alternative
                    energy technologies, the more weight will be given to our arguments in favor of
                    adequate production at manageable prices.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
