<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-01-23T12:05:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-01-23T10:30:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                        <head>180. Summary of Conclusions of a Presidential Review Committee
                                Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d180fn1">Source: Carter
                                Library, National Security Council, Institutional Files, Box 72,
                                    <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> 088, 1/23/79, Saudi Arabia
                                and Southwest Asia. Secret; Sensitive. The meeting took place in the
                                White House Situation Room. The minutes are not attached and were
                                not found. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> sent
                                the Summary of Conclusions to <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> under a January 29 memorandum, requesting
                                that he approve it. <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                                initialed the memorandum. (Ibid.)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1979-01-23T10:30:00-05:00" to="1979-01-23T12:05:00-05:00">January 23, 1979, 10:30 a.m.–12:05 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Summary of Conclusions: <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>
                                Meeting on Southwest Asia and Saudi Arabia</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">State</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Warren Christopher</persName>
                                        (Chairman), Deputy Secretary</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_ND_1">David Newsom</persName>, Under
                                        Secretary for Political Affairs</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SH_1">Harold Saunders</persName>,
                                        Assistant Secretary for Near Eastern and South Asian
                                        Affairs</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Treasury</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1">Blumenthal</persName>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SAM_1">Anthony Solomon</persName>,
                                        Under Secretary for Monetary Affairs</item>
                                    <item>Fred Bergsten, Assistant Secretary for International
                                        Affairs</item>
                                </list>
                                <pb facs="0628" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/><list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Defense</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BH_2">Brown</persName>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Charles Duncan</persName>,
                                        Deputy Secretary</item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MDE_1">David McGiffert</persName>,
                                        Assistant Secretary for International Security</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Office of Management and Budget</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WJ_1">John White</persName>,
                                        Deputy Director</item>
                                    <item>Ed Sanders, Associate Director for International
                                        Affairs</item>
                                </list>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Commerce</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>Stanley Marcuss, Deputy Assistant Secretary for Trade
                                        Regulations</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Energy</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>Harry Bergold, Assistant Secretary for International
                                        Affairs</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Joint Chiefs of Staff</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>General <persName corresp="#p_JDC_1">David C.
                                            Jones</persName>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Lt. General William Smith</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Central Intelligence Agency</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BR_2">Robert Bowie</persName>,
                                        Deputy Director for National Foreign Assessment</item>
                                    <item>Robert Ames, <gloss target="#t_NIO_1">NIO</gloss> for Near
                                        East and South Asia</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">White House</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <list>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">National Security Council</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TT_1">Thomas Thornton</persName>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_QWB_1">William Quandt</persName>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>Rutherford Poats</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> met to discuss the broad
                            question of strategy in Southwest Asia (the region from Yemen to
                            Bangladesh) as well as specific issues relating to Saudi Arabia. (S)</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Regional Strategy</hi>. There was a broad consensus
                            on the existence of domestic instability in many parts of this region
                            that either has external effects or could be exploited by outside
                            forces. While there are many interrelationships, differences within the
                            region preclude a single strategy except in the broadest terms. The
                            Indian subcontinent, Iran and the Arabian peninsula do, however,
                            comprise logical sub-regions. The group recognized that there was no
                            clear correlation between amounts of resources expended and positive
                            results; the region is sufficiently important, however, that we should
                            make a major effort to get whatever resources we believe are necessary,
                            and we should develop greater flexibility in applying resources such as
                            security supporting assistance. Several members commented on the need
                            for better analysis of the economic problems of the area and how they
                            relate to political and security factors. The State Department also
                            offered to circulate a list of current <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> commitments to the states of the region. (S)</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to Saudi Arabia.]</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Arabian Peninsula</hi>. While our strategy for South
                            Asia looks to a prominent Indian role, there is no similar strong point
                            in the Western part of the region where the situation is potentially
                            more explosive. There is greater concern about <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> capabilities and commitment and hence greater need for
                            an active <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> role of reassurance. We
                            need to communicate to the Arabs that our interests in the area are
                            vital and we will defend them. This could become more than an academic
                            exercise if the Saudis feel that they must eliminate the threat from the
                            South Yemen regime. It was widely agreed that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> is now perceived by many in the area as
                            uncertain of its purposes and failing to be responsive to the needs and
                            concerns of the area. (S)</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Saudi Arabia</hi>. Treasury presented an analysis of
                            what we want from the Saudis and the leverage we have over Saudi
                            decisions. Three related Saudi oil/economic decisions are of great
                            importance to us: continuation of present high-levels of production to
                            make up for the shortfall in Iranian output and to reduce upward
                            pressure <pb facs="0629" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/> on prices; moderation
                            on future oil prices; investment now to expand productive capacity in
                            the 1980s to 12.5 million bpd and perhaps as much as 14–16 bpd. The
                            decision to expand production is the most essential and will require
                            investments in excess of $5 billion just to get to 12.5 mbpd. Our
                            primary ability to influence these Saudi decisions lies not in the
                            economic area, where our choices are limited, but primarily in the
                            political/security area. We must recognize that the Saudis see the
                            Arab-Israeli conflict in security terms as well. It is this relationship
                            between Saudi economic decisions and what we can do in the security area
                            that we should focus on in preparation for Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BH_2">Brown</persName>’s trip and for <persName corresp="#p_FAAS_1">Fahd</persName>’s visit to Washington. We should
                            pay particular attention to the risks of developing a tight linkage
                            between these two sets of issues. (S)</p>
                        <p>Congressional support for Saudi Arabia is slipping, largely because of
                            Saudi actions at Baghdad and in <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d180fn2">See <ref target="#d175fn2">footnotes 2</ref> and <ref target="#d175fn3">3, Document 175</ref>.</note> This may complicate our ability
                            to meet Saudi security concerns. The Saudis are particularly anxious now
                            because of events in Iran, the apparent course of the Egypt-Israel
                            negotiations toward a separate agreement, and the strengthening of Arab
                            radical forces. Coupled with Saudi weakness from the standpoint of
                            internal and external security, these external threats have made the
                            Saudis more reliant upon our support and more fearful that it will not
                            be forthcoming. (S)</p>
                        <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Capabilities for Action</hi>. We need to look at our
                            economic and military resources for meeting the needs of some of the
                            countries in the region. A suggestion was made that we might try to
                            shorten lead times for delivering certain types of military equipment by
                            advance purchasing. This would help to overcome the belief that we are
                            unable to respond quickly to meet the requests of our friends. (S)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>