<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-01-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="238" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d238">
                        <head>238. Memorandum Prepared in the Central Intelligence Agency<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d238fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency,
                                Office of Support Services (<gloss target="#t_DI_1">DI</gloss>), Job
                                80T00634A, Production Case Files (1978), Box 13, Folder 3, Saudi
                                Arabia-North Yemen—Ambivalent Relations. Secret; [<hi rend="italic">handling restriction not declassified</hi>].</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <idno type="document-identifier">RPM 78–10006</idno>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-01-05">January 5, 1978</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Saudi Arabia-North Yemen—Ambivalent Relations</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Saudi Arabia’s ambivalent policies toward the Hamdi government reflected
                            its mixed feelings about North Yemen in general. While Crown Prince
                                <persName corresp="#p_FAAS_1">Fahd</persName> dominated policy
                            towards the Yemens for the past few years, the Saudi government appeared
                            to recognize that Hamdi was probably the most moderate national leader
                            they could hope for in Sana and that his efforts to modernize and
                            strengthen the central government deserved their support. This fairly
                            enlightened policy of <persName corresp="#p_FAAS_1">Fahd</persName>’s,
                            however, never erased the other strain in Saudi thinking about North
                            Yemen: deep suspicion—dating from the prolonged Yemeni civil war of the
                            1960s when Saudi Arabia supported the royalists—that any non-tribal
                            government in Sana could not be trusted because it had too many close
                            ties with leftists and other opponents of Saudi Arabia. As a result,
                            while they kept the Hamdi government afloat financially, the Saudis also
                            kept it weak by never giving it enough aid and support to defeat or
                            control the independent northern tribes which resisted any central
                            control from Sana.</p>
                        <p>Several factors color Saudi thinking about the Yemens and have
                            contributed to their desire to keep their hand in North Yemen’s internal
                            affairs. Because it is their “backyard,” the Saudis have always felt
                            free to meddle in North Yemen and have traditionally used the northern
                            tribes as their instrument. The Saudis also remember the series of
                            leftist regimes in Sana before Hamdi took power in 1974 and fear a
                            united North and South Yemen dominated by the Marxist regime in Aden.
                            Powerful elements in the Saudi government believe that the best
                            insurance against such an unpleasant eventuality is to keep the central
                            government in Sana perpetually weak by supporting the tribes.</p>
                        <p>In retrospect, it is evident the Defense Minister Sultan—a hardliner who
                            always distrusted Hamdi and strongly supported the tribes—began to
                            seriously challenge <persName corresp="#p_FAAS_1">Fahd</persName>’s
                            moderate policy last July.<note n="2" xml:id="d238fn2">In telegram 2662
                                from Sana, July 13, 1977, <persName corresp="#p_STJ_1">Scotes</persName> reported on the meeting between <persName corresp="#p_HI_1">al-Hamdi</persName> and Saudi officials.
                                (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770248–1179)</note> [<hi rend="italic">6 lines not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <pb facs="0800" n="757" xml:id="pg_757"/>
                        <p>Sultan’s campaign to prove that Hamdi was soft on the Yemeni left
                            undoubtedly received powerful support from Khalid ibn Sudayri, an uncle
                            of Crown Prince <persName corresp="#p_FAAS_1">Fahd</persName> and
                            Sultan. The Sudayris, a powerful tribe long closely aligned with the
                            House of Saud, have traditionally governed Najran Province, on the North
                            Yemen border, provided the ambassadors to Sana, and have been the
                            conduit for Saudi support to the Yemeni tribes. Involvement of the
                            Sudayris is, and undoubtedly will remain, an inescapable element in
                            Saudi-Yemeni relations.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Hamdi’s Assassination and its Implications</p>
                        <p>We do not know who, if anyone, was behind the assassination of Hamdi, but
                            it is widely believed in North Yemen that the Saudis were involved.<note n="3" xml:id="d238fn3">In telegram 15 from Sana, January 2, the
                                Embassy reported the latest information concerning <persName corresp="#p_HI_1">al-Hamdi</persName>’s assassination and the
                                question of Saudi involvement, noting that “Embassy Sana is now
                                prepared to go on record as saying that former <gloss target="#t_YAR_1">YAR</gloss> President Hamdi was killed by
                                fellow officers in coup.” The Embassy also reported that President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GAH_1">al-Ghashmi</persName> played a part
                                in the assassination, and that Lieutenant Colonel Ali Abdallah Saleh
                                was one of the killers. The Embassy commented: “Motive was belief in
                                Hamdi’s waxing relationship with South and waning one with Saudis.”
                                (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                P840139–2529)</note> [<hi rend="italic">2 lines not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (7½ lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>What is more important than who actually killed Hamdi, however, is the
                            implication of his murder for Saudi-North Yemeni relations. In late
                            October, Sultan took back control of Saudi relations with the Yemens
                            from <persName corresp="#p_FAAS_1">Fahd</persName> and his supporters.
                            Ironically, Sultan may well find that while dealing with Hamdi was
                            frustrating, he was probably preferable to the period of upheaval that
                            may lie ahead in Sana.</p>
                        <p>The Saudis appear to be concerned that Ghashmi lacks popular support.
                            Should they begin to distance themselves from Ghashmi, he will lose his
                            major pillar of outside support and his downfall might become a
                            self-fulfilling prophecy for the Saudis.</p>
                        <p>The Saudis, meanwhile, are maintaining close contact with an old favorite
                            of theirs, Abdallah al-Ahmar. Ahmar, a conservative [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] tribal leader from the
                            north, is totally unacceptable to the moderate and leftist portions of
                            the North Yemeni population. Sultan may find that his tougher policy
                            towards North Yemen does not produce any more satisfactory results than
                            did <persName corresp="#p_FAAS_1">Fahd</persName>’s more moderate
                            one.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>