<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Batavia ( (Livengood) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-04-06T03:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-04-06T03:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-04-06T03:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-04-06T03:30:00-05:00" n="107"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d107">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                    Indonesia/4–648: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d107fn1">Repeated in telegram 134, April 9, 6 p. m., to The
                        Hague.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-04-06T16:00:00+07:30"
                            >April 6, 1948—4 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>272. <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 219. Following is summary Indonesian
                    Delegation’s comments on Netherlands Delegation survey working paper reported
                        <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 206<note n="2" xml:id="d107fn2"
                        >Telegram 254, March 31, <ref target="#pg_129">p. 129</ref>.</note> (<gloss
                        target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 125, March 23<note n="3" xml:id="d107fn3"
                        >Not printed.</note>).</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Indonesian Delegation notes with satisfaction object envisaged by
                        Netherlands Government is settlement at earliest possible date.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Indonesian Delegation agrees that agreement on essentials be reached with
                        regard <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> and Union. Republic also resolved
                        conclude agreements on constitutional formation leaving no room divergent
                        interpretations.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Republic believes clear delineation of this objective will facilitate
                        parties in devising transitional measures by rendering issue understandable
                        to people.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Indonesian Delegation desirous that precedence be given questions
                        regarding <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> and Union, agreement on clear
                        outline of which should facilitate settlement on transitional measures since
                        these would then stand in light future. Order of political discussions
                        should be reverse to order actual events.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>For above reasons Indonesian Delegation cannot concur Netherlands
                        Delegation view that “aim of agreement shall be incorporate Republican
                        Government and its organs in Prov. Fed. Government and its organs”.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Indonesian Delegation sees aim of agreement as having greater
                        comprehensiveness, viz. creation <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> and
                        Union. Thus measures taken in transitional period will be of provisional
                        character and not of farreaching consequence.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Indonesian Delegation accepts formation of Prov. Fed. Government mentioned
                        in first of six additional principles on which Netherlands may confer
                        appropriate rights, duties and responsibilities as useful measure to arrive
                        at ultimate object; as such, however, aforementioned formation can only be
                        regarded as accessory to ultimate object.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Principles underlying Linggadjati Agreement still held in regard by
                        Republic which hopes clear agreement can be worked out removing differences
                        interpretation. However, Indonesian Delegation states that in addition
                        14-point formulation of Linggadjati principles by Netherlands Ministry of
                        Overseas Territories, Linggadjati contains recognition of Republic which may
                        be assumed to be known. In considering <pb facs="0152" n="138"
                            xml:id="pg_138"/> 18 principies accepted both parties January 17,
                        statement made by <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> January 17 should be
                        consulted.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Netherlands survey paper conveys idea “the” Prov. Fed. Government already
                        formed. Indonesian Delegation therefore inquires whether reference is to
                        Prov. Fed. Government installed by Lieutenant Governor General March 9. This
                        connection Republic Government has issued statement deeply regretting
                        formation by Van Mook of government under name of “Prov. Fed. Government”
                        which neither in form nor content corresponds Prov. Fed. Government
                        contemplated <hi rend="italic">Renville</hi> Agreement and is nothing more
                        than <gloss target="#t_NEI1">NEI</gloss> Government in slightly new form. In
                        opinion Indonesian Delegation, Prov. Fed. Government to be formed basis
                        first of six additional principles is a provisional government for interim
                        period on which Netherlands confers rights, duties and responsibilities.
                        Prov. Fed. Government of latter designation has yet to be discussed.
                        Discussions concerning formation of Prov. Fed. Government should principally
                        concern rights, duties and responsibilities to be conferred by Netherlands,
                        powers to be vested in Prov. Fed. Government in regard to individual states,
                        especially Republic, and powers to be retained by individual states,
                        especially Republic.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>First of six additional principles which stipulates that during stated
                        interval sovereignty throughout <gloss target="#t_NEI1">NEI</gloss> is and
                        shall remain with Netherlands, will form basis for negotiations leading
                        toward political settlement. At time this principle accepted as basis,
                        Republic which had earlier included Linggadjati Agreement with Netherlands
                        had already led existence as state. Republic had established and conducted
                        foreign relations. Republic willing become member <gloss target="#t_USI1"
                            >USI</gloss> on understanding that federation will have right to conduct
                        independent foreign relations. Present problem is manner in which during
                        interim period Republic’s foreign relations are to be maintained so there
                        will be no hiatus until emergence of foreign relations of <gloss
                            target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss>. Foreign relations of Republic constitute
                        undeniable reality. Republic has kept acting on <hi rend="italic">de
                            facto</hi> footing in some countries while several other countries are
                        entertaining foreign relations with Republic on <hi rend="italic">de
                            jure</hi> basis. Problem could be solved by Netherlands ceding such
                        sovereign rights to Prov. Fed. Government as to enable latter conduct
                        foreign relations.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Respect views expressed Netherlands survey paper concerning “future status
                        autonomous rulers, and special relations existing between crown and these
                        rulers”, Indonesian Delegation unable state its views since it not clear
                        what Netherlands Delegation has in mind. In Republic there are certain
                        regions called “special territories” but in current negotiations these
                        regions do not figure other than as being part Republic.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>Republic’s understanding is that free will of people mentioned in fourth
                        of six additional principles will be determined through <pb facs="0153"
                            n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/> plebiscite and not “in some other manner”.
                        Indonesian Delegation wishes it understood that plebiscite will be held to
                        determine wish of population of occupied territories of Java, Madura and
                        Sumatra within period not less than 6 months from signing of <hi
                            rend="italic">Renville</hi> Agreement.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
