<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Batavia ( (Livengood) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-11T00:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-11T00:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="129"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                    Indonesia/5–1148: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-11T13:00:00+08:00"
                            >May 11, 1948—1 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>387. <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 262. Republican Delegation departed
                    this morning for 3 days Jogja and perhaps crucial discussions Republican
                    Government.</p>
                <p>Yesterday afternoon saw Roem, Pringgo Digdo and Latuharhary and made unequivocal
                    presentation contents <gloss target="#t_Usgoc1">Usgoc</gloss> 97, May 7. Full
                    notes from which Dubois spoke, typed carelessly on yellow paper and without
                    heading or subscription, given to Roem at end talk to ensure receipt accurate
                    information by heads of Republican Government. We consider this sufficiently
                    direct approach Hatta since trip by US Delegation Jogja this juncture would
                    cause Republic much embarrassment and arouse great resentment Australian
                    Delegation.</p>
                <p>Roem appeared puzzled by basis our approach, namely that Republic delaying
                    negotiations, and cited Republic’s May 7 letter to <gloss target="#t_GOC1"
                        >GOC</gloss> complaining of press charge by Vredenburch to same effect.
                    Letter notes Republic submitted list subjects for discussion January 22, that
                    rules procedure not established until February 20, that Republic submitted list
                    members main committees February 19 while similar list from Netherlands not
                    submitted until March 10 and that Republic working paper on union was submitted
                    March 22 and Netherlands paper not until April 20. Roem further contended
                    Republic proceeding rapidly as possible in current talks view magnitude
                    decisions to be made. He said that while Netherlands insisted union not a state,
                    they proposed it have semi-legislative function in form ministerial council, <pb
                        facs="0183" n="169" xml:id="pg_169"/> treaty-making power, and judicial
                    power in union court to which individuals and corporations could appeal as well
                    as member states. In Republican view [these] were attributes of state.</p>
                <p>In course talk we stated we wished express overall US Delegation view of dispute.
                    We stressed fair settlement could and must be achieved here through assistance
                        <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>. By fair settlement, we meant settlement
                    in accord legitimate interests both parties, which in our view were not
                    irreconcilable. We considered Republic had right expect earliest creation
                    sovereign Indonesia in which elements constituting Republic would have full
                    opportunity play due part, that Netherlands had right expect sovereignty to be
                    transferred only to organized, functioning experienced federal government with
                    provision for all groups express themselves democratically. We emphasized <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> had given <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>
                    task assisting this settlement and that reference to <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss> of points at issue, leading contentious debates, could not serve
                    constructive purpose and would probably redound disadvantage Republic. We
                    frankly doing our best prevent such action. We believed West Java and Madura
                    reports would accomplish no useful purpose. In these and other reports we would
                    endeavor exclude all expressions controversial opinion and confine statement to
                    matters fact. If <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> finally failed, it would
                    then be necessary report failure and full circumstances to <gloss
                        target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, with what result we unable foresee, but until
                    then we believed negotiation should be conducted here in accordance intention
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> itself. Furthermore, we did not believe
                        <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> would fail.</p>
                <p>I respectfully suggest practice providing Netherlands full text my instructions
                    before I have had chance study or even receive them likely weaken position US
                    Delegation to disadvantage conduct negotiations here.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 387; Department pass The Hague.<note n="1" xml:id="d129fn1">This
                        was done the same day.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
