<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in the Netherlands</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d171</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">171</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-06-12T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-06-12T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-06-12T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-06-12T13:00:00-05:00" n="171"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d171">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                    Indonesia/6–1148: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in the Netherlands</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-06-12T14:00:00-04:00"
                            >June 12, 1948—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>243. For Bonsal from Butterworth: I take it that you will make an early
                    opportunity to make available to Boon the pertinent and appropriate info
                    contained in <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 302 (Batavia’s 493, June
                    11) particularly that contained in para no. 4.</p>
                <p>For your confidential info British Emb under instructions from London has
                    indicated its Govt will be pleased to join with this Govt in representing to
                    Dutch desirability of acceptance of proposals in question. While expressing
                    appreciation for offer I indicated Dept not yet in receipt of full airmail
                    details of proposal and therefore had not yet been able to reach considered
                    opinion and requested in the meantime British Emb query London as to whether in
                    effect British Govt merely acting in response to Australian Govt suggestion or
                    whether London had had opportunity carefully consider plan and in the light of
                    its vital interest in that area and its long experience with constitutional
                    govts in transition it was its considered view that it was in larger interest of
                    Dutch and others concerned for that Govt to make prompt acceptance. It was
                    obvious British Govt at least in part motivated by desire to prevent
                    disadvantageous discussions taking place in Security Council.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Batavia [as 257] for <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> as
                        <gloss target="#t_Usgoc1">Usgoc</gloss> 107.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
