<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Batavia (
                        Livengood
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d200</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">200</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-06-28T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-06-28T02:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-06-28T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-06-28T02:00:00-05:00" n="200" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d200">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                    Indonesia/6–2848: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-06-28T15:00:00+08:00">June 28, 1948—3 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>570. <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 325. Member <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> had illuminating talk June 26 with H. Adil
                    Puradiredja, Prime Minister Pasundan State and chairman Bandung Conference. Adil
                    said majority delegates Bandung favorably impressed by US-Aus plan, particularly
                    provisions regarding Constituent Assembly. He said delegates most important
                    states represented Bandung, especially Pasundan and East Indonesia, working on
                    plan transform Bandung Conference, which at least not entirely undemocratic in
                    origin, into provisional Senate of pre-federal government as off-set to present
                    autocratic Provisional Federal Government of representatives handpicked by Van
                    Mook. Next step would be formation new “pre-federal government of occupied
                    areas”. Delegation would be immediately dispatched to Republic, and with
                    Republic’s participation, pre-federal government of Indonesia would be set up.
                    Its sole important function would be call for elections to Constituent Assembly.
                    Whether Republic chose place its armed forces, foreign relations, etc., under
                    pre-federal government or hold out until formation <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss> would be immaterial, according Adil. Indonesia’s sole motive
                    now was obtain sovereignty soonest. Any matters likely impede <pb facs="0288" n="274" xml:id="pg_274"/> such transfer would be dropped. Adil said there no
                    interest in delineation states. He would accept anything Dutch proposed this
                    respect with view settling question after <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss>
                    sovereignty when full attention could be given desires populations various
                    territories.</p>
                <p>Adil admitted Bandung plan had only slightest chance success against certain
                    Dutch opposition but observed that Indonesians now had nothing lose. If motion
                    could be passed by Bandung Conference requesting conference be designated
                    provisional senate as step toward democraticization Provisional Federal
                    Government, action of Dutch in disapproving recommendation would at least reveal
                    that Dutch pose as champions democratic Indonesia is only pose. Adil thought
                    full publicity might possibly force Dutch accept recommendation, in which case
                    cooperation with Republic could be quickly established, revealing baselessness
                    Dutch contention that Indonesians divided in hostile camps. Asked if Republic
                    was informed of these plans to extent it would not hit ceiling if pre-federal
                    Senate formed at Bandung, Adil said he in continual touch with Hatta and Roem
                    and counted on full Republican support.</p>
                <p>Adil said original Dutch plan was to use “dependable” delegates at Bandung to lay
                    foundations <gloss target="#t_USI1">USI</gloss>. Unmistakable evidence
                    independence on part conference ease quick change plan, with conference reduced
                    to mere consultative body. First proof conference not to be dictated to was
                    rejection Urin, member <gloss target="#t_NethDel1">NethDel</gloss> and Van
                    Mook’s candidate for chairman conference, and election Adil who is known
                    Republican sympathizer. Dutch had previously tried block Adil’s appointment as
                    Prime Minister Pasundan, but Wiranatakusuma, head Pasundan state, had acted too
                    fast; Adil said any action put before conference with Dutch backing was now
                    automatically voted down.</p>
                <p>Adil enlarged upon difficulties confronting Indonesians in occupied territories.
                    Constant Dutch surveillance necessitated utmost circumspection in conduct
                    political activities. Adil said all his mail read by Netherlands, that political
                    discussions dangerous since it never certain who might be Dutch agent. He has
                    Dutch spies every department his government. There even Dutch spies every
                    ministry Jogja. Common Dutch practice is make summary arrests without charges,
                    hold victims for few days, then release them with warning. (This connection,
                    Republican Delegation has informed <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> Dutch
                    have closed all offices plebiscite movement Krawang, while Budiardjo says all
                    leaders plebiscite movement in Cheribon now in jail.)</p>
                <p>Adil remarked he expected outbreak local disorders for few days beginning July 17
                    since many Indonesians had got idea there would be plebiscite 6 months after <hi rend="italic">Renville</hi> Agreement and were determined have it. Regarding
                    apparent increase acts violence in Pasundan territory, Adil said Indonesians if
                    left to themselves would have no <pb facs="0289" n="275" xml:id="pg_275"/>
                    trouble maintaining order but that so long as Dutch troops present, constant
                    provocation to violence would exist. Asked if most Indonesians non-Republican
                    areas were pro-Republican, Adil replied this was like asking if most citizens US
                    were pro-American.</p>
                <p>Adil said any chance success Bandung plan would be lost if leaked to Dutch. If
                    plot could be put through, Netherlands-Republican, dispute would disappear and
                    Netherlands if it wished negotiate political agreement could negotiate with
                    representatives all Indonesia. Signed Ogburn.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
