<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-10T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-10T16:00:00-05:00" n="246" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d246">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                                Indonesia/9–1048: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Consulate General</gloss> at
                                    Batavia</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-10T17:00:00-04:00">September 10, 1948—5 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>427. <gloss target="#t_Usgoc1">Usgoc</gloss> 137. Counselor Neth Emb
                                and First Secretary called Sep 9 Dept’s request. Dept officers,
                                noting seriously increasing pressure on Hatta Govt of Communist
                                origin, stated Dept believed prompt action consolidate Hatta’s
                                position essential; suggested that only realistic means assuring
                                stability Hatta Govt lay in acceptance by parties just and practical
                                settlement which would accommodate legitimate nationalist
                                aspirations Repub and non-Repub Indonesians; such solution could not
                                be offered by one party to other under present circumstances with
                                any hope acceptance and only <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> or
                                    <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> was in position offer
                                plan which could be accepted by both parties; pointed out Cochran
                                had seen Neth plan and believed not only that it would be
                                unacceptable to Repub but its presentation this time would seriously
                                prejudice acceptance compromise <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> plan if offered subsequently; Cochran had
                                developed plan Dept believed entirely just and eminently practical
                                and was prepared energetically support, which Cochran would offer
                                both parties simultaneously within next few days. Dept officers
                                therefore requested Neth Emb Washington request Hague forego
                                presentation Neth plan to Repub, to <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> or to Bandung Conference and prepare favorably and
                                finally consider <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> proposal
                                when submitted Batavia.</p>
                            <p>Dept officers stated they were prepared describe contents plan to
                                Neth Emb Wash if Neth Emb desired but suggested representations to
                                Hague by Neth Emb would be less subject future complications if
                                contents plan not discussed this occasion. Neth Counselor
                                agreed.</p>
                            <p>Having expressed serious misgivings Hatta’s ability validate any
                                reasonable agreement, Neth Counselor expressed his willingness
                                recommend course suggested by Dept to Hague in most persuasive
                                manner; if Hague agreed this course action it would in effect be
                                placing its destiny in Indonesia in hands <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> sight unseen. Dept officers pointed out risk
                                involved relatively small in that Hatta’s failure validate agreement
                                would leave situation no worse in any important particular than it
                                now is. Dept officers made special point accommodation nationalist
                                aspirations Repub as necessary condition precedent action against
                                Communists whether taken by Hatta in concert with Neth and/or US or
                                alone. Dept officers also made clear in their opinion Hatta together
                                with <gloss target="#t_Masjoemi1">Masjoemi</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_PNI1">PNI</gloss> (Congen tel 763 Sep 7) could in
                                these circumstances be drawn into realistic cooperation with Neth in
                                degree impossible before.</p>
                            <pb facs="0345" n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/>
                            <p>Dept officers made clear plan was no “Dutch deal” and that
                                concessions to Repub were incorporated therein sufficient enable
                                Hatta return his govt bearing a square deal.<note n="1" xml:id="d246fn1">Repeated as 434 to The Hague.</note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>