<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Batavia (
                        Livengood
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d346</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">346</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-10-30T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-30T09:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-30T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-30T09:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.<gloss target="#t_BC1">BC</gloss>
                    Indonesia/10–3048: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Batavia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Livengood</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Batavia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-30T22:00:00+08:00">October 30, 1948—10 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>957. <gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 424. Arrived Jogja October 30, 9 a.
                    m. Met by Republic delegation chairman Roem to whom I delivered copy Netherlands
                    delegation letter 2473 dated October 28 (<gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss>
                        422)<note n="1" xml:id="d346fn1">Telegram 951, October 28, midnight, not
                        printed, but see footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_437">p. 437</ref>.</note>
                    under cover following letter October 29 addressed Roem signed Cochran: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have honor to refer to your letter of October 21, 1948, in which you
                            reaffirmed your desire to resume negotiations on basis of plan submitted
                            by <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> in its oral note dated
                            September 10, 1948.</p>
                        <pb facs="0459" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/>
                        <p>By a letter dated October 22, 1948, I transmitted a copy of your letter
                            to acting vice chairman of Netherlands delegation for confidential
                            information of his government. On evening of October 28, I received
                            letter number 2473, bearing same date signed by acting vice chairman of
                            Netherlands delegation. A copy of this letter is enclosed. You will note
                            that Netherlands Government states that it is prepared to resume
                            negotiations on basis of proposals of <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>, provided that the following are understood: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <list>
                                    <item>‘(A) That no agreement can be concluded before
                                        satisfactory proof of effected [<hi rend="italic">effective?</hi>] Republic measures to stop
                                        infringements of military terms of truce and to combat such
                                        infringements is obtained, and before appropriate measures
                                        are taken to implement economic terms of truce;</item>
                                    <item>(B) That in order to promote purposes referred to sub (A)
                                        the Republic delegation agrees, beforehand, that these
                                        points will be the first to be discussed when negotiations
                                        are resumed;</item>
                                    <item>(C) That if a solution regarding these points cannot be
                                        reached Netherlands Government will be forced to conclusion
                                        that negotiations to arrive at an overall agreement cannot
                                        have successful results;</item>
                                    <item>(D) That negotiations commence within few days after
                                        receipt of this letter.’</item>
                                </list>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The background of these ideas is set forth in the letter itself.</p>
                        <p>It will be noted the Republic delegation is called upon to agree that the
                            first subjects to be discussed upon resumption of negotiations will be
                            measures to be taken by Republic to stop infringements of military terms
                            of truce and measures to be taken to implement economic terms of
                            truce.</p>
                        <p>It becomes necessary therefore for me to inquire whether you are willing
                            to confirm your understanding of the points set forth above and in
                            particular to enter into the requested stipulation with regard to the
                            order of discussions as a preliminary to resumption of negotiations on
                            basis of plan proposed by <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>I shall be glad to transmit your reply to the acting vice chairman of
                            Netherlands delegation.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Discussed foregoing one hour with Roem and one hour with Pringgo Digdo. Received
                    by Hatta 12 noon. Discussed formal letter and Netherlands invitation to meet
                    Stikker. Hatta agreed proceed with party to Batavia Thursday November 4 on
                        <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> plane provided I procure Netherlands
                    approval for amphibian plane which Hatta hopes charter from Philippines pick up
                    him and party Batavia 2 days later and transport thence to Pajakomb near
                    Bukittinggi. Hatta would thus be visiting Batavia on first leg of fortnight tour
                    of Republic area Sumatra which he has planned for some time.</p>
                <p>Hatta is obliged remain Jogja through Wednesday November 3 because important
                    meeting that date. Above schedule would get Hatta and Stikker together middle of
                    latter’s anticipated 10 day stay Batavia. Hatta decision meant overruling some
                    advisors keenly resentful treatment accorded Republic in matter Batavia house,
                    hospital, immunities and evictees.</p>
                <p>Hatta will take advantage concession granted by Schuurman orally (<gloss target="#t_Gocus1">Gocus</gloss> 423<note n="2" xml:id="d346fn2">Telegram
                        953, October 29, <ref target="#pg_439">p. 439</ref>.</note>) and will not
                    answer my letter transmitting Netherlands <pb facs="0460" n="446" xml:id="pg_446"/> delegation letter October 28 until he has talked with
                    Stikker.</p>
                <p>Hatta promised speak as frankly with Stikker as he has talked with and written me
                    on conditions and problems of Republic and also on assurances he can give and
                    measures he can promise. He will endeavor clear up as much as possible of truce
                    implementation in conference with Netherlands Foreign Minister and prepare for
                        <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> opening negotiation soon <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> plan. He asked me suggest talks be directly
                    between Stikker and himself without assistants. I am to keep Hatta informed of
                    developments through Republic delegation secretary general Batavia.</p>
                <p>Hatta spoke with me in regard to Communism. Said as head of democratic regime he
                    had not seen fit outlaw Communism. Said he had however shown his determination
                    to crush Communists led in uprising by Moscow-trained Muso. He said GRR [<gloss target="#t_FDR1">
                        <hi rend="italic">FDR</hi>
                    </gloss>?] now groups several minorities including some Tan Malaka Communists.
                    Said he will crush any of these who follow example Muso group.</p>
                <p>Talked subsequently with Leimena and Republic Foreign Minister. They and others
                    mentioned above all consider Netherlands tactics play for time to prepare for
                    military action and a means of occupying <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>
                    with talks on truce while situation deteriorates further. They favor Hatta
                    leaving no stone unturned to evince willingness and sincerity in resuming
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>I telephoned Schuurman as soon as I reached Batavia. He called on me 7:30 p. m. I
                    told him result my visit to Jogja. It was agreed I would confirm on Sunday by
                    personal letter Hatta’s acceptance of invitation and also travel plans.
                    Furthermore I would include in this the fact with respect to my utilization of
                    concession granted orally by Schuurman of which Hatta is taking advantage in not
                    giving written answer until after meeting Stikker. Schuurman thanked me for
                    intervention with Republic and for benefit of having note from me which he can
                    show Stikker on anticipated arrival Batavia October 31, 2 p. m. Signed
                    Cochran.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 957; Department pass Hague.<note n="3" xml:id="d346fn3">This was
                        done the same day.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Livengood</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
