<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Far Eastern
                        Affairs (
                        Butterworth
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State
                    
                    Approved by the Under Secretary of State (Lovett),
                        March 18.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d510</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">510</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-03T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recd38b75873bd4a33" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="far-eastern-commission" subject="far-eastern-commission">Far Eastern Commission</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="510" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d510">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 FEAC/3–348</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Far Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Butterworth</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d510fn1">Approved by the Under Secretary of State (Lovett),
                        March 18.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-03">March 3,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Admission of Pakistan to Membership in the Far Eastern
                    Commission</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Problem:</hi> To determine what attitude United States
                    Government should take with regard to the application of Pakistan for membership
                    in the Far Eastern Commission.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi> The Department of State was notified on
                    January 12, 1948, by Dr. Blakeslee of the American Delegation to the Far Eastern
                    Commission that Pakistan had submitted a request to the Secretary General of the
                    Far Eastern Commission for permission to become a member of the Commission. The
                    terms of reference of the Far Eastern Commission state: “Membership of the
                    Commission may be increased by agreement among the participating powers as
                    conditions warrant by the addition of representatives of other United Nations in
                    the Far East or having territories therein.” On January 26, 1948, the British
                    Ambassador under instructions from his Government informed the Department that
                    he had been instructed to support the application of Pakistan for membership in
                    the Far Eastern Commission and that in the opinion of the Government of the
                    United Kingdom the views of the 11 participating powers could most conveniently
                    be exchanged in Washington through the respective diplomatic representatives. He
                    also pointed out that the Government of the United Kingdom presumes that the
                    term “agreement” in the terms of reference means “unanimous agreement”. On
                    February 20, 1948, the Department replied to the British Ambassador stating its
                    general agreement with the view that the terms of reference of the Far Eastern
                    Commission require that an application for membership receive unanimous approval
                    of the <pb facs="0692" n="678" xml:id="pg_678"/> member Governments and that the
                    Far Eastern Commission, as a body, is not competent to take action on such
                    applications. The Department also stated that, in the view of the United States
                    Government, Commission machinery could appropriately be utilized as a means of
                    polling the member Governments, the representatives on the Commission voting as
                    representatives of their Governments rather than as members of the
                        Commission.<note n="2" xml:id="d510fn2">A written reply to this effect was
                        dated March 1, not printed.</note> The New Zealand representative on the Far
                    Eastern Commission has informed the Department that the views of his Government
                    are in substantial agreement with those expressed above and that with regard to
                    the substantive aspect of the question New Zealand wholeheartedly supports
                    Pakistan’s application for membership. In view of the fact that Pakistan has
                    become a member of the United Nations and has presumably inherited certain
                    rights which it formerly shared with the Government of India on Far Eastern
                    matters it is believed that it would be difficult to oppose the application of
                    Pakistan for membership in the Far Eastern Commission.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The United States should favor the admission of Pakistan as a member
                            of the Far Eastern Commission.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The machinery of the Far Eastern Commission should be utilized as a
                            means of polling the member Governments, the representatives on the
                            Commission voting in such case as representatives of their Governments
                            rather than as members of the Commission.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The United States should take the position that the application of
                            Pakistan for membership in the Commission must receive the unanimous
                            approval of the member Governments of the Commission.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The United States member on the Far Eastern Commission should be
                            instructed in the sense of Recommendations 1, 2 and 3 above.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Concurrences:</hi> Concurrences have been received from the
                    following Offices and Divisions: A–S, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SOA1">SOA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NA1">NA</gloss>.<note n="3" xml:id="d510fn3">Mr. Lovett approved on March 18.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
