<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Political Adviser in Japan ( (Sebald) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d512</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">512</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rect4tQQCzcqVqdpO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98003467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democratization</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="512"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d512">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Japan)/3–548</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting Political Adviser in Japan</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sebald</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 145</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-05">March 5,
                            1948</date>.<lb/>[Received March 11.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to this Mission’s
                    despatch No. 109 of February 18, 1948<note n="1" xml:id="d512fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> and to previous correspondence in regard to meetings of the
                    Allied Council for Japan, and to forward as enclosures<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d512fn2">Enclosures not printed.</note>
                    <pb facs="0695" n="681" xml:id="pg_681"/> five copies each of the Agenda and
                    Corrected Verbatim Minutes of the fifty-third meeting of the Council held on
                    March 3, 1948.</p>
                <p>There was one official matter on the Agenda, “Regarding the New Japanese
                    Government”, proposed for discussion by the Acting Soviet Member. The Acting
                    Soviet Member opened the discussion by reading from a prepared statement. He
                    emphasized the importance to Japanese democratization of the change in cabinets
                    and said that the Katayama Cabinet and previous cabinets had done nothing to
                    improve economic conditions in Japan and that in fact the situation was becoming
                    more acute. This crisis had resulted, he claimed, from the fact that throughout
                    the Occupation no conditions were created which would allow the Japanese people
                    to form a government representative of a majority of the people and empowered to
                    implement really democratic reforms. He then asserted that the Shidehara,
                    Yoshida, and Katayama Cabinets had all contained ministers who should have been
                    excluded from public office in accordance with Allied policy and Occupation
                    directives; as ministers subject to purge in the Katayama Cabinet, he named
                    Ashida Hitoshi, Nishio Suehiro, Morito Tatsuo, Miki Takeo, Hitotsumatsu
                    Sadayoshi, and Hatano Kanae. Thereupon he began an attack on the record of Dr.
                    Ashida. (A copy of the Acting Soviet Member’s statement, which he subsequently
                    distributed to the press, is enclosed.<note n="3" xml:id="d512fn3">Not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>At this point I interrupted the reading of the Acting Soviet Member’s statement
                    and ruled that his remarks were out of order. In the ensuing discussion, I
                    supported my ruling by stating that the Allied Council was not the proper place
                    for an examination of the qualifications of government officials and that an
                    attack upon individuals now under consideration for posts in the Japanese
                    Government constituted an interference with the freely expressed will of the
                    Japanese people in violation of the Potsdam Declaration and other statements of
                    Allied and Occupation policy. I pointed out that machinery had been duly
                    established to administer the purge and any relevant information should be
                    conveyed to the appropriate authorities. I stated that there is no authority in
                    any of the controlling documents for the Allied Council which allows members to
                    interfere in the selection of a new cabinet.</p>
                <p>The Acting Soviet Member insisted that this ruling was in violation of the right
                    of Council members to express their opinions and requested the views of the
                    other members. The Member for China stated that he agreed with the Supreme
                    Commander—from whose public statement on the formation of a new Japanese cabinet
                    I had previously read—that the solution of internal political issues is
                    primarily the <pb facs="0696" n="682" xml:id="pg_682"/> responsibility of the
                    representatives of the Japanese people. The British Commonwealth Member
                    concurred that the Council should not examine into the qualifications of
                    individual political leaders and should not interfere with the democratic
                    processes of the Japanese Government; he further stated that the Allied Council
                    in the present situation could properly urge the early formation of a new
                    coalition government and should assure itself that the terms of the Japanese
                    Constitution, the provisions of the Terms of Surrender, and the policies of the
                    Occupation are properly executed.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, I emphasized that the Acting Soviet Member was at liberty to
                    express his views, provided that his remarks were in conformity with the general
                    principles for which the Allied Council was established. As the Acting Soviet
                    Member continued to insist that he should be allowed to complete his statement,
                    regardless of content, I adjourned the meeting.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>W. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sebald</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
