<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Assistant Secretary of State for Occupied Areas
                        (
                        Saltzman
                    ) to the Chief of the Civil Affairs Division,
                        Department of the Army (
                        Noce
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d640</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">640</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-01-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-01-26T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recd38b75873bd4a33" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="far-eastern-commission" subject="far-eastern-commission">Far Eastern Commission</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-01-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="640" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d640">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Japan)/1–2648</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State for Occupied Areas</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Saltzman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Chief of the Civil Affairs Division,
                        Department of the Army</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Noce</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-26">26 January
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear General Noce</hi>: <gloss target="#t_SANACC1">SANACC</gloss> 236/51 (U.S. Policy with Respect to Definition of Japanese
                    Occupation Costs and the Priority to be Accorded their Repayment) has been
                    introduced into the Far Eastern Commission as <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 288. The United States representation in the Far Eastern
                    Commission probably will require very full information on amounts and types of
                    costs which the United States Government has borne in connection with the
                    occupation of Japan, if other <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> countries are
                    to be persuaded to approve our proposals.</p>
                <pb facs="0962" n="948" xml:id="pg_948"/>
                <p>It is my understanding that the Department of the Army has in its possession full
                    reports on occupation costs for Japan incurred by the United States between the
                    Japanese surrender and September 1947. Can the Department of the Army make this
                    data available for use by the U.S. Delegation to the Far Eastern Commission? The
                    fullest possible information is desired, in particular, regarding expenditures
                    incurred for imports into Japan to prevent disease and unrest and to accomplish
                    the purposes of the occupation and regarding expenditures for maintenance and
                    repatriation of civilians and Japanese military personnel including expenses
                    incurred in returning Japanese nationals to Japan, removal of foreign nationals
                    from Japan, and transfer from points outside of Japan of persons displaced by
                    Japanese aggression. <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> 288 proposes that
                    repayment for these two types of expenditures should constitute first and second
                    priority charges against certain specified Japanese assets. All of the <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> countries, including the United States, will be
                    expected, shortly, to table estimates of such costs.</p>
                <p>An <gloss target="#t_FEC1">FEC</gloss> classification of “confidential” could be
                    given to any data which the Department of the Army supplies for use in the Far
                    Eastern Commission.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Saltzman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
