<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Political Adviser in Japan (
                        Sebald
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d658</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">658</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="textiles" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033350" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Textiles</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="cotton" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302" lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-06-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="658" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d658">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">694.0031/6–2248</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting Political Adviser in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sebald</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 379</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-06-22">June 22,
                            1948.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received July 2.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose copies of a personal
                    and confidential letter of June 16, 1948 to Mr. F. E. Pickelle,<note n="1" xml:id="d658fn1">Not printed.</note> Chief of the Foreign Trade and Commerce
                    Division of the Economic and Scientific Section of this Headquarters, from
                    Minister E. R. Lingeman, Counselor (Economic) of the United Kingdom Liaison
                    Mission in Japan, indicating a framework of general principles within which it
                    is suggested that the proposed sterling area trade negotiations with General
                    Headquarters of the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers be conducted,
                    together with a tentative balance sheet showing the scale of trade which might
                    be involved. Furthermore, the hope is expressed by Mr. Lingeman that, the
                    discussions regarding such an arrangement with the Economic and Scientific
                    Section of this Headquarters, be opened prior to, but not later than, July 6th
                    of this year.</p>
                <p>According to the enclosed letter, participants in such an arrangement will
                    definitely include the United Kingdom and Colonies (with the present exception
                    of Hong Kong), Australia, New Zealand and Ceylon. Although invited to
                    participate, neither South Africa, India nor Pakistan have indicated their
                    intention to do so as yet. The Supreme Commander’s and the sterling area
                    countries’ mutuality of interest in a balance of trade at the highest possible
                    level, to be accomplished by the conclusion of a trade arrangement on the widest
                    possible sterling area basis, is emphasized. The United Kingdom Liaison Mission
                        <pb facs="0994" n="980" xml:id="pg_980"/> envisages an arrangement whereby
                    Japan would purchase as much as possible of its raw materials from the sterling
                    area countries in return for textiles, raw silk, and other Japanese goods.
                    According to the provisional balance sheet enclosed, proposed sales to Japan by
                    sterling area countries are shown at $83,065,000 and proposed purchases from
                    Japan, at $82,588,000. The figures include contemplated purchases and sales by
                    the United Kingdom and Colonies, Australia and New Zealand, as well as estimated
                    South African wool exports, contingent of course upon that Dominion’s
                    participation. Figures for Ceylon are unavailable pending the arrival in Tokyo
                    of a special representative from that Dominion.</p>
                <p>The enclosed letter suggests that such an understanding might be predicated upon
                    an exchange of identical letters between this Headquarters and each sterling
                    area country concerned, in which would be included an indication of the volume
                    of sales and purchases expected to result therefrom, and a statement of
                    intention to take necessary governmental action to that end. An approximate
                    balance would be agreed upon and each party concerned would endeavor to
                    authorize or facilitate trade up to that level. Since a statement of intention
                    only is contemplated and not a definite governmental undertaking, the further
                    suggestion is made that the understanding be referred to as an “arrangement”
                    rather than as an “agreement”.</p>
                <p>Mr. Lingeman proposes that such an arrangement be made effective for one year
                    initially, that it include trade conducted through private as well as government
                    channels, and that it be on a sterling basis in accordance with the Overall
                    Payments Agreement enclosed to this Mission’s despatch No. 334 of June 8, 1948
                    entitled “Currency Arrangement Between Japan and the Sterling Area”.<note n="2" xml:id="d658fn2">Not printed.</note> Although the latter agreement provided
                    that all trade between Japan and the specified sterling area countries should be
                    conducted on a sterling basis with the exception of exports of cotton textiles
                    manufactured in Japan from raw cotton procured in the United States, Mr.
                    Lingeman indicates that one of the objects of the proposed trade arrangement is
                    to permit the unqualified sale of textiles by Japan to sterling area
                    participants.</p>
                <p>The proposed arrangement envisages a balance of trade between Occupied Japan and
                    the sterling area participants as a group. In the event that either party should
                    fail to comply substantially with the terms of the understanding, it is
                    suggested that consultations be held by them. In this connection, it is
                    contemplated that mutually satisfactory arrangements for the exchange of
                    information can be consummated. With respect to trade on government account, the
                    thought is expressed that this could best be done through the establishment of a
                        <pb facs="0995" n="981" xml:id="pg_981"/> consolidated account in Tokyo for
                    all sterling area participants, whereas, weekly reports from the British banks
                    in Tokyo (Hong Kong and Shanghai Banking Corporation and the Chartered Bank of
                    India, Australia and China) would afford information regarding trade on private
                    account.</p>
                <p>This Mission considers that the conclusion of an early mutually advantageous
                    trade arrangement between Japan and the sterling area, upon as wide a sterling
                    basis as possible, will give impetus to the economic rehabilitation of Japan and
                    will afford progress toward the reestablishment of normal trade relationships,
                    an important part of Japan’s pre-war trade having been conducted on a sterling
                    basis. Available sterling markets for Japanese goods, which in turn can supply
                    raw materials needed in the Japanese economy, must be utilized to the fullest
                    possible extent. Dollar purchases without equivalent dollar sales, as in the
                    case of U.S. raw cotton, should be kept to an absolute minimum if Japan is to
                    achieve an international balance of trade and payments.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>W. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sebald</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
