<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Political Adviser in Korea (
                        Langdon
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d768</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">768</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-12T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" subject="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" subject="free-elections" lcsh-match="no_match">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="recy94pCDcRAr4voG" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="freedom-of-expression" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003012251" lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of speech</term>
                    <term ref="recqhvaPBazS2SPQl" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="freedom-of-the-press" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051711" lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of the press</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="terrorism" subject="terrorism" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112" lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="768" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d768">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.42700 (R)/3–1248: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting Political Adviser in Korea</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Langdon</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-12">March 12,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>149. From Mitchell for Jacobs and Schuler: Following is text of statement made by
                    General Hodge today before approximately 100 provincial governors and police
                    chiefs assembled Seoul which we are widely publicizing and which excellent for
                        <gloss target="#t_VOUSA1">VOUSA</gloss>: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I will not dwell upon the importance to your nation of the next few
                            months of its history. The coming event of general elections to be
                            followed by formation of a national government will set up a most
                            critical period. The responsibility for the success or failure of the
                            holding of elections where all adults may freely express their choice of
                            representatives to form their government rests upon Korean leaders and
                            governmental officials as well as upon all Korean people personally
                            accruing to you gentlemen in this phase of your nation’s progress may be
                            listed briefly as follows: <list>
                                <label>(1).</label>
                                <item>Give all assistance to the election-educational program to see
                                    that all the people throughout your area are informed of the
                                    details concerning general election and regulations that govern
                                    it.</item>
                                <label>(2).</label>
                                <item>Insure by every possible means that a free atmosphere exists
                                    for holding the general election, both before and during the
                                    election.</item>
                                <label>(3).</label>
                                <item>Insure that all physical arrangements for the election that
                                    come within your scope are completed on time.</item>
                                <label>(4).</label>
                                <item>Encourage and lead all Koreans to vote in the election.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The principal item I wish to impress upon you is the absolute necessity
                            for a free atmosphere for elections. This one feature is of more concern
                            to the United Nations General Assembly and to the United Nations
                            Temporary Commission on Korea than any other. Unless there are free
                            elections we have gained nothing, because without free voting we will
                            not have the will of the people expressed. Democratic processes depend
                            entirely upon the full and free expression by the people at the polls to
                            gain their representation in government. The primary duty of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Commission here is to observe the
                            elections for the express purpose of determining if the representatives
                            elected do in fact represent the will of the people. The <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> resolutions make this clear and the
                            spokesmen of the Commission have reiterated that feature. We cannot
                            expect the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Commission to approve any
                            elections that do not produce true representatives of the Korean
                            people.</p>
                        <p>To insure our mutual understanding let me briefly enumerate the principal
                            factors involved in free elections. There will soon be published <pb facs="1168" n="1154" xml:id="pg_1154"/> some regulations designed to
                            insure these freedoms. The free atmosphere we speak of must include: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Freedom of speech. This means individuals must be free to
                                    discuss in an orderly manner issues at stake and discuss the
                                    qualifications of candidates both publicly and privately without
                                    interference or pressure from officials or groups. This freedom
                                    includes the use of all types of campaign handbills and wall
                                    posters, provided they are not inflammatory to the extent of
                                    inciting disorders or overthrow of government.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Freedom of the press in the same manner as free speech.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Freedom of assembly. Orderly assemblies and meetings indoors
                                    and outdoors must be encouraged, regardless of the political
                                    beliefs or followings of the participants. Leaders calling such
                                    meetings must of course be responsible that they are
                                    orderly.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>Freedom for candidates to campaign for election regardless of
                                    their political beliefs. This means that candidates must be
                                    allowed free movement to campaign without any direct or indirect
                                    interference or pressure from officials and must be given the
                                    same protection given to all other political or nonpolitical
                                    citizens.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>Law and order must be maintained but in so doing all measures
                                    smacking of oppression or suppression because of political
                                    beliefs must be avoided. No Korean man or woman can be arrested
                                    merely for a political belief. On the other hand, political
                                    hoodlumism and terrorism can not and will not be condoned if we
                                    are to keep a free atmosphere. Good judgment in maintaining this
                                    balance must be exercised.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>In maintaining the required free atmosphere it is absolutely necessary to
                            develop the understanding and help to that of the will of the people in
                            your areas.</p>
                        <p>I have great respect for the great faith in the good judgment of the
                            Korean people when they really understand the issues at stake. I believe
                            that if all of you exercise real leadership and spread understanding
                            among the people my task, your task and the task of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Commission will be greatly
                            simplified.</p>
                        <p>In closing, I wish to say that I have full confidence in you gentlemen,
                            who represent government and law and order in your areas, and I express
                            my complete belief that you will rise to meet the challenge offered by
                            this chance for great progress, and will team up and cooperate both
                            among yourselves and with the people in the provinces to make the first
                            democratic general election in Korea a complete success, thus gaining a
                            well deserved world wide approval and support.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Langdon</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
