<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Political Adviser in Korea (
                        Jacobs
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d803</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">803</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="democracy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647" lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recez5uVgqvmr6Nwm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="irrigation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006268" lcsh-match="exact">Irrigation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" subject="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" subject="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="803" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d803">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">895.00/5–1948</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Political Adviser in Korea</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jacobs</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 135</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-19">May 19,
                            1948</date>.<lb/>[Received May 31.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to present to the Department
                    five copies of a statement issued by the Directorate of the South Korea Interim
                        Government<note n="1" xml:id="d803fn1">Not printed.</note> on the
                    “North-South Conference” held at Pyongyang April 19–28, 1948. The statement was
                    released through the Department of Public Information May 7, 1948.</p>
                <p>Terming the South Korean leaders who attended the conference as “unsuccessful but
                    ambitious” the Directorate issued a five-pronged argument against the
                    conference: (1) The conference supported the trusteeship which was opposed by
                    all the Korean people; (2) The conference gave wholehearted support to Russia
                    which in reality is opposed to democracy and seeks to use Korea for her own
                    military and political ends; (3) Opposition to the so-called “unilateral”
                    election is a blind to cover up Russia’s opposition to any expression of popular
                    will in Korea; (4) Russia’s offer to withdraw her forces is based on the
                    knowledge that she has three hundred thousand trained Communist “stooges” to
                    leave behind; (5) The reports that the problems of electricity and irrigation
                    between North and South have been settled are <pb facs="1216" n="1202" xml:id="pg_1202"/> nothing but clumsy propaganda coming from Communists who
                    do not hesitate to say yes and no at the same time.</p>
                <p>The statement of the Directorate is a summation of the major criticisms of the
                    Conference which, despite any idealistic motives held by South Koreans attending
                    it, was obviously a propaganda vehicle to be used against the elections in the
                    South.</p>
                <p>Every reference to Russia is cast in opprobrious or caustic terms, e.g.,
                    “Russians who are trying to enforce the Communistic domination of all the
                    world”; “They (North Koreans) adopted ‘Russian justice’”; “Russia disclosed its
                    ambition to make Korea one of its satellites”; “Russia hated the independence of
                    Korea like poison almost up to the end of the war because of the Russo-Japanese
                    Neutrality Agreement”; “Russia …<note n="2" xml:id="d803fn2">Omission indicated
                        in the original.</note> fought (Japan) one long week”; etc. While no one
                    would question the truth of these observations, sober-minded persons might well
                    doubt the statesmanship and discretion of Korean officials publicly insulting
                    their powerful, unforgetting and unforgiving neighbor. It is, however,
                    characteristic of the historical protegee psychology of the Korean official, who
                    is insecure in his office and condition and must cling to the skirts of the
                    strong power which he determines will dominate the situation. In the case of
                    Koreans, this psychology in the past and today unfortunately finds expression in
                    egging on the protector against the rival so he will destroy the latter. It
                    would be obtuse to deny that this Korean psychology has not entered into and
                    obstructed a settlement of the Korean question or influenced local Soviet and
                    American objectivity.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacobs</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
