<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="270" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d270">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Dayton</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 141.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-04-22"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 22, 1862.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your despatch of March 31 (No. 131) has
                            been received.</p>
                        <p>I have already exhausted in other papers the principal topics it
                            presents.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Mercier proposed in a very proper manner that he would visit Richmond
                            if we should not object. Of course the President approved, being
                            satisfied that he would not in any way compromit the relations existing
                            between the French government and our own. It is impossible not to see
                            now that the insurrection is shrinking and shrivelling into very narrow
                            dimensions. I hope that Mr. Mercier may come back prepared with some
                            plan to alleviate the inconveniences of his countrymen in the south, who
                            are not acting against this government, and, in that way, against the
                            peace and harmony of the two countries.</p>
                        <p>The real difficulty is, that the southern ports are, and even the whole
                            southern country is, now actually in a state of siege, and communication
                            in anything like a normal manner is impossible.</p>
                        <p>You will notice that General McDowell has entered Fredericksburg, and
                            General Banks is marching successfully quite through the valley of
                            Virginia. We have reason to expect Savannah to come into our possession
                            within the next ten days, and Fort Macon to fall about as soon. The
                            insurrectionary leaders have made a conscription of all between 18 and
                            35. They issue new paper which sells for gold at the rate of one hundred
                            dollars for twenty.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Thouvenel’s assurances to you on the subject of Mexico are eminently
                            satisfactory to the President.</p>
                        <p>It is among the most gratifying indications of our speedy success in
                            restoring the peace of the country that all the foreign ministers here
                            (so far as I know) are now satisfied of the certainty of the event, and
                            more than one of them are asking leaves of absence to visit Europe, a
                            privilege they would not ask except under such a conviction. Mr.
                            Hülsemann thinks he can go home; Mr. Schleiden has gone.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">William L. Dayton</hi>, Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>