<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1862</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1862-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1862-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="war-of-1812" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="war-of-1812">War of 1812</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="32"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 131.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-03-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 13, 1862.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In obedience to the instructions contained in
                    your despatch No. 184, of the 14th of February, I have addressed a note to Lord
                    Russell in regard to the conduct of the master of the British steamer General
                    Miramon, a copy of which is herewith transmitted.</p>
                <p>It will be perceived that I have ventured to introduce another and a different
                    cause of complaint, which suggested itself to me in the perusal of the report of
                    the discussion in both houses of Parliament on the blockade. I have done so, not
                    in the expectation of effecting any purpose of checking the notorious tendency
                    of the commercial classes, but rather to put on record on the part of the
                    government of the United States the consciousness of its existence; for the time
                    may come when there will be attempts to deny it. There are people in England who
                    still pretend that the complaints which brought on the war of 1812 were ill
                    founded. But for the evidence perpetuated by the official records of the
                    government of the United States this story might become the established faith of
                    the nation. And so it may be in the event of a restoration of our affairs. It
                    will probably be affirmed here that there was a rigid abstinence throughout our
                    time of trial from all attempts to do us injury. In opposition to this, it may
                    be as well to have it in our power to show that, outside of the lines of the
                    rebel States, nearly all the active sympathy and positive assistance has come
                    from the subjects of Great Britain. At this very moment the means which the
                    insurgents have to carry on the war are derived from them, and vessels are
                    fitting out or actually on the way to supply them continually with more.</p>
                <p>I transmit a copy of a note just received from Lord Russell, in acknowledgment of
                    mine. It will probably be followed by explanations.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>You will scarcely have failed to observe in the course of the late discussion in
                    both houses of Parliament the nature of the <hi rend="italic">animus</hi> that
                    pervades the greater number of members towards the United States. It consists
                    not so much of partiality for one side over the other as of disinclination to
                    both and desire that their political power should be diminished by a permanent
                    separation. Even Lord Russell himself, though perhaps not conscious of the
                    influence that prompts it, distinctly betrays the tendency in his remarks on the
                    blockade. I am told by one of the members that the feelings of the House of
                    Commons were perceptibly with Mr. Gregory in his speech, at the same time that
                    they would not dispute the soundness of the policy of the ministry. It is
                    advisable that the government of the United States should clearly understand
                    this distinction, for upon its adaptation of a system to the emergency will
                    greatly depend the chance of preserving the present position of the two
                    countries towards each other. The successes of the campaign have done much for
                    us. I trust they may continue. But they <pb facs="0118" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/>
                    must not be made to depend merely upon good fortune. The stake is too great here
                    to be risked on the passions of ignorant or inexperienced men at home. If we do
                    not mean to give to the evil-inclined of this hemisphere the opportunity to turn
                    the scale in favor of our enemies in the other, we must take care to adhere to a
                    policy which will, by its ultimate success, prove at once our own capacity to
                    guide the country through its perils and the fallacy of the predictions of
                    failure so confidently paraded by those whose wish is father to the thought.</p>
                <p>We now anxiously await the news by every steamer, but not for the same reasons as
                    before. The pressure for interference here has disappeared. It will arise again
                    only in the event of some very decided reverse. Hence we look more for the
                    evidence of sensible and gradual progress than for an immediate triumph. On many
                    accounts this last result would scarcely seem to be desirable, and especially if
                    the attempt to attain it might lead to the possibility of a corresponding
                    reverse.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Adams to Earl Russell</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-03-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 10, 1862.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: It is with much regret that I am
                        constrained to lay before you the copy of a letter addressed to the
                        Department of State by the consul general of the United States at Havana,
                        containing a serious complaint against the conduct of the master of the
                        British steamer General Miramon, off the port of Mobile, in the month of May
                        last.</p>
                    <p>It would appear from the statements therein made, if in accordance with the
                        facts, that Captain Golding took advantage of a privilege granted to him to
                        enter the port of Mobile, upon his profession of a desire to perform an act
                        of humanity, to abuse the confidence thus placed in him, by discharging one
                        cargo of merchandise, and taking off another, in violation of the blockade
                        known to be established at that place.</p>
                    <p>It is almost needless to remind your lordship how much the disposition to
                        relieve to neutral nations the inconveniences inevitably attending a
                        blockade, must be affected by the misconduct of such of their citizens as
                        prove to have no respect for moral obligations. It is not without regret
                        that I am compelled to add that this is by no means the only instance which
                        has come within my observation of a desire of British citizens to interfere
                        with the blockade in every manner possible. Not only have the newspapers in
                        Great Britain contained advertisements of vessels about to depart with the
                        declared intention of violating it, but I have reason to believe that
                        respectable assurance companies in London have gone so far as to establish a
                        specific rate of premium at which they are prepared to guarantee the
                        property engaged in such unlawful ventures. The effect of such conduct, in
                        weakening the confidence which my countrymen desire to feel in the friendly
                        disposition of the people of Great Britain, is easily to be conceived. It is
                        no part of my intention in making this representation to imply the existence
                        of any desire on the part of her Majesty’s ministers or of the British
                        nation at large to give the smallest countenance to such hostile
                        demonstrations.</p>
                    <p>My purpose is rather to solicit such action, if it be within the power of the
                            <pb facs="0119" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> government as may, by putting
                        the seal of public reprobation upon a single well-authenticated act of
                        dishonesty, serve to deter other evil-minded persons from pursuing the same
                        path in future.</p>
                    <p>Praying your lordship to accept the assurances of my highest consideration, I
                        have the honor to be, my lord, your most obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Right Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl Russell,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Earl Russell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Adams</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-03-13">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 13, 1862.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt
                        of your letter of the 10th instant, calling attention to the conduct of the
                        captain of the British steamer General Miramon, as reported to your
                        government by the United States consul at the Havana, in discharging a cargo
                        of merchandise and taking off another at Mobile; the captain of the General
                        Miramon having been allowed to enter that port while under blockade, in
                        consequence of his having stated to the commander of the blockading squadron
                        that his object in going to Mobile was to perform an act of humanity. You
                        also call my attention to the number of vessels lading cargoes in this
                        country with the evident intention of running the blockade, and you request
                        that her Majesty’s government will take such action in the matter as may be
                        within their power.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor, in reply, to state that, if the facts as alleged against
                        the captain of the General Miramon are not susceptible of a satisfactory
                        explanation, her Majesty’s government would much regret that a British
                        shipmaster should have abused the confidence of the commander of the United
                        States blockading squadron; and, as regards the second point to which you
                        call my attention, I have to assure you that the matter shall have the due
                        consideration of her Majesty’s government.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your most
                        obedient, humble servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RUSSELL.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic"
                                >&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
