<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Cameron..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1862</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1862-09-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1862-09-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-09-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-09-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="393"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d393">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Cameron</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 13.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-09-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 16, 1862.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your despatch of August 19 (No. 8) has been
                    received. It relates chiefly to your application for temporary leave of absence.
                    That leave was granted in my despatch, No. 10, of the 6th instant.</p>
                <pb facs="0529" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"/>
                <p>At the time when your application was received here the efficiency of our armies
                    had been impaired in a vigorous though eminently successful campaign. It soon
                    became probable, and more lately it unhappily was proved, that we must fail in
                    the pending movement upon Richmond. Such a disappointment was not unlikely to be
                    followed by positive disasters, the extent of which could not be foreseen. That
                    failure was sure to encourage the emissaries of insurrection in Europe, and the
                    public mind too readily yielded to apprehensions of intervention in some form
                    which must increase the national embarrassment. Under these circumstances,
                    popular remedies were suggested and urged upon the President. Chief among them
                    was some form of Executive manifesto or declaration of a determination to make
                    the war more energetic, severe, sanguinary, and destructive in the insurgent
                    States. At the same moment a change long clamored for in the insurgent councils
                    was adopted there, namely, that of withdrawing their armies from their own
                    region, and rapidly throwing them forward upon not this capital alone, but the
                    loyal States of Maryland, Ohio, and Pennsylvania. For the moment the war on our
                    part, which had until now been an aggressive one, was to be one of defence,
                    attended with all the alarms and apparent if not real dangers of invasion.</p>
                <p>The President, in this emergency, decided to bring together the armies of the
                    Potomac and Virginia, and consolidate them on some line in that State between
                    this capital and Richmond; to re-enforce and augment not only that consolidated
                    army but also all the other forces at his command with six hundred thousand men,
                    to be raised as volunteers, with a draft, if necessary, and be thus prepared to
                    meet and, with promptness and without display of words, to roll back the tide of
                    invasion and complete the war by a vigorous campaign on the coasts, on the
                    Mississippi, and through the mountain passes of eastern Tennessee.</p>
                <p>The disasters which were threatened in Virginia actually occurred. The insurgents
                    drove the army of Virginia back upon the line of fortifications and the capital,
                    but not without losses probably equal to our own. They then advanced from
                    Manassas to the fordable passes of the Potomac, crossed that river and entered
                    Frederick, and invited Maryland to rise up and join the treasonable confederacy.
                    There they threatened equally Washington, Baltimore, and Pennsylvania. In like
                    manner they gathered forces in Kentucky, in the rear of the army of General
                    Buell, who was investing Chattanooga, and advanced towards the Ohio river, thus
                    threatening the loyal States of Ohio and Indiana, which lie on the north bank of
                    that river. The insurrectionary congress recently assembled approved these
                    aggressive movements, and solemnly proclaimed a purpose to carry the war into
                    the loyal States and inflict upon them, with increased severity, all the rigors
                    of desolating warfare.</p>
                <p>Under such changed circumstances, which could not have been foreseen when you
                    applied for leave of absence, the President thought the national interests
                    required the watchful care of all our trusted representatives in Europe, and he
                    thought it might be especially unfortunate if the mission at St. Petersburg were
                    left without the presence of a minister of the highest grade and authority known
                    in the diplomatic service. Hence his reluctance to accede to your wishes. It is
                    now hoped that your absence will not be productive of injury to the public
                    service.</p>
                <p>Having thus related the military events culminating in the invasion of the loyal
                    States, it is only just that I should bring the narration down to this point.
                    The volunteers are coming in as freely as was expected. More than seventy
                    thousand have reached this city; ten thousand or more are in Baltimore and its
                    vicinity. Sixty thousand have joined the army of the west, and the whole
                    proposed augmentation will be rapidly effected. The <pb facs="0530" n="460"
                        xml:id="pg_460"/> insurgents have receded and are retiring from their late
                    advance towards the Ohio. General McClellan has just met the invaders of
                    Maryland and driven them back towards the Potomac. The loyalty of Maryland has
                    not been disturbed, and Pennsylvania is freed from the apprehensions of danger.
                    With steadiness of purpose, prudence in council, and activity and energy of
                    execution on the part of our commanders, great advantages may be derived from
                    recent misfortunes, and the recklessness of the insurgents may result in the
                    speedy ruin of their always desperate cause.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Simon Cameron</hi>, Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
