<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Motley to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1862</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d457</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">457</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1862-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1862-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="457"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d457">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Motley</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 4.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Vienna</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-02-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 12, 1862.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Yesterday I had a long and interesting
                    conversation with Count Rechberg at the foreign office. He asked me what was the
                    latest intelligence from America. I spoke of the recent victory of the national
                    troops near Somerset, in Kentucky—news of which, with but few details, reached
                    us two or three days ago—observing that the movement seemed to be part of a
                    general plan to surround and crush the insurrection on land, even as it had been
                    already shut off from the sea by a stringent blockade along three thousand miles
                    of coast. I intimated that the weather, rendering the roads in Virginia almost
                    impassable at this season, would probably delay for a few weeks our operations
                    against the main body of the confederates, now intrenched in the neighborhood of
                    Manassas; but that the expeditions along the southern coast, the movements in
                    the direction of Tennessee and the Mississippi valley, seemed indications of a
                    plan to be developed before long on a large scale. We had been bringing our
                    armies into a state of discipline, and providing ourselves with the necessary
                    machinery to bring the war to a decisive issue when we once began to strike, and
                    I assured the minister that I felt perfect confidence in the cabinet and
                    commander-in-chief, the army, and the national spirit. Men, money, and munitions
                    of war were in superabundance. If I felt any apprehension, it arose rather from
                    the general impatience, not only in America, but in the world, that some result
                    should be reached. I said that the impatience seemed to me most unreasonable,
                    for, after all, six or seven months of discipline for an army of such colossal
                    dimensions was but a very short allowance. The minister said, energetically,
                    that this was, indeed, but a very brief space for bringing an army, even of the
                    best raw material, into training, and that it was almost impossible that a
                    really disciplined force could be created in so short a time.</p>
                <p>He then observed, spontaneously, that he and the Austrian government felt quite
                    certain of the result. It was impossible, he said, that the insurrectionists
                    could provide men enough or money enough to contend for any great length of time
                    with the United States power. The shorter or longer <pb facs="0632" n="562"
                        xml:id="pg_562"/> period which would elapse before they were reduced to
                    obedience must depend on the ability of our generals, but he could not doubt
                    that the government would be ultimately re-established over the whole country. I
                    think that, as nearly as possible, these were the minister’s words; and
                    throughout his whole conversation the sympathy and good will of the imperial
                    government for our cause was unequivocally manifested.</p>
                <p>There was no hint dropped on behalf of that government of preserving an even
                    balance of sympathy between both belligerents in America, of maintaining a
                    strict neutrality of sentiment, and of cherishing an equal friendship for both
                    parties. On the contrary, the professions of friendship and esteem were for the
                    United States government in this the hour of its trial. The sympathy expressed
                    was for the established, constituted, friendly power, bound to Austria, as to
                    other European governments, by treaties of amity and commerce, and now putting
                    forth all its strength to vanquish a causeless rebellion which had brought
                    bloodshed and desolation over a continent.</p>
                <p>I expressed my gratification at the friendly language used by the minister, and I
                    assured him that his expectations would be justified by the result The
                    insurrection, I told him, would soon prove to be a bad speculation. It had been
                    founded on the idea that foreign intervention—especially that of France and
                    England—was inevitable, and that the south, by means of its cotton crop, held
                    the power of life and death over both those countries. It had now been
                    demonstrated that this intervention was not to take place, and that cotton did
                    not reign supreme over the councils of the world. After the Union troops had
                    penetrated into the interior of the seceded country, and overcome the
                    confederates in a few decisive contests on a larger scale than that of Somerset,
                    the counter-revolution would begin, and men, whose mouths had been closed by
                    violence during the reign of terror, would proclaim lustily that they had always
                    been Unionists, and would rise in revolt against the men by whom they had been
                    deluded or forced into crime. It was not the case of invasion by a foreign army.
                    No foreign nation could conquer the south or the north. There was no resemblance
                    between our operations and the attempt of an invader on a foreign soil. The
                    United States government was at home on every inch of its own territory, and to
                    sustain itself against this wanton insurrection against its benignant and
                    legitimate authority, it relied confidently on its own overwhelming force,
                    supported by the latent loyalty of a majority of the inhabitants of the States
                    which had seceded. The time would soon come when this theory, scouted now by our
                    enemies in Europe who wished the downfall of the great republic, would prove
                    itself to be an unquestionable fact. The United States government would remain
                    and be respected when the names of those who had brought all this misery upon
                    our country had sunk into dishonored obscurity, and the ravings of their
                    European sympathizers had been utterly forgotten. It would one day awaken
                    astonishment that a general opinion should have prevailed in the world that the
                    American republic was powerless to preserve its national existence, because when
                    taken by surprise, by a treason utterly without a parallel in human history, it
                    had been held at bay for a twelvemonth, more or less, while preparing for its
                    defence. I shall not occupy any more of your time with the arguments, so
                    familiar to all loyal minds in America, with which I sought to strengthen the
                    conviction already existing in the minister’s mind as to the justice and the
                    favorable aspects of our cause. I am happy to say that nothing could be more
                    friendly or satisfactory than the language which he held.</p>
                <p>Something he said of the danger of our becoming a military power, and remaining
                    no longer a peaceful republic. I said this was a very improbable result, for we
                    were, by nature and habit, a peaceful, commercial people. Our commercial marine,
                    nearly the largest in the world, would require us to maintain <pb facs="0633"
                        n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/> in future a stronger navy than hitherto, but as we
                    had ever supported neutral rights against the maritime preponderance of England,
                    this would be an advantage to all other naval powers, and especially to the
                    modest mercantile marine of Germany. It was clearly their interest that our
                    naval strength should be increased. In case, however, the Union were hopelessly
                    broken into two or more rival confederacies, then, indeed, we should become of
                    necessity a military power—strong standing armies and navies would be
                    indispensible for domestic and foreign defence. <hi rend="italic">Now</hi> these
                    great armaments were but a levy of bucklers of the whole people. It was not an
                    army—it was a nation in arms. This was, necessarily, a passing phenomenon. When
                    the Union was re-established we should resume the peaceful tenor of our lives.
                    The young men who had flocked by hundreds of thousands to the national standard
                    came from every pursuit of life, and would return to them when the danger was
                    over. They had taken arms to defend a beloved country against traitors, not to
                    engage in the military profession.</p>
                <p>He spoke with hearty commendation of your correspondence with the Chevalier de
                    Hulsemann in regard to the questions raised by the Trent affair; and, indeed, I
                    have already had occasion to mention to you the strong language of approbation
                    and congratulation with which he alluded to the issue of that affair so soon as
                    it became known to us in Europe.</p>
                <p>I observed that perhaps it might hardly seem fitting that anything should be said
                    between us just now about the Mexican matter. On the contrary, said he, I am
                    quite ready. I then replied that I had nothing to say on the subject at present;
                    that the remarkable turn the affair was taking was unknown in America by last
                    advices, and that I was, of course, without any instructions with regard to it.
                    He said we are ourselves simply in a position of expectancy. The three maritime
                    powers had made an expedition to Mexico. We have nothing to do with it, and
                    intend to have nothing. Should the result of the enterprise be to establish a
                    stronger government in Mexico, a monarchy, it will then be for the Austrian
                    government to consider whether sufficient guarantees of various sorts as to its
                    stability can be offered in order to induce an archduke of our imperial house to
                    make the great sacrifice of mounting its throne.</p>
                <p>I think, as nearly as possible, these were the minister’s exact words. I have
                    already mentioned to you, in a private letter, that it is quite certain that the
                    Archduke Ferdinand Maximillian had been consulted by certain Mexican
                    refugees—Almonte, Estrada, and Gutierez—at Trieste, on this matter, and that the
                    Emperor of the French was in favor of his candidacy. Thus far the subject is <hi
                        rend="italic">in nubibus</hi>—the new Mexican throne is in the misty
                    future—and Austria has only agreed that the archduke shall ascend it, if proper
                    securities be offered.</p>
                <p>I made no reply to Count Rechberg’s observations. He then asked me if I thought
                    there would be opposition to the scheme in the United States.</p>
                <p>I said that, as he asked me the question, I had no hesitation in answering as a
                    private person, not officially, that I thought the opposition would be universal
                    and intense. He asked why? I gave two reasons: First, the American people,
                    abstaining from European politics, have always had a strong feeling in regard to
                    European interference with political arrangements on the North American
                    continent. Secondly, the republican form of government was the hereditary one
                    over the greater part of our continent, and attempts to supersede it by
                    monarchical forms, by means of force, would be regarded both by the lovers of
                    progress, and by more conservative parties, as revolutionary, unphilosophical,
                    and mischievous. He asked if the monarchical form of government was considered
                    so objectionable in America. I said, unquestionably <hi rend="italic">for
                        America.</hi> Whatever might be the case in Europe, with us there were
                    absolutely no materials for monarchy. And in Europe, <pb facs="0634" n="564"
                        xml:id="pg_564"/> said he, there are no materials for a republic. Then, I
                    replied, you can easily perceive the revolutionary shock to men’s ideas which
                    would be communicated by the sudden creation, on our frontier, of a foreign
                    monarchy by foreign arms. Suppose that the United States, acting in concert with
                    another powerful American republic, if such there were, should, on pretext of
                    debts owing to their citizens, or flagrant wrongs committed against individuals
                    through an unsatisfactory condition of the local administration, suddenly invade
                    some weak kingdom, or portion of a kingdom, in your neighbourhood, reduce its
                    cities and strong places with their armies and navies, without any declaration
                    of war, and proceed to establish a strong democratic republic, for example, on
                    the frontiers of Austria, and in close neighbourhood to your capital or great
                    commercial centres: you would certainly not regard such events with indifference
                    or without alarm. Governments and individuals would be full of suspicion. Men
                    would say, if a great power from the other end of the earth can be permitted to
                    come hither and subvert dynasties, and make radical changes in the political
                    institutions of independent nations, by means of superior military force, there
                    is an end forever to any separate national existence, or to any international
                    law. Every state would henceforth live upon sufferance. The great powers, acting
                    in concert, and making use of brute force, would reduce the world to obedience,
                    and change political institutions at their pleasure.</p>
                <p>I said, whatever might be the present condition of Mexico, that I could not
                    imagine that the nation was prepared to abandon the republican form of
                    government and suffer itself to be converted in a European monarchy without a
                    struggle. I had no special means of information, but I thought that, on general
                    principles, refugees were bad counsellors, and rarely represented the feelings
                    of a nation. I should be surprised if a Mexican kingdom could be established,
                    except by force. No doubt the allies were strong enough to crush resistance. But
                    bloodshed and massacre on a considerable scale would, I thought, be necessary to
                    overcome that resistance. I could not believe that the enlightened powers of
                    France, England, and Spain intended the perpetration of a crime, and it seemed
                    to me improbable that the end proposed could be accomplished except by crime. It
                    seemed to me, too, almost impossible that a monarchy thus established, unless
                    constantly supported by foreign bayonets, could maintain itself long. The idea
                    of European monarchy rests upon an established and historical order of things,
                    which are entirely wanting in North America. The feudal system, from which the
                    monarchies and aristocracies of Europe derived their origin, their sanction, and
                    their strength, is unknown in the western world; and the elements out of which
                    it was compounded can scarcely concur again. A foreign monarchy transplanted
                    from Europe would be a tender exotic, and would wither for want of sufficient
                    roots. A territorial aristocracy to surround the throne would seem almost
                    impossible on a continent where land of the best quality can be had, in fee
                    simple, for a dollar or two the acre. In certain portions of our own country a
                    pseudo aristocracy had grown up, founded not on the sword, not on military
                    conquest, nor on vast territorial possessions, but upon particular and
                    exceptional kind of property, as recognized by special legislation in an
                    unfortunate race of mankind. I did not know whether or not the new Mexican
                    monarchy was to be surrounded by an aristocracy of slaveholders, and in a land
                    where the republic had already abolished African slavery.</p>
                <p>Still speaking as a private person, and by no means officially, I took occasion
                    to say that all my feelings and political opinions were strongly opposed to the
                    absorption by the United States of an inch of Mexican soil, and that they always
                    had been, and probably always would be, opposed to any annexation, north or
                    south. We had territory enough and a sufficient mingling of <pb facs="0635"
                        n="565" xml:id="pg_565"/> races; especially the extension of our frontier
                    any further towards the tropics, together with the admixture of so foreign an
                    element as that of the Mexican population, I considered to be fraught with evil.
                    For my own part, I wished sincerely that the Mexican republic could be
                    strengthened and its administration improved; but I should deplore its conquest,
                    either by our own arms, or those of any European nation.</p>
                <p>I have endeavored to give the substance of our conversation as accurately as I
                    can from memory. It was to me an interesting one, and I trust it may be deemed
                    not unworthy of the President’s attention and your own. If it is desired that I
                    should say anything officially on the subject at any future day, you will of
                    course instruct me. I believe, however, the scheme in question to be so
                    doubtful, and at any rate so distant, as to make it preferable to leave the
                    matter for the present out of the region of formal discussion.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. LOTHROP MOTLEY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
