<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Motley to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1862</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d462</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">462</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1862-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1862-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417" lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421" lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696" lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="population-demographics" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969" lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650" lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249" lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218" lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recOAfZ9FRSJKK76a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064772" lcsh-match="exact">Income tax</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130" lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recdTuobyjHNvXKhT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011601" lcsh-match="exact">Bankruptcy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-10-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="462" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d462">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Motley</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 8.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> —, 1862.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your despatches Nos. 17, 18, 19, and 20
                            have been received.</p>
                <p>No. 17, which is printed and in the form of a circular, relates mainly to
                            the subject of possible intervention in our affairs on the part of
                            foreign powers, and of the probable effects of such a step should it be
                            taken.</p>
                <p>It is hardly necessary for me to state that the able and conclusive
                            reasoning of your despatch has my entire approval. You are better able
                            to judge, officially, of the probabilities of such a catastrophe, (for
                            an intermeddling by Europe with our domestic matters can be called by no
                            other name, and could have only the most tragical results,) because
                            there are but two governments in the world that have ever arrogated to
                            themselves the right to discuss the proprieties of such a step. The
                            government of the empire to which I have the honor of being accredited
                            has never hinted at any desire of interference, nor made any
                            ostentatious proclamation of “neutrality” between the government bound
                            to it by treaties of amity and commerce and an imaginary nation, which
                            has no existence, save in the visions of domestic treason and foreign
                            malice.</p>
                <p>In spite of the clamor of a portion of the English press and of that
                            fraction of the British public, which is incapable of lifting its
                            aspirations higher than its immediate material interests, I cannot
                            believe, now that the proclamation of September 22 has distinctly
                            defined the position of our government on the great question of the age,
                            that any English ministry can stand up in the face of God and man, and
                            extend the right hand of fellowship to a new commonwealth, avowedly
                            based upon the perpetuation and extension of negro slavery as its
                            corner-stone, until that commonwealth has proved its existence to be a
                            fact which can no longer be contradicted. That the fact is already an
                            accomplished one would be a childish assertion, and no man in Europe
                            deserving the name of a statesman or a reasoner has ventured to make
                            it.</p>
                <p>The venerable premier of England has been all his life a consistent and
                            determined hater of African slavery, and has always done battle with it
                            stoutly. I shall never believe that, so long as he guides the policy of
                            England, that country will be swift to recognize the claims of the slave
                            confederacy for recognition, now that all the clouds which sophistry has
                            collected in Europe about the causes of our war have been forever
                            dissipated. No man in Europe capable of reasoning has failed to
                            understand the bearings of a subject which in itself was simple, but
                            which passion and malice had rendered complex. It was perfectly
                            understood that slavery, as it existed in the States, was beyond the
                            reach of the federal government in time of peace, and that it was only
                            the war levied by the slaveholders upon the national existence which
                            placed the institution within the reach of the national power exercising
                            its belligerent rights.</p>
                <p>Wise and good men have appreciated the hesitation of the President to
                            make use of this tremendous weapon, and to meet revolution by
                            revolution; but nearly all have foreseen that this was the inevitable
                            issue of the great onslaught made by slavery upon the national life and
                            on our free institutions, and, more than all, that as the war went on,
                            emancipation by the commander-in-chief, in the exercise of his
                            unquestioned right to take all measures not repugnant to humanity to
                            overcome the resistance of the enemy, was really the only method of
                            averting that most horrible of catastrophes—a servile war.</p>
                <p>Insurrections, unorganized and private wars, whether by white men or
                            black men, may, and, I doubt not, always will, be suppressed by the
                            military arm; but the position of a great country, defending itself
                            against the deadly blows of the slave power with one hand while
                            protecting its enemy with the other,. had become an untenable and almost
                            an absurd one.</p>
                <pb facs="0639" n="569" xml:id="pg_569"/>
                <p>“We have the right to put in practice against the enemy,” says Vattel
                            “every measure that is necessary in order to weaken him, and disable him
                            from resisting us and supporting his injustice; and we may choose such
                            methods as are the most efficacious and best calculated to attain the
                            end in view, provided they be not of an odious kind, nor unjustifiable
                            in themselves, and prohibited by the law of nature.”—(B. 111, c.
                            VIII.)</p>
                <p>Whether the excellent Swiss would have thought the bestowing liberty upon
                            the captives of the enemy an unjustifiable measure, or one prohibited by
                            the law of nature, may be judged by his well known opinion in regard to
                            slavery.” If I spare his life and condemn him to a state so contrary to
                            the nature of man, I still continue with him the state of war. He lies
                            under no obligation to me, for <hi rend="italic">what is life without
                                freedom ?</hi> If any one counts life a favor when the grant of it
                            is attended with chains, be it so. * * * * I shall dwell no longer on
                            the subject; and, indeed, that disgrace to humanity is happily banished
                            from Europe.”</p>
                <p>From the tone of the liberal portion of the English press, and from
                            private correspondence, I am disposed to feel comparatively at ease in
                            regard to the possibility of immediate foreign intervention. Of course,
                            the danger is an ever impending one, and the most vigorous measures for
                            the prosecution of the war cannot be too earnestly urged on government
                            by those who know the anxiety with which the struggle is watched in this
                            hemisphere, and who feel the enmity which the progress and prosperity of
                            our great and free republic have awakened among the possessors of
                            privilege and the humble servants of those classes.</p>
                <p>The masses all over Europe sympathize with our cause, for they know,
                            without need of argument or illustration, that our great commonwealth
                            was the refuge of the downtrod and the oppressed, and the only hope of
                            humanity and civilization beyond the seas. That its existence is
                            endangered by an oligarchy founded on slavery, and that it is now
                            defending itself with a generous outpouring of its best blood and its
                            treasure, altogether unparalelled in the history of the world, does not
                            diminish the affection with which it is regarded by the lovers of
                            freedom.</p>
                <p>It is in this connexion that I refer to a passage in your despatch No.
                            19, in which you inform me that you can give me no fresh instructions in
                            regard to the multitude of brave and distinguished officers in this
                            empire seeking to serve under our flag. I have always given them the
                            same answer; that neither international law nor the statutes of our own
                            country permitted a diplomatic representative to come into engagements
                            with foreign soldiers. At the same time I have always expressed myself
                            as deeply touched by their manifestations of sympathy and devotion to
                            our cause. Hardly a day has passed since I have had the honor of
                            representing our republic, in which I have not received applications,
                            often from officers of high rank, who have gained reputation on many
                            battle fields of Europe, for permission to enter our army. And it is
                            with deep regret that I have been obliged to decline the services of men
                            who would have done honor to any cause. But as part of the current
                            history of the times it is well that these things should be recorded,
                            and the archives of this legation contain many eloquent letters from
                            chivalrous soldiers, who have asked to devote their swords and their
                            lives to the “starry banner,” which to them, as they uniformly assert,
                            is the symbol of freedom and civilization. It is right that the homage
                            so earnestly paid in a foreign land to that flag, under which so many of
                            our own best and bravest are laying down their lives, should be
                            remembered.</p>
                <p>In this connexion I deem worthy of your notice a brief extract from a
                            remarkable series of papers in the principal military journal of this
                            empire, in which the course of our campaigns is criticized, sometimes
                            severely, but never ungenerously; always with talent, and with thorough
                            knowledge of the subject, topographically and strategetically, and with
                            a firm disposition to do justice. <pb facs="0640" n="570" xml:id="pg_570"/> You will be interested to read the comments of so
                            able a writer upon the withdrawal of our armies from the James
                            river:</p>
                <p>“It is not to be wondered at, then, if the general-in-chief of the army
                            of the Potomac was in haste to save the army intrusted to him from the
                            dangers surrounding it, even from certain destruction; from a noose, in
                            fact, which required only to be drawn a little more closely together in
                            order to suffocate the soul of the Union. The manner in which he
                            acquitted himself of this most difficult of all military tasks redounds
                            to his infinite honor, and places him at once in the ranks of those
                            memorable commanders whose names history treasures for posterity; men
                            who, if they have, perhaps, not had the art to chain victory to their
                            banners, possessed, at any rate, the fortitude, the audacity, and the
                            circumspection to rescue their armies from impending ruin. * * * The
                            American general has made a thorough study of war in the swamps of the
                            Chickahominy, and has made himself a complete master in that most
                            difficult of professions. * * * He has manifested the unquestioned
                            talent to save his army, in a manner not sufficiently to be admired, out
                            of the most desperate of situations. Moreau made himself immortal by his
                            famous retreat from the Iller to the Rhine in the year 1796. What is due
                            to the American general-in-chief, who conducted, with a morally and
                            physically exhausted army, through a swampy, pathless country, covered
                            with ancient forests, and in face of an enemy outnumbering him two to
                            one, the most classical of all retreats recorded in military history,
                            without a single disaster?”</p>
                <p>The press of Austria has, on the whole, been friendly to our cause. An
                            extract or two from a recent number of one of the most widely circulated
                            journals of this capital may be interesting to you, written, as it is,
                            in my opinion, with singular talent:</p>
                <p>“The defeat of the great armies of the confederates, which had pressed
                            into Maryland, near Hagerstown, and were then compelled to retreat into
                            Virginia, and the proclamation issued by President Lincoln on the 22d of
                            September, abolishing slavery after January 1, form a turning point in
                            American events. Our London correspondent, with judgment unclouded by
                            the language of the English press, which is almost unanimously favorable
                            to the south and to the cause of slavery, makes the following
                            observations concerning the new situation in America:</p>
                <p>“‘The short campaign in Maryland has decided the fate of the American
                            civil war, however the fortune of war, for a longer or shorter time, may
                            hover between the contending parties. It was formerly developed in this
                            journal that the contest for the possession of the border States was the
                            contest for the sovereignty of the Union, and the confederacy has been
                            defeated in this struggle, which it undertook under most favorable
                            circumstances, which can never occur again.</p>
                <p>“‘Maryland was justly considered the head, Kentucky the arm of the
                            slavery party in the border States; Maryland’s capital, Baltimore, was
                            supposed to be maintained in its loyalty by force. It was a dogma not
                            only of the south, but of the north, that the appearance of the
                            confederates in Maryland would give the signal for a rising of the
                            population <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi> against the “satellites of
                            Lincoln.”</p>
                <p>“‘It would be a case not only of military success, but of moral
                            demonstration, which should electrize the southern elements in all the
                            border States, and carry them irresistibly into the vortex. With
                            Maryland Washington was to fall, Philadelphia to be threatened, and New
                            York to be rendered doubtful. The simultaneous invasion of Kentucky, by
                            population, situation, and resources the most important of the border
                            States, was, if considered as an isolate demonstration, only a
                            diversion. Supported by decisive success in Maryland, it would overwhelm
                            the Union party in Tennessee, outflank Missouri, secure Arkansas and
                            Texas, threaten New Orleans, and, above all, transfer the war to Ohio,
                            the <pb facs="0641" n="571" xml:id="pg_571"/> central State of the
                            north, the possession of which would subdue the north as entirely as
                            that of Georgia would subdue the south.</p>
                <p>“‘A confederate army in Ohio would cut off the western from the eastern
                            States, and would fight the enemy from his own centre.</p>
                <p>“‘After the failure of the main rebel army in Maryland, the Kentucky
                            invasion, carried forward, as it was, with little energy, and never
                            meeting with popular sympathy, shrinks to an insignificant guerilla
                            incursion. Even the occupation of Louisville would now only unite the
                            “giants of the west,” the masses of Iowa, Illinois, Indiana, and Ohio,
                            in a similar avalanche to the one which descended on the south during
                            the first glorious Kentucky campaign.</p>
                <p>“‘Thus the Maryland campaign has proved that the power is wanting to the
                            waves of secession to roll across the Potomac and up to the Ohio. The
                            south is compelled to the defensive, but only in the offensive lay the
                            possibility of its success. Deprived of the border States wedged in
                            between the Mississippi on the west and the Atlantic on the east, it has
                            now conquered nothing—but a grave.</p>
                <p>“‘One should not forget for a moment that the southrons possessed the
                            border States, and governed them politically when the banner of the
                            rebellion was planted. What they desired was the Territories. They have
                            lost the Territories with the border States. * * * * * *</p>
                <p>“‘<hi rend="italic">E puo si muove.’</hi> Reason conquers, after all, in
                            the world’s history. * * * * * * Nothing is easier than to show up
                            apparent inconsistencies and aesthetical shortcomings in many of
                            President Lincoln’s actions of state, as is done by the English Pindars
                            of slavery, the Times, Saturday Review, and <hi rend="italic">tutti
                                quanti.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>“And yet, in the history of the United States and of humanity, Lincoln
                            will take his place immediately next to Washington! Is it, then,
                            altogether without meaning, in our days, when the insignificant on this
                            side the Atlantic drapes itself so melodramatically, that in the New
                            World the important strides about in everyday clothes? * * * * *</p>
                <p>“Hegel has observed that, in truth, comedy stands higher than tragedy—
                            the humor of reason above its pathos. If Mr. Lincoln does not possess
                            the pathos of historical action, he possesses thoroughly its humor. In
                            what a moment does he issue the proclamation abolishing slavery on
                            January 1, 1863? In the very moment in which the confederacy, as an
                            independent power, had resolved, in the Richmond congress, on proposing
                            peace negotiations; in the same moment in which the slaveholders
                            considered their peculiar institution as much secured by their invasion
                            of Kentucky as was their dominion over their countryman, the Kentuckian,
                                Lincoln.”—<hi rend="italic">Presse of Vienna, October</hi> 12.</p>
                <p>You are far better able to judge of the attitude of the government of
                            France than I can be, and your relations with the French minister at
                            Washington, and with our excellent envoy at Paris, enable you to see how
                            much or how little truth there may be in the periodically recurring
                            rumors of an intended interference on the part of the French Emperor. So
                            far as I can decide, from private means of information of the highest
                            and most unquestionable character, I should say that, thus far, no
                            projects or propositions of interference have been presented by that
                            government to England. The proclamation of September 22 would seem to
                            make such projects, for the present, impossible. I doubt if there is a
                            government in Europe that would dare to confront the strong anti-slavery
                            feeling which is entertained by a large majority of the European
                            populations.</p>
                <p>The manifesto of the English chancellor of the exchequer at Newcastle
                            has, doubtless, engaged your attention, and you are better able to
                            decide than I am how much weight is to be attached to those remarkable
                            instances of sympathy with the slaveholders and their cause.</p>
                <p>I only allude to it in passing as forming a portion of the historical
                            record of these times. It is the first public, although unofficial,
                            response of an English <pb facs="0642" n="572" xml:id="pg_572"/>
                            minister to the emancipation proclamation of the President. I do not
                            believe it to represent the feeling either of the government or the
                            nation.</p>
                <p>The speech, so far as it related to the United States, was a consummate
                            work of art, and suggests the oration which the great dramatist has
                            imagined for Mark Anthony, arousing the citizens of Rome to fury over
                            the dead body of Cæsar. There is the same elaborate deprecation of
                            hostile feeling, the same subtle and successful fanning of flames of
                            hatred in his hearers, under pretence of cooling a popular frenzy.</p>
                <p rend="center">“Good friends, sweet friends, let me not stir you up</p>
                <p rend="center">To such a sudden flood of mutiny.</p>
                <p rend="center">They that have done this deed are honorable,”</p>
                <p>says the Roman.</p>
                <p>“Why, gentlemen, they are our kin; they were, at any rate, if they are
                            not now, <hi rend="italic">our customers ;</hi> and we hope that they
                                <hi rend="italic">will be our customers again!”</hi> says the
                            chancellor of the exchequer.</p>
                <p>A people struggling for its life against the most tremendous oligarchy
                            that the world has ever seen awakens not his respect, but his pity. He
                            is anxious, therefore, that a people so humiliated should be treated
                            with due compassion. “Let us bear with them all we can.” To assure a
                            people thus battling for freedom against slavery, for law, order, and
                            social progress against a despotism, avowedly founded on slavery as its
                            corner stone, that it is sure to be defeated, and that the sympathies of
                            the world are with its antagonist, is, it seems, the true way of
                            “manifesting a kindly temper.” To do this is to observe “great caution
                            about adverse criticisms.”</p>
                <p>The cup of humiliation and shame is ready for them, it appears. “They are
                            still endeavoring to hold it far from their lips; they have not yet
                            drunk of the cup which, notwithstanding all the world sees, they must
                            drink of.” Enjoying thus the advantage of reading the future with
                            perfect accuracy, the orator instructs his hearers to imitate his
                            Christian forbearance, and not to trample on the downfallen. He
                            “earnestly hopes that England will do nothing to inflict additional <hi rend="italic">shame</hi>, sorrow, or pain on those who have already
                            suffered much, and who will probably <hi rend="italic">have to suffer
                                much more.”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Those who know—as what American does not—the deeds of daring by men, of
                            self-devotion by women, the almost fabulous generosity of all, the
                            countless traits of individual heroism and chivalry with which the
                            simple annals of so many families, rich and poor, throughout our land
                            have been filled, during this dark but most honorable epoch of our
                            history; those who know what a great people is now doing and suffering
                            in defence of the free institutions bequeathed to them by their fathers,
                            will know how to appreciate the epithet of <hi rend="italic">“shame”</hi> which an English minister so genially bestows upon our
                            name.</p>
                <p>“Blistered be the tongue, that speaks of shame” is the only fit response
                            to such rhetoric and such prophecy.</p>
                <p>But there were words in the oration to which it is to be hoped America
                            will never refuse its assent. The Americans, it is admitted, “have warm
                            affections towards England.” England is “the country which, however they
                            may find fault with us, from time to time, has the highest place in
                            their admiration and respect.” This is perfectly true, and will, I
                            trust, long remain so. But the England thus venerated and beloved of
                            America is not the England which speaks through the lips of the
                            chancellor of the exchequer, and which cheers his prophecies of our
                            humiliation and shame.</p>
                <p>It cannot be denied that the tendency of European public opinion, as
                            delivered from high places, is more and more unfriendly to our cause.
                            This is to be ascribed, of course, to the interruptions which the
                            continuance of the war causes to material interests, and to the
                            increasing dislike in Europe to liberal institutions. It would be
                            weakness in us to expect sympathy from the privileged classes; but the
                            people everywhere sympathize with us, for they know that our <pb facs="0643" n="573" xml:id="pg_573"/> cause is that of free
                            institutions, that our struggle is that of the people against an
                            oligarchy. They are not deceived by the reiteration of the stale
                            commonplaces about the “wicked war,” the “miserable war,” the “causeless
                            war.” Not one of the critics and prophets with which the world swarms,
                            and who are so anxious to take the mote from their neighbor’s eye, has
                            ever suggested any possible project for the restoration of peace. They
                            content themselves with denouncing the war. It would be well for these
                            philosophers to ponder the motto which the State of Massachusetts
                            borrowed from Algernon Sydney, and has borne for nearly a century on her
                            seal:</p>
                <p rend="center">“Ense petit placidam sub libertate quietem.”</p>
                <p>The time comes to all nations when they can achieve peace <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi> liberty by the sword alone. And when those
                            blessings have been secured—as they only can be, on our continent, which
                            the hand of God has indicated as the residence of one people—by the
                            re-establishment of our federal Union and popular institutions, now
                            threatened by the slaveholders’ insurrection, it may be hoped that the
                            American sword may be sheathed for centuries.</p>
                <p>Nor do I think that optimism puerile or unphilosophical which looks
                            forward, through the war clouds that now envelop our land, to a day when
                            the passions, slaked in blood, shall at last permit reason to resume her
                            sway, and when the south as well as the north shall be both proud and
                            happy that an oppressed race has been converted from chattels into free
                            laborers, and the only obstacle removed which has ever lain in the path
                            of our united nation to prosperity and true glory.</p>
                <p>Even if these be dreams, I for one would not exchange my faith for that
                            short-sighted materialism which, in either hemisphere, can see any good
                            to the world in the downfall of our great and free republic.</p>
                <p>I have nothing special to report of the condition of this empire. Its
                            financial condition would seem to be improving, to judge by the rise of
                            twenty per cent, in the market value of its paper as compared with
                            specie. Ten pounds sterling, which at par are equivalent to 100 florins,
                            were worth 140 florins a year ago, and are now worth but 120. There are
                            hopes of a resumption of specie payments at the end of five years. The
                            measures are now pending before the Reichsrath, and I will inform you
                            duly of the result.</p>
                <p>The proposed budget for 1863 shows a probable expenditure of 388,698,000
                            florins, with an income of 304,300,000. The deficit is already
                            84,398,000, which in time of peace does not seem very encouraging,
                            particularly as about one-third of the whole annual expense is to be
                            charged to the army. It should never be forgotten, however, that the
                            resources of this empire are vast, and to a great extent still
                            undeveloped.</p>
                <p>The condition of the inhabitants is far from an unfortunate one in a
                            material point of view; the agricultural and mineral wealth is great,
                            and there is a steady effort to give fair play to the liberal
                            institutions with which the empire has recently been endowed.</p>
                <p>The taxation is heavy upon the wealthier classes, rather than upon the
                            nation. Thus the tax on real estate is about 331/3 per cent., and there
                            is an income tax of six per cent., which is shortly to be increased to
                            seven per cent.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the gross amount of the debt is, in round numbers, but
                            eleven hundred and fifty million dollars, which, for a population of
                            thirty-six millions, is but thirty-two dollars per head.</p>
                <p>The amount of annual taxation is but a fraction over four dollars per
                            head. To speak, therefore, of the Austrian empire as on the verge of
                            bankruptcy and impending dissolution is mere abuse of language. The
                            amount of debt and the ratio of taxation distributed per head over the
                            population show that the condition of the Austrian subject is better
                            than that of the subject of any monarchy in Europe, except Greece and
                            Russia. The amount of debt in Holland <pb facs="0644" n="574" xml:id="pg_574"/> is, per head, one hundred and thirteen dollars,
                            while in the same country the ratio of contribution to the public
                            revenue is more than eleven dollars per head. The amount of debt per
                            head in France is above fifty dollars, with a ratio of taxation of ten
                            dollars. The amount of debt per head in Great Britain is about one
                            hundred and forty dollars, with a ratio of taxation of more than eleven
                            dollars.</p>
                <p>Thus the condition of Austria is, comparatively, favorable, and there is
                            no doubt that the general aspect of the empire is one of thrift,
                            contentment, and prosperity. The capital is growing like an American
                            city, and the old feudal and picturesque town is surrounded by vast
                            suburbs, in which splendid streets and stately palaces are rising and
                            extending themselves in all directions.</p>
                <p>My despatch has reached a greater length than I intended, and I shall
                            therefore conclude these desultory remarks.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. LOTHROP MOTLEY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
