<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1862</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d65</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">65</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1862-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1862-05-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recfec047f5431758f" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="property-claims" subject="contraband-of-war">Contraband of war</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-05-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-05-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="65"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d65">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 160.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-05-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 15, 1862.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have had the honor to receive from the
                    department despatches numbered from 237 to 241, both inclusive; likewise a
                    telegraphic despatch, dated the 1st instant, containing the welcome intelligence
                    of the capture of New Orleans, which I immediately communicated by telegraph to
                    Mr. Dayton. The intelligence was received here with such general incredulity
                    that even my announcement of the official confirmation scarcely dispelled the
                    doubts. The cause of this possibly may be that it dissipated many illusions
                    indulged in of late on very small foundations I now transmit the copy of my
                    reply to Lord Russell’s note, a copy of which is already on its way to you, with
                    my despatch No. 158, of the 9th instant. Since that date I have received a note
                    from his lordship, dated the 10th, in answer to mine addressed to him on the
                    8th, to which I felt it my duty to make a rejoinder on the 12th instant. Copies
                    of these two notes likewise accompany this despatch.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Earl
                            Russell</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-05-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 10, 1862.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        reception of your lordship’s note of the 7th instant, touching the case of
                        the British vessel Emily St. Pierre.</p>
                    <p>I do not understand from the terms of that note that her Majesty’s law
                        advisers entertain a doubt of the correctness of the law as explained in my
                        application of the 24th of April for the restoration of that vessel. Indeed,
                        it would be difficult to find any doctrine more precisely laid down by the
                        highest judicial authority of Great Britain than that which applies to this
                        particular case. I pray your lordship’s attention to the language of the
                        late Lord Stowell, famed all over the world for his exposition of
                        international law. “If a neutral master attempts a rescue, he violates a
                        duty which is <pb facs="0162" n="92" xml:id="pg_92"/> imposed upon him by
                        the law of nations to submit to come in for inquiry as to the property of
                        the ship or cargo; and if he violates that obligation by a recurrence to
                        force, the consequence will undoubtedly reach the property of his owner; and
                        it would, I think, extend also to the confiscation of the whole cargo
                        intrusted to his care, and thus fraudulently attempted to be withdrawn from
                        the rights of war.”</p>
                    <p>If this be admitted to be a correct version of the law of the case, as
                        recognized by Great Britain, then little room appears to be left for doubt
                        that the neutral master of the Emily St. Pierre has brought himself within
                        the scope of the condemnation expressed in these words of Lord Stowell, for
                        the facts, as substantially presented by me, do not seem to be disputed.</p>
                    <p>But I further understand that the grounds upon which your lordship declines
                        to interfere on behalf of the United States do not in any way touch the
                        merits of the case. They are, so far as I can perceive, purely technical.
                        Your lordship remarks that her Majesty’s government have no jurisdiction or
                        legal power whatever to take or acquire possession of the vessel, or to
                        interfere with her owners, in relation to their property in her. And,
                        further, that “acts of forcible resistance to the rights of belligerents,
                        when lawfully exercised over neutral merchant ships on the high seas, such,
                        for instance, as rescue from capture, however cognizable or punishable as
                        offences against international law in the prize courts of the captor
                        administering such law, are not cognizable by the municipal law of England,
                        and cannot, by that law, be punished either by confiscation of the ship or
                        by any other penalty; and her Majesty’s government cannot raise, in an
                        English court, the question of the validity of the capture of the Emily St.
                        Pierre, or of the subsequent rescue and recapture of that vessel, for such
                        recapture is not an offence against the municipal law of this country.”</p>
                    <p>I cannot restrain the expression of my profound regret to your lordship that
                        by reason of the absence of a just and necessary power in her Majesty’s
                        government this wrongdoer should thus have the opportunity of escaping with
                        impunity from suffering the proper penalty for his fraudulent attempts. I am
                        the more deeply sensible of my disappointment from the fact that I had been
                        led to hope for an opposite result from the language of her Majesty’s
                        proclamation issued on the 13th day of May last, and evidently intended to
                        apply to precisely the class of cases to which this of the Emily St. Pierre
                        appears to belong. The closing paragraph of that paper expressly warns all
                        her Majesty’s subjects, and all persons whatsoever entitled to her
                        protection, that if any of them shall presume, “in contempt of that, her
                        royal proclamation, and of her high displeasure, to do any acts in
                        derogation of their duty, as subjects of a neutral sovereign, in the said
                        contest, <hi rend="italic">or in violation or contravention of the law of
                            nations in that behalf</hi> as, for example, * * * by breaking, or
                        endeavoring to break, any blockade lawfully and actually established by or
                        on behalf of either of the said contending parties, * * * all parties so
                        offending will incur and be liable to the several penalties and penal
                        consequences of the said statute, <hi rend="italic">or by the law of
                            nations</hi> in that behalf imposed or denounced.”</p>
                    <p>If it be not implied by the language to which I have taken the liberty to
                        call your lordship’s attention that there is a jurisdiction existing in
                        Great Britain capable of taking cognizance of cases arising under the law of
                        nations, and beyond the range of the municipal law, then does it appear, at
                        least to my judgment, that the proclamation has been most unfortunately
                        worded, for it can scarcely be denied that the government of the United
                        States, which it was certainly intended in part to protect, had a just right
                        to infer from it the power as well as the will of her Majesty’s government
                        to shelter it against such wrongful and fraudulent acts of her
                        ill-intentioned subjects as have been committed in the case of the ship
                        Emily St. Pierre.</p>
                    <pb facs="0163" n="93" xml:id="pg_93"/>
                    <p>Praying your lordship’s pardon for the trouble I have given you in this case,
                        and trusting I may find justification for my very natural mistake, I beg to
                        renew to your lordship the assurance of the highest consideration with which
                        I have the honor to be, my lord, your most obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Right Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl Russell</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >&amp;c.,&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Earl Russell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Adams</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-05-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 10, 1862.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In the letter I had the honor to receive from
                        you yesterday you appear to have confounded two things totally distinct.</p>
                    <p>The foreign enlistment act is intended to prevent the subjects of the crown
                        from going to war when the sovereign is not at war. Thus private persons are
                        prohibited from fitting out a ship-of-war in our ports, or from enlisting in
                        the service of a foreign state at war with another state, or in the service
                        of insurgents against a foreign sovereign or state. In these cases the
                        persons so acting would carry on war, and thus might engage the name of
                        their sovereign and of their nation in belligerent operations. But owners
                        and masters of merchant ships carrying warlike stores do nothing of the
                        kind. If captured for breaking a blockade or carrying contraband of war to
                        the enemy of the captor, they submit to capture, are tried, and condemned to
                        lose their cargo. This is the penalty which the law of nations has affixed
                        to such an offence, and in calling upon her Majesty’s government to prohibit
                        such adventurers you in effect call upon her Majesty’s government to do that
                        which it belongs to the cruisers and the courts of the United states to do
                        for themselves.</p>
                    <p>There can be only one plea for asking Great Britain thus to interpose. That
                        plea is, that the blockade is in reality ineffective, and that merchant
                        ships can enter with impunity the blockaded ports. But this is a plea which
                        I presume you will not urge. Her Majesty’s government have considered the
                        blockade as an effective blockade, and have submitted to all its
                        inconveniences as such.</p>
                    <p>They can only hope that, if resistance should prove to be hopeless, the
                        confederate States will not continue the struggle; that if, on the other
                        hand, the restoration of the Union should appear to be impossible, the work
                        of devastation now going on will cease.</p>
                    <p>Her Majesty’s government can only desire the prosperity of the inhabitants of
                        the United States, whatever may be the event of the present civil war.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your most
                        obedient, humble servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>RUSSELL.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic"
                                >&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Earl
                            Russell</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-05-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 12, 1862.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        reception of your note of the 10th instant. From the purport of it I am led
                        to fear that I may have been unfortunate heretofore in my attempts to
                        express my own meaning. <pb facs="0164" n="94" xml:id="pg_94"/> If I have
                        appeared to your lordship to confound two things so very dissimilar as the
                        penalties of the enlistment act and the liabilities which follow from the
                        attempt to break a blockade, I can only say that the fault must be laid to
                        my want of ability to use words properly to express my thoughts.</p>
                    <p>The position which I did mean to take was this: that the <hi rend="italic"
                            >intent</hi> of the enlistment act, as explained by the words of its
                        preamble, was to prevent the unauthorized action of subjects of Great
                        Britain, disposed to embark in the contests of foreign nations, from
                        involving the country in the risk of a war with these countries. This view
                        of the law does not seem to be materially varied by your lordship; when
                        speaking of the same thing you say that the law applies to cases where
                        “private persons so acting would carry on, and thus might engage the name of
                        their sovereign and of their nation in belligerent operations.” It is
                        further shown by that preamble that that act was an additional act of
                        prevention, made necessary by experience of the inefficiency of former acts
                        passed to effect the same object.</p>
                    <p>But it is now made plain that whatever may have been the skill with which
                        this latest act was drawn, it does not completely fulfil its intent, because
                        it is very certain that many British subjects are now engaged in
                        undertakings of a hostile character to a foreign state which, though not
                        technically within the strict letter of the enlistment act, are as much
                        contrary to its spirit as if they levied war directly. Their measures
                        embrace all of the operations preliminary to openly carrying on war—the
                        supply of men, and ships, and arms, and money to one party in order that
                        they may be the better enabled to overcome the other, which other is in this
                        case a nation with which Great Britain is now under treaty obligations of
                        the most solemn nature to maintain a lasting peace and friendship. The
                        government of the United States having, in the course of its hostile
                        operations, had occasion to experience the injurious effects of this virtual
                        levying of war against itself from the ports of a friendly power, and seeing
                        the obstacle in the way of the removal of them to be alleged to be the
                        inefficiency of a statute intended to effect that object, does not regard it
                        as asking anything unreasonable, or more than it would in like case be
                        willing itself to grant, if it solicits some action to render effective the
                        spirit as well of the law as. of her Majesty’s enunciation of the national
                        will.</p>
                    <p>I perceive that your lordship appears to be of opinion that, in this
                        proceeding, the government of the United States is asking more than is
                        reasonable. It is, in your view, sufficient to declare that owners and
                        masters of merchant ships, fitted out with intent to break a blockade or
                        carry contraband of war to one of two parties engaged in war, are subject to
                        capture, trial, and condemnation, if caught by the offended party. And
                        hence, in this case, that the government of the United States, in calling
                        upon her Majesty’s government to prohibit such adventures, is in effect
                        calling upon it to do that which it ought to do, and fails to be able to do
                        for itself. The only valid plea, your lordship remarks, for asking
                        interposition, is, that the blockade is in reality ineffective; and this,
                        you very justly presume, I shall not be disposed to urge.</p>
                    <p>But I pray your lordship’s pardon if I submit that you appear to have
                        entirely overlooked another plea, which I am confident enough to imagine of
                        no inconsiderable weight. That plea is that the kingdom of Great Britain
                        endeavor in spirit as well as in letter to preserve the principle of
                        neutrality, if not of friendship, towards a foreign power in amity with it
                        to which it has pledged itself. The precise mode in which that shall be
                        done, it does not presume to prescribe. That the toleration of such conduct
                        in subjects of Great Britain, as I have had the pain heretofore to expose,
                        is surely in violation of that neutrality, is justly to be inferred from the
                        very language of her Majesty’s proclamation. For it is therein declared that
                        precisely <pb facs="0165" n="95" xml:id="pg_95"/> such acts of theirs as I
                        have been compelled to complain of are done “in derogation of their duty to
                        her as a neutral sovereign, and incur her high displeasure.” If such, then,
                        be the true character of the proceedings to which I have heretofore called
                        your lordship’s attention, they surely merit something more of notice from
                        her Majesty’s ministers than an intimation that they will be suffered to
                        pass unreproved unless the punishment shall be inflicted by the nation whom
                        they are designed to injure. The object of the government of the United
                        States has not been to relieve itself of the duty of vigilance to capture
                        offenders against the law. It has rather been to avoid the necessity of
                        applying additional stringent measures for their own security against
                        British subjects found to be engaged in such illicit enterprises, made
                        imperative by the conviction that no preventive co-operation whatever can be
                        expected from her Majesty’s government. It has rather been to avoid the risk
                        of confounding the innocent with the guilty, because all happen to be
                        involved in a general suspicion. And, lastly, it has rather been to remove,
                        at as early a day as may be, consistently with its own safety, the
                        restrictions on the trade with foreign countries, which these evildoers are
                        laboring with so much industry to force it to protract. Your lordship’s
                        language leaves me little hope of any co-operation of her Majesty’s
                        government to these ends. Nevertheless, I trust I may be permitted to
                        indulge the belief that the time is not now far distant when the
                        difficulties thus interposed in the way of its progress will have been so
                        far removed by its own unassisted action as to relieve both countries from
                        the painful necessity of further continuing the discussion.</p>
                    <p>Renewing to your lordship the assurances of my highest consideration, I have
                        the honor to be, my lord, your most obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Right Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl Russell</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >&amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
