<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Harris..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1862</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d652</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">652</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1861-08-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1861-08-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1861-08-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1861-08-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="652"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d652">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Harris</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 18.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1861-08-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 1, 1861.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I recur again to your despatch of the 1st of
                    August, 1860, (No. 26.)</p>
                <p>In that paper you recommended a postponement for another year of the exercise of
                    the right of American citizens to reside in the city of Yedo for the purpose of
                    trade after the 1st of January next, saved to the United States by a clause in
                    the third article of the treaty of July 29, 1858.</p>
                <p>In my despatch to you of the 16th May last (No. 15) I stated that I had then
                    addressed a note in relation thereto to the minister of Prussia in the United
                    States, of which a copy was sent to you, and also that a similar note had been
                    addressed to the ministers of Great Britain, France, Russia, and Holland, and
                    that when replies to those communications should have been received by the
                    department, no time would be lost in acquainting you with their contents.</p>
                <p>The burden of the circular note thus addressed to the ministers of Great Britain,
                    France, Prussia, Russia, and Holland, was that the President might, perhaps,
                    have yielded to your suggestion if the circumstances which surround the subject
                    had remained unchanged; but we had learned by recent despatches that Mr.
                    Heusken, secretary of the American legation at Yedo, was, on the night of the
                    15th of January last, waylaid and assassinated in the streets of that city
                    without any other cause or provocation than the fact that he was a
                    foreigner.</p>
                <p>The Japanese government had made no satisfactory explanation of this great
                    violation of the rights of the United States, and, on the other hand, had
                    virtually confessed its inability to bring the offenders to punishment.</p>
                <p>It was argued by me in the aforesaid notes that the Japanese government would
                    infer that we are unwilling or unable to vindicate our rights, if, leaving that
                    transaction unpunished and unexplained, we should frustrate the effect of the
                    treaty stipulation for the opening of the city of Yedo.</p>
                <p>The President was, for this reason, of opinion that no postponement of the
                    opening of the city of Yedo ought to be conceded. He thought, however, that some
                    demonstration, which would render the residence of foreigners in Yedo safe,
                    ought to be made, and that the other powers consulted would probably be induced
                    to co-operate in such a demonstration, because their representatives are equally
                    exposed there with our own. The President therefore proposed that those powers
                    should announce to the government of Japan their willingness and their purpose
                    to make common cause and co-operate with this government in exacting
                    satisfaction, if the Japanese government should not at once put forth all
                    possible effort to secure the punishment of the assassins of Mr. Heusken, and
                    also in making requisitions with signal vigor if any insult or injury should be
                    committed against any foreigner residing in Yedo, after the opening of the city
                    in January next, according to the treaty.</p>
                <p>The ministers addressed, as I have reason to know, promptly submitted these
                    suggestions to their respective governments, together with a form of a
                    convention for carrying them into effect. This projected convention contemplated
                    the despatch of a fleet of steamers adequate to impress the Japanese government
                    with the ability and the determination of the states engaged, to secure a
                    performance of its treaty stipulations.</p>
                <pb facs="0885" n="815" xml:id="pg_815"/>
                <p>Subsequently to these proceedings, and while no answers had yet been received
                    from the governments consulted, your despatch (No. 20) of the date 01 May 8,
                    1861, was received, accompanied by a letter addressed by his Majesty the Tycoon
                    to the President of the United States, and also a letter to myself, written by
                    the Japanese ministers of foreign affairs.</p>
                <p>Those letters expressed the desire of the government of Japan that the opening of
                    the cities of Yedo and Osacca, and the harbors of Hiogo and Neegata, should be
                    postponed for the reasons more specifically set forth in the latter
                    communication. These reasons are, in substance, that the opening of the commerce
                    of Japan to the western nations has had immediate results very different from
                    what were anticipated. The prices of articles of general consumption are daily
                    advancing, owing to the extensive exportation, while but little is imported, and
                    the people of the humble class, not being able to supply their wants, as
                    heretofore, attribute this to foreign trade. Even higher and wealthier classes,
                    we are told, are generally not favorably disposed towards commerce, so that soon
                    there may be those who will condemn the abrogation of the prohibition of former
                    times and desire the re-establishment of the ancient law. We are informed, also,
                    that these results, following immediately upon the radical change of policy of
                    the government, have produced a very general uneasiness, which is increased by
                    referring to the stipulations in the treaties for the opening of the ports of
                    Hiogo and Neegata and the freedom of trade at Yedo and Osacca, in view of the
                    approach of the time when those franchises will be due by the effect of the
                    treaties with the United States, Great Britain, France, Prussia, Russia, and
                    Holland. We are informed that it would be a matter of great difficulty for the
                    government to exert its power and authority for the purpose of demonstrating the
                    benefits to be realized at some future day, and thus causing its subjects to
                    submit to the present uneasiness for some time longer. In reviewing the subject
                    in your despatch (No. 20) you observe that you have seen no reason to change
                    your own view of the expediency of consenting to a postponement of the opening
                    of the city of Yedo.</p>
                <p>You remark, also, that Osacca, being in the <hi rend="italic">Tien</hi> or
                    Heavenly district, where the Mikado or spiritual ruler of Japan resides, it is
                    probable a residence of foreigners there would be regarded with dislike by a
                    portion of the Japanese people; that Hiogo is simply the seaport of Osacca, and
                    its opening naturally depends on that of the city, while Neegata is a place of
                    minor consideration. Your argument on the subject concludes that the opening of
                    the Japanese commerce has temporarily produced a great increase in the cost of
                    subsistence of official persons enjoying fixed and limited incomes, while their
                    salaries have not yet been correspondingly increased. Upon the whole, you
                    suggest that discretionary power be given to you to act in concert with the
                    ministers of the other powers interested, in such manner as shall be most
                    advisable for the welfare of both countries.</p>
                <p>We are sensible of the very great perplexity of dealing with a government whose
                    constitution is so different from our own, and whose subjects have fixed
                    sentiments and habits so very peculiar. Moreover, we have the utmost confidence
                    in your ability and discretion, while we know that it might be hazardous to
                    every interest already secured to substitute a policy of our own, adopted at
                    this distance, for one which you find necessary on the spot.</p>
                <p>The President has, therefore, concluded to confer upon you the discretion
                    solicited by you. To make your way easier, this determination has not been
                    adopted without previous consultation here with the ministers before consulted,
                    who will, of course, communicate the result of the conference to their
                    respective governments. This proceeding will, for the present, suspend the plan
                    of a naval demonstration, before proposed by the United States. I must, however,
                    urgently insist that, except in the extremest necessity, you do not consent to
                    any postponement of any covenant in the existing treaty, without first receiving
                    satisfaction <pb facs="0886" n="816" xml:id="pg_816"/> of some marked kind for
                    the great crime of the assassination of Mr. Heusken while in the diplomatic
                    service of the United States.</p>
                <p>We leave the form and mode of that satisfaction to your own discretion. It would
                    be best, if possible, to secure the punishment of the assassins. But
                    circumstances unknown to us must enter into the question and will modify your
                    action. The principle, however, seems to us too important to be abandoned. If
                    the western states can keep their representatives safely in Japan, they can,
                    perhaps, wait for the facilities stipulated; but if their ministers shall be
                    obliged by force or terror to withdraw, all will be lost that has, at such great
                    cost, been gained. The President acknowledges the letter of the Tycoon, and I
                    reply briefly to the ministers for foreign affairs. Those replies accompany this
                    despatch.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Townsend Harris,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c., Yedo.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
