<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1862-07-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1862-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="92" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d92">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Adams</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 288.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-07-07"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 7, 1862.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I fear that the press, speaking as it does
                            under the influence of a hundred various forms of excitement arising out
                            of the incidents of the last ten days, will bewilder, if it does not for
                            the moment confound, our representatives abroad.</p>
                        <p>The military situation is, however, clearly intelligible, and ought to be
                            satisfactory to the cool and candid judgment of the country.</p>
                        <p>From the Mississippi we learn that after a long and vigorous bombardment
                            of Vicksburg, Commodore Farragut passed the batteries at that place from
                            below, and joined himself to the fleet which lay above it. Thus the last
                            obstacle of the navigation of the Mississippi has been overcome, and it
                            is open to trade once more under the flag of the Union from the
                            headwaters of its tributaries near the lakes and Prince Rupert’s Land to
                            the Gulf of Mexico.</p>
                        <p>White river and the Yazoo have been cleared of all hostile armaments. We
                            have a rumor that Vicksburg has actually been taken. But the report is
                            premature, although we have no doubt but the capture has, before this
                            time, occurred.</p>
                        <p>The fleet under Commodore Goldsborough has been efficient in seizing and
                            bringing into port many British vessels carrying contraband, and insured
                            at Lloyd’s against the perils of the blockade. So that it may be
                            expected risks of this kind will sensibly diminish. On the coast all is
                            safe and well.</p>
                        <p>In the west General Halleck is pushing a force from Corinth eastward
                            without any show of organized resistance to capture Chattanooga, and
                            close the only remaining railroad communication between Richmond and the
                            valley of <pb facs="0195" n="125" xml:id="pg_125"/> the Mississippi.
                            This achievement will effect deliverance of Eastern Tennessee,
                            distinguished for its loyalty, and so crown the pacification of the
                            whole region west of the Alleghany mountains, north of Georgia and
                            Alabama, and south of the Ohio river. But it is the vicinity of Richmond
                            that has been the scene of military events of the intensest interest
                            during the last two weeks, and it is that quarter that now chiefly
                            engages the attention of the government.</p>
                        <p>General McClellan’s original design for the capture of Richmond embraced
                            a march up the peninsula from Fortress Monroe and Yorktown, supported by
                            naval forces on both the York and the James river. The sudden appearance
                            of the Merrimack, with her terrible power of mischief, obliged him to
                            confine his march to the bank of the York river, with the aid of a fleet
                            in that river alone. He had, then, the Chickahominy, with its variable
                            flow, and its almost impassable swamps, between him and Richmond. The
                            Pamunkey, the chief tributary of the York, afforded him navigation only
                            to the White House, where he held his forces, twenty miles from
                            Richmond, without any other co-operation from our naval force on both
                            rivers there than protection they afforded to his rear. A large force
                            that was intended to be auxiliary to the army of the Potomac was
                            retained in front of Washington, necessarily, as it was thought, with a
                            view to the safety of the capital against forces sent to menace it from
                            Richmond. While General McClellan was thus obtaining a foothold on the
                            peninsula north of the Chickahominy, the insurgents succeeded in
                            obstructing the James river a distance of seven miles below Richmond,
                            and in constructing fortifications at Fort Darling, up a precipitous
                            elevation on the south bank of the James river, which rendered it
                            impossible for the fleet on that river to remove the obstructions
                            without the aid of a land force to carry that fort. General McClellan
                            was steadily, and, as it seemed, successfully, moving his army across
                            the Chickahominy to change his base to the James river, below Fort
                            Darling, on Wednesday last, when the insurgents concentrated large
                            forces upon what was yet the front of the moving column, and a series of
                            battles began which filled up seven successive days, at the end of which
                            the general, with his army, and substantially all his material, had
                            reached and established himself at Harrison’s Bar, upon the bank of the
                            James river, in full co-operation with the fleet of seventeen gunboats,
                            while the insurgents have not one man-of-war. This movement, which was a
                            meditated, prepared one, undoubtedly became a retreat when the enemy
                            pressed upon the withdrawing forces. The change of base involved a loss
                            of communication for a time between the army and the government and the
                            country. During this suspense, which lasted seven days, extravagant
                            reports of disasters and losses, and the wildest alarm for even the
                            safety of the army itself, obtained currency, and oppressed the public
                            mind. At length we have the results so far as they affect the military
                            situation. There have been immense losses, but more severe on the part
                            of the insurgents than on that of the Union. The efficiency of the army
                            of the latter is improved. That of the former, it is believed, is even
                            more reduced. Every one of the battles was a repulse of the insurgents,
                            and the two last, which closed the series, were decided victories. The
                            army of the Potomac is rapidly receiving reinforcements from several
                            sources, while the fleet is thought already equal in effect to an
                            additional army. General Pope, having taken command of all the troops in
                            Virginia, is pushing them forward from the north to cut off the railroad
                            communication beyond the Rappahannock, and threatens them on the
                            approach from the northwest. Within the next thirty days our navy,
                            already large, will receive an augmentation of ten new iron-clad
                            vessels, each equal to the Monitor. At the same time, the President,
                            upon the invitation of the <pb facs="0196" n="126" xml:id="pg_126"/>
                            governors of twenty of the thirty-four States, has called out three
                            hundred thousand men, a force amply sufficient to save all that has been
                            gained, and speedily close the civil strife.</p>
                        <p>You will read with interest and admiration General McClellan’s modest
                            conduct; his firm and decisive despatches and proclamation. The
                            government and popular bodies who have heretofore been so efficient in
                            filling up the armies are already in activity, and the prompt success of
                            the call is deemed assured. The destruction of human life which has
                            occurred is a sad and painful theme. But it brings its compensation in a
                            military and in a political view—aspects in which it is now our stern
                            duty to contemplate it. The delusion that the soldiers of the Union
                            would not fight for it with as much courage and resolution as its
                            enemies will fight against it, has been one of the chief elements of the
                            insurrection. It has now been effectually dispelled.</p>
                        <p>Secondly. If, as fatalists argue, a certain quantity of human blood must
                            flow to appease the dreadful spirit of faction, and enable a
                            discontented people to recover its calmness and its reason, it may be
                            hoped that the needful sacrifice has now been made.</p>
                        <p>Thirdly. If the representative parties had now to choose whether they
                            would have the national army where it is and as it is, or back again
                            where it was and as it was, it is not to be doubted that the insurgents
                            would prefer to it the position and condition on the Pamunkey, and the
                            friends of the Union the one now attained on the bank of the James.</p>
                        <p>Fourthly. The insurgents and the world abroad will see that the virtue of
                            the people is adequate to the responsibilities which Providence has cast
                            upon them.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>