<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Switzerland ( (Huddle) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d194</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">194</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-02-14T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-02-14T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recZobsyHhwdJPklD" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085246"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Occupied territory</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-02-14T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-02-14T10:00:00-05:00" n="194"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d194">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">340.1115A/2440: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Huddle</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bern</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-02-14T16:00:00+01:00"
                            >February 14, 1942—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 11:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>591. American Interests—Welfare. Department’s 354, February 6, 6 p.m. On request
                    of Consul Squire at Geneva by Legation, Vice Consul Elting and House
                        Amcross<note n="21" xml:id="d194fn21">American Red Cross.</note>
                    representative interviewed Inter Croix Rouge<note n="22" xml:id="d194fn22"
                        >International Committee of Red Cross Societies at Geneva.</note> officials
                    February 12 to ascertain willingness Inter Croix Rouge make welfare inquiries
                    relating Americans throughout Axis territory. Report summarized as follows.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Inter Croix Rouge entirely agreeable and prepared receive and make
                        inquiries through Red Cross societies in Axis territory.</item>
                    <pb facs="0274" n="262" xml:id="pg_262"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Amcross may forward inquiries direct following procedure employed on past
                        occasions since outbreak war.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Preferable make inquiries only by telegraph for time being because mail
                        difficulties and delays particularly for Far East. Amcross apparently
                        handling matter payment telegraphic charges through House.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Inter Croix Rouge suggests only straight whereabouts and welfare inquiries
                        be undertaken at present so greater number may be handled and replies
                        obtained more promptly. When procedure functioning smoothly transmission
                        brief personal messages may be undertaken.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In view of Swiss Foreign Office position indicated Legation’s 257, January
                        14 [<hi rend="italic">24</hi>] and, with respect to Far East inquiries, of
                        Japanese authorities’ refusal, as reported by Legation, to permit Swiss
                        representatives make inquiries and communicate on American matters in
                        Japanese occupied territory, Inter Croix Rouge seems only channel for making
                        American welfare inquiries. Elting and House believe there will be no delay
                        in clearing inquiries in and out of Inter Croix Rouge Geneva office. Inter
                        Croix Rouge officials stated their channels communication through own
                        delegates and various national Red Cross societies in Axis territory must be
                        considered more effective than any other possible channels and that
                        promptness obtaining replies naturally varies from country to country with
                        certain amount delay to be expected at least at the outset.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Legation has communicated with Swiss Foreign Office as directed in
                        Department’s 354 and using discretion given it therein will refer to Swiss
                        Government or Inter Croix Rouge inquiries received, endeavoring decide each
                        case which channel offers best facilities.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Huddle</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
