<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-12-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-12-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">125.0040/86: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Chargé in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Huddle</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-12-30">December 30, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>427. American interests. Your undated 449, received December 27.<note n="11" xml:id="d226fn11">Not printed; it reported that the
                                    Legation had requested the Foreign Office to endeavor to obtain
                                    names of all American official personnel to be evacuated from
                                    Germany, Italy, Hungary, Rumania, and Bulgaria.</note></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>This Government would be grateful if Swiss Government would
                                    obtain such lists wherever American official personnel is
                                    awaiting repatriation, including the Far East.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Lists should include diplomatic and consular officers; any
                                    other Government officers (specifying title of each); Government
                                    clerks and custodial personnel of American nationality; and
                                    American unofficial nationals of the following categories only:
                                    (A) such properly accredited representatives of the American Red
                                    Cross Society and their staffs as may wish to avail themselves
                                    of the facilities to be provided by the exchange agreements and
                                    (B) properly accredited newspaper correspondents (including
                                    radio reporters and press photographers) and their
                                    staffs.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>After the name of each person, list such persons of the
                                    following categories in his or her household as will be included
                                    in the exchange: <list>
                                        <label>(A)</label>
                                        <item>Members of the family, stating the name and
                                            relationship of each and the age of each minor;
                                            and</item>
                                        <label>(B)</label>
                                        <item>If they are American nationals: Members of the
                                            household staff, stating the name and position of
                                            each.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The Department wishes also to receive for its consideration
                                    the names of such persons of the following categories as might
                                    wish to be included in the exchange, each name to be followed by
                                    the list specified above in numbered paragraph 3: <list>
                                        <label>(A)</label>
                                        <item>Persons mentioned in numbered paragraphs 2 and 3 who,
                                            when hostilities commenced, were visiting in or
                                            traveling through the territories in question.</item>
                                        <label>(B)</label>
                                        <item>Nationals of friendly countries who were employed in
                                            connection with the representation by the United States
                                            of foreign interests.</item>
                                        <label>(C)</label>
                                        <item>Persons not otherwise covered by this instruction but
                                            considered by American officers to be entitled to
                                            inclusion in the official group. In all such cases,
                                            reasons should be stated fully and nationality
                                            indicated.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Lists from the Far East should include the United States Court
                                    for China, Legation Guard, Marine detachments, and any other
                                    employees of the United States Government.</item>
                                <pb facs="0309" n="297" xml:id="pg_297"/>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Please also request that the Swiss Government be so good as to
                                    prepare and transmit through you to this Government analogous
                                    lists of all Latin American official groups to be included in
                                    the exchange.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>