<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Sweden ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d300</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">300</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-05-19T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-05-19T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-05-19T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-05-19T08:00:00-05:00" n="300"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d300">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">701.0090/71: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-05-19T14:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 19, 1942—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 19—1:01 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1222. Swedish Legation in Berlin has reported by telephone to Foreign Ministry
                    that this morning German officials stated they would agree to departure of <hi
                        rend="italic">Gripsholm</hi> on May 23 with passengers whose names they will
                    then have approved. They added, however, that they do not think that they will
                    have had time to approve all of the names which they have received especially
                    those from Denmark and Norway. Please instruct whether the Legation should
                    authorize the departure of the <hi rend="italic">Gripsholm</hi> on May 23
                    irrespective of whether all names submitted by it to the Germans have been
                    approved.</p>
                <p>This Legation has submitted names of Americans in Sweden and Finland only. It is
                    probable, however, that Nordis Bureau submitted through Swedish Traffic
                    Commission names of persons in Denmark desirous of leaving on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gripsholm</hi>. Names of Americans in Norway could only have been obtained
                    by the Berlin authorities from German officials in Norway.</p>
                <p>Should ship depart before approval is given to all of names submitted to Germans
                    considerable hardship will be caused to Americans from Finland who are leaving
                    that country today and will be stranded in Sweden if they cannot depart on <hi
                        rend="italic">Gripsholm</hi> without sufficient funds to proceed to the
                    United States via Lisbon.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
