<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="321" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d321">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">701.9411/1630: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Chargé in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Huddle</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-02-07">February 7, 1942</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>379. American interests—Far East. Your 45, January 5; 180, January
                                    17;<note n="16" xml:id="d321fn16">Telegram No. 180 not
                                    printed.</note> 203, January 20 and 320, January 30. Department
                                has received from Spanish Embassy in charge of Japanese interests in
                                continental United States a memorandum dated January 17, 1942
                                stating: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“A cable has been received from the Spanish Government
                                        expressing the desire of the Japanese Government that all
                                        Japanese diplomatic exchange negotiations be handled through
                                        our Representatives. This does not imply that the interests
                                        of the Japanese Government in other countries cannot
                                        continue being protected by Representatives of other
                                        Nations.</p>
                                    <p>The Spanish Embassy would be deeply obliged to the Department
                                        of State for taking this matter into consideration.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>In accordance with the foregoing Department on February 5 delivered
                                to Spanish Embassy Washington a memorandum reading as follows:
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Department of State has received memorandum no. 42 of
                                        January 6, 1942 and memorandum no. 58 of January 16 from the
                                        Spanish Embassy in charge of Japanese interests in the
                                        continental United States.<note n="17" xml:id="d321fn17">Neither printed; for contents, see telegrams No. 45,
                                            January 5, and No. 203, January 20, from the Chargé in
                                            Switzerland, <ref target="#pg_386">pp. 386</ref> and
                                                <ref target="#pg_388">388</ref>,
                                            respectively.</note> The Embassy’s first memorandum
                                        constitutes a <pb facs="0404" n="392" xml:id="pg_392"/>
                                        basic proposal of the Japanese Government for the exchange
                                        of Japanese and American official personnel arising from the
                                        outline of such a proposal contained in the Department’s
                                        note of December 13, 1941 (Department’s 290, December 13, to
                                        you) to the Swiss Minister at Washington, a copy of which is
                                        attached. The Embassy’s second memorandum under
                                        acknowledgment constitutes an expression of the views of the
                                        Japanese Government in respect of the detailed proposal of
                                        the United States Government for the exchange of Japanese
                                        and American personnel, (Department’s 405, December 26 to
                                        you), the text of which was conveyed to the Embassy by the
                                        Department’s note of January 7, 1942. The Department has
                                        received through Swiss channels and through the American
                                        Legation at Bern texts of communications addressed by the
                                        Japanese Government to the Swiss Legation at Tokyo in
                                        language substantially similar to that of the memoranda
                                        under acknowledgment.</p>
                                    <p>The Department further acknowledges the receipt of the
                                        Spanish Embassy’s memorandum no. 59 of January 17, 1942<note n="18" xml:id="d321fn18">Not printed.</note> setting
                                        forth the desire of the Japanese Government that all
                                        negotiations for the exchange of Japanese official personnel
                                        be conducted through the representatives of the Spanish
                                        Government without prejudice to the representation of
                                        Japanese interests by other neutral governments in other
                                        countries.</p>
                                    <p>From examination of the basic proposal of the Japanese
                                        Government and of the Japanese Government’s views with
                                        respect to the detailed proposal of the United States
                                        Government, the United States Government believes that an
                                        agreement has been reached in the matter of the exchange of
                                        Japanese and American official and other personnel.</p>
                                    <p>With a view to clarifying certain details of the matter and
                                        to providing for certain practical points, the United States
                                        Government makes the following observations:</p>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> I—<hi rend="smallcaps">Observations on Japanese Basic
                                            Proposal</hi></p>
                                    <p>The following observations are made by the United States
                                        Government in respect of the basic proposal of the Japanese
                                        Government set forth in the Embassy’s memorandum no. 42:</p>
                                    <p>1. The version of this proposal received through Swiss
                                        channels was transmitted as an annex to a note dated
                                        December 30 to the Swiss Legation at Tokyo from the Japanese
                                        Foreign Office containing the following four points: (Here
                                        were quoted the four points of the ‘Japanese note dated
                                        December 30’ quoted in your 45, January 5).</p>
                                    <p>In respect to the third quoted paragraph above the United
                                        States Government observes that it has already taken steps
                                        looking toward the transportation to the United States of
                                        the Japanese official personnel in Hawaii. Upon arrival in
                                        this country these persons will be housed in an appropriate
                                        hotel pending their repatriation. It is assumed that the
                                        Japanese Government does not now raise any question
                                        regarding the repatriation of Japanese personnel in the
                                        Philippines. If this assumption is incorrect the Department
                                        would appreciate being informed of the views of the Japanese
                                        Government in the matter.</p>
                                    <pb facs="0405" n="393" xml:id="pg_393"/>
                                    <p>2. With respect to 1 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of the basic
                                        proposal of the Japanese Government this Government
                                        expresses its desire that all the persons referred to be
                                        included in the exchange. Furthermore, this Government
                                        expects that the Japanese Government will afford cooperation
                                        to the Thai and French authorities in providing facilities
                                        for transportation to the United States as part of the
                                        present exchange of American officials with their
                                        dependents, staffs and personal effects who are in Thailand
                                        and French Indochina. The French and Thai Governments are
                                        being informed of the wishes of this Government in this
                                        respect and further that the Japanese Government is being
                                        requested to extend them such cooperation in the matter as
                                        may be possible.</p>
                                    <p>3. In regard to 1 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the United
                                        States Government is agreeable as stated in its detailed
                                        proposal to the inclusion in the exchange of press and Red
                                        Cross representatives with their dependents in addition to
                                        the official personnel of the several governments. The
                                        United States Government is, furthermore, agreeable to the
                                        repatriation of all other non-official persons referred to
                                        in this portion of the basic proposal of the Japanese
                                        Government subject to the capacity of the vessel to
                                        accommodate such persons after all official personnel has
                                        been accommodated. Should the Japanese Government desire a
                                        further repatriation of persons who cannot be accommodated
                                        on the vessel to be used at this time, the United States
                                        Government will give consideration to the matter.</p>
                                    <p>4. With reference to 2 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the United
                                        States Government is willing on the basis of reciprocity to
                                        permit persons who might be included in the exchange to
                                        remain in this country pending the rehabilitation of their
                                        health and the provision subsequently of facilities for
                                        their repatriation.</p>
                                    <p>5. In respect to 2 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) this Government
                                        prefers in order to insure that the exchange can be carried
                                        out with the minimum of complication that all officials who
                                        were at the time when Japan began hostilities against the
                                        United States en route to any posts or away from posts to
                                        which they were accredited be included in the block exchange
                                        and be repatriated with all other officials.</p>
                                    <p>6. In the absence of any objection on concrete grounds to the
                                        continued stay of specified individuals, the United States
                                        Government agrees to 2 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>).</p>
                                    <p>7. The United States Government agrees to the provisions of
                                        all three subsections of point numbered 3. The United States
                                        Government further proposes that the Portuguese Government
                                        shall be requested to act as guarantor for the execution of
                                        the exchange on Portuguese territory at Lourenço Marques.
                                        This Government is addressing a request in this sense to the
                                        Portuguese Government and hopes that the Japanese Government
                                        will make a similar request.</p>
                                    <p>8. With reference to 4 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the United
                                        States Government agrees that the persons to be included in
                                        the exchange will be granted all necessary facilities of
                                        whatever description for taking with them a supply of funds
                                        which, without possibility of question, will be sufficient
                                        to meet all their needs on the ship and elsewhere until
                                        their arrival at the place of exchange. The necessary
                                        amounts may be subsequently determined on the basis of
                                        reciprocity and an expression of the views of the Japanese
                                        Government on this subject would be expected.</p>
                                    <pb facs="0406" n="394" xml:id="pg_394"/>
                                    <p>9. In regard to 4 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) this Government
                                        agrees that the officials to be exchanged and their
                                        dependents and their servants and their employees shall be
                                        permitted to bring with them all their personal effects
                                        including such things as silverware, linen and the like
                                        which can be packed in trunks, boxes with handles and
                                        handbaggage. Such effects will not be subject to search, be
                                        subject to any tax or duty nor subject to any limitations
                                        other than those imposed by availability of space on the
                                        vessel and the arrival of the effects at the port of
                                        embarkation in time to be laden aboard the vessel. This
                                        Government feeling that the character of the baggage is
                                        sufficiently established by the agreement between the
                                        governments does not consider that any individual
                                        declaration or even list of contents of the baggage is
                                        necessary. Should the Japanese Government feel such lists to
                                        be essential this Government will be forced to reconsider
                                        its entire position on this point. A statement of the
                                        Japanese Government’s concurrence in this position would,
                                        therefore, be appreciated.</p>
                                    <p>10. In compliance with the request made by the Japanese
                                        Government in 5 the United States Government is providing
                                        all necessary suitable facilities for the Japanese officials
                                        formerly accredited to the other American Republics which
                                        have broken relations with Japan, and to Canada, to embark
                                        on the exchange vessel. It is expected that the Japanese
                                        Government will act similarly in respect of American
                                        officials being repatriated from Thailand and French
                                        Indochina.</p>
                                    <p>The United States Government notes that certain of the former
                                        diplomatic and consular officials of Japan in other American
                                        Republics which have broken relations with or declared war
                                        upon Japan have apparently not received from their
                                        government instructions to proceed to this country for the
                                        purpose of being included in the exchange now being
                                        negotiated and are unwilling to accept offers made to them
                                        of facilities for the journey here. The Japanese Government
                                        should inform its officials in the other American Republics
                                        of its desire that they take advantage of the facilities now
                                        being negotiated and of the need that these persons depart
                                        promptly for the United States in order to be present when
                                        the exchange vessel departs.</p>
                                    <p>The United States Government is willing that a separate block
                                        exchange of non-American officials leaving Japan and
                                        Japanese officials leaving places outside the Americas shall
                                        take place at the same time and at the same port as the
                                        exchange of American and Japanese officials. It assumes that
                                        the Japanese Government will arrange the exchange of its
                                        officials in the Netherlands Indies in connection with the
                                        exchange it will arrange with other governments since it
                                        would seem for practical reasons that such Japanese
                                        officials might more suitably be brought to the port of
                                        exchange in such vessel as may bring there the Japanese
                                        officials from Australia and other British territory
                                        nearby.</p>
                                    <p>11. With respect to 6 the United States Government considers
                                        that misunderstanding might arise from designating as
                                        hospital ships under the Geneva Agreement of 1907<note n="19" xml:id="d321fn19"><ref target="frus1907p2#pg_903"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1907,
                                                pt. 2, p. 903</ref>.</note> the vessels to be used
                                        for the purpose of the exchange and assumes that the
                                        Japanese Government will select another method of marking
                                        the vessels. For its part the <pb facs="0407" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/> United States Government will mark
                                        distinctively the vessel to be used carrying Japanese
                                        official personnel and will communicate these markings to
                                        the Japanese Government in the near future. It is agreed
                                        that the markings of the vessels shall be such as to ensure
                                        the greatest possible visibility and that particulars of
                                        colors and markings shall be notified in due time before the
                                        departure on the voyage. The United States Government would
                                        wish to know, in addition to the data specified in 6 of the
                                        Japanese basic proposal, the speed of the vessels therein
                                        named.</p>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> II—<hi rend="smallcaps">Observations Upon Japanese Views
                                            Regarding the Detailed American Proposal</hi></p>
                                    <list>
                                        <label>12.</label>
                                        <item>With respect to 1 (1) and 1 (2) reference is made to
                                            item 7 in Part I above.</item>
                                        <label>13.</label>
                                        <item>With respect to 1 (3) and its subheadings see items 2
                                            and 3 above.</item>
                                        <label>14.</label>
                                        <item>The United States Government notes from 1 (4) that the
                                            Japanese Government agrees to include the personnel of
                                            the United States Court at Shanghai among the persons to
                                            be exchanged but that it does not agree to include the
                                            United States Marine Guards remaining in China. The
                                            United States Government may revert to this point at a
                                            later date.</item>
                                        <label>15.</label>
                                        <item>It is noted from 1 (5) that the United States consular
                                            officials at Hong Kong together with their staffs,
                                            dependents and servants will be included in the
                                            exchange. The United States Government expects that its
                                            other officials at Hong Kong as specified in a list
                                            transmitted to the Swiss representative at Tokyo through
                                            the Swiss Government as well as the other categories of
                                            persons mentioned in the first sentence of item 3 above
                                            will also be included.</item>
                                        <label>16.</label>
                                        <item>1 (6) regarding the provision of transportation
                                            facilities is understood to constitute acceptance of the
                                            proposal of the United States Government on this
                                            point.</item>
                                        <label>17.</label>
                                        <item>Except in so far as the proposal of the Japanese
                                            Government might call for the shipment of household
                                            effects not packed in boxes with handles, trunks or
                                            handbaggage coincidentally with the departure of the
                                            persons to be exchanged the United States Government
                                            considers that 1 (7) is a confirmation of its view in
                                            regard to the obligation of both governments to embark
                                            persons and things on the exchange vessels.</item>
                                        <label>18.</label>
                                        <item>1 (8) coincides with the views of the United States
                                            Government on this point.</item>
                                        <label>19.</label>
                                        <item>The United States Government notes in respect of 2
                                            that the Japanese Government agrees that the persons
                                            embarked on the vessel will be limited in respect of the
                                            personal effects accompanying them only by the space on
                                            the vessel and by the presence of the effects in time to
                                            be laden aboard.</item>
                                        <label>20.</label>
                                        <item>So far as concerns 3 the view of the United States
                                            Government regarding baggage declarations by officials,
                                            their dependents and staffs is set forth under item 9
                                            above. The United States Government perceives no
                                            objection to and will effect the lenient examination of
                                            the effects being taken with them by non-official
                                            persons who may be included in the official exchange.
                                            The question of the examination of the effects of
                                            non-official persons to be included in any subsequent
                                            phases of the exchange movement which may be arranged
                                            will be <pb facs="0408" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/> dealt
                                            with at another time. The persons of those to be
                                            exchanged will not be searched.</item>
                                        <label>21.</label>
                                        <item>The United States Government notes regarding 4 that
                                            the Japanese Government agrees to paragraphs 4 and 8 of
                                            the American basic proposal.</item>
                                        <label>22.</label>
                                        <item>Regarding 5 reference is made to items 2 and 16
                                            above.</item>
                                        <label>23.</label>
                                        <item>Concerning 6 reference is made to item 3 above.</item>
                                        <label>24.</label>
                                        <item>Concerning 7 the United States Government in order to
                                            facilitate the negotiations initiated by the Japanese
                                            Government with other governments and particularly the
                                            British Government and its associated Governments in
                                            Europe is providing the British Government with a copy
                                            of this reply and of the communications which have been
                                            exchanged through several channels with the Japanese
                                            government on this subject.</item>
                                        <label>25.</label>
                                        <item>There appears to be a meeting of views in respect of 8
                                            and 9.</item>
                                    </list>
                                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> III—<hi rend="smallcaps">Special Matters</hi></p>
                                    <p>The Government of the United States has received through
                                        Swiss channels information that the Japanese Government
                                        particularly wishes included in the exchange of official
                                        personnel the Japanese diplomatic and consular personnel in
                                        Iran and the eastern part of Samoa.</p>
                                    <p>The United States Government is ready to take all possible
                                        steps to facilitate the inclusion in the exchange of
                                        Japanese official personnel from the Americas and from
                                        insular possessions of the United States. It is not, however
                                        in a position to afford any physical assistance for the
                                        inclusion in the exchange of Japanese official personnel in
                                        other areas as, for example, Iran. It is assumed that the
                                        Japanese Government will be able to make arrangements for
                                        the travel to the exchange point of Japanese official
                                        personnel in Iran through the medium of the powers
                                        representing Japanese interests in intervening territories
                                        or that alternatively the Japanese Government will be able
                                        to arrange for the repatriation of this personnel through
                                        Soviet territory. So far as concerns those parts of the
                                        Samoan Islands which are under the jurisdiction of the
                                        United States this Government is unaware of the presence
                                        there of any Japanese official personnel. It would
                                        appreciate being informed further in the matter.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>Please request Swiss Government to provide full text of this reply to
                                Swiss Minister at Tokyo and to ask him to keep all other Swiss
                                representatives in the Far East fully informed in the matter.
                                Department stresses fact that it wishes to be informed as soon as
                                possible of additions or amendments to lists of officials and
                                newspaper correspondents which have already been provided the Swiss
                                Government through you and that it desires to receive at earliest
                                opportunity lists of non-official persons in the Far East who will
                                be repatriated under point 3 of the foregoing memorandum to the
                                Spanish Embassy. It is hoped that the Swiss representatives will
                                confer closely with Department’s officers in regard to these lists
                                and that they will transmit to Department any comments which may be
                                made by those officers <pb facs="0409" n="397" xml:id="pg_397"/>
                                regarding the lists or those details of the exchange arrangement
                                which have not yet been agreed upon.</p>
                            <p>Spanish Embassy’s memorandum of January 6 was identical with “Annexed
                                Note” quoted in your 45, January 5 with addition of following
                                paragraph: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“For the purpose of exchange and in accordance with the
                                        Geneva agreement of 1907, the Japanese Government appoints
                                        the following ships to serve as hospitals: <list>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic">Hicawe Maru</hi>—11,621 tonnage,
                                                155.9 length, two masts, two chimneys.</item>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic">Tacasgo Maru</hi>—9347 tonnage,
                                                length 142.09, two masts, two chimneys.</item>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic">Ahahi Maru</hi>—9326 tonnage,
                                                length 147.22, one chimney, two masts.</item>
                                        </list></p>
                                    <p>These ships have the following marks in common: Whole hull
                                        painted white, Red Cross emblem, upper part of hull supplied
                                        with electricity, Red Cross on port and starboard center of
                                        hull, green line running all along hull, in accordance with
                                        Convention regulations. Chimney bears Red Cross electrically
                                        outlined, and searchlights mark the flag-case or post of
                                        signals.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>Spanish Embassy memorandum of January 16 was identical with text
                                quoted in your 203, January 20 with slight differences in numbers of
                                heading and in phraseology not affecting the meaning of the
                                communication.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>