<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Spanish Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d379</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">379</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="379"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d379">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">390.1115A/1406</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Spanish Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 511</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Spanish Embassy in Washington in charge of Japanese interests in the United
                    States, present their compliments to the State Department and beg to communicate
                    that the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Madrid has informed that the United
                    States Government, through the Swiss Minister at Tokio, recently requested the
                    Imperial Japanese Government to state whether this Government had discarded the
                    idea of a second trip of the <hi rend="italic">Gripsholm</hi> asserting that in
                    what it concerned the American Government, its point of view on the matter had
                    not changed.</p>
                <p>The Imperial Japanese Government further informs that, after a perusal of the new
                    list of repatriations presented by the United States Government, it appears as
                    though the American Authorities had not taken the necessary interest in locating
                    the Japanese included in the list of priorities arranged by the Japanese
                    Government, adding that, in the Memorandum from the State Department<note n="72"
                        xml:id="d379fn72">Dated November 3, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> the
                    suggestions on the exchange made by the Japanese Government do not seem to have
                    been taken into consideration.</p>
                <p>Consequently, the Imperial Japanese Government does not think it possible to come
                    to an agreement on the projected second voyage of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gripsholm</hi>, if the Government of the United States does not clarify its
                    attitude on the points of reference.</p>
                <p>The Spanish Embassy would greatly appreciate the State Department’s consideration
                    of this matter, as well as a reply on it which can be transmitted to the
                    Imperial Japanese Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-16">December 16,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
