<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Gauss) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d509</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">509</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-03-10T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-03-10T01:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-03-10T01:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-03-10T01:00:00-05:00" n="509"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d509">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Pacific War/2101: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gauss</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-03-10T13:00:00+07:00"
                            >March 10, 1942—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 8:11 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>211. Reference my 144, February 23 [<hi rend="italic">22</hi>], 1 p.m.<note
                        n="29" xml:id="d509fn29">Not printed.</note> In an informal conversation
                    last evening with the Generalissimo<note n="30" xml:id="d509fn30">Chiang
                        Kai-shek.</note> I inquired whether he could tell me anything of his
                    estimate of the situation as he found it in India. He replied in effect that he
                    is greatly worried over that situation, that the British Government is blind to
                    the realities, and that he feels that the outcome may be serious for Britain in
                    India and at the same time for China. He added later that a radical change of
                    British policy toward India might possibly solve the situation but repeated that
                    the British Government is blind to the seriousness of the situation. He
                    commented that it was significant that the last remark made by former Ambassador
                    Clark Kerr as Chiang left Delhi was: “Do you think we are about to collapse” (in
                    India). Without saying so, Chiang inferred to me that he fears a collapse.
                    Chiang says he intends to write to the President on the India situation. He
                    asked that what he had told me be considered strictly confidential and not be
                    made known to others. I so request. He said that he had not realized the true
                    situation in India before his visit there.</p>
                <p>Earlier in the evening he made two remarks with a considerable show of
                    irritation: (1) The British do not inform their allies when they withdraw or
                    surrender, and (2) the British will not receive his Chinese staff officers. I do
                    not fully understand the last remark unless it relates to Burma where Chinese
                    forces have been sent to cooperate with the British. Madame Chiang in
                    translating made the remark that British strategy is always “super secret.”</p>
                <p>I have never previously seen the Generalissimo as depressed as I found him last
                    evening.</p>
                <p>During conversation with Madame Chiang who freely discussed her impressions of
                    the visit to India she made the remark that the Indians would not be satisfied
                    with dominion status, that unlike other dominions the Indians have no feeling of
                    racial affinity or common destiny with respect to the English and that although
                    realizing that perhaps independence cannot come immediately they seek and should
                    be given real political power and responsibility. She stated her opinion <pb
                        facs="0627" n="615" xml:id="pg_615"/> that the Indians are prepared to
                    discharge such responsibility to the benefit of the United Nation[s] Front.</p>
                <p>There is open anger owing [<hi rend="italic">in?</hi>] criticism of Britain in
                    Chinese official and other circles here.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gauss</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
