<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1942v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d568</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">568</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-06-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-06-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="568"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d568">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">845.00/1363</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-15">June 15,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Agent General for India, Sir Girja Shankar Bajpai, called at his request. I
                    inquired about the general trend of world affairs as they affected his country.
                    He replied that the United States’ victories in the Coral Sea and at Midway had
                    very much heartened the people of his country and that the morale had definitely
                    improved. I then proceeded to make several inquiries of him. First, I asked him
                    the size of the Indian Army. He replied that there were 750,000 men in the Army,
                    of which 250,000 were well trained and good fighting troops. He added that they
                    were without airplanes and sufficient <pb facs="0683" n="671" xml:id="pg_671"/>
                    tanks, et cetera, et cetera, leaving the impression that they were not in a
                    state of military preparedness to fight effectively. I then inquired as to how
                    soon they could get ready to make a real fight if they were so disposed. He
                    parried the question by falling back on the 250,000 men who he said could fight
                    almost any time and by referring also to the fact that his country had sent some
                    twenty odd divisions abroad to fight in Africa, Syria, Iran, Iraq and one
                    division to defend Singapore.</p>
                <p>I asked him pointblank as to what were the real points on which Cripps and the
                    Indian officials and leaders clashed with the resultant collapse of the
                        Mission.<note n="88" xml:id="d568fn88">For correspondence on the Cripps
                        Mission to India, see <ref target="#pg_619">pp. 619</ref> ff.</note> He said
                    that one point was that political leaders said that since Great Britain had
                    assumed responsibility for the protection of India and since they were looking
                    forward to freedom at no distant date, they felt that it was Britain’s
                    responsibility to furnish protection. The second point that governed the
                    situation was that the British, while proposing at the end of the war to place
                    India on all fours with other self-governing dominions in the British Empire,
                    insisted that all treaties existing between States in India and the Central
                    Government should not be breached unilaterally. This was understood to be in
                    deference to the Indian Princes who had supported the British Government in
                    carrying on the war. He said this latter was the biggest cause of the breakdown
                    of the Cripps Mission. I inquired whether a difference of opinion about who
                    should dominate the military operations of India against the Axis nations was
                    not another controlling factor. He replied that in his judgment it was not; that
                    the British agreed that the Indian officials could have complete control of all
                    military forces and supplies, et cetera, so far as the internal situation was
                    concerned, but that when it came to directing military forces externally against
                    the Axis powers the British were to have supreme command in the person of
                    General Wavell. To the objection of the Indian leaders that India should have a
                    greater voice in the conduct of the war the British reply was that an Indian
                    official was on their Supreme War Council exactly as were an Australian, a
                    Canadian and a South African official.</p>
                <p>I inquired about the future situation and stated that Gandhi is evidently doing
                    all in his power to play into the hands of the Japanese by preaching
                    non-resistance and that no practical steps of resistance were being advocated by
                    the other leaders, including Nehru. He said that the first step would be to
                    supply India with tanks and airplanes and that this would take care of the
                    situation against a possible Japanese attack which he did not anticipate within
                    the next few months. I inquired as to what strength and influence Gandhi is
                    exercising <pb facs="0684" n="672" xml:id="pg_672"/> to lead the Indian people
                    on the wrong course at this stage. He said that Gandhi did not have great
                    influence in spreading his doctrines but it was only when he would go to a given
                    city, such as Calcutta, and Bombay, and call on the people to adopt his policy
                    of non-resistance that his influence would be heavy. To this I replied that he
                    could within a short time go to the center of many of the most populous areas
                    and get in deadly results by his preachments. To this nothing was said in
                    reply.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C[<hi rend="smallcaps">ordell</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ull</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
