<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-06-21T02:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-06-21T02:30:00-05:00" n="573" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d573">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">845.01/210: Telegram</note>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The Officer in Charge at New Delhi</hi>
                                        (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Merrell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                                Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-06-21T13:00:00+05:30">June 21, 1942—1
                                            p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 1:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>405. Following is full text which will not be published of Gandhi
                                    letter to Chiang Kai-shek as requested in your number 292 of
                                    June 19, 6 p.m.<note n="91" xml:id="d573fn91">Not
                                        printed.</note>
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“Sevagram, Wardha C. P. June 14, 1942.</p>
                                        <p>Dear Generalissimo, I can never forget the 5 hours’ close
                                            contact I had with you and your noble wife in Calcutta.
                                            I had always felt drawn towards you in your fight for
                                            freedom, and that contact and our conversation brought
                                            China and her problems still nearer to me. Long ago,
                                            between 1905 and 1913, when I was in South Africa, I was
                                            in constant touch with the small Chinese colony in
                                            Johannesburg. I knew them first as clients and then as
                                            comrades in the Indian passive resistance struggle in
                                            South Africa. I came in touch with them in Mauritius
                                            also. I learnt then to admire their thrift, industry,
                                            resourcefulness and internal unity. Later in India I had
                                            a very fine Chinese friend living with me for a few
                                            years and we all learnt to like him.</p>
                                        <p>I have thus felt greatly attracted towards your great
                                            country and, iii common with my countrymen, our sympathy
                                            has gone out to you <pb facs="0687" n="675" xml:id="pg_675"/> in your terrible struggle. Our
                                            mutual friend Jawaharlal Nehru, whose love of China is
                                            only excelled if at all by his love of his own country,
                                            has kept us in intimate touch with the developments of
                                            the Chinese struggle.</p>
                                        <p>Because of this feeling I have towards China and my
                                            earnest desire that our two great countries should come
                                            closer to one another and cooperate to their mutual
                                            advantage, I am anxious to explain to you that my appeal
                                            to the British power to withdraw from India is not meant
                                            in any shape or form to weaken India’s defence against
                                            the Japanese or embarrass you in your struggle. India
                                            must not submit to any aggressor or invader and must
                                            resist him. I would not be guilty of purchasing the
                                            freedom of my country at the cost of your country’s
                                            freedom. That problem does not arise before me as I am
                                            clear that India cannot gain her freedom in this way,
                                            and a Japanese domination of either India or China would
                                            be equally injurious to the other country and to world
                                            peace. That domination must therefore be prevented and I
                                            should like India to play her natural and rightful part
                                            in this.</p>
                                        <p>I feel India cannot do so while she is in bondage. India
                                            has been a helpless witness of the withdrawals from
                                            Malay, Singapore and Burma. We must learn the lesson
                                            from these tragic events and prevent by all means at our
                                            disposal a repetition of what befell these unfortunate
                                            countries. But unless we are free, we can do nothing to
                                            prevent it, and the same process might well occur again,
                                            crippling India and China disastrously. I do not want a
                                            repetition of this tragic tale of woe.</p>
                                        <p>Our proffered help has repeatedly been rejected by the
                                            British Government and the recent failure of the Cripps
                                            Mission has left a deep wound which is still running.
                                            Out of that anguish has come the cry for immediate
                                            withdrawal of British power so that India can look after
                                            herself and help China to the best of her ability.</p>
                                        <p>I have told you of my faith in non-violence and of my
                                            belief in the effectiveness of this method if the whole
                                            nation could turn to it. That faith in it is as firm as
                                            ever. But I realize that India today as a whole has not
                                            that faith and belief, and the Government in Free India
                                            would be formed from the various elements composing the
                                            nation.</p>
                                        <p>Today the whole of India is impotent and feels frustrated
                                            (the Indian Army consists largely of people who have
                                            joined up because of economic pressure). They have no
                                            feeling of a cause to fight for, and in no sense are
                                            they a national army. Those of us who would fight for a
                                            cause, for India and China, with armed forces or with
                                            non-violence, cannot, under the foreign heel, function
                                            as they want to. And yet our people know for certain
                                            that India free can play even a decisive part not only
                                            on her own behalf, but also on behalf of China and world
                                            peace. Many, like me, feel that it is not proper or
                                            manly to remain in this helpless state and allow events
                                            to overwhelm us when a way to effective action can be
                                            opened to us. They feel, therefore, that every possible
                                            effort should be made to ensure independence and that
                                            freedom of action which is so urgently needed. This is
                                            the origin of my appeal to the British power to end
                                            immediately the unnatural connection between Britain and
                                            India.</p>
                                        <p>Unless we make that effort there is grave danger of
                                            public feeling in India going into wrong and harmful
                                            channels. There is every <pb facs="0688" n="676" xml:id="pg_676"/> likelihood of subterranean
                                            sympathy for Japan growing simply in order to weaken and
                                            oust British authority in India. This feeling may take
                                            the place of robust confidence in our ability never to
                                            look to outsiders for help in winning our freedom. We
                                            have to learn self-reliance and develop the strength to
                                            work out our own salvation. This is only possible if we
                                            make a determined effort to free ourselves from bondage.
                                            That freedom has become a present necessity to enable us
                                            to take our due place among the free nations of the
                                            world.</p>
                                        <p>To make it perfectly clear that we want to prevent in
                                            every way Japanese aggression, I would personally agree,
                                            and I am sure the Government of Free India would agree,
                                            that the Allied powers might, under treaty with us, keep
                                            their armed forces in India and use the country as a
                                            base for operations against the threatened Japanese
                                            attack.</p>
                                        <p>I need hardly give you my assurance that, as the author
                                            of the new move in India, I shall take no hasty action.
                                            And whatever action I may recommend will be governed by
                                            the consideration that it should not injure China, or
                                            encourage Japanese aggression in India or China. I am
                                            trying to enlist world opinion in favor of a proposition
                                            which to me appears self-proved and which must lead to
                                            the strengthening of India’s and China’s defence. I am
                                            also educating public opinion in India and conferring
                                            with my colleagues. Needless to say any movement against
                                            the British Government with which I may be connected
                                            will be essentially non-violent. I am straining every
                                            nerve to avoid a conflict with British authority. But if
                                            in the vindication of the freedom which has become an
                                            immediate desideratum, this becomes inevitable, I shall
                                            not hesitate to run any risk however great.</p>
                                        <p>Very soon you will have completed 5 years of war against
                                            Japanese aggression and invasion and all the sorrow and
                                            misery that these have brought to China. My heart goes
                                            out to the people of China in deep sympathy and in
                                            admiration for their heroic struggle and endless
                                            sacrifices in the cause of their country’s freedom and
                                            integrity against tremendous odds. I am convinced that
                                            this heroism and sacrifice cannot be in vain; they must
                                            bear fruit. To you, to Madam Chiang and to the great
                                            people of China, I send my earnest and sincere wishes
                                            for your success. I look forward to the day when a free
                                            India and a free China will cooperate together in
                                            friendship and brotherhood for their own good and for
                                            the good of Asia and the world.</p>
                                        <p>In anticipation of your permission, I am taking the
                                            liberty of publishing this letter in <hi rend="italic">Harijan</hi>.</p>
                                        <p>Yours sincerely, M. K. Gandhi.”</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Merrell</hi></signed></closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>