<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-08-08T00:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-08-08T00:30:00-05:00" n="596" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d596">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">845.00/1417: Telegram</note>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The Officer in Charge at New Delhi</hi>
                                        (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Merrell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                                Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-08-08T11:00:00+05:30">August 8, 1942—11
                                            a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 9:03 p.m.]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>578. If Government hoped that publication of Congress documents
                                    would produce in this country a typhoon of indignation against
                                    the Congress, it must be highly chagrined to find that it has
                                    only succeeded in producing a boomerang and in lowering itself
                                    still further in Indian public esteem at a moment when
                                    constructive statesmanship is the crying need of the hour.</p>
                                <p>The following is an extract from telegram received from the
                                    Consul at Bombay: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“Reports continue to reach me of the intensity of
                                            anti-British feeling throughout Bombay area. Shortages
                                            and high prices of foodstuffs and kerosene are
                                            contributing factors to this anti-British sentiment. If
                                            a civil disobedience campaign develops, these
                                            unfortunate economic factors will make start much worse.
                                            I must again point out that depth and intensity of
                                            anti-British feeling in western India can scarcely be
                                            overemphasized.” (Reference my 523, July 28, noon,<note n="28" xml:id="d596fn28">Not printed.</note> for
                                            situation in Bengal.)</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>Please telegraph whether recent statements of Gandhi and Nehru on
                                    publication of Congress documents and their speeches yesterday
                                    to All India Congress Committee have been published in American
                                    press. There is reason to think that some of the statements are
                                    being shortcircuited in London.</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Merrell</hi></signed></closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>