<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-10-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="624" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d624">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">845.24/237½</note>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                                        (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Acheson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                        Lend-Lease Administrator</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Stettinius</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-10-10">October 10,
                                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Ed</hi>: I have received your letter
                                    of August 19, 1942<note n="58" xml:id="d624fn58">Not
                                        printed.</note> in which you refer to the final report of
                                    the American Technical Mission to India.<note n="58" xml:id="d624fn1">Not printed.</note> It is noted that before
                                    exploring the suggested projects with the Indian Supply Mission
                                    and with the British, you desire an expression of this
                                    Department’s views with regard to the current Indian
                                    situation.</p>
                                <p>As you are no doubt aware, the Technical Mission proceeded to
                                    India under the auspices of the Department of State and at the
                                    invitation of the Government of India. The function of the
                                    Mission was to investigate and recommend ways and means by which
                                    the United States Government could assist in augmenting India’s
                                    war potentialities and to make general recommendation to the
                                    Government of India regarding wartime economic problems. In its
                                    work the Mission was concerned therefore only with the
                                    determination of such improvements in the Indian industrial
                                    set-up as might facilitate the war effort of the United Nations.
                                    It appears that the Mission in its recommendations has not
                                    diverged from this conception of its duties, and unless agencies
                                    of the Government possessing the requisite technical knowledge
                                    conclude that the implementation of any of the Mission’s
                                    recommendations would not result in an increase in the
                                    effectiveness of the war effort, it is the opinion of this
                                    Department that in so far as the United States Government is
                                    concerned the desirability of implementing the program in toto
                                    is limited only by considerations of practicability, of military
                                    exigency, and of the industrial needs of the United States.</p>
                                <p>In so far as the practicability of the various individual
                                    recommendations is concerned, the Office of Lend-Lease
                                    Administration, the Board of Economic Warfare, the War Shipping
                                    Administration, and similarly interested agencies will naturally
                                    make the decisions. Decision regarding expediency from the point
                                    of view of the industrial needs of the United States must of
                                    course likewise be made by the various civilian agencies
                                    concerned.</p>
                                <p>The military aspects of the problem will of course require
                                    decision by the War Department and by the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
                                    involving as they do not only the question of the defense of
                                    India as a whole, <pb facs="0752" n="740" xml:id="pg_740"/> but
                                    also the extent to which fighter plane protection can be
                                    anticipated for the vulnerable areas in which the erection of
                                    certain of the new installations is contemplated. It is
                                    understood that the War Department and the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                                    are now considering the report, and that an indication may be
                                    expected shortly of their decision with regard to the
                                    advisability of implementing or attempting to implement the
                                    various recommendations, in so far as the military side of the
                                    question is concerned.</p>
                                <p>It is, I may add, the hope and anticipation of this Department
                                    that, military developments permitting, India will become an
                                    increasing source of supply for products necessary to the
                                    prosecution of the war in the near eastern and far eastern
                                    areas. This Department is in favor of the allocation to India of
                                    all materials beneficial in this regard in so far as may be
                                    deemed advisable and possible by your organization and other
                                    interested agencies of the Government. It is hoped that pending
                                    advice from the War Department and the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
                                    the other agencies of this Government will examine the
                                    individual items recommended in the Mission’s report with a view
                                    to making their own decision in so far as the problems involved
                                    come within the scope of their responsibility.</p>
                                <p>The final action to be taken by this Government, unless entirely
                                    negative decisions are reached in the matter, will of course
                                    depend upon the reaction of the Governments of India and the
                                    United Kingdom to the several recommendations. While those
                                    Governments have indicated their complete sympathy with the work
                                    and recommendations of the Mission in principle, their attitude
                                    toward the individual items recommended has not yet been
                                    announced.</p>
                                <p>I may add that, as we are all well aware, the political situation
                                    in India is extremely delicate and any activities in the
                                    economic sphere can easily have political ramifications. I am
                                    sure you will agree in that connection that any representatives
                                    of your organization who may serve in India should keep in
                                    unusually close touch with the American Mission at New Delhi and
                                    that the greatest care must be taken by all American agencies
                                    concerned to insure that undesirable political repercussions do
                                    not ensue from the manner in which India’s supply questions are
                                    handled.</p>
                                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dean
                                    Acheson</hi></signed></closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>