<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="116" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                        <head>116. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d116fn0">Source: Department of State, Conference Files: Lot
                                64 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 560, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 1473. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1959-09-18">September
                                    18, 1959</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS<note n="1" xml:id="d116fn1">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MMA1">Menshikov</persName> was not listed among
                                    the participants, presumably in error.</note></head>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Henry Cabot Lodge</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAY1">Gromyko</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Troyanovski</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AA1">Akalovsky</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Trip from Hyde Park</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>On the way from the museum to Mrs. Roosevelt’s cottage I told Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> that in accordance
                            with his wishes arrangements had been made for a ride through Harlem
                            upon our return to New York City, to be followed by a ride on the
                            subway. I mentioned that the ride through Harlem would take 20 to 25
                            minutes.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MMA1">Menshikov</persName> then engaged
                            in a conversation with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>, whereupon he told me that in view of the
                            short time left before Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s appearance at the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                            wanted to go directly back to the hotel after the visit to the
                            cottage.</p>
                        <p>I replied that this was all right with me but that the Harlem visit had
                            been scheduled to meet his own request.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_MMA1">Menshikov</persName> then said that the time
                            scheduled was inconvenient and that therefore the ride had to be
                            canceled. He implied that the time had been selected on purpose so as to
                            make it difficult to have the ride because I did not want Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> to see Harlem. I objected to
                            his <pb facs="0455" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/> remark very strongly,
                            saying that it had been he who had requested the ride yesterday and that
                            now that his request had been fulfilled, I did not want him to say to
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> that I prevented
                            him from seeing things he wanted to see. I said this rather sharply in
                            order to let him know that I was aware of his attempts to misrepresent
                            various situations to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>.</p>
                        <p>He asked me not to raise my voice and I apologized for raising my
                            voice.</p>
                        <p>On the way back to New York City Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> and I had conversations on a variety of
                            subjects. Touching upon the subject of missiles Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> spoke very highly of his
                            scientists and engineers and, without mentioning his name, referred to
                            one young scientist in particular who had perfected a rocket that had
                            hit the bull’s eye on its first flight. The reason for that was that
                            this particular engineer had developed an engine that had performed
                            excellently during its very first test on the platform, while many other
                            types of rocket engines had exploded during their first tests and had to
                            be perfected in the course of subsequent tests. This achievement, Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> said, had reduced
                            the period required for the development of that particular rocket by two
                            years.</p>
                        <p>I said that I was aware of the high level of technological skills in the
                            Soviet Union and expressed my hope that both in our country as well as
                            in the Soviet Union, those skills would be devoted to peaceful ends
                            rather than to the production of means of war. I said that I was looking
                            forward to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s
                            forthcoming speech in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> where he
                            said he would make new disarmament proposals. I asked him whether the
                            proposals would be something entirely new, rather than based on the
                            Soviet proposals made in the past.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> replied that I
                            should be patient and wait until he made his speech. He indicated,
                            however, that he was going to introduce very broad proposals, which
                            would test the sincerity of the United States’ approach to the question
                            of disarmament.</p>
                        <p>I assured him that the United States was as anxious to achieve real
                            disarmament as any state in the world, provided it was under effective
                            control, so that all parties would be confident that neither side was
                            gaining a unilateral advantage.</p>
                        <p>I said then that out of the 500 foreign control post personnel envisaged
                            for control over a discontinuance of nuclear tests only 200 would be
                            American or British and that I could not see how the Soviet Union’s
                            security could be affected by such a small number of foreign personnel.
                            I also pointed out that these people would be stationed at control posts
                            and would not roam around the country.</p>
                        <pb facs="0456" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> said that he had
                            not followed the last stage of negotiations on nuclear tests very
                            closely and that therefore he did not know what the present respective
                            positions were.</p>
                        <p>I told him that our proposal was for one-third local control post
                            personnel, one-third <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and one-third from other countries. He
                            expressed the belief that agreement could be reached on this
                            subject.</p>
                        <p>I told him that if he and President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> during their talks would reach agreement on
                            the subject of nuclear tests, this would be a sign of confidence that
                            would be greatly encouraging.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> then said that he
                            was sorry the Soviet Union had accepted the U.S. proposal for nuclear
                            explosions for so-called peaceful purposes. He said that they would be
                            nothing but a continuation of testing because the only thing to be
                            tested was the device’s firing mechanism and that purpose could be
                            achieved through so-called peaceful explosions. In referring to Soviet
                            tests he said that each of the tests they had conducted had brought
                            about a decrease in the cost of production of nuclear weapons by 50%.
                            Therefore Soviet experts on atomic weapons were very anxious to continue
                            testing, but he had given them orders not to do so as long as the other
                            powers did not test. He also stated that the Soviet Union was not
                            interested in the production of so-called tactical nuclear weapons
                            because they were too expensive and also because strategic weapons could
                            be used much more effectively. He observed that the United States was a
                            very rich country and that perhaps for that reason it could waste money
                            on the development of tactical weapons. He also mentioned that the
                            Soviet Union had a number of new atomic devices ready for testing, but
                            repeated again that they would be kept in warehouses and not tested so
                            long as other countries did not test their devices.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>