<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>128. Memorandum of Conference With President Eisenhower</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v10p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d128</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">128</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-09-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recA0dBVr0ylL39Rv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Demarche</term>
                    <term ref="recTdbwPhSPuOaeNu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec5leqjXNtlx0kjy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85096156"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Outer space</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="128"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d128">
                <head>128. Memorandum of Conference With President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d128fn0">Source: Eisenhower Library, <persName
                            corresp="#p_WA2">Whitman</persName> File, DDE Diaries. Secret. Drafted
                        by <persName corresp="#p_GBGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName> on September
                        28.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1959-09-25">September 25, 1959</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>OTHERS PRESENT</head>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>, Ambassador
                            <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>, Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1"
                            >Merchant</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GBGAJ1">General
                            Goodpaster</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The President welcomed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>
                    back after his trip. He said he had read his reports with the greatest of
                        interest.<note n="1" xml:id="d128fn1">Copies of all of <persName
                            corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>’s memoranda of conversations with
                            <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> were sent to the White
                        House and are in the Eisenhower Library, <persName corresp="#p_WA2"
                            >Whitman</persName> File, International Series, or Staff Secretary
                        Records.</note> It seemed that the trip was going better all the while. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> confirmed that this was true,
                    after hitting bottom at Los Angeles. Leading to that were several incidents,
                    first the disrespectful and immature performance at the Press Club in
                    Washington, followed by heckling by a few drunks at the Economic Club session in
                    New York, and what was really a vulgar, even obscene show on the set in
                    Hollywood. The publicity people at the studio wanted pictures for promotional
                    purposes of the dancers with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    and quite obviously he was offended at this treatment of the Premier of
                    Russia.</p>
                <p>Although <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> had said he would arrange
                    for a trip to Disneyland, while on the plane, the Chief of Police of Los Angeles
                    said he would not accept responsibility after there was a tomato-throwing
                    incident coming in from the airport. <persName corresp="#p_GAY1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> presented his “demarche” to <persName corresp="#p_LHC1"
                        >Lodge</persName> at 2 AM and this was the low point of the trip. The
                    turning point came on the platform at Santa Barbara. Although the security
                    people <pb facs="0489" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> objected, Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> took responsibility for leaving the train
                    with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> and the crowds gave him a
                    very cordial reception. San Francisco was wonderful in every respect,
                    capitalizing on the poor performance at Los Angeles. The public were fine and
                    the President’s appeal had wide impact. Then there was a splendid day in Iowa.
                    Mr. <persName>Garst</persName> is a phenomenon in himself. Again there was an
                    excellent performance in Pittsburgh by Governor Lawrence<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d128fn2">David L. Lawrence, Governor of Pennsylvania.</note> who
                    strongly supported what the President is doing.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> said that from his week
                    of travel he had the clear conviction that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> is a remarkable, although very difficult, man. He
                    then gave a personality sketch of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>
                    spoke from notes which he will furnish as the basis for his oral report to the
                        President.<note n="3" xml:id="d128fn3">Not found.</note> He said that Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> has an open mind on some
                    things, although not on the Communist “religion.” He is a very good and
                    attentive listener. While he says that he saw nothing he did not know about on
                    the trip, it is obvious that it has had an impact on him. First, he better
                    understands the independent, separate nature of our local government. Second, he
                    is deeply impressed by much that he has seen—the condition and attitudes of our
                    people, our roads, automobiles, factories, etc. He was struck by the vitality of
                    our people. He probably does not now really think that the Soviets are likely to
                    surpass us, at least anytime soon.</p>
                <p>With regard to policy questions, it is clear that he wants peace and thinks that
                    Russia needs peace in order to do what he wants the nation to do. He thinks his
                    disarmament scheme has serious merit. He is ready to ease up on jamming of Voice
                    of America broadcasts, but will not allow appeals to rebel against the
                    government to be made to the Russian people. He is very correct and conventional
                    regarding China, but says no more than he absolutely has to say on this subject.
                    He seems ready to agree on an exchange of books. He also is agreeable to an
                    information questionnaire on national needs for internal security forces. He
                    seems to be ready to settle the lend-lease accounts. He is boastful of having
                    penetrated the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>. He says he has cut down the
                    number of Soviet Secret Police by 75%. He wants to trade jet planes with us, and
                    leave his TU–114 with us. (Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>
                    said it is having mechanical difficulties.) He is keenly interested in having a
                    treaty of peace and friendship with the United States. He is interested in
                    expanding trade and removing restrictions upon trade. He may gradually remove
                    some of the restrictions on travel within the Soviet Union, but should be
                    allowed to do this by himself, in his own time, without being pressed.</p>
                <pb facs="0490" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> said he hopes that the
                    atmosphere when <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> leaves will be
                    one of “let’s keep on talking.” It is important to decide whether the President
                    is going to Russia or not. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1"
                        >Thompson</persName> suggested that this should not be put on the basis of
                    making them pay some price to get the President to come. The President said he
                    would of course not do this, but would simply leave the timing uncertain. The
                    minimum in his mind is that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                    must make some proposal by which the world could understand that we are not to
                    have a catastrophe over Berlin.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> suggested that some time
                    the President should thank the Air Force, the railroads, the police and others
                    who had a hand in the arrangements for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> for the splendid work they did. At the same time he
                    thought we should make a study of our system of handling the visits of Chiefs of
                    State. This was too casual and decentralized. Mayors are much too independent to
                    leave to work matters out on their own. In fact, we should not rely heavily on
                    local politicians.</p>
                <p>The President recalled that no one had thought of taking <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> around on this kind of a trip when
                    the proposal was made. This was something he asked for. There is an obvious risk
                    since he is the embodiment of evil in the eyes of many people.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> said that some of the worst
                    difficulty came from the turmoil created by newsmen. They were all right at
                    fixed installations where they were kept under careful control, but where there
                    was movement in the open the situation was terrible.</p>
                <p>The President thought that if in his talks with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> they could get two or three significant things lined
                    up, he could then take <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> up to
                    his farm, giving no advance notice. He might even drop in with him at the Navy
                    football game, although this seemed unlikely.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> observed that
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> did not consult <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAY1">Gromyko</persName> in preparing his speeches. Rather he
                    called on his son-in-law and members of his personal staff; his daughters also
                    apparently had a hand in them. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1"
                        >Thompson</persName> said that <persName corresp="#p_MMA1"
                        >Menshikov</persName> was constantly feeding poison to <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> throughout the trip. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> confirmed this, saying that whenever
                    there was something that could be criticized, <persName corresp="#p_MMA1"
                        >Menshikov</persName> would do this. He also tried to keep <persName
                        corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> away from <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> but failed in this. The President agreed with this
                    judgment, indicating that he considers <persName corresp="#p_MMA1"
                        >Menshikov</persName> evil and stupid.</p>
                <p>The President said he is trying to get a central idea on which to base the
                    discussions. He thought he might say that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> has now had a good introduction to our country, and
                    that the big thing that he wants to know is whether <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> truly wants to promote the conditions that will bring
                    true peace and make it last, and not just spar for <pb facs="0491" n="457"
                        xml:id="pg_457"/> advantage in the discussions. If the former is true, while
                    we may have fluctuations in our relations and occasional difficulties, we can go
                    back to this principle and make progress. Under this concept, Berlin is just
                    something that they want, an advantage they are trying to gain. The President
                    said he would try to set some such pattern as this in the discussions this
                    evening.</p>
                <p>The President said he is considering going to church at 8:30 AM in Gettysburg. He
                    could be back at Camp David at 10:00. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> said that in the meantime Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        >Dillon</persName> could talk about trade questions with the Soviets.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> felt that <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> would probably not want to go to
                    church. He was offered the opportunity to do so on the trip, but said it would
                    be misunderstood.</p>
                <p>In commenting about Germany, the President noted that we have a treaty with West
                    Germany, and cannot of course keep him from having one with East Germany. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> said the real point is that he
                    cannot, by concluding a treaty, terminate our rights. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName> suggested asking <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> what he thinks the consequences of
                    such a peace treaty would be. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1"
                        >Merchant</persName> thought this would be a good way of bringing out that
                    he cannot sign away our rights. The President commented that if <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> could agree to let the German
                    question rest for three years while we go ahead with actions in other fields, we
                    may find that it becomes easier to solve. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> added that they must not push us on reducing troops or
                    curtailing our freedoms there in the meantime. The President asked whether there
                    would be any point in his taking this matter up with <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> alone. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> thought this was a promising thing to do. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> commented, however, that
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAY1">Gromyko</persName> had proved to be a good
                    influence on <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> during the trip.
                    He returned again to the subject of <persName corresp="#p_MMA1"
                        >Menshikov</persName>, indicating that <persName corresp="#p_MMA1"
                        >Menshikov</persName> had arranged the dinner last night<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d128fn4">See <ref target="#d127">Document 127</ref>.</note> directly
                    with Mr. <persName>Ridder</persName> of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                        Commerce</hi> and that the dinner had been a gross mistake, both because Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> was so tired and needed
                    the rest and also because it became the occasion for a couple of very unskilled
                    and rather stupid people to try to “bait” and heckle Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>.</p>
                <p>The President said he might start off by saying that he realized that there had
                    been some unpleasant incidents on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName>’s trip and that he is sorry for them. At the dinner
                    last night, people were picked to attend who had no more sense than to try to
                    needle him. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> said that the
                    trouble arose in several places where the group tried to treat Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> like a visiting lecturer rather than
                    the head of a powerful nation. He said that it is possible to reason with
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>, providing <pb facs="0492"
                        n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/> one approaches him correctly. The President
                    suggested that someone tell <persName corresp="#p_GAY1">Gromyko</persName> that
                    he feels we should not make Berlin the one thing that governs and controls our
                    entire relationship. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>
                    said that he believes <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> really
                    does want us to accept the status quo as the price of having peace. He thought,
                    therefore, that a good approach would be to say that the settlement of the cold
                    war does not remove the issue of Eastern Europe. The split of Germany is
                    dangerous. Regarding Eastern Europe, we have no thought of the use of force, but
                    we do hope that the governments there will become more responsive to the will of
                    their people. The President recalled that in 1952 he had said we would use all
                    peaceable means toward their liberation, and that he had confirmed that
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Foster Dulles</persName> agreed with this (after
                    some initial public confusion). The President asked whether he could call on
                    someone on the subject of disarmament to expound what we think about the matter
                    generally and about <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s
                        proposal.<note n="5" xml:id="d128fn5">See <ref target="#d117fn2">footnote 2,
                            Document 117</ref>.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> initially misunderstood and told the President what is
                    being prepared on the longer range basis. The President asked who would be ready
                    to talk on this tomorrow—who knows the details of <persName corresp="#p_KNS1"
                        >Khrushchev</persName>’s plan. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> commented on some elements of the plan—for example, that
                    no control machinery is provided for its early stage. However, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> did see an element of genuineness in
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s proposal. He hoped the
                    “Committee of Ten” of the United Nations could go into it very thoroughly and in
                        detail.<note n="6" xml:id="d128fn6">Reference is to the Ten-Nation
                        Disarmament Committee established by the U.N. General Assembly on September
                        10.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> said there is good prospect of
                    some agreement on exchanges and contacts, and on the peaceful application of
                    atomic energy. The President said he is rather dubious as to whether anything
                    can be done regarding outer space agreements. The President told the group that
                    the networks have indicated they would give him a half hour at 10:30 on Sunday
                        night<note n="7" xml:id="d128fn7">September 27.</note> if he found it
                    necessary, and that he could let them know as late as 7 P.M. on Sunday. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> thought it might be as well or
                    perhaps better simply to issue a statement by the President if one were needed.
                    He thought it is better not to have the notion of a “reply” speech hanging over
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s head. The President
                    said, however, that our people are worried, and he is anxious that they should
                    not have a wrong impression concerning the talks. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> also thought it would not look good to
                    say that we are holding time in reserve. The President emphasized that he has no
                    thought of letting this be known publicly.</p>
                <pb facs="0493" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"/>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> strongly recommended
                    holding a press conference next Tuesday to sum up and comment on the visit.<note
                        n="8" xml:id="d128fn8">For the transcript of Eisenhower’s press conference,
                        held on Monday (not Tuesday), September 28, see <hi rend="italic">Public
                            Papers of the Presidents of the United States: <persName
                                corresp="#p_EDD1">Dwight D. Eisen-hower</persName>, 1959</hi>, pp.
                        694–702.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> said he
                    hoped the President could then express appreciation to the people who helped on
                    the trip. The President asked that the State Department prepare a three-minute
                    statement he could read to open the press conference which he might decide to
                    hold on Monday.</p>
                <p>As the meeting broke up, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1"
                        >Thompson</persName> said he hoped the President might find an opportunity
                    to express awareness that <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> is
                    trying to raise the living conditions of his people.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">G.</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Brigadier General, <gloss target="#t_USA1">USA</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
