<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-09-08T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-09-08T09:00:00-05:00" n="164" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d164">
                        <head>164. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Soviet
                                Union</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d164fn0">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 611.61/9–860. Secret; Priority;
                                Limit Distribution.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-09-08T17:00:00+03:00">September
                                    8, 1960, 5 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>699. This morning when <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>
                            said he wished to speak personally, frankly and confidentially I could
                            of course not continue to take notes and he spoke rapidly in Russian
                            without translation. Following is therefore to best of my recollection
                            but should not be taken literally.<note n="1" xml:id="d164fn1">For
                                reports of the rest of <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Thompson</persName>’s conversation, see <ref target="#d162">Documents 162</ref>, <ref target="#d163">163</ref>, and <ref target="#d165">165</ref>.</note> In explaining why Soviet Union
                            did not intend war and believed world would eventually go Communist and
                            our grandchildren live under Communism, he said this was because Soviet
                            system was better and <pb facs="0587" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/> when
                            this was demonstrated even we would adopt it. He then launched into long
                            harangue, much of which along usual Communist lines. He referred to fact
                            that our steel mills were producing at only half capacity and said this
                            could never happen in Soviet Union and was fatal handicap to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. He had read statements by President
                            Truman about our rate of production<note n="2" xml:id="d164fn2">Not
                                further identified.</note> but said the high rate in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> at end war was due to necessity of
                            supplying war-torn countries. Now even Japan and Germany were able sell
                            in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> market. He was utterly convinced
                            Soviets would exceed our production per capita by 1970. He mentioned
                            unemployment in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and referred to his
                            conversation with American labor leaders in San Francisco.<note n="3" xml:id="d164fn3">See <ref target="#d122fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                    122</ref>.</note> He contemptuously referred to them as having
                            sold out to capitalism. He realized I would not agree with such
                            appraisal but that was his view. He referred to opportunities in Soviet
                            Union, citing his own case. He mentioned some figures regarding surplus
                            agricultural products in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and said
                            “Imagine what we could accomplish with our system if we had such
                            surpluses to dispose of” and then indicated they expected to achieve
                            them. He said he had read statements of American Congressmen and others
                            arguing against American tourists visiting Soviet Union and said it was
                            natural they would be favorably impressed by Soviet Union after picture
                            that had been painted for them. He said our two defectors<note n="4" xml:id="d164fn4">William H. Martin and Bernon F. Mitchell, both
                                former employees of the National Security Agency, announced their
                                defection to the Soviet Union in a news conference in Moscow on
                                September 6.</note> had been astounded at what they had seen of
                            Soviet Union and mentioned incidentally that they were intelligent
                            people and that Soviet Union had not known about them nor had any
                            responsibility for their defection. He said Francis Powers was also a
                            not unintelligent fellow and had been much impressed with what he had
                            been shown on trips around Moscow. He said in these circumstances how
                            could anyone in his right mind in Soviet Union want to settle matters by
                            war with awful destruction this would bring. He said I had lived in
                            Soviet Union now for three years and had seen with my own eyes progress
                            they had made. He observed that we often spoke of freedom under our
                            system but I surely had been able to see the extent to which people
                            enjoyed freedom in Soviet Union. He started to say I was free to go
                            anywhere I liked but then corrected this to Moscow and its environs. He
                            exuded confidence and it was impossible not to be convinced that he
                            genuinely believed what he was saying.</p>
                        <p>When he had finished this long discourse I pointed out he had covered a
                            large field and that his time was limited as this was his last day in
                            Moscow. I would therefore not deal with all points he had made. I said I
                                <pb facs="0588" n="554" xml:id="pg_554"/> was glad he believed they
                            could win through economic competition since this meant they did not
                            intend use force. I had no reason therefore to disabuse him of his
                            conviction but rather than argue some of the economic points he had made
                            I would send him two articles by American economists which would
                            summarize for him some thinking in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> on
                            question of economic competition. (I later sent him articles by Willard
                            Thorp and W. Rostow contained in part III of Joint Economic Committee of
                            Congress on comparisons of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and Soviet
                                economies.)<note n="5" xml:id="d164fn5">For the papers by Willard L.
                                Thorp, Merrill Center for Economics, Amherst College, and Walt W.
                                Rostow, economist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, see
                                Joint Economic Committee, Congress of the United States, <hi rend="italic">Comparisons of the United States and Soviet
                                    Economies: Papers Submitted to Panelists Appearing Before the
                                    Subcommittee on Economic Statistics</hi>, 86th Congress, 1st
                                Session (Washington: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1959), Pt.
                                III, pp. 571–608.</note> I said both our systems had strengths and
                            weaknesses. They frequently spoke of overtaking us in butter production
                            but we had all the butter we could use and why should we try to
                            out-produce them. Their rate of industrial production was higher than
                            ours but our system was geared to produce what we needed. He indicated
                            his agreement with this. I said however I wished particularly to draw
                            his attention to what I considered an error in their thinking; this was
                            their tendency to over-simplify question of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> motives in foreign relations. I said they tended to
                            interpret them entirely in terms of class warfare and this was quite
                            wrong. He had mentioned repeatedly monopoly capitalism and I said that
                            while profit motives could on occasion enter into these things, this
                            factor very minor. I said we were fully as confident as he was in our
                            system and would welcome peaceful competition to show which was
                            better.</p>
                        <p>Referring back to that part of his conversation which related to U–2, I
                            said one thing had very much struck me in what he said now and in many
                            previous statements by himself and others in Soviet Govt; that was
                            references to being treated as equals, humiliation, Soviet power, etc. I
                            said I knew there was never any intention to humiliate Soviet Union or
                            discount their power. I had lived long time in both countries and
                            thought to some extent I was in position to understand both points of
                            view. No question that both our peoples wanted peace and that neither
                            govt wanted war. Since each knew this true, each tended to regard his
                            own actions as purely defensive but this was not view taken by other
                            side. There was distrust, suspicion, and even fear on both sides and
                            this accounted for some actions of those responsible for security.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> repeated they desired
                            understanding and did not themselves intend do anything provocative, at
                            which point I again pressed for release of RB–47 fliers.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_TLE1"><hi rend="strong">Thompson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>