<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-08-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-08-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="165" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d165">
                        <head>165. Memorandum From the Director of the Arms Control and Disarmament
                            Agency (<persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Warnke</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d165fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                                Security Affairs, Staff Material, Agency File, Box 1, Arms Control
                                and Disarmament Agency: 8/77–2/78. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-08-01">August 1, 1977</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Report on Trilateral Consultations on a Comprehensive Test
                                Ban</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>We have recently concluded two weeks (July 13–27) of consultations with
                            the Soviets and British in Geneva on the question of a comprehensive
                            test ban. This initial round of trilaterals, like the bilateral
                            discussions held in Washington with the Soviets in June,<note n="2" xml:id="d165fn2">See <ref target="#d159">Document 159</ref>.</note>
                            was exploratory and somewhat tentative in nature. Nonetheless, the three
                            delegations proceeded quickly beyond a general discussion of objectives
                            and negotiating procedures to an intensive and highly purposeful
                            exchange of views on the major substantive issues.</p>
                        <p>The question of peaceful nuclear explosions (<gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>) was clearly the dominant issue of the round, and the
                            one which U.S. and Soviet positions diverged most sharply.<note n="3" xml:id="d165fn3">The Soviet position is discussed in telegram 6401
                                from Geneva, July 28; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770271–0123.</note> The Soviets devoted most of their energies to
                            making their case for a <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> exception,
                            and were reluctant to deal with other matters in comparable detail. All
                            three Delegations presently regard the <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> issue as, by far, the most serious obstacle to an
                            agreement. It could also become a critical bottleneck, with the So<pb facs="0417" n="386" xml:id="pg_386"/>viets unwilling to adjust their
                            positions on less central matters until the <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> issue is resolved.</p>
                        <p>Despite the concentration on <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>, the
                            initial round gave us an opportunity to probe Soviet thinking on the
                            other substantive matters covered in your instruction letter of July
                                11,<note n="4" xml:id="d165fn4">See Tab A, <ref target="#d163">Document 163</ref>.</note> including such verification measures
                            as secure, internal seismic networks and on-site inspections as well as
                            such political/legal issues as the adherence requirement for entry into
                            force, duration, and withdrawal provisions. Although the Soviets
                            consistently stood by the provisions of their draft <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> treaty covering these matters, the
                            consultations gave us a better impression of where they may eventually
                            be flexible.</p>
                        <p>The British were a positive factor in the talks, reinforcing our
                            positions effectively on key matters while taking exception with us
                            infrequently and only on minor issues. The Soviets see this as a
                            two-sided negotiation which, with the convergence of U.S.–U.K. positions
                            and close coordination between the U.S. and U.K. Delegation,<note n="5" xml:id="d165fn5">The U.S.–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                                discussions held before the trilateral talks are reported in
                                telegram 172338 to London, July 22; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770263–1012.</note> it really is.</p>
                        <p>Both the British and the Soviets expressed reluctance to accept our
                            suggestion that the first round of formal negotiations be held in London
                            this Fall. They both expressed a preference for Geneva on the ground
                            that their facilities in Geneva were more adequate for their
                            purposes.</p>
                        <p>The three Delegations have agreed to resume the trilaterals in Geneva on
                            October 3 and to remain in close contact during the interval preceding
                            the next round.</p>
                        <p>The following is a summary of the major issues covered during the initial
                            round of trilaterals.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Peaceful Nuclear Explosion</p>
                        <p>Discussions on <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss> focused on two
                            principal questions; whether it is possible to carry out PNEs without
                            acquiring military benefits and whether non-proliferation objectives
                            would best be served by a <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> ban or a
                                <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> accommodation.</p>
                        <p>On the first question, we explained in detail our position that <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss> would inevitably provide military
                            benefits, no matter how intrusive the arrangements designed to constrain
                            those benefits. In this connection, we pointed out that a <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> program: would (a) provide the
                            infrastructure to the state carrying out the program to maintain
                            personnel and facilities specialized in the design, fabrication, and use
                            of nuclear explosives at a substantially higher level of competence and
                            readiness than <pb facs="0418" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> would be the
                            case if all nuclear explosions were banned; (b) provide information on
                            the effects of nuclear explosions that would assist in the design and
                            protection of weapon systems; and (c) facilitate assessments of the
                            reliability of a state’s stockpile of nuclear weapons, whose explosive
                            design features could parallel or be identical to design features of the
                            explosives used in the <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> program. In
                            addition, we indicated that we were unaware of any reliable means of
                            verifying that design improvements were not being introduced while
                            conducting <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>, but emphasized that,
                            even if device standardization could be guaranteed, this would not
                            eliminate the other military benefits enumerated above.</p>
                        <p>The Soviets, however, took a more narrow view of military benefits,
                            claiming that such could be precluded by freezing explosive device
                            design and by prohibiting diagnostic measurements of explosions and by
                            verifying that each device used in the <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> program conformed to certain specified parameters (in
                            this connection, mentioning as examples total yield, fission yield, and
                            the ratios of amount of selected radioactive debris products). <persName corresp="#p_MI_1">Morokhov</persName>, head of the Soviet
                            Delegation, repeatedly sought to draw us into a technical examination of
                            how device improvement could be effectively precluded. We resisted those
                            efforts, indicating that we did not consider it promising to get
                            involved in the technical consideration of proposals which, even if
                            feasible and practicable, did not even purport to deal with a number of
                            important military benefits (e.g., maintenance of nuclear explosive
                            device “infrastructure”) that we had identified. It should be noted that
                            their proposals as stated would not assure that some device development
                            was not being carried out.</p>
                        <p>On non-proliferation, the Soviet side contended that a ban on all nuclear
                            explosions would be resisted by non-nuclear weapon states wishing to
                            receive the benefits of <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> technology
                            and would give some of those states the excuse that only indigenous
                            nuclear explosive development would enable them to realize those
                            benefits. On the other hand, we maintained that non-nuclear weapon
                            states have showed little interest in PNEs, and that a number of
                            critical states that have not joined the Non-Proliferation Treaty would
                            almost certainly reject a discriminatory agreement which permitted only
                            existing nuclear powers to carry out nuclear explosions.</p>
                        <p>It is still difficult to predict how firmly the Soviets will maintain
                            their position on <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_MI_1">Morokhov</persName>, who represents the Soviet
                            agency responsible for <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>, has
                            certainly made every effort to demonstrate inflexibility. He has claimed
                            that all Soviet government agencies are agreed on the need to preserve
                                <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>, that the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> cannot afford to give up a
                            technology that will make a major contribution to the national economy,
                            and that there will be no <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> treaty
                            without <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>. The question remains,
                            however, whether the Soviet political leadership will <pb facs="0419" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/> permit the alleged potential benefits of
                                <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss> to stand in the way of an
                            objective to which the Soviets have long been committed and which could
                            have important effects on U.S.-Soviet relations as well as global
                            non-proliferation efforts. Interestingly, the Soviet military Delegate
                            volunteered to our military Delegate informally that military benefits
                            would accrue from <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>, albeit he
                            minimized their importance. It is also interesting that the Ministry of
                            Foreign Affairs representatives on the Soviet Delegation, when asked
                            this question, do not attempt to defend the Soviet <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss> position, but rather say that the
                            issue will have to be resolved at the highest levels.</p>
                        <p>Our overall impression is that the Soviet government has not made the
                            political decision to press ahead with <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss> at the cost of abandoning a <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss>. However, it is clear to us that it will be futile to
                            try to resolve the issue of <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss> solely
                            in the context of the trilateral negotiations. Our case will have to be
                            presented at a higher political level. <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Cy
                                Vance</persName>’s meeting with <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName> in early September would provide a good
                            opportunity to demonstrate our firmness on the issue and to appeal to
                            U.S.-Soviet interests that transcend the possible economic value of
                                <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNEs</gloss>.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Verification</p>
                        <p>Our presentations on verification were devoted mainly to outlining, and
                            seeking Soviet reactions to, our ideas on the installation of secure
                            seismic stations on U.S. and Soviet territory, and to calling for a
                            stronger position on on-site inspections than the one contained in the
                            Soviet draft treaty. On the question of internal seismic stations, the
                            Soviet side expressed the view that such supplementary verification was
                            unnecessary in view of the adequacy of national technical means. This
                            response, however, was tentative and far from a categorical rejection.
                            They maintained, for example, that the U.S. side had failed so far to
                            submit sufficiently convincing technical arguments for internal
                            stations. They did, however, exhibit a good bit of interest in the
                            technical details we presented. The Delegation has the impression that
                            the Soviets ultimately will be prepared to accept some number of secure
                            stations on their territory—although we would not expect them to show
                            flexibility on this point until the <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss>
                            issue is resolved.</p>
                        <p>With respect to on-site inspections, we pressed the Soviets to go along
                            with the idea that, once an inspection visit is authorized, the rights
                            and functions of observers should not be left to <hi rend="italic">ad
                                hoc</hi> determination, but should instead be explicitly agreed upon
                            in advance in an annex or protocol to the treaty. Although the Soviet
                            Delegation was not prepared to say so formally, we received informal
                            indications that such a detailed annex or protocol would ultimately be
                            acceptable. However, the Soviets continued to emphasize the importance
                            they place on the “principle of voluntariness,” which, as contained in
                            the Soviet draft <pb facs="0420" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/> treaty,
                            provides for on-site inspection only if the party suspected of a
                            violation agrees on the need for an inspection.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Entry into Force and Withdrawal</p>
                        <p>The Soviets continued to support the provisions in their draft treaty
                            which requires adherence by all nuclear powers before entry into force.
                            They also reiterated their suggestion that, upon signature of a <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> treaty with such an entry into force
                            provision, the U.S., U.K., and U.S.S.R. should suspend testing for 18–24
                            months. If by the end of that period the requirement for entry into
                            force of the treaty was not met, the three would be free to resume
                            testing.</p>
                        <p>We pointed out that the Soviet idea was counter-productive in terms of
                            the objective of encouraging all nuclear powers to join a <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss>, that the scheme would at best result
                            in a short hiatus in <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            testing, and that it would not as effectively constrain non-nuclear
                            weapons states not party to <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> from
                            developing an indigenous nuclear explosive capability. We suggested
                            instead a treaty that would enter into force without adherence by all
                            nuclear powers, but would provide for the right to withdraw after about
                            five years. From several discussions with the Ministry of Foreign
                            Affairs representatives on the Soviet Delegation, we have the clear
                            impression that the Soviets will eventually be able to accept something
                            along the lines of our proposal.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Moratorium</p>
                        <p>As instructed in your July 11 letter, I followed up on the exploratory
                            question I had raised with <persName corresp="#p_MI_1">Morokhov</persName> during the June bilateral meetings about the
                            desirability of suspending nuclear explosions at an early stage of the
                            negotiations. In a meeting of the heads of the two Delegations, he again
                            maintained that such a moratorium would serve no useful purpose, but
                            might instead remove incentives for completing the negotiations and
                            could thus delay their conclusion. He went on, however, to state
                            somewhat cryptically that others might decide on a moratorium
                            “unconnected with the treaty.” I would suggest that we hold off on the
                            question of a moratorium at the Delegation level until such time as we
                            have reached trilateral agreement on the key elements of a <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> treaty. At that time, the Soviets are
                            likely to see the matter in a different perspective.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WP_1"><hi rend="strong">Paul C.
                                    Warnke</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>