<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>187. Telegram From the Mission in Geneva to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d187</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">187</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-02-09T13:44:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-02-09T13:44:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recFUg0jqFk2tUZ15" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006127"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Nuclear power</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-02-09T13:44:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-02-09T13:44:00-05:00" n="187"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d187">
                <head>187. Telegram From the Mission in Geneva to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d187fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D780061–0359. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>.
                        Sent for information Priority to London and Moscow.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-02-09T18:44:00+00:00">February 9, 1978, 1844Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1993. <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss> USCTB. Pass to DOE. Subject:
                        <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> Negotiations: <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> Bilateral Meeting, February
                    8.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> Message No. 123.</p>
                <p>1. Summary. <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> Delegations met on February 8 to discuss issue of <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> role in <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> separate agreement on
                    verification. <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> Alt <gloss target="#t_Rep_1"
                        >Rep</gloss> (Neidle) reviewed principal reasons why, in <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> view, verification agreement should be bilateral
                    in nature with <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> association. He outlined
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> proposals for specific features of <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> role as per instructions. <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> Delegation was generally receptive to <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> approach which acting <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> (Edmonds) said was consistent with
                    formulation used in <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> December 16 plenary
                    statement (agreement between <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> with <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                        association)<note n="2" xml:id="d187fn2">The <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                            >UK</gloss> statement is in telegram 12360 from the Mission in Geneva,
                        December 17, 1977; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy File, D770471–0209.</note> and with general guidance
                    issued by <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> ministers. On specific features of
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> role, <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    Deloff (Fakley) said that, from standpoint of technical requirements for giving
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> confidence that Western security
                    interests are protected, <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> proposals
                    corresponded to what <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> Delegation had in mind.
                    End summary.</p>
                <p>2. <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> outlined reasons why, in <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> view, agreement should be bilateral in nature,
                    particularly because straightforward, bilateral arrangement that did not appear
                    to be subjecting Soviets to unequal verification burden would serve overriding
                    Western interest of getting the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> to accept
                    detailed and effective verification provisions. At the same time, he said <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> welcomed association of <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> in such a way as to permit benefits of <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> expertise and participation, and to give <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> a higher level of assurance regarding Soviet compliance than
                    would be available to the non-nuclear parties to the treaty (see full text of
                    talking notes, <gloss target="#t_para_1">para</gloss> 8). Drawing on <gloss
                        target="#t_Del_1">Del</gloss>’s instructions,<note n="3" xml:id="d187fn3"
                        >Not found.</note> he outlined proposed nature of <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> association, as envisaged by <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>,
                    i.e., inclusion of <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> personnel on <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> on-site inspection teams operating in the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>; possibilities for <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> consultations in event of
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> concerns about Soviet behavior; <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> right to receive all data from internal stations
                    in <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>; <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    participation in <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> seismic station installation
                    teams on Soviet territory. On legal form, he said <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> had in mind an exchange of notes between <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> which would specify
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> intentions with regard to in<pb
                        facs="0475" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/>clusion of <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> personnel in carrying out certain functions. He said <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> envisaged frequent bilateral consultations with
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>, as well as possibility of ad hoc
                    trilateral consultation when this seemed appropriate and noted that <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> would have option of requesting <gloss
                        target="#t_OSI_1">OSI</gloss> on Soviet territory independently of <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> under multilateral treaty.</p>
                <p>3. <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> noted that <gloss target="#t_HMG_1"
                        >HMG</gloss> had made political decision that <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> should be associated with bilateral US-Soviet verification
                    agreement, consistent with formulation in <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    plenary statement of December 16, but had not thought out details of
                    association. He indicated <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> Delegation’s views
                    on best form of association would influence London’s thinking. He said <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> approach seemed consistent with <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> December 16 formulation and acknowledged the
                    importance of proposing an arrangement that was capable of achieving Soviet
                    support for effective verification provisions.</p>
                <p>4. <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> Deloff, in supplementary comments, stressed
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> requirements that a separate agreement
                    provide assurance of treaty compliance and ensure <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> cooperation. He said, from
                    technical point of view, <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> proposals were what
                    his Delegation had in mind. Stating that there was no justification for
                    independent British <gloss target="#t_OSI_1">OSI</gloss> capability, he said
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> would favor integration of <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> personnel in <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_OSI_1">OSI</gloss> inspection teams. On <gloss
                        target="#t_ISIS_1">ISIs</gloss>, access to regional seismic data from
                    stations in <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> satisfied <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> requirement. On installation of <gloss
                        target="#t_ISIS_1">ISIs</gloss>, he said <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    envisaged involvement in three phases: (1) site selection; (2) installation and
                    station checkout; and (3) maintenance. He said this was extent of <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> technical involvement envisaged.</p>
                <p>5. <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> responded that <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> concept of site installation did not exclude site selection. We
                    had not suggested <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> involvement in site
                    maintenance, since this might be conducted infrequently with very limited number
                    of personnel, and would probably be more of a chore than anything. But he said
                    we would be prepared to discuss this. Fakley said basis for <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> desire to be included in maintenance phase was
                    that it would be only available basis for continuing <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> involvement after initial installation of stations. <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> noted that explicit references to <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> association in body of bilateral agreement would
                    establish basis for working out extent and details of <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> role. <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> expressed agreement with this concept and
                    stressed that <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> wanted <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> participation to be a positive, not a complicating factor.</p>
                <p>6. <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> raised issue of procedure for
                    consultations. <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> noted, as practical matter, that in many
                    cases, <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    would presumably want to consult promptly in the event of a suspected Soviet
                    violation. Tripartite consultations might on occasion be deemed desirable as
                    well, but in view of wide range of possible scenarios, it would not seem
                    appropriate to make them obligatory.</p>
                <pb facs="0476" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/>
                <p>7. <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss> said he would report discussions back to
                    London and would receive instructions in the near future.</p>
                <p>8. Text of <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Rep_1">Rep</gloss>’s talking notes follows: Begin text:</p>
                <p>—The overall Western objective for the separate agreement should be to ensure
                    effective verification of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> without
                    undercutting our goal of obtaining broad non-nuclear weapon state adherence to
                    the treaty.</p>
                <p>—We thus have an interest in making effective verification procedures as
                    palatable and negotiable as possible to the Soviets. Our judgment is that we are
                    more likely to achieve Soviet acceptance of such procedures if we make the
                    arrangements as simple as possible and do not in any way appear to be subjecting
                    them to double jeopardy.</p>
                <p>—We also have an interest in avoiding the perception of discriminatory
                    verification arrangements. In our view, the separate agreement will be more
                    palatable to the non-nuclear states if it is perceived to be based on such
                    factors as special mutual security concerns (such as those between the two
                    super-powers) and geographical considerations (large land masses with locations
                    suitable for evasive testing).</p>
                <p>—We both also have certain domestic considerations to take into account. We
                    understand that the form of British association could be of some importance to
                    you, and that there will be other questions, including, for example, the costs
                    that may be involved. For us, it is important that the separate agreement be
                    seen as capable of operating in a streamlined and prompt manner.</p>
                <p>—For these reasons, we believe that emphasis should be given to the bilateral, as
                    opposed to the trilateral (or nuclear weapon state), aspects of the
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>—At the same time, we recognize and welcome the <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss>’s interest in being associated. We believe it is important for
                    the measures contained in the agreement to benefit from <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> expertise and participation. And as a leading nuclear weapon
                    power, and the only other nuclear power to join the treaty from the start, the
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> should be able, through a practical form
                    of association, to obtain a higher level of assurance regarding Soviet
                    compliance than would be available to the non-nuclear parties.</p>
                <p>—Taking these factors into consideration, we have devised an approach to <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> association that we believe would meet overall
                    Western objectives. The agreement we have in mind would be bilateral, with the
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> as its parties. At the same time, the agreement would be
                    developed on a trilateral basis, with the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    playing an active role in the negotiations.</p>
                <p>—The agreement, under our suggested approach, would apply to activities on <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and Soviet territory. As far as OSIs are
                    concerned, it <pb facs="0477" n="446" xml:id="pg_446"/> would cover <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> requests for OSIs on Soviet territory and Soviet
                    requests for OSIs on <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> territory. In the event
                    that a <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> request was accepted, the agreement
                    should permit <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> to include <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> personnel on <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    inspection teams. Moreover, if the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> had
                    concerns about Soviet behavior, the two of us could discuss the matter and, on
                    the basis of those discussions, the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> might
                    make an <gloss target="#t_OSI_1">OSI</gloss> request under the agreement. On the
                    other hand, the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> might wish to raise the
                    matter with the Soviets independently and to make a <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_OSI_1">OSI</gloss> request, as it would be entitled to do
                    under the multilateral treaty. Either option would be available.</p>
                <p>—As far as the possibility of Soviet inspections on <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> territory is concerned, we believe this could be handled under
                    the multilateral treaty. We doubt that the Soviets would insist on dealing with
                    this contingency under the separate agreement, and we see no reason to
                    anticipate their concerns.</p>
                <p>—As far as internal stations are concerned, we also doubt that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> would desire such stations on <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> territory and therefore see no reason why this
                    possibility should be offered to them.</p>
                <p>—With respect to internal stations, we believe the <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> should have the right to receive all of the data from internal
                    stations in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. In addition, the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> might want the right to participate in <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> installation teams on Soviet territory. These
                    rights could be provided for explicitly in the bilateral agreement.</p>
                <p>—With respect to consultations, we would naturally plan to consult bilaterally
                    with you frequently and on all aspects of the separate agreement. There may also
                    be circumstances when ad hoc trilateral consultations would be desirable.</p>
                <p>—As far as the legal form of <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> association is
                    concerned, we have in mind an exchange of notes between the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>. The
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> note would express how we intended to
                    exercise our rights under the agreement to include the <gloss target="#t_UK_1"
                        >UK</gloss> in carrying out certain functions and our intention to share all
                    internal seismic data. The <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> note would express
                    your readiness to cooperate and participate in implementing the agreement. The
                    signing of the notes could take place simultaneously with the signing of the
                    bilateral agreement. End text.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Warnke</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
