<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-07-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-07-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="213" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d213">
                        <head>213. Memorandum From the Director of the Arms Control and Disarmament
                            Agency (<persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Warnke</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d213fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 383, Records of the Arms Control and
                                Disarmament Agency, Office of the Director, <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Paul C. Warnke</persName> Files, December
                                1974–July 1979, Accession #383–98–0154, Box 1, Memoranda to the
                                President Regarding <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>, Cruise
                                Missiles, <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss>, and Indian Ocean Arms Control,
                                January–October 1978. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-07-28">July 28, 1978</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Duration of a Comprehensive Test Ban (<gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss>)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Our trilateral talks with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and
                                <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> on a Comprehensive Test Ban
                            Treaty are continuing to proceed well.<note n="2" xml:id="d213fn2">The
                                trilateral <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> negotiations resumed
                                on May 4 in Geneva and continued into August.</note> A good number
                            of the formal treaty provisions have been agreed and the Soviet
                            Delegation is talking seriously on the issues of the way in which
                            on-site inspections would be conducted and the characteristics of the
                            national seismic stations that would be established in the Soviet Union
                            and the U.S.</p>
                        <p>The question of the initial duration of the treaty is, however, impeding
                            the final development of on-site inspection procedures and, even more
                            seriously, Soviet consideration of the number, timing and specific
                            characteristics of the national seismic stations. Accordingly,
                            substantial further progress will require that we state soon our final
                            position on treaty duration.</p>
                        <pb facs="0564" n="533" xml:id="pg_533"/>
                        <p>It is, however, also clear that a final decision that moves from a five
                            year treaty to a three year treaty will interfere seriously with our
                            ability to negotiate any extensive and effective network in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. This could make our ratification
                            problems more severe. There are also indications that moving to a three
                            year term could adversely affect prospects for gaining adherence by
                            key-nuclear states, and thus reduce a <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss>’s non-proliferation value.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Verification</hi>. Our discussions with the Soviet
                                <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> Delegation suggest strongly
                            that, for a five-year treaty, the Soviets would be prepared to come
                            quite close to meeting our proposals on national seismic stations,
                            including our proposal that they accept a substantial number of
                            stations. After press accounts alerted them to a possible U.S. move to
                            three years, however, they have taken a much more reserved position. The
                            head of the Soviet Delegation has made it clear that his government
                            would accept substantially less in terms of verification, particularly
                            seismic stations, for a three-year treaty than for a five-year one. He
                            maintains that, for a three-year duration, it is virtually impossible to
                            justify a seismic network that would take over two years to install,
                            would require considerable effort and expense, and would involve
                            advanced equipment that has not yet even been fully developed or
                            tested.</p>
                        <p>In addition, we are told by members of the Soviet Delegation that our
                            far-reaching seismic station proposals have encountered strong
                            resistance in the Soviet bureaucracy because of their unprecedented
                            intrusiveness. While the Soviet government appears reluctantly prepared
                            to accept most of our proposals in the context of a relatively durable
                                <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss>, it can be expected to have
                            much greater difficulty swallowing what they probably regard as a
                            serious compromise of Soviet doctrine for the sake of a treaty that
                            could lapse after only three years.</p>
                        <p>We believe, therefore, that a U.S. shift to three years would result in a
                            significant weakening of the verification package we could hope to
                            negotiate. It is unlikely, for example, that we could obtain more than a
                            few stations on Soviet territory, and even then the Soviets would be
                            very reluctant to agree in advance or in any detail to the sophisticated
                            technical features we are proposing.</p>
                        <p>The implications of having to settle for less could be quite serious.
                            Clearly, verification will be a key factor in the ratification debate,
                            and the type of seismic network that seems attainable for a five-year
                            treaty could be a major asset. It would have substantial appeal both in
                            the Senate and with the American public as a breakthrough in terms of
                            Soviet acceptance of intrusive verification measures and as an important
                            precedent for future arms control measures, such as <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>. Our shift to three years could
                            undercut this opportunity.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Effect on India and other key states.</hi> Foreign
                            Secretary Mehta recently told our Ambassador that the Indian Government
                            was troubled by a <pb facs="0565" n="534" xml:id="pg_534"/>
                            <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> story<note n="3" xml:id="d213fn3">Telegram 178021 to Geneva, July 14, reported that the Indian
                                Government was “troubled” by a July 1 story in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> that said “<gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> military and nuclear experts have forced a change in
                                our position so that certain kinds of testing will be permitted and
                                the duration of the <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> will be
                                reduced to 3 years.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D780289–0851)</note> indicating that we had decided to permit
                            certain kinds of nuclear testing under a <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> and to shift to a three-year treaty. Ambassador Goheen
                            reported that Mehta seemed to be saying that India would not become
                            party to so limited a <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The Indians are probably more concerned by the prospect of movement away
                            from a comprehensive ban than they are by a possible shift to three
                            years—and they may well be prepared to go along with the shorter
                            duration provided that the treaty is comprehensive. Nonetheless, they
                            would almost certainly find the five-year approach easier to
                            support.</p>
                        <p>We would expect other key non-nuclear states also to favor a longer
                            treaty, and in some cases this preference could be a decisive factor in
                            whether they choose to adhere. A number of these states may interpret
                            the three-year approach as lack of a true commitment on our part to a
                                <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> and as a clear indication of
                            our intention to resume testing, and they may decide that, rather than
                            join from the start, they should wait and see whether the nuclear powers
                            are serious enough about a test ban to continue it after the three-year
                            moratorium.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Negotiating Leverage.</hi> Because the Soviets earlier
                            proposed a form of three-year treaty, we had assumed that, by moving to
                            three years, we could seek to obtain corresponding Soviet movement on
                            other issues. However, not only have the Soviets signaled clearly that
                            they could accept a five-year treaty, but the Soviet Delegation leader
                            has told us that he prefers five to three. If anything, our move to
                            three would give the Soviets additional leverage on us. The Deputy
                            Chairman of the Soviet Delegation recently expressed to the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> Deputy his disappointment that with the
                            three year duration we would end up with only “a brief self-imposed
                            moratorium.” He complained about the influence of the U.S. Joint Chiefs
                            of Staff and said that he regretted now that the Soviet side had failed
                            to accept the idea of unlimited duration.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">United Kingdom Position.</hi> The British have
                            repeatedly emphasized to us their strong view that five years is the
                            minimum term which should be negotiated. Their Delegation head informed
                            me that Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Callaghan</persName>
                            planned to mention this to you in Bonn.<note n="4" xml:id="d213fn4">Not
                                found.</note> Although the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> would
                            probably go along with a three year term if we urge it, they will do so
                            reluctantly.</p>
                        <pb facs="0566" n="535" xml:id="pg_535"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Stockpile Reliability Implications.</hi> No technical
                            basis has been adduced for questioning our ability, without nuclear
                            testing, to maintain high confidence in the reliability of our stockpile
                            for a substantial period of time, and certainly for five years. Any
                            expressions of preference for a three year period seem to derive more
                            from an eagerness to resume testing than from any serious contention
                            that the problems of maintaining stockpile reliability for five years
                            are significantly greater than those for a three year period.</p>
                        <p>Indeed, a three year treaty might be insufficient time to provide
                            experience in maintaining the stockpile without testing to enable us to
                            make a sound judgment on whether a test ban can be continued.</p>
                        <p>These various circumstances tend strongly to support a five year treaty
                            duration. The longer term would permit negotiation of more effective and
                            more domestically attractive verification measures and would elicit
                            greater support among key non-nuclear countries. The three year period
                            would, as a practical matter, foreclose the installation of a
                            significant seismic network in the Soviet Union and could be regarded by
                            other countries as, in the words of the Soviet Deputy, just “a brief
                            self-imposed moratorium”. Indeed, if other considerations lead you to
                            modify your earlier decision in favor of a five year treaty, I would
                            suggest that a four year treaty would much more adequately advance our
                                <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> objectives than one of three
                            years.</p>
                        <p>In short, the costs to our negotiating position and to our
                            non-proliferation objectives resulting from the reduction of the <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> term would be heavier than I believed
                            when we first discussed this possibility. I wonder whether the gains in
                            quieting <gloss target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> opponents would be
                            sufficient to offset these costs.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>