<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-12-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="258" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                        <head>258. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>In his memoirs, <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Zbigniew
                                Brzezinski</persName>, President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Jimmy
                                Carter</persName>’s Assistant for National Security Affairs,
                            recalled that upon taking office, he and his staff quickly set a number
                            of foreign policy goals that the <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> administration should pursue. One was the
                            restriction of “the level of global armaments, unilaterally and through
                            international agreements. We were determined to reduce by 15 percent,
                            with the exclusion of transfers to <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, Australia, New Zealand, and Japan, the dollar value
                            of transfers from the 1976 totals.” (<hi rend="italic">Power and
                                Principle</hi>, p. 55) In his first National Security Council
                            meeting, President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                            “directed that all requests for arms sales come to him” for approval.
                            (Summary of Conclusions, January 22, 1977; Carter Library, National
                            Security Affairs, Staff Material, Office, Meetings File, Box 1, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Meeting #1: Held 1/22/77, 1/77)</p>
                        <p>In a January 23, 1977, interview, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> said that while he did not want to institute a
                            “moratorium” on arms sales “because that is an abrupt and total
                            termination of all ownership,” he noted that his advisers, “in I think
                            unanimity,” supported “the necessity for reducing arms sales or having
                            very tight restraints on future commitments to minimize the efforts by
                            arms manufacturers to initiate sales early in the process. The Secretary
                            of State will be much more hesitant in the future to recommend to the
                            Defense Department the culmination of arms sales agreements. I have
                            asked that all approvals of arms sales, for a change, be submitted to me
                            directly before the recommendations go to Congress. We also have asked
                            Vice President [Walter] <persName corresp="#p_MWF_1">Mondale</persName>
                            in his early trip among our own allies and friends, some of whom are
                            heavy arms exporters, to join with us on a multilateral basis. We will
                            also be talking to some of the primary arms purchasers, particularly the
                            Middle East when Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>
                            goes there very shortly, to hold down their purchases of arms from us
                            and other countries. This will be a continuing effort on my part.” (<hi rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament, 1977,</hi> p. 20)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>