<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-03-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="26" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                        <head>26. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d26fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                                Security Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                                Material, Subject File, Box 4, Anti-Satellite System (<gloss target="#t_ASAT_1">ASAT</gloss>): 7/77–10/80. Top Secret.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> initialed the
                                upper right-hand corner of the memorandum.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-03-22">March 22, 1978</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and Soviet Laser Weapons
                                Capabilities</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BH_2">Harold Brown</persName> has responded to
                            your request for more information on present and potential <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and Soviet laser weapons capabilities
                            with his memo at Tab A.<note n="2" xml:id="d26fn2">Not attached.</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0085" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/>
                        <p>The projected dates for achieving some of the capabilities that Harold
                            refers to are several years later than those you may have heard before.
                            This is because while most technical reports give dates for initial
                            operational capabilities—Harold speaks in terms of the date at which
                            sufficient numbers of any given device could be fielded to achieve a
                            “meaningful effect.” Given an agreed definition of what a meaningful
                            effect is for a system, Harold’s date is probably more useful, though
                            somewhat harder to predict. When Harold speaks of meaningful
                            capabilities—in Table 1, he means one or two systems; in Table 2, he
                            means the numbers I have added in the left hand column.</p>
                        <p>Harold’s memo does not mention two other applications of high energy
                            lasers that may be of interest to you—space based lasers for use
                            against: 1) ballistic missiles in the powered portions of their
                            trajectories (where they are most vulnerable), or 2) bombers in the high
                            altitude mid-course phase of their missions. Accordingly, I asked Harold
                            for information on these applications and have summarized it below.</p>
                        <p>—[<hi rend="italic">12½ lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>—[<hi rend="italic">6 lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>I think the whole area of high energy laser weapons bears careful
                            watching. As these systems develop, they may pose some significant
                            challenges to our arms control interests, particularly in the <gloss target="#t_ASAT_1">ASAT</gloss> area.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>