<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>312. Memorandum From Secretary of Defense Brown and Secretary of State and
                    Secretary of State Vance to President to President Carter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-08-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9ptkWICFUk7Mvu" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers">Arms
                        Transfer Policy</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006001993"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Interagency</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms control and disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-08-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-08-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="312"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                <head>312. Memorandum From Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_BH_2"
                        >Brown</persName> and Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1"
                        >Vance</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"
                        >Carter</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d312fn1">Source: Library of Congress,
                        Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_BH_2">Harold Brown</persName>
                        Papers, Box 78, 1977 Arms Transfer/FMS Policy. Secret. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> initialed the top of the
                        memorandum.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-08-14">August 14, 1979</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Assessment of U.S. Arms Transfer Policy</item>
                </list>
                <p>We have recently assessed our experience of the past two years with the arms
                    transfer restraint policy established by <gloss target="#t_PD_1"
                        >PD</gloss>–13.<note n="2" xml:id="d312fn2">See <ref target="#d271">Document
                            271</ref>.</note> On the whole, we believe the policy has supported U.S.
                    interests in restraint without denying us the capability to meet our foreign
                    policy requirements and the defense needs of our allies and friends.</p>
                <p>There has been considerable criticism of the policy from several quarters. Some
                    allies and friends perceive the policy as being artificially restrictive to the
                    point of denying legitimate access to U.S. military equipment. U.S. industries
                    complain that it disadvantages them in international markets vis-a-vis other
                    exporters. Most significantly, however, members of Congress continue to be
                    skeptical of the policy. Some believe its only achievement has been creative
                    bookkeeping; others feel that arms transfers are no longer being used as an
                    effective instrument of foreign policy. We believe that all these criticisms
                    have been overstated, but we nevertheless expect them to emerge once more as
                    Congressional studies currently under way are completed and the Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee moves to hearings at the end of the year.</p>
                <p>Our own principal conclusions are:</p>
                <p>—The policy has required the creation of a planning system that allows us to look
                    at the flow of U.S. arms transfers over a multi-year period and to establish
                    priorities.</p>
                <p>—The machinery created to implement the policy ensures that the Executive Branch
                    takes a wide range of factors—political, security, arms control, economic, and
                    human rights—into account in all major arms transfer cases.</p>
                <p>—The policy has imposed measurable restraint on U.S. arms transfers.</p>
                <p>—Even though we have sold less than we could have, there has not been a
                    subsequent reduction in the total volume of the world’s arms trade.</p>
                <p>(U) In the course of this policy reassessment, we have identified the following
                    issues that will require attention in the near future.</p>
                <pb facs="0806" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Qualitative Controls</p>
                <p>(C) The qualitative controls of <gloss target="#t_PD_1">PD</gloss>–13 have been
                    generally effective. Nevertheless, there are a couple of questions that may
                    require decisions over the coming months.</p>
                <p>(S) 1. We are currently considering whether to authorize the development of an
                    intermediate fighter aircraft solely for export. (The F–5E currently fills this
                    role.) If we decide that this is a good idea for policy reasons, we shall then
                    have to decide whether it requires an exception to <gloss target="#t_PD_1"
                        >PD</gloss>–13.</p>
                <p>(S) 2. Several countries are expressing interest in the F–18L, a land-based
                    version of the Navy aircraft modified solely for export. In 1977 an Iranian
                    request for the F–18L was denied because the aircraft was not operationally
                    deployed with U.S. forces. It is necessary that we review our position on this
                    at an early date because of renewed interest in the aircraft.</p>
                <p>(S) Another area of concern is co-production. We have chosen to make exceptions
                    to this guideline in a number of instances. This is a basic dilemma for U.S.
                    policy. As our non-<gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> friends and allies
                    continue to expand their own production capabilities, the long-term task of arms
                    control becomes more difficult; on the other hand, co-production provides us a
                    measure of control that would be lost if other suppliers sold the concerned
                    equipment. An interagency study, chaired by <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1"
                        >ACDA</gloss>, is currently under way to examine the trends in Third-World
                    arms production capability.</p>
                <p>(C) A related problem has been the reluctance on the part of some <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> countries to enter into RSI co-production
                    arrangements because of our control over third-party sales outside of <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>. These controls have their foundation in our
                    statutes as well as in the arms policy. We are trying to work out these problems
                    on a case-by-case basis.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Quantitative Control (The Ceiling)</p>
                <p>(C) The ceiling on sales to non-exempt countries has been the most controversial
                    aspect of <gloss target="#t_PD_1">PD</gloss>–13. Its positive features include
                    its visibility as a symbol of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> commitment
                    to arms transfer restraint and the managerial reforms associated with it. While
                    it has not led to the rejection of any specific arms transfer requests, it did
                    achieve its purpose of reducing sales in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 78
                    compared to <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 77. In <gloss target="#t_FY_1"
                        >FY</gloss> 79, because of cancellations by Iran, total sales could drop
                    significantly and come in well under the ceiling. This could lead to pressure to
                    lower the base for calculating the <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 80
                    ceiling. Such pressure should be resisted because in <gloss target="#t_FY_1"
                        >FY</gloss> 80 important sales to Israel, Egypt and Saudi Arabia could
                    largely fill the gap left by Iran in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 79.</p>
                <p>(C) In any case, we believe that no further reductions in the ceiling should be
                    made unless there is evidence of progress in our multilateral restraint effort.
                    After four rounds of negotiations with the Soviets we <pb facs="0807" n="776"
                        xml:id="pg_776"/> have no tangible evidence of Soviet restraint, and our
                    European allies have made future restraint on their part (they have not shown
                    any in the past) contingent on our ability to get restraint from the Soviets. We
                    will be submitting our formal recommendation to you later this summer in the
                    context of our <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 80 plan.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Multilateral Cooperation</p>
                <p>(C) <gloss target="#t_PD_1">PD</gloss>–13 recognized that achievement of the
                    objective of a worldwide reduction in arms transfers required the cooperation of
                    other suppliers and recipients. We have not yet made concrete progress toward
                    such cooperation although our efforts will continue. Nevertheless, we believe
                    that the qualitative controls in <gloss target="#t_PD_1">PD</gloss>–13 support
                    U.S. national interests regardless of such cooperation. The substantive and
                    procedural benefits of the qualitative controls, as distinct from the <gloss
                        target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 80 ceiling level noted above, are not vitiated
                    by the lack of multilateral progress. We shall be assessing the results of the
                    multilateral restraint effort and commenting on its implications in a report due
                    to the Congress by December 31, 1979.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Conclusions</p>
                <p>(C) We believe that <gloss target="#t_PD_1">PD</gloss>–13 continues to support
                    our national objectives in arms restraint and that the policy should be
                    maintained with no further reductions under the ceiling. As noted above, our
                    experience suggests that certain aspects of the policy will raise questions of
                    interpretation as circumstances change. We will continue to review <gloss
                        target="#t_PD_1">PD</gloss>–13 to ensure that it remains in consonance with
                    our basic foreign policy needs and arms control objectives. We will also
                    continue to tailor carefully rhetoric about the policy and specific policy
                    decisions in order that it reflect realistically the objectives and achievements
                    of <gloss target="#t_PD_1">PD</gloss>–13.</p>
                <p>(U) The Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff and the Director, Arms Control and
                    Disarmament Agency concur in this memorandum.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BH_2">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Harold Brown</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Cyrus Vance</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
