<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>322. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski) to President ) to President Carter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d322</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">322</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-02-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-02-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Plutonium</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-02-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-02-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="322"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d322">
                <head>322. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>) to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d322fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                        Security Affairs, Staff Material, Global Issues, <persName corresp="#p_OG_1"
                            >Oplinger</persName>/Bloomfield File, Box 42, Proliferation: Clinch
                        River Breeder Reactor, 2/77–9/79. Confidential. Sent for information. At the
                        top of the memorandum, an unknown hand wrote “NOTE: Delivered to the <gloss
                            target="#t_Pres_1">Pres</gloss>. Via Rich Hutcheson [illegible.]”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-02-16">February 16, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Funding for the Clinch River Reactor</item>
                </list>
                <p>I understand that you have spoken with <persName corresp="#p_SJR_1">Jim
                        Schlesinger</persName> and are considering approving the <gloss
                        target="#t_ERDA_1">ERDA</gloss> request for Clinch River funding. <hi
                        rend="italic">I feel that you should know that such a course could have
                        extremely serious effects on the success of your non-proliferation efforts
                        in the critical next six months.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>We are asking other nations to make profound changes in their own energy plans
                    because of our concern with the proliferation risks of the global trend toward a
                    plutonium economy. The only way in which we can demonstrate our willingness to
                    share in the sacrifices we are asking of others is by clearly slowing down our
                    breeder program and that we no longer look upon it as the centerpiece of our
                    energy strategy. This is entirely consistent with your campaign statements to
                    “minimize our efforts in the breeder field.”</p>
                <pb facs="0824" n="793" xml:id="pg_793"/>
                <p>It is for these reasons that I—as well as the <hi rend="italic">Department of
                        State, <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss>,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                        >CEQ</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Domestic Council</hi>—strongly recommend
                    that you either zero out the Clinch River budget item or make a much more
                    meaningful cut in the program than <gloss target="#t_ERDA_1">ERDA</gloss>
                    contemplates. The funding level they have recommended in no way slows the heart
                    of the Clinch River program and in fact entails a $41 million <hi rend="italic"
                        >increase</hi> in spending over <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> ’77. <hi
                        rend="italic">I submit that this will not be seen as a serious action on our
                        part by the Germans, the French, the Brazilians, the Pakistanis or the
                        Japanese.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At the same time, the course of action I am advocating does not require any
                    concrete sacrifice in our domestic energy situation. If either <gloss
                        target="#t_PRM_1">PRM</gloss>–15<note n="2" xml:id="d322fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d317">Document 317</ref>.</note> or the breeder program
                        review<note n="3" xml:id="d322fn3">See <ref target="#d337">Document
                            337</ref>.</note> indicate that the Clinch River Reactor is not inimical
                    to our efforts in the proliferation field or is essential to our domestic energy
                    needs (both extremely unlikely), then a <hi rend="italic">budget supplemental
                        can be sent to Congress in plenty of time for action before the beginning of
                        the new fiscal year, with no interruption in the program.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At your request I will be forwarding to you first thing tomorrow, a paper on what
                    we can do in regard to international restraints with the hope of getting other
                    nations to join in our efforts. <hi rend="italic">By far the most potent option
                        available to us is exactly this one: to clearly tell the rest of the world
                        that we consider the dangers of proliferation seriously enough to halt for
                        the time being our own progress toward commercialization of the breeder by
                        stopping or dramatically slowing the first big step—further work on the
                        Clinch River Reactor.</hi>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d322fn4">In his memoirs, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"
                            >Carter</persName> wrote “My first veto” of a congressional bill was a
                        “$6 billion authorization bill for energy research,” including “$80 million
                        for commencing construction of a nuclear breeder reactor on the Clinch River
                        near Oak Ridge, Tennessee. Because it was enormously expensive and
                        unnecessary, and would open up a new and dangerous plutonium industry in our
                        country, I was determined to prevent construction of this prototype plant.”
                            (<persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Keeping Faith</hi>, pp. 101–102)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
