<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>372. Paper Prepared in the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d372</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">372</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-07-14T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-07-20T22:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQI8RFLxCFovNr2" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092985"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nuclear fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recAZ6vp0KaSfYUeW" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation">Nuclear non-proliferation</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general">Technological development</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="reccOg5QXDp3EJxaF" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">SALT II</term>
                    <term ref="recFKwbJC7hOq07wX" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation">Comprehensive Test Ban</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Plutonium</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear arms control</term>
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="general" subject="international-organizations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">EURATOM</term>
                    <term ref="recOJxlJVfRvlJiXp" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-material" lcsh-match="no_match">Nuclear materials</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-07-20T22:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-07-14T23:00:00-05:00" n="372"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d372">
                <head>372. Paper Prepared in the Department of State<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d372fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Staff
                        Material, Global Issues, <persName corresp="#p_OG_1"
                        >Oplinger</persName>/Bloomfield File, Box 31, Chron: 7/79. Confidential.
                        Sent under cover of a July 20 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1"
                            >Vance</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"
                        >Carter</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            notAfter="1979-07-20T23:59:59-04:00"
                            notBefore="1979-07-15T00:00:00-04:00">undated</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">STATUS REPORT FOR THE PRESIDENT ON NON-PROLIFERATION POLICY/NUCLEAR
                    FUEL CYCLE INITIATIVES</p>
                <p>Events of the past several months—particularly the <gloss target="#t_INFCE_1"
                        >INFCE</gloss> plenary last November and the bilateral talks with our major
                    nuclear cooperation partners in November and January, as well as our talks with
                    India and Pakistan on nuclear issues—allow us to take a broad look at the
                    progress and prospects of our non-proliferation policy, especially our
                    initiatives on managing the nuclear fuel cycle.</p>
                <p>In the two years since your April 1977 non-proliferation policy
                        announcements,<note n="2" xml:id="d372fn2">See <ref target="#d338fn3"
                            >footnote 3, Document 338</ref>.</note> we have clearly achieved a
                    heightened sensitivity <pb facs="0976" n="945" xml:id="pg_945"/> abroad to the
                    dangers that nuclear proliferation would pose and to the importance of deterring
                    proliferation. We have also made progress in renegotiating some of our nuclear
                    cooperation agreements, gained new adherents to the Nuclear Non-Proliferation
                    Treaty, and won limited support from other nuclear suppliers for restraints on
                    sensitive nuclear exports, particularly in the case of exports to Pakistan.</p>
                <p>At the same time, and especially because of the insecurity of global energy
                    supply that was accentuated by events in Iran,<note n="3" xml:id="d372fn3">In
                        the wake of the Shah’s decision to leave Iran, the nation’s new government
                        suspended oil exports, which affected the world’s energy supply. See <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d181">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. XXXVII, Energy
                            Crisis, 1974–1980, Documents 181</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d182">182</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d187">187</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d188">188</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d189">189</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d192">192</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d193">193</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d194">194</ref>, and <ref
                            target="frus1969-76v37#d200">200</ref>.</note> our efforts to restrain
                    the use and transfer of sensitive nuclear technologies and materials are still
                    viewed by many governments as an unacceptable infringement on their nuclear
                    energy development plans. These governments defend their nuclear energy plans
                    primarily on political grounds, specifically on their right to increase their
                    energy independence and to undertake related technological development.</p>
                <p>As a result, although our <gloss target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss> consultations
                    show a growing consensus between ourselves and several of our industrialized
                    partners on most issues concerning the nuclear fuel cycle and sensitive
                    technology transfers, we have not been able to win many other governments’
                    support for our fundamental position: that non-proliferation concerns, as well
                    as technical and economic factors, indicate that the transfer and use of
                    sensitive technologies should be significantly restrained and delayed.</p>
                <p>In talks with us even the Canadians, whom we view as close allies in our
                    non-proliferation effort, have voiced doubts about the effectiveness of an
                    attempt to deny sensitive technologies to the developing states even if they
                    accept safeguards and give other non-proliferation assurances. Canadians argue
                    that such a discriminatory approach could weaken the <gloss target="#t_NPT_1"
                        >NPT</gloss>. They also stress their interest in maintaining an option for
                    Canadian enrichment and reprocessing facilities.</p>
                <p>If the problems of access to peaceful nuclear technology and nuclear arms control
                    cause a serious confrontation at the June 1980 <gloss target="#t_NPT_1"
                        >NPT</gloss> Review Conference, the <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss>
                    regime, which has served us so well over the last decade, could be significantly
                    undercut. The situation would be even more acrimonious if the outcome of <gloss
                        target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss> appears discriminatory or if <gloss
                        target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II and a Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty are
                    not concluded before the conference. We are currently consulting with the other
                        <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> depositary states (<gloss
                        target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>) and
                    other key countries to promote a more productive atmosphere at the
                    conference.</p>
                <pb facs="0977" n="946" xml:id="pg_946"/>
                <p>As an outcome of <gloss target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss>, we look forward to a
                    reasonably balanced technical analysis of fuel cycle issues in the final <gloss
                        target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss> report in February 1980. But we do not
                    expect to achieve a formal new international regime under which governments are
                    committed to a set of norms and rules corresponding to our policy preferences.
                    Rather, alongside the <gloss target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss> process, we hope
                    to achieve a growing informal consensus among the major industrial countries on
                    a set of general principles for nuclear commerce and fuel cycle management that
                    can serve as a guide for national policies. To reach even an informal
                    understanding, we will have to make some compromises. We also believe that such
                    a consensus among suppliers may evoke a strong negative reaction on the part of
                    many developing countries, although we are trying to bring them into the
                    consensus as well.</p>
                <p>We have begun to develop certain illustrative elements of the consensus we hope
                    to achieve. These include strictly limiting and multinationalizing new
                    enrichment and reprocessing plants; using plutonium only for research,
                    development, and deployment in breeders and advanced thermal reactors; no
                    recycling of plutonium in current generation thermal reactors; and pacing
                    construction of any new reprocessing plants to meet only breeder and advanced
                    reactor requirements and to avoid stockpiling of plutonium. We have also
                    encouraged multinational safeguarded interim spent fuel repositories.</p>
                <p>We hope that restraints of these kinds can be made acceptable on the basis of an
                    evolutionary principle: that is, that various nuclear technologies and
                    facilities may be transferred to developing countries but only when their energy
                    needs and electric grids would support such transfers. However, we expect that a
                    number of developing countries will resist this approach because they want
                    complete access now to all nuclear technologies and will resent in principle a
                    formula that discriminates between states on the basis of level of
                    development.</p>
                <p>In the near term, we will have to compromise on some of our illustrative elements
                    in relation to the advanced countries. In particular, West Germany, Japan and
                    Canada want to pursue, or to retain the option for, national enrichment and
                    reprocessing programs. Winning their agreement to place such sensitive
                    facilities under multinational auspices will require efforts that continue
                    beyond the conclusion of <gloss target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss>. Also, West
                    Germany and Belgium (and possibly Japan) are not likely to be dissuaded from
                    their programs for research and development for thermal recycle of plutonium,
                    although they may agree not to enlarge such programs for at least a decade.</p>
                <p>To reach a consensus on fuel cycle issues, we believe that we will have to move
                    beyond our present case-by-case consideration of approvals of retransfers of
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-supplied fuel for reprocessing because
                    this confronts our nuclear partners with uncertainties they believe they <pb
                        facs="0978" n="947" xml:id="pg_947"/> cannot manage. We believe it may be
                    possible to deal with such approvals on a generic basis within the framework of
                    the restriction on reprocessing that we are now considering proposing.</p>
                <p>Our approval right on reprocessing is the main issue in the renegotiation of our
                    nuclear cooperation agreements. We have signed a new agreement with Australia
                    and initialed one with Norway.<note n="4" xml:id="d372fn4">The United States
                        signed an agreement concerning the peaceful use of nuclear energy with
                        Australia on July 5 and initialed an agreement with Norway on nuclear
                        cooperation on May 11.</note> Our negotiations are well under way with
                    Finland and several other countries. Reaching agreed conditions on reprocessing
                    would allow us to move forward with our renegotiation program in particular with
                        <gloss target="#t_EURATOM_1">EURATOM</gloss> and Japan.</p>
                <p>Beyond the fuel cycle consensus we are seeking, we also face certain critical
                    cases posing a high risk of proliferation. Pakistan’s sensitive nuclear programs
                    aim at achieving an explosives capability, directly challenging efforts to
                    restrain proliferation. We are working with other suppliers to restrain
                    sensitive exports to Pakistan, while exploring internally and with other
                    governments various approaches to the problem.</p>
                <p>At the same time, we do not believe that India will agree to place all its
                    peaceful nuclear activities under <gloss target="#t_IAEA_1">IAEA</gloss>
                    safeguards by March 1980 as the law requires for continued <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> cooperation, and the collapse of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> Government raises new uncertainties about
                    India’s future nuclear course.<note n="5" xml:id="d372fn5">Indian Prime Minister
                            <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Moraji Desai</persName> resigned, July 15,
                        after Deputy Prime Minister Charan Singh and Minister of Health Raj Narain
                        withdrew from his ruling Janata Party.</note> We have not been successful in
                    gaining South Africa’s agreement to adhere to the <gloss target="#t_NPT_1"
                        >NPT</gloss> or to accept <gloss target="#t_IAEA_1">IAEA</gloss> safeguards
                    on its enrichment activities. Meanwhile, we believe South Africa is already
                    producing weapons-grade enriched uranium. Finally, the <gloss target="#t_FRG_1"
                        >FRG</gloss> contract with Brazil for the transfer of sensitive nuclear
                    technology, while encountering some delays and difficulties, remains intact with
                    sensitive facilities planned to come online in Brazil in the mid-to-late 1980’s.
                    This situation is complicated by Argentina’s plans for the indigenous
                    development of a reprocessing facility.</p>
                <p>All these critical cases pose difficult challenges for us this year and beyond.
                    On other non-proliferation issues, we also foresee a difficult 1980 scenario
                    that we believe we should signal to you. The following sequence is likely:</p>
                <p>—A final <gloss target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss> conference in February whose
                    formal results are extremely modest in comparison to the hopes we originally
                    entertained, but which may still discomfit many of our nuclear partners,
                    especially the developing countries.</p>
                <pb facs="0979" n="948" xml:id="pg_948"/>
                <p>—A March 10 <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> embargo on nuclear supply to
                    non-nuclear weapon states that have not placed all their peaceful nuclear
                    facilities under <gloss target="#t_IAEA_1">IAEA</gloss> safeguards (this is
                    likely to affect India in particular).</p>
                <p>—In the case of <gloss target="#t_EURATOM_1">EURATOM</gloss>, a need for you to
                    extend for one year the March 10 deadline for obtaining their agreement to grant
                    the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> the right to veto reprocessing of spent
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-supplied fuel.</p>
                <p>—A June Non-Proliferation Treaty Review Conference marked by challenges on the
                    part of countries which believe the nuclear-weapon states have not fulfilled
                    their <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> obligations to transfer nuclear
                    technology for peaceful uses and to reduce their own nuclear weapons forces.</p>
                <p>—An industrialized-nation summit in which we, as well as our partners, may be
                    called upon to make certain explicit concessions (for example with regard to the
                    agreed conditions under which reprocessing of spent <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>-supplied fuel will normally be approved).</p>
                <p>On these and other issues, our leverage is limited and declining. We are not the
                    only supplier of essential nuclear materials, equipment, or services, and some
                    countries will be willing to forego our nuclear supplies despite the value they
                    place on good overall relations with us.</p>
                <p>Also, it is not likely that the principles we hope to establish will receive
                    early formal approval internationally or be reflected in new institutions in the
                    near term. However, we believe that the potential problems can be moderated if
                    we use a more informal and flexible approach to our non-proliferation goals,
                    especially because other governments will accept significant restraints on their
                    nuclear activities far more readily in practice than in principle.</p>
                <p>We also believe that achieving an effective global consensus on non-proliferation
                    policy, and especially on managing the nuclear fuel cycle, will require a
                    continuing effort through the 1980s and beyond. Even if the process we foresee
                    moves forward reasonably successfully, we must expect that some “problem states”
                    will elect to remain outside the consensus that begins to develop and that we
                    will, on occasion, be confronted with difficult dilemmas in restraining
                    potential proliferators.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
