<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>461. Telegram From the Embassy in Brazil to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d461</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">461</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-12-10T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-12-10T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear energy</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="public-diplomacy" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomacy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-12-10T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-12-10T11:00:00-05:00" n="461"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d461">
                <head>461. Telegram From the Embassy in Brazil to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d461fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files,
                        D790595–0619. Secret. Sent for information to the U.S. Interests Section in
                        Baghdad, Bonn, Buenos Aires, Madrid, Mexico City, and Vienna.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Brasilia</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-12-10T16:00:00+00:00">December 10, 1979, 1600Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>10578. USIAEA. Subject: Status Report on Non-Proliferation: 1979, The Transition
                    From <persName corresp="#p_GE_1">Geisel</persName> to Figueiredo. Ref: (A)
                    Brasilia 7869;<note n="2" xml:id="d461fn2">Telegram 7869 from Brasilia,
                        September 5, reported that Hervasio de Carvalho, the Brazilian
                        representative to the <gloss target="#t_IAEA_1">IAEA</gloss>, said “that
                        Brazil would not waive the entry-into-force requirements” of the Treaty of
                        Tlateloloco. He also said “that the Treaty was designed as a whole and it
                        would not make sense unless all Latin American countries adhered and unless
                        the major powers accepted the protocols.” (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files,
                        D790412–0684)</note> (B) Brasilia 8069;<note n="3" xml:id="d461fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d455">Document 455</ref>.</note> (C) Brasilia 6944;<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d461fn4">Telegram 6944 from Brasilia, August 6, reported that during
                        a July 25–28 visit to Caracas by Brazilian Foreign Minister Guerreiro, the
                        Brazilian and Venezuelan governments “concluded a general agreement for
                        cooperation in peaceful applications of nuclear energy. According to the
                            <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> Foreign Ministry, cooperation is
                        planned to be limited to personnel training in Brazil and uranium
                        prospecting techniques and will not include technology transferred from the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_FRG_1"
                            >FRG</gloss>.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                        59, Central Foreign Policy Files, D790357–1212)</note> (D) Brasilia
                        9285;<note n="5" xml:id="d461fn5">Telegram 9285 from Brasilia, October 22,
                        informed the Department that “a Delegation of Brazilian nuclear specialists,
                        headed by NUCLEBRAS President Paulo Nogueira Batista, visited Iraq in early
                        October for further discussion of a possible nuclear agreement between the
                        two countries.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy Files, D790488–0082)</note> (E) Brasilia 4687;<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d461fn6">Telegram 4687 from Brasilia, May 25, relayed
                        Brazilian press reports that “during the visit of the Iraqi Vice President a
                        secret agreement was reached between Iraq and Brazil under which Iraq could
                        obtain plutonium from Brazil.” A spokesman from the Brazilian Foreign
                        Minister “denied ‘categorically’ that Brazil had entered into a secret
                        agreement and said that the report ‘is entirely out of the question.’ He
                        stressed that Brazil does not have functioning nuclear reactors capable of
                        producing plutonium, thus indicating that the transaction could not possibly
                        be implemented.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy Files, D790258–0783)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1167" n="1136" xml:id="pg_1136"/>
                <p> (F) State 290745;<note n="7" xml:id="d461fn7">Telegram 290745 to Brasilia,
                        November 7, informed the Embassy that Carvalho told <persName
                            corresp="#p_PT_1">Pickering</persName> on October 24 that “there was
                        pressure from those in the nuclear energy field in Brazil to terminate
                        nuclear relations with the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> altogether and
                        give the business to <gloss target="#t_URENCO_1">URENCO</gloss> or Brazil’s
                        own enrichment plant when it came on stream, rather than renegotiate the
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-Brazil agreement. Carvalho said that
                        he wanted to continue cooperation with the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >US</gloss> and wanted to find out what the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >US</gloss> was willing to do to avoid a renegotiation and fulfill its
                        supply commitment for Angra I.” <persName corresp="#p_PT_1"
                            >Pickering</persName> said “we were not demanding renegotiation of the
                        agreement but needed confirmation that all of Brazil’s nuclear activities
                        were under safeguards.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files, D790515–1126)</note> (G)
                    Brasilia 9251;<note n="8" xml:id="d461fn8">Telegram 9251 from Brasilia, October
                        20, reported that a Foreign Ministry Energy official “denied a press report
                        of Oct 13 that the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> is planning to
                        renounce its agreement with the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> for
                        cooperation in peaceful uses of atomic energy. He commented that the
                        possibility had not even been raised.” (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files,
                        D790481–0646)</note> (H) Brasilia 8791;<note n="9" xml:id="d461fn9">Telegram
                        8791 from Brasilia, October 5, reported that the Brazilian Minister of Mines
                        had “publicly stated October 1 that the Brazilian nuclear program with West
                        Germany had slowed down and that the eight 1300–MWS originally envisaged
                        under the accord would not be built until 1995 (when the accord expires).
                        Even this estimate appears optimistic according to informed sources which
                        indicate that present plans call for only four power plants to be built by
                        1995.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                        Foreign Policy Files, D790460–0882)</note> (I) Brasilia 10313;<note n="10"
                        xml:id="d461fn10">Telegram 10313 from Brasilia, November 28, reported
                        numerous delays, rising cost estimates, and “an apparently unrealistic
                        schedule calling for completion of the fuel cycle technology transfer by
                        1986 and for all nine reactors of the Brazilian nuclear program to be in
                        operation by 1995 continues to be defended in public by the Minister of
                        Mines and Energy, but statements and plans by other government officials and
                        agencies do not support this.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files, D790553–1042) </note> (J)
                    Brasilia 9281;<note n="11" xml:id="d461fn11">Telegram 9281 from Brasilia,
                        October 22, reported that according to press accounts, General Dirceu
                        Coutinho, the former head of Nucleim, the uranium enrichment subsidiary of
                        NUCLEBRAS, “urged that the Brazilian reactor construction program be
                        suspended after three units presently contractor for, until nuclear power
                        became economically competitive in Brazil and Brazil could develop a viable
                        enrichment system.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                        59, Central Foreign Policy Files, D790487–0329)</note> (K) Brasilia
                        9814.<note n="12" xml:id="d461fn12">Telegram 9814 from Brasilia, November 8,
                        reported a member of the Argentine Embassy “confirmed press reports” that
                        “Argentina and Brazil are negotiating agreement for peaceful nuclear
                        cooperation.” Such cooperation would “cover uranium mining, training, long
                        term research and industrial exchange,” including “one sensitive area: laser
                        production of heavy water.” Representatives from both Argentina and Brazil
                        “ruled out any military or <gloss target="#t_PNE_1">PNE</gloss>
                        application.” The Embassy said “such bilateral cooperation would serve to
                        improve capabilities and hence independence of both nations in nuclear
                        technology. However cooperation could also serve to open each nation’s
                        nuclear programs and to create trust between two potential nuclear rivals.
                        Hence we support Embassy Buenos Aires’ assessment that nuclear cooperation
                        between Brazil and Argentina is on balance in <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                            >US</gloss> interests.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files, D790519–0839)</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. (S—Entire text).</p>
                <p>2. Begin summary: The transition in 1979 from <persName corresp="#p_GE_1"
                        >Geisel</persName> to the Figueiredo administration bought few major changes
                    to Brazilian non-proliferation policies. The <gloss target="#t_GOB_1"
                        >GOB</gloss> continues to refuse to consider the <gloss target="#t_NPT_1"
                        >NPT</gloss>
                    <pb facs="1168" n="1137" xml:id="pg_1137"/> or to waive Tlatelolco into force.
                    It also continues to foreswear any action contravening Tlatelolco’s objectives
                    and any intentions of developing a nuclear explosive device. The major new
                    developments of non-proliferation concern in 1979 were: (a) a more active
                    nuclear diplomacy, with <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> negotiating nuclear
                    arrangements for cooperation in peaceful applications of nuclear energy with
                    Argentina, Venezuela, and, of most concern, Iraq; and (b) a marked slow-down in
                    the nuclear program undertaken with the West Germans. Of the factors causing the
                        <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> to defer decisions to undertake costly
                    new projects envisaged under <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>–<gloss
                        target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> nuclear accord, the troubled economy stands
                    out as the most important and the least susceptible to change. If the nuclear
                    power development continues to drag, there will be correspondingly less
                    incentive to expand future enrichment and reprocessing capabilities beyond the
                    experimental stage. The U.S. continues to have little influence on <gloss
                        target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> nuclear policies. Our early full adherence to
                    the Tlatelolco protocols would be well received here. A clear message to the
                        <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> restating U.S. requirements for
                    continued cooperation—perhaps tied to Tlatelolco protocal adherence—might
                    prepare the way for a resumption of a more active nuclear relationship. End
                    summary.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is the body of the telegram.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
