<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-04-20T11:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-04-20T10:30:00-05:00" n="486" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d486">
                        <head>486. Summary of Conclusions of a Mini-Special Coordination Committee
                                Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d486fn1">Source: Carter
                                Library, National Security Council, Institutional Files, Box 117,
                                SCM 013, Mini-<gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SSOD_1">SSOD</gloss>: 4/20/78. Confidential. The
                                meeting took place in the White House Situation Room. Draft minutes
                                of the meeting are ibid.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1978-04-20T10:30:00-05:00" to="1978-04-20T11:45:00-05:00">April 20, 1978, 10:30–11:45 a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Special Session on
                                Disarmament</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">State</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Gerald Helman</item>
                            <item>Jerome Kahan</item>
                            <item>David Gompert</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Defense</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Lynn Davis</item>
                            <item>Susan Flood</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_YA_1">Adam Yarmolinsky</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WL_1">Lawrence Weiler</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_FCC_1">Charles Flowerree</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Lt. Gen. Arnold Braswell</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SR_1">Sayre</persName> Stevens</item>
                            <item>George Allen</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">AID</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Alexander Shakow</item>
                            <item>Mary Jane Heyl</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Energy</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Donald Kerr</item>
                            <item>Ray E. Chapman</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">White House</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">David Aaron</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Samuel Huntington</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PR_2">Robert Putnam</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The question of whether or not the President should speak at <gloss target="#t_SSOD_1">SSOD</gloss> depends heavily on the content of
                            the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> presentation. If he is to speak,
                            it is highly desirable that the presentation not be limited to <pb facs="1232" n="1201" xml:id="pg_1201"/> the sorts of initiatives
                            currently under study. A Presidential address should offer an ambitious
                            10-Year Disarmament Program, outlining long range goals and objectives
                            for enhancing global security in such areas as strategic arms control
                            and regional stability. <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss> will pull
                            together agency suggestions for a 10-Year Disarmament Program into a
                            draft for <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> review within the next
                            week. No final decision was taken on the date for the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> presentation.</p>
                        <p>A proposal for extending <gloss target="#t_nsa_1">negative security
                                assurances</gloss> beyond the President’s statement of October,
                                1977,<note n="2" xml:id="d486fn2">On October 4, 1977, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> told the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> General Assembly that “In order to
                                reduce the reliance of nations on nuclear weapons, I hereby solemnly
                                declare on behalf of the United States that we will not use nuclear
                                weapons except in self-defense; that is, in circumstances of an
                                actual nuclear or conventional attack on the United States, our
                                territories, or Armed Forces, or such an attack on our allies.” (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, 1977,</hi> pp. 1715–1723)</note> is now
                            being put into final form. Regional bureaus and <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> are particularly concerned about the impact of such an
                            initiative on relations with our allies. More complete information is
                            needed about the probable reactions of key allies. Some of this
                            information may be obtained from the May 2 meeting of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> disarmament experts, at which the
                                <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> proposal for <gloss target="#t_nsa_1">negative security assurances</gloss> may be
                            discussed. When more information on allied attitudes is available and
                            when the options paper has been completed, the issue will be raised for
                            consideration at the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The “eyes and ears of peace” proposal for <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> technical assistance for regional peace-keeping will be
                            considered in the Backstopping Committee next week.<note n="3" xml:id="d486fn3">Reference is to a <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> proposal that the United States provide equipment
                                to monitor compliance with disarmament agreements to nations or
                                regions who requested such assistance.</note> Agencies were urged to
                            make any technical objections to the proposal as precise as
                            possible.</p>
                        <p>Further consideration of our treatment of <gloss target="#t_ERW_1">ERW</gloss> at <gloss target="#t_SSOD_1">SSOD</gloss> will be
                            postponed until additional policy guidance is available.</p>
                        <p>Within the next week, interagency agreement within the Backstopping
                            Committee is anticipated on initiatives on regional confidence-building
                            measures, nuclear accident reporting, and preferences for <gloss target="#t_NPT_1">NPT</gloss> parties. (The offer of fuel cycle
                            services has been deleted from the latter proposal.) Views of State/EA
                            will be solicited on the nuclear accidents initiative. A split paper is
                            anticipated on the Disarmament/Development proposal for a <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Special Development and Security Fund.
                            All these proposals, as well as the report of the group studying the
                            cutoff proposal, will then be submitted to the <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> for decision or endorsement.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>