<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-12-01T10:37:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-12-01T09:37:00-05:00" n="96" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d96">
                        <head>96. Minutes of a Special Coordination Committee Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d96fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                                Security Council, Institutional Files, Box 100, <gloss target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> 170, Chemical Weapons, 12/1/78.
                                Secret. The meeting took place in the White House Situation
                                Room.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1978-12-01T09:37:00-05:00" to="1978-12-01T10:37:00-05:00">December 1, 1978, 9:37–10:37 a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Chemical Weapons (U)</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">State</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Deputy Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Warren
                                    Christopher</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. Jerome Kahan, Deputy Director, Bureau of Politico-Military
                                Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_OSD_1">OSD</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Deputy Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Charles
                                    Duncan</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Lt. Colonel Robert K. Weekley, Assistant for Negotiations and
                                Policy Plans, OSD/ISA</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Acting Director <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Spurgeon
                                    Keeny</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Dr. Robert Mikulak, Staff Officer</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>General David C. Jones, Chairman</item>
                            <item>Lt. General <persName corresp="#p_SG_1">William Y.
                                    Smith</persName>, Assistant to the Chairman</item>
                            <pb facs="0242" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Dr. Karl Weber, Director, Office of Scientific Intelligence</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. Edward R. Jayne, Associate Director for National Security and
                                International Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">White House</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">David Aaron</persName>
                                (Chairman)</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. Leslie G. Denend</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">MINUTES</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">David Aaron</persName> began the meeting at
                            9:37 by calling for views on how the chemical weapons stockpile figures
                            in the deterrence of chemical warfare. <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Duncan</persName> said that the stockpile provides substantial
                            deterrence if we have a true <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss>
                            capability. Jones pointed out that <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss>
                            was not used in World War II because each side had a capability. He
                            agreed with <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Duncan</persName>’s view and
                            added that the U.S. stockpile is not very good and that only a small
                            amount of artillery rounds were deployed in Europe. He felt the U.S.
                            must have a reasonable war-fighting capability along with adequate
                            protection. <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Keeny</persName> acknowledged
                            that the existence of the stockpile has a deterrent role; however, he
                            questioned how effective it was operationally. He felt sure that if the
                            Soviets used <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> they would also have
                            adequate protection. He asked whether the U.S. in light of Congressional
                            and <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> political realities could
                            achieve a credible retaliatory capability. <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Duncan</persName> noted the political problems associated with
                            deployment but added that a <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss>
                            capability was still necessary. Jones added that the likelihood of
                                <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> in Europe could increase as our
                            tactical nuclear advantage narrowed, and added that the deployment of
                            binary munitions would be easier than conventional types. <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Keeny</persName> pointed out that <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> was a potential super neutron bomb in a
                            political sense and said that the Europeans do not even want to think
                            about the prospect of <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> in Europe.
                                <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> observed that
                            there was value in a retaliatory capability, but how it was developed
                            would be affected by three realities: how the allies view it;
                            Congressional reaction; and the prospects in the <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> negotiations. Jayne agreed with <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> and stressed the importance
                            of the political dimension of <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss>. [<hi rend="italic">7 lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">Aaron</persName> outlined the <hi rend="italic">three options</hi> developed in the <gloss target="#t_PRM_1">PRM</gloss>: (1) maintain the stockpile without
                            improvement; (2) undertake steps short of new production facilities to
                            modernize the stockpile; or (3) build a binary facility deferring the
                            production decision. <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Duncan</persName>
                            favored building the binary facility. Jones strongly supported the
                            binary facility. He added that roughly two thirds of the cost of the
                            facility could be recovered in the event of a treaty since it could be
                            used for the destruction of U.S. stocks. <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> disagreed and said that option 2 <pb facs="0243" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/> had not been fully developed.
                            He suggested that modest steps (those at the low end of option 2) might
                            be undertaken to arrest further erosion of the stockpile. He added that
                            to go binary would send very negative political signals. <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Keeny</persName> agreed with <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName>, and Jayne did also.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Duncan</persName> called into question
                            the notion that in reality option 2 would be cheaper than option 3 for
                            similar capabilities. Jones agreed. <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">Aaron</persName> questioned whether formulating the question so
                            that only the binary facility seemed at stake adequately reflected the
                            true scope of the decision at hand. <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Duncan</persName> added that the U.S. needs a <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> capability for deterrence and given
                            that, binary was the best way to go. <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">Aaron</persName> pointed out that it was not a question of whether
                            or not to maintain a stockpile but rather one of which type the U.S.
                            would commit to. He framed the issue for the President as on the one
                            hand replacing and increasing the present stockpile with binary
                            munitions versus more modest steps to improve the effectiveness of the
                            current stockpile with no increase in deployments to Europe. <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> added that option 2 needed
                            to be fleshed out. Jones stated that without a verifiable treaty, we
                            need <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> capability and in the long run,
                            binary is the only way to go. <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> noted that before a decision in favor of
                            binaries was made more information about Congress and our allies was
                            needed. (S)</p>
                        <p>Next, <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Keeny</persName> described the proposed
                            changes to the negotiating instructions. All agreed that the time period
                            allowed for the destruction of facilities should be clarified and made
                            independent of the destruction of stocks. On the conversion of
                            facilities, <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Keeny</persName> said it would
                            only be offered if the Soviets agreed to the higher on-site verification
                            requirements. Jones commented that because there was so much necessary
                            information about Soviet facilities which we did not have that it was
                            premature to discuss conversion. <persName corresp="#p_SG_1">Smith</persName> asked why the decision had to be made now.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Duncan</persName> added that the
                            Soviets are not even prepared to tell us where their facilities are at
                            this point. <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> asked if
                            the negotiators would be willing to agree to explore the topic but agree
                            to nothing. Mikulak responded that up to this point conversion had been
                            mentioned in the talks only to say that if conversion were allowed more
                            intrusive on-site inspection would be required. <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">Aaron</persName> felt that the Delegation should
                            be limited to exploring the conversion issue with the Soviet Delegation.
                            All agreed. Jones added that the Soviets may even prefer destruction
                            because of the on-site inspections associated with conversion. On the
                            issue of bilateral versus multilateral inspection of facilities,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Keeny</persName> explained that this
                            would be an option which might be used only if it proved important in
                            reaching agreement with the Soviets. Jones emphasized that we were
                            seeking a true multilateral convention and that bilateral inspections
                            should not be a part of such an agreement. <persName corresp="#p_DCW_1">Duncan</persName> felt that it was important to talk to our allies
                            about this possibility. <persName corresp="#p_AD_1">Aaron</persName>
                            offered a compromise, stating that <pb facs="0244" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> he sensed there was some receptivity to this idea
                            but that the first step was to talk to our allies. All agreed. The
                            meeting ended at 10:37 a.m. (S)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>