<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>48. Telegram From the United States Delegation at the North Atlantic Council
                    Ministerial Meeting to the to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-12-13T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-12-13T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recLA85IoR5zyxTTT" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006127"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Nuclear power</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="rec0YzQ4Y7ayjLsvS" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="decolonization"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008006757"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">National independence</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-balance" lcsh-match="no_match">Military program</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-12-13T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-12-13T11:00:00-05:00" n="48"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                <head>48. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">United States Delegation at the North
                        Atlantic Council Ministerial Meeting</gloss> to the <gloss type="to"
                        >Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d48fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 740.5/12–1356. Confidential. Transmitted in two sections and repeated
                        to the other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> capitals and
                        Moscow.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-12-13T17:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 13, 1956—5 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Polto1">Polto</gloss> 1408. Subject: Restricted <gloss
                        target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> session 10:30 December 13.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d48fn2">The summary, C–R(56)73, and verbatim, C–VR(56)73, records of
                        this session, both dated December 13, are <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>,
                        Conference Files: Lot 62 D 181, CF 827.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Martino</persName> in chair referred with regret to
                    press leaks again today. <persName corresp="#p_LHM1">Lange</persName> felt
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> press officer should be allowed make
                    little fuller statement on sessions in order provide press more balanced
                    picture. The Secretary approved this. <persName corresp="#p_PLB1"
                        >Pearson</persName> also approved and hoped press officer could correct
                    impression given by press that US and Federal Republic have issued cold blasts
                    yesterday.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_IBHL1">Ismay</persName> announced that in response his
                    request Netherlands and Norway Foreign Ministers had offered prepare first draft
                        communiqué<note n="3" xml:id="d48fn3">Not printed. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid.</hi>, CF 808)</note> which would be circulated delegations for
                    comment before going to council. The Secretary asked permission have record
                    restricted session corrected to eliminate certain errors.</p>
                <pb facs="0174" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/>
                <p>Council then reverted to review of situation (item 2). <persName corresp="#p_BH1"
                        >Brentano</persName> then spoke about situation in Eastern Europe and recent
                    events Hungary. He made following points: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>He agreed with estimate of Secretary that danger was greater. He noted
                            Soviets have recently been re-arming their forces Eastern Europe with
                            modern weapons. USSR by resorting brutal methods could safeguard their
                            line of communications through satellites. And finally he agreed
                            internal difficulties might lead such regime turn to external
                            adventures.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>He felt Hungary events reinforced need for forward strategy in order
                            strengthen <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> as instrument of peace
                            and freedom as <persName corresp="#p_LHM1">Lange</persName> had said.
                            Despite delays <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> is pressing its
                            military program. He welcomed statement of Secretary reaffirming our
                            determination react against aggression. But in addition nuclear power
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> needs conventional forces
                            against limited attack. This of special interest <gloss
                                target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Policy toward satellites should not foster violence but should let
                            situation ripen as it is doing in Poland, encouraging it by economic and
                            political relations, taking care any economic help did not strengthen
                            Soviets. We must seek especially prevent Soviets from stirring up
                            anti-German nationalist feelings in satellites. <gloss
                                target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> reaffirms its pledge not resort
                            force except for defense.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> conscious dangers inherent
                            German split. It has sought moderate reaction in Eastern Zone to recent
                            events. Soviet satellite policy has been shaken but consequences cannot
                            be predicted either with respect future of Gomulka Poland or Soviet
                            position Hungary. Soviets not likely be able re-establish their former
                            domination satellites. The October 30 declaration of Soviets<note n="4"
                                xml:id="d48fn4">See <ref target="#d41fn9">footnote 9, Document
                                    41</ref>.</note> cannot be relied on too much. The new situation
                            might cause new Soviet initiatives on German unity. In general we will
                            have to await developments but <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>
                            will continue discussions with Soviets in close consultation with its
                            allies despite poor prospects.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members should make known to
                            Eastern European peoples their sympathy and support for freedom in area,
                            reassuring them against any efforts interfere their affairs. For this
                            purpose it might be desirable adopt declaration affirming <list>
                                <label>(a)</label>
                                <item>Support for self-government in full freedom</item>
                                <label>(b)</label>
                                <item>Right national independence and freedom from imperialist
                                    subjugation</item>
                                <label>(c)</label>
                                <item>Right determine own social order freely</item>
                                <label>(d)</label>
                                <item>Right be free in internal affairs from military, economic, or
                                    political pressure</item>
                                <label>(e)</label>
                                <item>Support for human rights, and</item>
                                <label>(f)</label>
                                <item>
                                    <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> to insure observance these
                                    obligations.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>He hoped Council might agree these principles.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName> said <persName corresp="#p_BH1"
                        >Brentano</persName> proposal important and should be carefully studied. He
                    doubted, however, Council should say <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                    should insure observance. That would be both inappropriate and impractical. <pb
                        facs="0175" n="147" xml:id="pg_147"/> The Secretary suggested <persName
                        corresp="#p_BH1">Brentano</persName> declaration be referred communiqué
                    committee for inclusion at least essence subject <persName corresp="#p_PLB1"
                        >Pearson</persName>’s comment. In main US sympathized with point of view
                    expressed. In absence objection <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Martino</persName>
                    said statement would be so referred. At suggestion of Secretary, Council then
                    turned to discussion report of three ministers still in restricted session.</p>
                <p>On behalf of three <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Martino</persName> thanked Council
                    for expressions of confidence yesterday and replied to some comments by Council: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>He stressed that report while taking account views Foreign Ministers
                            reflected opinions of three. But recommendations had stated flexibly
                            especially as to political and economic consultation.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>He stressed three had expected consultation only on matters direct or
                            indirect interest to members and that paragraph 47<note n="5"
                                xml:id="d48fn5">Paragraph 47 of the Report of the Committee of Three
                                (see <ref target="#d47fn4">footnote 4, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                                </ref>) stated that there were practical limitations to consultation
                                on foreign policies.</note> should be interpreted this sense.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Replying to Secretary, committee while seeking harmonize policy as much as
                    possible did not intend hamstring US President or establish hierarchy of treaty
                    obligations. He was glad US ready discuss its policy anywhere and recognized it
                    might have to respond to aggression other parts of world even before discussion.
                    Where matter directly affects Atlantic Alliance there should be prior discussion
                    but even there it might not be practical some cases. On attendance by ministers
                    at meetings he was keenly aware criticism about absences himself but urged such
                    attendance “where possible.” He mentioned US had proposed members be represented
                    by top officials who could speak for their governments. He hoped committee would
                    find it possible accept report and suggested turning to resolution for that
                    purpose. <persName corresp="#p_LJMAH1">Luns</persName> then raised question
                    about wording resolution on settlement disputes. He thought it might imply
                    possibility not settling by peaceful means and should be re-drafted to remove
                    this implication. <persName corresp="#p_SPH1">Spaak</persName> felt first
                    question was decide on approval report itself and publication.</p>
                <p>At request <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Martino</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName> then commented on various proposals for
                    changes in text, mainly French and German: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>He was sure <persName corresp="#p_LJMAH1">Luns</persName>’ objection
                            could be met pointing out wording was now same as Article I of
                            treaty.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Regarding paragraph 52(c)<note n="6" xml:id="d48fn6">Reference is
                                apparently to paragraph 51c, which stated that a member government
                                should not, without adequate advance consultation, adopt firm
                                policies or make major political pronouncements on matters which
                                significantly affect the Alliance unless circumstances make such
                                prior consultation obviously impossible.</note> he felt obligation
                            consult was flexibly stated and applied only matters significantly
                            affecting allies. It certainly did not cover all national action or
                            statements. He thought there was no need change language and only feared
                            limitations too broad.</item>
                        <pb facs="0176" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>On paragraph 54(b)<note n="7" xml:id="d48fn7">See <ref
                                    target="#d47fn8">footnote 8, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                                </ref>.</note> committee was willing drop reference “failures”
                            consult as unnecessary in reference annual review by Secretary
                            General.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>On paragraph 58(e)<note n="8" xml:id="d48fn8">See <ref
                                    target="#d47fn8">footnote 8, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                                </ref>.</note> French objected right of Secretary General select
                            three permanent representatives in relation good offices. He explained
                            permanent representatives would not be obliged act without approval
                            their government and hoped this would satisfy French.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>Paragraphs 72 to 74<note n="9" xml:id="d48fn9">Paragraph 72
                                recommended the establishment of a Committee of Economic Advisors
                                under the Council. Paragraph 73 stressed the importance of cultural
                                cooperation among the Allies. Paragraph 74 is discussed in <ref
                                    target="#d47fn15">footnote 15, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                                </ref>.</note> had concerned several delegations. Committee thought
                            paragraph 72 could be left in report and was not harmful even if
                            published. They agreed, however, 73 and 74 might better be transferred
                            confidential covering letter and additional changes made to run it into
                            next section without new heading. French had suggested omission Chapter
                            7 (on organization) but committee felt was desirable publish this except
                            for paragraph 93<note n="10" xml:id="d48fn10">Paragraph 93 recommended
                                the member countries consider the appointment of a high official,
                                who can speak authoritatively for their governments, to be concerned
                                primarily with <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> affairs.</note>
                            dealing with security which they would shift to confidential letter.
                            There upon <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Brentano</persName> said he fully
                            satisfied with explanations. <persName corresp="#p_PCP1"
                                >Pineau</persName> said he too now prepared go along if resolution
                            made clear council only noted report and approved merely conclusions. He
                            would rely Secretary General’s discretion in using right choose three
                            permanent representatives. <persName corresp="#p_PLB1"
                                >Pearson</persName> said committee now favored resolution which
                            merely approved conclusions and which would publish report as that of
                            three ministers.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LJMAH1">Luns</persName> said he still wondered about
                    wisdom publishing some of statement in paragraphs 8, 21, and 26<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d48fn11">Paragraph 8 stated that the political commitment for
                        collective defense is the best deterrent against military aggression.
                        Paragraph 21 recommended a review of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>’s
                        ability to meet effectively the challenge of Soviet penetration of Western
                        Europe under the guise of coexistence. Paragraph 26 warned that while Soviet
                        leaders may place greater emphasis on political, economic, and propaganda
                        action, the high level of Soviet military power will be maintained.</note>
                    which suggested fear aggression had been removed. In reply <persName
                        corresp="#p_LHM1">Lange</persName> felt report made perfectly clear
                    importance <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> maintaining adequate defense
                    even though situation was not static. <persName corresp="#p_LJMAH1"
                        >Luns</persName> said he would bow as majority. <persName corresp="#p_PCP1"
                        >Pineau</persName> then proposed three wise men take last look at report
                    before publishing it to see whether they might want revise few statements or
                    translations. The Secretary endorsed idea of approving only recommendations and
                    suggestion that three ministers take last look in light debate and current
                    situation. <persName corresp="#p_LHM1">Lange</persName> saw merit this proposal
                    as long as three did not have to refer text back to Council. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SPH1">Spaak</persName> questioned whether they should attempt
                    modernize it completely. <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName> said <pb
                        facs="0177" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> they had taken account events Hungary
                    in preparing their draft but felt it useful look it over again.</p>
                <p>Council took up resolution and agreed add paragraph suggested by <persName
                        corresp="#p_LJMAH1">Luns</persName> authorizing three ministers publish it
                    on their own responsibility and approving Secretary’s proposal substitute word
                    “recommendations” for “conclusions.” Revised resolution was then adopted. After
                    brief discussion, resolution on disputes was also adopted with addition words in
                    preamble and first operative paragraph making reference paragraph I of
                        treaty.<note n="12" xml:id="d48fn12">For text of the Resolution on the
                        Peaceful Settlement of Disputes and Differences Between Members of the North
                        Atlantic Treaty Organization, the Resolution on the Report of the Committee
                        of Three on Non-Military Co-operation in <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss>, and the Report of the Committee of Three on Non-Military
                        Co-operation in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, released by the
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Information Division on December
                        14, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, January 7,
                        1957, pp. 17–28.</note> Meeting then adjourned until 3:30 for discussion
                    political directive (item 4) which would be held in restricted session but with
                    two additional advisors.<note n="13" xml:id="d48fn13">See <gloss
                            target="#t_Polto1">Polto</gloss> 1422, <ref target="#d49">
                            <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
