<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-03-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="55" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d55">
                        <head>55. Message From the <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                            Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1" type="to">Adenauer</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d55fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                Central Files, 740.5/3–1757. Top Secret. Transmitted in telegram
                                2539 to Bonn, March 17, with the instruction that it be delivered to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>. Bonn was also
                                instructed to add orally that the United States had unsuccessfully
                                attempted “at the highest level” to postpone the British
                                action.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-03-17"><hi rend="italic">March 17,
                                1957</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>I have received your message regarding the proposed reduction in British
                            forces on the continent.<note n="2" xml:id="d55fn2">Reference is to a
                                message from <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> delivered to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> by
                                    <persName>Pauls</persName> of the German Embassy in Washington
                                on March 15 in which the Chancellor again expressed his deep concern
                                about the British plan to reduce forces in Germany. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Presidential Correspondence: Lot 66 D
                                204, German Officials with <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>
                                1953–57) On February 12, <persName corresp="#p_KHL1">Krekeler</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> he had been asked by <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> to find out what the U.S.
                                position was regarding the proposed reduction of British forces in
                                Germany and specifically whether the U.S. Government had agreed or
                                disagreed with the proposals. (Memorandum of conversation by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RJJ1">Reinstein</persName>, February 12,
                                scheduled for publication in a forthcoming <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi> volume.)</note> I wholly share your concern
                            regarding these proposals, particularly with regard to the possibility
                            that they might be followed by actions in other countries. As you <pb facs="0194" n="166" xml:id="pg_166"/> know, I discussed this matter
                            with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_BH1">von Brentano</persName>
                            when he was in Washington two weeks ago.<note n="3" xml:id="d55fn3"><persName corresp="#p_BH1">Von Brentano</persName> visited
                                Washington, March 3–7, for talks with U.S. officials on topics of
                                mutual concern.</note> I pointed out to him that we must recognize
                            that the British are under a serious economic and financial strain and
                            that we had reluctantly and after much effort come to the conclusion
                            that a reduction in British forces on the continent was unavoidable. It
                            seemed to me that we should try to make the reduction as gradual as
                            possible and as consistent as possible with the military views of <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>As you know, <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss> has made certain
                            recommendations with regard to the British proposals which he considers,
                            if adopted, would go a long way toward mitigating the effects from a
                            military viewpoint, provided that other countries maintain their force
                            goals. I believe that, if it were publicly known that the British had
                            generally met <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss>’s views, this
                            would do a great deal to avoid the psychological and political effects
                            of the proposal which have concerned us all.</p>
                        <p>I feel that, after we have done all we can, we must make the utmost
                            effort to avoid an open break over this matter, which I feel would have
                            the most grave effects on the alliance. I doubt very seriously that the
                            British would be able to agree to a postponement by a full year of their
                            plans, as you have proposed. It seems to me that we must also consider
                            what the effect would be of announcing a review of our over-all <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> defense position in the light of the
                            British proposal. If the public gained the impression that the <gloss target="#t_UKG1">UK</gloss> proposals raised issues of such
                            seriousness, we might well have set in motion the very forces which we
                            have been anxious in all of our considerations of the British proposals
                            to avoid.</p>
                        <p>My own view is that we should reach an agreement now on the best position
                            which we can get the British to accept. This I think will enable us best
                            to preserve our unity. I hope that you will give these thoughts your
                            most earnest consideration in connection with the instructions given to
                            your representatives in London.<note n="4" xml:id="d55fn4">On March 27,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHL1">Krekeler</persName> delivered
                                    <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>’s reply. The
                                Chancellor thanked <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> for
                                his letter indicating that the results of the <gloss target="#t_WEU1">WEU</gloss> Council meeting in London, March
                                15–18, demonstrated to all participants the need to “keep their
                                unity and solidarity alive.” <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> expressed the hope that further discussions
                                in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> would occur “in the same
                                spirit and will lead to fruitful decisions.” (Department of State,
                                Presidential Correspondence: Lot 66 D 204, German Officials with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> 1953–57)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>