<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Wharton to Mr.
                                Grant..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1891</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1891-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1891-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205" lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-08-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="20" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d20">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wharton</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Grant</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-08-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 10,
                            1891</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 134.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the receipt of your No.
                        173, of the 27th ultimo, in relation to the case of Mr. Mazel, who was born
                        in this city on September 17, 1869, and who is consequently now nearly 22
                        years of age. At the time of his birth his father was the minister of the
                        Netherlands at this capital and had married an American woman. In 1871 the
                        family removed to Europe, and they have successively resided in Stockholm,
                        St. Petersburg, and Vienna, at each of which places Mr. Mazel, senior, has
                        served his Government in a diplomatic capacity. You state that it is now
                        young Mr. Mazel’s wish to come to this country and be a citizen thereof, and
                        you inquire whether, in view of his birth in the United States, he can claim
                        citizenship here without awaiting the lapse of a period of five years and
                        performing the ordinary conditions of naturalization.</p>
                <p>The Department is of opinion that Mr. Mazel can enjoy the privileges of
                        citizenship in the United States only after naturalization in the ordinary
                        way. Section 1992 of the Revised Statutes of the United States reads as
                        follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>All persons born in the United States and not subject to any foreign
                                power,* * * are declared to be citizens of the United States.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>There has been not a little diversity of opinion as to the scope to be given
                        to the words “not subject to any foreign power” in the section just quoted,
                        but it does not appear ever to have been doubted that the child of a
                        diplomatic officer came within the class whose birth in the United States
                        did not warrant a claim to citizenship. In this relation it is proper to
                        refer to the case of <hi rend="italic">McKay</hi> v. <hi rend="italic">Campbell</hi>, 2 Sawyer, 118, in which it is stated that the “children
                        of ambassadors” form an exception to the rule as to persons being born in
                        the allegiance of a sovereign who are born on his soil.</p>
                <p>It is not thought that the fact of Mr. Mazel having married an American woman
                        affects the case, since legitimate children follow the status of their
                        father.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William F. Wharton</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
