<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Denby to Mr. Blaine..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1891</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d373</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">373</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1891-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1891-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="373"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d373">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Blaine</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-06-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 28, 1891</hi>.</date> (Received August
                        17.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1330.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With the view of keeping you informed of the
                    condition of things in China, I have the honor to inclose a copy of a letter
                    from a missionary doctor at Liao Yang, in Manchuria, describing some of the
                    reports that are circulated amongst the people against foreigners.</p>
                <p>That credence should be given to rumors that foreigners buy lice, poison them,
                    and scatter them among the people, and that they poison eggs would seem
                    incredible if we did not know that more improbable stories have already caused
                    twenty riots. My advices are that great disaffection exists in Manchuria.</p>
                <p>The secret societies are at the bottom of it, of which the Tsai Li is supposed to
                    be the most important. Antiforeign placards have been posted in Manchuria, but
                    Gen. Tso, who cooperated heartily with the missionaries in relief work some
                    years ago, is confident of his power to protect the missionaries. He is a
                    Mohammedan.</p>
                <p>At Newchwang the residents seem to think that there is no danger of a riot, but
                    they live in dread nevertheless.</p>
                <p>The excitement prevailing in central and western China has not reached the south.
                    If it ever becomes rife among the excitable people of that section, I fear that
                    dreadful scenes will be enacted.</p>
                <p>For some days now there has been no new report of outrages. It is to be feared
                    that the summer inundations, with their attendant starvation and misery, will
                    greatly aggravate the unfavorable conditions now existing in China.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0520" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 1330.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName type="from">Westwater</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Bandinel</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Liao Yang</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-06-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 17, 1891</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear</hi> Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bandinel</hi>: * * *
                        Regarding your query as to the state of Chinese feeling with reference to
                        foreigners in this province, there is no doubt whatever that at present
                        there is considerable and widespread excitement. At our return from Moukden
                        I found the city in a great state of excitement and a great many absurd
                        rumors afloat. Some of these I may mention: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>The foreigners were buying lice at 2 or 3 cash each; they gave
                                them poison and then scattered them abroad among the people, and
                                their bite was fatal in a very short time. This may seem a very
                                absurd story, but it was sufficient to have a very powerful effect
                                on the people. A man was actually found buying these animals, and,
                                on being asked who for, he said it was for the hospital; he
                                unfortunately made off before he could be got hold of. It was also
                                given out that at the great spring fair held here last month these
                                poisonous lice would be thrown among the people, and the result was
                                a very meager attendance at the festival and theater.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>Eggs also were said to be poisoned, and these were a drug in the
                                market for some time.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>Tufts of hair were said to have been mysteriously cut off from the
                                heads of many in the city, and special cord was sold in the streets
                                guarantied to act as a charm and effectually prevent this
                                disaster.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Then they heard that there had been difficulties in the south and a lot of
                        foreign gunboats at Tien-Tsin, etc. Next, when we left for Moukden, the
                        story got abroad that we had all fled to foreigndom; crowds went off to see
                        the new premises that we are building and, it being Sunday, work was
                        stopped, and this fact was taken as proof positive that we had cleared out.
                        At my return I received cards and inquiries from all directions, and,
                        finding really very great excitement among the great majority of the people,
                        I at once showed myself in the streets and rode up and down the city a good
                        deal during the next few days.</p>
                    <p>After our return I found the excitement rapidly subside, and matters now are
                        perfectly quiet again. During the three first days of the Chinese month when
                        the dispensary was opened the attendance was only about 15 patients a day,
                        instead of from 70 to 100, which showed the scare the people were in.</p>
                    <p>The “lice” story is not local, but is circulated all over the province, and I
                        have no doubt it is the work of one of the secret societies.</p>
                    <p>Of the stories afloat in Liao Yang the “lice” story was the one distinctly
                        ascribed to us, but for the others the people blamed the Pai-lien Chiao, or
                        White Lily sect, as well as the foreigners. I don’t think, however, the sect
                        is very powerful here.* * *</p>
                    <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Macdonald Westwater</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
