<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-09-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-09-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="392" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d392">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blaine</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-09-21"><hi rend="italic">September 21, 1891</hi>.</date>
                            (Received November 10.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 1390.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose a clipping from
                        the North China Daily News of the 11th instant, which gives the fullest
                        account that I have seen of the recent riot at Ichang.</p>
                    <p>You will notice that at Ichang the first mission that was attacked was the
                        small station of the American Episcopal Mission to which no wrong whatever
                        was imputed. In this as in all other cases the mob did not distinguish
                        between foreigners, but attacked all alike.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby</hi>.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 1390.—From the North
                                China Daily News, September 11, 1891.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ichang riot—from an eyewitness and
                            sufferer</hi>.</head>
                        <p>For several months a riot at Ichang has been feared by those having
                            access to reliable sources of information, yet at 12:30 p.m., on
                            Wednesday, 2d September, it came like a thunderbolt from a clear sky,
                            taking the most wary by surprise, and the programme was carried out with
                            a thoroughness and dispatch which are altogether unprecedented. There
                            was no indication of danger until the signal of attack was given, and in
                            twenty minutes all was over. Nothing was left to chance; everything was
                            carefully planned, and in no sense can the Ichang riot be attributed to
                            popular excitement or the rash act of a European. The pretext for
                            collecting a crowd was cunningly devised. On Tuesday, 1st September, a
                            child was brought to the Roman Catholic convent, and the ordinary papers
                            were duly signed making it over to the Sisters. The child was
                            represented to be a girl (only girls were received at the convent), and
                            when it was discovered to be a boy the circumstance caused some
                            uneasiness. On Wednesday morning parties appeared at the convent
                            declaring their child had been stolen and saying it was within. In due
                            course the child was produced and delivered to the claimants. Meanwhile
                            a crowd had collected, but nothing serious was suspected, although, as
                            was proper under the circumstances, information was sent to the
                            magistrate. But the ringleaders had also gone clamoring to the yamén,
                            collecting the dregs of the city as they went along. Instead of shutting
                            the yamên doors and keeping all parties concerned under restraint until
                            the case was investigated, the magistrate, with his runners and
                            bodyguard, proceeded to the convent, taking the crowd from the city
                            along with him. The military commandant of the rank of chêntai was also
                            on the scene with a large number of soldiers, and <pb facs="0550" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/> some show was made of protecting the
                            convent. All at once a rush was made for the house in the adjoining
                            compound, belonging to the American Episcopal Mission. The gate was
                            smashed in, two trumpets were blown, and a man, beating his breast,
                            shouted out: “Come on, brothers, slay the foreigners; I am willing to
                            die for you.” The riot had commenced, yet up to the last moment so
                            paltry did the whole thing appear, and so little sign was there of
                            anything stirring going to happen, that the coolies whom the Rev. Mr.
                            Sowerby had carrying earth in the compound never left off their work or
                            went to see what was doing next door.</p>
                        <p>In came the rioters with a rush, one of the foremost men snatching a
                            spade from a cooly and aiming a murderous blow at Mr. Sowerby, who
                            managed to disarm this assailant and evade another. The coolies shouted
                            at him to run for his life, and none too soon, for the mob was of the
                            most desperate character and bent on murder from the very first. By
                            jumping a fence and running for life, Mr. Sowerby was just able, to
                            reach the consulate in an exhausted condition, with a sprained ankle,
                            and exposed hatless to the midday sun. From the consulate Mr. Sowerby
                            was able to get on board the <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi> with no
                            further adventure.</p>
                        <p>To set fire to the American mission house was the work of an instant, and
                            as soon as the signal of destruction was given yamên runners and
                            soldiers fell back, nor did either military or civil mandarins give a
                            single order to protect life or property. It is particularly to be noted
                            that against Mr. Sowerby, whose house was the first to be burned, there
                            was not even the semblance of a grudge. In less time than it takes to
                            write it the torch was applied to the convent, the Sisters, seven in
                            number and of various nationalities (French, German, and British),
                            escaping as best they could down a lane to the river, escorted by Father
                            Braun, a very powerful man and formerly an officer in the German army.
                            To give them their due, officials and soldiers also escorted the
                            Sisters. The mandarins seemed to receive some rough usage, the chêntai’s
                            hat being knocked off, an indignity which the natives speak of with
                            bated breath, and evidently consider of more gravity than anything else
                            that has occurred. As soon as the steep bank of the river was reached
                            the Sisters were thrown headlong over it by the very soldiers who had
                            aided in their protection so far, an incident fortunately noticed
                            onboard the <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi>, which was anchored opposite,
                            and Capt. Lewis instantly launched a boat, which proceeded to the rescue
                            and found the Sisters and Father Braun exposed to the full fury of a
                            shower of missiles in a sampan, without oars, into which they had
                            scrambled. The ship’s boat took the sampan in tow, and the whole party
                            were soon in safety on board the <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi>, which
                            had steam up to run down any boat loads of rioters who might attempt to
                            board, and was defended by the repeating rifles of Capt. Lewis, Mr.
                            Moore, and Mr. Grouleff. Right down to the river bank the orphans in the
                            convent had clung to the Sisters, but here they were violently seized by
                            the soldiers and kept back. It is suspected that a number of children
                            must have been burned in the convent; one, unable to walk, could not
                            have escaped. On reaching the <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi> the Sisters
                            presented a pitiable sight, their long robes being covered with blood,
                            and one has been so badly wounded that she is still unable to rise.
                            Father Braun, who acted nobly throughout, shielding the Sisters with his
                            own person, has received a very severe cut on the head, not to mention
                            contusions and bruises all over his body.</p>
                        <p>From the convent the rioters made a rush to the river front and went
                            tearing down the Bund, the ringleaders armed with pickaxes and knives,
                            and the rest with such weapons as they could lay their hands on.</p>
                        <p>Down the lane at the end of the consulate and along the street in front
                            of it they swept with the violence of a tropical storm, but not a finger
                            was lifted against the consulate. The house, owned by a native—a
                            mandarin’s secretary—in which the Rev. Mr. Deans and Dr. Pirie, of the
                            Church of Scotland Mission, lived; Capt. Cain’s house (empty), the mat
                            shed in front of Messrs. Jardine, Matheson &amp; Co.’s godown, Mr.
                            Creagh’s house, inhabited by Dr. Aldridge, Of the customs, and the
                            Franciscan Mission, were fired simultaneously. The pickaxes made short
                            work of the doors, and no time was wasted by the slightest attempt to
                            loot. Mr. Cockburn was in a boat on the river within 50 yards of the
                            scene and saw the whole thing done with a quickness and precision which
                            leave no room to doubt that all had been planned beforehand, and that
                            each man knew exactly what to do, a conclusion which is forced home by
                            the fewness of the numbers of the active rioters, not over half a
                            hundred at the outside, and the strange coincidence that no attempt
                            whatever was made to burn Mr. Cockburn’s own house, which adjoins
                            Messrs. Jardine, Matheson &amp; Co.’s on the one side and Dr. Aldridge’s
                            on the other.</p>
                        <p>This is what took place at one house, and it is substantially what took
                            place at all: As soon as the door was staved in the boy was seized and
                            at the risk of his life asked to point out where the foreigner kept his
                            silver. “He keeps none, but changes Hankow checks at the native cash
                            shops.” “Then where is your kerosene tin?” and the house was blazing in
                            an instant.</p>
                        <p>The plans were well laid, and, what is far more difficult to secure, the
                            ringleaders kept perfect command all through the proceedings. As has
                            been remarked, Messrs. Jardine, <pb facs="0551" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/> Matheson &amp; Co.’s property was fired and the mat shed burned down.
                            On this their Chinese agent and compradores fell on their knees and
                            implored the rioters not to burn the godown, as it contained only goods
                            belonging to natives. The request was granted on condition that the
                            goods were removed within three days, when the godown would be burned. A
                            petition was also made that Mr. Cockburn’s house might be spared, as it
                            adjoined the godown, and the one would set fire to the other. A mandarin
                            was also in Mr. Cockburn’s compound vociferating, “Do not burn Mr.
                            Coekburn’s house; you all know him; he has been here over ten years and
                            does works of charity (<hi rend="italic">hao-sz</hi>); take anything you
                            want, but do not burn his house.” Some sinologue may be able to explain
                            whether it would be more honorable to have one’s goods stolen than
                            burned as being too vile for a Chinaman to handle. One fact is clear;
                            the original plan was to loot and not to burn the house of the Rev. Mr.
                            Coekburn, of the Church of Scotland Mission. With the celerity with
                            which all others were fired by the ringleaders, who carried kerosene and
                            gunpowder along with them, all entreaties to spare it came too late.</p>
                        <p>As for the consulate, a native building belonging to Mr. Little, it was
                            never attacked, and the consul remained inside in perfect security. No
                            pretense of protecting it by soldiers was made until all was over.</p>
                        <p>There is a shrewd suspicion that the ringleaders may have taken their cue
                            from a remark of his excellency the viceroy of the province, that those
                            murdered at Wusueh were nobody in particular, and concluded that so long
                            as they kept their hands off officials the punishment meted out would
                            not be grievous.</p>
                        <p>True to the traditions of the service, the customs staff stood to arms,
                            but had only to present their bayonets to keep back stragglers, for here
                            also the rioters made no real attack. Yet they made it sufficiently
                            clear that their favors were distributed to all foreigners with strict
                            impartiality. The land bought for the site of a new custom-house was
                            taken possession of, the fine tennis lawn destroyed, and such other
                            mischief done as the place afforded opportunity.</p>
                        <p>At the new consulate, in course of building, the strong gate of the
                            compound was broken to pieces, the teakwood doors and window frames torn
                            from their positions, the place becoming a thorough wreck. All the wood
                            and builders’ materials and quantities of the very bricks were carried
                            off, and at the date of writing the public are freely helping themselves
                            to whatever remains.</p>
                        <p>A freak of the riot which would tax even the perfervid imagination of the
                            author of Defensio Populii to explain is that the extensive mission
                            premises of the Church of Scotland, within the city, remain intact. Up
                            to the very moment of the riot, male and female schools, dispensary,
                            hospital, not to speak of that terrible red rag preaching in the church
                            both forenoon and afternoon, were carried on.</p>
                        <p>Amidst all the ferment the very existence of the mission was overlooked
                            alike by mandarins and rowdies. The only people who manifested the
                            slightest interest were the patients, who came in nearly the usual
                            number and took no pains to conceal their annoyance that Dr. Pirie was
                            prevented from attending to them in the ordinary way. Not till Friday
                            did the mission receive any attention. Long before that time the Bund
                            was covered with the tents of soldiers guarding the blackened and
                            battered ruins. Already some twenty scholars, children of heathen
                            parents, had resumed their places in the school; but casual remarks were
                            now heard on the street that the premises had been left without official
                            recognition or protection.</p>
                        <p>The schoolmaster now went to the yamên and stated that when all the
                            officials had gone out of the city and proved themselves unable to
                            prevent a riot, he had remained at his post and succeeded in preventing
                            any mischief being done to property within the city walls; but the time
                            had come when he must either be told to leave, in which case the
                            property would be left to its fate, or something must be done to show
                            publicly that the place was protected. A ray of hope dawned on the
                            magistrate at once. He could at least report all foreign property within
                            the city to be safe and sound. Without delay four runners were sent by
                            the chihsien, and a like number by the chifu, with strict injunctions to
                            arrest anyone causing the slightest annoyance. The American Episcopal
                            Mission in a native house within the city, the Roman Catholic Mission
                            within the city, also in a native house, and the Church of Scotland
                            Mission station outside the north gate are all of them safe. No
                            protection was given, but everything was as quiet as on ordinary
                            occasions. If Christianity be offensive to the Chinese and mission work
                            felt to be a grievance, it is passing strange that the very centers of
                            proselyting should not have a single stone cast at them. What happened
                            at Ichang should convince all parties that it is not this or that
                            individual class of Europeans that is aimed at, but all Europeans,
                            without distinction of nationality or occupation.</p>
                        <p>But it is time to tell how it fared with the residents about whom you
                            have not already heard. They were Mrs. Roberts and daughter, of
                            Shanghai, visitors to Ichang; Mr. and Mrs. Coekburn and five children,
                            Dr. Pirie, Mr. Deans, and Mr. McNair, of the C. I. M., from Shasi. After
                            a variety of adventures and remarkable concomitances of favorable
                            incidents, all reached the steamship <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi> in
                            safety, for which a debt of <pb facs="0552" n="446" xml:id="pg_446"/>
                            gratitude is due to Capt. Lewis, the ship’s boat in command of Mr.
                            Grouleff having not only rescued the Roman Catholic missionaries, but
                            also picked up Dr. Pirie, Mr. Deans, and Mr. McNair, similarly exposed
                            to a shower of stones, in a sampan with a broken oar.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Cockburn brought off Mrs. Roberts and daughter with his own family to
                            the steamer, and immediately returned to see if he could carry from his
                            house a few things of special value that can never be replaced. He was
                            too late, but succeeded in getting an excellent view of what actually
                            took place. Seeing numbers of soldiers mixed in the crowd, he insisted
                            on the boatman putting him ashore, feeling confident he would be
                            protected from personal violence. The reply he got was, “Soldiers will
                            not strike soldiers.” “That one, and that one, and that one,” pointing
                            to men armed with pickaxes and foremost in the riot, “these are all
                            soldiers with their coats of.” Seeing how matters stood, and with stones
                            coming from the shore fast an thick, there was no help for it but to
                            return to the steamer by a long detour.</p>
                        <p>Were anything more needed to show the utter helplessness and incompetence
                            of the mandarins the proof is not far to seek. On Wednesday afternoon
                            two of the customs staff walked down to Mr. Cockburn’s house, and amidst
                            the general wreck particularly noticed that the carpet was still on the
                            sitting-room floor, whilst the compound was already occupied by a
                            lieutenant and company of soldiers, who, to make doubly sure that no
                            stragglers should enter, had barricaded the door and pitched a tent
                            across it. Mr. Cockburn and Dr. Pirie went to the house on Thursday and
                            found the carpet gone, the floor bearing evidence of the tacks having
                            been carefully extracted. The inevitable conclusion is that the carpet
                            was appropriated by the lieutenant himself. During the whole time the
                            Bund has been full of mandarins on horseback and in chairs rubbing
                            shoulders with people openly carrying away plunder of every description,
                            from half-burnt wood to a silver tea service, which was observed to be
                            taken to a house next door to a yamên. By Friday everything worth taking
                            was gone, and then the official wrath burst forth against the poor
                            people who came to get a little firewood cheaply.</p>
                        <p>Crowds of those caught with burdens of charred wood have been lodged in
                            the yamên, but the mandarins durst not lay a finger on any of the real
                            criminals. They are no doubt prepared to inflict any punishment demanded
                            by foreign powers on the miserable creatures they have arrested, the
                            very utmost limit of whose offenses does not exceed petty theft. More
                            than all this, there was an open attempt to commence the riot ten days
                            before it actually occurred. At that date three Chinese entered the
                            Scotch Mission by the back door, loudly demanding to be shown the place
                            where the foreigners picked out children’s eyes. Making their way to the
                            church, in which a native helper was preaching, they commenced tossing
                            the seats about and shouting abuse which need not be repeated. Then
                            seeing the various proclamations which have been issued in reference to
                            the riots on the lower river posted up in front of the church, one of
                            them went up to them and shouted out, “These too are fabrications of the
                            foreigners; not one of them is genuine, nor bears the proper seals; I am
                            an official myself and know the seals to be forgeries; see, here is a
                            proper seal,” pulling something from his pocket. By this time a crowd
                            had collected; but, contrary to expectation, the people of the
                            neighborhood, among them a military graduate, stoutly interfered, saying
                            they all knew what was done in the mission and they would permit no
                            disturbance to be raised by such slanderous statements. Then, taking him
                            by the shoulders, they forcibly ejected him and saw him in safety to his
                            home. What he said was not all false. He actually turned out to be a
                            military officer named Wang, of the rank of wai-wei. Through the consul,
                            who personally examined the witnesses, the chêntai was informed of what
                            had taken place, and a reply was received that Mr. Wang had got a black
                            mark put against his name, three of them being enough to ruin a man.
                            After what has transpired, the sooner the other two black marks are
                            added the better.</p>
                        <p>The bearing Ichang has on the rest of China can not be appreciated
                            without knowing that the chêntai is an official of exceptional honesty
                            and energy, who has hitherto been regarded with good reason as very
                            friendly to Europeans. For China his soldiers are in an excellent state
                            of discipline. But he is a Hunan man, and his soldiers are from Hunan.
                            Hunan people in the employment of officials are at the bottom of
                            everything. Of the chihsien not much need be said. He was on the Chinese
                            commission as to steamers running to Chungking, and was looked up to as
                            a sort of leader, having had experience in dealing with foreigners at
                            some former period of his career. Such a name did he make for himself
                            when the steamship <hi rend="italic">Killing</hi> was stopped from going
                            to Chungking that he is now made the ruler of Ichang.</p>
                        <p>There is but one recommendation to make as to settlement. Let the
                            punishment fall on the officials, the only culpable if not criminal
                            parties that can be found. Let there be no demand for the cutting off of
                            heads; the creatures taken into custody on Friday are deserving only of
                            our pity.</p>
                        <p>The writer can not conclude without a public acknowldgement to Capt.
                            Lewis, <pb facs="0553" n="447" xml:id="pg_447"/> Mr. Moore, and Mr.
                            Grouleff, of the steamship <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi>, the only
                            parties who could render assistance to those in danger. The customs
                            staff could and would have made short work of the rioters before they
                            had gone very far; the most courageous of Hunan braves respect a
                            foreigner with a rifle. Greatly to their own chagrin, they had no option
                            but to stay on the customs premises. The kindness shown to the fugitives
                            on board the steamship <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi> was unbounded.
                            Rooms, wardrobes—everything was placed at their service and pressed on
                            their acceptance, those in command sleeping on deck. Those who were at
                            Ichang on the 2d of September have no higher hope than to be near
                            practical seamen in the next trouble they may get into.</p>
                        <p>It only remains to be stated that those in the riot simply escaped in the
                            clothes they stood in. They saved absolutely nothing, and the houses
                            fired were burned to the ground. Mr. Cockburn’s house is as completely
                            wrecked and ruined as if it had been burned with the rest. Without a
                            single hitch the rioters carried out their plans with thoroughness with
                            the single exception of Messrs. Jardine, Matheson &amp; Co.’s godown,
                            where a compromise was effected. Fortunately there has been no loss of
                            life, but infuriated men brandishing knives mean murder, and had the <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi> not been in port there would have been a
                            sadder tale to tell.</p>
                        <p>Another correspondent, under date 4th instant, says that the mob, after
                            burning down Capt. Cain’s house, pulled down the walls and uprooted the
                            trees in the compound. The foreigners, to the number of nine, were under
                            arms to protect the consulate and customs. They each received 20 rounds
                            of ball ammunition, but did not need to fire their guns, for their
                            bayonets were sufficient to keep the mob back. The <hi rend="italic">Paohua</hi> was kept back until the arrival of the <hi rend="italic">Tehhsing</hi>. The people in the city were still very
                            excited on the 4th, but otherwise things were quiet. The mandarins,
                            however, were quite unable to cope with the rioters. None of the C. N.
                            Co.’s property was burnt.</p>
                        <p>From another letter we learn that the mob on the 3d threatened to blow up
                            the custom-house with bags of gunpowder, but fortunately they did not
                            carry out their threat.</p>
                        <p>Information received by Her Britannic Majesty’s office of works at
                            Shanghai confirms the news of the destruction of the new British
                            consulate at Ichang. At the time of the outbreak the walls, which were
                            of brick, had reached a height of about 4 feet from the ground, and the
                            scaffolding had just been fixed. The rioters tore down the scaffolding
                            and all the woodwork and carried it off, besides knocking down all the
                            brickwork they had time to attend to. All the materials for the building
                            had been sent from Shanghai, a process which will now have to be
                            repeated at Ichang’s expense.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Correspondence—Wusueh and Ichang.</hi>.</head>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">To the Editor of the North China Daily
                                News</hi>.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In the September number of the Messenger,
                            just to hand, there is an account given of the Wusueh riots, in which
                            the following sentences occur: The crowd were about to proceed to
                            further roughness, when luckily the erh-fu arrived in the nick of time
                            with his guard and rescued the ladies and the children they had with
                            them. Great credit is due to the erh-fu for his humane and resolute
                            conduct on this occasion. He took and sheltered the refugees in his
                            yamên, where they had the happiness of being reunited to some of their
                            children who had been missing during the progress of the whole
                            riot.”</p>
                        <p>As the above account of the erh-fu’s conduct is quite misleading, and as
                            it is very important that all the information published at this time on
                            matters connected with these riots should be thorougly trustworthy, I
                            shall feel obliged if you will find space for the insertion of the
                            following statement of facts in the columns of the Daily News. Being
                            based upon information received direct from C. T. Gardner, esq., Her
                            Britannic Majesty’s consul at Hankow, the statement may be regarded as
                            perfectly reliable. At Wusueh there are three Chinese officials. The
                            head official is called the erh-fu; the other two are called lungpingsze
                            and the makowsze. On the evening of the 5th of June Mr. Green was on
                            duty by the river with Mr. Argent, who was waiting for the steamer to
                            return to Hankow in it. The ladies were quietly sitting at home. At 7
                            p.m. a mob broke into the ladies houses and set fire to them. The ladies
                            had just time to get their children and try to fly, accompanied by two
                            native servants and some native Christians. The streets were crowded
                            with men, who struck the ladies and children with poles. Some of the mob
                            only <pb facs="0554" n="448" xml:id="pg_448"/> pretended to strike, and
                            really warded off blows. Two of the ladies, Mrs. Boden and Mrs. Warren,
                            got separated from the other and went for protection to the official
                            residence of the makowsze, who, in spite of the entreaties of his own
                            women folks, turned them out to the fury of the mob. Afterwards these
                            two ladies and two children got into the mat hut of a market gardener,
                            who allowed them to lie on his wife’s bed, and there they remained,
                            wounded and sore, but safe. The other lady, Mrs. Protheroe, also managed
                            to get into the official residence of the makowsze, but he turned her
                            out in the same brutal way he had turned out the other ladies.</p>
                        <p>The Christians appealed again and again to the erh-fu for men to quell
                            the riot, but he refused. The lungpingsze, on the other hand, was doing
                            his duty. He applied three times to the erh-fu for men, and the erh-fu
                            each time refused. The solitary lady, Mrs. Protheroe, was still exposed
                            to the fury of the mob, when a man said: “I will have her ring,” and,
                            seizing her by the hand, dragged her through the mob to the erh-fu’s
                            residence. Here he turned suddenly round, faced the mob, and threatened
                            it that if they touched the lady they should be punished. The erh-fu
                            kept Mrs. Protheroe at his door for more than fifteen minutes, and was
                            only persuaded by the threats of Chinese friendly to us to open it and
                            give her shelter. He was also induced by the same threats and the
                            earnest entreaties of Mrs. Protheroe to send and search for the other
                            ladies and the children. Not till Mrs. Protheroe was admitted was any
                            attempt made to discover, help, or rescue the other ladies. But they
                            were actually rescued by the Christians, with the help of a few of the
                            more well-disposed heathen. One child was being carried by a Christian.
                            The Christian was knocked down; the baby, however, was caught up by a
                            native woman (a non-Christian), who faced the fury of the mob for
                            three-quarters of an hour and declared that they should rather kill her
                            than the innocent child. One child was hidden in a cellar by one of the
                            missionary’s servants. This boy, a lad of 17, went to warn Mr. Argent
                            and Mr. Green of what was happening. He met Messrs. Green and Argent,
                            who, seeing the conflagration, were coming to put it out. He begged them
                            to turn back, but of course they would not. The mob was very violent,
                            and Argent tried to escape by running into a shoemaker’s shop. The
                            shoemaker cried out, “Kill him outside and not in my shop.” Argent was
                            pushed outside the shop and brutally killed, in spite of the efforts of
                            the Chinese boy to save him, by having his brains dashed out with huge
                            blocks of stone used as hammers. Green escaped into a pond, where he
                            remained two hours, but at last came out under the promise that his life
                            would be spared. When he came out he was hacked in pieces by swords.</p>
                        <p>The Christians found and took the other two ladies to the erh-fu’s
                            residence, whence in a short time they were taken on board the steamer
                            and brought to Hankow.</p>
                        <p>Such is the true story of this riot. The lungpingsze did his duty well;
                            the Christians acted splendidly, and some of the non-Christian natives
                            showed great kindness. But what about the erh-fu? Mr. Bramfitt, one of
                            the missionaries of the Wesley an Mission, charged the erh-fu with
                            culpable neglect, and in open court sustained the charge. To speak of
                            this official as worthy of great credit, and of his conduct as humane
                            and resolute, is simply ludicrous. I hear that this heartless man has
                            been cashiered. Why was he not deprived of his button? Two men have been
                            beheaded and ten more have been variously sentenced. The sum of $25,000
                            as indemnity has been sent in, and $40,000 has been offered as solatium
                            to the mothers of the deceased. All this is very well in its way, but it
                            was a great mistake to allow the erh-fu to escape so lightly. Of all the
                            sinners in that riot there was no greater than he, and if one man more
                            than another deserved to be made an example of, surely the erh-fu was
                            that man.</p>
                        <p>The steamer of to-day will bring you full account of the riot in Ichang.
                            It has been supposed by many that these riots are purely antimissionary.
                            The Ichang riot will, it is hoped, convince all such that they are
                            antiforeign.</p>
                        <p>The aim of the rioters was to destroy all foreign property, whether
                            mission or otherwise, and to drive all foreigners from the place. It has
                            also been maintained that these riots are to be ascribed to the hatred
                            of the missionaries among the masses of the Chinese people. So far as
                            the Ichang riot is concerned, it can be proved that the masses of the
                            people had very little to do with it, and that it was got up by the
                            soldiers under whose protection the foreigners are supposed to be. The
                            intercourse of the missionaries with the people of Ichang has been of
                            the most friendly nature. In the beginning of last year I received an
                            invitation from Mr. Cockburn to come and assist at the opening of his
                            new chapel at Ichang. Having had something to do with the establishing
                            of the mission twelve years previously, and having taken a deep interest
                            in its work and welfare ever since, I felt it to be both a duty and
                            privilege to comply with my friend’s request. Whilst walking with Mr.
                            Cockburn in the city and the surrounding country I could not but observe
                            how well he was known to the people as a teacher and friend. For some
                            time he had been the doctor as well as the clergyman of the place, and
                            both the natives and the foreigners <pb facs="0555" n="449" xml:id="pg_449"/> seemed to depend upon him for physical healing as
                            well as spiritual instruction. The kindness of Mr. and Mrs. Cockburn
                            seemed to have won many hearts among the natives, and wherever we went
                            we were treated with the greatest respect and friendliness. My first
                            visit to Ichang was in 1868, before any missionary had settled down in
                            the place. The change for the better in the bearing of the people toward
                            me was very marked, and I could not but ascribe it in a large measure to
                            the presence and work of the missionaries in their midst.</p>
                        <p>We have been brought face to face with another great crisis in China. I
                            believe that there is a deeply laid plot which has for its aim the
                            immediate expulsion of all foreigners from the Yangtse Valley, and
                            ultimately from all China. “Can you control your own people?” asks the
                            British Government. The yamên has given its answer to that question, and
                            so has Ichang. It behooves the foreign powers to consider carefully and
                            well the Ichang answer, for it is significant. It is reported that a
                            grand conclave was held in Wuchang last week, at the head of which were
                            many influential Hunanese. The resolution come to was that no foreigners
                            are to be allowed to dwell in the provinces of Hunan, Hupeh, and
                            Kiangsi. This morning two anonymous placards were found in the compounds
                            of the Roman Catholic and London missions in the city of Wuchang,
                            warning the foreigners of the coming storm. Hunan is bent upon mischief.
                            How to deal with it I can not tell; but I am anxious to call attention
                            to the fact, and that for the sake of the people of China as well as for
                            our own sake.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Griffith John</hi>.</signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Hankow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-09-07"><hi rend="italic">September
                                7</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>