<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-04-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-04-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="476" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d476">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName> to Sir
                                    <persName type="to">Julian Pauncefote</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-04-14"><hi rend="italic">April 14,
                                1891</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The modifications which Lord Salisbury
                            suggests in the questions for arbitration do not wholly meet the views
                            of the President; but the President changes the text of the third and
                            fifth in such manner, it <pb facs="0655" n="549" xml:id="pg_549"/> is
                            hoped, as will result in an agreement between the two Governments. While
                            Lord Salisbury suggests a different mode of procedure from that embodied
                            in the sixth question, the President does not understand him actually to
                            object to the question, and he therefore assumes that it is agreed
                            to.</p>
                        <p>The six questions as now proposed by the President are as follows: <list>
                                <item>First. What exclusive jurisdiction in the sea now known as the
                                    Behring Sea, and what exclusive rights in the seal fisheries
                                    therein, did Russia assert and exercise prior and up to the time
                                    of the cession of Alaska to the United States?</item>
                                <item>Second. How far were these claims of jurisdiction as to the
                                    seal fisheries recognized and conceded by Great Britain?</item>
                                <item>Third. Was the body of water now known as the Behring Sea
                                    included in the phrase “Pacific Ocean,” as used in the treaty of
                                    1825 between Great Britain and Russia 5 and what, rights, if
                                    any, in the Behring Sea were held and exclusively exercised by
                                    Russia after said treaty?</item>
                                <item>Fourth. Did not all the rights of Russia as to jurisdiction
                                    and as to the seal fisheries in Behring Sea, east of the water
                                    boundary described in the treaty between the United States and
                                    Russia of March 30, 1867, pass unimpaired to the United States
                                    under that treaty?</item>
                                <item>Fifth. Has the United States any right, and if so, what right,
                                    of protection or property in the fur seals frequenting the
                                    islands of the United States in Behring Sea when such seals are
                                    found outside the ordinary 3-mile limit?</item>
                                <item>Sixth. If the determination of the foregoing questions shall
                                    leave the subject in such position that the concurrence of Great
                                    Britain is necessary in prescribing regulations for the killing
                                    of the fur seal in any part of the waters of Behring Sea, then
                                    it shall be further determined: First, how far, if at all,
                                    outside the ordinary territorial limits it is necessary that the
                                    United States should exercise an exclusive jurisdiction in order
                                    to protect the seal for the time living upon the islands of the
                                    United States and feeding therefrom? Second, whether a closed
                                    season (during which the killing of seals in the waters of
                                    Behring Sea outside the ordinary territorial limits shall be
                                    prohibited) is necessary to save the seal-fishing industry, so
                                    valuable and important to mankind, from deterioration or
                                    destruction? And, if so, third, what months or parts of months
                                    should be included in such season, and over what waters it
                                    should extend?</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The President does not object to the additional question respecting
                            alleged damages to English ships, proposed by Lord Salisbury, if one
                            condition can be added, namely, that after the issues of the arbitration
                            are joined, if the United States shall prevail, all the seals taken by
                            Canadian vessels during the period shall be paid for at the ordinary
                            price for which skins are sold. This seems to the President to be the
                            complement of Lord Salisbury’s proposition, and he doubts not that it
                            will secure his lordship’s assent.</p>
                        <p>In the first paragraph of Lord Salisbury’s dispatch of February 21 he
                            makes the following declaration: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>It is now quite clear that the advisers of the President do not
                                    claim Behring Sea as <hi rend="italic">mare clausum</hi>, and,
                                    indeed, that they repudiate that contention in express
                                    terms.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Lord Salisbury’s expression is put in such form as to imply (whether he
                            so intended I know not) that the United States had hitherto been resting
                            its contention upon the fact that the Behring Sea was <hi rend="italic">mare clausum</hi>. If that was his intention it would have been
                            well for his lordship to specify wherein the United States ever made the
                            assertion. The emphatic <pb facs="0656" n="550" xml:id="pg_550"/> denial
                            in my dispatch of December 17 last was intended to put an end to the
                            iteration of the charge and to eliminate it from the current
                            discussion.</p>
                        <p>Lord Salisbury complains that I did not deal with certain protests,
                            written by Lord Londonderry and the Duke of Wellington in 1822, which he
                            had before quoted. If he will recur to the twenty-sixth and
                            twenty-seventh pages of my dispatch of December 17, he will observe that
                            I specially dealt with these; that I maintained and, I think, proved
                            from the text that there was not a single word in those protests
                            referring to the Behring Sea, but that they referred, in the language of
                            the Duke of Wellington of the 17th of October, 1822, only to the lands
                            “extending along the shores of the Pacific Ocean from latitude 49° to
                            latitude 60° north.” In the first paragraph of Lord Londonderry’s
                            protest of January 18, 1822, addressed to Count Lieven, of Russia, he
                            alluded to the matters in dispute as “<hi rend="italic">especially
                                connected with the territorial rights of the Russian Grown on the
                                northwest coast of America bordering on the Pacific Ocean, and the
                                commerce and navigation of Sis Imperial Majesty’s subjects in the
                                seas adjacent thereto.”</hi> From these and other pertinent facts it
                            is evident that the protests of Lord Londonderry and the Duke of
                            Wellington had nothing whatever to do with the points now in issue
                            between the American and British Governments concerning the waters of
                            the Behring Sea. They both referred, in different but substantially
                            identical phrases, to the territory south of the Alaskan peninsula
                            bordering on the Pacific, and geographically shut out from the Behring
                            Sea. I regret that my arguments on a point which Lord Salisbury
                            considers of great importance should have escaped his lordship’s
                            notice.</p>
                        <p>In Lord Salisbury’s judgment the contention of the United States now
                            rests wholly upon the ukase of 1821 by the Emperor Alexander I of
                            Russia. The United States has at no time rested its argument solely on
                            the ground mentioned, and this Government regrets that Lord Salisbury
                            should have so misapprehended the American position as to limit its
                            basis of right in Behring Sea to the ukase of 1821. The United States
                            has, among other grounds, insisted, without recurring to any of its
                            inherited and superior rights in Alaska, that this Government has as
                            full authority for going beyond the 3–mile line in case of proved
                            necessity as Great Britain possesses.</p>
                        <p>Two or three instances of the power which Great Britain exercises beyond
                            the 3–mile line have already been quoted, but have failed thus far to
                            secure comment or explanation from Lord Salisbury. Another case can be
                            added which perhaps is still more to the point. In 1889, only two years
                            ago, the British Parliament enacted a law, the effect of which is fully
                            shown by a map inclosed herewith. Far outside the 3–mile line the
                            Parliament of Great Britain has attempted to control a body of water
                            situated beyond the northeastern section of Scotland, 2,700 square miles
                            in extent, and to direct that certain methods of fishing shall not be
                            used within that great body of water under a prescribed penalty. It will
                            be observed that the inhibition is not alone against British subjects,
                            but against “any person.” I here quote the pertinent section of the
                            Parliamentary act in question: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>7 (1) The Fishing Board may, by byelaw or byelaws, direct that
                                    the methods of fishing known as beam trawling and otter trawling
                                    shall not be used within a line drawn from Duncansby Head, in
                                    Caithness, to Rattray Point, in Aberdeenshire, in any area or
                                    areas to be defined in such byelaw, and may from time to time
                                    make, alter, and revoke byelaws for the purposes of this
                                    section, but no such byelaw shall be of any validity until it
                                    has been confirmed by the secretary for Scotland.</p>
                                <p>(2) Any person who uses any such method of fishing in
                                    contravention of any such byelaw shall be liable, on conviction
                                    under the summary jurisdiction (Scotland) acts, to a fine not
                                    exceeding five pounds for the first offense, and not
                                    exceeding</p>
                                <pb facs="0657" n="[]" xml:id="pg-seq-0657"/>
                                <figure>
                                    <graphic url="figure_0657"/>
                                </figure>
                                <pb facs="0658" n="[]" xml:id="pg-seq-0658"/>
                                <pb facs="0659" n="551" xml:id="pg_551"/>
                                <p rend="flushleft">twenty pounds for the second or any subsequent
                                    offense, and every net set, or attempted to be set, in
                                    contravention of any such byelaw may be seized and destroyed or
                                    otherwise disposed of as in the sixth section of this act
                                    mentioned.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>If Great Britain may thus control an area of 2,700 square miles of ocean
                            on the coast of Scotland, why may not the United States prescribe a
                            space around the Pribyloff Islands in which similar prohibitions may be
                            enforced? The following would be the needed legislation for such a
                            purpose by Congress, and it is but a paraphrase of the act of
                            Parliament: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The Fur-Seal Board may, by by-law or by-laws, direct that the
                                    methods of sealing known as spearing, or harpooning, or with
                                    firearms, shall not be used within a line drawn from the shores
                                    of the Pribyloff Islands, 60 miles in the Behring Sea, and said
                                    Board may, from time to time, make, alter, and revoke by-laws
                                    for the purpose of this section; but no such by-law shall be of
                                    any validity until it has been confirmed by the Secretary of the
                                    Treasury.</p>
                                <p>Second. Any person who uses any such method of sealing in
                                    contravention of such by-laws shall be liable on conviction to a
                                    fine not exceeding $100 for the first offense and not exceeding
                                    $500 for the second or any subsequent offense, and every spear,
                                    harpoon, or firearm attempted to be used in contravention of any
                                    such by-law may be seized and destroyed or otherwise disposed of
                                    as said Fur-Seal Board may direct.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>It must not escape observation that the area of water outside the 3–mile
                            line on the coast of Scotland, whose control is assumed by Great
                            Britain, is as large as would be found inside a line drawn from Cape Cod
                            to Portland harbor, on the New England coast.</p>
                        <p>Lord Salisbury reasserts his contention that the words “Pacific Ocean,”
                            at the time of the treaty between Russia and Great Britain, did include
                            Behring Sea. Undoubtedly the Pacific Ocean includes Behring Sea in the
                            same sense that the Atlantic Ocean includes the Gulf of Mexico, and yet
                            it would be regarded as a very inaccurate statement to say that the
                            Mississippi River flows into the Atlantic Ocean. I think Lord Salisbury
                            fails to recognize the common distinction between the “Atlantic Ocean”
                            and “the waters of the Atlantic.” While the Mexican Gulf is not a part
                            of the Atlantic Ocean, it would, I am sure, comport with general usage
                            to say that it belonged to the waters of the Atlantic; and, while
                            Behring Sea is not technically a part of the Pacific Ocean, it
                            undoubtedly belongs to the waters of the Pacific.</p>
                        <p>The English Channel would not ordinarily be understood as included in the
                            term “Atlantic Ocean.” One would not say that Dover or Calais is on the
                            coast of the Atlantic Ocean, and yet clearly the English Channel belongs
                            to the waters of the Atlantic. In point of fact, therefore, according to
                            the usage of the world, there is no dispute of any consequence between
                            the two Governments on the geographical point under consideration. The
                            historical point is the one at issue. The explanatory note from Russia
                            filed in the State Department of this country, specially referred to in
                            Mr. John Quincy Adams’s diary and quoted in my note of December 17,
                            1890, plainly draws a distinction between the Pacific Ocean on the one
                            hand, and the “Sea of Okhotsk, the sea of Kamsehatka, and the Icy Sea”
                            on the other; and so long as Russia drew that distinction it must apply
                            to, and must absolutely decide, all the contentions between the two
                            countries as far as the waters of the Behring Sea are concerned. To
                            discuss this point further would, in the opinion of the President,
                            contribute nothing of value to the general contention.</p>
                        <p>In the opinion of the President Lord Salisbury is wholly and strangely in
                            error in making the following statement: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Nor do they [the advisers of the President] rely, as a
                                    justification for the seizure of British ships in the open sea,
                                    upon the contention that the interests of the seal fisheries
                                    give to the United States Government any right for that purpose
                                    which, according to international law, it would not otherwise
                                    possess.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <pb facs="0660" n="552" xml:id="pg_552"/>
                        <p>The Government of the United States has steadily held just the reverse of
                            the position which Lord Salisbury has imputed to it. It holds that the
                            ownership of the islands upon which the seals breed, that the habit of
                            the seals in regularly resorting thither and rearing their young
                            thereon, that their going out from the islands in search of food and
                            regularly returning thereto, and all the facts and incidents of their
                            relation to the island, give to the United States a property interest
                            therein; that this property interest was claimed and exercised by Russia
                            during the whole period of its sovereignty over the land and waters of
                            Alaska; that England recognized this property interest so far as
                            recognition is impliedly abstaining from all interference with it during
                            the whole period of Russia’s ownership of Alaska, and during the first
                            nineteen years of the sovereignty of the United States. It is yet to be
                            determined whether the lawless intrusion of Canadian vessels in 1886 and
                            subsequent years has changed the law and equity of the case theretofore
                            prevailing.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James G. Blaine</hi>.</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>