<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-02-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="545" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d545">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName> to Sir
                                    <persName type="to">Julian Pauncefote</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-02-06"><hi rend="italic">February 6,
                                1892</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am in receipt of your note of this date,
                            in which you give me the official notification of the appointment of Sir
                            George Baden-Powell and Prof. Dawson as commissioners on the part of the
                            British Government on the joint commission created in view of the
                            proposed fur-seal arbitration.</p>
                        <p>In acknowledging your note, I deem it important to direct your attention
                            to the fact that the Government of the United States, in nominating the
                            commissioners on its part, selected gentlemen who were especially fitted
                            by their scientific attainments, and who were in no wise disqualified
                            for an impartial investigation and determination of the questions to be
                            submitted to them, by a public declaration of opinion previous or
                            subsequent to their selection. It is to be regretted that a similar
                            course does not seem to have been adopted by the British Government. It
                            appears from a document which you transmitted to me, under date of March
                            9, 1890 (inclosure 4), that one of the gentlemen selected by your
                            Government to act as a commissioner on its part has fully committed
                            himself in advance on all the questions which are to be submitted to him
                            for investigation and decision.</p>
                        <p>I am further informed that the other gentleman named in your note had
                            previous to his selection made public his views on the subject, and that
                            very recently he has announced in an address to his parliamentary
                            constituents that the result of the investigation of this commission and
                            of the proposed arbitration would be in favor of his Government.</p>
                        <p>I trust, however, that these circumstances will not impair the candid and
                            impartial investigation and determination which was the object had in
                            view in the creation of the commission, and that the result of its
                            labors may greatly promote an equitable and mutually satisfactory
                            adjustment of the questions at issue.</p>
                        <p>The commissioners on the part of the United States have been instructed
                            to put themselves in communication with the British commissioners, to
                            tender them an apartment at the Department of State for the joint
                            conference, and, if it shall suit their convenience, to agree with them
                            upon an hour for their first conference on Monday next, the 8th
                            instant.</p>
                        <p>It is proper to add that when I indicated to you on the 13th ultimo that
                            the British commissioner, then in London, might come at once to <pb facs="0718" n="610" xml:id="pg_610"/> Washington, I supposed we
                            should before this date have signed the arbitration convention, and thus
                            have enabled the commissioners to proceed officially to a discharge of
                            their duties. But as it became necessary to await the approval of the
                            draft of that instrument which you have forwarded to London, I have
                            interposed no objection to preliminary conferences of the commissioners,
                            anticipating the signature of the convention within a very brief
                            period.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James G. Blaine</hi>.</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>