<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Wharton to Mr. MacNutt..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1891</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d681</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">681</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1891-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1891-09-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-09-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="681"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d681">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wharton</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">MacNutt</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-09-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 3, 1891</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 245.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose herewith copy of a letter from the Rev.
                    Judson Smith, foreign secretary of the American board of commissioners for
                    foreign missions, dated the 27th ultimo, and of its inclosure, in relation to
                    the indignities said to have been perpetrated on the Rev. Mr. Richardson by
                    Turkish officials. Your report on the case is awaited.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William F. Wharton</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 245.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Smith</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blame</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Board of Commissioners for Foreign
                                    Missions</hi>,<lb/>1 <hi rend="smallcaps">Somerset Street,
                                    Boston, Mass</hi>.</placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-08-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">August 27, 1891</hi>.</date> (Received August
                            29.)</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: Allow me to call your attention to the
                        inclosed copy of a letter written by Rev. H. O. Dwight, our missionary in
                        Constantinople, who is the special means of communication between our
                        missionaries and the United States legation in that city, and addressed to
                        Mr. MacNutt, who is at present in charge of the affairs of our Government in
                        Constantinople. It is quite probable that a copy of this letter has already
                        reached the Department of State directly from Constantinople, but I send
                        this to make sure that it comes to your attention.</p>
                    <p>The indignity to which Mr. Richardson, our missionary at Erzerum, has been
                        exposed at the hands of Turkish officials is one of unusual boldness and
                        calls for special attention. Mr. Richardson seems to have taken every
                        precaution to insure the safety of himself and his possessions in the
                        journey on missionary business which he was pursuing at the time he was so
                        summarily placed under arrest. The right to travel freely in the pursuits of
                        missionary duties within the limits of the Turkish Empire is one of the
                        points, as you are well aware, which has been guarantied again and again in
                        the treaty stipulations between our Government and the Sublime Porte. The
                        invasion of this right in this bold and inexcusable way, and the apparent
                        shielding of the wrongdoer by the governor-general of Erzerum, whose duty it
                        was rather to rebuke the unlawful exercise of power by his subordinate, adds
                        seriously to the gravity of the situation.</p>
                    <p>The further fact that Mr. Richardson’s goods were forcibly seized when in the
                        house of a friend, and their detention for examination, is practically an
                        invasion of the right of domicile, which constitutes in itself an additional
                        and serious infraction of the rights guarantied to American citizens
                        resident in the Turkish Empire. The case seems to be one calling for prompt
                        and vigorous action on the part of our Government, and I do not doubt that
                        instructions have already gone from Washington to Mr. MacNutt to make demand
                        for reparation and to secure suitable guar-antys for the future. A case of
                        this kind, if neglected, will certainly open the way for repeated wrongs of
                        this kind and will amount to the serious interruption, if not the
                        termination, of missionary work in the Turkish Empire,</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Judson Smith</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Sec’y</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0866" n="754" xml:id="pg_754"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Dwight</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">MacNutt</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Bible House, Constantinople</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-08-13">
                                <hi rend="italic">August 13, 1801</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: I desire to beg your attention to the
                        following account of an aggravated interference with the liberty and the
                        rights of an American missionary living in Erzerum:</p>
                    <p>In the latter part of May of the current year Mr. Richardson obtained from
                        the authorities in Erzerum tezkara (permit to travel) to go on business to
                        Van by way of Bitlis. He also obtained from the governor-general of Erzerum
                        a special road order (bouyouroultou) informing subgovernors that Mr.
                        Richardson was authorized to travel, and directing them to protect him by
                        armed escort.</p>
                    <p>Having completed his business in Van, Mr. Richardson had his tezkara written
                        for the return to Erzerum by way of the Alashgerd district, where he also
                        had business, and obtained from the governor-general of Van a fresh
                        bouyouroultou for the sub-governors along that route.</p>
                    <p>Traveling thus under protection of a Government escort, Mr., Richardson
                        reached the town of Toprakkate on the 1st of July, and at once called on the
                        subgovernor (kaimakam) of Alashgerd to present his respects and to ask for a
                        fresh escort to go to Karakilise, the next district to the east of
                        Alashgerd. This was promised him by the kaimakam, and Mr. Richardson
                        returned to the house where he was guest.</p>
                    <p>About an hour later the kaimakam summoned Mr. Richardson and sent him to the
                        house of a Moslem named Bitlisli Ahmed under charge of a policeman, who was
                        instructed to keep Mr. Richardson from communicating with any Armenians of
                        the town. Here Mr. Richardson was treated with great incivility and his
                        servant was beaten without provocation.</p>
                    <p>Meanwhile the kaimakam sent police to the village of Khunsur, on the
                        Karakiliss road, where Mr. Richardson had left his baggage at the house of
                        the Protestant preacher, seized the baggage from the custody of Mr.
                        Richardson’s friends, and, after it had been brought to Toprakkate, unpacked
                        it and took possession of all the books, written documents, letters, and
                        letter-copy book, all of which he sent to Erzerum under his own official
                        seal.</p>
                    <p>He also placed Mr. Richardson under charge of the policemen, who had the
                        package of documents, directing them to deliver their prisoner to the
                        governor’s headquarters in Erzerum and to prevent his speaking to any
                        Christian on the way. This order was carried out with strictness and
                        brutality, the guard even beating a young Armenian acquaintance who saluted
                        Mr. Richardson on the road. The policemen delivered Mr. Richardson to the
                        commander of gendarmerie at Erzerum on the 5th of July. This official, after
                        taking possession of Mr. Richardson’s American passport as well as of his
                        Turkish road papers, allowed him to go to his home under promise to report
                        whenever summoned.</p>
                    <p>The governor-general, to whom Mr. Richardson is well known, refused all
                        requests for the return of the private documents seized by the kaimakam of
                        Alashgerd. Instead of this he called to his aid the teachers of an Armenian
                        school in Erzerum and had these documents translated, only returning them
                        after he had thus made public property of them during seventeen days. At the
                        date of the last letter from Mr. Richardson, July 25, the governor-general
                        still refused to return Mr. Richardson’s American passport, tezakara and
                        bouyouroultou, and a manuscript copy of the gospel of St. Matthew in the
                        Kurdish language.</p>
                    <p>The British consul (Acting Consul Hampson) was willing to remonstrate with
                        the governor-general for this infringement of Mr. Richardson’s rights, and
                        offered to telegraph to Constantinople for instructions from his embassy.
                        But since the governor-general had violently threatened Mr. Richardson for
                        appealing for protection to the consul last year, and since the consul
                        admitted that he could not press for redress without special instructions,
                        Mr. Richardson declined his assistance.</p>
                    <p>It appears to me that when an American has complied with all police passport
                        regulations, and in addition to this has secured the special bouyouroultou
                        obtained by Mr. Richardson, and, moreover, is traveling under protection of
                        the Government escort furnished by the official of the district from which
                        he has come, the question of his right to travel freely is not left to the
                        discretion of petty officials along the road. The clauses of the treaties
                        securing to Americans the right to travel freely in Turkey on their
                        legitimate business here, expressly designed to prevent such petitions of
                        incapable officials as occurred at Toprakkate, it certainly is not within
                        the jurisdiction of subgovernors to set aside these clauses of the
                        treaties.</p>
                    <p>Furthermore, the seizure of Mr. Richardson’s baggage from the house where he
                        had left it in charge of his friends was clearly a violation of domicile.
                        The Turkish Government would hardly claim the right to seize the papers, out
                        of curiosity to learn their contents, by forced entry into his house in
                        Erzerum. The forced entry into his temporary quarters at Khunsur is of
                        precisely the same nature.</p>
                    <pb facs="0867" n="755" xml:id="pg_755"/>
                    <p>Again, it seems clear to my mind that the governor-general of Erzerum, had he
                        the qualities to be expected in one occupying his high position, would make
                        haste to disown the arbitrary proceedings of his subordinate, and to make
                        reparation to Mr. Richardson by promptly restoring to him his papers in some
                        way that would clear himself from any complicity in a direct violation of
                        the treaties. His act of keeping the documents illegally seized, and making
                        such use of them as he chose, is one of approval of the act of the kaimakam
                        of Toprakkate. If the governor-general has such ideas of the rights of his
                        office, there is an end to all freedom of travel on the part of American
                        citizens in the great province confided to his charge.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, allow me to say that I regard this affair as possessing
                        extreme gravity. In case the action of the governor-general of Erzerum is
                        allowed to pass unrebuked and unredressed, I hope that you may see the
                        propriety of reporting the case to Washington as an action logically
                        implying the repudiation by the Sublime Porte of its treaty obligations
                        concerning the freedom of Americans to travel in the empire.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">H. O. Dwight</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
