<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Wharton to Mr. MacNutt..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1891</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d684</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">684</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1891-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1891-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyGjAcEpLpFYanH" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107027"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Privacy</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="684"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d684">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wharton</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">MacNutt</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-10-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 1, 1891</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 249.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your No. 344, of the 10th ultimo,
                    upon the subject of the alleged conversion of private dwellings into places of
                    religious worship or teaching, and inclosing a <hi rend="italic">note
                        verbale</hi> from the Turkish minister for foreign affairs respecting the
                    matter, together with draft of your proposed answer conjointly with the British
                    ambassador.</p>
                <pb facs="0870" n="758" xml:id="pg_758"/>
                <p>While approving the general sense of your proposed note, the Department is
                    inclined to modify the terms of it somewhat, with the purpose of presenting a
                    broader or more liberal appreciation of the attitude of the Porte towards the
                    practice as complained of in the note to you from the foreign office.</p>
                <p>A private dwelling is no more to be regarded as “converted” into a church or
                    school by household worship or teaching therein than as converted into a public
                    ballroom or hotel by reason of a dancing party or a dinner party given by the
                    householder to friends and acquaintances, provided the reasonable conditions of
                    privacy are observed. On the other hand, for the virtual conversion of such a
                    dwelling into a church or public place of worship outward and visible signs and
                    public advertisement are not wholly essential. A meeting gathered together in a
                    private residence by means of a general although oral invitation or notice to
                    the neighborhood might, under certain circumstances, be justly described as a
                    public meeting; and the continued repetition of such a meeting at such a house
                    might result in a reasonable description of the house as a place of public
                    worship.</p>
                <p>The line between public participation in such meetings and their private
                    limitation to the members of the household and their personal guests should be,
                    if not already, sharply and consistently drawn and scrupulously observed by
                    everybody concerned.</p>
                <p>It is not difficult to see that the attendance of natives of the place at the
                    private assemblies of foreign householders for prayer and religious instruction
                    may be so numerous and constant as to pass the commonly understood bounds of
                    private hospitality, and it is very desirable that the missionaries, for their
                    part, should keep strictly within the rights of alien domicile.</p>
                <p>The Department approves your purpose, with this instruction in mind, to answer
                    the Porte’s note in concert with the British ambassador. Should your note, as
                    modified by this instruction, and his note not prove identical, he will probably
                    not object to acquainting you with the text of his communication.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William F. Wharton</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
