<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-11-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="688" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d688">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">MacNutt</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-11-05"><hi rend="italic">November 5,
                            1891</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 254.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I transmit for your further information a copy
                        of a letter from Mr. Judson Smith, with its inclosed letter from Mr. Henry
                        O. Dwight, of Constantinople, in relation to the continued interference of
                        the authorities of Erzerum with the freedom of Mr. Richardson, an American
                        citizen residing at that place, this being the case reported in your No. 347
                        of the 26th of last September.</p>
                    <p>It would seem that the delivery to Mr. Richardson of the travel permit, or
                            <hi rend="italic">teskeré</hi>, although repeatedly promised to the
                        legation by the foreign office, has not been effected by the authorities at
                        Erzerum. It is not for a moment supposed that the Government of the Porte
                        can tolerate any such dereliction of duty on the part of the provincial
                        authorities, or fail to rebuke so grave an act, in the face of its positive
                        assurances that the needed <hi rend="italic">teskere</hi> would be
                        given.</p>
                    <p>If when you receive this instruction you find that Mr. Richardson is still
                        denied the permission to travel to which he is clearly entitled, and his
                        right to which has been solemnly admitted by the imperial Government, and if
                        he should still be virtually a prisoner in the province, you will earnestly
                        invite the attention of the minister for foreign affairs to the situation,
                        and will ask that positive and peremptory orders be issued which will admit
                        of no further evasion or delay on the part of the local authorities. Under
                        the circumstances you are justified in asking that the necessity of a
                        provincial <hi rend="italic">teskeré</hi> be obviated by the issuance of
                        such a document or its equivalent travel permit by the imperial authorities
                        at the capital, and that the permit be delivered to you, for dispatch to
                        Erzerum by the dragoman of the legation, whom you will send thither <pb facs="0877" n="765" xml:id="pg_765"/> for that purpose. Mr. Gargiulo can
                        go by steamer to Trebizonde, from which point you will ask for a suitable
                        guard to accompany him to Erzerum.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Gargiulo will take advantage of his visit to Erzerum to investigate and
                        report fully touching the situation there as it affects our citizens. A
                        separate account should be rendered covering the actual and necessary
                        expenses of his journey.</p>
                    <p>Should Mr. Richardson have received his travel permit, it will not be
                        necessary for Mr. Gargiulo to go to Erzerum. In that case after the return
                        of the minister to Constantinople, it is probable that he will be instructed
                        to cause a special investigation to be made on the spot by the secretary of
                        legation.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James G. Blaine</hi>.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>