<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Special Representative ( (House) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-11-23T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-11-23T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-11-23T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-11-23T11:00:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">033.1140/252: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Special Representative</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HCEM1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">House</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-23T16:00:00+00:00"
                            >November 23, 1918—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 23—2:49 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>150. Secret for the President and Secretary of State. Referring further to our
                    number 135.<note n="17" xml:id="d106fn17">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_138">p. 138</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AG1">Auchincloss</persName> visited today the house placed
                    at the President’s disposal by the French Government. This house is number 28
                    Rue de Monceau, a couple of blocks above the Boulevard Hausmann and in one of
                    the highest parts of the city. The house, however, is not far from the street,
                    in the center of spacious grounds, which are surrounded by a high wall. The
                    interior of the house is beautifully furnished and is in first-class repair. On
                    the ground floor there are the following rooms: A. Large dining room capable of
                    seating 35 persons; B, large ballroom or salon; C, three medium-sized drawing
                    rooms. On the second floor there are the following rooms: A, small suite of two
                    rooms; B, small study or library; C, large study or writing-room, which could be
                    used as the President’s workroom; D, bedroom and drawing room and bath which
                    could be used by the President; E, connecting suite of three rooms, bedroom,
                    boudoir and sitting room which could be used by Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_WW1"
                        >Wilson</persName>; F, medium-size breakfast or dining room. On the third
                    floor there are seven bedrooms and four sitting rooms, all of which are
                    attractively furnished. There is a private garage on the grounds. I am taking
                    steps to have proper telephonic and wire connections installed in a manner, as
                    near as possible, similar to that at present existing in the White House. All in
                    all I believe the house placed at the President’s disposal by the French
                    Government is as attractive a residence as there is in Paris, and I have
                    informally advised the Foreign Office that I felt sure the President would be
                    altogether pleased with the arrangements made in his behalf. If there are any
                    particular points that you wish me to attend to with respect to these
                    accommodations, I trust that you will communicate them to me in the near future.
                    The Foreign Office have asked me not to make public the arrangements they are
                    making for the present.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCEM1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward House</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
