<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-11-21T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-11-21T13:00:00-05:00" n="338" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d338">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72119/9182: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Special Representative</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HCEM1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">House</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-21T18:00:00+00:00">November 21, 1918—6 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 7:08 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>133. The French Government has made the following changes in scheme of
                            procedure submitted in my number 109:<note n="3" xml:id="d338fn3">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra.</hi>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Article N under I should read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“For matters not concerning the treaty of peace properly speaking
                                    between belligerents, but the general new organization intended
                                    to bring about the peace of the world, the decisions of the
                                    Congress must be unanimous. (This applies also to question of
                                    procedure, unless the minority registers a formal protest).
                                    [”]</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Fifth [<hi rend="italic">Fourth?</hi>] paragraph under II should read:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“It is necessary that a decision be reached with regard to our
                                    Allies who have treated with the enemy without our recognition
                                    of these treaties; Roumania and Russia; the interest of the
                                    latter country could be defended by an invitation to Allied
                                    committee with which Russian advisers could be associated.
                                    [”]</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0423" n="353" xml:id="pg_353"/>
                        <p>Eighth [<hi rend="italic">Seventh?</hi>] paragraph under number II should
                            read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Finally, the enemies; Germany, Bulgaria, Turkey, Bavaria,
                                    German-Austria and Magyarie. The conditions of the participation
                                    of enemy states should be defined: for example, it would not be
                                    admissible for the twenty-five states of the German Empire to
                                    avail themselves of the rupture of the bond of federation to
                                    pretend to register each one a vote in the deliberations and
                                    votes.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Second paragraph under number III should read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The work must evidently be divided between preparatory
                                    commissions composed solely of members chosen amongst the
                                    plenipotentiaries with the addition of technical, legal,
                                    financial, geographical, military, naval, industrial and
                                    commercial experts, having a consulting vote.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Fifth paragraph under number III should read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The necessity of defining and limiting delegations of the powers
                                    is imperative. While at the same time reconsidering engagements
                                    made by the British Government with regard to its principal
                                    colonies, it would be well to define precisely the limits of
                                    this special representation, which should be embraced in the
                                    total British representation.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Clause A under IV should read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Right of peoples to decide their own destinies by free and
                                    secret vote combined with the principle of the guarantee of the
                                    rights of minorities. A certain homogeneousness of states should
                                    be reserved [<hi rend="italic">preserved?</hi>] however. The
                                    principle to be applied to Bohemia, perhaps to the Tyrol, to the
                                    south of the Brenner, to Dalmatia, to Luxemburg, et cetera.
                                    [”]</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The fourth paragraph of B under IV omitted, it should read: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Another principle could be introduced with advantage at the very
                                    start: that of the holding [?] of merchant vessels and colonial
                                    territories in the possession of the powers on August 1st, 1914.
                                    This would avoid the dangerous campaign waged by the Germans and
                                    supported by certain imprudent and suspected elements amongst
                                    the Allies, tending to the neutralization of the great African
                                    colonies for the purpose of making a kind of universal domain
                                    for commercial intercourse. [”]</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The following paragraph omitted under IV. Should follow after paragraph
                            beginning “Finally this Congress,” et cetera.</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Nor can the fourteen propositions of President <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName> be taken as a point of
                                departure because they are the principles of public right which may
                                inspire the negotiations, but which do not possess the concrete
                                character indispensable for approaching the precise regulations of
                                concrete stipulations.”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <pb facs="0424" n="354" xml:id="pg_354"/>
                        <p>Under A—Settlement of the War—article 7 is added reading as follows:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Stipulations of a moral nature, recognition by Germany of the
                                    responsibility and preferences of its rulers, which would
                                    emphasize the ideas of justice and of responsibility, and would
                                    legitimize the measures of punishment and precaution taken
                                    against her. Solemn repudiation of the violation of the right of
                                    nations and of the crimes committed against humanity.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HCEM1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward House</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>