<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
  <text>
    <body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-07-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-07-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="198" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                        <head>198. Letter From Yugoslav President <persName corresp="#p_SP_3">Stambolic</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RR_1">Reagan</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d198fn1">Source:
                                Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_DP_1">Paula J.
                                    Dobriansky</persName> Files, Yugoslavia (2). No classification
                                marking. Printed from an unofficial translation.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Belgrade</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-07-06">July 6,
                                1982</date></dateline>
                            <salute>Dear Mr. President,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <!--<pb facs="d198-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d198-2"/>-->
                        <p>In keeping with our established practice of exchanging messages on the
                            highest level, which both sides deem to be highly useful, and in the
                            spirit of the friendly relations and understanding between our two
                            countries, I would like to take this opportunity to underline our great
                            interest in advancing cooperation with U.S. commercial banks. Therein,
                            in our view, the support of the government of the United States would be
                            most helpful.</p>
                        <p>Your administration, as well as business circles and banks in the United
                            States, have followed the efforts we have exerted over the past two
                            years to achieve economic stabilization. This policy has yielded
                            manifold results, particularly in terms of reducing our balance of
                            payments deficit. In this context, our cooperation with the
                            International Monetary Fund has been most productive. However, as you
                            are no doubt aware, we are pursuing this policy against the background
                            of highly unfavorable international developments, and particularly
                            adverse economic and monetary conditions.</p>
                        <p>Although we remain firmly committed to reducing our foreign debt, at this
                            moment new credits are essential in order to retain the complete
                            solvency of our country and to continue our policy of economic
                            stabilization.</p>
                        <pb facs="0594" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/>
                        <!--<pb facs="d198-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d198-3"/>-->
                        <p>Representatives of your administration have, on several occasions,
                            reiterated their support and understanding for the course we have
                            embarked on. We particularly value your willingness, Mr. President,
                            which you conveyed to my predecessor, <persName corresp="#p_KS_3">Sergej
                                Kraigher</persName>, in Cancun,<note n="2" xml:id="d198fn2">Reagan
                                was in Cancun from October 21 until October 24, 1981, to attend the
                                Inter- Meeting on Cooperation and Development.</note> to extend your
                            support in securing new credits for Yugoslavia from U.S. banks.</p>
                        <p>Financial cooperation is a long-term and essential part of our economic
                            and overall bilateral cooperation. This view was shared by preceding
                            U.S. administrations also.</p>
                        <p>The campaign Yugoslavia launched toward the end of last year to secure
                            new credits has not, to our regret, been brought to a close. However, I
                            would like to inform you that the West European countries have
                            manifested their understanding for the steps we have taken with regard
                            to their banks.</p>
                        <p>I feel, Mr. President, that you are fully aware of the economic and
                            political import that successful long-term cooperation between Yugoslav
                            and U.S. banks has in terms of relations between our two countries. In
                            view of our renewed efforts to secure the medium-term and short-term
                            credits that we need, your personal attention, Mr. President, and the
                            support of your administration in this regard would be highly
                            appreciated.</p>
                        <p>I avail myself of this opportunity to express great pleasure at the
                            successful development of relations and fruitful cooperation between our
                            two countries on long-established principles which have an enduring
                            value.</p>
                        <p>Please accept, Mr. President, the renewed assurances of my highest
                            consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SP_3"><hi rend="strong">Petar
                                        Stambolic (signed)</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d198fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                                    signature.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>