<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
  <text>
    <body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1988-06-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1988-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="252" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                        <head>252. Telegram From the Embassy in Hungary to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d252fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Official Correspondence of Deputy Secretary of State
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WJ_1">John C. Whitehead</persName>, July
                                1982–January 1989, Lot 89 D 139, Potsdam Trip, June 4–16, 1988
                                (Eastern and Western Europe). Secret; Immediate; Nodis. Drafted by
                                Kelly (D); approved by Whitehead.</note></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#left">5861/Depto 3004.</seg><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Budapest</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1988-06-07">June 7, 1988,
                                    1354Z</date></dateline></opener>
                        <!--<pb facs="d252-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d252-2"/>-->
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>My Stop in Yugoslavia.</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Secret—Entire text.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>My visit to Yugoslavia could not have come at a better time.
                                Yugoslavia, or at least the people running it, is absolutely
                                consumed with its financial and economic problems. Since I arrived
                                here Sunday,<note n="2" xml:id="d252fn2">June 5.</note> the only
                                government official who hasn’t talked about <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> standbys or financing gaps or bridge loans was our
                                tour guide in Split. I’ve been able to do some important
                                hand-holding at a critical moment, give some valuable advice, and
                                perhaps most important, assure the Yugoslavs that we believe what
                                they are doing is positive, worthy of our support, and bound to
                                succeed. I also beat Adamishin here by a day with our view of the
                                Moscow Summit, which Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MB_3">Mikulic</persName> and Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LB_1">Loncar</persName> in particular
                                appreciated.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The basic problem here is that Yugoslavia has finally realized it
                                was making no progress on paying back its dols. 20 billion in
                                external debt, and recently reached an internal consensus to do
                                something about it. The <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> has
                                approved a standby plan, but before it goes into effect June 30, the
                                Yugoslavs must have identified some dols. 1.2 billion to close the
                                gap between expected receipts and obligations. That is problem
                                number one. The second, and more immediate, problem is that they
                                need about dols. 250 million in short-term cash to cover a series of
                                immediate reforms they have put into effect. These include devaluing
                                the dinar 24 percent, liberalizing the foreign exchange market, and
                                doing away with import controls on about 40 percent of their
                                imports. Further fundamental economic reforms, which Mikulic
                                correctly termed evolutionary, are to follow in the form of
                                constitutional amendments.</item>
                            <!--<pb facs="d252-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d252-3"/>-->
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Depending on who’s counting, the Yugoslavs seem to have identified
                                about one billion dollars from the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>, the World Bank, commercial banks, and rescheduled
                                interest to plug the dols 1.2 billion gap. That still leaves them
                                short of the mark. And the <gloss target="#t_BIS_1">BIS</gloss> has
                                agreed to provide a dols 250 million bridge loan to get them over
                                the immediate <pb facs="0785" n="754" xml:id="pg_754"/> hurdles as
                                they open their exchange markets, a process which after the first
                                six days seems to be functioning without crisis.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>I think you get the best flavor for how dramatic all this is from
                                my conversation with Mikulic.<note n="3" xml:id="d252fn3">See <ref target="#d253">Document 253</ref>.</note> This is a man
                                whose government survived an unprecedented no-confidence vote May
                                14. Who ever would have thought even ten years ago that a communist
                                country would get to the point of holding such a vote? What’s more,
                                two of the Yugoslav republics voted against Mikulic’s government.
                                The former president of one of them, Ante Markovic of Croatia, who
                                was my host last year in Zagreb, told me Monday<note n="4" xml:id="d252fn4">June 6.</note> Croatia voted against Mikulic
                                not because they thought his economic reform package was too
                                radical, but because it isn’t radical enough.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Mikulic told me Tuesday<note n="5" xml:id="d252fn5">June 7.</note>
                                he thought the country was united behind his plans to open
                                Yugoslavia to the rest of the economic world. He noted that there
                                has been resistance already from those who will be hurt by these
                                economic reforms, particularly large and inefficient enterprises and
                                others unable to adjust to the realities of an open marketplace. But
                                he said he was confident that the efficient parts of the Yugoslav
                                economy would be able to pull the rest of the country along into a
                                brighter future. We are in for some hard times, Mikulic said, adding
                                with some of the bunker vocabulary I often heard expressed, quote,
                                although we are few, we are brave, unquote.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>My approach in the speech I delivered Monday morning to the annual
                                meeting of the U.S.-Yugoslav Economic Council, and in meetings with
                                Mikulic, <persName corresp="#p_LB_1">Loncar</persName>, Deputy Prime
                                Minister <persName corresp="#p_MM_2">Milosavljevic</persName>, and
                                Finance Minister <persName corresp="#p_RS_1">Rikanovic</persName>,
                                was to stress that the U.S. strongly supports what Yugoslavia is
                                doing.
                                <!--<pb facs="d252-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d252-4"/>--> I
                                also tried to counteract a mistaken impression that we weren’t
                                willing to help with a long list of measures we’ve taken. I noted
                                our willingness to contribute dols. 50 million to the <gloss target="#t_BIS_1">BIS</gloss> package, the dols. 50 million we
                                were adding to Yugoslavia’s <rs corresp="recxmLIT5ymFOK58D" type="topic">Commodity Credit Corporation</rs> credits,
                                and the jawboning we are doing with commercial banks to encourage
                                them to provide some of the needed new money. In private, I briefed
                                Rikanovic and Milosavljevic on our efforts to twist the Kuwaiti
                                bankers’ arms, noting that we have raised the question of their
                                participation to a political level since the bankers have turned
                                their thumbs down. I also promised that we would support Yugoslavia
                                when the Paris Club meets Thursday<note n="6" xml:id="d252fn6">June
                                    9.</note> on their request for rescheduling, although I said
                                their request must be within reason.</item>
                            <pb facs="0786" n="755" xml:id="pg_755"/>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>With <persName corresp="#p_LB_1">Loncar</persName>, as with the
                                others, I said we admired the courage it took to make the kinds of
                                economic adjustments Yugoslavia faced, and I talked to him in detail
                                about the advantages of a free market. I told him that centrally
                                planned economies simply don’t work, adding that this wasn’t a
                                question of ideology, but one of practicality. I also made some
                                practical suggestions to Rikanovic on ways to convince the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> that sufficient funds were
                                identified so it would give the standby agreement the final green
                                light.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>I also managed with <persName corresp="#p_LB_1">Loncar</persName>
                                and Mikulic to give them our readout of the summit. Loncar’s
                                analysis is that there is no question that Gorbachev will succeed;
                                the only question is how fast. <persName corresp="#p_LB_1">Loncar</persName> said that Gorbachev had been tremendously
                                successful in changing the Soviet Union’s image (indeed, they are
                                getting the credit for leaving Afghanistan), and that this new
                                atmosphere was especially seductive to the public in Western
                                Europe.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_LB_1">Loncar</persName> and I also went over
                                some of the nuts and bolts of our relationship. We signed the
                                consular convention that we initialed last time I was here. This
                                will help us more effectively protect dual nationals who get
                                arrested here, a big problem in the past. We also reviewed the talks
                                on terrorism the Yugoslavs had in Washington last week. They were
                                impressed with what they saw and heard, and <persName corresp="#p_LB_1">Loncar</persName> said they came back ready to
                                extend even greater cooperation.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>Finally, <persName corresp="#p_LB_1">Loncar</persName> made a big
                                pitch to have you visit Yugoslavia. He said that their relationship
                                with the U.S. has top priority, and that they want to do more with
                                us in all fields. He argues that it is time for a visit at the quote
                                highest level unquote.</item>
                            <!--<pb facs="d252-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d252-5"/>-->
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>I agree. From the interaction of American and Yugoslav businessmen
                                in a crowded reception room in Split, to the frank economic and
                                political talks I had with top officials in Belgrade, I can see our
                                countries have never been closer. Yugoslavia has major problems;
                                there’s no disguising it. But if we can help them solve their
                                problems with Western solutions, the precedent will have a powerful
                                effect on Yugoslavia’s less liberal neighbors, and represent a real
                                victory for our step-by-step approach to this part of the
                                world.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_PR_1"><hi rend="strong">Palmer</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>