<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
  <text>
    <body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1983-12-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1983-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="323" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d323">
                        <head>323. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Hungary<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d323fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Central Foreign Policy File, D830729–0673. Secret; Exdis.
                                Sent for information to Moscow. Drafted by Palmer; cleared by P.
                                Hughes (<gloss target="#t_OVP_1">OVP</gloss>), Richard Kauzlarich
                                    (<gloss target="#t_S-S_1">S/S</gloss>), Dobriansky, <persName corresp="#p_RR_3">Roger Robinson</persName> (<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>), and William Garland (<gloss target="#t_S-S-O_1">S/S-O</gloss>) and in <gloss target="#t_EUR-EEY_1">EUR/EEY</gloss>; approved by John Kelly
                                    (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>). The <gloss target="#t_EUR-EEY_1">EUR/EEY</gloss> clearance line was
                                illegible.</note></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#left">350275.</seg><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1983-12-09">December 9, 1983,
                            2221Z</date></dateline></opener>
                        <!--<pb facs="d323-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d323-2"/>-->
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Hungarian Ambassador’s Meeting With Vice President.</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Secret—Entire text.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>(Begin summary) In meeting on November 28, Vice President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BG_1">Bush</persName> and Ambassador
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HV_1">Hazi</persName> discussed Vice
                                President’s trip to Budapest,<note n="2" xml:id="d323fn2">September
                                    19–20. See <ref target="#d322">Document 322</ref>.</note> his
                                speech in Vienna,<note n="3" xml:id="d323fn3">See <ref target="#d21">Document 21</ref>.</note> US-Hungarian <rs corresp="recW6DpFu8d7ioWcO" type="compound-subject">relations</rs> and
                                overall East-West situation. (End summary.)</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The Vice President opened the meeting by expressing his positive
                                memories of Budapest and the stimulating talks he had with <persName corresp="#p_KJ_1">Kadar</persName>. He had been criticized in
                                this country for some of the things he said in Budapest, but he
                                stood by his remarks.<note n="4" xml:id="d323fn4">Telegram 5722 from
                                    Budapest, September 21, conveyed the uncleared transcript of
                                    Bush’s September 20 <rs corresp="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic">press conference</rs>. (Department of State,
                                    Central <rs corresp="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic">Foreign Policy</rs> File, D830545–1016)</note> He asked for
                                the Ambassador’s frank views of the Vienna speech. Ambassador Hazi
                                said that <gloss target="#t_GOH_1">GOH</gloss> had been surprised
                                with those elements of speech which differed from positions Vice
                                President had taken in Budapest. In Vienna, the
                                <!--<pb facs="d323-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d323-3"/>-->
                                Vice President had said he had seen on the faces of people in
                                Eastern Europe eagerness for liberty. In his <rs corresp="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic">press conference</rs> in
                                Budapest he had said just the opposite. Where was the <rs corresp="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic">Iron</rs> Curtain,
                                when millions had been coming and going from Hungary for years. Hazi
                                cited Kreisky’s statement that it is better not to speak so loudly,
                                that nobody should ask for Hungary to break away from the Soviet
                                Union. Ambassador Hazi stressed that it was mistake to put countries
                                of Eastern Europe into good and bad categories.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Vice President noted that we believe there are differences among
                            Eastern European countries, that we are pleased to see greater openness
                            in Hungary, and that one purpose of speech was to state our support for
                            further movement in direction of <rs corresp="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic">human rights</rs> and independence. We have
                            serious problems with conduct of a number of Eastern European countries,
                            with their involvement in <rs corresp="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic">terrorism</rs>, <pb facs="1048" n="1017" xml:id="pg_1017"/> <rs corresp="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic">export</rs> of <rs corresp="rec26FVg4SV48wXxH" type="topic">socialism</rs> and spying. There must be
                            changes for the U.S. to be willing to improve <rs corresp="recW6DpFu8d7ioWcO" type="compound-subject">relations</rs>. We are upset
                            about repression in Poland. We are attacked every day at the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>. We cannot be taking all the positive
                            actions. Governments in Eastern Europe must show some effort, as Hungary
                            had done. That was the message he conveyed in Vienna and wanted
                            Ambassador Hazi to convey to the Hungarian leadership as well.</p>
                        <p>Hazi responded that there are differences. For example, 50 percent of
                            Hungary’s <gloss target="#t_GNP_1">GNP</gloss> was involved in
                            international trade, while only 7 percent of the Soviet Union’s <gloss target="#t_GNP_1">GNP</gloss> involved trade. But there were no
                            fundamental differences, for example on ideology, among the East
                            European countries. The Vice President noted that this certainly was not
                            true with regard to <rs corresp="recTdbwPhSPuOaeNu" type="topic">religion</rs> and other matters.</p>
                        <p>Hazi again stressed how highly the Hungarian leadership appreciated the
                            Vice President’s visit—the highest U.S. visitor ever—and how important
                            it is for them to be taken as a partner. He made a brief reference to
                            bilateral issues—return of the crown and Hungarian “expectation” that
                                <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> would be extended on a
                            multi-year basis so that companies could calculate more than a year
                            ahead. He then noted that Hungary is an
                            <!--<pb facs="d323-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d323-4"/>-->
                            “island” with the US-Soviet confrontation taking place overhead. They
                            were afraid as a small country. The Vice President stated that we think
                            the Soviets have made a big mistake by walking out in Geneva. They have
                            hurt their promotion of peace movements. Somehow they will have to come
                            back. President <persName corresp="#p_RR_1">Reagan</persName> is serious
                            about <rs corresp="recPup8iFysWzHs3K" type="topic">arms control</rs>, as he demonstrated even after KAL. There is a lot of
                            suspicion, but we know we have to find ways to live peacefully and one
                            way is to really reduce <rs corresp="recnsEXlwQs8HvH6c" type="topic">nuclear weapons</rs>. We won’t grant Soviets a
                            monopoly. We want to make a deal based on equality. There also are
                            plenty of other problems to resolve, like Afghanistan. What did Hazi
                            hear about the leadership situation in Moscow, about Andropov’s
                            <rs corresp="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic">health</rs>.</p>
                        <p>Hazi said he knew the thinking of “our side.” They are saying that the
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> wants to dominate the whole world
                            including the Soviet Union and socialist countries. If he listens here,
                            he hears the same text with the opposite target. Since <persName corresp="#p_SJ_4">Stalin</persName> there had been collective
                            decisions in Moscow. It will be quiet as long as civilians retain
                            control, but military takeover would present another picture. <persName corresp="#p_AY_1">Andropov</persName> is different than Brezhnev and
                            others. He is a little bit more European. Educated, knows English and
                            French, and knows Europe pretty well. This makes a difference but
                            Ustinov and the other marshals are taking the floor and taking political
                            positions.</p>
                        <p>Hazi then returned to the need to avoid extremes in talking about Hungary
                            in public. Hungary is prepared to take lessons from anywhere to improve
                            living standard. But after highest level meetings, there is discussion
                            and exaggeration. This causes problems. The Soviets and <pb facs="1049" n="1018" xml:id="pg_1018"/> other East Europeans ask what is
                            happening. Of course, this will not decide Hungary’s fate. US-Soviet
                            <rs corresp="recW6DpFu8d7ioWcO" type="compound-subject">relations</rs> are more important.</p>
                        <p>The Vice President concluded the meeting by noting that we see degrees of
                            difference in Hungary, that we are not trying to “peel” them away from
                            the Warsaw Pact, but that we hold certain values very strongly and that
                            these are important in how we treat the nations of Eastern Europe.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DK_1"><hi rend="strong">Dam</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>