<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
  <text>
    <body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-03-20T17:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-03-20T17:15:00-05:00" n="424" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d424">
                        <head>424. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d424fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_DP_1">Paula J. Dobriansky</persName> Files, Country Files, Albania
                                1981–1982. Confidential. Drafted on March 26. The meeting took place
                                in room 375 of the Old Executive Office Building.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" from="1981-03-20T17:15:00-05:00" to="1981-03-20T17:45:00-05:00">March 20, 1981, 5:15–5:45
                                    p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <!--<pb facs="d424-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d424-2"/>-->
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Summary of <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Advisor’s Meeting
                                with Leka I (C)</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_ARV_1">Richard V. Allen</persName>,
                                Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                            <item>James W. Nance, Deputy Assistant to the President for National
                                Security Affairs</item>
                            <item>Janet Colson, Executive Assistant to the Assistant to the
                                President for National Security Affairs</item>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_DP_1">Paula Dobriansky</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staff Member</item>
                            <item>Leka I of Albania</item>
                            <item>Abedin Mulosmanaj, Minister of Court</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral Nance</hi> opened the meeting by asking Leka I
                            to provide background on his current situation and his views of the
                            present Albanian regime. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Leka I</hi> remarked that after his father’s death in
                            1961, he became the leader of his father’s Albanian exile network. Thus,
                            in the mid-1960s, he started to coordinate liberation efforts abroad and
                            internally. He travelled extensively and finally settled in South
                            Africa. One of his main achievements, he said, was the formation of the
                            Military Council for the Integration of Albanians. Leka I then went on
                            to characterize Albania’s current regime under <persName corresp="#p_HE_1">Enver Hoxha</persName> as unstable, as it was
                            enduring considerable economic difficulties. Moreover, he asserted,
                            Albania’s domestic situation has been further exacerbated by Hoxha’s
                            poor health which has essentially precipitated a succession struggle.
                            (C)</p>
                        <p>In light of Albania’s present internal situation, <hi rend="italic">Leka
                                I</hi> contended that he could overthrow the current regime with
                            minimal time and international repercussions. However, to do so, he
                            stated he must secure moral and psychological support from the U.S. He
                            mentioned that the previous Administration requested that Saudi Arabia
                            and other Gulf States not give support to Leka I’s operation;
                            subsequently, their aid was halted. Thus, Leka I requested that the
                            United States reverse this policy. He asserted that his organization has
                            the <pb facs="1433" n="1402" xml:id="pg_1402"/> manpower, penetration
                            capabilities and even a military base—so they are not seeking material
                            support from the U.S., only moral support and a clear signal to Saudi
                            Arabia and the Gulf States to financially support their operation.
                            (C)</p>
                        <!--<pb facs="d424-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d424-3"/>-->
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Admiral Nance</hi> asked what would be the
                            ramifications and the anticipated East European reactions if Albania
                            were to be liberated. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Leka I</hi> responded that he could foresee no negative
                            consequences because Albania is geographically and ideologically
                            isolated, and the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is currently
                            occupied with the Polish crisis. He added that the possibility of
                            Yugoslav intervention is unlikely due to its internal problems.
                            Moreover, he maintained that even though the Albanians in the Kosovo
                            region of Yugoslavia want liberation and hope to be reunited with their
                            homeland, they will not simultaneously revolt. He stated that he
                            particularly wanted to allay our fears of imminent destabilization
                            resulting in Yugoslavia due to the liberation of Albania. Leka I also
                            mentioned that a change of government would be advantageous for the
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> because Albania could then permit
                            us to utilize their four ports.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_ARV_1">Richard
                                Allen</persName></hi> arrived at this point, and after exchanging
                            amenities, asked Leka I to provide an overview of Albanian alignment,
                            communications, and trade.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Leka I</hi> characterized Albania as an “orphan of the
                            communist world” for it has cut off its political ties with the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and China. In regard to Albania’s
                            communications, Leka stated that there are air flights from Belgrade and
                            Athens to Tirana. He also cited Yugoslavia as Albania’s prime trading
                            partner.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Allen</hi> then queried Leka I on what specifically is
                            his liberation strategy and time frame, how much financial support he
                            needs, and has South Africa provided any assistance, how long has this
                            effort been in progress, and what kind of government did Leka I envision
                            for Albania?</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Leka I</hi> replied that his network has been operative
                            since 1965–66. They have drawn up eight different plans by which they
                            seek to foment internal revolution in Albania within the next 2–3 months
                            or during the next 1–2 years. However, there is a need for a catalyst
                            within Albania. He mentioned that he will be moving to Egypt relatively
                            soon. This will put him in proximity to Albania and enable him to better
                            assess their various options and determine a conceivable catalyst.
                            Moreover, he said he would be more readily in touch with their Middle
                            East military base where they are training special teams to invade
                            Albania. Financially, Leka I stated no aid has been received from South
                            Africa, but due to Albania’s 75 percent Moslem composition, monetary
                            assistance was given by Saudi Arabia and other Gulf States. He estimated
                            that they needed $20 million, with a $5 million reserve to implement <pb facs="1434" n="1403" xml:id="pg_1403"/> their operation
                            successfully. However, he pointed out that this did not constitute their
                            current operating budget. Lastly, Leka maintained that Albania’s future
                            government would be determined by a referendum. Ergo, whether Albania is
                            to become a republic or monarchy depends on the Albanian people.</p>
                        <!--<pb facs="d424-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d424-4"/>-->
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_ARV_1">Richard
                                Allen</persName></hi> further questioned Leka I about how well known
                            he is, what exactly is the number of his supporters, and what would be
                            the impact of this liberation movement on Yugoslavia. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Leka I</hi> asked the Minister of Court to respond to
                            the first question. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Mulosmanaj</hi> maintained that Leka is quite well
                            known and respected among Albanians. (C)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Leka I</hi> then refused to divulge the exact number of
                            his supporters for security reasons. However, he went on to maintain
                            that the contention that a liberation of Albania would precipitate an
                            explosion in Yugoslavia and would bring in the Russians is erroneous.
                            Rather, he asserted that the Albanians in Yugoslavia will remain calm
                            and not revolt. [<hi rend="italic">less than 2 lines not
                                declassified</hi>] However, he still sought an answer from Mr. Allen
                            in regard to our conceivable support. (C)<note n="2" type="source" xml:id="d424fn2">The final sentence, was scribbled through by an
                                unknown hand.</note></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_ARV_1">Richard
                                Allen</persName></hi> responded that Leka I will get an answer.
                            (C)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
