<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 21.Mr. Osborn to Mr. Frelinghuysen</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1882</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1882-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1882-06-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1882-06-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1882-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="21"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d21">
                <head>No. 21.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Osborn</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-06-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 19, 1882.</date> (Received July
                        21.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 37.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>In consequence of two questions which have arisen between Brazil and the Republic
                    of Uruguay their relations have become somewhat strained.</p>
                <p>It is claimed by this government that in November of 1880 a battalion of
                    Uruguayan cavalry which was employed in the Uruguayan province of Tuacarembo
                    pressed into the military service a considerable number of Brazilian citizens,
                    five of whom were, with the approval of the commander of the force,
                    Lieutenant-Colonel Santos, brutally and without cause put to death. During the
                    past year a vast deal of testimony has been taken by the Brazilian
                    consul-general in Montevideo, all tending to sustain this general charge.</p>
                <p>The Uruguayan authorities, at the solicitation of the Brazilian legation in
                    Montevideo, undertook an investigation of the charges, and the result has
                    recently been laid before this government. The commission intrusted with the
                    inquiry conclude that the complaint is groundless, and the Uruguayan Government,
                    in forwarding the determination here, express the hope that the incident may be
                    regarded as at an end. The Brazilian Government, however, do not appear to be
                    content to let the affair drop. They are confident of the truth of the
                    allegations made, <pb facs="0103" n="31" xml:id="pg_31"/> and seem inclined to
                    urge upon the republic the punishment of the offenders; but I fail to discover
                    any indications of a disposition upon their part to press their view of the
                    matter to the extent of interrupting their friendly relations with their
                    comparatively defenseless neighbor.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>The other question has reference to financial transactions between the two
                    governments. It is conceded, I believe, that Uruguay is indebted to Brazil on
                    account of advances made at various times to the extent of some millions of
                    dollars, but I am not sure that they agree as to the exact condition of the
                    account. According to the Brazilian claim the debt now amounts to about nine
                    millions, the major part of which is for interest. This government has been
                    urging an adjustment of the matter, and some steps have been recently essayed by
                    the Uruguayan legation here, having apparently that object in view; but I am not
                    aware that anything approaching an understanding has been reached.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>The government professes to believe that these questions will ultimately be
                    amicably arranged. They disclaim any purpose of an attempt to enforce their
                    demands by other than peaceful means, and I know of no reason for distrusting
                    their sincerity. There is, it is true, some sentiment here which would justify a
                    bold movement, having for its object the forced absorption of Uruguay, but it
                    has not reached dangerous proportions. The present government have expressed
                    themselves quite emphatically in opposition to any step in that direction, and I
                    do not doubt that they have correctly interpreted the will of the nation. In
                    addition to the causes which I have enumerated, it is urged in support of the
                    said policy that the government of the republic is weak and inefficient to the
                    extent of being incapable of performing its proper functions. There are some
                    forty thousand Brazilians in the northern portion of the republic. These people
                    and their property, it is claimed, receive no efficient protection at the hands
                    of the government. It is also urged that the recklessness of that country, in
                    its dealings with foreigners and foreign interests, is liable at any moment to
                    produce a war in which this government might find it difficult to maintain a
                    position of neutrality; that its existence is a constant menace to peace in this
                    part of the world; and that the only effectual remedy for these evils is a
                    destruction of its nationality.</p>
                <p>There are those, too, who profess to believe that the interests of civilization
                    would be subserved by a forced division of that country between Brazil and the
                    Argentine Republic. This scheme has been quietly discussed by some of the
                    prominent politicians of the country, but as yet there are no indications that
                    it would meet with favor at the hands of this government, even if it should be
                    acceptable to the Argentine Republic. The minister of foreign relations, in the
                    course of a response to an interpellation in the House of Deputies a few days
                    ago, approached this subject very delicately, and apparently with much caution,
                    measuring his words, deprecated its public discussion, asserting at the same
                    time that Brazil was disposed to observe her treaty obligations with Uruguay,
                    and was not anxious for territorial acquisition in that quarter.</p>
                <p>It has occurred to me, however, that the day may come when the republic will
                    propose to pay its debt to the empire with territory. The policy of accepting
                    such a proposition would undoubtedly find many influential advocates here, and
                    it is possible that the government might feel inclined to give it a favorable
                    consideration. Just how far the President of the United States ought to
                    acquiesce in a voluntary transfer by an American republic of its domain to a
                    monarchical power <pb facs="0104" n="32" xml:id="pg_32"/> presents, I apprehend,
                    a question of no slight moment. There may be no occasion for its consideration
                    on account of the situation here, and yet I shall not be surprised if the
                    contrary proves to be true.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>THOMAS A. OSBORN.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
