<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 23.Mr. Logan
                            to Mr. Frelinghuysen..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1882</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1882-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1882-03-03T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1882-03-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1882-03-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="23" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                <head>No. 23.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Logan</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala
                                    City</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-03-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 3, 1882</date>.
                            (Received April 17.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 273.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Under cover of this dispatch I inclose the
                        translation of an editorial article from El Guatemalteco, the official organ
                        of the Guatemala Government, relating to the proposed American Peace
                        Congress. Its utterances are important. * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C. A. LOGAN.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0105" n="33" xml:id="pg_33"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 273.—From the
                                Guatemalteco, of February 18, 1882.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the peace congress.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The document which is published in the present number gives an account to
                            the public of the result of the projected Congress of Panama, which
                            should have been inaugurated in that city on the 1st of December of the
                            past year, according to the invitation directed with this object by the
                            United States of Colombia.</p>
                    <p>The government of General Barrios, understanding that peace is the great
                            necessity of the American republics, overrun with wars which nearly
                            always were without reason or object, had accepted the invitation thus
                            opportunely sent, and fulfilling the obligation which voluntarily it had
                            desired to accept, accredited in due form the citizen who ought to
                            represent it. But the generous proposition to establish arbitration as a
                            principle of American public right, and to proscribe war, with its sad
                            train of calamities and misfortunes, from the beautiful continent of
                            Columbus, was defeated for the time being. Nevertheless it is not
                            necessary to be discouraged. The grand ideas which bring with them the
                            seed of a profound transformation and improvement for the peoples are
                            immortal, and must succeed sooner or later, although they may have to
                            encounter obstacles opposed to their propagation and increase which, for
                            the moment, appear insuperable. Humanity never loses sight of them, and
                            when the propitious moment arrives, avails itself of, and obtains from
                            them, all the fruit they are destined to produce.</p>
                    <p>This reflection is suggested to us by the circumstance that the
                            Government of the United States of North America has just addressed,
                            through its respective ministers, an invitation to all the independent
                            governments of America to take part in a general peace Congress, which
                            will meet in the city of Washington in the month of November of
                            1882.</p>
                    <p>The Government of Guatemala immediately, and with the greatest
                            enthusiasm, accepted this new invitation; and it is certain that,
                            partaking of the initiative of the great nation called upon to sustain
                            and lend such great services to the liberty of other countries of
                            America, the generous impulse of peace will now go forth from the sphere
                            of beautiful ideals to convert itself into a beneficent reality,
                            fruitful for all Latin-American countries in precious guarantees of
                            tranquillity and respect for right.</p>
                    <p>The note in reply to the invitation of the Government of the United
                            States is a frank manifestation of the particular principles which the
                            Government of Guatemala professes, and an unequivocal demonstration of
                            those sentiments of admiration, sympathy, and respect which that
                            extraordinary people inspire, without example in history, who, at each
                            step, make the most valiant and surprising conquests in politics,
                            industry, arts, and in all branches of progress and. civilization.</p>
                    <p>Abounding in the same sentiments expressed in the note referred to, we
                            can say that all America is to be congratulated. Soon, very soon, that
                            Congress, which cannot fail to realize its objects, because the idea
                            proceeds from a nation of unbreakable energy, which without receding
                            marches ever forward in all it undertakes, will be a work that will
                            honor America and all humanity, and will figure without comparison among
                            the greatest and grandest events of this century.</p>
                    <p>We also send our most cordial felicitations to the Government of the
                            United States of America, because it will be the one that realizes that
                            magnificent and consolatory theory of peace, inasmuch as it was
                            reserved, without doubt, to the greatest people to bring to a
                            culmination the greatest idea.</p>
                    <p>The endeavors which some other nations of America have made, pursuing
                            that ideal, are certainly laudable, but it becomes necessary to confess
                            that the undertaking is of such magnitude, that it has not yet had a
                            champion who, under all circumstances, might be able to sustain it
                            without bending under its weight. To-day it is the great Colossus of the
                            American continent, which takes upon itself the realization of that
                            brilliant and philanthropic thought, and equal as it is to the magnitude
                            of the idea, the greatness of the people which is its powerful
                            sustainer, assures us, without doubt, that we are now upon the eve of
                            those fortunate days in which the tree of peace will extend its shade
                            over all the American peoples; in which only the respect for right will
                            reign, and in which war will not return to visit these regions which for
                            so long a time have suffered from its ravages.</p>
                    <p>Our conviction is that not one of the Latin-American powers will refuse
                            to proceed promptly to the rendezvous which gives promise to realize the
                            generous purpose which has inspired the invitation which occupies our
                            attention, nor fail to be worthily represented in that great Congress of
                            peace.</p>
                    <p>Guatemala felicitates itself that to the United States shall belong the
                            glory of acquiring so splendid a conquest, and that the nation which has
                            shown itself so great in war, so great in work and in industry, so great
                            in its organization, in its principles and institutions, so great in all
                            that is civilization and advancement, shall be equally great in bringing
                            to its consummation a work which must figure as one of the most
                            beautiful pages in her brilliant history, because it will be of the most
                            transcendental importance to the cause of America, and of all
                            humanity.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
