<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 44.Mr. Trescot to Mr. Frelinghuysen..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1882</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1882-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1882-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recxoy5ut8BiKquym" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006004857"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Littoral</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recfec047f5431758f" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="property-claims" subject="contraband-of-war">Contraband of war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1882-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1882-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="44"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                <head>No. 44.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Trescot</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Special Mission of the United States in South
                                America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Viña del Mar, Chili</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-02-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 3, 1882</date>. (Received March
                        7.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 8.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my dispatch, numbered seven, I have
                    to inform you that after mailing it I received a letter from Mr. Hurlbut, saying
                    that he had already extended the invitation of the President to the Government
                    of Peru to attend the proposed congress in Washington.</p>
                <p>This action, of which I had been so apprehensive, rendered it necessary that the
                    invitation should also be extended to Chili, for I had no doubt that the fact
                    would be published in the Lima papers. And by the last mail from Lima, I find
                    that not only the fact but the invitation in full has been published.</p>
                <p>I therefore wrote to Mr. Adams, at La Paz, and to Mr. Blaine, who is <hi
                        rend="italic">chargé d’affaires</hi> here, to say that I desired them to
                    consider my request for delay in the presentation of the invitation as now
                    withdrawn. These letters, with one to Mr. Hurlbut in reply to his information,
                    will be found in inclosures numbered 1, 2, and 3.</p>
                <p>As an interview with the secretary for foreign affairs had been appointed for
                    Tuesday last (January 31), Mr. Blaine accompanied me, in order to read the
                    invitation in conformity with his instructions.</p>
                <p>Our interview had been arranged for the purpose of comparing our respective
                    drafts of a protocol summarizing the substance of our former confidential
                    conferences, a proceeding to which the secretary seemed to attach considerable
                    importance. After reading over Mr. Balmaceda’s draft in Spanish, and receiving a
                    copy for more careful consideration, I explained to him the purpose of Mr.
                    Blaine’s visit. To my great surprise, he expressed the wish that Mr. Blaine
                    would not read the communication, and then, turning to me, he said, “It is
                    useless. Your government has withdrawn the invitation.” Seeing, I suppose, an
                    expression of astonishment, which I did not pretend to conceal, he added, “Your
                    own instructions have been changed. Your instructions from Mr. Blaine have been
                    published, and others are on their way to you modifying your original
                    instructions in very important particulars. The whole question about Calderon is
                    out of the way, and you are told to be entirely neutral.”</p>
                <p>I replied, “I do not understand that there is any such thing as a Calderon
                    question between us,” and then said, “Do you mean, Mr. Secretary, that both my
                    original instructions and the instructions from the present administration are
                    published?”</p>
                <p>He said, “Yes, before you have received them I have a telegram, not in cipher,
                    but open,” to which I replied that I supposed so, because I could not see the
                    use of a cipher dispatch in referring to papers already published.</p>
                <p>He added, “Yes, they have been published, and will be soon published here in La
                    Patria” (a newspaper). He then went out of the room and returned with a
                    telegram, which, he said, had come from Paris only two days before, and of which
                    he read me the first line, which, as I recollect, was, “The Blaine-Trescot
                    instruction has been published,” and then paused, smiling and looking over the
                    telegram, as if he were uncertain whether he should communicate the rest. I
                    said, “As you say that all this is confidential, don’t make a half confidence of
                    it. If I am to receive my instructions through you let me know them in full.” He
                        <pb facs="0140" n="68" xml:id="pg_68"/> smiled, shook his head, and folded
                    up the telegram, saying, “This, however, will not interrupt our negotiation,”
                    and then proceeded, at some length, to state why and to explain what he
                    considered the advantages of the condition of things under the new
                    instructions.</p>
                <p>I said to him, “That may all be so, Mr. Secretary, but I think that a diplomatist
                    of ordinary experience would conclude, when he learns that his instructions have
                    been communicated to the government with which he is negotiating, before he
                    receives them himself, that it is time for him to be silent until he does
                    receive them. I think there must be some mistake about all this, but at any rate
                    I must decline to say a word more until I learn from my government what it has
                    done and what it means me to do.”</p>
                <p>He said that he hoped that I would receive my instructions very soon; that the
                    position was strained and could not be maintained for an indefinite time, that
                    is, Chili could not wait much longer for the United States to decide what action
                    it would take, and then, for the first time in our conferences, his manner
                    became excited and his language somewhat too demonstrative. “Since you have been
                    here,” he added, “two occurrences have taken place which I am sure are
                    disagreeable to you as they are to Chili. Mr. Hurlbut has refused to consent to
                    the export of certain goods from the blockaded port of Mollendo, unless we will
                    consent to the import of coal, an article contraband of war, tor the use of the
                    railroad, and although we have a right to disregard his refusal, we have not
                    done so. And secondly, Mr. Adams, in Bolivia, has addressed a letter to the
                    government at La Paz, advising them of your mission, and endeavoring to induce
                    them not to make a separate peace before Peru has effected some arrangement, and
                    I do not know how long Chili can bear such interference.”</p>
                <p>I said, “Mr. Secretary, the facts which you state are grave, so grave that even
                    in the most confidential conversation I will not express an opinion unless you
                    communicate them to me officially; then I will meet the questions you
                    raise.”</p>
                <p>He said, “I have no intention of doing so; I did not even intend to draw a
                    confidential answer from you.”</p>
                <p>There the interview ended.</p>
                <p>The facts of Mr. Hurlbut’s action, as I have heard them, are these: At the
                    blockaded port of Mollendo, on the Peruvian coast, there has been a large
                    accumulation of produce waiting for exportation. An application was made by Mr.
                    Adams, without consultation with Mr. Hurlbut, to the Chilian authorities in Lima
                    for license to certain mercantile firms, German, I believe, to take out their
                    goods. Fearing that such permission might be considered as an abandonment of the
                    blockade, the Chilian authorities asked the consent of the diplomatic corps in
                    Lima to the issue of the license. Mr. Hurlbut replied that the only American
                    interest in Mollendo was the railroad from Mollendo to Puno, and if that
                    corporation were allowed to import the coal and supplies necessary for its wants
                    he would consent.</p>
                <p>You will observe that these facts, if correct, furnish ground for a very
                    different estimate of Mr. Hurlbut’s action than that made by the secretary for
                    foreign affairs. But as I had no official information, either from Mr. Hurlbut
                    or from the Chilian Government, I deemed it injudicious to enter upon any
                    confidential discussion of the subject.</p>
                <p>As to Mr. Adams there has been a general impression here that Bolivia had
                    consented or would consent to a separate peace with Chili, by which, in exchange
                    for her littoral territory upon the Pacific, she would be indemnified by some
                    cession of Peruvian territory. When Mr. Adams returned to La Paz he communicated
                    the purpose of the special <pb facs="0141" n="69" xml:id="pg_69"/> mission to
                    the government, and did, I believe, succeed in inducing them to suspend any such
                    action until it could be ascertained if the good offices of the United States
                    could effect a general and satisfactory solution. In this I conceive that Mr.
                    Adams was only acting in the line of his duty, but I did not deem it proper to
                    discuss it in a confidential or informal way, for reasons which I think will be
                    obvious to you.</p>
                <p>Having thus given you a concise account of the interview, you will allow me to
                    express the hope that my conduct will be approved. My original instructions were
                    in the alternative, and if I failed to obtain such a settlement as the President
                    deemed he had a right to expect, I was directed to take certain action, which
                    could not have been agreeable to the Chilian Government. I could not suppose
                    that such an instruction would be made public while I was endeavoring to secure,
                    and not without some hope of success, the amicable solution of this delicate and
                    difficult question. Still less could I believe that if my original instructions
                    had been seriously modified any communication of such change would have been
                    made to the public, or even confidentially to the Chilian Government, before I
                    could possibly have received it. I could not admit, what the Secretary’s
                    conversation clearly implied, that I did not represent the wishes or intention
                    of my government, and that he was better instructed than myself as to the
                    purposes of my mission.</p>
                <p>But as his language and action were evidently based upon his confident knowledge
                    of these supposed instructions, any further conference with him was useless
                    until I heard from the Department.</p>
                <p>As both the telegram which I received upon my arrival at Valparaiso, and that of
                    the 10th of January, which reached me only on the 31st ultimo, the translations
                    of which are herewith inclosed, indicated the propriety of very great caution in
                    the execution of my original instructions, and as my telegram of January 23,
                    stating the terms upon which Chili would accept the good offices of the United
                    States, and a reply to which was absolutely necessary for any further
                    negotiation, has not yet been answered, I have determined to do nothing whatever
                    until the receipt of instructions from the government.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WM. HENRY TRESCOT.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 8.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Trescot</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Adams</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Special Mission of the United States in South
                                    America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Viña del Mar, Chili</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-01-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 30, 1882</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my last communication, transmitting the
                        dispatches which had been intercepted, I called your attention to that one
                        in which you were instructed to convey to the Government of Bolivia the
                        invitation from the President of the United States to that government to
                        send representatives to the proposed peace congress at Washington.</p>
                    <p>In doing so, I asked you to suspend action upon this instruction until you
                        heard further from me on the subject. In the mean time I have been informed
                        by Mr. Hurlbut, the minister of the United States at Lima, that he received
                        similar instructions, and has already communicated them to the Government of
                        Peru. He does not say to whom he has communicated them, as the
                        representative of that government.</p>
                    <p>You will understand that however inopportune I may consider this
                        communication of Mr. Hurlbut, it renders necessary the communication of the
                        invitation to the other powers.</p>
                    <p>You will therefore consider the request for delay which I made you as now
                        withdrawn.</p>
                    <p>I beg to acknowledge your communication of January the 12th, with its
                        inclosure. I am waiting in hourly expectation of telegraphic instruction
                        from the Department, upon the receipt of which I will write you again.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. H. TRESCOT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0142" n="70" xml:id="pg_70"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 8.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Trescot</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Walker Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Special Mission of the United States in South
                                    America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Viña del Mar, Chili</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-01-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 30, 1882</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The reasons which induced me to ask you to
                        withhold for the present the invitation from the President of the United
                        States to the Government of Chili to take part in the proposed peace
                        congress at Washington are known to you.</p>
                    <p>The dispatches which I have addressed to the Department upon this subject
                        have also been communicated to you, and you are aware that a similar request
                        was made of Mr. Hurlbut, at Lima, and Mr. Adams, at La Paz.</p>
                    <p>I have received from Mr. Hurlbut a communication under date of January 18, in
                        which he informs me that he has already communicated this invitation to the
                        Peruvian Government.</p>
                    <p>However inopportune I may consider this communication, it renders the
                        delivery of the invitation to the Chilian Government at once absolutely
                        necessary.</p>
                    <p>My request that the invitation be withheld is therefore now withdrawn.</p>
                    <p>I have written to Mr. Adams to the same effect, and inclose you copies of my
                        communication to Mr. Hurlbut and himself.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. H. TRESCOT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 8.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Trescot</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hurlbut</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Special Mission of the United States in South
                                    America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Viña del Mar, Chili</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-01-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 30, 1882</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge your communication of
                        January 18, in which you inform me that you have received and communicated
                        to the Peruvian Government the invitation from the President of the United
                        States to the proposed peace congress in Washington.</p>
                    <p>The circumstances under which I asked that you would suspend action upon this
                        instruction until after consultation with me were these:</p>
                    <p>When I was about leaving Washington I was informed by the Secretary that such
                        an invitation would be issued, indeed that it had already been sent to
                        Mexico and Guatemala. I understood that the invitations to Chili, Peril, and
                        Bolivia were to be sent through me to be delivered as the circumstances of
                        the anticipated negotiation seemed to render opportune.</p>
                    <p>Not finding any such instructions, I telegraphed and wrote from Panama,
                        saying in my dispatch of December 12, “I beg to inform you that the mail
                        contains no such communication, and it will occur to you without suggestion
                        from me that if at some later date these invitations are transmitted to the
                        ministers at Lima, Santiago, and La Paz they should be instructed not to
                        present them without my knowledge and approval. Their delay might, under
                        circumstances by no means improbable, cause very serious embarrassment in
                        the conduct of the special mission with which I have been charged. A
                        reference to my instructions will, I think, sufficiently explain my
                        meaning.”</p>
                    <p>The difficulty which I anticipated must, I think, have occurred to you.</p>
                    <p>I could not with any fitness extend this invitation to the Chilian Government
                        until I had ascertained what were the relations between us. If the
                        negotiations should terminate in failure, disturbing the amicable relations
                        between us, the invitation would be either offensive or idle; Chili might,
                        if irritated by the position of the United States as defined in my
                        instruction, construe it to mean an appeal to the public opinion of the
                        American republics against her. But still more important was it that this
                        invitation should not be communicated to Peru and Bolivia without at the
                        same time being communicated to Chili.</p>
                    <p>My hope therefore was that Mr. Adams and yourself would wait until the time
                        came when the invitation could be properly extended to Chili. I thought it
                        not improbable that you would consider the instructions sent you in
                        reference to the special mission as sufficiently indicating that all
                        questions bearing upon this very delicate and difficult negotiation were to
                        be left to my discretion.</p>
                    <p>But if your instructions did not in your opinion bear this construction, I
                        felt sure that you would, at my request, co-operate with me in such a line
                        of conduct as, in my judgment, seemed necessary here. I can only regret
                        therefore that my request reached you too late, and after you had carried
                        out your instructions as you understood them.</p>
                    <p>The communication of the invitation to Peru of course now renders it
                        absolutely <pb facs="0143" n="71" xml:id="pg_71"/> necessary to extend the
                        invitation to Chili at once, and I have so informed Mr. Blaine, to whom, as
                        the successor of General Kilpatrick, the invitation is intrusted.</p>
                    <p>I have also written to Mr. Adams that he will consider my request of delay on
                        his part as now withdrawn.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. H. TRESCOT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
