<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 72.Mr. Holcombe to Mr. Frelinghuysen..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1882</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1882-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1882-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1882-01-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1882-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="72"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                <head>No. 72.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Holcombe</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-01-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 21, 1882</date>. (Received April
                        7.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 54.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the voluminous correspondence
                    between this legation and the Department in regard to the “Woosung Bar,” and the
                    repeated <pb facs="0193" n="121" xml:id="pg_121"/> efforts made to secure, the
                    removal of this very serious obstruction to the commerce of Shanghai, I have the
                    honor to inclose, herewith, a newspaper extract from which the Department will
                    learn with pleasure that steps have at last been taken by the Chinese
                    authorities to dredge the bar and deepen the channel of water communication
                    between Shanghai and the sea.</p>
                <p>I have no further information as to the details of the scheme than may be found
                    in the extract inclosed.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHESTER HOLCOMBE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 54.—Extract from the Shanghai
                            Courier of Friday, January 6, 1882.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">away with it.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>At the end of last month we were able to give our readers the intelligence
                        that at length the Woosung Bar is to be eradicated. A contract was signed on
                        27th December by the Taotai Liu on behalf of the Chinese Government on the
                        one side, and Mr. W. Watson, of Messrs. Maclean &amp; Co., on the other, for
                        the importation of a dredging machine to be used specially for the removal
                        of the “heaven sent barrier.” Thus, after ten years’ continuous exertion on
                        the part of the weightiest and wealthiest circle of the community, backed by
                        the Chamber of Commerce, and aided by the influence of China merchants in
                        England, that which these combined agencies have failed to achieve has been
                        accomplished by an individual firm. It is a significant fact that the China
                        of to-day is a country which at last has awakened from its long repose in
                        Sleepy Hollow, and is fully aroused to the necessity of keeping pace with
                        the giant strides of the West. In olden days the Woosung bar was regarded by
                        Prince Kung and the official celestials generally as an omnipotent barrier
                        to the Western barbarian. By them it was looked upon as a fragment of the
                        great wall of China sunk in the mouth of the Whangpo. As the great wall was
                        thought to be a most perfect means of excluding the outer barbarians from
                        entering on the domains of the Son of Heaven, so this bar was looked upon as
                        a most effective protection against foreign war-ships attempting to come up
                        to Shanghai. It was this feeling that caused the Chinese officials to offer
                        that impalpable but persistent opposition to any preliminary measures
                        proposed to abolish this obstacle that has, until lately, characterized the
                        celestial nation in dealing with the foreigner. As we have stated, the
                        determined outcry of the foreigners, and their customary energy in
                        endeavoring to remove this bar, dates from some ten years back. In olden
                        days when the vessels visiting this port were nearly all sailing ships,
                        those of deep draught were content to wait for days at the bar for water.
                        Those were the “good old times” when there was only a monthly mail delivered
                        by the P. and O. in steamers no bigger than the present Tientsin packets,
                        when Shanghai made pleasure a business and business a pleasure, when there
                        was none of the hurry-scurry worry, and fight for existence which
                        characterises the settlement of to-day. But now, immediately ships arrive at
                        Woosung, it is imperative that they should force a way over the bar, and
                        come into port with all possible speed. To assist them in doing this a swarm
                        of cargo-boats have cropped up on the river, and they are always in
                        readiness to hurry to the bar, and lighter ships of deep draught
                        sufficiently to enable them more easily to force their keels through the mud
                        of the bar.</p>
                    <p>In consequence of this, the leading merchants, and notably the Chamber of
                        Commerce, brought their weight and energy to bear on the Chinese with a view
                        to the removal of the obstruction. Thus at great expense, and with
                        considerable perseverance in this direction, Messrs. Escher and De Ryke were
                        instructed to survey the river and report upon the cheapest and most
                        efficient method by which a clear channel could be maintained. The
                        exhaustive and elaborate reports of these gentlemen will be sufficiently
                        fresh in the recollection of our readers to dispense with recapitulation.
                        But able and practical as were the suggestions of these experts, and backed
                        as they were by the influence of the Chamber of Commerce, they were never
                        practically recognized by the Chinese authorities. Nor did Major Bridgford’s
                        report achieve any greater success, although the method which he advocated
                        for clearing the river was estimated to cost no more than Tls.150,000. We
                        may here remark that, at the period when the name of the Heaven-sent barrier
                        was given to this bar, if the foreign merchants had agreed to remove the
                        obstruction at their own expense, it is more than questionable if the
                        Chinese authorities would have permitted such an action, judging from the
                        spirit in which they regarded this impediment to the navigation of <pb
                            facs="0194" n="122" xml:id="pg_122"/> the Whangpoo. Comparing the
                        opinions held by the Chinese on this matter some ten years since with those
                        which have been just recently expressed by them in their latest action, we
                        are struck with the advance the “black-headed people” have made in regard to
                        emerging from a strict and bigoted conservatism into a liberal and
                        progressive mode of thinking and acting.</p>
                    <p>The contract just signed is a significant fact of China’s progressiveness,
                        and forms a conclusive answer to those who are ringing eternal changes on
                        the antiquated opinions formed of the conservatism of the nation. In respect
                        to the method to be employed in removing the bar under the contract recently
                        signed, we know but little, except that a dredger vessel is being built by
                        Messrs. William Simon’s &amp; Co., of London Works, Renfrew, Scotland. It
                        will be schooner-rigged, with twin screws, and of 80-horse power, nominal.
                        It will be what is designated the “patent hopper dredger,” and will carry
                        600 tons of mud at an average speed of seven miles per hour, lifted from the
                        bottom to a maximum of 30 feet, at the rate of 300 tons per hour.</p>
                    <p>As to whether this dredger is to be employed directly upon the bar, or what
                        is known as the false channel of the Whangpoo, we are not in a position to
                        say. But from the several reports upon the best methods of clearing the
                        river which we have seen, most of the experts concur in advocating the
                        “development” of the north or junk channel. The advantage of this method of
                        procedure has been ably explained and advocated in Major Bridgford’s report.
                        In this he states: “When man attempts to meddle with nature he can only
                        succeed in permanently modifying its aspects by studying the constant laws
                        of its phenomena and by making his works conformable to these.” And in
                        following out this axiom Major Bridgford points out that if by any
                        reasonable means the whole volume of the river could be diverted into one
                        channel instead of as at present being divided by Gough’s Island into two,
                        the false bars would cease to exist. Thus the junk channel would be made the
                        true and deep course of the river, and the ship channel would silt up
                        entirely. To accomplish this the major points out that the first object to
                        be attained is the enlargement of the sectional area of the most shoal
                        portion of the junk channel, as by having an enlarged area a much greater
                        volume of flood-tide water will be projected past Gough’s Island, and sp
                        stored for supplying the ebb with increased volume. As this enlargement
                        progresses the strength of the ebb will at first increase in the ship’s
                        channel owing to the increased volume of water received through the junk
                        channel; and will also from the same cause (plus the enlargement of the
                        channel) increase the ebb in the junk channel.</p>
                    <p>By this method it is shown that gradually the volume discharged by the junk
                        channel would exceed that discharged by the ship channel to such an extent
                        that the false bar or lip at its lower end would commence to silt up, thus
                        increasing the choke to the ebb in that channel. The principal advantages
                        claimed by Major Bridgford for this method of attack are summarized as
                        follows: First, that the navigation will not be impeded during the progress
                        of the works; second, it will give more rise of tide up the river; third,
                        the restoring of that section of the river to one channel, navigable at all
                        times of tide, instead of at present having two channels that are only
                        navigable at certain times of tide.</p>
                    <p>As we have already stated, we are in ignorance as to whether the dredger
                        which is to arrive in Shanghai within nine months from the present time will
                        work upon the system advocated by the above report. But experts in this
                        matter are of opinion that instead of using steam hoppers and carrying mud
                        out to sea, it might be cheaper to discharge it on the banks where it could
                        be utilized. This could easily be accomplished by what is known as an
                        “overhead traveller,” or if it were discovered that sand had accumulated in
                        the bed of the channel, it could speedily be conveyed ashore by a “flume,”
                        similar to those used with such signal success in the Suez Canal. But by
                        whatever means the new dredger is to work, we have all to be thankful that
                        at length the barrier is to be abolished, and that at the end of the present
                        year we can exclaim, “Away with it.”</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
