<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>183. Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs’
                    Special Assistant (Sullivan))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d183</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">183</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-10-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-10-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="183"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                <head>183. Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs’ Special
                    Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d183fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_KJF1"
                            >Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security Files, Vietnam Country
                        Series, Memos and Miscellaneous. Secret. A note on the source text indicates
                        that this memorandum was taken from the President’s weekend reading of
                        October 6, and that its approximate date was October 5. <persName
                            corresp="#p_SWH1">Sullivan</persName> was a member of the <persName
                            corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                            >McNamara</persName> Mission to Vietnam, September 24-October 1, and he
                        labeled this a “Mission Memorandum.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1963-10-05">undated</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Divergent Attitudes in U.S. Official Community</item>
                </list>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> has asked me to
                    examine the nature and the cause of differing opinions and attitudes in the
                    official US community in Vietnam. Specifically, he is concerned with the
                    divergent evaluations of the success which we are having in “winning the war
                    against the Viet Cong.”</p>
                <p>I have talked with various members of the official community and have, in
                    general, covered the same ground with each element of the Country Team. My first
                    observation is that there are divergencies but that they do not divide cleanly
                    and sharply along Service and Department lines. Within each of the elements of
                    the Team, there are individuals who hold views more or less at variance with the
                    majority of others in their element. However, insofar as any general watershed
                    of opinion can be detected, it finds the civilian components of the Country Team
                    on one hand and the military components on the other.</p>
                <p>In approaching the views of these two general communities or the basic question
                    of “winning the war”, I soon became aware that, in their answers, they were
                    addressing themselves fundamentally to two different questions. The military
                    directed themselves primarily to the more active, physical task of
                    counterinsurgency, i.e., conducting clear and hold operations, building
                    strategic hamlets, isolating the population from the Viet Cong, organizing
                    protection for the cleared areas, and prodding the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1"
                        >ARVN</gloss> into search and destroy actions against Viet Cong
                    strongholds.</p>
                <p>The civilians, on the other hand, directed themselves more to the psychological
                    aspects of the problem. They were concerned less with the physical task of
                    eliminating Viet Cong operations and more with the job of eliminating those
                    mental attitudes among the population which made the people receptive and
                    susceptible to the subversive and propaganda activities of the Viet Cong.</p>
                <pb facs="0407" n="381" xml:id="pg_381"/>
                <p>Moreover, the military are oriented towards a specific mission which they are
                    undertaking. They feel a justifiable sense of accomplishment in the results they
                    have achieved to date. They can measure the indices of their progress and have a
                    “can-do”, “gung-ho” sense of confidence in their ability to complete their
                    mission.</p>
                <p>The civilians, on the other hand (with the exception of <gloss target="#t_USOM1"
                        >USOM</gloss>), are oriented towards a more passive and more frustrating
                    task of attempting to dissuade an oriental regime from its method of governing
                    and to persuade it to use other methods which involve more empathy towards the
                    popular mind. They constantly watch the Government, despite their urgings, throw
                    away opportunities to gain greater popular acceptance. They feel that each of
                    these occasions gives new advantages to the Viet Cong and that each constitutes
                    a step backward in the psychological battle. They do not, in general, discount
                    the physical progress that has been made in the counterinsurgency effort, but
                    they are inclined to question the quality of its efforts in the light of the
                    Government’s political ineptness.</p>
                <p>Hence, the military and the civilian components of the Country Team approach the
                    same set of data from different perspectives. They fall almost inevitably into
                    the classic postures of the two men who look at the same glass of water—one sees
                    it half full, the other sees it half empty. This difference in perspective is
                    then magnified by the imprecision of the data examined. All honest US observers
                    admit that there are great margins of tolerance and doubt in the statistics on
                    which they base their conclusions. Therefore, there is an opportunity for a
                    great deal of subjective interpretation in deriving a conclusion from a given
                    set of “facts”.</p>
                <p>Moreover, and compounding this essential occasion for divergence, there enters
                    into the picture a considerable emotional element. On the military side, this
                    takes the form of professional or service pride. Any suggestion that success is
                    not being attained is considered a personal affront, a reflection impugning the
                    achievements of the US armed forces. On the civilian side, any effort by the
                    military to reach essentially political or intelligence conclusions is
                    considered an incursion into or even the pre-emption of a field of activity
                    which should be properly civilian.</p>
                <p>Finally, and as the ultimate fillings to the emotional charge, is the simple
                    problem of the pecking order. When I came here a year ago with General <persName
                        corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>, it was my observation that the “top
                    banana” in the US official community was General <persName corresp="#p_HGPD1"
                        >Harkins</persName>. This was understandable, not only was he a senior
                    officer in the Army, but he was a man with a considerable reputation and
                    experience. He disposed of infinitely more resources than the Ambassador and he
                    had a far more impressive establishment responsive to his direct command.
                    Moreover, he and his command represented the new and the current thrust <pb
                        facs="0408" n="382" xml:id="pg_382"/> of highest level US policy interest in
                    Vietnam. He was the executor of the main US drive of the day in which there was
                    invested a great measure of US prestige.</p>
                <p>Fritz <persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1">Nolting</persName>, on the other hand, was a
                    fairly junior US Foreign Service Officer of no particular international
                    reputation and prestige. He was undertaking his first assignment as an
                    Ambassador in a part of the world in which he had no depth of experience. He had
                    very limited resources at his direct disposal and a relatively small staff. He
                    knew and understood the direction and the design of top-level US policy. With
                    good common sense and discretion, Fritz “got on the team” and made no contest to
                    assume a prerogative of control. This does not suggest that he was a doormat; it
                    merely means that he chose what he quite sensibly considered to be the most
                    effective way to exercise his talents and to utilize his resources.</p>
                <p>This arrangement caused some grumbling in the civilian side of the Country Team.
                    As disciplined professionals, they buckled down and did their part in
                    contributing to the US operational effort. However, they had a number of nagging
                    doubts about the qualitative effect of the effort in which they were engaged. A
                    number of them expressed these doubts to me privately when I was here. When I
                    suggested that they report them officially through regular channels, I was later
                    advised that most of their critical analysis was moderated before being sent or
                    else was not finally sent on to Washington.</p>
                <p>As a result of this situation, a certain head of emotional pressure built up in
                    the Embassy which finally erupted into the open after Fritz went on home leave
                    and while <persName corresp="#p_TWC1">Trueheart</persName> was in charge. Once
                    again, this was brought in check upon Fritz’s return to duty here.</p>
                <p>Finally, when Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> arrived on
                    the scene, two things happened. First, he was a man of international political
                    stature, considerable experience as an Ambassador and the bearer of Presidential
                    assurances that he was, and should act as US “top banana” in Vietnam. This
                    change of style was immediately apparent to everyone in the official US
                    community and has had the usual intangible effects which go with such
                    changeovers. Second, he has come to the conclusion that the “doubting Thomases”
                    in the civilian component, those who hold the “we cannot win with <persName
                        corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName>” attitude are correct. This, in turn, has
                    had its predictable and largely intangible consequences in the emotional
                    quotient of the problem.</p>
                <p>Finally, however, I believe a word of evaluation is necessary with respect to
                    current attitudes among the diverging components. With very rare exceptions,
                    there is no bitterness. The period of operational harmony built up in the
                        <persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1">Nolting</persName> period has resulted in some
                    very close friendships and good working relations across the board. The
                    dedication of all sequents [segments?] of the Team to make the program succeed
                    is great enough and the men involved are mature enough to <pb facs="0409"
                        n="383" xml:id="pg_383"/> be submerged in hard work. On operational
                    problems, there is no impairment of effectiveness discernible as yet. All
                    officers I have talked to show a genuine concern that this situation will
                    continue without change no matter what the more introspective differences may
                    bring in the way of divergencies.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_SWH1">W.H. Sullivan</persName>
                        </hi>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d183fn2">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
