<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-08-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                        <head>19. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Central Intelligence
                                Agency</gloss> Station in Saigon to the <gloss type="to">Agency</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d19fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 26 S VIET Secret; Operational Immediate; Eyes Only.
                                The source text is a copy the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                                sent to the Department of State exclusive for <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName>. Copies were also sent to the White House
                                exclusive for <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Bundy</persName>, and to
                                the Assistant Chief of Staff for Intelligence, Department of the
                                Army, exclusive for <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Gilpatric</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_KMGVH1">Krulak</persName>. Received at the Department of State at 4:45
                                a.m.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-08-30"><hi rend="italic">August 30,
                                1963</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">document number not declassified</hi>] 1. On evening
                            29 August, [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]
                            informed <gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> that he had a report from a
                            source of medium reliability to the effect that within 24 hours the govt
                            would begin the arrest of Generals who might not be fully loyal. The
                                [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] rep
                            intimated that this was the same source who on 20 Aug had provided
                            report forecasting govt attack on the pagodas.</p>
                        <p>2. It was decided to attempt alert the Generals to this information while
                            cautioning them that info was not confirmed and could be speculative. Of
                            the various means available to pass this in best was thought to be
                            contact with Major Nhieu who is next-door neighbor of Colonel Ralph E.
                            Newman, <gloss target="#t_USAF1">USAF</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss>. Major Nhieu is the Administrative Assistant of
                            General Duong Van Minh. Newman, Nhieu and General <persName corresp="#p_MINH1">Minh</persName> have a close relationship
                            resulting from fact Colonel Newman was General <persName corresp="#p_DVBMMG1">Big Minh</persName>’s advisor for approx 7
                            months.</p>
                        <pb facs="0063" n="37" xml:id="pg_37"/>
                        <p>3. Col Newman was contacted by a <gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss>
                            officer. Col Newman immediately attempted contact with Major Nhieu but
                            was unable to telephone him or to find anyone at home at Major Nhieu’s
                            residence. Col Newman volunteered that he was also on good terms with
                            General <persName corresp="#p_LVKBG1">Le Van Kim</persName> and could
                            probably pass message to General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>.</p>
                        <p>4. Newman was requested to call General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName> and state he had been approached by Vietnamese
                            friend who was extremely worried about his son who had been arrested on
                            Sunday during roundup of students and that Newman very much wanted talk
                            with General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName> with respect to
                            securing release of arrested boy.</p>
                        <p>5. Colonel Newman placed call to General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>’s residence and noted immediately that telephone
                            line was being monitored. An individual attempting to imitate General
                                <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>’s voice came onto the
                            line and repeatedly requested Colonel Newman’s location. Col Newman then
                            asked to speak to Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>. A
                            woman then came on line and Colonel Newman recognized her voice as that
                            of Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>. Col Newman passed
                            message concerning fictitious arrested student and asked come to General
                                <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>’s house. The line was
                            then broken. Very soon thereafter, General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>’s aide came to Col Newman’s house and escorted Col
                            Newman and <gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> officer to General
                                <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>’s house. The message was
                            passed to General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName> who was
                            most appreciative of the warning. General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName> promised to get the message to General <persName corresp="#p_DVBMMG1">Big Minh</persName> immediately. General
                                <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName> did state that it was
                            very dangerous for Col Newman to come to his house and that for the time
                            being these contacts should be suspended. Col Newman noted the presence
                            of approx one platoon of troops in the vicinity of General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>’s house. Upon departure from
                                <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>’s house Newman and <gloss target="#t_CAS1">CAS</gloss> officer were escorted away from the
                            house over a back road and through gates apparently very seldom
                            used.</p>
                        <p>6. There are at least two among other hazards in the present situation at
                            the Generals’ end of this operation. The first is that the arrest of
                            four or five key figures among the Generals might bring this operation
                            to a halt at least for the short run. This action seems easily within
                            capability of <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>. It is puzzling that
                            action of this nature has not already been taken. We can only be
                            speculative on this subject. <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> may be
                            attempting to avoid direct confrontation in hope that steam will
                            gradually go out of Generals’ present course. It may worry about causing
                            further disaffection throughout Armed Forces or revolt in corps areas.
                                <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> could be waiting for premature
                            coup to crush military opposition. Or it may be building up its dossiers
                            on course of coup plotting to present to armed forces and general public
                            after arrest of key Generals in effort diminish impact these arrests.
                            Another hazard is that one or another of Generals involved might betray
                            details of operation. So far we cannot point fingers at anyone. Hope
                                <gloss target="#t_HQS1">HQS</gloss> will <pb facs="0064" n="38" xml:id="pg_38"/> understand that speculation on possible negative
                            factors does not represent negative station attitude. We are bringing
                            all capabilities we can think of to bear.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>