<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-10-29T05:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-10-29T05:40:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                        <head>226. Telegram From the Ambassador in Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1" type="from">Lodge</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d226fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 26 <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>
                                VIET Top Secret; Immediate; Eyes Only. The source text is <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> Station telegram [<hi rend="italic">document number not declassified</hi>] from Saigon sent to the
                                Department of State eyes only <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_HTL1">Hughes</persName>. Also sent to the Department of Defense eyes
                                only for <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Gilpatric</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KMGVH1">Krulak</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName>; to the White House
                                eyes only for <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>;
                                repeated to Honolulu eyes only for <persName corresp="#p_FAHD1">Felt</persName> and to <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> eyes
                                only for <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CLGMS1">Carter</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_HR1">Helms</persName>. Received at the Department of
                                State at 7:59 a.m.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-10-29T18:40:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">October 29,
                                        1963—18:40 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>I have reviewed the following factors which appear to me to be
                                particularly relevant in a balanced examination of the positive and
                                negative forces affecting the chances of a successful coup d’etat: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>Of immediate concern is the apparent lack of detail
                                        furnished by General <persName corresp="#p_DON1">Don</persName> both with regard to the military units
                                        to be involved and the politico/<gloss target="#t_PSYWAR1">psywar</gloss> side. This appears to me to be at least
                                        in part explained by the Generals’ reticence to reveal these
                                        details at this point and because of what must be a much
                                        greater regard for security than was the case in August. The
                                        Generals also acknowledge a certain amount of
                                        compartmentation and division of labor among the principals
                                        which on balance should work to our advantage.</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>The acknowledged involvement of General <persName corresp="#p_DINH1">Dinh</persName> is an extremely
                                        variable factor. The Generals seem acutely aware of this and
                                            <persName corresp="#p_DON1">Don</persName> states that
                                        they have him under 24-hour a day surveillance and are
                                        prepared to neutralize him at any time should he kick over
                                        the traces.</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>The possibility of a premature, unrelated and precipitate
                                        coup by Col Pham Ngoc Thao or others looms large as a
                                        negative factor. Again, the Generals appear completely aware
                                        of this and as you know, we have never been particularly
                                        sanguine that Thao has this capability.</item>
                                    <label>D.</label>
                                    <item>Knowledge of the involvement of certain civilian
                                        opposition elements, notably <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bui
                                            Diem</persName>, who has stated that he is liaison
                                        between General <persName corresp="#p_KIM1">Kim</persName>
                                        and civilian leaders, probably Dang Van Sung and <persName corresp="#p_PHQ1">Phan Huy Quat</persName>, represents
                                        both a positive and negative factor. On the negative side,
                                        it represents an extension of knowledge weakening the
                                        security element but on the positive side, it indicates an
                                        awareness of the necessity of civilian political inclusion
                                        and the fact that as <persName corresp="#p_DON1">Don</persName> has stated it is not intended to
                                        establish a military junta. Tran Trung Dung’s knowledge and
                                        probable involvement despite his disclaimer, further
                                        indicates intention to form civilian government, probably
                                        within frame of reference of constitutional
                                        succession.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0480" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                                    <label>E.</label>
                                    <item>I am disturbed over the reported discussion of Col
                                            <persName corresp="#p_NKC1">Nguyen Khuong</persName>’s
                                        approaches to U.S. military personnel without the
                                        authorization of the coup principals. It should be
                                        remembered that Khuong’s role was obscure in the August coup
                                        activities. <persName corresp="#p_DON1">Don</persName> has
                                        stated that the coup principals would discipline Khuong and
                                        that he has been removed from the scene.</item>
                                    <label>F.</label>
                                    <item>It would seem to me that the existence of an imminent coup
                                        atmosphere would reduce the element of surprise necessary
                                        for the successful implementation of a coup d’etat. This
                                        coup atmosphere has pertained, however, for several months
                                        which would tend to reduce the state of readiness for
                                        countering such a coup attempt. We have some information
                                        that counter-coup combat elements have been suborned. The
                                        fact that the coup principals remain as the responsible
                                        military authority enhances both their knowledge and ability
                                        to dispose the units both for and against.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Additional factors which should be noted are: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>To date the Generals have not indicated either a desire
                                        for or dependence on our support or actions for successful
                                        implementation of a coup. On the contrary, the Generals have
                                        repeatedly demanded the least possible American
                                        involvement.</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>Although we are well aware of the profundity of student
                                        and Buddhist dissidence and unrest and even ability to
                                        undertake certain limited action, we do not know of any
                                        plans to utilize these elements and of course cannot
                                        calculate the extent of spontaneous action they might
                                        undertake.</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>Action taken with respect to the Commercial Import Program
                                        and the severance of support and certain elements under Col
                                            <persName corresp="#p_TUNG1">Tung</persName> have
                                        created a coup atmosphere and some deterioration in the
                                        economic situation characterized by the fluctuation of the
                                        piastre value, the disappearance of gold on the market, and
                                        the rising prices of consumer commodities.</item>
                                    <label>D.</label>
                                    <item>Please note <persName corresp="#p_DON1">Don</persName>
                                        does not want me to change date of my departure for
                                        Washington. We are reviewing whole situation Wednesday night
                                        to see whether change my departure is justified.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>A point which must be completely understood is that we are not
                                engineering the coup. The sum total of our relationship thus far is:
                                that we will not thwart a coup; that we will monitor and report; and
                                that Conein’s long-standing friendship with <persName corresp="#p_DON1">Don</persName> may be a real help. Although
                                there have been no requests to date by the Generals for material or
                                financial support, we must anticipate that such requests may be
                                forthcoming.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In summary, it would appear that a coup attempt by the Generals’
                                group is imminent; that whether this coup fails or succeeds, the USG
                                must be prepared to accept the fact that we will be blamed, however
                                unjustifiably; and finally, that no positive action by the USG <pb facs="0481" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> can prevent a coup attempt
                                short of informing <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu</persName> with all the
                                opprobrium that such an action would entail. Note too <persName corresp="#p_DON1">Don</persName>’s statement we will only have
                                four hours notice. This rules out my checking with you between time
                                I learn of coup and time that it starts. It means U.S. will not be
                                able significantly to influence course of events.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>