<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-11-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="313" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d313">
                        <head>313. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_FMV1" type="from">Michael
                                V. Forrestal</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to
                            the President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_BMG1" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d313fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, National
                                Security Files, Vietnam Country Series, Memos and Miscellaneous.
                                Confidential.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-11-13"><hi rend="italic">November 13,
                                    1963</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>I had a brief talk with Bob Kleiman of the New York Times editorial board
                            this morning. I told him that I thought the <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Halberstam</persName> article in this morning’s edition was
                            irresponsible and mostly reflected a personal animus against General
                                <persName corresp="#p_HGPD1">Harkins</persName> instead of accurate
                            news reporting.<note n="2" xml:id="d313fn2">See <ref target="#d313fn2">footnote 2</ref>, <ref target="#d312">Document
                                312</ref>.</note> Kleiman admitted that this might be so, but
                            pointed out that there must have been some differences of opinion
                            between the Embassy and <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss>, since
                                <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Halberstam</persName> quoted inconsistent
                            Embassy sources and <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> public
                            statements.</p>
                        <pb facs="0621" n="595" xml:id="pg_595"/>
                        <p>Kleiman suggested rather strongly that we move as soon as possible toward
                            a reconvening of the Geneva Conference and a negotiated settlement of
                            the differences between North and South Vietnam. He argued that the
                            political strength of the South will never be as strong again as it will
                            be during the next few months, and that we should seize this opportunity
                            for negotiations before the situation deteriorated and we found
                            ourselves back in a 10-year, Malayan-type effort. In connection with
                            such negotiations he raised the possibility of effecting a mass
                            population transfer in an effort to get all of the Viet Cong moved from
                            the South back up to the North.</p>
                        <p>I told him that I had great difficulty with this suggestion and thought
                            that it would be folly to pursue this line at the present time. South
                            Vietnam was still not strong enough to approach the bargaining table
                            with any hope of coming away whole. Furthermore, there was no indication
                            that responsible Vietnamese in Vietnam would view the prospects of a new
                            Geneva Conference as anything less than a complete sellout by the U.S. I
                            emphasized that we definitely looked toward the time when South Vietnam
                            would be strong enough to deal with the North on at least a basis of
                            equality. I referred to the President’s statement of last year and the
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> statement of last month,<note n="3" xml:id="d313fn3"><ref target="#d170">Document
                                170</ref>.</note> indicating that the U.S. was prepared to withdraw
                            its presence from South Vietnam as soon as Hanoi ceased its interference
                            in the South or as soon as the South was able to handle the problem on
                            its own. We had not yet reached that point, however. I also questioned
                            whether a population transfer would be feasible in view of the
                            difficulty of identifying the bulk of the Viet Cong, to say nothing of
                            the political problems involved in a forced emigration.</p>
                        <p>Kleiman will no doubt continue to peddle his Geneva Conference idea, and
                            we should be preparing ourselves to counter it.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong">MF</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>