<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-12-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="369" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                        <head>369. Report on the Situation in Long An Province<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d369fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                                Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 71-1-3470, 12/19-12/20/63, <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> Visit. Confidential. Authorship of
                                this report is not given, but a note in <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>’s handwriting on the source text reads: “By an
                                intelligent American who recently visited Long An and doesn’t want
                                to sign his name.” It was handed to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> in Saigon by <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Saigon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-12-20"><hi rend="italic">December 20,
                                    1963</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>As a result of your demonstrated interest, Long An has become the center
                            of interest, at least momentarily. Some facts and figures: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Of the 219 hamlets previously reported as completed (with some 50
                                    more supposedly in advanced stages of construction), no more
                                    than 35 now are considered to be capable of achieving the
                                    purpose for which built-that is, of separating the people from
                                    the Viet Cong while providing them both security and an
                                    opportunity for social and economic development. Please note: 9
                                    of these 35 hamlets actually comprise a part of the provincial
                                    capital or of district towns.</p>
                                <p>147 armed militia squads previously were reported to be available
                                    in this province (even this figure seems low for the 219 hamlets
                                    supposedly in existence—some of them immense in area). Actually,
                                    no more than 50 squads exist and they are quartered in 37
                                    hamlets.</p>
                                <p>167 hamlets now are said to have suffered extensive damage from
                                    the Viet Cong. Of this number, only 5 still have any armed
                                    militia available (the key to their defense).</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Some personal observations.</hi></p>
                        <p>Three of the six districts were visited briefly during recent trip. Some
                            particulars on at least one hamlet in each of these districts:</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Nguyen Huynh Duc</hi> (Thu Thua District). Located
                            about 5 kilometers south of Tan An and just off Highway 4, this is said
                            to be the best hamlet in the province. Homes are pleasant, look
                            permanent, have shade and fruit trees, gardens, etc. Since the Village
                            Administrative Headquarters is located here, there is also a 45-man
                                <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> post. The post is in a fairly
                            poor state of repair—weapons looked barely serviceable, no evidence of
                            recent attempts to improve defenses. Directional arrow for air support
                            was in very poor repair-no tallow pots available for night use. The
                            hamlet militia were said to accompany <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> on patrols “for training” but were armed only with
                            grenades. All <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> questioned were most
                            vague as to extent of patrol activity. <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> were not uniformed despite <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss> representative’s assurance that uniforms were readily
                            available. It was reported that no hamlet radio was available for three
                            of the four hamlets in this village complex.</p>
                        <pb facs="0741" n="715" xml:id="pg_715"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Hoa Phu</hi> (Binh Phuoc District). No more than 4
                            kilometers west and south of Tan An, this hamlet has been destroyed.
                            Only 3 or 4 families remain of some 130. Many of the houses have been
                            pulled down completely; the fence is down almost everywhere and much of
                            it has been cut into small pieces. Interviews with the hardy survivors
                            indicated they stayed because they felt they had the permission of the
                            Viet Cong because of special circumstances. (One woman, for example, had
                            a husband in prison at Tan An.) Hamlet militia previously existed and
                            had been armed but had dispersed and turned in their weapons to the
                            nearby <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> post. This hamlet was
                            described by Rosenthal as the worst thing he had seen in his travels
                            throughout the country.</p>
                        <p>Within easy pistol shot of Hoa Phu, there was an <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> platoon ensconced behind a moat, barbed wire, etc. This
                            platoon apparently did not move out to aid the nearby hamlet when (it
                            was said) a small number of Viet Cong came and “asked” the people to
                            pull down their houses, cut the fence, etc. The post showed no evidence
                            of recent improvement. The arrow for air support was completely
                            overgrown by weeds, for example. <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> had
                            no uniforms, generally seemed apathetic. Detachment was armed with
                            French MAS rifles, had no automatic weapons. However, this platoon did
                            have the weapons of previously armed hamlet militia squads from two
                            nearby hamlets. (Why—with Long An less than 4 kilometers away—were these
                            weapons unnecessarily exposed to <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                            capture?)</p>
                        <p>In very early afternoon, with a fairly large armed escort, the deputy
                            province chief was reluctant to stop at Hao Phu. We drove back to Tan An
                            at breakneck speed after our visit.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Tap An</hi> (Thanh Duc District). District, as a whole,
                            is considered by local Americans to be the best in the province. Two of
                            the eleven armed militia squads still available to the district are in
                            Tap An. The hamlet had no radio—was dependent upon wire which was
                            clearly visible and could easily be cut. Nonetheless, this hamlet is in
                            extraordinarily good shape when compared with another nearby—<hi rend="italic">Thu Bo</hi>. About 40% of the dwellings were destroyed
                            there. Those persons remaining seemed to feel they did so at the
                            sufferance of the Viet Cong. This hamlet was “supported” by an <gloss target="#t_SDC1">SDC</gloss> post across the river—by “patrols” and
                            by “direct automatic weapon fire”! Questioning developed that this fire
                            was over the roofs of the houses. District chief (who seemed both able
                            and energetic) said that only about 8% of those families entitled to a
                            relocation allowance in the entire district had received same. Although
                            his district is divided by a broad river, the district chief had no
                            patrol craft under his jurisdiction.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>