<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-09-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="98" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                        <head>98. Draft Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of
                                State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                Vietnam</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d98fn1"><p>Source:
                                    Kennedy Library, National Security Files, Meetings and Memoranda
                                    Series, Meetings on Vietnam. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>. In a telephone call to
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName>, at 8:23
                                    p.m., September 11, <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>
                                    discussed the drafting of this telegram:</p>
                                <p>“Sec said he would go home tonight and draft a fairly long
                                    discursive message to Lodge to give his own views on paper but H
                                    might go ahead on the letter idea. Sec would think that is the
                                    means by which we try to get this fellow on board there through
                                    persuasion without at this stage a lot of other things that go
                                    along with it. Sec replied it would be a presidential letter. H
                                    will be sending Lodge cable tonight and will call Sec tonight on
                                    WH phone.” (Department of State, <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> Files: Lot 72 D 192, Telephone
                                    Conversations)</p>
                                <p>Regarding the Presidential letter, see <ref target="#d115">Document 115</ref>. The cable <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> mentioned is presumably telegram 391,
                                        <ref target="#d97">Document 97</ref>. There is no record of
                                    another telephone conversation between <persName corresp="#p_HRJ1">Hilsman</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> on the night of September
                                    11. The cable printed here was not sent; see <ref target="#d99"><hi rend="smallcaps">Infra</hi></ref>.</p></note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-09-12"><hi rend="italic">September 12,
                                    1963</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Eyes only for Ambassador from Secretary. Following are some of my
                            thoughts against the background of the voluminous and most helpful
                            information coming from you and country team.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Although situation in Saigon is understandably intensive
                                preoccupation of those who have been carrying such a heavy load for
                                us under difficult and dangerous circumstances, this is not first
                                time that the US Government has been confronted with far-reaching
                                issues affecting vital interests in a country whose leadership
                                stubbornly resists measures which we consider necessary to achieve
                                desired results. One thinks of Chiang Kai-shek on the mainland,
                                Syngman Rhee, <persName corresp="#p_SPN1">Sihanouk</persName>,
                                Nasser, Mossadegh and others.</item>
                            <pb facs="0223" n="197" xml:id="pg_197"/>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Our central objective remains a secure and independent South
                                Viet-Nam even though, at some future date, it may be possible to
                                consider a free, independent and non-communist unified country. This
                                central objective was what brought us into South Viet-Nam and its
                                achievement is the condition for our leaving. No one would be
                                happier than we to leave under that circumstance.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>It seems to me that there are outer limits of policy within which
                                we must therefore operate unless the situation forces us to break
                                through those limits. One would be that we do not get out and turn
                                South Viet-Nam over to the Viet-Cong. The other would be that we do
                                not use large-scale forces to occupy the country and run it
                                ourselves.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The key question is what has gone wrong to block or reverse the
                                favorable developments of the first six months of this year when we
                                were beginning to feel that a corner had been turned and that we
                                could anticipate a successful conclusion. The central fact appears
                                to be that the political solidarity of the Vietnamese, notably that
                                of the elite and leadership groups, has disintegrated under the
                                impact of the Buddhist problem, press policy, student and
                                intellectual disaffection, and increasing fears and distrust within
                                the leadership itself. This seriously negative development seems to
                                be geared to brother and <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Madame
                                    Nhu</persName> and in the process the position of President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> has been weakened
                                politically at home, overseas, and more specifically with our
                                Congress and public opinion. The two <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu</persName>s seem clearly to be at the heart of the problem
                                both on the merits and symbolically at home and abroad.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>I agree fully with your sense of urgency which I am inclined to
                                measure in weeks rather than in days. It seems to me that at present
                                we should concentrate on <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> himself to make him see that everything he has
                                been working for for the past ten years is threatened with collapse
                                and failure and that bold and far-sighted action on his part is
                                urgently required in order to unite the country and get it back on a
                                favorable course. This may require persistent talks with him in the
                                days ahead in which we would insist that he listen for a change and
                                break through the flood of words which he uses to avoid coming to
                                grips with his real problems. The question of what type of pressures
                                and when such pressures should be applied is the essence of the
                                judgement which you will have to make on the spot. I am inclined to
                                think that in the next immediate stage we should not threaten what
                                we will not or cannot deliver and that we are not yet ready to cut
                                off assistance which affects the war effort or which would inflict
                                serious damage to the people as contrasted with the regime. You have
                                unlimited information to make clear to him that real statesmanship
                                from him is now required to reverse the collapse of his position at
                                home, internationally and in the United States. Our next approach to
                                him <pb facs="0224" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/> might well be,
                                therefore, to review with him the record of his tenure of the
                                Presidency, including the admittedly positive and courageous
                                contributions he has made and appeal to his pride and patriotism to
                                move toward success and not failure. This could introduce frank and
                                firm discussion of what needs to be done including the baleful
                                effect which the <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu</persName>s have
                                been having on his country. Incidentally, we shall be sending you a
                                separate message on <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Madame
                                Nhu</persName>’s visit to the United States,<note n="2" xml:id="d98fn2">Apparent reference to telegram 405 to Saigon,
                                    September 13, in which the Department informed <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> that “our feeling is
                                    that official approach to <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> on <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Madame
                                        Nhu</persName>’s possible activities in US not desirable at
                                    this time. Would appreciate your ideas on how <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Madame Nhu</persName>’s trip to US could be
                                    discouraged in a manner not attributable to official US action,
                                    for example, do you think there is any possibility that Asta
                                    could accomplish it?” (Department of State, Central Files,
                                        <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 S VIET-US)</note> a
                                visit which could well be disastrous for Viet-Nam and not merely an
                                irritant for the US Government.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>In sum, and reviewing some of our successes and failures in the
                                past in dealing with similar difficult personalities, it seems to me
                                that our real problem now is to come to grips with <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> and be prepared to exchange
                                our full confidence and support for the actions which he must take,
                                however difficult, if there is to be a chance for success. I mention
                                confidence because, despite the fact that his position both
                                originally and now has been made possible by persistent and costly
                                American support, he has on several occasions over the past several
                                years undoubtedly gotten the impression that we were trying to
                                unhorse him. It may be that it will be impossible to succeed along
                                this line but the alternatives are so far-reaching that the present
                                effort seems to me to be worth the tedious and frustrating hours
                                which will undoubtedly be required to get through to him and get him
                                to carry out his own full responsibility.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>