<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Adams..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="13"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d13">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Adams</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 786.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-12-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 17, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your despatch of the 27th of November (No. 545)
                    has been received. We await with much interest the end of the prosecution in the
                    case of the Alexandra. Meanwhile the bold and flagrant crime committed in the
                    name of the insurgents here, by seizing the steamer Chesapeake, and using the
                    British colonial coasts and waters as a base of their piratical operations,
                    ought to bring home to the British government the discovery that its premature
                    toleration of the anomalous belligerent is engendering a border war, which would
                    be a sad and dangerous sequel to our unhappy insurrection.</p>
                <p>Again, if the northern states of Europe are to become a theatre of a civil war in
                    Denmark, with the intervention of foreign states on opposing sides, according to
                    their sympathies or dynastic interests, it will soon become important to know by
                    what code of neutrality our own conduct is to be regulated—whether the one we
                    have set up, or the one that has been adopted by Great Britain and France in
                    regard to ourselves.</p>
                <p>The President thinks that her Majesty’s government cannot fail to see the
                    importance of removing all existing causes of discontent between their own
                    country and the United States. I learn from your despatch that the perverseness
                    of disunion agitators in Great Britain still continues to manifest itself in
                    operations designed to influence Parliament at its approaching session. The most
                    effectual way to quiet them would be to publish as widely as possible the (so to
                    speak) official expositions of the leaders of the insurrection given forth by
                    the conspirators themselves at Richmond. We cannot properly address ourselves to
                    the press in a foreign country. Perhaps the subject may be thought worthy of
                    Earl Russell’s attention.</p>
                <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles F. Adams</hi>, Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
