<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-10-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-10-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="392" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d392">
                    <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 12.</seg></opener>
                    <head><persName type="from">Acting Consul Fullarton to Earl
                        Russell</persName>.—(Received February 1, 1864.)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Savannah,</hi></placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-10-23"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 23, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord:</hi> I have the honor to enclose to your
                        lordship a copy of my reply to Mr. Benjamin’s despatch to me of the 8th
                        instant, conveying the president’s order to depart promptly from the
                        confederacy, and in the mean time to cease the exercise of consular
                        functions.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Benjamin has thought proper to publish his despatch to me in the Richmond
                        newspapers.</p>
                    <pb facs="0873" n="863" xml:id="pg_863"/>
                    <p>Having had committed to my charge the interests of several parties absent in
                        Europe, which my departure would seriously injure, I have requested Mr.
                        Benjamin to rescind that portion of the order requiring me actually to
                        withdraw from the confederacy.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. FULLARTON.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure in No. 12.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><persName type="from">Acting Consul Fullarton</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Benjamin</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Savannah,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-10-22"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 22, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt, on the 14th instant, of your despatch to me of the 8th,
                            communicating to me the president’s order that I should promptly depart
                            from the confederacy, and in the mean time cease to exercise any
                            consular functions within its limits.</p>
                        <p>Your despatch conveys to me the reasons which have induced this action.
                            These reasons have no existence in fact, and I should content myself
                            with a simple denial of the charges you make, were it not that you found
                            them upon language used by me which I should have supposed could not
                            fairly be misconstrued; but as it has been so strangely misinterpreted,
                            and such serious and I may say unheard of charges have been preferred by
                            you against her Majesty’s government, and against all her Majesty’s
                            consuls in the confederacy, it seems to be due to them at least that I
                            should endeavor to disabuse your mind.</p>
                        <p>In the first place, I will observe that your accusations are made against
                            her Majesty’s consular servants in the plural number. Mr. Cridland, of
                            Mobile, has not exercised any of the functions of his office; therefore,
                            Mr. Walker, her Majesty’s acting consul in Charleston, and myself, are
                            the only officers to whom your charges can refer. Mr. Walker will
                            doubtless deal with the matter in his own way, and I propose to defend
                            myself only.</p>
                        <p>That you may be under no mistake as to what my instructions in reference
                            to the service of British subjects in the armies of the confederacy or
                            any of the confederate States really are, I will here repeat them, viz:
                            “That the plainest notions of reason and justice forbid that a
                            foreigner, admitted to reside for peaceful and commercial purposes in a
                            State forming a part of a federal Union, should be suddenly and without
                            warning compelled by the State to take an active part in hostilities
                            against other States which, when he became domiciled, were members of
                            one and the same confederacy.”</p>
                        <p>Therefore, both in contemplation of the organization of the militia of
                            the State of Georgia, and in anticipation of a State draft from that
                            organization for purposes inconsistent with that instruction, it was my
                            duty to advise such of her Majesty’s subjects as might be enrolled for
                            militia service and subjected to such draft, in the language you have
                            first quoted; and unless you possess the information that all her
                            Majesty’s subjects in the State of Georgia have enlisted in confederate
                            service, I am at a loss to understand how you can regard this as an
                            assumption on my part of “the power of determining whether enlisted
                            soldiers of the confederacy are properly bound to its service.”</p>
                        <p>The second quotation of my language is as easily explained. Militia
                            service is peculiarly an organization for neighborhood defence, and if a
                            British subject, being a militia-man, is called from his neighborhood,
                            which is properly defined by the word home, or involuntarily drafted
                            into service for which he is not liable, I have done no wrong in
                            directing him to refuse the required service by rejecting the arms that
                            may be thrust upon him; and it is this advice to British subjects, not
                            enlisted, but willing to perform all that the laws of the State can
                            justly require of them, that you have been pleased to magnify into
                            advice “to soldiers of the confederate armies to throw down their arms
                            in the face of the <pb facs="0874" n="864" xml:id="pg_864"/> enemy.” It
                            seems to me impossible to read the language you have quoted without
                            perceiving that it has no application at all to the enlisted confederate
                            soldier, unless, as I said before, you assume that all British subjects
                            have enlisted in the confederate service, and I should imagine it is not
                            necessary for me to tell you that the fact of enlistment deprives the
                            soldier of all protection, as of right, from the consequences of his
                            enlistment.</p>
                        <p>Having thus shown how extravagant is the construction you have placed
                            upon my language, I have only to deny the correctness of every
                            conclusion you have drawn and every assertion you have made. I have not
                            failed to forward to her Majesty’s government a copy of your despatch,
                            and I shall inform them of the publication and circulation you have
                            thought proper to give to it.</p>
                        <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>A. FULLARTON.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>