<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1864-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1864-02-11T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662" lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recFUg0jqFk2tUZ15" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="confidence-building-measures" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257" lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-02-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 594.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                        States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic"> London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-02-11">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 11, 1864.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Your despatch (No. 820) was the only one
                            received this week. Five copies of the President’s annual message and
                            accompanying documents came with it.</p>
                <p>I have sent an answer to the address of the Order of Memphis, in the
                            identical terms of the despatch.</p>
                <p>As Mr. Evarts has not yet returned from the continent, I have the honor
                            to transmit copies of the London Times of the 8th and 9th instant,
                            containing a report of the further proceedings in the case of the
                            Alexandra. It appears that the government has been again foiled in its
                            purpose to gain from the higher courts a judicial exposition of the
                            enlistment act, by the interposition of technical objections to the
                            process. I think they are by no means insensible to the awkward position
                            in which this difficulty places the country in its relations with
                            foreign nations. Inasmuch as the majority of the judges, whilst
                            declining to take jurisdiction themselves, left open a way to the
                            transfer of the question to the House of Lords, it is generally
                            understood that that course will be adopted. The effect will be to cause
                            another delay for a considerable time. And this delay will, in its turn,
                            cause a postponement of any definite action upon the representations
                            made by me to this government under the instructions contained in your
                            despatch (No. 802) of the 6th of January. A report of my conference with
                            Lord Russell on that subject was sent to you in my despatch (No. 584) of
                            the 28th ultimo.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P. S.—Mr. Evarts has called at the legation since the above was
                                written.</p>
                </postscript>
                <pb facs="0144" n="134" xml:id="pg_134"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>The Alexandra Case.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">The Court of
                                        Error</hi>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-02-06">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">February</hi>
                                6</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Present: The lord chief justice of England, the lord chief justice of
                                the common pleas, Mr. Justice Williams, Mr. Justice Crompton, Mr.
                                Justice Willes, Mr. Justice Blackburn, and Mr. Justice Mellor.</p>
                    <p rend="center">THE ATTORNEY GENERAL <hi rend="italic">vs.</hi> SILLEM
                                AND OTHERS.</p>
                    <p>This case came before the court upon appeal from the decision of the
                                court of exchequer, come to on the 11th of January last.</p>
                    <p>As soon as the case was called on for hearing, Sir Hugh Cairns, on
                                the part of the defendants, took an objection to the means by which
                                the case had been brought into the court for argument.</p>
                    <p>In order to make the present proceeding intelligible to our readers,
                                it will perhaps be necessary to give some short outline of the case,
                                bringing it down to the present moment. An information was filed by
                                the crown against the defendants, following a seizure made by an
                                officer of customs of the ship Alexandra, and the substantial
                                question for the jury to determine at the trial was whether the
                                condition of that vessel, at the time of her seizure, brought her
                                within the provisions of the foreign enlistment act, 59 Geo. III, c.
                                69. The trial commenced before the lord chief baron on the 22d of
                                June last, and terminated on the 24th of that month in favor of the
                                defendants. The late Sir William Atherton, when attorney general,
                                conducted the prosecution, and before the finding of the verdict
                                proposed to tender a bill of exceptions to a portion of the learned
                                lord chief baron’s ruling, and a brief note of the exceptions was
                                handed up to him, when his lordship objected that it did not contain
                                a correct statement of his ruling, and refused to accept it as a
                                bill of exceptions; but ultimately it was agreed that a bill of
                                exceptions should be formally prepared from such materials as could
                                be found for that purpose and tendered for signature. The lord chief
                                baron declined, when the formal exceptions were tendered, to sign
                                them, for the same reason as above stated. On the 3d of November the
                                present attorney general, Sir Roundell Palmer, upon an application
                                to the court, said that the main point raised in the case was of
                                such very grave and momentous importance that the crown was desirous
                                that it might go to the court of error, and the last court of
                                appeal, viz: the House of Lords, should it ultimately prove that one
                                or both steps were necessary. The lord chief baron said he saw no
                                prospect whatever of any change in the view he had taken as to his
                                duty in signing the bill of exceptions. That so far from laying down
                                the law, as the bill of exceptions tendered to him for signature had
                                assumed he had, he had taken great pains to avoid doing anything of
                                the kind. After the matter had been further discussed, the lord
                                chief baron suggested that the object the crown had in view might be
                                obtained by a motion without any reference to the bill of exceptions
                                at all. It was true there had been no point reserved at the trial so
                                as to give the crown a right of appeal in the event of the rest of
                                the court concurring with his ruling and the direction he had given
                                to the jury. It was a matter to be regretted, however unanimous the
                                court might be in opinion, if they did not give the crown, as they
                                had the power of doing, a right of appeal from their decision to a
                                superior court. Baron Bramwell suggested that a difficulty might
                                arise upon the question whether the common law procedure act applied
                                to proceedings like those before the court. The act, which, to a
                                certain extent, assimilated crown proceedings to civil actions, did
                                not comprehend the case of an appeal from making absolute or
                                discharging a rule; whether that was so or not, he thought, was open
                                to some considerable doubt. On a subsequent day the attorney general
                                moved to apply the common law procedure acts of <pb facs="0145" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/> 1852 and 1854, and the rules of
                                pleading and practice to the revenue side of the court, so that an
                                appeal would be competent under the 26th section of the Queen’s
                                remembrancers act, 22d and 23d Victoria, cap. 21. The section
                                states, “It shall be lawful for the lord chief baron, and two or
                                more barons of the court of exchequer, from time to time, to make
                                all such rules and orders as to the process, practice, and mode of
                                pleading on the revenue side of the court,” and as to some other
                                things, “as may seem to them necessary and proper, and also, from
                                time to time, by any such rule or order to extend, apply, or adapt
                                any of the provisions of the common law procedure act of 1852, and
                                the common law procedure act of 1854, and any of the rules of
                                pleading and practice on the plea side of the said court to the
                                revenue side of the said court, as nearly as may be uniform with the
                                process, practice, and mode of pleading on the plea side of such
                                court.” Their lordships, after some consideration of the matter, on
                                the 4th of November, 1863, issued the following rules:</p>
                    <p rend="center">“Court of exchequer.—Revenue side.</p>
                    <p>“In pursuance of the provisions contained in the 26th section of the
                                22d and 23d Victoria, cap. 21, entitled ‘An act to regulate the
                                office of Queen’s remembrancer, and to amend the practice and
                                procedure on the revenue side of the court of exchequer’—</p>
                    <p>“It is ordered that the following provisions of the common law
                                procedure act of 1854 be extended, applied, and adapted to the
                                revenue side of the court of exchequer; and also that the following
                                rules as to giving bail in cases of appeal shall be in force on the
                                revenue side of the court of exchequer.</p>
                    <p>“1. In all cases of rules to enter a verdict or non-suit upon a point
                                reserved at the trial, if the rule to show cause be refused or
                                granted, and then discharged or made absolute, the party decided
                                against may appeal.</p>
                    <p>“2. In all cases of motions for a new trial upon the ground that the
                                judge has not ruled according to law, if the rule to show cause be
                                refused, or, if granted, be then discharged or made absolute, the
                                party decided against may appeal, provided any one of the judges
                                dissent from the rule being refused, or, when granted, being
                                discharged or made absolute, as the case may be, or provided the
                                court in its discretion think fit that an appeal should be allowed,
                                provided that where the application for a new trial is upon matter
                                of discretion only, as on the ground that the verdict was against
                                the weight of evidence or otherwise, no such appeal shall be
                                disallowed.</p>
                    <p>“3. The court of error, the exchequer chamber, and the House of Lords
                                shall be courts of appeal for this purpose.</p>
                    <p>“4. No appeal shall be allowed unless notice thereof be given in
                                writing to the opposite party or his attorney and to the Queen’s
                                remembrancer within four days after the decision complained of, or
                                such further time as may be allowed by the court or a judge.</p>
                    <p>“5. The appeal hereinbefore mentioned shall be upon a case to be
                                stated by the parties, (and in case of difference to be settled by
                                the court or a judge of the court appealed from, in which case shall
                                be set forth so much of the pleading, evidence, and the ruling or
                                judgment objected to as may be necessary to raise the question for
                                the decision of the court of appeal.</p>
                    <p>“6. When the appeal is from the refusal of the court below to grant a
                                rule to show cause, and the court of appeal grant such rule, such
                                rule shall be argued and disposed of in the court of appeal.</p>
                    <p>“7. The court of appeal shall give such judgment as ought to have
                                been given in the court below, and all such further proceeding may
                                be taken thereupon as if the judgment had been given by the court in
                                which the record originated.</p>
                    <p>“8. The court of appeal shall have power to adjudge payment of costs
                                and to order restitution, and they shall have the same powers as the
                                court of error in respect of awarding process, and otherwise.</p>
                    <pb facs="0146" n="136" xml:id="pg_136"/>
                    <p>“9. Upon an award of a trial <hi rend="italic">de novo</hi> by the
                                court, or by the court of error upon matter appearing upon record,
                                error may at once be brought; and if the judgment in such or any
                                other case be affirmed in error, it shall be lawful for the court of
                                error to adjudge costs to the defendant in error.</p>
                    <p>“10. When a new trial is granted on the ground that the verdict was
                                against evidence, the costs of the first trial shall abide the
                                event, unless the court shall otherwise order.</p>
                    <p>“11. Upon motions founded upon affidavits it shall be lawful for
                                either party, with leave of the court or a judge, to make affidavits
                                in answer to the affidavits of the opposite party upon any new
                                matter arising out of such affidavits, subject to all such rules as
                                shall hereafter be made respecting such affidavits.</p>
                    <p>“12. Notice of appeal shall be a stay of execution, provided that
                                within eight days after the decision complained of, or before
                                execution delivered to the sheriff, bail to pay the sum recovered
                                and costs, or to pay costs when adjudged, be given in like manner
                                and to the same amount as bail in error is required to be given
                                under the rules of this court, made on the 22d day of June, 1860, or
                                as near thereto as may be applicable, provided that such bail shall
                                not be necessary to stay execution in cases where the appellant is
                                the crown, the attorney general on behalf of the crown, or the
                                Prince of Wales, or the Duke of Cornwall for the time being.</p>
                    <p>“The foregoing rules shall come into operation and take effect
                                forthwith, and apply to every cause, matter, and proceeding now
                                pending.”</p>
                    <p>On the 5th of November the attorney general moved for a new trial on
                                the ground of misdirection by the lord chief baron, the verdict
                                being against evidence as well as the weight of evidence, it being
                                distinctly and clearly understood that the crown had abandoned their
                                bill of exceptions and brought the matter before the court as an
                                ordinary motion, there being no right of appeal from the decision of
                                the court on either side, except upon a matter of law. The rule
                                having been obtained, it came on for argument on the 17th of
                                November, and occupied the court until Monday, the 23d. The crown
                                relied very strongly on the evidence adduced for the prosecution,
                                which it was said was, and ought to have been, conclusive as to the
                                character of the Alexandra at the time of the seizure, and that the
                                jury ought to have found for the crown. The defendants had called no
                                witnesses, but contended that the crown had been beaten in their own
                                case, and that the verdict ought not to be disturbed. The arguments,
                                as it will be remembered, were very long, and the summing up of the
                                learned judge who tried the case was not only cut up by the counsel
                                for the crown, but very carefully and minutely dissected afterwards,
                                contrary, as it was said by the defendant’s counsel, to all
                                precedent, as a judge had a right to the expression of his own
                                opinion upon a case, provided he did not mislead the jury by leading
                                them to believe that they were bound to accept that opinion as a
                                direction how to find their verdict. The court took time to consider
                                judgment, and on the 11th of last month judgment was delivered, the
                                lord chief baron and Mr. Baron Bramwell being of opinion that the
                                rule ought to be discharged, and Mr. Baron Channell and Mr. Baron
                                Pigott thinking the rule for a new trial should be made absolute.
                                Mr. Baron Pigott, the junior judge, having, according to the
                                practice in such cases when the court is divided in opinion,
                                withdrawn his judgment, the majority was left with the defendants,
                                and the rule discharged accordingly. The crown availed itself of the
                                rules made on the 4th of November, (as stated above,) and gave
                                notice to the defendants of their intention to appeal, and the
                                hearing of that appeal was fixed for to-day.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general, the solicitor general, the Queen’s advocate,
                                Mr. Locke, Q. C., and Mr. Thomas Jones appeared for the crown; and
                                Sir Hugh Cairns, Mr. Mellish, Q. C., Mr. Karslake, Q. C., and Mr.
                                Kemplay for the defendants.</p>
                    <p>Sir Hugh Cairns said that he had a preliminary objection to make
                                which affected the jurisdiction of the court to hear the appeal. The
                                court of <pb facs="0147" n="137" xml:id="pg_137"/> exchequer, after
                                having heard the arguments upon the rule, were equally divided in
                                opinion, but the junior judge yielding, according to the practice
                                upon such occasions, the rule was discharged, and the proceedings in
                                that court upon the information brought to a close. The crown had
                                served the defendants with notice of appeal, and the question now
                                arose under what authority was that appeal brought. Before the
                                common law procedure acts there could have been no such appeal, as
                                those acts apply only to personal actions commencing by writ of
                                summons. It is said that the appeal lies under a general rule or
                                order of the court of exchequer made on the 4th of November last
                                year, upon an application by the crown before the rule <hi rend="italic">nisi</hi> in the case had been granted. Rules
                                first and second he would read, and call attention to rule three,
                                which stated, “The court of error, the exchequer chamber, and the
                                House of Lords shall be courts of appeal for this purpose.” It might
                                be remarked that it was to be regretted that a little more
                                consideration had not been bestowed upon the rules. It was obvious
                                that there had been an entire overlooking of what the meaning of the
                                term “court of error” in the common law procedure act of 1854 was.
                                The section in that act supposed to be analogous to the rule three
                                reads thus: “The court of error, the exchequer chamber, and the
                                House of Lords shall be courts of appeal for the purpose of this
                                act.” The rule says, “The court of error, the exchequer chamber, and
                                the House of Lords shall be courts of appeal for this purpose”—viz.,
                                for the purpose of the appeal before mentioned. The clause was
                                utterly unmeaning so applied—that is, that that part of the clause
                                which contained the term “the court of error” in the common law
                                procedure act has had a meaning quite different from the term
                                “exchequer chamber,” and a most intelligible and necessary meaning;
                                for the common law procedure act applied not merely to the superior
                                courts at Westminster, but to the courts of Lancaster and Durham,
                                and might be made applicable to other inferior courts of record. As
                                to those inferior courts the court of Queen’s Bench was the court of
                                error, and therefore the common law procedure act said, “the court
                                of error, the exchequer chamber, and the House of Lords,” as the
                                case might be, “for the purposes of this act,” which for all those
                                various purposes shall be the court of appeal, but in this rule it
                                was for the appeal mentioned in the clause immediately before. “The
                                court of error” could have no meaning, introduced as it was into the
                                third rule. Sir Hugh, having read all the above rules to the court,
                                continued: It might be that the court of exchequer had power by a
                                general order to create a new court of appeal, to give new rights to
                                suitors with regard to appeal which they never had before, to order
                                what should or should not be done by the court of appeal and by the
                                House of Lords, and to confer upon the House of Lords and upon the
                                court of Queen’s Bench the powers which were proposed to be
                                conferred by those rules. All that might be so, but he (Sir Hugh
                                Cairns) would like to see the authority, for he supposed no person
                                would say that without parliamentary authority that was a power
                                which could have been exercised. The Queen’s remembrancers act, the
                                21st and 22d Victoria, cap. 21, was an act to regulate the office of
                                Queen’s remembrancer, and to amend the practice and procedure on the
                                revenue side of the court of exchequer. It recived that a certain
                                act had been passed with regard to the office of remembrancer,
                                &amp;c., and then went on to say:</p>
                    <p>“And whereas it is expedient further to regulate the said office and
                                to make other provision in relation thereto, and to the precedure on
                                the revenue side of the said court.” Of course, the preamble could
                                not restrain the act of Parliament if there were express provisions
                                afterwards going beyond it; and so far as there were express
                                provisions going beyond the preamble they would be quite
                                intelligible, and not at variance with what might be expected; but
                                where there were no express provisions going beyond the preamble,
                                then the preamble was for the purpose of the act to regulate the
                                precedure on the revenue side of the court of exchequer. Passing at
                                once to the 9th clause, it runs thus:</p>
                    <pb facs="0148" n="138" xml:id="pg_138"/>
                    <p>“Section 222 of the common law procedure act, 1852, for the amendment
                                of defects and errors in any proceedings in civil cases, and
                                concerning the costs and terms of such amendment, shall extend to
                                all suits and proceedings on the revenue side of the court of
                                exchequer.”</p>
                    <p>Then follows the 10th section:</p>
                    <p>“In any suit or proceeding on the revenue side of the court of
                                exchequer the parties may at any time before judgment, by consent
                                and order of a judge, state any question or questions of law in a
                                special case for the opinion of the court, without pleadings, and
                                upon judgment thereon error may be brought as on a judgment in a
                                special verdict, unless the parties agree to the contrary; and the
                                proceedings for bringing a special case before the court of error
                                shall, as nearly as may be, be the same as in the case of a special
                                verdict, and the court of error shall either affirm the judgment or
                                give the same judgment as ought to have been given in the court in
                                which it was originally decided, the said court of error being
                                required to draw any inferences of fact from the facts stated in
                                such special case which the court below ought to have drawn.”</p>
                    <p>This section, continued Sir Hugh, was an incorporation of two
                                sections of the common law procedure acts—the one, section 42 of the
                                act of 1852, and the other, section 32 of the act of 1854.
                                Parliament thus treats the court of exchequer as one court, and the
                                court of appeal or the court of error as the other. The legislature
                                confers on the suitors the right of bringing error upon a special
                                case before the court of error, and it points out what the court of
                                error shall do with reference to that case. The 11th clause provides
                                that, in the absence of “any agreement as to the costs of the
                                special case, the costs shall follow the event.” Sir Hugh Cairns
                                then read the subsequent sections, and, coming to the 18th and
                                following sections, said that he found the provisions of the common
                                law procedure act, 1852, as to error in the proper and strict sense
                                of the term, the proceedings which formerly commenced by writ of
                                error, and those provisions had been adopted and applied by
                                Parliament to the revenue side of the court of exchequer. The 18th
                                section of the Queen’s remembrancer’s act stated that no judgment on
                                the revenue side of the exchequer should be reversed or avoided
                                unless error be commenced or brought and prosecuted with effect
                                within six years, with a proviso with regard to parties under
                                disability. That section answered to the 146th and 147th sections of
                                the procedure act of 1852. The 19th section was:</p>
                    <p>“A writ of error shall not be necessary or used in any suit or
                                proceeding in error on the revenue side of the court of exchequer,
                                and the proceeding to error shall be a step in the cause, and shall
                                be taken in manner and subject as to such terms and conditions as to
                                giving bail,” &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>That was the same as the 148th section of the procedure act, with a
                                special interpolation authorizing the barons of the exchequer to
                                make a rule as to giving bail or surety. Then, the 20th clause was
                                that any party might tender a bill of exceptions on a trial arising
                                on the revenue side of the court of exchequer, and the like
                                proceedings might be taken as between subject and subject. Up to
                                this point the legislature had taken up every proceeding with regard
                                to the courts of error, minus one—all but that one proceeding which
                                the procedure act, 1854, provided in the event of rules for new
                                trials being refused or being made absolute by the court. Now, the
                                26th section enacts:</p>
                    <p>“It shall be lawful for the lord chief baron, and two or more barons
                                of the court of exchequer, from time to time, to make all such rules
                                and orders as to the process, practice, and mode of pleading on the
                                revenue side of the court, and as to the allowance of costs, and for
                                the effectual execution of this act, and the intention and objects
                                thereof, as may seem to them necessary and proper; and also from
                                time to time, by any such rule or order, to extend, apply, or adapt
                                any of the provisions of the common law procedure act, 1854, and any
                                of the rules of pleading and practice on the plea side of the said
                                court, to <pb facs="0149" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/> the revenue side
                                of the said court, as may seem to them expedient for making the
                                process, practice, and mode of pleading on the revenue side of the
                                said court as nearly as may be uniform with the process, practice,
                                and mode of pleading on the plea side of such court.”</p>
                    <p>The act was divided into two parts. Referring to the first part,
                                power was given to three or more of the barons to make rules. It did
                                not require the whole court. The part of the court could not be
                                greater than the whole What was the meaning of the first part of the
                                section? That they (the barons) might regulate the internal
                                arrangements with the four corners of their own court; they were
                                absolute as to the process, practice, and mode of pleading; they
                                could not create new courts; they could not go outside their own
                                court, and give to suitors rights external to their court; they
                                could not say they ordained that the privy council, the House of
                                Lords, and the exchequer chamber should hear appeals from their own
                                court. Their jurisdiction might be termed territorial; they were
                                masters at home, and there only. After discharging their duties in
                                their own court, in hearing and disposing of a case, they were <hi rend="italic">functi officio;</hi> and as to the present case,
                                it had escaped from them, and there was an end to their control over
                                it, as over all the cases in this court in a similar position. There
                                was a matter, looking at the outside of the court, upon which they
                                might make a rule, because the act of Parliament had provided for
                                error. It had contemplated bail in error—error shall be a stay of
                                proceedings upon bail being given as the barons of the exchequer
                                should order. But they could not make rules as to who shall have
                                error and who not, and where the error should be heard, Now, take
                                the words in the second part of the section, “and also from time to
                                time by any such rule or order” (that meant a rule or order made by
                                the majority of the court) “to extend, apply, and adapt any of the
                                provisions of the common law procedure acts to the proceedings on
                                the plea side of the court to the revenue side of it.” To what were
                                they to extend, apply and adapt? Why, to the revenue side of their
                                own court. Take the words following on in the section:</p>
                    <p>“As may seem to them expedient for making the process, practice, and
                                mode of pleading on the revenue side of the said court as nearly as
                                may be uniform with the process, practice, and mode of pleading on
                                the plea side of such court.”</p>
                    <p>In the rules made prior to the 4th of November, 1863, every stage in
                                a suit is taken up step by step, and is dealt with with extra care
                                and propriety, and great attention was paid to the power and
                                jurisdiction given to the court, but on the 4th of November, 1863,
                                contrary to everything that had ever been done before, legislation
                                was taken up by the court, and those provisions laid down under the
                                guise of rules which might be introduced into an act of Parliament,
                                but which could not find their justification in any authority short
                                of an act of Parliament. Was it the practice or pleading or mode of
                                proceeding in the exchequer to say that a suitor in that court,
                                against whom a decision had been pronounced, should have an appeal
                                to another court, and the exchequer to say what that other court
                                shall be? The defendants had the verdict, and the order of the court
                                discharging the rule obtained by the crown, and all they had to ask
                                of the exchequer was for the performance of the ministerial act of
                                entering up judgment, which in strictness could not be stayed by any
                                of the after proceedings. They were now summoned before this court
                                to show cause why their verdict should not be reversed. It was a
                                misconception for the crown to suppose that there was in this case
                                any appeal, and the defendants now asked to have the case struck out
                                of their lordships’ paper.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General,</hi> on behalf of the
                                crown, said if the legislature had given the court of exchequer
                                power to make the rules, there was nothing extraordinary in the
                                rules made. The second part of the 22d section gave the barons of
                                the exchequer power to extend the provisions of the procedure acts
                                to the matter now before the court, and also from time to time by
                                any such rule <pb facs="0150" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/> or order to
                                extend, apply, or adapt any of the provisions of the common law
                                procedure acts to the revenue side of the court. Now, what was it
                                that Parliament had authorized to be done? Not that the court of
                                exchequer should legislate by giving jurisdiction to courts of
                                appeal, or creating new courts of appeal, but to extend, adapt, or
                                apply any of the provisions contained in certain acts which
                                Parliament had already passed, and which were there mentioned, to
                                the revenue side of the court, and the sole question was whether
                                that which had been done was or was not an extension or application
                                of certain provisions of these acts to the revenue side of the
                                exchequer. If it be that, then it was clearly within the powers
                                granted by Parliament. Some of the observations on the other side
                                depended upon the assumption that within the meaning of the act of
                                Parliament procedure in error from the court of exchequer was no
                                part of the process, practice, and pleading of the revenue side of
                                that court. Procedure in error was and must be intended to be within
                                the meaning of those words. The <hi rend="italic">formula</hi> to
                                introduce the first common law procedure act runs thus: “An act to
                                amend the mode of process, practice, and mode of pleading in the
                                superior courts of common law at Westminster,” and so on. The
                                preamble was, “Whereas the process, practice, and mode of pleading
                                in the superior courts of common law at Westminster may be rendered
                                more simple and speedy, be it enacted,” &amp;c. The whole of the
                                clauses in that enactment are declared by that recital to be enacted
                                for the purpose of rendering more simple the process, practice, and
                                mode of pleading in the superior courts at Westminster, an
                                expression which was intended to comprehend all proceedings in
                                error, though those proceedings might be carried to the House of
                                Lords, which was not itself a superior court of common law at
                                Westminster. The clauses as to error are from 154th to the 166th of
                                the common law procedure act, 1852, and under that designation of
                                “the process, practice, and mode of pleading in the superior courts
                                of common law at Westminster” all the subject-matter of clauses
                                which must be referred to were included. The first clause on error
                                is the 148th; the 154th section speaks of a certain memorandum
                                alleging error which is to be entered, and the form in which that
                                was to be done. Then the 155th section enacts that the judgment roll
                                is to be brought into court instead of the transcript; the record
                                which passed through the courts of error as the record of the court
                                from which the error is brought. It was the record of the court of
                                exchequer which goes up to the court of error, and ultimately the
                                court of exchequer would enter up the judgment awarded. The 156th
                                clause enacts:</p>
                    <p>“That courts of error shall have power to quash the proceedings in
                                error in all cases in which error does not lie, or when they are
                                taken against good faith, or in any case in which proceedings in
                                error might heretofore have been quashed by such courts, and such
                                courts shall in all respects have such jurisdiction over the
                                proceedings as over the proceedings in cases commenced by writ of
                                error.”</p>
                    <p>Other sections were read by the learned attorney general, but no
                                comments were made upon them. He then pressed their lordships to
                                consider the 155th, 156th, and 157th sections, which related to the
                                manner in which the case was to be brought into error, whether the
                                exchequer chamber or Parliament, and there to be dealt with in
                                error, and to the manner in which the court of error was to give its
                                judgment, and the effect of that judgment when given, and the power
                                which the court of error was to exercise, and that was part of the
                                course of procedure introduced by the act for the purpose, as
                                recited in the preamble, “of amending the process, practice, and
                                mode of pleading in the superior courts of common law at
                                Westminster;” and it was plain that a procedure before the court of
                                error in Parliament, where the record was brought from one of the
                                superior courts at Westminster, was regarded within the meaning of
                                those acts as part of “the process, practice, and pleading of the
                                superior courts.”</p>
                    <pb facs="0151" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Erle.</hi>—Will you forgive
                                me for saying that a writ of error was heretofore a new action in
                                law? Section 148 bears on this—“A writ of error shall not be
                                necessary or used in any cause, and the proceeding to error shall be
                                a step in the cause.”</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General</hi> said he had not
                                intended to overlook that clause, and it was very important that its
                                effect should be properly considered. The words, “the proceeding to
                                error shall be a step in the cause, and shall be taken in manner
                                hereafter mentioned,” were a clue to the whole matter, and confirmed
                                what he (the attorney general) had stated, that it is regarded as
                                being in a certain sense a proceeding in the court and in the cause,
                                although, for the purpose of correcting the error of the court in
                                the cause, the record of that court was brought up before a superior
                                tribunal, and then the error corrected and the record returned with
                                the correction made; but it was still a cause such as it was
                                before—a cause on the revenue side of the court of exchequer, a
                                cause on the plea side, or a cause in the Queen’s bench. It was
                                still a matter belonging to the courts of common law, and it was not
                                because subjects got justice done by the correction of their errors
                                that it therefore ceased to be of that nature within the meaning of
                                the act. A proceeding in error was a step in that cause, and that
                                reconciled the whole with the preamble, and showed that the
                                legislature did not stultify itself when in the act it spoke of
                                amending the process, practice, and pleading in the superior courts
                                of common law at Westminster. It always was, from first to last, a
                                record depending in the court of exchequer, and this was only a
                                particular manner which Parliament had pointed out of making it a
                                right record. With regard to the 19th clause of the Queen’s
                                remembrancer’s act, that, upon examination, would prove very fatal
                                to the arguments used upon that act by his learned friend Sir Hugh
                                Cairns. It said that “a writ of error shall not be necessary or used
                                in any suit or proceeding in error on the revenue side of the court
                                of exchequer, and the proceeding to error shall be a step in the
                                cause, and shall be taken in manner and subject to such terms and
                                conditions, as to giving bail or security, as may be directed by any
                                rule or order made by the barons under this or any other act or acts
                                of Parliament authorizing the same, provided that nothing herein
                                contained shall invalidate any proceeding already taken by reason of
                                any writ of error issued before the commencement of this act, or
                                before such rules and orders came into effect.” This was an
                                independent and substantive enactment, and made no reference
                                whatever to the common law procedure act of 1852, and, but for the
                                orders made under the authority now disputed—the authority of the
                                26th section—by the court of exchequer, would not be applicable to a
                                writ of error under the 19th section. The section distinctly
                                recognizes the proceedings in error on the revenue side as being a
                                step in the cause, and afterwards, in the 26th section, words are
                                found saying that the provisions of the common law procedure act may
                                be extended by the court to the revenue side of the court.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Cockburn.</hi> This is not a
                                proceeding in error that we are dealing with now; it is a proceeding
                                by way of appeal. The 19th section does not apply at all to the
                                proceeding before us now.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General.</hi> It will assist us in
                                seeing the construction to be placed upon the power which we find in
                                the 26th section. Now, the court of exchequer have considered that
                                the power was communicated to them. The learned attorney general
                                here remarked upon the rules made by the court of exchequer in June,
                                1860. By the 101st the court ruled thus: “The several provisions
                                contained in the 154th, 155th, 156th, and 157th sections of the
                                common law procedure act, 1852, when applicable, shall extend and be
                                applied in like cases on the revenue side of the court;” the 103d
                                also extends sections 159 to 166, and it was for that reason, said
                                the attorney general, I read to your lordships the 155th, 156th, and
                                157th sections of the common law procedure act, 1852, which relate
                                to the mode in which error is to pass through the court <pb facs="0152" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/> of exchequer chamber and
                                the House of Lords, what is to be done in those courts and what is
                                to be the consequence of what they do. There is not a word said in
                                the Queen’s remembrancer’s act which says how the clauses 155, 156,
                                157 of the procedure act shall be applied; and, therefore, it would
                                be entirely a <hi rend="italic">casus omissus</hi> if it were not
                                within the power granted to the court of exchequer in the 26th
                                section. The exchequer, under this power, have declared the sections
                                just mentioned, which relate entirely to what is to be done in the
                                court of error, shall be applicable, and if it should be held by the
                                present court that that was <hi rend="italic">ultra vires,</hi> the
                                crown must submit to that decision, and it must be taken as
                                established that the old process of error must apply in every such
                                case. It was a fallacy to say that the court of exchequer had taken
                                upon themselves to legislate. The court of exchequer had interpreted
                                the powers which Parliament had given to it to extend <hi rend="italic">quoad hoc,</hi> to enable it to say that
                                henceforth these provisions of the common law procedure acts were to
                                be applicable to causes upon the revenue side of the court of
                                exchequer. Apart from whether there is any obstacle to that being
                                done, the thing is to be understood that those particular clauses
                                which relate to the subject are merely transcripts from the common
                                law procedure act of 1854. Looking at and examining the clauses,
                                (the 35th in particular,) it will be seen how impossible it is to
                                separate these matters from the procedure of the court; of exchequer
                                itself. The 35th section enacts, “In all cases of motions for a new
                                trial upon the ground that the judge has not ruled according to law,
                                if the rule to show cause be refused, or, if granted, be then
                                discharged or made absolute, the party decided against may appeal,
                                provided any one of the judges dissent from the rule being refused,
                                or, when granted, being discharged or made absolute as the case may
                                be, provided the court in its discretion think fit that an appeal
                                should be allowed,” with a proviso that there is to be no appeal
                                upon matters of discretion as to where the verdict is against
                                evidence. Every single condition, said the attorney general, there
                                mentioned, is a condition to be fulfilled in the court of exchequer.
                                It is in the court of exchequer that the motion is made, on the
                                ground that the judge has not ruled according to law. It is in the
                                court of exchequer that the rule to show cause is refused, or
                                granted, or discharged, or made absolute. It is in the court of
                                exchequer that the judges dissent, whose dissent must have given
                                rise to the appeal, and a discretion is exercised by that court as
                                to whether the court think fit that an appeal shall be allowed. Down
                                to that point at all events, beyond the possibility of dispute,
                                every ———that constitutes the <hi rend="italic">locus standi</hi> of
                                the appellant arises out of that which is matter of process and
                                practice in the court of exchequer in the most exact and literal
                                sense of those words.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Cockburn.</hi> What strikes
                                me most forcibly, and presents to my mind the most serious
                                difficulty in the matter, is this: if it was intended to give an
                                appeal, as the legislature clearly did give an appeal, in all civil
                                causes from one of those three courts of exchequer chamber, why
                                should not the legislature have expressly said so, and why should it
                                have left it to that inferior tribunal to determine whether or not
                                there should be an appeal from it to the court of exchequer
                                chamber?</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General.</hi> Upon that and many
                                other points the legislature thought fit to leave discretion to the
                                court of exchequer to determine whether there were good reasons for
                                or against extending any of the provisions of the common law
                                procedure act to the cases on the revenue side of the court. If we
                                had not the right of coming by way of appeal to this court upon a
                                bill of exceptions, then it might have been said that it was a
                                matter of substance and not of form—that it was not a mere question
                                of the mode of procedure, whether we should come in the manner in
                                which the common law procedure act in the 35th section had said that
                                other people might come. But it becomes a different question the
                                moment the legislature has said that we shall have the ordinary
                                right of coming by bill of exceptions. Then, inasmuch as the common
                                    <pb facs="0153" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/> law procedure act only
                                gives a different form of appeal by the 35th section upon matters of
                                law, that is to say, the same matters which we should have a right
                                to raise by a bill of exceptions, the common law procedure act
                                having considered that the other form, that is, the power of
                                appealing upon a motion for a new trial upon matters of law, would,
                                in many cases, be a more convenient mode of arriving at the same
                                result, and asserting the same right as the bill of exceptions, the
                                legislature considered that in these revenue cases the subject or
                                the crown had a right to appeal upon a matter of law. It did not
                                think it necessary to determine upon the face of this act whether or
                                no the alternative mode introduced in civil proceedings by the
                                common law procedure act is the more convenient mode of procedure in
                                raising the same question of law by way of appeal from a refusal of
                                a rule or from granting one for a new trial, and whether it should
                                be introduced in revenue causes, because there were peculiarities in
                                the nature of revenue causes which it thought would make it
                                expedient to leave a very large discretion to the court of exchequer
                                to determine what part of the new provisions introduced by the
                                common law procedure act should be applied to these causes; but if
                                this portion of these new provisions was applied, that was not
                                giving a right of appeal which was not existing before; it was
                                merely applying for the same purpose other means as being more
                                convenient means of raising the same question of law which had been
                                raised by way of a writ of error. Where you have the right to go by
                                a bill of exceptions, it is merely change of procedure to grant the
                                appeal the benefit of which we are now claiming. Suppose your
                                lordship had found in the act of Parliament clearly these words,
                                “All the provisions of the common law procedure act of 1854 shall be
                                applied to the revenue side of the court of exchequer,” would there
                                have been the slightest difficulty in the interpretation of those
                                words—would it not have been perfectly clear that those clauses were
                                as capable of being applied to the revenue side of the court of
                                exchequer as any others in the act? What is the meaning of applying
                                and extending them to the revenue side? The meaning is, cases on the
                                revenue side shall be subjected to and regulated by these
                                provisions. After the attorney general had answered at some length
                                several questions which had been put to him by the court, he went on
                                to say that the 35th section of the act operated upon the cause
                                while it was in every sense still in the hands of the court of
                                exchequer. In all cases of motions for a new trial if certain things
                                be done, the party decided against may appeal, provided any one of
                                the judges dissent from the rule being refused, &amp;c. The 37th,
                                38th, and 39th clauses all go on to state certain things which are
                                to be done still in the court of exchequer. Could there be a doubt
                                that the operation and incidence of clauses 35, 37, 38, and 39 are
                                upon the cause, while it is still, to all intents and purposes, in
                                the court of exchequer? The present case is a record from the court
                                of exchequer from first to last; it never ceases to be so, and when
                                final judgment is passed, execution will be by that court. It comes
                                up from the court of exchequer to be reviewed and have the errors
                                corrected, and in that sense only it is in the court of error.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Cockburn.</hi> That is now
                                equally so with regard to a bill of exceptions, and yet when a cause
                                comes up upon a bill of exceptions it is governed by the practice of
                                the court of error.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General.</hi> Yes, but the record
                                from first to last is a record of the court of exchequer, a record
                                of a cause depending upon the revenue side of the court, which
                                record, no doubt, is removed for a time from that court to the court
                                of error, but it does not cease for an instant of time to be a
                                record of the court of exchequer, from which it came, and to which
                                it must return. Therefore I say, that if the act of Parliament had
                                said these clauses shall extend to the revenue side of the court of
                                exchequer, the working out of them would be the easiest thing in the
                                world. In the first place, the thirty-fifth clause would <pb facs="0154" n="144" xml:id="pg_144"/> attach, and that would
                                tell us that when the record had at no time left the court of
                                exchequer upon certain conditions to be determined in the court of
                                exchequer, the right of appeal would arise. The two or three
                                subsequent clauses say what, while it is still in the court of
                                exchequer, is to be done, that right having attached. It is still,
                                while in the court of exchequer, an appellable cause, and being so,
                                certain things will determine whether the right has arisen or not,
                                and what is to be done when it does arise to transmit the cause from
                                the court of exchequer to the court above. Therefore, if the words
                                had been “These clauses of the common law procedure act, 1854, shall
                                extend and apply to the revenue side of the court of exchequer,”
                                there would not have been the slightest difficulty in the
                                interpretation of these words. The legislature authorizes the court
                                of exchequer to extend, apply or adapt any of the provisions of this
                                act, which, as I say, means “all or any,” to the revenue side of the
                                court of exchequer, “and any of the rules of pleading and practice
                                on the plea side of the said court to the revenue side of the said
                                court, as may seem to it expedient for making the process, practice,
                                and mode of pleading” (words which in this act mean procedure) “on
                                the revenue side of the court, as nearly as may be, uniform with the
                                process, practice, and mode of pleading on the plea side of such
                                court.” Now the legislature had extended, by the common law
                                procedure act, to the plea side of the court the procedure which is
                                contained in the clauses which have been referred to, and which, in
                                certain events, and upon certain conditions happening in the
                                inferior court, give a right of appeal, and prescribe the mode in
                                which that appeal shall be pursued, instead of a bill of exceptions.
                                The object of the power given in the 26th section is to enable the
                                court of exchequer to assimilate, as far as they think fit to do so,
                                the whole of the proceedings in revenue causes to the proceedings
                                upon the plea side, part of which under the provisions, part of
                                which under the provisions and express enactments of the common law
                                procedure acts are referred to as the part which the court of
                                exchequer may think it expedient to adopt.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Erle.</hi> It appears to me
                                that the court of exchequer have the discretion to adopt so much of
                                the common law procedure act of 1854 as they think expedient. As far
                                as I can see, in the court of exchequer they have not given to them
                                the right of stating a special case between the parties and going to
                                a court of error.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General.</hi> I think you will see
                                that earlier sections of this act deal with matters upon which it
                                was not thought expedient to give any discretion to the court of
                                exchequer. It is in the 10th section.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Cockburn.</hi> The 10th
                                section gives it specially. That is what makes such an impression on
                                my mind. The common law procedure act gives a right of appeal upon a
                                special case; then the act goes on to give an appeal in the case of
                                misdirection, &amp;c. This act of Parliament introduces the
                                enactment of the common law procedure act with regard to the special
                                case, and I should have expected it to go on and say that there
                                should be an appeal.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General,</hi> having replied to two
                                or three questions put by the court, went on to say that the
                                legislature had said that in all matters of procedure the court of
                                exchequer should be the judge. There might be difficulties as to
                                some matters which have not been dealt with, and which required
                                consideration by the court; and, with regard to those matters, the
                                court of exchequer should judge whether it is expedient to go
                                further than this act has gone towards a complete assimilation of
                                the revenue side to the plea side of the court of exchequer. That
                                court was to have the power to determine that; and for that purpose
                                it might extend or apply all or any provisions of the common law
                                procedure act; and, unless those provisions were such as in their
                                nature could not be applied, if the court had said one of them
                                should be applied, nobody could say that it had not been so applied
                                by act of Parliament. My argument, continued the learned attorney
                                general, comes to this: the whole is expressed <pb facs="0155" n="145" xml:id="pg_145"/> by the words “extend or apply any of
                                the provisions of these acts to the revenue side of the court.” Such
                                words occurring in the act of Parliament itself could have been,
                                without the least difficulty, applied in point of interpretation to
                                the clauses of the act of 1854 with which we are dealing, the power
                                being general, and the object being the assimilation of the two
                                sides of the court. It was not meant so to limit the power given to
                                the court by words not in the clause as to put it out of their power
                                to do something without which it would be impossible that the two
                                sides of the court could be thoroughly assimilated together. If the
                                court should accede to this objection, we are, I apprehend, entirely
                                remediless. But if, on the other hand, you should overrule it, there
                                is another tribunal, which, if the objection is well founded, would
                                of course be enabled to give effect to it. I do not mean to say that
                                there is any reason, if you thought the objection to be well
                                founded, you should not give effect to it; no doubt it would be your
                                duty to do so; but if you were not well satisfied upon the matter, I
                                think it would be some satisfaction to your lordships to know that
                                the parties on the other side would have the same objection open to
                                them in another place. The attorney general, in concluding his
                                argument, said, what seems to me to cause the fallacy in my learned
                                friend’s argument is the not attending to the distinction between
                                the exercise of a parliamentary power to determine whether
                                particular enactments of Parliament shall apply to a particular,
                                class of causes or not, and the exercise of a power upon legislative
                                subjects which undoubtedly would be beyond the proper jurisdiction
                                of the particular court if Parliament had not given them to it.</p>
                    <p>Sir <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh Cairns</hi> replied upon the attorney
                                general’s argument; and at the termination of the reply,</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General</hi> claimed the right, on
                                the part of the crown, to the last word.</p>
                    <p>After their lordships had consulted together,</p>
                    <p>The Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Cockburn</hi> said: The
                                court will hear you, Mr. Attorney General; but we wish to add, in
                                order that this may not be considered as establishing a practice,
                                that it is laid down in the case of “O’Connell and others against
                                the Queen,” in the House of Lords, that it is not a necessary
                                incident to cases in which the crown is defendant in error that the
                                counsel for the crown is to have the last word. But we think it
                                fully open to us in the exercise of our discretion to hear you; and,
                                therefore, we will hear you in reply.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Attorney General</hi> having been heard in
                                reply,</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Court</hi> announced that judgment would be
                                given on Monday morning.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>The Alexandra Case.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">The Exchequer Chamber, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-02-08">February
                                    8</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Present: the lord chief justice of England, the lord chief justice of
                                the common pleas, Mr. Justice Williams, Mr. Justice Crompton, Mr.
                                Justice Willes, Mr. Justice Blackburn, and Mr. Justice Mellor.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">The Attorney General</hi> vs. <hi rend="italic">Sillem and others.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Their lordships, at the sitting of the court this morning, proceeded
                                to give judgment upon the preliminary objection taken on Saturday by
                                Sir Hugh Cairns, on behalf of the defendants, to the jurisdiction of
                                the court to hear the appeal.</p>
                    <p>In accordance with the practice of the court the junior judge present
                                first delivered judgment.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Mellor</hi> said: After a careful
                                consideration of the arguments which were urged by the attorney
                                general in this case, and with every desire to support the validity
                                of the rules made by the court of exchequer on the 4th of <pb facs="0156" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/> November last, under the
                                provisions of the 22d and 23d Victoria, cap. 21, intitled “An act to
                                regulate the office of Queen’s remembrancer and to amend the
                                practice and procedure on the revenue side of the court of
                                exchequer,” I am compelled to come to the conclusion that the rules
                                1, 2, and 3, under the authority of which the present appeal is
                                brought, are not warranted by that statute, and that the claimants
                                are entitled to succeed upon the objections which were made by Sir
                                Hugh Cairns to our proceeding with the cause. In order to sustain
                                the right to appeal, the attorney general was driven to contend that
                                the legislature, in providing for the amendment of the “practice and
                                procedure on the revenue side of the court of exchequer,” had
                                incidentally delegated to the lord chief baron and two or more
                                barons the power to determine whether or not an appeal should lie
                                from a judgment of their own court, in certain cases, to the court
                                of exchequer chamber and the House of Lords. The suggestion is of a
                                power so unusual that it appears to me to require a clear and
                                unambiguous expression of the intention of the legislature that such
                                should be the case in order to support it. In the common law
                                procedure act of 1852 the legislature, after making many express
                                alterations and amendments in the process, practice, and mode of
                                pleading in the superior courts of law, did, by section 223, confer
                                upon the judges or any eight or more of them, of whom the chiefs of
                                each of the said courts should be three, power from time to time to
                                make all such general rules and orders for the effectual execution
                                of the said act and of the intention and object thereof, &amp;c.,
                                “as in their judgement might be necessary and proper;” but it gave
                                no larger power than was necessary in order to enable the judges to
                                make such rules and orders as were incidental to the complete
                                carrying into effect of the alterations and amendments made by the
                                legislature itself. The common law procedure act of 1854, which was
                                for “the further amendment of the process, practice, and mode of
                                pleading in and enlarging the jurisdiction of the superior courts of
                                common law,” was framed upon similar principles, and by section 32
                                it expressly gave to litigants the right to bring error on a special
                                case in the same manner as on a special verdict. By section 34, in
                                case of rules to enter a verdict, or for a non-suit upon a point
                                reserved at the trial, it gave the power to appeal against the
                                judgment of the court in refusing, discharging, or making absolute
                                such a rule. By section 35, in cases of misdirection, it conferred a
                                similar right of appeal from the judgment of the court in the event
                                of one judge dissenting, or the court, in its discretion, granting
                                permission to appeal; and by section 36 it enacted that the court of
                                error, the exchequer chamber, and the House of Lords, should be
                                courts of appeal for the purposes of that act. By the 97th section
                                it gave power to the judges, under the like conditions as in the
                                procedure act of 1852, to make several general rules and orders for
                                the effectual execution of the act. I have referred to several
                                sections of the common law procedure act of 1854, because they
                                contain the provisions which the court of exchequer has by the rules
                                of the 4th of November assumed to extend, apply, and adapt, in order
                                to provide a remedy by way of appeal to the particular circumstances
                                of the present case. Upon the passing of the common law procedure
                                act of 1852 the judges did make general rules regulating the
                                pleading and practice of the superior courts of common law, in
                                conformity with the power conferred upon them by that act.</p>
                    <p>In the act of the 22d and 23d of Victoria, chapter 21, now under
                                consideration, the legislature appears to me to have proceeded on
                                similar principles—namely, to have provided for certain cardinal
                                alterations in the practice and procedure on the revenue side of the
                                court of exchequer, and to have given new but special and limited
                                rights of appeal to litigants, and to have left the details
                                necessary to carry them into effect to the discretion of the judges
                                of the court of exchequer. By section 10 the act enables litigants,
                                by consent and by order of a judge, to state any question of law in
                                a special case for the opinion of the court without pleadings, and
                                upon a judgment thereon error may be brought as <pb facs="0157" n="147" xml:id="pg_147"/> on a judgment on a special verdict,
                                unless the parties agree to the contrary, and it provides that the
                                proceedings for bringing such special case before the court of error
                                shall be the same as in the case of a special verdict, except that
                                the court of error is to be required to draw inferences of fact,
                                which the court below ought to have drawn. By section 11 the costs
                                of the proceedings are regulated. By section 12 an appeal is given
                                to a court of error from a decision of the court of exchequer in
                                appeals under the provisions of the succession duty act, 1853, and
                                by section 13 it is expressly enacted that such appeal shall lie to
                                the court of error in the exchequer chamber, and that the decision
                                of the said court of error shall be subject to appeal to the House
                                of Lords. By section 15 further provision is made for bringing error
                                on special cases to be stated with reference to legacy duty, and by
                                section 16 the powers of the 1st of William IV, chapter 22, and
                                sections 46, 47, 48, and 49 of the common law procedure act, 1854,
                                are expressly incorporated into that act. By section 19 it is
                                expressly provided that a writ of error shall not be necessary, and
                                that the proceeding to error shall be a step in the cause. By
                                section 20 power is expressly given to either party to tender a bill
                                of exceptions on the trial of any issue, and section 21 provides for
                                the costs of all suits, informations, and other proceedings. By
                                these sections a power to state a special case, a power of appeal in
                                certain cases, and a power to each party to tender a bill of
                                exceptions on the trial, are carefully and specially provided for,
                                but no appeal is given against the judgment of the court on
                                granting, refusing, making absolute, or discharging a rule for a new
                                trial, or to enter a non-suit, or a verdict upon a point reserved at
                                the trial. There may be, and probably are, considerations which
                                might render such a power inexpedient in revenue suits, and it can
                                scarcely be imagined that the propriety of giving such a power
                                escaped the consideration of the legislature when the special
                                provisions above referred to were framed. The omission of such a
                                power, while other provisions are made for appeal and writs of
                                error, leads me to the conclusion that this larger power of appeal
                                was intentionally omitted from the act. The answer attempted to be
                                given to this view is, that by section 26 power is given to “the
                                lord chief baron and two or more barons,” not only to make rules and
                                orders as to the process, practice, and mode of pleading on the
                                revenue side of the court for the effectual execution of the act,
                                but also “from time to time, by any such rule or order, to extend,
                                apply, or adapt any of the provisions of the common law procedure
                                acts of 1852 and 1854, and any of the rules of pleading and practice
                                on the plea side to the revenue side of the said court as may seem
                                to them expedient for making the process, practice, and mode of
                                pleading on the revenue side of the court as nearly as may be
                                uniform with the process, practice, and mode of pleading on the plea
                                side of the said court.” It is argued that this clause gives an
                                absolute discretion to “the lord chief baron and two or more barons”
                                to incorporate with the act under consideration any provision of the
                                two common law procedure acts of 1852 and 1854, whether it gives new
                                remedies to the subject, or enlarges the jurisdiction of the courts,
                                or gives a new authority to the court of error in the exchequer
                                chamber and to the House of Lords, or only alters or amends the
                                process, practice, and mode of pleading in the superior courts of
                                common law. Surely it is more reasonable to consider that a power
                                which is to be exercised “from time to time” is more applicable to
                                the extension, application and adaptation of such provisions of the
                                common law procedure acts as refer to process, practice, and
                                pleading in their ordinary sense, and which may well be altered and
                                amended from “time to time,” than to provisions which confer new
                                remedies and enlarged jurisdiction. This is made more apparent when
                                it is considered that the reference to the provisions of the common
                                law procedure acts is immediately followed by the words, “and rules
                                of pleading and practice on the plea side of” the said court as may
                                seem to them expedient for making the process, practice, and mode of
                                pleading on the revenue side of the said court as nearly as may be
                                    <pb facs="0158" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/> uniform with the
                                “process, practice, and mode of pleading” on the plea side of the
                                said court. I can readily understand that the legislature may have
                                intrusted “to the lord chief baron and two or more barons” power to
                                make rules and orders, and to apply and adapt such provisions of
                                common law procedure acts and such rules of pleading and practice as
                                affect “process, practice, and the mode of pleading,” so as to carry
                                into effectual operation the alterations in the practice and
                                procedure of the revenue side of the court of exchequer introduced
                                by the act. But I cannot understand the policy of intrusting to the
                                lord chief baron and two or more barons of that court the power to
                                determine whether or not the court of error in the exchequer chamber
                                and the House of Lords shall have jurisdiction to entertain an
                                appeal against a judgment of the court of exchequer in granting, or
                                refusing, or discharging a rule for a new trial. The limited power
                                to make rules and orders conferred upon the judges by the common law
                                procedure acts required for its exercise a quorum of eight, of which
                                the three chiefs of the courts were to be members; but, according to
                                the argument of the attorney general, the present act has conferred
                                this most unusual and unprecedented authority to legislate for the
                                court of error and the House of Lords upon a bare majority of the
                                barons of the exchequer. I cannot adopt that view; and inasmuch as I
                                cannot consider the rules of the 4th of November as warranted by the
                                statute 22d and 23d of Victoria, I come to the conclusion that we
                                have no jurisdiction to proceed with the appeal, and that it must
                                therefore be dismissed. If I am wrong in the opinion I have formed,
                                and the rules are authorized by the statute, the House of Lords
                                will, by virtue of the very rules in question, have power to give
                                the judgment which we ought to have given.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Blackburn.</hi>—In this case the
                                defendant in a case on the revenue side of the court of exchequer
                                has obtained a verdict at the trial; a rule to set aside that
                                verdict and grant a new trial on the ground of misdirection has been
                                obtained in the court of exchequer, and, after argument, discharged.
                                The attorney general has come to this court, treating it as a court
                                of appeal, from the court of exchequer on this matter, with the
                                object that we should inquire into the grounds of the decision; and,
                                if satisfied that the court of exchequer ought to have made the rule
                                absolute, that we should now do so, and set aside the verdict
                                obtained for the defendants. The defendant has objected to our
                                jurisdiction to entertain the cause, contending that we are not a
                                court of appeal from the exchequer on this matter; that the decision
                                of the court of exchequer is final, and that he has a right in point
                                of law to retain his verdict undisturbed. I am, I think, as a judge,
                                bound to form my opinion on this as a matter of law, and to deliver
                                judgment according to what I think, without inquiring whether the
                                result as affecting this particular case is satisfactory or not; and
                                after considering the case carefully, I have come to the conclusion
                                that the defendant is right on this point, and that we have no power
                                to interfere with the verdict. The whole question depends upon the
                                construction of the 22d and 23d Victoria, cap. 21. That act does not
                                itself give the power of appeal, but it contains a section (the
                                26th) which gives power to the lord chief baron and any two or more
                                barons of the court of exchequer from time to time to make all such
                                rules and orders as to the process, practice, and mode of pleading
                                on the revenue side of the court, and as to the allowance of costs,
                                and for the effectual execution of this act and the intention and
                                objects thereof as may seem to them necessary and proper; and also
                                from time to time by any such rule or order to extend, apply, or
                                adapt any of the provisions of the common law procedure act, 1852,
                                and the common law procedure act, 1854, and any of the rules and
                                practice on the plea side of the said court to the revenue side of
                                the said court as may seem to them expedient for making “the
                                process, practice, and mode of pleading on the revenue side of the
                                said court as nearly as may be uniform with the process, practice,
                                and mode of pleading on the plea side of such court.” In intended
                                pursuance of this power rules have been made in last Michaelmas
                                term, <pb facs="0159" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> of which the
                                following seem to me material: By the second rule an appeal is
                                allowed in such cases as the present; by the third, the exchequer
                                chamber and the House of Lords are constituted courts of appeal for
                                that purpose; by the seventh, it is prescribed that the court of
                                appeal shall give such judgment as ought to have been given in the
                                court below; and by the eighth, the court of appeal shall have power
                                to adjudge payment of costs and to order restitution, and they shall
                                have the same powers as the court of error in respect of awarding
                                process and otherwise. If the chief baron and barons of the
                                exchequer had power given them by the statute to make enactments to
                                the effect just stated, then, no doubt, the appeal lies, and we
                                ought to hear it. Each of the rules I have above quoted is a
                                transcript of a provision in the common law procedure act, 1854, by
                                sections 35, 36, 41, and 42, of which act these powers are given to
                                the House of Lords and the court of exchequer chamber in all civil
                                suits between subject and subject, including those that originate on
                                the plea side of the exchequer, as well as those originating in the
                                Queen’s bench, common pleas, common pleas of Lancaster, and the
                                other courts of record to which the common law procedure act of 1854
                                applies. And if the true construction of the 22d and 23d of
                                Victoria, cap. 21, sec. 26, is that the lord chief baron and two or
                                more barons can apply any of the provisions of the common law
                                procedure act, 1854, to all suits which originated on the revenue
                                side “of the court of exchequer at all stages after the litigation
                                has passed out of the court of exchequer, as well as while still in
                                the court of exchequer, no doubt that power has been exercised.
                                Certainly a power so extensive as this is not one which one would
                                expect to find given to the judges of any court. The regulation of
                                the process, practice, and mode of pleading in any court involves a
                                great many questions of detail, and therefore may properly be
                                delegated by the legislature to some one; and when it is delegated
                                at all, the power is naturally confided to the judges of that court.
                                But it seems highly improbable that the legislature should intend to
                                delegate to any one a discretionary power to determine whether the
                                exchequer chamber and the House of Lords should or should not have a
                                new jurisdiction which they had not before to prescribe to the
                                exchequer chamber and the House of Lords how they should exercise
                                that jurisdiction, and to give to the exchequer chamber and the
                                House of Lords new powers of awarding process to enforce this
                                jurisdiction. Whether these things should be done or not is a
                                question of principle which the legislature ought to determine for
                                itself. Still less likely is it that they would delegate this power
                                to the judges of one court to be exercised from time to time. It was
                                perfectly competent for the legislature to do so; but, before
                                construing the act in such a way as to produce this startling
                                result, we ought to see the intention to do so pretty clearly
                                expressed. Now, section 26<hi rend="italic">,</hi> in terms, gives
                                power to the barons to apply the provisions of the two common law
                                procedure acts to the process, practice, and mode of pleading on the
                                revenue side of the court of exchequer, with the purpose of making
                                it as nearly as may be uniform with the process, practice, and mode
                                of pleading on the plea side of the court of exchequer. These words
                                seem to me to show an intention to confine the power to the process,
                                practice, and mode of pleading in that court, and while the cause is
                                before that court. I do not think that, in any fair and ordinary
                                construction of language, the judgment of the House of Lords
                                reversing or affirming the judgment of a court below, or the award
                                of process by the House for the purpose of enforcing their judgment,
                                can be considered part of the process, or practice, or mode of
                                pleading of that court below. I think that it would be a great
                                strain upon the words to construe them so as to include such matters
                                in them; and, as I have already said, I think that it is so
                                improbable that the legislature meant to include them in the power
                                given to the lord chief baron and the barons that the intention
                                ought to be clearly shown.</p>
                    <pb facs="0160" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/>
                    <p>Hitherto I have only referred to the 26th section, and reasoned as to
                                its construction from the terms of that section alone; but when we
                                look at the whole act of the 22d and 23d of Victoria, chap. 21, and
                                construe section 26 as a part of the whole statute, 1 think that,
                                according to the ordinary rules of construction of a statute, it
                                becomes clear that the legislature did not intend to give the power
                                of appeal in cases on the revenue side of the exchequer. Before the
                                common law procedure act of 1852 a writ of error might issue to
                                remove the record of a cause in the exchequer, whether it was on the
                                plea side or the revenue side of that court; and the court of error
                                might examine into any errors apparent on the record, but nothing
                                else. In suits between subject and subject a further power had been
                                given to tender a bill of exceptions and thereby to annex to the
                                record a statement of the direction of the judge to the jury, and
                                thereby to bring any alleged misdirection before the court of error;
                                but that power had not been given in suits in which the crown was a
                                party, and, consequently, not in proceedings on the revenue side.
                                The act of 1852 made many alterations in the form of the writs of
                                summons and execution, and other matters, properly called process,
                                and also in the practice and also in the mode of pleading; and it
                                also contained a series of enactments, beginning with section 146,
                                as to error, and the manner in which, after error has been brought,
                                the proceedings are to be conducted in the court of error. The
                                attorney general argued that, because the preamble of the act of
                                1852 recited that it was expedien tthat the process, practice, and
                                mode of pleading of the superior courts should be rendered more
                                simple and speedy, therefore the enactments relating to error in
                                that act must relate to process, practice, or mode of pleading. I
                                think Sir Hugh Cairns gave the true answer when he said that in all
                                acts were many provisions going beyond the scope of the preamble,
                                which merely pointed out the principal object of the legislature. He
                                also argued that there was a necessity for the more extensive
                                construction of section 26, in order to work the provisions as to
                                the mode of proceeding in error. I think this is not so. In the 22d
                                and 23d of Victoria, cap. 22, by section 18 the legislature made an
                                enactment equivalent to sections 146 and 147 of the common law
                                procedure act of 1852; but when they come to section 148 there is a
                                difference made which I think is very important. By the common law
                                procedure act, 1852, section 148, it is provided that “a writ of
                                error shall not be necessary, or used in any cause, and the
                                proceeding in error shall be a step in the cause, and shall be taken
                                in manner hereinafter mentioned.” The 19th section of the 22d and
                                23d of Victoria is in the same precise words till it, comes to the
                                manner in which error shall be taken—that is, to be “in manner and
                                subject <hi rend="italic">as</hi> (a word, I presume, inserted by a
                                clerical error) to such terms and conditions as to giving bail or
                                security as may be directed by any rule or order made by the barons
                                under this or any other act,” &amp;c. It seems to me that the
                                express power here given to the barons to regulate by rule the
                                manner in which error shall be taken, not only puts an end to the
                                last-mentioned argument of the attorney general, but also affords a
                                strong argument that the legislature did not suppose that the power
                                to do so was included in the power given by section 26. Again, the
                                common law procedure act of 1854, by section 32, allowed error to be
                                brought upon a special case. The legislature in the 22d and 23d of
                                Victoria, chapter 21, section 10, enacts the same thing in so many
                                words, and in section 20 the power to tender a bill of exceptions is
                                expressly given. We find the legislature providing by express
                                enactment for error on a special case, for making error a step in
                                the cause, and for a bill of exceptions. The power of appeal was
                                created by the act of 1854, section 35, and those following it. It
                                is a different kind of proceeding from error, and it is nowhere
                                expressly mentioned in the 22d and 23d of Victoria, cap. 21. There
                                were four matters, and, as far as I know, only four, in which the
                                mode of questioning in a court of error the decision of the
                                exchequer on a matter arising on the plea side differed from the
                                mode of questioning <pb facs="0161" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/> its
                                decision on a matter arising on the revenue side. When the
                                legislature expressly enacted that three of those shall apply to the
                                revenue side, it seems to me to afford a strong argument that the
                                legislature did not intend the fourth—namely, the power of appeal—to
                                apply to them. <hi rend="italic">Expressio unius est exclusio
                                    alterius.</hi> Surely, the spirit of that maxim applies here? It
                                was said by the attorney general, when pressed by this argument,
                                that it might be that the legislature thought it quite certain that
                                error on a special case was expedient, and therefore enacted
                                expressly that it should be, but that they were not sure whether the
                                power of appeal would be expedient, and so delegated to the lord
                                chief baron and the barons the power to determine that for them.
                                Such humility on the part of the legislature as this, amounting to
                                an admission of their incompetency to determine a point, not of
                                detail, but of principle, is inconceivable; but I cannot think it is
                                so probable as to justify me in straining the words of section 26
                                out of their ordinary sense for the purpose of making them express
                                such humility. It seems to me that a far more natural solution is
                                afforded by what my brother Bramwell stated in the court below. It
                                appears that the officers of the revenue thought that the power of
                                appeal was inexpedient. It has been assumed rather hastily, both in
                                the court of exchequer and in this court, that this was an
                                unreasonable thought, and that when it was determined that a bill of
                                exceptions might be tendered, it ought to have followed as of course
                                that an appeal should be given; but it is to be recollected that
                                revenue cases are confined to the court of exchequer, and that
                                consequently the members of that court acquire an experience not
                                possessed by the judges of the other courts; but the trials at <hi rend="italic">nisi prius</hi> on circuit are now before any
                                judges. It might, therefore, be reasonably expected that the
                                comparatively experienced judge would readily reserve points for the
                                more competent tribunal, and it might be thought that if an appeal
                                were given wherever a point was reserved there would be delay and
                                vexatious litigation, to the detriment of the revenue. Consistently
                                with this, it might be thought that a bill of exceptions would
                                seldom be tendered except on some point on which the opinion of the
                                court of exchequer was already known, and which was of importance. I
                                do not say that these suggestions are good, but only that they are
                                plausible enough to make it far from improbable that the officers of
                                the revenue had influence enough to cause the bill to be prepared
                                with the deliberate intention not to give the power of appeal,
                                However this may be, I think, for the reasons I have given, that the
                                true legal construction of the act is not to give that power.
                                Entertaining this view of the law, I am bound (with whatever regret
                                as to this particular case) to say that I think that this court
                                ought not to hear the appeal. I think, however, that we ought not to
                                do anything which can in the least impede the taking of this appeal
                                to the House of Lords. I think our judgment should be that the
                                appeal be dismissed. If the attorney general is right in saying that
                                we are bound to give the judgment which the court of exchequer ought
                                to have given, the judgment I propose would be erroneous, and on
                                appeal the House of Lords would set it right (as, on that
                                supposition, the House would be bound to do,) and pronounce the
                                judgment which this court ought to have pronounced.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Willes.</hi>—I am of opinion that an
                                appeal well lies in this case, and that the present appeal ought not
                                to be dismissed. Of course, for the purpose of founding any
                                proceeding by way of appeal against the judgment of one of the
                                superior courts of law at Westminster, it is necessary to produce
                                statutory authority, and I am of opinion that there is statutory
                                authority for this appeal in the 26th section of the 22d and 23d of
                                Victoria, cap. 21, and for the action which the barons of the court
                                of exchequer have taken upon that section, by making the rule
                                extending the power of appeal granted between subject and subject in
                                the common law procedure act of 1854 to cases on the revenue side of
                                the court of exchequer, as between the crown and the subject. Of
                                course this question depends altogether upon the construction of
                                that 26th section, and <pb facs="0162" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/>
                                many objections have been taken to applying it to the support of the
                                rule made in the court of exchequer in the present case. With
                                respect to the objection, that that rule so construed would be a
                                delegation of legislative authority, I think that must fail in the
                                mind of any one who considers the numerous instances of similar
                                delegation within the experience of us all. The course of pleading,
                                for instance, in the courts which I may call courts of first
                                instance, was always considered to be as much a part of the law of
                                the land as any substantive rule for determining the right of
                                property or any other rights, and it was always held that such a law
                                could not be changed without the authority of Parliament; and yet
                                the noble and learned framer of the act, known as Parkes’s act, the
                                3d and 4th of William IV, cap. 42, conferred upon the judges the
                                power, in effect, of legislating with respect to such a portion of
                                the law of the land. It is true that the power given in that act was
                                subject to the rules being laid for a certain period before
                                Parliament; but inasmuch as Parliament, without the crown, could not
                                make a law, inasmuch as Parliament constitutionally could not give
                                its assent to an act of Parliament, simply by having the paper upon
                                which the bill was written or printed laid before it, and inasmuch
                                as in form and substance the assent of the crown could only be given
                                when both houses of Parliament were present, in effect, the power of
                                legislating was given to the judges with respect to such portion of
                                the law. I conceive that the right of appeal is no more important a
                                part of the law, (and, indeed, it is less important,) because it is
                                resorted to in rare cases, than the form of proceedings which take
                                place every day in the superior courts, and by means of which the
                                rights of subjects are ascertained and enforced. Now, after
                                referring to such an instance as that, one is almost ashamed to
                                refer to the numerous cases in which towns and other local
                                communities are allowed to determine by the voice of a majority
                                whether certain acts of Parliament for local government shall or
                                shall not have power within the limits in which the inhabitants
                                reside; and to make amends for referring to such an instance, I
                                shall content myself for a proof that the delegation of legislative
                                power is no objection with referring to the 228th section of the
                                common law procedure act of 1852, by which her Majesty, in council,
                                was authorized to direct that all or any part of that act of
                                Parliament, making very great changes indeed in the law, should
                                apply to all or any court or courts of record in England or Wales,
                                and that without any authority of the House of Lords or the House of
                                Commons. So much with respect to the delegation of legislative
                                power. I shall now turn to the section itself, and endeavor to
                                ascertain whether that section does delegate to the barons of the
                                exchequer the power of making such a rule as they have made in the
                                present case. I am of opinion that it does. Assuming that there is
                                nothing in the objection that Parliament cannot delegate its
                                authority to this extent, in which I think it is proved that there
                                is nothing having in view the instances of the exertion of such a
                                power to which I have referred, is there a delegation of such a
                                power as has been exercised in the present case? At this stage of
                                the argument I am entitled to assume, as was put by the attorney
                                general in his argument, that instead of delegating the power to the
                                court of exchequer, and the court of exchequer exercising such
                                power, the legislature had made this enactment themselves, and then
                                all I have further to do is to see whether the 26th section is large
                                enough to cover the extent of the rule made by the court of
                                exchequer in terms, assuming such a rule to have been made in the
                                form of an enactment by the legislature itself.</p>
                    <p>Now, for the purpose of testing that, I must strike out the word
                                “any”—“any of the provisions of the common law procedure act, 1852
                                and the common law procedure act, 1854,” and I must read, “such of
                                the provisions of the common law procedure act, 1852,” and so on;
                                and I must strike out “as may seem to them expedient,” because I am
                                now assuming that it appears to the legislature to be proper, “as
                                may seem to them expedient for making the process, practice, <pb facs="0163" n="153" xml:id="pg_153"/> and mode of pleading on
                                the revenue side of the court of exchequer the same as that on the
                                plea side.” Well, then, if the enactment he “to extend, apply, and
                                adapt such of the provisions of the common law procedure act of
                                1854,” which is the act with which we are dealing, as are proper for
                                making the process, practice, and mode of pleading on the revenue
                                side of the said court as nearly as may he uniform with the
                                practice, process, and mode of pleading on the plea side of such
                                court, to deal with such an enactment all you have to do is to
                                ascertain whether the process, practice, and mode of pleading on the
                                revenue side of the court do include proceedings by way of appeal on
                                that side of that court. I own that, upon the best consideration
                                which I can give to the matter, I am of opinion that they do, not
                                only from one’s experience with respect to the practice of the
                                court, which has always been considered to include error, and now
                                appeals, but also upon the terms and out of the enactments of this
                                act itself. First of all, with regard to the experience of us all,
                                with respect to practice, (of course the mode of pleading is out of
                                the question,) and I pass over process because it has a technical
                                meaning, such as has been put upon it in Comyns’s Digest, title
                                “Process;” it relates to writs, either original or of mesne process,
                                judicial writs in the courts of record, or writs of execution, and I
                                therefore do not place any reliance upon the use of the word
                                “process;” but coming to “practice,” “practice” is not a term of
                                art; “practice” is a word applying to all the proceedings by which a
                                cause is brought to judgment and execution, and it is impossible to
                                dispose of the subject of the practice of the court without
                                disposing of all the steps which may be taken before the judgment of
                                the court is carried into execution; and accordingly, looking at the
                                question as a popular one, if I take up any of the recognized books
                                of practice of these courts I find that one of the heads in such a
                                work will be the head of “error.” Error will be considered, and now,
                                since the recent alterations, appeal will be considered, otherwise
                                such a work would be as it were maimed of an arm or a leg. A member
                                of the practice of the court is the proceeding by which the judgment
                                of the court may be stayed, and the execution of the court put off
                                until it is determined whether the judgment pronounced by the court
                                is right or not. The understanding to be gathered from works with
                                respect to practice is this, that a proceeding by way of error or
                                appeal is part of the practice on the side of the court in which the
                                process originates. I think it necessarily must be so now, because
                                we are all aware that no court possesses any jurisdiction over the
                                subjects of the Queen without the writ of the Queen. Neither this
                                court nor the court of exchequer has any power to proceed, unless
                                upon the express authority of an act of Parliament, without the
                                process of the Queen; and, accordingly, the jurisdiction of courts
                                of error, before which appeals were formerly brought exclusively,
                                was initiated by the Queen’s writ of error out of chancery. That is
                                abolished, and the only process under which the courts act now, from
                                the beginning to the end of any proceeding, is a process which
                                issued out in the court of first instance—the execution, or the stay
                                of execution, of which process is the object, of course, of every
                                proceeding in error in any cause. In modern times an appeal has been
                                substituted, as being found more convenient than a writ of error.
                                The appeal takes the place of the writ of error, and, indeed, more
                                peculiarly so, because appeal is only a proceeding in the court
                                below upon whichever side the process is commenced. There is no
                                record in the court of error; the appeal is a mere information,
                                without any formal process to the court, which is substituted for
                                the first court of what has taken place there, with a view to have a
                                decision without being hampered by the technical forms which
                                affected the proceeding in error. So much with respect to the
                                meaning of the word “practice,” as understood in the profession.
                                With respect to the act itself, I apprehend that, as was suggested
                                on Saturday by my brother Williams, this 26th section is framed with
                                express reference to the amendments in the law introduced by the
                                common law procedure acts. As already pointed <pb facs="0164" n="154" xml:id="pg_154"/> out, the first common law procedure
                                act was founded upon the report of a commission to improve the
                                process, practice, and mode of proceeding in the courts of common
                                law at Westminster. The recital of the act is, that that was its
                                object, and its only object, and that act includes proceedings in
                                error. The second and third common law procedure acts followed. The
                                second act is headed “An act for the further amendment of the
                                process, practice, and mode of pleading in and enlarging the
                                jurisdiction.” I need hardly observe that that latter clause applied
                                only to the attempt which was made, and made to a great extent
                                unsuccessfully by the framers of those two statutes to extend to the
                                common law courts an equitable jurisdiction, and that it had nothing
                                whatsoever to do with the proceedings in error or appeal. In truth,
                                appeal was not an extension of jurisdiction, but only the
                                substitution of a more convenient mode of obtaining the opinion of a
                                superior court; and unless the legislature is to be considered as
                                having stultified itself in the first common law procedure act, by
                                reciting an improvement in the practice of the courts, and then
                                proceeding to make various enactments with respect to error, not
                                only affecting the courts of first instance, but affecting the
                                courts of error also, and touching even the powers and jurisdiction
                                of the House of Lords, I am at a loss to see why “practice” in the
                                26th section should not be construed to extend to the mode of taking
                                the opinion of a court of error on appeal before the execution
                                issues from the court in which the proceedings commenced; and I
                                apprehend that that is quite as much a part of the practice of the
                                court of first instance, as is in the case of those revenue
                                proceedings, the trial of the issues arising on a record out of the
                                court of exchequer in the court of <hi rend="italic">nisi prius</hi>
                                at the assizes, which we all know is a court whose jurisdiction is
                                created in as different a manner, and is in itself in every way as
                                distinct from the court at Westminster as is the court of exchequer
                                chamber or the court of appeal.</p>
                    <p>It is said, however, that this construction is excluded by certain
                                clauses of the act, and it is said that it is excluded by the fact
                                of the legislature having given in certain cases a right of error
                                and appeal, and having omitted the case in question, and by the
                                supposed absurdity of the legislature intending to give a right of
                                appeal in a case which it has not expressly mentioned. I apprehend,
                                with the greatest deference to those who are of that opinion (and
                                nobody has better learnt how necessary and how just that deference
                                is than myself) that that argument may be retorted with double force
                                upon those who assert that the right of appeal in this particular
                                case is excluded by a right of appeal being given in the cases
                                mentioned in the act. Because not only will this be found to be a
                                case of appeal <hi rend="italic">ejusdem generis, but</hi> it will
                                be found that the cases in which appeal is granted by the
                                legislature, first of all, are cases in which the special
                                interference of the legislature was necessary, because under the
                                26th section such a power could not have been given; and, secondly,
                                that, at least, one of those cases of appeal is a peculiar one, and
                                belonging to the revenue jurisdiction only. Now, I may at once
                                refer, in support of that suggestion, to the 15th section. That
                                section gives an appeal in a case in which an appeal was never known
                                before—not even known in those courts to which the act of 1854 in
                                terms applied, because it gave an appeal upon a rule. It is
                                unnecessary that I should say more than that, or go into any
                                discussion of the form of proceeding under which the court of
                                exchequer has revenue jurisdiction upon a rule. It is a summary
                                process, without a writ, and it is enough to say that it is a case
                                in which no appeal had ever previously been allowed, and therefore
                                an appeal is granted, and granted distinctly in a case which goes
                                far beyond any that was contemplated in the act of 1854. I rather
                                collect from that that the legislature thought that appeal was a
                                remedy which should be extended and enlarged. With regard to the
                                other cases in which an appeal might lie under the common law
                                procedure act, the first of them is to be found provided for in the
                                22d and 23d of Victoria, section 10, where I observe that the
                                attorney general is included under the <pb facs="0165" n="155" xml:id="pg_155"/> general expression of “the parties.” That was
                                an appeal upon a special case agreed to between the parties,
                                including the attorney general, on behalf of the crown. In such a
                                case no intervention of the court was necessary; the crown is
                                sufficiently protected by the attorney general having the power of
                                preventing such an appeal by refusing to give his consent to the
                                special case upon which it might be brought. The 17th section is a
                                very remarkable one, as it appears to me, because before that
                                statute, up to the act of the 2d and 3d of the Queen, cap. 22, no
                                cause out of the exchequer could have been tried at <hi rend="italic">nisi prius</hi> without a commission. That act
                                abolished a commission in all cases between subject and subject.
                                This act, by the 17th section, reduces the crown to the same
                                condition as the subject in that respect, and it allows the justices
                                of assize a distinct court from the court of exchequer to try
                                revenue cases without any commission. The 19th section is one which
                                requires a remark. It is the section abolishing a writ of error, and
                                then it goes on to enact that “the proceeding in error shall be a
                                step in the cause, and shall be taken in manner and subject as to
                                such terms and conditions as to giving bail or security as may be
                                directed by any rule or order made by the barons.” Why? Because the
                                provisions of the common law procedure act, following the statute of
                                Elizabeth, were not applicable to the case of the attorney general,
                                because it was thought, no doubt, an absurdity that the attorney
                                general should enter into a recognizance, or that any security
                                should be given by him; and, accordingly, it was necessary that
                                there should be rules by which the law applicable to parties should
                                be modified, and that to me seems quite a sufficient reason why this
                                provision as to the abolishing of a writ of error should be
                                specially introduced into the act. And moreover, I think, with
                                reference to the 27th section, that such a section as the 19th was
                                necessary, because it enacts that “new or altered writs and forms of
                                proceeding” shall be framed by the barons; but it does not give the
                                barons a power which would include the abolishing of the Queen’s
                                writ of error. The introduction of the 19th section appears to me to
                                be fully explained in that way. Then comes the section with respect
                                to a bill of exceptions, and that, of course, was necessary, because
                                the right to a bill of exceptions is founded upon the statute of
                                Westminster the second, and not upon the first or second common law
                                procedure act, and, therefore, an express section was necessary.
                                This being so explained, I apprehend that the introduction of such
                                an enactment by the legislature strongly fortifies the position
                                which I take, because it shows that the legislature intended to put
                                the crown in the same condition as the subject in every respect in
                                which that course could be taken. But now comes the question of an
                                appeal upon a rule for a new trial, which may be without the leave
                                of the court when it is divided, and without the leave of the
                                attorney general. Why should that discretion be vested in the barons
                                of the court of exchequer, and why should it be for them to say that
                                appeal should lie in such a case? I own that I see no difficulty in
                                answering that question, because I conceive that the appeal upon a
                                special case after the argument of a new trial is only a more
                                convenient mode of raising a question which could have been raised
                                upon a bill of exceptions. Am I right in saying that you could raise
                                under a bill of exceptions the sort of question which is desired, so
                                far as I can judge from the proceedings, to be raised here? I am
                                clearly of opinion that you can. It is said ordinarily that you
                                cannot except to a non-direction—that is to say, to the judge not
                                having directed upon a particular point. That is so ordinarily, no
                                doubt; and, if it were not so, a judge could never select the point
                                which he perceives to be the only real one in dispute, and leave
                                that alone to the jury, disembarrassing their minds of that which
                                has become immaterial for them to consider, because it has either
                                expressly or tacitly been admitted. Such was the ruling of the House
                                of Lords in a case which is cited so frequently—the case of
                                “Anderson <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Fitzgerald,” (4 House of Lords,
                                484.) But it would be quite a mistake to suppose that if a judge,
                                having omitted to state a proposition which ought to be stated in
                                the affirmative or in the <pb facs="0166" n="156" xml:id="pg_156"/>
                                negative, states, or omits to state, a point of law to the jury so
                                as that they may be misled as to the facts in the case, which it was
                                material for them to consider, and counsel calls the attention of
                                the court to that omission, and the judge declines to correct the
                                impression which has been produced by the omission and by his
                                silence upon the subject, it would be a mistake, I repeat, to say
                                that a bill of exceptions may not be tendered. In order to tender a
                                bill of exceptions upon an omission, the counsel must expressly call
                                the attention of the court to it, and it must be the omission of a
                                direction in point of law which induces the jury to look to facts
                                which they ought to consider as irrelevant, or to omit from their
                                minds facts which they ought to consider important. And such was the
                                opinion of the judges in the recent case of M’Mahon against Leonard,
                                (6 House of Lords, 996.) Mr. Justice. Wightman, in delivering the
                                opinion of the judges in that case in the House of Lords, (page
                                996,) so laid down the law with the assent of all the judges who
                                were then present; and I repeat, therefore, that those points which
                                may be taken at the trial by a bill of exceptions, if the exceptions
                                are properly framed, may be taken, and none other that I know of,
                                upon the argument of such an appeal. If the statute with respect to
                                bills of exceptions had directed, as we know it does in one part of
                                the kingdom, that the exceptions should first be argued before the
                                court of first instance, and should afterwards go to the exchequer
                                chamber, this would be nothing more than in substance changing a
                                proceeding by bill of exceptions, which is full of expense and
                                technicality, into a simpler and more beneficial proceeding by way
                                of appeal against the ruling of the court upon a point which might
                                have been raised at <hi rend="italic">nisi prius</hi> upon a bill of
                                exceptions. The court of exchequer seems to me, therefore, in making
                                this rule, to have been authorized by the 26th section, and to have
                                kept strictly within its provisions; and the rule appears to me to
                                be a rule with regard to the practice of the court, and not
                                exceeding the jurisdiction which the legislature intended to confer
                                upon the court of exchequer, to which exclusively are confided those
                                complicated and unusual cases—proceedings <hi rend="italic">in
                                    rem</hi>—questions that would not arise between subject and
                                subject in the other courts. I think this appeal is competent, and
                                that we ought to proceed.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Crompton</hi> said: The question
                                before us in this case is, whether the chief baron and three barons
                                of the court of exchequer had authority, by a general rule made by
                                them under the 26th section of the Queen’s remembrancer’s act, to
                                give to parties litigant on the revenue side of the exchequer an
                                appeal against the decision of the court upon a rule for a new trial
                                upon matter of law arising at the trial. It was not contended on the
                                part of the crown that any such appeal existed independently of that
                                statute, nor was it, nor could it be, pretended that such right of
                                appeal was directly given to the parties by that statute which
                                regulates proceedings in error, and gives, in distinct and express
                                terms the right of appeal in several cases where the legislature
                                thinks it ought to exist. The attorney general was, therefore,
                                obliged to insist upon a supposed delegation to the barons of the
                                power of creating such appeal by virtue of the 26th section of the
                                act. No doubt the legislature might, had it so pleased, have given
                                such a power of creating such appeal to this court, and ultimately
                                to the House of Lords, but it certainly would be a new and unusual
                                course of legislation in creating a new statutory appeal. Parliament
                                has frequently delegated powers as to pleading and practice, and has
                                authorized persons interested in particular localities to adopt the
                                provisions of particular acts of Parliament; but, as far as I know,
                                this is the first time that a power of creating an appeal has been
                                intrusted—if it has been intrusted—to the court from whose decision
                                the appeal is to be; and the general rule that an appeal, the
                                creature of a statute, must be very distinctly and unequivocally
                                given, seems to me to apply still more strongly to the supposed
                                power of creating such appeal. I cannot think that the power of
                                creating such an appeal is given to the barons by the 26th section.
                                In the earlier parts of the act provision is distinctly and
                                expressly made creating <pb facs="0167" n="157" xml:id="pg_157"/>
                                appeals in some cases, and for regulations as to the matters of
                                error and appeal where the legislature thought that such appeals
                                should be made, and that such regulations were desirable; and in
                                giving such appeals and making such regulations, and in introducing
                                such provisions of the procedure acts, and in making them applicable
                                to cases on the revenue side of the exchequer, they seem carefully
                                to have abstained from giving the right of appeal from decisions of
                                the court on motion, although such right of appeal is given
                                expressly by the procedure act of 1854 in civil cases in the same
                                set of clauses from which they selected some for giving rights of
                                appeal in other cases. The legislature may possibly have thought it
                                better not to give so much facility to appeals in cases for the
                                breach of customs and excise laws as might operate as a temptation
                                to parties to bring forward appeals in many cases for the purpose of
                                delay and vexation, especially when the court peculiarly conversant
                                with revenue matters had decided upon them. They certainly appear to
                                have abstained, probably upon some such ground, from inserting
                                provisions for such an appeal where we should have expected them to
                                be found if so intended; and this makes me think it the less likely
                                that they would delegate the power of creating such appeal to the
                                barons. It was contended that the legislature, by the use of the
                                words “process, practice, and mode of pleading” in the 26th section,
                                must be taken to include the right to appeal, as those words are
                                used in the preamble and in other parts of the procedure acts; and
                                that, as the later procedure act contains provisions for appeals on
                                motions, the words in question must be taken to have a statutory
                                meaning, and to include therein such right to appeal, and that such
                                right is either process, practice, or mode of pleading when used in
                                the subsequent act. I agree, however, with Sir Hugh Cairns that it
                                would be a very unsafe construction to infer from the preamble or
                                recital of a statute that it contains all it refers to, and that it
                                contains nothing more than what may be said to be included in the
                                recital or preamble. As observed by Sir Hugh Cairns, it may contain
                                all that is in the recital and preamble, and something more, as a
                                right to a new statutory appeal. It seems to me that the 26th
                                section refers to process, practice, and mode of pleading in the
                                ordinary sense of those words, and that they cannot fairly be
                                construed as intended to include the right of appeal, especially in
                                a statute where various rights of appeal are given before by express
                                words. The words following the first branch of the section give
                                power “from time to time, by any such rule or order, to extend,
                                apply, or adapt any of the provisions of the procedure acts, and any
                                of the rules of pleading and practice on the plea side of the court
                                to the revenue side of the court;” but this general power is
                                qualified by words plainly applicable to the whole of the preceding
                                powers as to adapting the provisions of the procedure act. Those
                                words are, “as may seem to them expedient for making the process,
                                practice, and mode of pleading on the revenue side of the said court
                                as nearly as may be uniform with the process, practice, and mode of
                                pleading on the plea side of such court.” The whole section seems to
                                me clearly intended to give powers to make rules respecting process,
                                practice, and pleading. It is analogous to the provisions in many
                                cases for courts to make rules as to their own process, practice,
                                and pleading. It refers to the rules of pleading and practice, and,
                                as I think, to the provisions of the procedure act, so far as
                                relates to process, practice, and pleading. The words “from time to
                                time” appear to apply to cases like those where the courts are
                                empowered to make rules for the purpose of pleadings, amendments,
                                time for pleading, writs, processes, and the like, and not to be so
                                applicable to the case of giving a new right of appeal, which I
                                agree with the attorney general could hardly be intended to be given
                                one day, and taken away or altered on another, as might well be the
                                case with mere rules of practice or pleading, which might be found
                                inconvenient, and altered again. Another argument urged upon us was,
                                that as the bill of exceptions was given by the act, the appeal on
                                motion was only a new kind of practice and mode of obtaining the
                                same result. I cannot <pb facs="0168" n="158" xml:id="pg_158"/>
                                think that the giving a bill of exceptions to correct a mistake made
                                at the trial by a single judge who may by the act in question be the
                                judge of another court is at all the same thing as giving an appeal
                                against the decision on motion of the court particularly conversant
                                with matters of revenue; and though in many cases a question of law
                                might be raised in both methods, they would be raised with very
                                different incidents to the parties. The bill of exceptions, which
                                could formerly be used only on writ of error, and since the
                                procedure acts can only be used on suggestion of error, is an
                                expensive and troublesome remedy, seldom resorted to except on
                                important and fitting occasions; and it may well be that the
                                legislature has given that remedy, and purposely abstained from
                                encouraging appeals on the smaller matters of the breach of the
                                excise and custom laws which so frequently come before the court of
                                exchequer. There certainly has been some ground for complaining of
                                the number of appeals which have been brought under the provisions
                                of the procedure act from decisions upon motions in the common law
                                courts; and from what passed in the court below there seems to have
                                been some fear of the consequences of extending this provision to
                                proceedings on the revenue side. It is sufficient, in my mind, as to
                                this argument, to say that the bill of exceptions and the new appeal
                                from decisions on motions is not the same remedy, nor can the one, I
                                think, be fairly treated as process or practice by which to carry
                                out the other. I think that the words “process, practice, and
                                pleading,” in the 26th section, cannot, without great straining, be
                                construed as delegating the power of creating a right to appeal. The
                                right of appeal can hardly be process or pleading; and as to the
                                word “practice,” I cannot help thinking that there is a great
                                difference between the machinery of the appeal and the right of
                                appeal. The former might with less difficulty be called “practice,”
                                but I have great difficulty in seeing how the giving a right to
                                appeal is “practice.” The power given to eight judges to make
                                pleading and practice rules in ordinary actions could never have
                                been imagined to give any power of creating an appeal; and it seems
                                to me, from the reference in the Queen’s remembrancer’s act, section
                                26, to those prior rules, and from the qualifications limiting the
                                power of adopting the provisions of the former acts to the purposes
                                of practice, pleading and process, and from the other reasons I have
                                referred to, that I cannot say that the legislature has by the 26th
                                section delegated to the barons any such power as that contended
                                for. I think, therefore, that there is no right to appeal from the
                                decision on motions of the court of exchequer in cases on the
                                revenue side of that court, and consequently that we have no
                                jurisdiction to interfere with the decision of the court of
                                exchequer in the present case. I agree entirely with my brothers
                                Blackburn and Meller, that if we are wrong our error may be set
                                right by the House of Lords, who, if they are bound by the rule of
                                court of the barons, are directed by the same rule to give the
                                judgment that we ought to have given.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Williams</hi> said: I am of opinion
                                that we ought to hear this appeal because I think the barons of the
                                exchequer had power under the statute 22d and 23d Victoria, cap. 22,
                                sec. 26, to make the order which they have made, extending to the
                                revenue side of their court the provisions contained in the 35th and
                                36th secs. of the common law procedure act, 1854. The 26th section
                                of the former statute authorizes the barons by their order, “to
                                extend and apply or adapt any of the provisions of the common law
                                procedure acts, &amp;c., to the revenue side of the said court as
                                may seem to them expedient for making the process, practice, and
                                mode of pleading on the revenue side of the said court as nearly as
                                may be uniform with the process, practice, and mode of pleading on
                                the plea side of such court.” It cannot be controverted that if this
                                section confers on the barons a general power to extend such of the
                                provisions of the common law procedure acts as they think proper to
                                the revenue side of the court all question ceases. But it is argued
                                that the language of the section confines the extension to such
                                provisions of the common law procedure acts as relates to <pb facs="0169" n="159" xml:id="pg_159"/> proceedings in the court
                                of exchequer itself, and does not allow of the application of such
                                of those provisions as relate to appeals to the exchequer chamber
                                and the House of Lords, which, it is said, are foreign to the court
                                of exchequer, and are not part of its “process, practice, or mode of
                                pleading.” But it should be observed that the proceedings in error,
                                generally speaking, are not regulated by any rules of the courts of
                                error themselves, but “by <hi rend="italic">regulæ generales</hi>”
                                of the superior court of Westminster, out of which the proceedings
                                in error come, and this appears to show that proceedings in courts
                                of error by way of appeal may well be regarded as parts of the
                                practice of those courts respectively. It may further be remarked
                                that the phrase “process, practice, and mode of pleading” is a
                                familiar phrase which the legislature appears to have purposely used
                                as one of well-known signification. It was, I believe, first
                                employed when the commissioners were appointed to inquire into the
                                “process, practice, and pleadings of the superior courts of law at
                                Westminster,” and afterwards in the preamble of the common law
                                procedure act, 1852, and again in the title of the common law
                                procedure act, 1854, and lastly, in the title and preamble of the
                                common law procedure act, 1860. But in accomplishing the great work
                                of rendering more simple and speedy “the process, practice, and mode
                                of pleading in the superior courts at Westminster,” it was not
                                thought to be going beyond that purpose to reform and simplify the
                                “proceedings in error.” None of the wholesome enactments, however,
                                contained in these statutes extended to the revenue side of the
                                court of exchequer until the passing of the statutes the 22d and 23d
                                of Victoria, cap. 21, now in question. And looking at the clauses in
                                this statute which were introduced for that purpose, it appears to
                                me plain that they were framed with reference to the anomalous
                                character of suits and proceedings in that branch of the court.
                                Their nature is so peculiar that the legislature appears to have
                                deemed it inexpedient to enact generally that the common law
                                procedure acts shall apply to the revenue side as well as the plea
                                side. Accordingly, some of their reforms, which are unquestionably
                                beneficial, are at once applied. For example: by section 9 the
                                general power of amendment given by the 222d section of the common
                                law procedure act is expressly extended to the revenue side. Again,
                                by section 10, the improvements as to the stating of special cases
                                and bringing error thereon are also expressly applied at once.
                                Again, by sections 18, 19, and 20, certain other of the provisions
                                of the common law procedure act, as to the propriety of the
                                application of which no doubt could be entertained, are at once and
                                absolutely extended to the revenue side. But as to the rest the
                                statute leaves it to the discretion of the barons, as being best
                                able to judge of the expediency, to extend to the revenue side so
                                many of the provisions of the common law procedure act as they think
                                right, in order to carry into effect the declared purpose of
                                uniformity. It has been objected that if the statute meant to give
                                the right of appeal it would have said so in so many words. But this
                                would be to deprive the barons of the discretion which, in my
                                opinion, that statute meant to confer on them, as to adopting this
                                provision of the common law procedure act. Nor should we, in hearing
                                this appeal, violate the rule that an appeal never lies unless it is
                                given by statute, because it is so given if the statute in question
                                authorizes the barons to extend the enactment which confers the
                                right. And being of opinion, for the reasons I have given, that
                                proceedings in error by way of appeal are part of the practice of
                                the court below within the meaning of that statute, I think the
                                legislature confers the right of appeal in this case.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Erle.</hi>—Upon this motion
                                to dismiss the appeal the question has been whether the barons of
                                the exchequer had jurisdiction to order that the following provision
                                of the common law procedure act, 1854, should be applied to the
                                revenue side of the court of exchequer—namely, that an appeal, with
                                its ordinary incidents, should lie to the exchequer chamber and the
                                House of Lords, where a rule for a new trial on the ground of
                                misdirection by a judge has been discharged. In my opinion, the
                                answer to this question should be in <pb facs="0170" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/> the affirmative, that there was jurisdiction,
                                on the ground that the Queen’s remembrancer’s act, the 22d and 23d
                                of Victoria, cap. 21, sec. 26, gave to them the power to make that
                                order. In support of this opinion I proceed to consider that
                                statute, together with the state of the law which led to its
                                passing. And first, I would premise that procedure in a suit
                                includes the whole course of practice, from the issuing of the first
                                process, by which the suitors are brought before the court, to the
                                execution of the last process on the final judgment; and throughout
                                the common law procedure acts and this act “procedure” is used as
                                equivalent to “process, practice, and mode of pleading.” Procedure
                                in civil suits in the superior courts of common law received
                                memorable improvements by the common law procedure acts, 1852 and
                                1854. Those acts are declared in the preamble of the first and the
                                title of the second to be for the amendment of process, practice,
                                and mode of pleading in the superior courts. Those acts provide that
                                each suit, from the issuing of the first to the execution of the
                                last process, should be taken to be one entirety. They contain
                                provisions for the practice to be followed in obtaining redress for
                                erroneous judgments by appeal to the exchequer chamber and the House
                                of Lords, the writ of error being abolished and proceedings in error
                                being declared to be steps in the cause by the common law procedure
                                act, 1852, section 148. Appeal is very essential for maintaining the
                                right administration of law, and careful provisions are made to give
                                the use and prevent the abuse of the right of appeal. According to
                                those provisions, the appeal is effected by the act of the suitor in
                                the court of first instance delivering a memorandum to the officer
                                of the court, without writ or other authority, and the right to
                                deliver that memorandum is vested in him in his capacity of suitor,
                                derived from the first process in the suit. That memorandum so
                                delivered, if the conditions of procedure are complied with, compels
                                the officer of the court below to bring the record into this court
                                and into the House of Lords, and may compel each of those higher
                                courts to hear his appeal against the judgment entered on the roll
                                of the court below so brought by that officer into the higher court,
                                and he is to record thereon the judgment of those higher courts, and
                                then to take back that judgment to the court below as the judgment
                                in that suit to be executed by that court according to the practice
                                thereof. The provisions are ample for the practical guidance of the
                                suitor in carrying his appeal through each court, and they are clear
                                to show that each court of appeal has no other function than to fix
                                the time for hearing the case; neither court can interfere with the
                                record, or do any effective act, but hear and determine on the
                                judgment to be pronounced. The whole of these provisions in the
                                common law procedure acts are constantly described as relating to
                                “process, practice, and mode of pleading,” and they extended to the
                                plea side of the court of exchequer, but not to the revenue side of
                                that court. And this brings me to the passing of the statute above
                                mentioned—the 22d and 23d of Victoria, cap. 21—under which the
                                barons claimed to make this order. I assume that the procedure on
                                the revenue side of the exchequer was adapted, to usages now
                                obsolete, and so was in need of being amended; also, that the
                                legislature intended to adopt this amended procedure of the common
                                law procedure act, as being consonant to the interests of truth and
                                justice, reserving no privileges to the crown as a suitor against a
                                subject inconsistent with those interests. I would also refer to the
                                rule that the rights of the crown cannot be taken away without clear
                                words of enactment as explaining the insertion of some of the
                                sections of this act.</p>
                    <p>But to come to the statute itself, the preamble recites the
                                expediency of making provision in relation to the procedure on the
                                revenue side of the court; then several sections, adapting the
                                spirit of the common law procedure acts to matters of revenue,
                                contain provisions suited to the intended change of procedure. Those
                                which seem to me relevant to the matter now in hand are as follows:
                                Section nine gives full powers to amend all defects of form. Section
                                ten to state a special case and bring error theron. Sections twelve
                                and thirteen, in case of <pb facs="0171" n="161" xml:id="pg_161"/>
                                appeal to the exchequer from the assessment of the commissioners
                                relating to succession duty, give power to appeal from the exchequer
                                to the two higher courts. Section fifteen, in case of a suit for
                                succession duty, enables the court to refer the matter to a master,
                                and to take his report as a special case, and error to be brought
                                thereon. Section seventeen empowers the judges of assize to try
                                issues on the revenue side as on the plea side. Section nineteen
                                makes proceedings in error to be a step in the cause without writ of
                                error, to be taken in manner as may be directed by any order made by
                                the barons under this or any other act. Section twenty gives power
                                to tender a bill of exceptions on trial of issues from the revenue
                                side, and section twenty-one to give costs for and against the
                                crown. We then come to section twenty-six, which gives large powers
                                for making orders. It contains two distinct clauses. By the first
                                clause the barons are empowered from time to time to make all such
                                orders as to “process, practice, and mode of proceeding on the
                                revenue side, and for the effectual execution of this act and the
                                intention and objects thereof as may seem to them necessary and
                                proper.” And by the second clause “also from time to time by such
                                order to extend, apply, or adapt any of the provisions of the common
                                law procedure act, 1852, and of the common law procedure act, 1854,
                                and any of the rules of pleading and practice on the plea side of
                                the court to the revenue side as may seem expedient for making the
                                process, practice, and mode of pleading on the revenue side as
                                nearly as may be uniform with the process, practice, and mode of
                                pleading on the plea side of the court.” I have referred to several
                                sections creating specific appeals. For all of these appeals, both
                                to the exchequer chamber and to the House of Lords, the barons must
                                make order under section twenty-six when making order as to process,
                                practice, and mode of pleading on the revenue side; for if they did
                                not do so, the effectual execution of the act would be prevented.
                                Section nineteen, relating to proceedings in error, seems to me to
                                refer expressly for the practice in those proceedings to the orders
                                to be made by the barons under section twenty-six. It refers to
                                orders to be made under this act, and section twenty-six is the
                                section which empowers them to make the required orders. If this
                                view of the effect of the statute be correct, it is certain that the
                                power of the barons to make orders as to the process, practice, and
                                mode of pleading on the revenue side was not confined to the court
                                of exchequer, but extended to the courts of error into which suits
                                should be brought from the revenue side of the court of exchequer.
                                It may also be worth noting, that under section 26 the barons must
                                make orders for the practice on the appeals under sections 10 and 12
                                above referred to, as the appeal is created by the name “appeal,”
                                and no specific procedure is created. The first clause of section 26
                                gives very ample powers, but the second clause is that which is more
                                immediately applicable to the order in question. It empowers the
                                barons, <hi rend="italic">inter, alia,</hi> to apply any of the
                                provisions of the common law procedure act of 1854 to the revenue
                                side, as may seem expedient for making the procedure on the revenue
                                side as nearly as may be uniform with the procedure on the plea
                                side. The order in question applies, section 35, which is one of the
                                provisions of the common law procedure act of 1854, to the procedure
                                on the revenue side. The barons are directed to make that procedure
                                uniform with the procedure on the plea side. Section 35 is part of
                                the procedure which is in use on the plea side, and the barons,
                                therefore, are not only empowered, but required, to make an order
                                for applying it, if they are to make the procedures on the two sides
                                uniform, and if they think it expedient. The order of the barons
                                seems to me, therefore, to be supported by the words of section 26,
                                and to accord with the intention to be collected from the context.
                                The objections on which Sir Hugh Cairns relied to prove want of
                                jurisdiction depend on the construction of section 26; and if the
                                construction above stated is right, it follows that his objections
                                fail Against that construction he pressed two principal arguments,
                                as I understood him—first, that the order which the barons were
                                empowered to make was <pb facs="0172" n="162" xml:id="pg_162"/>
                                intended to operate only on proceedings while in their own court,
                                and had no effect upon the courts above; and, secondly, that the
                                said order, if valid, subjected suits to a ground of appeal which
                                did not exist before. As to the first ground, I have already given
                                my reasons for saying that procedure on the revenue side includes
                                not only proceedings in the court of first instance, but also those
                                in the sequel of courts through which the same suit may be carried
                                by the suitor, and that power was given to the barons over the whole
                                of the procedure. The statute, in my opinion, delegated to them an
                                authority to make orders, and all orders made within that authority
                                have the same effect as the statute. It may well be that the
                                legislature thought that the barons of the exchequer were best
                                qualified to decide how far the collection of the revenue could be
                                reconciled with the new rights proposed to be granted—rights which
                                might be subject to abuse by dishonest debtors sued by the crown.
                                But my reasons for dissenting from this argument have been
                                sufficiently explained. With regard to the second objection, that
                                the order, if valid, would subject suits to a ground of appeal which
                                did not exist before, my answer is a denial of the fact. In my
                                opinion the order of the barons did not create any new ground of
                                appeal. The order applies (section 35 of the act of 1854) to the
                                revenue side, and thereby, when a motion is made for a new trial on
                                the ground that the judge has not ruled according to law—that is,
                                has misdirected—a party may have the decision on that rule reviewed
                                in a court of appeal. Before 1854, in case of misdirection by a
                                judge, a party aggrieved might seek redress either by tendering a
                                bill of exceptions, or by moving <hi rend="italic">in banco</hi> for
                                a new trial. Each remedy had its defects. The bill of exceptions,
                                though a most salutary check against mistakes by judges, was
                                subject, in practice, to much expense, delay, complication, and
                                other defects. The motion for a new trial had the defect of being
                                final without appeal, and as the court, according to usage, accepted
                                the statement made by the judge of the course he had taken at the
                                trial, the suitor was often dissatisfied with the result. Section 35
                                introduced a salutary amendment of the practice, which was to be at
                                the suitor’s option in case of misdirection, by enabling him to
                                appeal from the decision of the court of first instance upon a
                                motion for misdirection. By this amendment a bill of exceptions can
                                only be needed when the suitor has a distrust of the judge or of his
                                court. If there is mutual confidence, the point can be reserved
                                subject to appear, and the suitor has facility for obtaining the
                                judgment of each of the three courts in their order. But on a bill
                                of exceptions, the opinion of the court in which the action is
                                brought is not taken, and the proceeding is encumbered with the
                                difficulties before referred to. The 22d and 23d of Victoria enabled
                                the party to tender a bill of exceptions in suits on the revenue
                                side. It thereby enabled him to bring any complaint of misdirection
                                before a court of appeal, the ground of appeal being misdirection,
                                but the practice to be followed being bill of exceptions. The order
                                in question left the ground of appeal precisely the same as it would
                                have been under a bill of exceptions, but altered the practice to be
                                followed in seeking redress. If the party, instead of tendering a
                                bill of exceptions, moves for a new trial, he may bring the question
                                of misdirection before the court of appeal under the order of the
                                barons. But it is still the same misdirection which might have been
                                the subject of exception. The course for redress under a bill of
                                exceptions would have been more circuitous; but still misdirection,
                                and nothing but the misdirection, which might have been an
                                exception, can be the ground of appeal under the order in question.
                                Thus it seems to me to be true that the order relates only to the
                                practice to be followed in appealing on account or misdirection, and
                                leaves the rights of the parties under the law in respect of
                                misdirection as they were before, and in this sense did not create a
                                new ground of appeal. For these reasons I am of opinion that the
                                order in question is valid, and that this court has jurisdiction to
                                hear and determine this appeal.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice <hi rend="smallcaps">Cockburn.</hi> After the best
                                consideration I can give to <pb facs="0173" n="163" xml:id="pg_163"/> this case, the only conclusion at which I can arrive is, that we
                                have no jurisdiction to entertain this appeal. The question depends
                                upon whether, by the 26th section of the 22d and 23d Victoria, cap.
                                21, “An act to regulate the office of Queen’s remembrancer, and to
                                amend the practice and procedure on the revenue side of the court of
                                exchequer,” power is given to the latter court to establish the
                                proceeding by appeal on motions for new trial in revenue causes, and
                                to give an appellate jurisdiction to the court of exchequer chamber.
                                The section first provides that “it shall be lawful for the lord
                                chief baron and two or more barons of the court of exchequer from
                                time to time to make all such rules and orders as to the process,
                                practice, and mode of pleading on the revenue side of the court, and
                                as to the allowance of costs, and for the effectual execution of the
                                act, and the intention and objects thereof, as may seem to them
                                necessary and proper.” It is admitted that this part of the section
                                relates only to the procedure in revenue causes so long as a cause
                                is pending in the court of exchequer itself. But the section goes on
                                to give power to the barons “from time to time by any rule or order
                                to extend, apply, or adapt any of the provisions of the common law
                                procedure act, 1852, and the common law procedure act, 1854, and any
                                of the rules of pleading and practice on the plea side of the said
                                court to the revenue side of the said court, as may seem to them
                                expedient for making the process, practice, and mode of pleading on
                                the revenue side of the said court as nearly as may be uniform with
                                the process, practice, and mode of pleading on the plea side of the
                                said court.” The question is, whether the power of adapting the
                                provisions of the common law procedure acts, for the purpose of
                                assimilating the procedure on the revenue side to that on the plea
                                side of the court, enables the court of exchequer to create for the
                                first time an appellate jurisdiction in this court in causes
                                relating to the revenue. It is, no doubt, true that the proceeding
                                by appeal on motions for new trial is one of the provisions of the
                                common law procedure act of 1854; but I cannot bring myself to think
                                that, when the language of the 26th section of the 22d and 23d of
                                Victoria, chapter 21, is looked to, the application of this
                                provision is within the scope of the authority conferred on the
                                barons of the exchequer. Still less, when the other enactments of
                                this statute are taken into account, does it seem to me possible to
                                adopt that view. It is admitted that the words “process, practice,
                                and mode of pleading on the revenue side of the court,” occurring in
                                the first branch of the 26th section, apply only to the procedure of
                                the court itself properly so called. It is not contended in support
                                of the jurisdiction that, under the power conferred by the first
                                branch of the section, the court would have had power to create a
                                proceeding by appeal. Why, then, should the words be read
                                differently when occurring in the second branch of the section?
                                Besides which, independently of this argument, it appears to me that
                                the term “process, practice, and mode of pleading on the revenue
                                side of the court” must be taken to have reference to the procedure
                                of the court while the cause is still pending within it, and cannot
                                be taken, without a very forced construction of the language, to
                                apply to the creating of an appellate jurisdiction, or to the
                                procedure to be adopted, when the cause has quitted the sphere and
                                precincts of the inferior court, and has passed into the
                                jurisdiction of the appellate tribunal. It is true the process out
                                of which the appeal emanates and springs is that of the court below,
                                as also that the record after the appeal has been disposed of
                                returns to the court out of which it came, in order that effect may
                                there be given to the judgment. It is also true that in acts of
                                Parliament relating to procedure the term “process, practice, and
                                mode of pleading” is applied to the procedure of courts of error and
                                appeal. But who on an appeal in a civil suit ever thought of
                                speaking of the practice of the court of exchequer chamber as the
                                practice of either of the three courts from which, to its superior
                                jurisdiction, an appeal lies? In the court of exchequer, on a rule
                                for a new trial, a plurality of counsel may be heard on the same
                                side. In the court of appeal we hear but <pb facs="0174" n="164" xml:id="pg_164"/> one on each side. This is because our
                                proceedings are here regulated by the practice of this court, and
                                not by that of the court of exchequer. Again, the time within which
                                the appeal must be brought, the form in which it shall be brought
                                before the court, the awarding of process (as to which power is
                                expressly given to the court of appeal)—all these are matters of
                                practice, as to which, if special statutory enactments had not been
                                made, the court of appeal must have made rules to regulate its own
                                proceedings. How can these matters be said to appertain to the
                                procedure on the revenue side of the court of exchequer? Yet these
                                provisions as to the jurisdiction and procedure of this court the
                                court of exchequer has taken upon itself to prescribe and settle as
                                though it formed part of its own. The fundamental fallacy of the
                                whole proceeding appears to me to consist in supposing that because
                                a cause commences on the revenue side of the court of exchequer,
                                and, in a certain sense, may be said to be a cause in that court,
                                the practice and procedure of this court is, therefore, to be a part
                                of the practice and procedure of the court of exchequer. The revenue
                                side of the court of exchequer is a separate and distinct court;
                                this court of exchequer chamber is another. The practice and
                                procedure of the one is not that of the other, and a power to amend
                                the practice and procedure of the one is not, as it seems to me, a
                                power to amend that of the other.</p>
                    <p>But can it be supposed, in the absence of clear legislative
                                enactment, that Parliament intended to confer on the court of
                                exchequer the power of creating or withholding an appeal in matters
                                of revenue at its pleasure and discretion? Where, in the history of
                                juridical legislation, was such a thing ever heard of as the
                                legislature leaving it to a tribunal to decide whether its authority
                                should be subject to revision and correction on appeal? No doubt, in
                                order to prevent vexatious and frivolous appeals, the right to
                                appeal may be made conditional on the permission of the court; but
                                no one ever heard of its being left to a court to decide whether its
                                authority should be generally subject to an appellate jurisdiction
                                or not. Statutory power has been given to courts to make rules and
                                regulations as to procedure, but never to determine whether there
                                should be a superior appellate court. Is it conceivable that
                                Parliament would, in a matter of so much importance, and so
                                eminently fitted for the determination of the legislature, have
                                delegated its functions to a court of law? It does not appear to me
                                enough to say that by this act the proceeding by bill of exceptions
                                is allowed in revenue cases, and therefore the legislature might
                                well intend to give power to the court of exchequer to superadd the
                                proceeding by way of appeal. The obvious answer to such an argument
                                is, that, had such been the case, nothing would have been more easy
                                than for Parliament so to enact—a few short lines, and the matter
                                would have been set at rest. But there are material distinctions
                                between the proceeding by bill of exceptions and that by appeal. The
                                proceeding by appeal, consisting as it does of three stages instead
                                of two, is more likely to be resorted to for the purpose of delay.
                                The case on which the appeal is to be brought must be stated between
                                the parties, or, in case of disagreement, must be settled by a
                                judge. It may not have been deemed advisable to place the crown in
                                this position. I am warranted in thinking that the adoption of this
                                mode of proceeding in revenue cases was deemed of doubtful
                                expediency, from the, fact that, though the act of the 22d and 23d
                                of Victoria, cap. 21, passed as far back as 1859, it was not till
                                November last—that is, after an interval of four years—that the
                                court of exchequer, in consequence of the difficulty which arose as
                                to settling the bill of exceptions in this case, had recourse to the
                                26th section, and made the rule of the 4th of November, 1863, in
                                order to get rid of the embarrassment in which it found itself
                                placed. It may be that, from a doubt of the propriety of extending
                                the right of appeal to revenue causes, the legislature may purposely
                                have stopped short of introducing an appeal clause into the act of
                                1859, and may have contented itself with affording a remedy by bill
                                of exceptions, as being of a more <pb facs="0175" n="165" xml:id="pg_165"/> formal character and less likely to be
                                resorted to, except on very substantial grounds, and as avoiding the
                                inconvenience of making the crown a party to the special case to be
                                stated. This view of the case becomes materially confirmed when it
                                is observed how much of the provisions of the common law procedure
                                acts in relation to proceedings on error has been introduced by
                                specific enactment into the statute in question. In the 9th, 10th,
                                18th, and 19th sections we have the provisions of those acts
                                relating to error applied to revenue causes. It follows that either
                                Parliament did not consider the adoption of these provisions as
                                within the competency of the court of exchequer within the 26th
                                section, or did not think proper to leave legislation on such a
                                matter to the court instead of providing it by act of Parliament.
                                Why, then, should a different course have been pursued in the
                                perfectly analogous case of proceeding by appeal? Again, in the 20th
                                section we have a provision for the right to a bill of exceptions.
                                If the legislature had intended to give the proceeding by appeal as
                                well, why should it have stopped short of saying so? Still more
                                striking are the provisions of the 12th and 13th sections, by which,
                                in cases of appeal from the assessments of the commissioners of
                                inland revenue to the court of exchequer under the succession duty
                                act (proceedings clearly on the revenue side of the court,) an
                                appeal is given in the very terms of the common law procedure act to
                                the court of error in the exchequer ehamber, and from this court to
                                the House of Lords. Can it be supposed that if the legislature had
                                intended to extend the right to appeal further, it would have
                                confined its specific application to this particular instance?
                                According to the well-known rule of construction, must not the
                                express enactment in the particular case be taken to negative the
                                intention to extend the provision generally? If, indeed, there were
                                no provisions of the common law procedure acts which were applicable
                                to assimilating the procedure of the two sides of the court of
                                exchequer, except the provision as to appeal, I should feel greater
                                difficulty as to the construction of the 26th section. But there are
                                several most valuable provisions which would fall plainly within the
                                procedure of the court, in my sense of the term. Among these may be
                                enumerated the provisions as to evidence, as to discovery and
                                inspection, and as to trial—provisions which have had the effect of
                                improving the administration of justice in the courts of law in a
                                very eminent degree. To the adoption of these and similar provisions
                                of the common law procedure acts the power of the court of
                                exchequer, in my opinion, alone extends. To push it further would
                                be, I think, to make Parliament say what it has not said, and do
                                what it has not done; to legislate, in short, instead of expounding
                                the statute, which alone is within our province. I regret to be
                                obliged to come to this conclusion, partly because the proceeding by
                                bill of exceptions appears to have been given up on the belief that
                                this proceeding could be adopted; still more because, if the view I
                                have taken be correct, the opportunity will be lost of settling the
                                law on the very important question of the construction of the act of
                                the 59th George III, cap. 69, as to the equipment of ships for the
                                service of belligerents. We should, however, be altogether departing
                                from the principles on which, in the discharge of our judicial
                                functions, it is our solemn duty to act, if we allowed ourselves to
                                be influenced by considerations such as these. We must interpret
                                this act of Parliament, on which alone the present question depends,
                                as we would do any other statute, and as though the discussion and
                                decision of a great question of national importance were not
                                depending on our judgment on this preliminary objection. I cannot,
                                however, but observe, in conclusion, that in all probability we
                                shall neither prejudice the parties nor delay the ultimate decision
                                of this great question by dismissing this appeal. Whatever might
                                have been our decision on the main question, had we proceeded to
                                hear this appeal, this case would, no doubt, have been taken to the
                                House of Lords. Doubtless such will be the case now; and if the
                                highest appellate tribunal should hold the decision of this court on
                                the <pb facs="0176" n="166" xml:id="pg_166"/> question of
                                jurisdiction to be erroneous, the case will be heard upon its
                                merits, as it would have been had we heard this appeal, and decided
                                the main question involved in it. It is satisfactory, therefore, to
                                think that no injury of delay can be occasioned by dismissing this
                                appeal in the present stage, even should we be wrong. I concur with
                                those members of the court who think that, according to the true
                                construction of the 26th section, we have no jurisdiction to
                                entertain this appeal, and that our only course is to dismiss
                                it.</p>
                    <p>The majority of their lordships being in favor of a dismissal of the
                                appeal, it is dismissed accordingly, the crown, as has been
                                intimated, having a right of appeal to the last and highest
                                court—the House of Lords.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
