<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-06-30T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-06-30T04:00:00-05:00" n="24" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d24">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 180.0501/25</note>
                        <head>Supreme Economic Council: Twenty-fifth Meeting Held at the Ministry of
                            Commerce [on 30th June, 1919, at 10 a.m.]</head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-30T10:00:00+01:00">June 30, 1919,
                                10 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>The Supreme Economic Council held its Twenty-fifth Meeting on Monday 30th
                            June 1919, at 10 a.m. under the Chairmanship of Lord Robert Cecil.</p>
                        <p>The Associated Governments were represented as follows:— <table cols="2" rend="width: 70%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="20">
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">United Kingdom</hi>:</cell>
                                    <cell>Mr. Wise,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Sir Wm. Goode,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Waley,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Barrie.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">United States</hi>:</cell>
                                    <cell>Mr. Hoover,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Gordon,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Dr. Taylor,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Dulles,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Mr. Riley.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>:</cell>
                                    <cell>M. Clémentel (part time),</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>M. Loucheur,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>M. Claveille,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>M. Vilgrain,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>M. Seydoux,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>M. Celier (part time).</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi>:</cell>
                                    <cell>Signor Crespi,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Commendatore Attolico.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Belgium</hi>:</cell>
                                    <cell>M. Jaspar,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>M. de Cartier de Marchienne,</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell>Lieut. Col. Theunis.</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">240.</hi></p>
                        <p>The Minutes of the Twenty-fourth Meeting were approved.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">241. Allied Economic Co-operation
                                After Peace.</hi></p>
                        <p>With reference to Minutes 216 and 238, memoranda from the American (217)
                            and French Delegates (218) dated 22nd [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] and
                            28th June respectively were submitted.</p>
                        <p>In this connection the following decision reached by the Council of Heads
                            of States at their Meeting on 28th June was reported:—<note n="1" xml:id="d24fn1">See CF–97. minute 8. <ref target="frus1919Parisv06#pg_741">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, 741</ref>.</note>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“That in some form international consultation in economic matters
                                    should be continued until the Council of the League of Nations
                                    has had an opportunity of considering the present acute position
                                    of the economic situation, and that the Supreme Economic Council
                                    should be requested to suggest for the consideration of the
                                    several Governments <pb facs="0441" n="431" xml:id="pg_431"/>
                                    the methods of consultation which would be most serviceable for
                                    this purpose.”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>It was agreed that the Committee on Policy should consider and report to
                            the Council as soon as possible upon the best means of carrying into
                            effect the decision of the Council of Heads of States and that the
                            Committee should meet in Paris or London as might be more
                            convenient.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">242. Removal of Blockade on
                                Germany.</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(i)</label>
                            <item>A Minute of the 31st Meeting of the Blockade Section held on 25th
                                June (219) embodying proposals for the termination of the
                                restrictions upon trade with Germany was submitted and
                                approved.</item>
                            <label>(ii)</label>
                            <item>The instructions (220) given by the Council of Heads of States to
                                the Blockade Section<note n="1a" xml:id="d24fn1a">See CF–92, minute
                                    8, <ref target="frus1919Parisv06#pg_671">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 671</ref>.</note> to the
                                effect that the arrangements for rescinding restrictions upon trade
                                with Germany should be based upon the assumption that the Blockade
                                will be raised immediately on the receipt of information that the
                                Treaty of Peace has been ratified by Germany, were noted.</item>
                            <label>(iii)</label>
                            <item>In connection with the above decisions the position, as regards
                                censorship and the execution of the Brussels Agreement, was
                                considered.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>It was agreed:— <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>As regards censorship, that a communication in the following
                                    sense should be sent by the Delegates present, to the
                                    representatives of their respective Governments on the Council
                                    of Ten:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“The Supreme Economic Council desires to have
                                            instructions from the Council of Ten as to the removal
                                            of the censorship. It is the personal view of the
                                            majority of the members of the Supreme Economic Council
                                            that the censorship should be removed co-incidently with
                                            the removal of the blockade which, as indicated in the
                                            note from the Council of Heads of States of 26th June,
                                            should be raised upon the ratification of the Treaty of
                                            Peace by Germany.</p>
                                        <p>The Supreme Economic Council would be glad to receive
                                            instructions upon this matter.”</p></quote></item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>As regards the execution of the Brussels Agreement, and the
                                    other Agreements entered into with Germany under the Armistice,
                                    that the Sub-Committee on Germany should be instructed to
                                    examine the position and inform the Council what action, if any,
                                    will be necessary in connection therewith, in the event of the
                                    blockade on Germany being raised.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">243. Blockade of Hungary.</hi></p>
                        <p>With reference to Minute 225 a letter dated 26th June (221) reporting
                            that the Council of Heads of States had decided to authorize <pb facs="0442" n="432" xml:id="pg_432"/> the raising of the Blockade on
                            Hungary as soon as Hungary has complied with the requirements of the
                            Allied and Associated Governments, was noted and referred to the
                            Blockade Section.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">244. Allied Economic Policy in
                                Russia.</hi></p>
                        <p>The Council had before them memoranda from all the Sections regarding the
                            extension of the operations of the Supreme Economic Council to include
                            Russia, as follows: <table cols="2" rows="5">
                                <row>
                                    <cell>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Food</cell>
                                    <cell>(198)<note n="2" xml:id="d24fn2"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_368">p.
                                            368</ref>.</note></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Communications</cell>
                                    <cell>(209)<note n="3" xml:id="d24fn3"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_407">p.
                                            407</ref>.</note></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Finance</cell>
                                    <cell>(222)</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) Shipping</cell>
                                    <cell>(223)</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) Raw Materials</cell>
                                    <cell>(224)</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table></p>
                        <p>It was agreed that a special Sub-Committee should be appointed to
                            consider in detail the memoranda put forward by the Sections, and
                            co-ordinate the proposals made therein and that the Delegations should
                            appoint their representatives on the Sub-Committee as soon as
                            possible.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">245. Railway Assistance to
                                Bulgaria.</hi></p>
                        <p>A Minute from the Communications Section (225) regarding the allocation
                            of responsibility for assisting in improving the railway transport
                            facilities in Bulgaria, was considered.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that, as no urgent demands for assistance had been
                            received, the matter did not call for immediate action by the Council.
                            There was no objections, however, to the Italian Government despatching
                            liaison officers to be attached to the French Military Mission in charge
                            of the Bulgarian railways.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">246. Use of Ex-Enemy Tonnage.</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(i)</label>
                            <item>Note from the Belgian Delegates (226) regarding the port of
                                discharge of German vessels carrying foodstuffs purchased by Germany
                                in the Argentine through the Agency of the Compañía Mercantil, was
                                submitted and referred to the Allied Maritime Transport Executive
                                for examination and report.</item>
                            <label>(ii)</label>
                            <item>A Note from the Belgian Delegates (227) referring to the decision
                                reached by the Council at the Meeting held on the 12th May with
                                regard to the allocations to Belgium for management of a number of
                                German ships, was considered.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>It was agreed to refer the note to the Allied Maritime Transport
                                Executive for action in consultation with the Belgian
                                representatives, on the understanding that in the event of a
                                disagreement the matter was to be submitted to the next Meeting of
                                the Council.</item>
                            <pb facs="0443" n="433" xml:id="pg_433"/>
                            <label>(iii)</label>
                            <item>Proposals (228) put forward by the British Delegates regarding the
                                allocation and management of ex-enemy tonnage until the final
                                ownership is decided in pursance of the terms of the Treaty of
                                Peace, were considered.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>It was agreed:— <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>that, in view of the anticipated early visit of the principal
                                    Delegates to London, it should be proposed to the Allied
                                    Maritime Transport Executive that a special meeting should Be
                                    held on their arrival to discuss these problems.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>that it should be recommended to the Allied Maritime Transport
                                    Executive that when ex-enemy tonnage is being re-allocated for
                                    management, the division should be made as far as possible, on
                                    the basis of the terms of the Treaty of Peace as regards the
                                    final disposition of the boats.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In accepting the above decisions the following reservation was made:—</p>
                        <p>The American Delegates stated that the United States Government had
                            undertaken to repatriate a number of Czecho-Slovakian refugees at
                            Vladivostock and that their Government would require to use for this
                            purpose the ex-enemy passenger tonnage now being used for the
                            repatriation of American troops;</p>
                        <p>The French Delegates called attention to their urgent needs of cargo
                            tonnage for coal and wheat and of passenger tonnage for their essential
                            repatriation and colonial services.</p>
                        <p>The Italian Delegates requested that in the re-allocation of ex-enemy
                            passenger tonnage due regard might be had to the requirements of the
                            Italian Government in respect of the repatriation of Italian emigrants,
                            particularly refugees in Macedonia.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">247. Gold Deposit at Vienna by
                                Hungarian Syndicate as Security for Foodstuffs To Be Supplied to
                                Hungary.</hi></p>
                        <p>With reference to Minute 227 the following decision reached by the
                            Finance Section at their Meeting on 27th June was noted and
                            approved.</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“It was agreed that the three million gold crowns in question should
                                be sent to the Bank of Italy at Trieste and should remain there and
                                not be removed except on order of the Italian Treasury who would
                                only act on the authority of the Allied and Associated
                                Governments.”</p></quote>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">248. The Danube Situation.</hi></p>
                        <p>(i) The Director General of Belief referred to the impossibility of
                            maintaining adequate communication with the States adjacent to the
                            Danube until such time as an arrangement was made whereby the passage of
                            goods through Hungary could be facilitated and urged upon the Council
                            the imperative necessity for ensuring that some immediate <pb facs="0444" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/> action would be taken in order
                            to prevent an economic disaster.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that the Director General of Relief should prepare a
                            statement of the position for submission to the Council of Ten,
                            recommending that immediate steps should be taken to alleviate the
                            present situation.</p>
                        <p>(ii) With reference to Minute 231, amended resolutions from the
                            Inter-Allied Danube Commission (229) and draft resolutions submitted by
                            the Communications Section (230) regarding the arrangements to be made
                            for control of the Danube traffic until the execution of the terms of
                            the Treaty of Peace, were submitted and approved.</p>
                        <p>The French Delegates requested that their reservation to the effect that
                            “the final decision would be subject to any objections raised by the
                            High. Command or by the Foreign Offices of the several Countries
                            represented on the Inter-Allied Danube Commission”, might be placed on
                            record.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="strong">249. Consideration of Economic
                                Problems Arising in Connection With the Treaty of Peace.</hi></p>
                        <p>The French Delegates referred to the probable necessity for constant
                            discussion between the Delegates of the Allied and Associated
                            Governments and the German Delegates regarding economic problems which
                            would arise in connection with the execution of the Treaty of Peace.
                            They pointed out that the Reparation Commission provided for by the
                            Treaty had not yet been established and that some of the problems needed
                            immediate attention.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that the Council should take no action regarding this
                            matter it being their view that the problems referred to by the French
                            Delegates would more properly be dealt with by the existing Reparation
                            Commission under the Peace Conference, rather than by the Council.</p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 217<note n="4" xml:id="d24fn4">Appendixes 217 to 230
                                    filed separately under Paris Peace Conf.
                                180.0501/35.</note></head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">American Note on Suggestions of
                                    Various Allies as to Economic Co-operation After Peace</hi></p>
                            <p>With respect to the note by the British Delegation,<note n="5" xml:id="d24fn5">Appendix 212, <ref target="#pg_414">p.
                                    414</ref>.</note> the American Delegates would like to observe
                                as to paragraph 2, that they cannot at all agree with the
                                constructions placed on the expressions in the Treaty with regard to
                                German supplies. Such construction will imply the rationing of
                                Germany over a term of years the establishment of priorities, and a
                                control over commercial relations of Germany, and <pb facs="0445" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/> by agencies outside the Separation
                                Commission which are in contradiction to the spirit of the Treaty,
                                and the American Delegates who were members of the Committee, who
                                settled these phases of the Treaty, absolutely repudiate any
                                suggestion that such intention was ever discussed or determined.
                                They also find themselves in entire disagreement with many other
                                propositions contained in the note. They simply want to record the
                                fact that they do not accept the propositions laid down.</p>
                            <p>With respect to the French propositions,<note n="6" xml:id="d24fn6">Appendix 213, <ref target="#pg_418">p. 418</ref>.</note> they
                                wish to observe that from a historical point of view co-operation in
                                economic measures between the nations engaged against Germany have
                                grown gradually since the beginning of the war, and do not take
                                their root in any particular document or agreement. The
                                organisations for this purpose have expanded and contracted with the
                                problems to be met. Many forms of organisation have already been
                                abandoned and new ones created as necessities suggested, nor are any
                                of the arrangements entered into in any way obligatory of
                                continuation after the signature of Peace. The American Delegation
                                wishes to place on record the fact that so far as the United States
                                is concerned all economic arrangements binding the American
                                Government fall absolutely with the Peace signature, and bear no
                                relation to any subsequent arrangements that may be entered upon,
                                which must be of world character and not limited to a particular
                                block of nations.</p>
                            <p>As to the role of the various executives and sections now extant,
                                they cannot agree to any participation in the continuation of these
                                bodies except in the sheer sense of liquidation at the earliest
                                possible moment.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">H. Hoover</hi></signed>
                                <lb/><dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-27"><hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 27 [<hi rend="italic">sic?</hi>], 1919</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 218</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Memorandum From the French Delegation
                                    on National Control Policy</hi></p>
                            <p>The French Government, owing to the complete suppression by the
                                United States of all measures of control, has given complete freedom
                                to exports, the only reservation being that of laws connected with
                                trading with the enemy.</p>
                            <p>The French Government has also, by a recent decree, permitted the
                                importation of the majority of products, freedom of import which
                                will very shortly be extended to almost all goods.</p>
                            <pb facs="0446" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/>
                            <p>This has been done in accordance with the desires constantly
                                expressed by the American and British Delegates on the Supreme
                                Economic Council.</p>
                            <p>But the Allies, as a whole, have not taken corresponding measures,
                                and the situation created in France by the maintenance of national
                                control in other Allied countries is extremely grave.</p>
                            <p>Two instances of this stand out clearly and are as follows:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p><hi rend="italic">Coal.</hi>—England instituted a control of
                                        coal which enabled her to supply the Allies with coal at the
                                        same price as that used for national consumption.</p>
                                    <p>At present the only person profiting by it is the English
                                        consumer. The French purchaser pays 60 to 80 f. o. b. more
                                        than the English buyer. Further, France is compelled, owing
                                        to the destruction of her mines, to turn to England for
                                        supplies.</p>
                                    <p>Moreover, the freight rates to France are now extremely high,
                                        owing to the control of tonnage by the British.</p>
                                    <p>A limited price was fixed by the Franco-English agreement of
                                        December 1918, but this price is very high and it is
                                        impossible to charter under it owing to the restrictions
                                        imposed on the ships carrying coal to Dunkerque, for
                                        example, to go to Bilbao to carry a cargo of ore for England
                                        at a ridiculous price.</p>
                                    <p>The result that this has on the French metallurgical industry
                                        is that she pays an exorbitant price for her coal, whereas
                                        the English industry buys coal and ore at a very low
                                        price.</p>
                                    <p><hi rend="italic">Freight.</hi>—When a quarter of wheat is
                                        sent from New York to Liverpool, one has to pay 9<hi rend="italic">s</hi>.; from New York to Le Havre, 15<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. For a ton of wheat 110<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. from Australia to England; France
                                        cannot even find ships at 250<hi rend="italic">s</hi>.</p>
                                    <p>France cannot get the necessary ships to carry the stocks in
                                        her Colonies which are deteriorating on the spot, and is
                                        compelled to purchase in England the same commodities coming
                                        from the English Colonies.</p>
                                    <p>Besides, the French trade has always had need of British
                                        tonnage, now more than ever, since the war has reduced
                                        considerably French tonnage.</p></quote></p>
                            <p>Other instances could easily be given of similar differences in the
                                price of a number of essential products.</p>
                            <p>Import restrictions produce the same disastrous results.</p>
                            <p>Consequently the French Delegation desire:— <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>That the Supreme Economic Council draw the attention of
                                        the Heads of Governments to the gravity of the situation
                                        resulting from the want of balance at present existing, and
                                        of the necessity, having regard to the circumstances, of
                                        returning to a uniform condition of freedom.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>That the Council recommend, as being absolutely necessary,
                                        the Allied and Associated States to guarantee between them
                                        freedom to purchase, at equal prices and conditions, all
                                        products and materials coming from their respective
                                        territories, as well as permission to use under the same
                                        conditions, the means of transport under their control <pb facs="0447" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/> or at their
                                        disposal; also mutually to guarantee permission to import
                                        and export.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>That, if in certain exceptional cases national control is
                                        maintained by any one of the Allied countries, this country
                                        should take all necessary measures in order that the other
                                        Allied countries should not suffer therefrom.</item>
                                </list></p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 219</head>
                            <p rend="flushleft">[<hi rend="italic">Minute of Meeting of the Blockade
                                    Section Held June 25, 1919, Regarding</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Termination of Restrictions Upon Trade With Germany</hi></p>
                            <p>The Council adopted the following resolutions:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Resolved.</hi></p>
                                    <p>“That, in accordance with the decision of the Supreme Council
                                        of the Principal Allied and Associated Powers, the Superior
                                        Blockade Council recommend that the War Trade Board, in the
                                        case of Norway and Denmark, and the Governments of Great
                                        Britain, France and Italy in the case of Sweden, and the
                                        said Governments in conjunction with the War Trade Board in
                                        the case of Switzerland and Holland, shall at once instruct
                                        their representatives in the respective countries to
                                        arrange, if possible, for the termination of the General
                                        Agreements with those countries by mutual consent upon such
                                        date as may be fixed by the Supreme Council; or failing
                                        consent by the neutral parties to such termination, to give
                                        upon the date fixed as aforesaid formal notice to terminate
                                        said agreements; and the Council further recommend that the
                                        Governments of Great Britain, France and Italy, and the War
                                        Trade Board, in the case of agreements to which they were
                                        not principal parties, but merely adhered, shall instruct
                                        their respective representatives to advise the neutral
                                        parties to such agreements of their concurrence in the
                                        proposal of the principal Allied parties to the agreements
                                        to terminate the same.”</p>
                                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Further resolved.</hi></p>
                                    <p>“That in regard to other matters affecting the liquidation of
                                        the blockade, such as the termination of sundry Blockade
                                        Agreements, including the various agreements between the
                                        British and General Trading Association, Limited, and
                                        certain bodies in Holland, the Council entrusts to the
                                        Allied Blockade Committee, the Inter-Allied Commission,
                                        Berne, and the Comité du Blocus de l’Orient in the case of
                                        the northern neutrals, Switzerland and the East
                                        respectively, the duty of taking into consultation with
                                        their Governments any measures necessary to carry into
                                        effect the above decision of the Supreme Council of the
                                        Principal Allied and Associated Powers.”</p>
                                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Further resolved</hi>.</p>
                                    <p>“That the Council adjourn sine die.”</p></quote></p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0448" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 220</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Decision of Council of Heads of
                                    States</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Regarding</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Removal of Blockade on Germany</hi></p>
                            <p>The Superior Blockade Council is instructed to base its arrangements
                                for rescinding restrictions upon trade with Germany on the
                                assumption that the Allied and Associated Powers will not wait to
                                raise the blockade until the completion of the ratification, as
                                provided for at the end of the Treaty of Peace with Germany, but
                                that it is to be raised immediately on the receipt of information
                                that the Treaty of Peace has been ratified by Germany.</p>
                            <closer><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>W. W.</item>
                                        <item>G. C.</item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">D. Ll.-G.</hi></item>
                                        <item>N. M.</item>
                                        <item>S. S.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-26"><hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 26, 1919</date>.</dateline>
                            <postscript>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Note.</hi>—On the 27th June the Council
                                    agreed that the above decision should be notified to the Germans
                                    by the President of the Peace Conference on behalf of the Allied
                                    and Associated Governments immediately after the signature of
                                        Peace.<note n="7" xml:id="d24fn7">See CF–95, minute 2, <ref target="frus1919Parisv06#pg_720">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 720</ref>.</note></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 221</head>
                            <p rend="center">[<hi rend="italic">Letter From Sir Maurice Hankey
                                    Embodying</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Decision Reached by Heads of
                                    States Regarding the Blockade of Hungary</hi></p>
                            <p>The Council of the Principal Allied and Associated Powers this
                                morning had before them a proposal which had been forwarded to
                                President Wilson by Mr. McCormick,<note n="8" xml:id="d24fn8">See
                                    CF–93, minute 8, <ref target="frus1919Parisv06#pg_701"><hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>, p. 701</ref>.</note>
                                recommending that— <list>
                                    <item>After the Treaty of Peace has been accepted and signed by
                                        Germany;</item>
                                    <item>After the Bela Kuhn Government of Hungary has withdrawn
                                        its military forces within the lines fixed by the Allied and
                                        Associated Powers;</item>
                                    <item>After the Bela Kuhn Government of Hungary has suspended
                                        military operations against surrounding States, as specified
                                        by the Allied and Associated Powers;</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">the blockade of Hungary be raised in the same manner
                                as has been done for German Austria, to permit shipments of food,
                                raw materials, animal products, manufactured articles, and all
                                ordinary commodities, <pb facs="0449" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/>
                                excluding, however, all implements of war, gold, securities or other
                                values, which would reduce the power of Hungary to complete such
                                reparations as may be imposed upon her.</p>
                            <p>It was agreed that the Superior Blockade Council should be authorised
                                to carry out this recommendation as soon as they are notified by the
                                Allied and Associated Powers that Hungary has actually complied with
                                the requirements of the Principal Allied and Associated Powers.</p>
                            <p>I am directed to communicate the above decision for your Excellency’s
                                information in order that the Superior Blockade Council and other
                                interested parties may be notified, and in order that the necessary
                                notification may be made to the Superior Blockade Council if and
                                when Hungary actually complies with the requirements of the
                                Principal Allied and Associated Powers.</p>
                            <p>Believe me [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">M. P. A. Hankey</hi></signed>
                                <lb/><dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-26"><hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 26, 1919</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 222</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Report of the Finance Section on the
                                    Extension of the Operations of the Supreme Economic Council To
                                    Include Russia</hi></p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Importance of Assistance to
                                    Russia.</hi></p>
                            <p>It must be borne in mind that no Government can hope to keep in power
                                in Russia and to avoid fresh civil wars unless it is able
                                substantially to improve the economic condition of the country. This
                                aspect of the matter is at least as important as questions of a
                                purely military character. The financial assistance which would
                                probably be required by any Government which may establish itself in
                                Russia is dealt with below.</p>
                            <p>The Finance Section wish to point out that the relief funds of the
                                United States and the United Kingdom are almost exhausted, and the
                                French relief fund entirely so. It is therefore an urgent matter for
                                the Governments concerned to consider what further financial
                                provision will be required to assist Russia in order that
                                Parliamentary sanction may be asked for whatever funds are decided
                                to be necessary.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Financial
                                Requirements.</hi></p>
                            <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The Food Section have reported that it
                                would cost 30,000,0002. a year to finance a relief programme for
                                Russia. It is understood, however, that Russia should be
                                self-supporting as regards food to a large extent if stable
                                Government and transport were restored. It is not therefore
                                considered that any large financial provision need be made for food
                                supplies.</p>
                            <pb facs="0450" n="440" xml:id="pg_440"/>
                            <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The Communications Section stated that the
                                immediate requirements for the whole of European Russia would cost
                                    8,000,000<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. It is understood that the
                                requirements for the parts of Russia at present occupied by the
                                Anti-Bolshevik Government would cost 2,000,000<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. to 3,000,000<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. Of this,
                                    500,000<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. to 1,000,000<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. has been promised by the British War Office for the
                                area occupied by General Denikin. It is important to realise that
                                delay in meeting these demands involves a much greater expenditure
                                hereafter.</p>
                            <p>The Siberian Railway is already being supervised by an Inter-Allied
                                Committee, and financial assistance is being given by the United
                                States, British, and Japanese Governments. The British Government
                                have also allocated 500,000<hi rend="italic">l</hi>. for railways in
                                Poland.</p>
                            <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) The report from the Raw Materials Section
                                has not yet been received.</p>
                            <p>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) Currency reorganisation.</p>
                            <p>The complete disorganisation of Russian currency is undoubtedly one
                                of the chief obstacles to the resumption of trade and normal
                                conditions.</p>
                            <p>The rouble—which is worth 2<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. at par—fell to
                                    5<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. in the beginning of 1919, and has now
                                fallen to 2<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. to 1 1/2<hi rend="italic">d</hi>.; the reasons for this depreciation are:— <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The issue of vast quantities of Imperial and Kerensky
                                        rouble notes by the Bolsheviks.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The issue of large quantities of paper money made in
                                        America by the Omsk Government.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The prohibition of export and import of roubles in most
                                        countries throughout the world.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The lack of exports from Russia owing to political and
                                        transport conditions.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>There are numerous varieties of rouble notes in circulation, the Czar
                                rouble, the Kerensky rouble (at a depreciation of 10 to 20 per cent,
                                in different parts), the Omsk Government rouble, manufactured in
                                America (at a depreciation of 15 to 20 per cent., as against Czar
                                and Kerensky roubles in Siberia), and innumerable local issues, of
                                which there are no less than thirty-two in South-East Russia
                                alone.</p>
                            <p>The only solution of the difficulties will probably be found to lie
                                in a currency reorganisation scheme, under which all existing
                                currency will be called in and a new paper currency issued at the
                                rate of, for example, one new rouble for ten existing roubles, and
                                considerable dollar and sterling loans to the Russian Government to
                                assist in the provision of foreign exchange.</p>
                            <p>The Finance Section are decidedly of opinion that:— <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>No attempt can be made to deal with the problem until
                                        Russia is freed from civil war, and</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>The initiative should come from the Government of Russia
                                        and not from any outside Powers.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <pb facs="0451" n="441" xml:id="pg_441"/>
                            <p>It should, however, be realised that this problem will require to be
                                very speedily dealt with as soon as Russia is freed from civil war,
                                and that a large measure of financial assistance will inevitably be
                                required.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">3. <hi rend="italic">Co-operation.</hi></p>
                            <p>The problem of assisting Russia is much too great for any one Power
                                to tackle alone, and it will have to be faced by all the Governments
                                concerned in close co-operation. It is essential that a concerted
                                policy should be framed as soon as possible and suitable methods of
                                cooperation worked out.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-24"><hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 24,
                                1919</date>.</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 223</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Note From the Allied Maritime
                                    Transport Executive</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Regarding</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Allied Economic Policy in Russia</hi></p>
                            <p>With reference to the Supreme Economic Council Minute 212, regarding
                                the economic policy to be adopted as regards Russia in the event of
                                the re-establishment of a stable Government, I am instructed by the
                                Allied Maritime Transport Executive to inform the Supreme Economic
                                Council that, in the view of the Executive, it appears that the
                                question of relief in Russia is primarily one of food and finance,
                                and that in the absence of estimates as to the extent of relief
                                contemplated, the Executive are not in a position to say how the use
                                of ex-enemy tonnage would be affected thereby.</p>
                            <p>On behalf of the Executive I am also desired to point out that the
                                only tonnage under their control is ex-enemy tonnage, and on
                                conclusion of Peace this tonnage will in due course be divided
                                between the Associated Powers for final ownership, with the result
                                that the Allied Maritime Transport Executive will not have the same
                                control over their employment as they now possess.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">C. C. Barrie</hi></signed>
                                <lb/><dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-26"><hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 26, 1919</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 224</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Extract From Minutes of an Informal
                                    Meeting of the Raw Materials Section</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Regarding</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Allied Economic Policy in
                                    Russia</hi></p>
                            <p>Continuation of the discussion of the effect of the inclusion of
                                Russia within the scope of the activities of the Supreme Economic
                                Council.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Baruch stated that, so far as the United States were concerned,
                                the Delegation in Paris had no authority to take any action in this
                                matter, and it would be necessary to consult Washington before any
                                    <pb facs="0452" n="442" xml:id="pg_442"/> definite decision
                                could be taken. Mr. Baruch added that the solution of the financial
                                problem, which appeared to him to be the most important side of the
                                question, would, in all probability, go a considerable way towards
                                settling the difficulties of the supply of raw materials in Russia.
                                He gave it as his opinion that the declaration of Peace would, in
                                all probability, bring about a considerable reduction of freight
                                rates, and a consequent lowering of prices in Europe.</p>
                            <p>Major Bemelmans referred to the statement which he was preparing,
                                more particularly in connection with the requirements of Belgian
                                firms in the Donetz basin, and in other parts of Russia, and
                                enquired whether there would be any objection to the submission of
                                this report, when ready, to the Supreme Economic Council.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Baruch was of the opinion that the collection of information on
                                the problem might be of considerable use if and when any executive
                                action were decided upon.</p>
                            <p>It was resolved that the Section should report to the Supreme
                                Economic Council that the work of the Raw Materials Section, as
                                regards the reconstruction of Russia, could not in the present
                                circumstances go beyond the collection of data and the exchange of
                                information on the subject, with a view to the speedy execution of
                                Inter-Allied policy, if and when such common executive action were
                                decided upon.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-26"><hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 26,
                                1919</date>.</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 225</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Minute From Communications
                                    Section</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Regarding</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Railway Assistance to Bulgaria</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The Italian representative, referring to Minute 47 of the
                                    eighth meeting of the Supreme Economic Council,<note n="9" xml:id="d24fn9"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_67">p. 67</ref>.</note> of date the 17th
                                    March, 1919, requested that this matter should be again brought
                                    forward by the Communications Section to the Supreme Economic
                                    Council for a decision.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The American representative called attention to the fact that,
                                    as no reports on the importance of economic railway conditions
                                    had reached the Section, and in view of the probable short
                                    existence of the Supreme Economic Council and its composite
                                    sections, he could not see the advisability of sending out an
                                    economic mission at this late date.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>It was agreed that the matter should be referred to the
                                    Supreme Economic Council as an Italian request.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0453" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 226</head>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Note From the Belgian
                                    Delegation</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Regarding</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Relief Supplies Purchased by Germany in
                                    America</hi> [<hi rend="italic">Argentina</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Through the Compañia Mercantil</hi></p>
                            <p>Item 7 of the Agenda of the meeting of the Supreme Economic Council
                                held on the 23rd June refers to a report from the Freight Committee
                                of the Food Section, regarding the use of enemy tonnage.<note n="10" xml:id="d24fn10">Appendix 205, <ref target="#pg_382">p.
                                        382</ref>.</note></p>
                            <p>In paragraph 7 of the report it is stated that a part of the German
                                tonnage has been utilised for the transport of food supplies
                                purchased by Germany in the Argentine through the agency of the
                                Compania Mercantil; the Company in question effected these purchases
                                through their agents, M. W. Müller &amp; Co., at La Haye.</p>
                            <p>In this connection it is thought possible that the German tonnage
                                thus utilised will be diverted to Dutch ports instead of to
                                Antwerp.</p>
                            <p>The Belgian Delegation, therefore, begs the Supreme Economic Council
                                to do all in their power to ensure that a part, at least, of the
                                tonnage be diverted to Antwerp.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 227</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Note From the Belgian Delegation</hi>
                                    [<hi rend="italic">Regarding</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Management
                                    of Enemy Merchant Tonnage</hi></p>
                            <p>At its meeting held on the 12th May the Supreme Economic Council
                                    decided:—<note n="11" xml:id="d24fn11">Minute 154, <ref target="#pg_250">p. 250</ref>.</note>
                                <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>That the Belgian Government should be requested to provide
                                        the Transport Executive, at the earliest possible date, with
                                        full details regarding the number of Belgian officers,
                                        engineers, and seamen now seeking employment.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>That the Transport Executive should endeavour to use these
                                        crews for manning the ships at present unallocated.</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>That if, after the completion of these arrangements, the
                                        Belgian Government are dissatisfied with the division made,
                                        the matter shall, at their request, be reconsidered by the
                                        Council.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>In accordance with these decisions, the Belgian Government informed
                                the Transport Executive that they were willing to supply a minimum
                                of ten complete crews, and requested, therefore, the management of
                                ten German ships.</p>
                            <p>Up to the present, however, the Transport Executive are only disposed
                                to allow Belgium the management of three German ships, which were
                                previously managed by the British, and one German ship now under
                                French management.</p>
                            <pb facs="0454" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/>
                            <p>In accordance with the decision arrived at by the Supreme Economic
                                Council in Clause (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) above, the Belgian
                                Delegation requests the Supreme Economic Council to be good enough
                                to reconsider the question of the division of management of German
                                tonnage, in order that, if possible, a number of German ships equal
                                to the crews which Belgium can furnish may be allocated to her for
                                management.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 228</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Proposals Relating to Enemy Tonnage
                                    To Be Put Forward by the British Representatives</hi></p>
                            <p>Enemy ships delivered to the Allied and Associated Governments by
                                Germany under the Armistice arrangements shall continue to be
                                managed by the country at present managing them until the final
                                ownership is decided, in pursuance of the Treaty of Peace, subject
                                to the following conditions:—</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Cargo vessels.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>It shall at once be ascertained from the German Government
                                    which of the ships able to deliver cargoes in Germany by the
                                    31st August are still required and can be financed by the German
                                    Government. The Allied and Associated Governments shall be free
                                    to dispose of any boat not required by Germany, the Germans
                                    being definitely so informed.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>That German tonnage up to the amount required for German food
                                    to be delivered by the 31st August shall be employed for this
                                    purpose.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>All surplus German tonnage shall be directed by the managing
                                    country until the final division is made, subject to the general
                                    supervision of the Allied Maritime Transport Executive.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Up to the date at which the ownership of a vessel passes to
                                    the Reparation Commission, hire, at net Blue Book rates, shall
                                    continue to be payable to the German Government.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                <item>From that date hire shall be paid at commercial net rates to a
                                    Central Allied Fund, to be held in trust ship by ship for the
                                    country to which the vessel is finally allotted. It is suggested
                                    that this central fund should be the fund at present
                                    administered by the Allied Maritime Finance Committee, who, for
                                    this purpose, should act on behalf of the Reparation
                                    Commission.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The Government using a ship before handing it over to another
                                    Government to which the ship has been allotted for ownership
                                    shall be liable to the Reparation Commission for the expense of
                                    reconditioning. Where a vessel has been managed by more than one
                                        <pb facs="0455" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/> Government, the
                                    expenses of reconditioning shall be allocated between them by
                                    the Reparation Commission.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Passenger vessels.</hi></p>
                            <p>As repatriation of troops, prisoners of war and refugees is not yet
                                completed, any enemy passenger vessels allotted to any country in
                                pursuance of and for the purposes indicated in the resolutions of
                                the Allied Maritime Transport Council which may cease to be required
                                for the prescribed services by that country shall be placed by that
                                country at the disposal of the Allied Maritime Transport Executive
                                for reallocation.</p>
                            <p>The financial arrangements as regards hire and reconditioning to be
                                similar to those for cargo boats.</p>
                            <p>The foregoing resolutions relate primarily to German tonnage, but
                                will apply equally to Austrian tonnage, it being assumed that there
                                is a corresponding obligation on Austrian tonnage to be used for
                                non-German relief up till the 31st August. Austrian cargo vessels
                                shall be employed on the same principles as proposed for German
                                cargo vessels, and Austrian passenger vessels shall be available for
                                the specified repatriation purposes as long as required.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 229</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Amended Resolution of Inter-Allied
                                    Danube Commission</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>In the navigable waters of the Danube River System all craft,
                                    whether captured, requisitioned or taken under the Armistice and
                                    not already entrusted to an Allied Power shall, except as needed
                                    for military purposes, be under the control of the Inter-Allied
                                    Danube Commission until other dispositions are made conformably
                                    to the Treaties of Peace. The Commission shall cause such craft
                                    to be employed for the furtherance of commerce by operating them
                                    under the Inter-Allied flag or by arranging for them to be
                                    operated under other flags and upon conditions approved by
                                    it.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>International services conducted by the instrumentality of any
                                    Danubian State or by any subsidised or unsubsidised company or
                                    individual are to be operated in accordance with such rules and
                                    regulations as the Inter-Allied Danube River Commission may
                                    approve or prescribe.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Pilots and pilotage shall be regulated by the Commission,
                                    which shall have power to fix and collect charges for pilotage
                                    and other services rendered and for the carriage of passengers
                                    and freight in craft operated under its flag or control.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The Commission shall have power to make works of repair and
                                    improvement calculated to facilitate or increase navigation and
                                    to <pb facs="0456" n="446" xml:id="pg_446"/> requisition or
                                    lease such harbour facilities and quarters on land as it may
                                    deem necessary to the performance of its work. It shall exercise
                                    such powers in accordance with the regulations that govern any
                                    Allied military forces in the particular locality.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>This resolution shall not affect the control of naval crews or
                                    the boats or equipment of the European Commission of the Danube
                                    or be construed to abridge that Commission’s
                                    jurisdiction.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-06-19"><hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 19,
                                1919</date>.</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Appendix 230</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Draft Resolution Submitted by
                                    Communications Section on the Danube Situation</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The functions of the Inter-Allied Danube Commission, whether
                                    as regards regulating the navigation of the river until this
                                    duty is transferred to the Commission referred to in Article 247
                                    of the Treaty with Germany, or as regards the control and
                                    effective utilisation of captured, requisitioned or Armistice
                                    craft pending final disposal conformably to the provisions of
                                    the Treaties of Peace, are exercised in virtue of the authority
                                    of the High Command, which is competent to authorise the issue
                                    of instructions on all the points covered by the resolution of
                                    the Inter-Allied Danube Commission dated the 19th June,<note n="12" xml:id="d24fn12">Appendix 229, <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi></note> with which the Supreme Economic
                                    Council concurs.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The Supreme Economic Council consider it will be best for the
                                    High Command to notify the riparian States of the formation of
                                    the Commission under its authority, and the powers delegated to
                                    it for the execution of its functions.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The Communications Section will take the necessary
                                    action.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>