<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>152. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-09-15T14:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-09-15T14:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recv6AMbtMSgUYM1C" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military buildup</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="reczJcBmJJ2LmpWWy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace plan</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recvabcT1yIMTGWuZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85003003"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Air corridor</term>
                    <term ref="recCErkkm3wP0wOxd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Air access</term>
                    <term ref="reckz6KR6qJLArS7N" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade">Naval blockade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-09-15T14:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-09-15T14:30:00-05:00" n="152"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                <head>152. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d152fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 396.1-WA/9-1561. Secret.
                        Drafted and initialed by <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName>, also
                        initialed by <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName>, and approved in
                        S on October 1. A summary of the conversation was transmitted to Bonn in
                        telegram 733, October 16. (Ibid., 762.0221/9-1661)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1961-09-15T15:30:00-04:00"
                            >September 15, 1961, 3:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Washington Foreign Ministers’ Conference (Restricted Session)</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United Kingdom</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Sir <persName corresp="#p_CSHA1">Harold Caccia</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Sir <persName corresp="#p_SSCAE1">Evelyn Shuckburgh</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AH9">Alphand</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LCE1">Lucet</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Carstens</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>(Interpreter—Mr. Kasterer)</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The Secretary, after referring to the fact that the luncheon conversation at the
                    White House<note n="2" xml:id="d152fn2">See <ref target="#d151">Document
                            151</ref>.</note> had been a good start for this meeting, asked <pb
                        facs="0440" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> the French Foreign Minister if he
                    could give them the French view as to negotiations and the general courses they
                    should follow, looking down the road. He had in mind that in his conversation
                    with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, he could say that the
                    Soviet Union and the Western Powers were on a collision course; the Western
                    Powers had rights and obligations and were in Berlin and intended to abide by
                    these rights in which they were supported by <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>; if <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> signed
                    his treaty and as a result considered that these rights were canceled, then they
                    were indeed on a collision course. He asked <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve
                        de Murville</persName> to please let his colleagues know what he saw for the
                    future.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said it was a
                    difficult enterprise to foresee the future. He said the French did not disagree
                    with the idea of any discussions or even negotiations with the Soviets, but
                    rather questioned the type of negotiation. It was clear that the Soviets would
                    certainly not object to a discussion on their proposals for peace treaties and a
                    free city for Berlin, but it was also possible that they might be prepared to
                    consider variations of this in which Western rights were not prejudiced. If, for
                    example, the Soviets renounced their threats then there would be a basis for
                    discussion. (In reply to the question from the Secretary, <persName
                        corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> outlined what he meant by
                    threats.) The Russians say they will sign a treaty and that as a result the
                        <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> would control access and the Western
                    Powers then must make separate deals with the <gloss target="#t_GDR1"
                        >GDR</gloss> or possibly the three allies collectively, but if not, there
                    will be no access and any attempt by the Western Powers to go through would be
                    aggression and the Soviet Union, with all its power, would support the <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> against such aggression. This was what he meant
                    as a threat. If there was an indication that the Soviets accept our access
                    rights, this would remove the threat. He was speaking in general terms and there
                    were, of course, many variations on this point, but this is essentially the
                    basis. He continued that if there were to be talks, and repeated that the French
                    did not object to talks, then roughly speaking, the aim should be in the
                    direction of the removal of the Soviet threat. If we are to talk business, this
                    can only be achieved if the real issues are clearly understood by both sides. He
                    said the French fully understand the gravity of the situation and would fight if
                    necessary, but that one aspect was not clear, and that was whether the Soviet
                    Union wants a war or thinks that it can achieve its objectives without war
                    because the West is divided or lacking in determination. Therefore, the aim in
                    any talks with the Soviets should be to convince them of our purpose and
                    determination. The Soviet threats against one country after another must be
                    clarified. He concluded by saying that these talks begun with <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would be protracted as the issues were
                    not simple. He said <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would not be
                    given requisite authority and that they would certainly go on as long as
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> is in New York. He concluded
                    that the general idea was to bring the Soviets <pb facs="0441" n="417"
                        xml:id="pg_417"/> back to reality unless they want a war, and that as he had
                    said at lunch, he felt the dangers of war lay in misunderstanding.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> said that he agreed with the
                    objective of bringing the Russians back to reality, and inquired if <persName
                        corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> would contemplate
                    negotiations if something concerning access came out of the discussions. This,
                    in essence, was the case for probing, but he was not sure that the Secretary
                    would get very far with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> on
                    substance since <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would have no
                    authority. The maximum that might be expected would be an agreement on an agenda
                    for future negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> replied that the
                    Russians were quite clearly putting their case to the world, saying that they
                    had put forth their views and inquiring what was the position of the Western
                    Powers. In effect, they had put their case in such a way that we could take it
                    or leave it and, in effect, were merely asking for our acceptance. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> says that access will be guaranteed,
                    but generally, do we know what conditions he had in mind. It was possible that
                    the Secretary could ascertain this from <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName>. He thought, however, it meant the continuance of the
                    Western right for military access but the suppression of the unlimited right we
                    now enjoy in the air corridors in respect to German travel.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed that this might be the main purpose, but that he was
                    thinking of what he could say to his colleagues after his talk with <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said it would be
                    difficult to foretell until the conversations had taken place.</p>
                <p>The Secretary continued that what he wanted to know was what was the object of
                    the enterprise and specifically what his colleagues would consider a
                    success.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said he imagined two
                    stages, not necessarily separated by a long term. The first stage, as he had
                    mentioned at the luncheon, would be one of warning the Soviets. No one could
                    tell what <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s reaction would be
                    and, therefore, it was difficult to plan the second stage. But, the second stage
                    would deal with the question of the Soviet attempts against the rights of access
                    in Berlin. For example, an unlikely but good solution would be to transfer to
                    the treaty the Bolz-Zorin agreement.<note n="3" xml:id="d152fn3">For text of
                        letters between Soviet Deputy Foreign Minister Zorin and German Democratic
                        Republic Foreign Minister Bolz, September 20, 1955, see Otnosheniia SSSR s
                            <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>, pp. 649-652; for the Bolz letter
                        alone, see Documents on Germany, 1944-1985, pp. 460-461. See also <ref
                            target="frus1955-57v26#pg_537">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1955–1957, vol. XXVI, pp.
                            537</ref>–<ref target="frus1955-57v26#pg_538">538</ref>.</note> In the
                    second stage he felt that it would be important to find out how rigid the
                    Soviets were on their positions.</p>
                <pb facs="0442" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/>
                <p>The Secretary said he had the impression that what <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1"
                        >Couve de Murville</persName> had in mind would be a successful negotiation
                    and inquired if there was anything that would be satisfactory short of a
                    successful solution.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said that these talks
                    would take a long time. The Secretary agreed and added that he felt that
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> would wish to participate
                    personally at some stage.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> remarked that they did not
                    have unlimited time, and pointed out that <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> intended to make his treaty in December and that it
                    would be very awkward for the Western Powers if he got to this point before
                    there were any real negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> pointed out that the
                    Secretary’s talks with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would
                    constitute real negotiations. He felt that the Secretary would have something to
                    tell them in a week or so regarding <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName>’s reaction and they could then see. He felt that the
                    British idea was that <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> should see
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> and propose a conference in
                    November. In such an event, let us say the twenty-fifth of September to
                    November, everything would be frozen and then in November at the conference it
                    would break down.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> said he did not see why
                        <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> saw a breakdown
                    and he thought that the Secretary might go quite a way with <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said that this could
                    be done without fixing a conference date. He said, for example, the military
                    build-up would be affected by the fixing of the conference, there would be
                    general relaxation and people would feel that there was nothing to worry
                    about.</p>
                <p>The Secretary inquired how important was it for us to have the situation in
                    Berlin maintained until the conference. He felt that this should be a
                    pre-condition for any conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said that if we fixed
                    a conference, the Soviets would become more confident and would go ahead with
                    whatever plans they had in mind, and that after the conference had failed, the
                    West would be confronted with the choice of capitulation or war.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> said that he believed that
                    whether you got the conference or not that situation might come when the treaty
                    was signed with the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said that if he
                    understood <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> correctly there
                    would be a conference in the beginning of November but there would be no
                    conversations with the Soviets. He personally believed in discreet talks rather
                    than a conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> inquired why there should be
                    a stagnation between now and November.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said that once they
                    had achieved a conference, the Soviets would not be disposed to discuss any
                    subject. He felt the subject <pb facs="0443" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/> of fixing
                    a date for a conference should await the outcome of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> talks. <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de
                        Murville</persName> and the Secretary agreed that the Soviets might discuss
                    substance bilaterally.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that it was obvious that they could not negotiate on Soviet
                    terms for Gemany and Berlin, but that they had in mind a wider agenda under
                    which each side would put forth its proposals. He inquired whether, if the
                    agenda were open to both sides, this would be acceptable to his colleagues or
                    did they feel that they could only accept an agenda which excluded the Soviet
                    item of a peace treaty and a free city for Berlin. In other words, was this a
                    matter of openness of agenda for us or a rejection of the Soviet item.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> said that in any negotiations
                    both sides have a right to put forward their proposition, a general agenda which
                    seemed to him to be in accord with <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName>’s. He then read what <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> had said to Nehru.<note n="4" xml:id="d152fn4">Nehru
                        visited Moscow September 6-8 following the Belgrade Conference.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said that what was of
                    interest to the West was the question of access; that the occupation statute was
                    an academic question provided it had no consequences.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he was anxious to explore his colleagues’ thinking since he
                    was not anxious to talk to <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> with
                    his flanks or rear exposed.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said the Secretary
                    would be doing it with the general support of them all.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> said there was no need to
                    name dates now, but he personally was doubtful if the talks would get that far.
                    He felt that public opinion would sooner or later get them all around the table
                    and the question was how long they could avoid this development.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> remarked that the
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> talks may show there is no prospect of a conference.</p>
                <p>The Secretary inquired whether we would be better off with no conference or a
                    conference that met and failed—that is a Foreign Ministers’ conference since a
                    summit was a different matter.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said it was too soon
                    to speak of a conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> said that we would not be
                    allowed not to have a conference. People who are about to be blown to atomic
                    dust would insist upon a conference. He personally would prefer to do this on
                    our own initiative than be forced into it. He felt that the Secretary’s
                    conversation with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would give us
                    some idea on the subject, adding that if the conference were fixed, it would be
                    more difficult for <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> to
                    undertake unilateral action in regard to Berlin.</p>
                <pb facs="0444" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that it appeared to be <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName>’s plan to concentrate on our rights rather than on
                    the status of the GDR; since 1955 the GDR had been treated by the Soviets as a
                    sovereign state, and that he felt that a peace treaty would not change this
                    relationship. The chief effect of a peace treaty would be on our rights,
                    although it might have some effect on the Oder-Neisse line. Otherwise, he did
                    not see why <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> would run all the
                    risks merely to achieve something that he already had. He asked Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> if there was any consensus in the
                    Working Party as to what kind of status the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>
                    was expected to get. He went on to say that the Russians did not seem to be
                    thinking in terms of de jure recognition but rather de facto dealings.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> said that his colleagues in the
                    Working Group felt that the Soviet purpose was to strengthen the <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> internationally, and to afford the <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> some control over the access question, in
                    addition to breaking the ties between the Federal Republic and Berlin. He said
                    he was leaving aside the more general possibilities such as humiliation of the
                    Western Powers and an impressive demonstration of Soviet power. He said they did
                    not know whether the Russians would insist upon the Western Powers’ dealing
                    directly with the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and that the military
                    buildup might have had some effect on this point.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Carstens</persName> said he felt that there were
                    two points the Soviets were seeking: (1) the recognition of the <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> as an independent state; and (2)<gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> authority over Berlin access; and that the
                    second was the more important.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said it seemed to him that there would be little reason in
                    establishing the competence of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> unless
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> intended to accomplish
                    something specific by utilizing this competence.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> said that he thought that
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>’s intention was the
                    transfer of the control rights over access to the <gloss target="#t_GDR1"
                        >GDR</gloss>. This would result in a situation where today you might have
                    something but the day after it would be changed; that Mr. <persName>X</persName>
                    would be permitted to go to Berlin and Mr. <persName>Y</persName> not. The same
                    procedures would apply to types of goods. The Soviets would then deny any
                    responsibility. He felt that this path was dangerous, if not fatal.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> pointed out that the Soviets
                    could virtually do that now in regard to German travel by land, although not by
                    air.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> mentioned that one thing was
                    certain, that no West German official would be permitted to go to West Berlin if
                    the East Germans controlled the access; that one of their main purposes was to
                    break the ties between West Berlin and West Germany.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> said that the removal of
                    the ties with the Federal Republic would be the beginning of the end for West
                    Berlin. He said we should not try to interpret what the Russians really mean,
                    but should <pb facs="0445" n="421" xml:id="pg_421"/> read what they say. He
                    mentioned there were people in Germany who lived by interpreting Soviet actions
                    but what they say was very clear. They intend to sign a peace treaty with the
                        <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and turn over the access to <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> control. The Soviet guarantee would not be a
                    guarantee of the status quo, but merely a guarantee of whatever agreement the
                        <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> might make. There would be no rights
                    left and the West would be in a very difficult position and the Soviets would be
                    completely disengaged.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that while we are all vitally interested in Berlin, it was of
                    greater interest to Germany. He would, therefore, like to inquire of the German
                    Foreign Minister what he saw in the future as to relations between the Federal
                    Republic and East Germany, and between West Berlin and East Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> said that this was not an
                    easy question to answer, but, in general, he thought that the division of
                    Germany would become more acute. He said up to now, while traffic had been
                    obstructed by the Soviet Zone, it still continued, but he felt that the travel
                    would now become much more difficult. Trade, he felt, would continue since it
                    was in <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> interest but in September it was made
                    very plain that the negotiators could deal only with trade and with other
                    matters of traffic; they specifically stated they did not have any authority,
                    especially in the financial and currency field. He felt that human contacts
                    would decline and saw little prospect of any improvement in this respect and
                    none whatsoever for any move towards reunification. He mentioned the example of
                    church matters, pointing out that the new bishop of Berlin who lived in the
                    Eastern Sector had not been permitted to come to West Berlin, nor had the
                    Catholic bishops in Eastern Germany been permitted to attend the conference of
                    German bishops. The successor to Dibelius had not been permitted to return to
                    his home in the Eastern zone after a trip to West Berlin. He said the toughness
                    of the East German attitude in regard to the churches indicated what their
                    attitude would be on other matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> said that the revised Western
                    peace plan contained provision for “mixed commissions” and he wondered whether
                    or not one of these commissions might not be a vehicle to make access
                    arrangements.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> said that he had agreed to
                    the proposal of mixed commissions with the exception of the third commission on
                    human rights, which he felt was a little perverse. He had agreed to these
                    commissions because he thought possibly the one on freedom of movement might
                    effect some slight improvement despite their basic objection to the commissions
                    where you would have coming into one body two incommensurable elements. He was
                    willing, however, to try in the faint hope that this might improve
                    communications. He felt, however, that any cooperation was impossible in
                    political fields, no matter whether the commission met once or a thousand times.
                    The Communists’ ideas <pb facs="0446" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/> in the political
                    field were so different from their own that there was no hope.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> said that he would agree on
                    the political elements and human rights but felt that technical arrangements
                    might be helpful in regard to access, particularly if these were guaranteed by
                    the Soviets.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> felt that this would be a
                    very dangerous idea since if allied rights were considered by this commission,
                    made up as it would be of completely disparate elements, the Communists would
                    try and refer this matter to Bolz, the East German Foreign Minister, with
                    implications of recognition. He felt the three Western allies should not favor
                    this course.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1">Lord Home</persName> explained that he had not had
                    allied rights in mind, but German.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he felt that at some stage <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> was going to sign a peace treaty, but supposed that
                    in the peace treaty there was a reservation along the lines of the Bolz-Zorin
                    letter. There would be no question in regard to rights themselves but it might
                    involve some dealings with East Germans. In other words, the reservation might
                    contain a reaffirmation of the allied rights but the exercise of the rights
                    would be with the East Germans. He inquired what alternatives there would be to
                    the allies in this event: to endeavor to obtain some <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> responsibility; or, have the three allies deal with the East
                    Germans; or transfer such dealing to the West Germans.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> said the situation would be
                    different if allied rights were the subject of the reservation and with the East
                    Germans to implement. It would be necessary to negotiate with the East Germans,
                    and he felt that the difference between rights and their implementation was
                    razor-thin. The reservations might be in very general terms, which would have to
                    be spelled out in negotiations with the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>. An
                    opinion on this would only be possible when they saw the language.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed and added that we should seek to have as little to do with
                    the East Germans as possible. He said he previously, in a somewhat light vein,
                    had referred to the fact that allied rights were in relation to Germany as a
                    whole and that, therefore, it might be possible to have these rights worked out
                    by Germans, if the rights themselves were not involved.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> said they would be prepared
                    to accept this fiction but pointed out by reading from the Bolz-Zorin letter the
                    fact that this had been merely done with a part of Germany, the <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>. He also mentioned that these rights were
                    temporarily handled by the Soviets, pending a subsequent agreement.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said the Ministers may have strayed somewhat from the purpose of
                    this meeting, which was primarily the talks with <pb facs="0447" n="423"
                        xml:id="pg_423"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>. He wished to return to <persName
                        corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName>’s remark at the luncheon
                    when <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName> had stressed the necessity of
                    warning the Russians. He would like to inquire what his colleagues thought were
                    the casi belli. For example, we had been speaking of the three vital Western
                    interests: (1) the Western presence in Berlin, (2) the freedom and viability of
                    West Berlin, and (3) access. He wondered whether these were sufficiently
                    precise, since <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> might say that if
                    we accepted the Soviet propositions these would be taken care of.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> said that there was
                    general disagreement between what the Soviets meant and what the Western Powers
                    meant, both on freedom and on access. The Soviets give the term “free city” one
                    meaning, but we have a completely different idea. What we mean is the democratic
                    order with freedom of speech, freedom of political parties, etc. The Soviets
                    have a completely different point of view on ties with the Federal Republic. He
                    mentioned that West Germany paid out 1.2 billion marks a year to the “lost
                    child” of Berlin. He said of course we could say to the Soviets that if they
                    included a definition of our requirements for freedom this might be a
                    possibility, but he felt the incompatibility of ideas was very profound. He
                    continued that it was awkward for a German to talk of these matters but he felt
                    that in this small privileged gathering he could be frank. He said there were
                    many people who said that the situation in Berlin was basically the fault of the
                    Germans but the President had stated at the luncheon that it was not Berlin but
                    our common policy that was at issue. If we started to liquidate the status of
                    Berlin there would be an exodus from Berlin and that this would mean the
                    liquidation of an advanced free world post. He recalled a 1958 conversation at
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> in which it had been said that if
                    Berlin goes, there is no certainty what will go next, and that he felt that in
                    that event there would be more than one Foreign Minister on the way to Moscow to
                    negotiate the circumstances of his country’s suicide.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName>
                    had graphically stated the problem. He himself felt that with <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> the three vital interests were not
                    enough and it might be necessary to go into further detail. He said we were all
                    agreed on the importance of these three vital issues: our presence in Berlin,
                    our protection of Berlin’s freedoms, and the right of access, over which we
                    could not accept control or censure, but that he would feel that we should go
                    beyond this and it might be a good idea to draw up a check list.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BH4">Von Brentano</persName> said he was very grateful
                    for the Secretary’s words which had said what he had in mind. He felt it would
                    be dangerous to attempt to stick to the three points since <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> might consider that anything not
                    mentioned would not be considered important.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> said he wished to make
                    two points. He said that for life in Berlin it was very important to have links
                    with the outside <pb facs="0448" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/> world, and especially
                    with Western Germany. The Russians have raised the matter of political activity,
                    but there were, in addition, many other kinds of ties—economic, financial,
                    currency. He recalled that in 1959 in Geneva on the subject of political
                    relations the Western delegations had said that Berlin was not a part of the
                    Federal Republic. He was sure that <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> would mention this point to the Secretary. He pointed
                    out that political activities in West Berlin, in effect, were part of the
                    question of access of West Germans to West Berlin. He felt that the main idea
                    was, therefore, the uncontrolled nature of the air corridor for German traffic.
                    He summarized that the two questions which he felt that <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would logically raise were, (1)
                    political activities, and (2) air access.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said the Ministers should devote a good deal of their time to the
                    consideration of the proposals which might be made to the Russians. He felt they
                    might think about the possibility of telling the Russians that since East Berlin
                    has been made the capital of East Germany, that they did not have any right to
                    go into the question of the ties between West Berlin and the Federal Republic.
                    He said he felt that when we had first said that West Berlin was not part of the
                    Federal Republic, we had, in effect, been reserving our position on all Berlin.
                    He was not suggesting incorporation of West Berlin in the Federal Republic.</p>
                <p>He mentioned that tomorrow the Ministers would also discuss the question of a
                    naval blockade.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
