<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-12-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-12-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="233" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d233">
                        <head>233. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d233fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 762.00/12-1061. Secret; Niact.
                                According to another copy this telegram was drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, who was in Paris attending the
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Ministerial Meeting.
                                (Ibid., Conference Files: Lot 65 D 366, CF 2000)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1961-12-10">December 10, 1961,
                                    midnight</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Secto 2. Eyes only for the President. I had a good talk with Lucius Clay
                            this afternoon and reviewed in considerable detail our policies
                            regarding Berlin and Germany. I pointed out that on the one hand some of
                            his concerns were based on local misunderstandings and on the other that
                            he was performing an invaluable service in reporting such matters to us
                            promptly for possible correction. I emphasized the points you made in
                            our last private conversation and he appeared to take them
                            seriously.</p>
                        <p>He will be in touch with me again this week but I do not believe that he
                            will take any precipitate action which would embarrass the
                            administration. He fully understands that you are carrying the primary
                            load of firmness in Berlin and Germany, as contrasted with the general
                            attitudes of most of our Allies, and that most of the concessions which
                            have resulted in erosion of our position in Berlin were in fact made
                            during the past eight years of a Republican administration. I am certain
                            that he will not act hastily without full opportunity for further
                            consultation.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>