<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>300. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d300</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">300</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-02-19T16:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-02-19T16:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="reckz6KR6qJLArS7N" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade">Naval blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recTNMFmPG15mKxJQ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-02-19T16:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-02-19T16:30:00-05:00" n="300"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d300">
                <head>300. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d300fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 762.00/2-1962. Secret; Eyes
                        Only. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HMJA1">Hillenbrand</persName> and
                        approved by the White House on March 5 and in S on February 23. A summary of
                        this conversation was transmitted to Bonn in telegram 2283, February 19.
                        (Ibid., 611.62A/2-1962) Memoranda of the President’s conversations with
                            <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName> on <persName
                            corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName>’s meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName>, German vested assets, and German
                        purchase of U.N. bonds are in the Kennedy Library, President’s Office Files,
                        France, and Department of State, Presidential Memoranda of Conversation: Lot
                        66 D 149.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1962-02-19T16:30:00-05:00"
                            >February 19, 1962, 4:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Berlin</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName>Schnippenkoetter</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>The President</item>
                            <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HMJA1">Hillenbrand</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName> said he had just returned
                    from twelve days in Bonn and had had the opportunity to see the Chancellor prior
                    to his departure for Washington. The Chancellor had told him to express his
                    gratitude for the information given him by Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> during their recent talk.<note n="2" xml:id="d300fn2"
                        >See <ref target="#d298">Document 298</ref>.</note> The President commented
                    that our reports also indicated that they had a good conversation, but that he
                    was concerned that we did not seem to be able to get our position across
                    clearly. The Chancellor had expressed certain concern about matters which we
                    thought had previously been completely clarified, and there always seemed to be
                    a necessity to provide reassurances. We had been trying to make the points
                    stressed by <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> since last June.
                    Referring to the Chancellor’s remarks about the decline of US prestige, the
                    President said he could not understand what the basis of this observation was.
                    We were carrying the major burden of the struggle against the Communists by
                    providing economic assistance on a major scale throughout the world, and we were
                    making every effort to strengthen both our nuclear and conventional military
                    capacity. Yet there was this constant need to reassure the Germans.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName> observed that he
                    sympathized with the President’s point but there were special circumstances. The
                    President again asked why it was so hard to obtain understanding of our
                    position. The Secretary observed that Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> had gone to Germany without any special instructions.
                    He had covered matters which we took for granted, <pb facs="0855" n="831"
                        xml:id="pg_831"/> and yet the Chancellor had found his remarks reassuring as
                    if they contained new information. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1"
                        >Grewe</persName> said a source of misunderstanding was that the Chancellor
                    was inclined too much to listen to narrow advice from the military, who did not
                    think in terms of the political implications of US strategy within the framework
                    of Berlin contingency plans.</p>
                <p>The President stated that the situation which might develop over Berlin deserved
                    serious thought. We wanted to convince the Soviets, in the event of a major
                    confrontation, that the US was prepared to go all out and that this deserved a
                    last thought on their part. No one expected to fight a conventional war in
                    Europe, which we could not do without being overwhelmed. While the naval
                    blockade favored by the Chancellor had a role to play in the context of Allied
                    contingency plans, by itself it would not suffice and would certainly cause the
                    Soviets to react with military force elsewhere. The President again expressed
                    concern that it seemed necessary to reiterate repeatedly clarifications of US
                    policy and of our strategic position which we thought had been fully explained
                    during the November visit of the Chancellor. We were accordingly concerned that
                    our effort to communicate with the Chancellor in the past had not seemed to make
                    the desired impression.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName> said that the basic
                    agreement reached during the November meetings with the Chancellor in Washington
                    still existed.<note n="3" xml:id="d300fn3">See <ref target="#d216">Documents
                            216</ref>–<ref target="#d219">219</ref>.</note> We had come much closer
                    together in our military concepts than at the time of the August crisis. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>’s explanation of the four-stage
                    approach was close to German thinking.</p>
                <p>The President said we were aware that German estimates of Soviet conventional
                    strength and availabilities in Europe were greater than ours. We have stated
                    that, if we face a major defeat in Europe, then nuclear weapons will be used,
                    but we must exhaust the full battery of other possibilities before pressing the
                    button. The Secretary said he hoped one point at least had been cleared up.
                    Although <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> plans at the time of the
                        <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> visit contemplated a fallback
                    to the Weser-Rhine Line, we were talking in terms of a conventional force which
                    would permit a forward strategy. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1"
                        >Grewe</persName> again referred to the fact that the Chancellor was
                    old-fashioned in his thinking and was influenced too much by the views of the
                    generals. The President observed that 30 divisions was not too much to expect of
                    Europe and the Western countries could afford to raise them. The US took this
                    question quite seriously. We felt our survival was tied up with that of Western
                    Europe. We should all start with this common premise and not have to restate it
                    and to reassure the Chancellor all the time. We will go as far as any and
                    farther than <pb facs="0856" n="832" xml:id="pg_832"/> most in the defense of
                    West Berlin. The Ambassador said he believed that as a result of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> conversation, the Chancellor was now
                    convinced of the military superiority of the US over the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>The President then referred to the Chancellor’s somewhat derogatory remarks about
                    the product of the Ambassadorial Group in Washington, and asked what <persName
                        corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName>’s view was regarding the discussions
                    which had been held in this forum. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1"
                        >Grewe</persName> said he did not feel such remarks should be taken too
                    seriously; the Chancellor generally tended to be disparaging about such
                    activities. The President observed that the Soviets certainly had not given us
                    much reason for hope. He believed that, with the present stalemate in
                    discussions with the Soviets, we were moving into a difficult spring and summer
                    during which <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> might feel
                    impelled to move ahead with his signature of a separate peace treaty. If such a
                    treaty brought with it the consequences which the Soviets had threatened, a
                    confrontation between the Soviets and Western Powers would result. The Secretary
                    asked what the German view was as to the next steps to be taken. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName> said his Government felt that
                    the <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> talks had come close to an impasse, but should be
                    extended as long as possible. His Government did not feel, however, that the
                    substantive scope of talks with the Soviets should be expanded at the present
                    time since they were apparently not prepared to negotiate seriously but merely
                    wanted one-sided Western concessions which they could pocket for the future.</p>
                <p>After reiterating his belief that the Soviets might feel impelled to move ahead
                    with their signature of a separate peace treaty in the spring or summer, the
                    President said that the conversations with the Soviets had been useful in
                    demonstrating their intransigence so far on two critical points: their
                    insistence on the presence of Soviet troops in West Berlin if Western troops
                    were to remain, and their insistence on the termination of the Allied presence
                    in Berlin after a temporary period. Before a confrontation on this issue we
                    wanted to be sure that we had covered the entire range of possibilities with the
                    Soviets and had confirmed their intransigence in other areas as well. Then we
                    could move into a crisis with the assurance that we had done all we reasonably
                    could do, and would thus have greater certainty of the support of our public
                    opinions and of other countries. The President said he did not have particular
                    points in mind about “the range of possibilities”, but he thought all of us
                    should be thinking about them.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName> said he was not so sure
                    that the Soviets would move ahead with their signature of a separate peace
                    treaty. They had taken the position that such a peace treaty would have serious
                    consequences, and these consequences would inevitably lead to a crisis. Bonn was
                    not certain that <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> wanted this.
                    The developments since August 13, particularly the US military build-up, had
                    convinced <pb facs="0857" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> that a dangerous situation was
                    developing. The President observed that the military build-up had done this more
                    than <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName>’s refusal to negotiate,
                    but he felt we must still look forward to a difficult spring and summer for the
                    reasons he had stated.</p>
                <p>In the exchange which followed, the President reiterated his point about the
                    desirability of making sure that we had exhausted all reasonable possibilities
                    with the Soviets before moving into the stage of crisis, while the German
                    Ambassador reaffirmed the German view that talks with the Soviets should
                    continue to be restricted to the narrow front so far observed by <persName
                        corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName> in his talks with <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>.</p>
                <p>In response to the President’s query as to whether there was much pressure in the
                    Federal Republic in the direction of bilateral talks with the Soviets,
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName> said that such pressure
                    did not exist on any significant scale. No major segment of German public
                    opinion supported a bilateral initiative.</p>
                <p>Referring to a talk which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>
                    recently had with the Chancellor,<note n="4" xml:id="d300fn4">Not further
                        identified.</note> the President wondered whether the Bonn view was that
                    West Berlin was essentially a tripartite problem. <persName corresp="#p_GWG1"
                        >Grewe</persName> said this was true only in a formal sense. The Federal
                    Republic obviously had a great substantive interest in Berlin but felt that the
                    basic principle of over-all Four-Power responsibility had to be maintained. The
                    President said he understood this, but that the maintenance of Western rights in
                    Berlin was not essentially a legal problem. It was the threat of force which
                    deterred the Soviets. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName>
                    said the Germans accepted this, and had indicated that they stood together with
                    the three Western Powers in the common cause and were not seeking an escape
                    clause.</p>
                <p>The President again returned to the Chancellor’s emphasis on the role of a naval
                    blockade which had been reported by Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>, and repeated his point that while this obviously had
                    a role to play in Allied contingency planning along with economic
                    countermeasures, it was important that <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> not get the wrong idea that this was all the Allies
                    would do. What was important was the impression given the Soviets.</p>
                <p>After the President had once again mentioned the need to explore all reasonable
                    possibilities, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GWG1">Grewe</persName> said he
                    agreed with the need to explore, but his Government had difficulty in extending
                    the field of exploration to so-called “broader questions”. It knew perfectly
                    well that this meant “European security”, and discussions of this subject would
                    not improve the Western position. Before the Geneva talks start in mid-March,
                    his Government felt the need for a common reassessment of the present situation.
                    It considered it inevitable, if the Soviet Foreign <pb facs="0858" n="834"
                        xml:id="pg_834"/> Minister and the Secretary were in Geneva at the same
                    time, that the subject of Berlin would arise. The President observed that this
                    would be true even if <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> went to
                    Geneva and the Secretary were there. He agreed that there should be a complete
                    exchange of views before the Geneva meetings using the mechanism of the
                    Ambassadorial Group.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
