<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-02-19T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-02-19T13:00:00-05:00" n="301" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d301">
                        <head>301. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Germany</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d301fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 651.62A/2-1962. Secret; Limit Distribution. Received at 4:55
                                p.m.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-02-19T19:00:00+01:00">February
                                    19, 1962, 7 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1951. Because of change in his schedule, Chancellor asked to see me today
                            instead of February 20. Purpose of visit appeared to convey his
                            assurance that <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> had no desire
                            to become involved in direct talks with Soviets. Chancellor said he had
                            had talks with Mende and other <gloss target="#t_FDP1">FDP</gloss>
                            leaders in this sense, pointing out to them his view that Soviets were
                            unlikely to make any concessions to Germans which they were unwilling to
                            make to three Western powers.</p>
                        <p>In response to my query whether he thought Soviets really desired direct
                            talks, he said he doubted they were greatly interested, and again
                            expressed view Soviets had no concessions to make to Germans. When I
                            speculated that one Soviet gambit might be offer to improve lot of East
                            Germans in response to more forthcoming attitude on part of <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>, he said this would be
                            spectacular development, but felt it would be difficult for Soviets to
                            come up with.</p>
                        <p>In response to my query whether he had any thoughts re present course of
                                <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> talks, <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> was somewhat reserved. He
                            remarked that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> had told
                            him at Baden-Baden<note n="2" xml:id="d301fn2"><persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> met at Baden-Baden on
                                February 15.</note> that talks merely proved he (<persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName>) had been right, and there
                            was some slight implication that Chancellor was now inclined to agree.
                            He went on to say, however, that it was important in further
                            conversations to make Soviets aware West was not afraid, and at same
                            time to convey as great a sense of Western unity as was possible.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>