<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>32. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-06-04T04:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-06-04T04:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec5leqjXNtlx0kjy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85096156"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Outer space</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recP1TxBSuFrpDZ2S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Interim agreement</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade relations</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Reparations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-06-04T04:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-06-04T04:15:00-05:00" n="32"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                <head>32. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d32fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Conference Files: Lot 66 D 110, CF 1901.
                        Secret; Eyes Only. Drafted by Akalovsky and approved by the White House on
                        June 23. The meeting was held at the Soviet Embassy. A summary of the
                        conversation was transmitted in Secto 25 from Paris, June 5. (Department of
                        State, Central Files, 751J.00/6-651) For two other accounts of this
                        conversation, apparently based on this memorandum of conversation, see
                            <persName corresp="#p_STC3">Sorensen</persName>, <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName>Kennedy</persName>
                        </hi>, pp. 504-505, and Schlesinger, A Thousand Days, pp. 370-373. The texts
                        of all the memoranda of conversation between <persName>Kennedy</persName>
                        and <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> at Vienna are printed
                        in <ref target="frus1961-63v05">Foreign Relations, 1961–1963, volume
                        V</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Vienna</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1961-06-04T10:15:00+01:00"
                            >June 4, 1961, 10:15 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Meeting Between The President and Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                            >Khrushchev</persName> in Vienna</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">US</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>The President</item>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KFD1"
                                    >Kohler</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>D—Mr. <persName>Akalovsky</persName> (interpreting)</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">USSR</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Dobrynin</persName>, Chief, American Countries
                                Division, USSR Ministry of Foreign Affairs</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MMA4">Menshikov</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Sukhodrev</persName>, Interpreter, USSR Ministry of
                                Foreign Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of Laos and disarmament.]</p>
                <p>Turning to the question of Germany, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> said that he wanted to set forth his position. He
                    said that he understands that this will affect the relations between our two
                    countries to a great extent and even more so if the US were to misunderstand the
                    Soviet position. Conversely, if the US understood the Soviet position correctly
                    our two countries would be brought closer together rather than be divided.
                    Sixteen years have passed since World War II. The USSR lost 20 million people in
                    that War and many of its areas were devastated. Now Germany, the country which
                    unleashed World War II, has again acquired military power and has assumed a
                    predominant position in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Its generals hold
                    high offices in that organization. This constitutes a threat of World War III
                    which would be even more devastating than World War II. The USSR believes that a
                    line should be drawn under World War II. There is no explanation why there is no
                    peace treaty 16 years after the war. This is <pb facs="0112" n="88"
                        xml:id="pg_88"/> why the USSR has suggested that a peace conference be
                    convened. In this connection, the USSR proceeds from the actual state of
                    affairs, namely, that two German States exist. Our own wishes or efforts
                    notwithstanding, a united Germany is not practical because the Germans
                    themselves do not want it. No delay in the matter of signing a peace treaty is
                    justifiable and only West German militarists gain from such a delay. A peace
                    treaty would not prejudice the interests of the US, the UK, or France; on the
                    contrary, these interests would be best served by a peace treaty. The present
                    situation looks as if the US opposes a peace treaty while the USSR wants it. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> said that he wanted the
                    President to understand him correctly. He would like to reach agreement with the
                    President—and he said he wanted to emphasize the words “with you”—on this
                    question. If the US should fail to understand this desire the USSR will sign a
                    peace treaty alone. The USSR will sign a peace treaty with the <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and with the <gloss target="#t_FRG1"
                        >FRG</gloss> if the latter so desires. If not, a peace treaty will be signed
                    with the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> alone. Then the state of war will
                    cease and all commitments stemming from Germany’s surrender will become invalid.
                    This would include all institutions, occupation rights, and access to Berlin,
                    including the corridors. A free city of West Berlin will be established and
                    there will be no blockade or interference in the internal affairs of the city.
                    West Berlin should have a clearly defined status. If the US desires, guarantees
                    could be given to ensure non-interference and the city’s ties with the outside
                    world. If the US wants to leave its troops in West Berlin, that would be
                    acceptable under certain conditions; however, the Soviet Union believes that in
                    that case Soviet troops should be there too. Likewise, the USSR would be
                    agreeable to having neutral troops stationed in Berlin. <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> guarantees would be acceptable as well. The USSR would be
                    prepared to join the US in ensuring all the conditions necessary for preserving
                    what the West calls West Berlin’s freedom. However, if the US rejects this
                    proposal—and the USSR will regard such an action as having been made under the
                    pressure of Adenauer—the USSR will sign a peace treaty unilaterally and all
                    rights of access to Berlin will expire because the state of war will cease to
                    exist.</p>
                <p>The President said that first of all he wanted to express his appreciation of the
                    fact that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> had set forth
                    his views in such a frank manner. At the same time the discussion here is not
                    only about the legal situation but also about the practical facts which affect
                    very much our national security. Here, we are not talking about Laos. This
                    matter is of greatest concern to the US. We are in Berlin not because of
                    someone’s sufferance. We fought our way there, although our casualties may have
                    been not as high as the USSR’s. We are in Berlin not by agreement of East
                    Germans but by contractual rights. This is an area where every President of the
                    US since World War II has been committed by treaty and other contractual rights
                    and where every President has reaffirmed his <pb facs="0113" n="89"
                        xml:id="pg_89"/> faithfulness to his obligations. If we were expelled from
                    that area and if we accepted the loss of our rights no one would have any
                    confidence in US commitments and pledges. US national security is involved in
                    this matter because if we were to accept the Soviet proposal US commitments
                    would be regarded as a mere scrap of paper. West Europe is vital to our national
                    security and we have supported it in two wars. If we were to leave West Berlin
                    Europe would be abandoned as well. So when we are talking about West Berlin we
                    are also talking about West Europe. The President said he would like to see the
                    relations between our two countries develop in a favorable direction so that
                    some arrangement could be found. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> seems to agree that the ratios of power today are
                    equal. Therefore, it is difficult to understand why a country with high
                    achievements in such areas as outer space and economic progress should now
                    suggest that we leave an area where we have vital interests. How can the US
                    agree to East Germany’s preventing it from exercising our rights we had won by
                    war? The United States cannot accept an ultimatum. Our leaving West Berlin would
                    result in the US becoming isolated. The President emphasized that he is not
                    President of the US to preside over isolation of his country just as Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>, as leader of the USSR,
                    would not want to see his own country isolated.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> interjected that he
                    understood this to mean that the President did not want a peace treaty. He said
                    that the President’s statement about US national security should mean that the
                    US might wish to go to Moscow because that too would, of course, improve its
                    position.</p>
                <p>The President replied that the US was not asking to go anywhere; we were not
                    talking about the US going to Moscow or of the USSR going to New York. What we
                    are talking about is that we are in Berlin and have been there for 15 years. We
                    suggest that we stay there.</p>
                <p>The President continued by saying that the US was interested in maintaining its
                    position in Berlin and its rights of access to that city. He said he recognized
                    that the situation there is not a satisfactory one; he also recognized that in
                    the conversations Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> had had
                    with former President Eisenhower the term “abnormal” had been used to describe
                    that situation.<note n="2" xml:id="d32fn2">For documentation on <persName
                            corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>’s discussions of Berlin with
                        President Eisenhower during his visit to the United States in September
                        1959, see <ref target="frus1958-60v09#pg_35">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1958–1960, vol. IX, pp.
                            35</ref> ff.</note> However, because conditions in many areas of the
                    world are not satisfactory today it is not the right time now to change the
                    situation in Berlin and the balance in general. The United States does not wish
                    to effect such a change. The US is not asking the USSR to change its position
                    but it is simply saying that it should not seek to change our position and thus
                    disturb the balance of power. If this balance should <pb facs="0114" n="90"
                        xml:id="pg_90"/> change the situation in West Europe as a whole would change
                    and this would be a most serious blow to the US. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> would not accept similar loss and we cannot accept it
                    either. The question is not that of a peace treaty with East Germany but rather
                    of other aspects of this proposal which would affect our access to Berlin and
                    our rights there.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> said that he was sorry that
                    he had met with no understanding of the Soviet position. The US is unwilling to
                    normalize the situation in the most dangerous spot in the world. The USSR wants
                    to perform an operation on this sore spot—to eliminate this thorn, this
                    ulcer—without prejudicing the interests of any side, but rather to the
                    satisfaction of all peoples of the world. It wants to do that not by intrigue or
                    threat but by solemnly signing a peace treaty. Now the President says that this
                    action is directed against the interests of the US. Such statement is difficult
                    to understand indeed. No change in existing boundaries is proposed; a peace
                    treaty would only formalize them. The USSR wants a peace treaty because such a
                    treaty would impede those people who want a new war. Revanchists in West Germany
                    will find in a peace treaty a barrier impeding their activities. Today they say
                    that boundaries should be changed. But if a peace treaty is signed there will be
                    no ground for revision of the boundaries. Hitler spoke of Germany’s need for
                    Lebensraum to the Urals. Now Hitler’s generals, who had helped him in his
                    designs to execute his plans, are high commanders in <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss>. This logic cannot be understood and the USSR cannot accept
                    it. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> said he was very sorry
                    but he had to assure the President that no force in the world would prevent the
                    USSR from signing a peace treaty. 16 years have passed since World War II and
                    how long should the signing of a peace treaty be delayed? Another 16 years,
                    another 30 years? No further delay is possible or necessary. As far as US losses
                    in the last war are concerned, losses are difficult to measure. Loss of a drop
                    of blood equals the loss of a pint of blood in the minds of those who shed that
                    blood. The US lost thousands and the USSR lost millions, but American mothers
                    mourn their sons just as deeply as Soviet mothers shed tears over the loss of
                    their beloved ones. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> said
                    that he himself had lost a son in the last war; Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> lost two brothers, and <persName corresp="#p_MAI1"
                        >Mikoyan</persName> a son. There is not a single family in the USSR or the
                    leadership of the USSR that did not lose at least one of its members in the war.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> continued by saying that
                    he wanted the US to understand correctly the Soviet position. This position is
                    advanced not for the purpose of kindling passions or increasing tensions. The
                    objective is just the opposite—to remove the obstacles that stand in the way of
                    development of our relations and to normalize relations throughout the world.
                    The USSR will sign a peace treaty and the sovereignty of the GDR will be
                    observed. Any violation of that sovereignty will be regarded by <pb facs="0115"
                        n="91" xml:id="pg_91"/> the USSR as an act of open aggression against a
                    peace loving country, with all the consequences ensuing therefrom.</p>
                <p>The President inquired whether such a peace treaty would block access to Berlin.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> said that it would.</p>
                <p>The President then said that the US is opposed to a buildup in West Germany that
                    would constitute a threat to the Soviet Union. The decision to sign a peace
                    treaty is a serious one and the USSR should consider it in the light of its
                    national interests. Referring to the question of boundaries, the President said
                    that General <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de Gaulle</persName> had made a
                    statement on this question.<note n="3" xml:id="d32fn3">Presumably reference is
                        to a statement on Germany made by <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">de
                            Gaulle</persName> at his first press conference on March 25, 1959, and
                        reiterated at his second on November 10.</note> This problem has been
                    discussed in the Western world and there is some division of opinion on this
                    matter. However, the US is committed to the defense of Western Europe and has
                    assisted Western Europe in the past. The President said that one of his brothers
                    had been killed in the last war, when the US came to Western Europe’s
                    assistance. If the US were driven out of West Berlin by unilateral action, and
                    if we were deprived of our contractual rights by East Germany, then no one would
                    believe the US now or in the future. US commitments would be regarded as a mere
                    scrap of paper. The world situation today is that of change and no one can
                    predict what the evolution will be in such areas as Asia or Africa. Yet what Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> suggests is to bring about
                    a basic change in the situation overnight and deny us our rights which we share
                    with the other two Western countries. This presents us with a most serious
                    challenge and no one can foresee how serious the consequences might be. The
                    President said it had not been his wish to come here to Vienna to find out not
                    only that a peace treaty would be signed but also that we would be denied our
                    position in West Berlin and our access to that city. In fact, the President
                    said, he had come here in the hope that relations between our two countries
                    could be improved. The President stressed he hoped that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> would consider his responsibility
                    toward his country and also consider the responsibility the President of the
                    United States has toward his people. What is discussed here is not only West
                    Berlin; we are talking here about Western Europe and the United States as
                    well.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> replied that he could not
                    understand the President’s reference to Western Europe. The USSR does not wish
                    any change; it merely wants to formalize the situation which has resulted from
                    World War II. The fact is that West Germany is in the Western group of nations
                    and the USSR recognizes this. East Germany is an ally of the socialist countries
                    and this should be recognized as a fait accompli. East Germany has new
                    demarcation lines and these lines should <pb facs="0116" n="92" xml:id="pg_92"/>
                    become borders. The Polish and Czech borders should be formalized. The position
                    of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> should be normalized and her
                    sovereignty ensured. To do all this it is necessary to eliminate the occupation
                    rights in West Berlin. No such rights should exist there. It would be impossible
                    to imagine a situation where the USSR would have signed a peace treaty with the
                    US retaining occupation rights, which are based on the state of war. The US may
                    say that its blood was shed, but the USSR shed blood too and not water.</p>
                <p>The President interjected that our rights were based on a four-power agreement.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> replied that this was so
                    in the absence of a peace treaty, but said that a peace treaty would end the
                    state of war and those rights would therefore expire.</p>
                <p>The President said this meant unilateral abrogation of the four-power agreement
                    by the USSR and emphasized that the US could not accept such an act. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> replied that this was not
                    so because the USSR would invite the US to sign a peace treaty and would sign it
                    alone only if the US should refuse to do so. In that event the US could not
                    maintain its rights on the territory of the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>.
                    The President again referred to the four-power agreement, but Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> replied that the USSR considered all
                    of Berlin to be <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> territory. The President
                    stated this may be Soviet view but not ours. If the USSR transfers its rights,
                    that is a matter for its own decision; however, it is an altogether different
                    matter for the USSR to give [away?] our rights which we have on contractual
                    basis. He said that the USSR could not break the agreement and give US rights to
                    the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> rejoined by saying that this was a familiar point of
                    view but had no juridical foundation, since the war had ended 16 years ago. In
                    fact, President Roosevelt indicated that troops could be withdrawn after two or
                    two and a half years.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> continued by saying that
                    all the USSR wants is a peace treaty. He could not understand why the US wants
                    Berlin. Does the US want to unleash a war from there? The President as a naval
                    officer and he himself, a civilian although he participated in two wars, know
                    very well that Berlin has no military significance. The President speaks of
                    rights, but what are those rights? They stem from war. If the state of war ends,
                    the rights end too. If a peace treaty is signed US prestige will not be
                    involved, and everybody will understand this. But if the US should maintain its
                    rights after the signing of a peace treaty, that would be a violation of East
                    Germany’s sovereignty and of the sovereignty of the socialist camp as a whole.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> recalled that President
                    Eisenhower had agreed that the situation in Germany was abnormal. Eisenhower had
                    said that US prestige was involved. Then the possibility of an interim agreement
                    was discussed, an arrangement that would not involve the prestige of our two
                    countries. Perhaps this could serve as a basis for agreement. The USSR is
                    prepared to accept such an <pb facs="0117" n="93" xml:id="pg_93"/> arrangement
                    even now. Adenauer says that he wants unification but this is not so. As far as
                    unification in concerned, we should say that the two German governments should
                    meet and decide the question of reunification. A time limit of say 6 months
                    should be set and if there is no agreement we can disavow our responsibilities
                    and then anyone would be free to conclude a peace treaty. This would be a way
                    out and it would resolve this question of prestige, which, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> said, he did not really understand.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> said that he had hoped
                    that Eisenhower would agree subsequently at the Summit, but the forces which are
                    against improvement of relations between the US and USSR sent the U-2 plane and
                    the USSR decided that in view of the tensions prevailing as a result of that
                    flight this question should not be raised. However, the USSR believes that time
                    for such action is ripe now. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> expressed regret on his own behalf and on behalf of
                    his colleagues and allies at not having found understanding on the President’s
                    part of the Soviet Union’s good intentions and motivations. If only the German
                    question were resolved the road would be clear for the development of our mutual
                    relations. The USSR does not want to infringe upon any-body’s interests, but
                    neither would it concede its own interests. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> said he believed that the US does not want
                    territorial gains although there is ideological disagreement between the US and
                    the USSR. However, ideological disagreements should not be transferred onto the
                    plane of a devastating war. He said that he was confident that people would be
                    reasonable enough not to act like crusaders in the Middle Ages and would not
                    start cutting each other’s throats for ideological reasons. If the United States
                    disagrees with the Soviet proposal it should at least understand the Soviet
                    position. The USSR can no longer delay. It will probably sign a peace treaty at
                    the end of the year, with all the ensuing consequences, i.e., all obligations
                    will come to an end. The status of West Berlin as a free city will be guaranteed
                    and complete non-interference will be ensured. West Berlin will be accessible to
                    all countries with which it will want to maintain ties. However, access will be
                    subject to <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>’s control, since communication
                    lines go through its territory. If the US is concerned about what it calls
                    freedom of West Berlin, let us develop guarantees jointly or invite the UN. No
                    nation will understand the US position of perpetuating the state of war with
                    Germany. The USSR will explain its position to the world. It wants to prevent
                    the possibility of war. If the US refuses to sign a peace treaty, the USSR will
                    have no way out other than to sign such a treaty alone. The USSR lost 20 million
                    people in the last war while the US lost 350 thousand.</p>
                <p>The President interjected that this was why the US wanted to prevent another
                    war.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> continued by saying that if
                    the US should start a war over Berlin there was nothing the USSR could do about
                    it. However, <pb facs="0118" n="94" xml:id="pg_94"/> it would have to be the US
                    to start the war, while the USSR will be defending peace. History will be the
                    judge of our actions. The West has been saying that <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> might miscalculate. But ours is a joint account and
                    each of us must see that there is no miscalculation. If the US wants to start a
                    war over Germany let it be so; perhaps the USSR should sign a peace treaty right
                    away and get over with it. This is what the Pentagon has been wanting. However,
                        <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_MHS2">Macmillan</persName> know very well what war means. If
                    there is any madman who wants war, he should be put in a straight jacket.
                    Nations close to USSR territory know what war will mean for them. The USSR
                    thinks of peace, of friendship, and it is happy with its trade relations with
                    West Germany, France, Great Britain and Italy. It is not by accident that trade
                    between the US and the USSR is still frozen but that is a problem for the US. So
                    this is the Soviet position. The USSR will sign a peace treaty at the end of
                    this year. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> concluded by
                    saying that he was confident that common sense would win and peace will
                    prevail.</p>
                <p>The President said he recognized that the situation in Germany was abnormal.
                    Germany is divided today. When President Roosevelt talked about the withdrawal
                    of troops he was not able to foresee this situation or the fact that our two
                    countries would be on different sides. The US does not want to precipitate a
                    crisis; it is Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> who wants to
                    do so by seeking a change in the existing situation. The President then said the
                    US was committed to this area long before he had assumed a position of high
                    government responsibility. Now Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> suggests a peace treaty at the end of the year, which
                    would deny our rights in that city and our rights of access. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> knows very well that Berlin is much
                    more than a city and yet he makes such a suggestion. Is that a way to secure
                    peace?</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> replied he did not
                    understand how the signing of a peace treaty could worsen the world situation.
                    Peace is always regarded as something beneficial while the state of war is
                    regarded as something evil.</p>
                <p>The President said that the signing of a peace treaty is not a belligerent act.
                    He had not indicated this at all. However, a peace treaty denying us our
                    contractual rights is a belligerent act. The matter of a peace treaty with East
                    Germany is a matter for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>’s
                    judgment and is not a belligerent act. What is a belligerent act is transfer of
                    our rights to East Germany. West Berlin is not important as a springboard.
                    However, the US is committed to that area and it is so regarded by all the
                    world. If we accepted Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>’s
                    suggestion the world would lose confidence in the US and would not regard it as
                    a serious country. It is an important strategic matter that the world believe
                    the US is a serious country.</p>
                <pb facs="0119" n="95" xml:id="pg_95"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> wondered what he should do
                    in these circumstances. He said he believed that US intentions led to nothing
                    good. The USSR would never, under any conditions, accept US rights in West
                    Berlin after a peace treaty had been signed. He said he was absolutely convinced
                    that the peoples of the world would understand such a position. Moreover, the US
                    had deprived the USSR unilaterally of its rights and interests in West Germany,
                    it had deprived the USSR of reparations in West Germany, and it had signed a
                    unilateral peace treaty with Japan. As a result of this latter action the Soviet
                    Union still has no peace treaty with Japan.</p>
                <p>The President interjected that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2"
                        >Khrushchev</persName> had said to President Eisenhower that he would have
                    signed the treaty. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>
                    confirmed this, while Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said
                    that the fact remained that the US had signed the Japanese peace treaty without
                    the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> went on to say that the US
                    regarded all this as appropriate, but now it says what the USSR wants to do is
                    immoral. The USSR would like to do it together with the US, but if the US
                    refuses to sign a peace treaty the USSR will do it alone. East Germany will
                    obtain complete sovereignty and all obligations resulting from German surrender
                    will be annulled. The factor of the USSR’s prestige should be taken into
                    account. What the US wants is to retain the rights gained after World War II
                    even after a peace treaty has been signed. This is a policy of “I do what I
                    want”. The USSR regards East Germany as a completely sovereign state and it will
                    sign a peace treaty with it. Responsibility for violation of that sovereignty
                    will be heavy.</p>
                <p>The President said that there is every evidence that our position in Berlin is
                    strongly supported by the people there, and we are committed to that area. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> says that we are for a
                    state of war. This is incorrect. It would be well if relations between East
                    Germany and West Germany improved and if the development of US-USSR relations
                    were such as to permit solution of the whole German problem. During his stay in
                    office, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> has seen many
                    changes, and changes will go on. But now he wants a peace treaty in six months,
                    an action which would drive us out of Berlin. If we accepted such a proposition
                    we would lose our ties in West Europe and would lose all our friends there. We
                    do not wish to act in a way that would deprive the Soviet Union of its ties in
                    Eastern Europe. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> had said
                    that the President was a young man, but, the President continued, he had not
                    assumed office to accept arrangements totally inimical to US interests. The
                    President said he was prepared to discuss any problem but Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> should take into account our
                    interests just as he says we should take into account his views.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> said that then an interim
                    agreement should be concluded. However, no matter how long a time limit such an
                    agreement <pb facs="0120" n="96" xml:id="pg_96"/> were to provide for, the
                    Germans would not agree because no one wishes reunification. An interim
                    agreement would be a formal factor, it would give the semblance of the
                    responsibility for the problem having been turned over to the Germans
                    themselves. If the US does not wish such an arrangement there is no other way
                    but to sign a peace treaty unilaterally. No one can force the US to sign a peace
                    treaty but neither can the US make the Soviet Union accept its claims. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> then said that an
                    aide-mémoire on the Berlin question had been prepared so that the US could study
                    the Soviet position and perhaps return to this question at a later date, if it
                    wished to do so.<note n="4" xml:id="d32fn4">The Soviet translation of its
                        aide-mémoire was transmitted in Secto 21 from Paris, June 5. (Department of
                        State, Central Files, 762.00/6-561) For the Department of State translation,
                        which is basically the same, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on
                        Germany</hi>, 1944-1985, pp. 729-732. For the Russian text, see <hi
                            rend="italic">Pravda</hi>, June 11, 1961.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The group then moved to the dining room for lunch.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
