<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>93. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v14</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-01-09T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-03-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-03-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-09T11:00:00-05:00" n="93" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d93">
                <head>93. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On July 27, 1961, a U.S. Delegation, led by Assistant Secretary of State
                        <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> and including Legal Adviser
                        <persName corresp="#p_CAJ1">Chayes</persName>, Director of the Office of
                    German Affairs Hillenbrand, Under Secretary of the Treasury <persName
                        corresp="#p_FHH1">Fowler</persName>, and Assistant Secretary of Defense
                        <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>, flew to Paris for a week of
                    meetings with representatives of France, the United Kingdom, and the Federal
                    Republic of Germany to lay the groundwork for the Foreign Ministers meeting
                    beginning August 5. At its first meeting this Four-Power Working Group agreed on
                    the following order of business: 1) Political problems; 2) Politico-military
                    problems; 3) Economic phases of contingency planning; and 4) Information
                    program.</p>
                <p>The U.S. memorandum on Berlin, which was distributed to the other Western powers
                    on July 21 (see Document 79), served as the basis for discussion.</p>
                <p>By August 2 the Working Group had drafted a report on Soviet motives and
                    intentions; reached general agreement, although the French and Germans had
                    doubts, that negotiations with the Soviet Union <pb facs="0292" n="268"
                        xml:id="pg_268"/> should be opened before it signed a peace treaty with the
                    German Democratic Republic; and discussed the forum, scope, and substance of the
                    negotiations. Discussion of politico-military problems revealed that the other
                    Western powers had reservations about a large-scale ground probe, while talks on
                    the economic aspects of contingency planning reached a consensus on a total
                    embargo of the Soviet bloc in the event of a “substantial” blockage of access to
                    Berlin. (Memorandum for the Secretary, August 2; Department of State, Central
                    Files, 762.00/8-261)</p>
                <p>In commenting on the early meetings of the Working Group, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName> told the President that the U.S.
                    Delegation “was even less ready to think of new positions than the <persName
                        corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_MGGC2"
                        >McGhee</persName> papers recommend,” and suggested that the President talk
                    to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> about this rigidity.
                    (Memorandum attached to telegram 588 from Paris, August 2;
                        <persName>Kennedy</persName> Library, President’s Office Files, Germany)</p>
                <p>On August 4 the Working Group completed its discussions and submitted its report
                    to the four Western governments. Entitled “Report of the Four-Power Working
                    Group on Germany and Berlin, Paris, July 28-August 4, 1961,” it consisted of six
                    sections: I) Soviet Motives and Intentions, II) Tactics, III) Substantial
                    Political Questions, IV) Strengthening of the Forces of the Alliance, V)
                    Recommended Minute on Economic Countermeasures, and VI) Review of Berlin
                    Contingency Plans. A copy of the report, with 10 attached U.S. papers on various
                    aspects of the Berlin problem (MCB Memo 3(I)), August 4, is in Department of
                    State, Conference Files: Lot 65 D 366, CF 1945. <persName corresp="#p_KFD1"
                        >Kohler</persName>’s telegrams summarizing the activities of the Working
                    Group are ibid., Central Files, 762.00/7-2861 through 762.00/8-461. For
                        <persName corresp="#p_CAJ1">Chayes</persName>’ recollections of the
                    meetings, see his oral history interview at the <persName>Kennedy</persName>
                    Library.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
