<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 144.Mr. Seward to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1880</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d144</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">144</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1880-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1880-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recItilmdY8wKocmo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005329"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Conservation</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="144"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d144">
                <head>No. 144.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Seward</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-01-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 16, 1880</date>. (Received March
                        15.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 563.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>:Recurring to my various letters in regard to the
                    Shanghai harbor rules, and more particularly to my dispatch No. 544, with which
                    I sent to you a copy of a code of sixteen rules for that part of the harbor
                    which is above the foreign anchorage, I have now the honor to hand to you a note
                    which Prince Kung has addressed to the several foreign representatives, stating
                    that the rules of 1878 will be put in operation at once for the district
                    opposite the foreign settlements (the foreign anchorage) and the new rules for
                    the district above the settlements (the native anchorage).</p>
                <p>This adjustment of the matter appears to me entirely satisfactory, and I have no
                    doubt that it will meet the views of other members of the diplomatic body.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>In the matter of the control of harbors our troubles arise, not because the
                    authorities endanger our interests by discriminations in favor of their own
                    people, nor by cutting off privileges necessary for the free use of their
                    harbors, but because no adequate measures have been adopted for their
                    conservancy. At Shanghai any one owning a front lot has been able to make a pier
                    or wharf or to fill up the foreshore almost uncontrolled. The serious
                    deterioration of the harbor has resulted as a matter of course.</p>
                <p>It has been my object, in view of such facts, to impress upon the administration,
                    both at Shanghai and here, the fact that it is their interests which are mainly
                    involved, and that responsibility for the care of the harbor devolves properly
                    upon them.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I shall request the consul general to give the local authorities cordial support
                    in the administration of the harbor rules, new and old, so soon as I learn that
                    my colleagues will take the same course.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEOEGE F. SEWAED.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 563.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Prince <persName type="from">Kung</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Seward</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Prince Kung, chief secretary of state for foreign affairs, herewith makes a
                        communication.</p>
                    <p>In the matter of the rules for the conservation of the harbor at Shanghai,
                        Mr. Holcombe, secretary of the legation of the United States, came to this
                        office December 7, 1879, to inquire of the ministers whether they had
                        anything to propose regarding the enforcement of the rules adopted in
                        January, 1878, or anything to suggest which they might desire to communicate
                        to the diplomatic body, &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>The ministers handed to Mr. Holcombe a draft of sixteen new rules which
                        provide for the conservancy of the Upper Whangpoo River, above the foreign
                        concessions, and place this part of the river under the jurisdiction of a
                        harbor office and a deputy, requesting Mr. Holcombe to communicate them to
                        the diplomatic body for its information.</p>
                    <p>I beg leave now to remark that the Whangpoo is a river under the sovereignty
                        of China. Lying beside the foreign concessions, it must still be held to be
                        outside of those concessions. In reference to section II of the rules
                        adopted in January, 1878, which stipulates that “the authority and control
                        of the harbor master, as hereinafter denned, extend to that part of the
                        river opposite to the city, the suburbs, and the foreign settlements, and to
                        that part of Loochow Creek between the settlements, &amp;c.,” <pb
                            facs="0313" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> it would appear that the provision
                        of the sixteen new rules which places the Whangpoo River above the foreign
                        concessions under the control of a deputy and a harbor office is a
                        modification for the better.</p>
                    <p>With this exception, the necessary instructions will be given by me to put
                        into operation all the stipulations of the rules of January, 1878.</p>
                    <p>Although the harbor deputy and the harbor master have separate areas of
                        jurisdiction, they will still consult together and act in concert as
                        occasion may require.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">I have reached a decision in this business as indicated
                            above. But as these matters affect the interests of both Chinese and
                            foreign merchants and people, I have thought it my duty to furnish your
                            excellency with a copy of the sixteen rules for your information</hi>,
                        and request the favor of a response.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>Peking</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1880-01-12">January 12, 1880</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">George F. Seward</hi>, &amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
