<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-01-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="260" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d260">
                    <head>No. 260.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">White</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-01-23"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 23, 1880</date>.
                            (Received February 11.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 82.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The project of a law laid yesterday before the
                        Bundesrath (Federal Council) of the empire indicates that this government
                        has decided to go still further in the military development of the
                        nation.</p>
                    <p>Under this proposal, which will doubtless become a law, there will be added
                        to the German army from the 1st of April next, of—</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Infantry</hi>, eleven new regiments (eight Prussian, one
                        Bavarian, two Saxon), and one additional battalion will be added to the
                        regiment of the Grand Duchy of Hesse;</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Field artillery</hi>, one regiment (Prussian) of eight
                        batteries, and thirty-two batteries (twenty-four Prussian, four Bavarian,
                        two Saxon, two Würtemberg) which will be added to the regiments already
                        existing;</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Lighter artillery</hi>, one regiment (Prussian);</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Pioneers</hi>, one regiment (Prussian).</p>
                    <p>The German army will thus be strengthened by about 30,000 men and 300 guns;
                        and the number of men under arms during peace will, in future, be about
                        427,270.</p>
                    <p>An especially noteworthy feature in the proposal is one under which all men
                        who were exempted from military service and enrolled in the reserve shall be
                        drilled a total number of twenty weeks at four different periods. Thus a
                        large number of men hitherto undrilled will be instructed and prepared to
                        enter actual service in time of need.</p>
                    <p>The project makes an estimate of the cost of these additions and changes as
                        follows: Immediate outlay, 26,713,166 marks; and the yearly outlay for their
                        maintenance, 17,116,242 marks.</p>
                    <p>It is evident from this step on the part of the Imperial Government that all
                        hopes of the slightest diminution of the enormous European standing armies
                        must be given up for some years to come, and that Count von Moltke’s famous
                        remark, to the effect that for the next fifty years Germany must make
                        constant exertions to consolidate her power and maintain her recent
                        acquisitions, embodies a truth which all other nations have to bear in
                        mind.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>AND. D. WHITE.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>