<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 299.Mr. Hoppin to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1880</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d299</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">299</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1879-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1879-10-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-10-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="299"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d299">
                <head>No. 299.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hoppin</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-10-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 29, 1879</date>. (Received November
                        11.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 89.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my dispatch No. 66, of the 8th
                    instant, in relation to Mormon emigration to the United States, I have the honor
                    to acquaint <pb facs="0566" n="466" xml:id="pg_466"/> you that I have received
                    communications on this subject from the consulate general of the United States
                    and from the consuls at Bradford and Liverpool and the commercial agent at
                    Nottingham. The only information of importance in these letters is that given by
                    Mr. Smith of Nottingham and Mr. Packard of Liverpool, copies of whose letters I
                    herewith inclose.</p>
                <p>Immediately upon the receipt of Mr. Packard’s communication, I addressed a letter
                    to Lord Salisbury informing him of the contemplated departure of a party of
                    Mormons on the 18th instant, from Liverpool. I have had no reply to this until
                    this morning, when I received a note from his lordship, stating the action which
                    was taken by the home secretary in relation to this matter, and inclosing a
                    notice signed by Sir E. Y. W. Henderson, the commissioner of metropolitan
                    police, I herewith transmit copies of all these papers.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>W. J. HOPPIN.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 89.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Smith</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hoppin</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Commercial Agency</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Nottingham</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-09-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi>, 16, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: A few days ago I received a circular from the
                        Secretary of State at Washington, on the subject of Mormon emigration to the
                        United States, with instructions to report to the legation at London any
                        facts in relation to that subject which might come to my notice. In
                        compliance with that instruction, I have the honor to report that there has
                        been for some years past a Mormon congregation in this place. Mr. William
                        Bramall is the head elder of the Nottingham branch, which numbers about 200
                        members. Their meeting place is in the assembly room, Low Pavement. Services
                        are held on Sundays at 2.30 and 6 p.m., and on Wednesday at 8 p.m.</p>
                    <p>Money is sent from Utah to the Mormon emigration office at Islington,
                        Liverpool, for the benefit of the poor who have not the means to pay their
                        passage. Each person who receives money from this fund is expected to repay
                        it in work when settled in Utah. No money has been sent to the Nottingham
                        branch this year. Each emigrant who has the means with which to pay his
                        passage, is required to pay the necessary amount to the elder of the
                        district. The names of the emigrants, with the money paid, are sent to the
                        office at Liverpool, and when all is complete, and the number of emigrants
                        is known, a contract is made to take them to New York.</p>
                    <p>When landed they are taken in charge by the elder and forwarded by rail to
                        their destination. Emigration commences in May and ends in October. Three or
                        four parties usually go out each year. The last party for this year is
                        expected to leave Liverpool on the 18th of October. It is expected that a
                        company of from 200 to 300 will leave Liverpool at that time, composed of
                        English, Germans, Scandinavians, and others.</p>
                    <p>The above are all the facts I have been able to collect with regard to the
                        Mormons in this town.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JASPER SMITH,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Commercial Agent.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 89.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Packard</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hoppin</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate United States of America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liverpool</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-10-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 15, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In compliance with a circular from the State
                        Department dated August 26, 1879, which instructs me to report to the
                        legation without loss of time any facts relative to the emigration of
                        Mormons to the United States, I have the honor to inform you that a large
                        number, probably about 70 persons, known as Mormons, have engaged <pb
                            facs="0567" n="467" xml:id="pg_467"/> passage and are expected to
                        emigrate from this port on Saturday next, the 18th instant, destined for the
                        Territory of Utah, in the steamship Arizona of the Guion line of steamers
                        bonnd for New York.</p>
                    <p>Also, in compliance to Department instruction, I have called the attention of
                        his worship the mayor of the borough of Liverpool to the proposed departure
                        of Mormon emigrants. A copy of my letter to him is inclosed.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>S. B. PACKARD, <hi rend="italic">Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in Mr. Packard’s letter.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Packard</persName> to the <gloss
                                type="to">Mayor of Liverpool</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate United States of America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Liverpool</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-10-15">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 15, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that the
                        United States Government has communicated to its diplomatic representative
                        in Great Britain a circular letter, dated at the State Department August 9,
                        1879, on the subject of Mormon emigration (a printed copy attached) and,
                        under date of August 26, the State Department, in a communication to this
                        consulate, instructs me with reference to the departure of Mormon emigrants,
                        and adds: “discreet and opportune suggestions on your part to the local
                        authorities concerning such movements would doubtless aid the general
                        representations which the legation is instructed to make.”</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to state that I am credibly informed that a large number,
                        say seventy persons, Mormons, intend to sail per steamship Arizona next
                        Saturday, October 18, destined for the Territory of Utah, there to join a
                        Mormon community at Salt Lake, Utah, with intent there to violate the laws
                        of the United States.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>S. B. PACKARD, <hi rend="italic">Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His worship the <hi rend="smallcaps">Mayor</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">for the Borough of Liverpool.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 89.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hoppin</persName> to the <gloss
                                type="to">Marquis of Salisbury</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-10-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 16, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        receipt of your note of the 6th instant in reply to mine of the 25th of
                        August upon the subject of Mormon emigration from this country to the United
                        States, and to state that I did not fail to transmit a copy of it by the
                        earliest opportunity to Mr. Evarts.</p>
                    <p>Referring to your lordship’s statement that Mr. Cross will cause a notice to
                        be inserted in the newspapers cautioning persons against being deceived by
                        Mormon emissaries, and making generally known the law of the United States
                        affecting polygamy, and the penalties attaching to infringements thereof, I
                        have the honor to acquaint your lordship that I have received to-day a
                        letter from S. B. Packard, esq., the consul of the United States at
                        Liverpool, informing me that a large number, probably about seventy persons,
                        known as Mormons have engaged passage and are expected to emigrate from that
                        port on Saturday next, the 18th instant, destined for the Territory of Utah,
                        in the steamship Arizona, of the Guion line of steamers, bound for New
                        York.</p>
                    <p>I have to add that the consul also informs me that he sent yesterday a
                        written communication to his worship the mayor of the borough of Liverpool,
                        calling his attention to the proposed departure of these people with intent
                        to violate the laws of the United States in the Territory of Utah.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. J. HOPPIN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 89.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Marquis of Salisbury</gloss> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hoppin</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-10-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 29, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acquaint you, with
                        reference to my note of the 6th instant, on the subject of the Mormon
                        emigration from this Country to the United States, that <pb facs="0568"
                            n="468" xml:id="pg_468"/> I have been informed by Her Majesty’s
                        secretary of state for the home department that a notice, * * * was about to
                        be inserted in the newspapers, with a view to check the emigration of
                        persons from this country for the purpose of joining the Mormon community in
                        the United States.</p>
                    <p>I have further the honor to acquaint you that I have been informed by Her
                        Majesty’s secretary of state for the home department, to whom I referred a
                        copy of your note of the 16th instant, calling attention to the intention of
                        certain persons to leave this country on the 18th instant with a view, as it
                        would appear, to join the Mormon community in the United States, that a
                        communication was at once addressed to the mayor of Liverpool, requesting
                        that steps might be taken to publish at that port a notice similar to the
                        one to be published in London, warning persons desirous of joining the
                        Mormon community of the illegal nature of the practice of polygamy existing
                        at Salt Lake City.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>SALISBURY.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
