<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 328.Sir Edward Thornton to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1880</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d328</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">328</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1879-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1879-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1879-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1879-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="328"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d328">
                <head>No. 328.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Edward Thornton</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1879-12-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 13, 1879</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Her Majesty’s Government has been informed that
                    the Austro-Hungarian Government has received a communication from the minister
                    of the United States stating that the Government of Nicaragua has begged that
                    certain documents in the archives of the United States relating to the question
                    in dispute between Nicaragua and Great Britain should be laid before the
                    arbitrator, but that the Government of the United States does not consider
                    itself justified in handing over these documents merely on the request of one
                    party, but is ready, in case the arbitrator think the requests of the Government
                    of Nicaragua justifiable, to examine at once what documents would have to be
                    sent over for the purpose proposed.</p>
                <p>The Marquis of Salisbury has instructed me to express to you the <pb facs="0603"
                        n="503" xml:id="pg_503"/> sense entertained by Her Majesty’s Government of
                    the friendly conduct of your government in this matter.</p>
                <p>His lordship has conveyed to the Austro-Hungarian Government his opinion that any
                    application of the Government of Nicaragua to that of the United States for
                    papers which the former may think will be of use to it in the arbitration, is a
                    matter entirely between those two governments, and does not affect in any way
                    either the arbitrator or Her Majesty’s Government, although the course taken by
                    the Governments of the United States and of Austria-Hungary has been dictated by
                    friendly intentions as regards Her Majesty’s Government.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>EDW’D THORNTON.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
