<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-04-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="468" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d468">
                    <head>No. 468.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Weill</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-04-02"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 2, 1880</date>.
                            (Received April 19.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 5.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 16th ultimo information reached this
                        legation to the effect that three Americans had been murdered at or near
                        Anganqueo, a mining town in the State of Michoacan, and within a few minutes
                        thereafter a telegram was placed in my hands which confirmed the above
                        report.</p>
                    <p>Without waiting for further information than that contained in the said
                        telegram, which was sent by a prudent and reliable person, I addressed a
                        note, of which I inclose a copy, to the secretary of foreign affairs,
                        transcribing the telegram, and stating that I felt assured the Mexican
                        Government would act in the premises with due energy. The day following I
                        received a note from the department of foreign affairs, of which a
                        translation is herewith transmitted, inclosing copies of telegrams exchanged
                        between the federal authorities in this city and the federal and local
                        authorities in the State of Michoacan in relation to the occurrence at
                        Anganqueo, the secretary stating that the government expected further
                        details. Subsequently I have received a communication from Messrs. Stephens
                        and Fagan, the only survivors of the Americans engaged in mining at
                        Anganqueo, and a statement of the whole occurrence by Mr. Arthur Kitchener,
                        the director of the Trojes Mining Company for which the Americans were
                        boring a tunnel. I inclose copies of these communications. Mr. Kitchener’s
                        statement is accompanied by legal documents proving the fact of the death of
                        John Connolly, Henry Toumans, and George Arnold, all three, it is asserted,
                        being natives of the State of New York.</p>
                    <p>As will be seen by the documents furnished by the department of foreign
                        affairs, the government acted with all possible promptness, although, so far
                        as I am informed, the only arrests made up to the present time are the two
                        referred to by Mr. Kitchener.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>EDWARD M. NEILL.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 5.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Neill</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Ruelas</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-03-16"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 16,
                                1880</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It is my painful duty to inform your
                            excellency that a telegram has been received in this city announcing the
                            murder at or near the Trojes Mines, Anganqueo, Michoacan, of three
                            American citizens. The telegram referred to is as follows:</p>
                        <p>“Three of our Americans killed. Great disturbance. Troops on the road to
                            our assistance. Communicate to consul. Particulars to-morrow.”</p>
                        <pb facs="0840" n="740" xml:id="pg_740"/>
                        <p>I make this communication to your excellency, fully assured that such
                            prompt and energetic measures will be taken by your government as the
                            circumstances of the case may require.</p>
                        <p>I embrace, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>EDWARD M. NEILL.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                            5.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Ruelas</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Neill</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-03-17"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 17,
                                1880</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I had the honor to receive your honor’s
                            note of yesterday, in which you are pleased to transcribe a telegram
                            from Anganqueo, State of Michoacan, in which is announced the murder of
                            three American citizens, and you ask that the government dictate such
                            prompt and energetic measures as the circumstances of the case
                            require.</p>
                        <p>Even before receiving your honor’s note, immediately upon receipt of
                            intelligence of that unfortunate event, the President had earnestly
                            recommended, through this department of government, the governor of that
                            State to take, with the greatest activity, all the measures within his
                            power to discover the culprits, for the purpose of inflicting upon them
                            prompt and exemplary punishment, as your honor may see by the inclosed
                            copy, numbered 1.</p>
                        <p>According to Nos. 2 and 3, which I also inclose, it appears that the
                            tumult was caused by several Americans having killed a Mexican
                            operative. The goverement expects soon to receive an exact statement of
                            the occurrence at Anganqueo.</p>
                        <p>Upon replying with the foregoing to your honor’s note, I improve,
                            &amp;c.</p>
                        <closer><signed>M. RUELAS.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <p rend="center">(Copy, No. 1.)</p>
                        <p>The governor of the State of Michoacan, in a telegram of yesterday,
                            says:</p>
                        <p>“The prefect of Zitácuaro says to me: ‘Yesterday there was a tumult
                            between the operatives and the Americans of the mining district of
                            Anganqueo. Of the former two were killed and one wounded; and of the
                            latter, three were killed; a house was hurt.’ The prefect is already <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to that point with a force. I take
                            measures. I will communicate details when they are received.</p>
                        <p>“In the same manner I replied to said governor the following: ‘Your
                            telegram of yesterday, relating to a tumult, which occurred on the 13th
                            in Zitacuaro, between operatives and Americans of the mining district of
                            Anganqueo, has been received. By direction of the President, I recommend
                            you to be pleased to dictate with the greatest activity the measures
                            which you may deem necessary in order to discover the persons
                            responsible for such a serious crime, consigning them to the proper
                            authorities, with a special recommendation to hasten the proceedings so
                            as to secure prompt and exemplary punishment.’ And I have the honor to
                            transcribe it to you for your information.”</p>
                        <p>Liberty in the Constitution.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-03-16">March 16,
                                1880</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>BERRIÓZABAL.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>To the <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of Foreign Affairs.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <p rend="center">(Copy, No. 2.)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexican Republic, Department of War and Marine,
                                Section</hi> 1.</p>
                        <p>General Abraham Plata telegraphs me the following from Morella:</p>
                        <p>“To-day, the colonel of the second corps of auxiliaries communicated to
                            me from Maravatio the following: ‘Captain Ocanas reports from Zitácuaro
                            a mutiny in Anganqueo. There were five persons killed, I have ordered
                            forces to that point. I go with 50 cavalry.’</p>
                        <p>“I asked information and the major of the same corps replied to me with
                            the following: ‘The colonel has marched with 55 men. The detachment from
                            Zitácuaro has marched. A. servant of the house of Murga, who left
                            Anganqueo this morning, reports that the miners mutinied against the
                            company on account of the killing of an operative, <pb facs="0841" n="741" xml:id="pg_741"/> and burnt a house, and that four
                            foreigners were killed. Nothing unusual on this line.’”</p>
                        <p>And I transcribe it to you for your information.</p>
                        <p>Liberty in the Constitution.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-03-16">March 16,
                                1880</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>MONTESINOS.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>To the <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of Foreign Affairs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Present.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <p rend="center">(Copy, No. 3.)</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexican Republic, Department of War and Marine,
                                Section</hi> 1.</p>
                        <p>General Abraham Plata reports to this department to-day, by telegraph,
                            the following: “In a telegram, which I received last night, the colonel
                            of the second corps of auxiliaries reports to me the following from
                            Anganqueo: ‘Order restored; tumult between operatives and American
                            company, the result being three Americans and five operatives killed. I
                            will give you a detailed report by mail. I await your orders.”</p>
                        <p>“I directed said officer to remain at that point until further
                            orders.”</p>
                        <p>And I inclose it to you for your information.</p>
                        <p>Liberty in the Constitution.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-03-16">March 16,
                                1880</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/> By order of the
                            minister.<lb/><signed>MONTESINOS.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>To the <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of Foreign Affairs</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Present.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 5.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Messrs. <persName type="from">Stephens and
                                    Fagan</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Neill</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Trojes</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-03-16"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 16,
                                1880</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: We are the two men mentioned by Mr.
                            Kitchener as being the only ones of our party of five who escaped from
                            the Mexicans who attacked us on Sunday last. He has read his letter over
                            to us, and we wish to state that his description of the disturbance, as
                            far as evidence will allow at present, is correct.</p>
                        <p>As citizens of America we appeal to you as the representative of our
                            country, and we feel confident that you will do all in your power to
                            obtain compensation to us for our losses, and protection for our lives;
                            also protection for the company, which, through their officers here,
                            have made such heroic efforts to deliver us, and to whom we owe our
                            safety at this moment.</p>
                        <p>As soon as possible we shall inform you as to the extent of our losses,
                            which we cannot clearly estimate at present, as the authorities have yet
                            in their keeping the goods saved from the wreck.</p>
                        <p>We are, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><list>
                                    <item>CLINTON STEPHENS.</item>
                                    <item>ANSEL FAGAN.</item>
                                </list></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 5.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kitchner</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Robert Geddes</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">The
                                        Trojes Mining and Smelting Company</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Anganqueo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-03-16"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 16, 1880</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: I have to inform you of a very
                            painful occurrence which happened to three of the Americans who were
                            engaged in mining operations for the Trojes Mining and Smelting Company,
                            which I represent, and I must request you to place the following
                            information before the proper American officials in Mexico, to enable
                            them to take any steps that their government may think advisable for
                            obtaining compensation for the loss of life and property.</p>
                        <p>First of May, 1879, Messrs. Sullivan and Fagan signed in the city of New
                            York the inclosed contract with the Trojes Mining and Smelting Company.
                            In the month of November they commenced work on a large scale under the
                            immediate direction of <pb facs="0842" n="742" xml:id="pg_742"/> Mr.
                            Clinton Stephens. He was accompanied by Ansel Fagan, one of the parties
                            to the contract, Mr. Arnold, son of a gentleman who was directly
                            interested in the undertaking, Mr. Connolly, managing engineer under Mr.
                            Stephens, and Mr. Henry Youmans, machinist, all of them American born
                            citizens. Since their arrival the work has been in constant progress,
                            native labor being largely employed by them, but until the late
                            disturbance we saw no serious signs of any outbreak amongst them. It is
                            true that several times the lives of all us Protestants have been
                            threatened, and some little time before the Americans arrived printed
                            notices had been posted on the walls of the houses stating that the
                            foreigners in the company’s employ would all be killed. Later on it
                            seems that Mr. Connolly, one of the deceased, had received notices that
                            he would be one of the sufferers, but like the rest of us took little
                            notice of their repeated threats; indeed, we were all under the
                            impression that he was one of the most popular foreigners amongst us,
                            being a good Roman Catholic, strict in his attendance at chapel, and a
                            great friend with the priest of the village.</p>
                        <p>Our company had their smelting works and chief offices, &amp;c., situated
                            at Trojes, a distance of about 5 miles from the village of Anganqueo.
                            The American contractors hired the use of a house situated near the
                            mouth of the San Hilario tunnel, on the road to Trojes, and about
                            three-fourths of a mile from the village of Anganqueo.</p>
                        <p>On the evening of Saturday, the 13th, I left Anganqueo to spend the
                            Sunday at Trojes, as was my custom. The following day being Sunday and a
                            general holiday, my manager, Mr. Tregoning, an Englishman, and Mr.
                            Fagan, one of the American contractors, came over to spend the day at
                            Trojes, with the intention of returning to Anganqueo that same evening.
                            This was quite a rare occurrence, that both my manager and myself should
                            be absent from Anganqueo at the same time. About 6.20 p.m. Don Emilio,
                            Mexican, brother-in-law of my manager, appeared at Trojes, having ridden
                            in great haste. He informed us that he had met Mr. Clinton Stephens
                            walking in the midst of an excited crowd towards the Casa Municipal. He
                            accompanied him to the office and there stated to the authorities that a
                            man had been killed by the Americans in self-defense, and that a large
                            crowd was attacking the house, begging them to take soldiers and use
                            their influence to stop further outrage. The crowd which accompanied Mr.
                            Stephens being still much excited, the authorities took Mr. Stephens
                            into the Casa Municipal for protection. In about fifteen minutes after
                            their arrival the troops, numbering eight men, started for the scene of
                            disturbance. Mr. Stephens remained under the charge of the authorities
                            whilst Don Emilio started off for the scene of disturbance, arriving
                            there about the same time as the soldiers. He described to us that there
                            was an excited crowd of fully a thousand men surrounding the building
                            which Connolly, Arnold, and Youmans had shut themselves into; he heard
                            many shots fired, and attempts were being made to fire on the building
                            lighted fagots to burn the house down. The soldiers on arrival did not
                            in any way better matters, but seemed to Don Emilio to mix with the
                            crowd and rather increase the excitement. We have several witnesses who
                            saw the soldiers later on fire on the Americans. Don Emilio tried to
                            pass the crowd on the road to Trojes, but was finally turned back; he
                            managed, however, in the excitement, to make his way by a small bridle
                            track past the crowd, and as mentioned brought the first notice of the
                            disturbance to us at Trojes. No other notice from the authorities or
                            otherwise reached Trojes either then or later in the evening.</p>
                        <p>In a few minutes I and three men were in the saddle and galloped as fast
                            as the horses could go to the scene of disturbance. Mr. Hillegust
                            remained in charge of the smelter and arranged to collect further forces
                            to follow us as soon as possible. On our arrival we found the
                            contractor’s house still burning, and the dead bodies of Conolly,
                            Arnold, and Youmans distributed about and so mutilated they were
                            scarcely to be recognized. There were several small crowds of excited
                            people about, but no attack was made on us, nor were there any signs of
                            any soldiers or authorities to protect the bodies or property. As there
                            was still doubt as to Mr. Stephens’s safety, and also, as I fully
                            expected an attack might be made on the company’s house in Anganqueo, we
                            followed on into the town, which was crowded with excited people, mostly
                            collected around the Casa Municipal, in which Mr. Stephens was lodged.
                            Being only a small party, we thought it better to remain in charge of
                            the house until a superior force arrived. In the haste of our departure
                            from Trojes I was quite unaware that Mr. Fagan intended coming to
                            Anganqueo. I learned, however, after arriving that he had started a few
                            minutes later than we; his horse, however, would not keep up, and he had
                            been left behind by himself. Knowing, however, that a superior force
                            would follow as speedily as possible, and that Mr. Fagan would naturally
                            turn back to meet them, we remained in the house and received a
                            communication from the authorities to say that Mr. Stephens was still
                            unhurt, but that a large mob was still surrounding the building.</p>
                        <p>In about an hour and a half, an extra force in charge of our conductor,
                            Herr Rieckmann, arrived, bringing with them Mr. Fagan, whom they had met
                            waiting for them on the road, not, however, before three shots had been
                            fired at him from the close neighborhood of the burning building. We now
                            had a force of some 12 or 13 men, <pb facs="0843" n="743" xml:id="pg_743"/> and the authorities sent word to say they would he
                            glad if we would take charge of Mr. Stephens, as the crowd was still
                            very excited, and liable to break into the Casa Municipal. This I only
                            too gladly agreed to do, if they retained all the responsibility for his
                            life, and in a short time he was handed over to our care. I then
                            requested the authorities to remove the dead bodies, which was effected
                            before morning.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Stephens then gave me the following account of what he had seen of
                            the disturbance. He, Mr. Stephens, was in the engine-house, about 200
                            yards from their dwelling-house, when he heard five shots fired in that
                            direction. He at once proceeded down to the house to make inquiries.
                            Before turning the corner, however, he perceived an excited Mexican
                            throwing stones at the house; he then heard another shot, and upon
                            turning the corner he found a man wounded in the street. He next
                            proceeded into the house and found there Connolly, Arnold, and Youmans.
                            Mr. Connolly then gave to Mr. Stephens the following account of the
                            disturbance: That the man wounded outside had in the morning disputed
                            about the payment of an extra real (12½ cents) in his wages; that
                            becoming troublesome, he, Connolly, had ejected him from the house. In
                            the afternoon the same man returned and found Connolly sitting outside
                            the house, and instantly commenced throwing stones at him, breaking the
                            bench he was sitting on. Connolly retired into the house to avoid him;
                            the man, however, commenced to stone the door, and Connolly was obliged
                            to come out to put the man away. The man then attacked Connolly with a
                            sword and drove him back into the house. Connolly then armed himself
                            with a Colt revolver, and fired five shots without effect. This must
                            have been intentional, as the distance was so close he would hardly fail
                            in his aim. The man still persevering in his attack, Connolly, who in
                            the mean time had armed himself with a breech-loading shot-gun, found
                            himself obliged in self-protection to fire on him; the charge took
                            effect in the legs, showing clearly even then that Connolly was trying
                            to spare life.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Stephens, on hearing this account, told Connolly to accompany him at
                            once to deliver himself up to the authorities. Mr. Stephens started on
                            the road, and at once an excited crowd collected, as Connolly still
                            remained behind in the house. Mr. Stephens returned for him, and they
                            started together in the direction of the village, telling the crowd as
                            they went that they were on their way to deliver themselves up to the
                            authorities. For several hundred yards no violence was offered them,
                            though the crowd increased in numbers and continued to insult them. Mr.
                            Stephens then saw a man called Pedro Mondragon, gefe de Mangano, one of
                            the authorities in the district, and who had previously expressed
                            considerable friendship for Connolly, coming forward to meet them, and
                            at once told Connolly to ask his friend to proceed with him to the
                            authorities. Pedro Mondragon, however, drew his sword and rushed forward
                            to strike Connolly, who avoided the blow by springing to one side, drew
                            his pistol and shouted to the man to wait. Still, however, the man came
                            on with his sword, and Connolly, wishing to prevent bloodshed, and
                            seeing an opening in the crowd, turned to escape towards the house, when
                            Pedro Mondragon gave him a blow with his sword. Mr. Stephens saw
                            Connolly followed by Mondragon, and the crowd reached the house and
                            closed the doors.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Stephens being unable to return to the house on account of the crowd,
                            and wishful to seek assistance, proceeded on his way to the Casa
                            Municipal, about three-fourths of a mile distant, followed the whole way
                            by an excited crowd insulting him, whilst one man on horseback threw his
                            lasso at him, luckily without success. He then met Don Emilio and
                            proceeded to the authorities and gave himself into their charge as
                            before mentioned.</p>
                        <p>On the same night (Sunday) the authorities took up the bodies to the Casa
                            Municipal and also some of the goods saved from the burning building.
                            Ail that evening-there was an excited crowd around the house containing
                            the bodies, but only one shot was fired; in the morning Achilos Arinas,
                            gefe de Policia de Ocampo, and Leon Torres arrived with an armed force
                            of some 40 well-armed men, to our assistance. Being anxious to take
                            Messrs. Stephens and Fagan to a place of safety, we notified the
                            authorities of our intention to proceed to Trojes, after Mr. Stephens
                            had given his declaration before the authorities. We started with the
                            guard. On the way, part of our guard seized Pedro Mondragon, and took
                            him to prison.</p>
                        <p>Owing to the probable excitement which might be caused by a foreign
                            burial under such painful circumstances, we determined to bring the
                            bodies to Trojes, for burial in the company’s vault. For this purpose I
                            proceeded back to Anganqueo to take the bodies, but was detained several
                            hours, through their having to await the arrival of officials from
                            Zitácuaro, the capital of the district. They arrived late with a force
                            of about 90 men and we started with the bodies on mules about half past
                            six in the morning, arriving at Trojes about nine o’clock. When I read,
                            over the bodies, the English burial service, several natives informed me
                            that they saw the soldiers fire on the Americans. The inclosed letter
                            from the doctor will show you the frightful death our friends were
                            subjected to. Several of those present described the fearful madness of
                            the people in mutilating the bodies, before and after death. One boy, by
                            order of his father, lassoed poor Connolly when he was in a dying
                            condition and dragged him about. By the first report we heard that six
                            Mexicans were killed and many more wounded, but <pb facs="0844" n="744" xml:id="pg_744"/> subsequently we heard that only two are dead and
                            four wounded dangerously. As the Mexican bodies were at once removed, we
                            had no means of judging the number. It is an important fact to note,
                            that upon the authorities wishing to send a telegram for assistance
                            Flaviano Arguillo, telegrafisto, refused to forward the message because
                            it was Sunday and not office hours. The authorities did not enforce
                            it.</p>
                        <p>The only men implicated in this affair that are yet taken are Pedro
                            Mondragon and the boy who lassoed poor Connolly.</p>
                        <p>During the trouble, Mr. Hillegust in the company’s name applied to the
                            inhabitants of Ocampo village, near Trojes. These responded to his call
                            most promptly, and more-men than were required instantly offered their
                            services. We wish especially that Achilos Arinas and Leon Torres might
                            be officially thanked for the prompt manner in which they brought their
                            forces to their assistance. We trust that when the excitement is
                            somewhat less to give you more full details, and also to send you the
                            certificates of death. I thought it advisable to at once stop all
                            workings at the mines so long as this excitement lasts.</p>
                        <p>I trust you will represent these sad details to the representative of the
                            American Government, as Messrs. Stephens and Fagan, as well as the
                            company, are heavy losers-by the late disturbance, and we have every
                            confidence that the American Government will do all that is fitting to
                            obtain compensation for the loss of life and property and for the
                            protection of all foreigners in the district. The goods saved from the
                            burning house are still in the hands of the authorities, so that we are
                            unable as yet to form an estimate of the losses.</p>
                        <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer><signed>ARTHUR B. KITCHENER,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Director of
                                    Trojes Mining Company.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>