<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-09-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="500" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d500">
                        <head>No. 500.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Navarro</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Mexico in the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-09-03"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 3, 1880</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Assistant Secretary</hi>: I have had the honor
                            to receive your polite note, in which you do me the favor to inform me
                            that eight individuals, who are suspected of belonging to a party of
                            revolutionists against the Government of Mexico, have been arrested by
                            the forces of the United States and placed under the custody of Captain
                            Rafferty.</p>
                        <p>This legation has received dispatches from the Mexican consul at Tucson,
                            giving notice that a special messenger had come from the State of Sonora
                            to demand the extradition of the above-mentioned persons, but that the
                            government of the Territory of Arizona does not believe that to be a
                            matter within its jurisdiction, granting that the capture of those
                            criminals may have been executed by Federal authorities.</p>
                        <p>Upon this occasion, I have the honor to beg your Department to procure
                            the corresponding orders, in order that the extradition demanded may be
                            confirmed in accordance with Article III of the treaty of the 11th of
                            December, of 1861, which cites, among crimes for which the seizures
                            shall be restored, that of taking goods or money, of whatever value, by
                            means of violence or intimidation.</p>
                        <p>Your Department should ascertain whether the seizures of which we speak
                            may not have some political motive, which might serve them as a pretext
                            to enter the town of Magdalena, exacting of the inhabitants a large sum
                            of money under penalty of hanging those who offer resistance.</p>
                        <p>My government will accept as a new proof of the sentiments which animate
                            the Government of the United States for the peace and tranquillity of
                            Mexico the action of the American authorities in the capture of those
                            criminals, in order that they may be delivered to the commissioner, <pb facs="0888" n="788" xml:id="pg_788"/> who requests their extradition
                            in the name of the government of the State of Sonora, in accordance with
                            Article II of the treaty to which I have referred.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>JUAN N. NAVARRO.</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>