<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 509.Mr. Mathews to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1880</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d509</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">509</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1880-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1880-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recfABRQvTqVuIjoA" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="antisemitism" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361" lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-04-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="509" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d509">
                <head>No. 509.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mathews</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                    States Consulate at Tangier</hi>
                        </placeName>,<lb/>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-04-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi>
                                17, 1880</date>. (Received May 17.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 362.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my dispatch No. 354, dated the
                        8th of March, I have the honor to transmit to you herewith a copy and
                        translation of the reply to my letter addressed to the Sultan through his
                        prime minister on the occasion of the recent persecution of the Jews of this
                        empire.</p>
                <p>From most reliable information on the subject of the burning of a Jew aged
                        eighty-five, at Fez, the statement in the Sultan’s prime minister’s letter
                        to me is incorrect. It is well known that no Barbary Jew would ever dare to
                        even carry a walking-stick at Fez; they are only allowed to use a reed as a
                        cane to walk, and it must be of a certain length.</p>
                <p>The well known timid character of all Moorish Jews who are obliged to walk
                        barefooted and never permitted to ride any kind of an animal through the
                        streets of Fez, makes it ludicrous to learn from a Sultan’s <pb facs="0902" n="802" xml:id="pg_802"/> minister that an old Jew, eighty-five years
                        old, insulted and threatened a crowd of Moors at the fanatical city of Fez,
                        when they are pent up in a ghetto, in constant fear of their lives. I have
                        the most reliable evidence of the fact that no Moor died, nor even was
                        wounded at the hands of a Jew, and that the story is a fabrication got up to
                        extenuate the magnitude of the crime.</p>
                <p>I herewith beg to inclose copy of a letter from Captain John Cobb, our
                        consular agent at Casablanca, who happened to be at Fez at the time this
                        affair took place.</p>
                <p>I am happy to state that my letter to the Sultan has been productive of good
                        in preventing thus far further ill-treatment on the Israelites, and it has
                        been a source of satisfaction to the European Jews, who have expressed their
                        gratitude and thanks to me through their various delegations, and through
                        the press.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>FELIX A. MATHEWS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 362.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Prime Minister</gloss> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Mathews</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Praise be to the only God!</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">To our dear friend the judicious, the gentleman, the
                            honorable mediator for the welfare between the two nations, the
                            representative of the powerful American nation, Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Felix A. Mathews</hi>:</p>
                    <p>We always inquire for you, and we pray to God for your preservation and
                            welfare. We received your letter relative to the Jew that was burned,
                            and we have taken note of all you have said and heard, and that His
                            Majesty should take more care of his Jewish subjects, and that those
                            that committed the crime were not punished, also that we should see that
                            the Jews are well treated, &amp;c. We have informed ourselves of all you
                            have stated, which is all due to the good friendship which exists
                            between us; and you also state that we must punish the aggressor, and
                            you recommend us the safety of the persons and property of the Jews and
                            that we should write to our governors so that they be well treated and
                            that no injustice should be done to them.</p>
                    <p>We have read your letter to His Majesty the Sultan, who attentively took
                            note of all its contents, and His Majesty recognizes and considers that
                            your good advice emanated from the good friendship which you profess
                            towards him, and His Majesty the Sultan ordains us to make known to you
                            his acknowledgment, which we now do in his name.</p>
                    <p>You must be acquainted of the fact of the matter as we have been
                            informed: that a Moor of the suburbs of Fez came into the Yames Market
                            in company with his wife to make purchases, and on returning in the
                            afternoon the husband remained behind and she waited for him alone, when
                            a French Jew appeared in her presence intoxicated, and the woman got
                            frightened and called for help; her husband came up and pushed the Jew
                            away, and the latter drew a pistol and wounded the Moor on the head, and
                            afterwards threw stones at him; when those present arrested the Jew, who
                            was imprisoned by the authorities. Soon after an old Jew made his
                            appearance, insulting the government and menacing the people with an arm
                            then the crowd gathered, and it ended in his death and in his being
                            burned.</p>
                    <p>From the foregoing you will observe that the fault rests on the Jews. His
                            Majesty the Sultan was much annoyed when he was informed of what
                            happened, and he gave orders for the arrest of some of those who were
                            present, both of the country people as well as those of the city, but
                            they could not make out who were the guilty parties, and when the Jews
                            became acquainted with the facts they came to an understanding, and the
                            prisoners were set free, and the governor of Fez was deprived of his
                            official position for being a man of little energy, and we appointed in
                            his place Kaid El Arby Usef Urbah Mohamed Shergin.</p>
                    <p>The husband of the woman, who was wounded, died from the effects of the
                            wounds inflicted on him by the Jew; and there was a settlement of the
                            affair with the widow of the Jew who was burned, for the life of her
                            husband, but there has been no settlement for the life of the Moor. You
                            will thus see how well behaved are the people of Fez, which, if it had
                            not been for those of good sense, we cannot imagine what would have
                            taken place, as the populace never reflects upon consequences, therefore
                            the Jews must behave well with the Moors.</p>
                    <p>You are one of the oldest representatives in this happy empire, and you
                            know what <pb facs="0903" n="803" xml:id="pg_803"/> difference is in the
                            present behavior of the Jews from what it was; and His Majesty, the
                            protected by God, does not countenance injustices, and heeds what you
                            advise us as to ordain our governors recommending the Jews. His Majesty
                            the Sultan has issued strict orders on behalf of the Jews, and any one
                            molesting them will be severely punished.</p>
                    <p>His majesty wishes you much happiness, and for friendship and peace.</p>
                    <p>The Sultan’s vizier, protected by God,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>MOHAMED BEN LARBY EL MAJTAR.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">At the city of <placeName>Fez</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="hijri" when="1880-02-18">7th Rabi the 1st,
                                    1297</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 362.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Cobb</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Mathews</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">City of
                                        Fez</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-02-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 3,
                                1880</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: I regret to state that a sad affair
                            took place at this city just on my arrival, and I now beg to give an
                            account as related to me by an eye-witness, and which has been
                            corroborated by many respectable Moors and Jews during this day, which
                            is as follows:</p>
                    <p>An Algerine Jew, strongly under the influence of liquor, walking near the
                            Sultan’s residence at the city of Fez, met a Moor with a woman; the Jew
                            made an attempt to take the woman with him; the Moor retaliated by
                            striking him; the Jew then drew a pistol and fired it off, not injuring
                            any one; he was then set upon by a number of passers by and severely
                            beaten and taken off to prison; soon after, three Jews were passing by
                            the Sultan’s residence, when they were suddenly surprised by a party of
                            Moors in a most violent manner; two of the Jews being young and strong
                            made good their escape, but the victim, some eighty-five years old, was
                            stopped; he inquired why he was to be dealt with in this foul manner,
                            assuring them that he was not aware he had committed any wrong; when
                            they told him they wanted to show him about that, and immediately threw
                            him down, saturated his clothes with petroleum, set fire to him, and
                            there and then he was burned to death. A Moor of a most respectable
                            appearance to-day informed me that he was an eye-witness to this
                            operation.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>Since which the authorities have asked the Jews to let the matter pass,
                            offering $400 to the family of the deceased, and say no more about the
                            affair. The Sultan liberated the French Jew who, during his state of
                            intoxication, fired the pistol, without inflicting upon him any
                            punishment whatever. After this affair the Jews all remained in their
                            houses four days with barred doors, not daring to show their faces
                            outside, under a terrible state of excitement, fearing death was to be
                            dealt out to them all in the same cruel manner; but now they go out
                            unmolested, otherwise than by occasional threats from Moors that soon
                            the day will come when they will all share the fate of the aged
                            victim.</p>
                    <p>From the Melah, where the Jews are quartered, to the house where I now
                            reside, as you know, is a long walk, and many of them have come to lay
                            their complaints before me, and, although the weather is cold for this
                            country, the streets muddy, and very roughly paved, they all, rich and
                            poor, male and female, come barefooted, assuring me that they would be
                            murdered if they attempted to walk the streets of Fez otherwise; which
                            is truly a barbarously cruel state of affairs and should be noticed by
                            the more civilized governments, and a matter which I believe could most
                            easily be remedied.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>You have no doubt, ere this, been made aware of the petroleum murder, but
                            as these reports as they travel come in to you so conflictingly, I give
                            it to you as I believe it actually occurred, and shall give you further
                            information if such appears.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN COBB.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
