<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 555.Mr. Hoffman to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1880</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d555</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">555</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1880-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1880-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-02-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-02-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="555"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d555">
                <head>No. 555.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hoffman</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-02-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 27, 1880</date>. (Received March
                        16.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 187.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In my dispatch No. 136 of September 13th last I
                    had the honor to inform you that certain changes among the high officers of
                    Russia had been determined upon, and that among others General Loris Melikoff
                    was to succeed General Gourko as military governor of this city. This change was
                    announced yesterday. General Melikoff is set not only over St. Petersburg, but
                    over the whole empire, as regards crimes against the state. Every one is made
                    subordinate to him, even the minister of war. He is to report to and receive
                    orders from the Emperor alone, and he is empowered to associate with himself, as
                    a commission, such persons as he may see fit. His title is “Chief of the Supreme
                    Executive Commission.”</p>
                <p>As you have probably learned from telegrams in the public journals a printing
                    press was lately seized in a house on Vassily Ostroff, and the persons connected
                    with it arrested. It appears that the “dvornik,” or porter of the house, having
                    observed suspicious circumstances, gave notice to the police, who thereupon made
                    their descent. The “dvornik” received a hundred roubles for his services. Two
                    days ago he was found murdered.</p>
                <p>Great excitement prevails at present in this city. Many persons are leaving town,
                    going to their country places, or to neighboring cities. Others have telegraphed
                    to their families not to return at present. The police is visiting every house,
                    inspecting the cellars and attics, and <pb facs="0972" n="872" xml:id="pg_872"/>
                    giving instructions to keep the gas burning all night, to look well to the water
                    and gas pipes, and to have tubs of water ready for instant use. In short, every
                    precaution is being taken against an outbreak, which the Nihilists threaten for
                    Tuesday next.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WICKHAM HOFFMAN.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
