<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 646.Mr. Evarts to Mr. Farman.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1880</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d646</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">646</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1880-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1880-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBIWbnPJBWQERtR" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402" lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807" lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-06-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="646" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d646">
                <head>No. 646.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Evarts</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Farman</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-06-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 28,
                                1880</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 170.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The project of a commission of liquidation
                            to take control of the finances of Egypt has had careful consideration
                            in view of your dispatch No. 372 of March 8.</p>
                <p>This government has been approached by that of France, in the sense of
                            obtaining our adhesion to the scheme, but without any favorable
                            respéonse. I have, in fact, replied to the representations of Mr.
                            Outrey, the French minister, that this government could not agree to
                            accept, in advance, as binding upon our citizens, the action of a
                            commission in which we were to have no part.</p>
                <p>I have now to instruct you to say to the officers of the Khedive’s
                            Government with whom you may have occasion to discuss the matter, that,
                            although it is not considered necessary, for the protection of American
                            interests, that this government should participate in the organization
                            of the commission and be represented therein by an American
                            commissioner, yet it is regarded as proper to leave undecided, for the
                            present, the question of the acceptability of such action as that
                            commission might hereafter take, so far as concerns its operation upon
                            the rights of citizens of the United States. Not, therefore, being
                            disposed to accredit, by anticipatory action, the dispositions of a
                            mixed administration, in which we have no share, and which may yet
                            affect the material interests of their citizens, the United States
                            reserve their relations to the Egyptian Government in the matter in case
                            they should have any interests to protect calling for diplomatic
                            representation.</p>
                <p>Your telegram, informing me that the Russian Government has made a
                            somewhat analogous reservation of right, has been received. You may, if
                            it should appear necessary, make, in like manner, formal notification to
                            the Government of His Highness the Khedive, of the present reserve
                            maintained by the United States, as above explained to you.</p>
                <p>The clause of your recent telegram, received on the 21st instant,
                            relating to this subject, has been duly considered. With every
                            disposition to favor the wishes of the Khedive in any matter important
                            to Egyptian interests, it is not perceived that the position above taken
                            should be regarded as interfering with the entire freedom of that
                            government to make any administrative adjustment of its financial
                            relations with nations which are represented in such administration. If
                            the Government of His Highness should point out to you any such
                            embarrassment, I shall be ready to consider it with the most favorable
                            disposition towards the Egyptian Government.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WM. M. EVARTS.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
