<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 667.Mr. Evarts
                            to Mr. Baker.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1880</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d667</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">667</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1880-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1880-10-15T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183" lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495" lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recHKBrLbO74DsZpb" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136190" lcsh-match="exact">Torture</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1880-10-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1880-10-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="667" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d667">
                <head>No. 667.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Evarts</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Baker</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1880-10-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 15,
                            1880</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 91.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your dispatch of the 8th ultimo, No. 274, in
                        relation to the claim of Mr. John E. Wheelock, and inclosing copy of the
                        correspondence between yourself and Mr. Saavedra, the minister of exterior
                        relations for Venezuela, on that subject, has been received.</p>
                <p>Your course in presenting the subject to the Venezuelan government, in
                        pursuance of my instruction of the 28th of January last, No. 62, is
                        approved. When that instruction was dictated the facts in relation to the
                        barbarous outrage perpetrated upon a citizen of the United States by a
                        public officer of the Venezuelan government, acting under color of law, were
                        all before the Department. There appeared no ground for question as to the
                        truth of the statements. They were substantially the same as received from
                        Mr. Wheelock, the victim of the outrage, from Mr. Dalton, the consul at
                        Ciudad Bolivar, and from your legation. Nor do I now find the facts directly
                        controverted by the Venezuelan minister of exterior relations in his note to
                        you of the 24th of August last, a copy and translation of which you inclose
                        in your No. 274.</p>
                <p>To characterize this cruel and unusual proceeding in its true light it is
                        only necessary to give a brief recital of the occurrences attending it.</p>
                <p>Mr. John E. Wheelock, an American citizen, in the legitimate pursuit of his
                        regular business, visited, in June, 1879, the mines of the Carstal district,
                        situate about 200 miles southeast of Ciudad Bolivar. He remained there until
                        the 13th of September following. On the morning of that day he was arrested,
                        at the instance of an Italian, who alleged that he had had $1,200 stolen
                        from his safe, and accused Mr. Wheelock of the theft. The arrest was made by
                        an officer having the official title <pb facs="1142" n="1042" xml:id="pg_1042"/> of “commissary,” combining, as it appears in one
                        person the dual functions of a magistrate and police constable. This
                        functionary, as it further appears, acting at once as judge and executioner,
                        directed his subordinates to pinion Wheelock’s arms behind his back, and
                        compelled him to march a mile from the place of arrest—Chilé—back to the
                        mining camp. The cords with which his arms were bound cutting into his
                        flesh, Wheelock paid, to one of the armed guards who were driving him, $5 to
                        have the cords loosened a little. This guard then stepping back a short
                        distance, a second one stepped up and again tightened them, when a third
                        offered to slacken the cords for another $5, which offer was, however,
                        declined by the unfortunate prisoner.</p>
                <p>Arriving at the scene of the supposed larceny, Mr. Wheelock was requested by
                        the commissary to confess what he had done with the Italian’s money. Upon
                        replying that he knew nothing of it, his arms were again tightly pinioned
                        behind him by the orders of this same officer, and he was suspended, by the
                        cord with which his arms were bound, from a peg in the wall at a height
                        which took his feet some distance from the ground. Again asked to confess,
                        he protested his innocence. The mode of torture was then changed, a
                        slipnoose was made, the rope was put tightly around his body, and he was
                        suspended in mid air, with the fore part of his body bearing towards the
                        ground. Still refusing the invitations to confess, he was, when nearly dead,
                        taken down. He was then taken to the woods, half a mile distant, and from a
                        strong rope stretched between two trees he was suspended by cords tightly
                        tied around his ankles, with his head down but not so as to reach the
                        ground. Again urged to confess, Mr. Wheelock indignantly denied his guilt.
                        Failing through all these barbarous methods to wring a confession from Mr.
                        Wheelock, this inhuman official committed him to jail, when, after remaining
                        there a few days, his case came in order before the district court, and,
                        after a full and searching investigation before that tribunal, Mr. Wheelock
                        was honorably acquitted and discharged, with the personal assurance from the
                        district judge that “there was nothing whatever found against him, not even
                        grounds for a suspicion of the offense with which he had been charged.”</p>
                <p>It is unnecessary to comment on proceedings of the character of these by an
                        officer of a civilized government, perpetrated under the guise of official
                        authority. Such atrocities as resorting to “the torture” to extract a
                        confession of guilt from persons accused of crime, are now, happily,
                        considered by all civilized governments and peoples as belonging to an age
                        long past, and it might well have been hoped that such inhuman cruelties
                        would never have found an opportunity for revival in any of the
                        constitutional governments established on this continent.</p>
                <p>Believing, as I did, when the transaction was first brought to the attention
                        of this government, and as I do not now allow myself to doubt, that the
                        Government of Venezuela shared in this common sentiment of abhorrence of
                        such practices, and conceiving that the enlightened sense of justice of that
                        government, strengthened by the recollection of the long and unbroken
                        friendship which has heretofore subsisted, and still subsists, between the
                        people and Governments of the United States and Venezuela, would at once
                        prompt it to disavow the conduct of this unworthy official, by degrading him
                        from his office and handing him over to the proper tribunals for trial and
                        merited punishment, and, at the same time, spontaneously making to the
                        victim of his cruelties the only remaining reparation it could for his
                        wrongs by a reasonable pecuniary indemnity, the instruction which I
                        forwarded in January last was conceived in the most friendly spirit toward
                        the Venezuelan Government, <pb facs="1143" n="1043" xml:id="pg_1043"/> as it
                        was dictated in the most moderate tone. It is, therefore, with the greatest
                        regret and surprise that this government receives the information conveyed
                        to you in the note of Mr. Saavedra of the 24th of August, giving the result
                        of the promised investigation into the conduct of Señor Sotillo, the author
                        of the illegal and cruel acts from which Mr. Wheelock suffered. The minister
                        of exterior relations states in that communication that “Two judges the
                        departmental of Roscio and that of the first instance of the State, had
                        decided in accord and successively that there did not exist merit for
                        continuing the proceeding (sumario), nor for ordering the arrest of Señor
                        Sotillo.” Upon what character of evidence this conclusion was reached does
                        not appear from the minister’s note. It is sufficiently evident that neither
                        the testimony nor deposition of Mr. Wheelock formed any part of it; nor is
                        there any intimation that the facts as first stated by Mr. Wheelock were
                        refuted or even directly controverted, beyond the suggestion that he had
                        exaggerated them. That the successive decisions of the two judges were
                        submitted to the executive authorities of Venezuela, is evident from the
                        further statement of Mr. Saavedra that “Doctor Parejo, actual President of
                        that state, notwithstanding the investigation had terminated, moved (excito)
                        the tribunal, with vivid earnestness, to open it <hi rend="italic">de
                            novo.</hi>” “Such,” says Mr. Saavedra, “is the state of the matter,” and
                        he concludes by informing you that the supreme federal government having
                        done as much as has been in its power to bring “the truth to light” and
                        secure “the punishment of the offense which might turn out to be committed,”
                        the minister adds that his government “thinks that if there has actually
                        been a crime, the obligation of the republic is satisfied by the judgment
                        and punishment of its author, and that it would not owe pecuniary
                        indemnification to the offended.”</p>
                <p>The general principle here invoked by Mr. Saavedra, that if a crime is
                        committed against the person, property, or character of an alien resident of
                        the country by a citizen of the country in which such alien may be resident,
                        and the government of such country secures the judgment and punishment of
                        its author, its obligations to the government of the party wronged are
                        satisfied, and that it would not in such case owe pecuniary indemnity to the
                        offended, may very well be admitted; but to claim this for the proceedings
                        had before the Venezuelan judges in the case of Commissary Sotillo would
                        seem little less than a mockery of justice.</p>
                <p>To the worst features of the outrage perpetrated on Mr. Wheelock (the
                        occurrence in the woods) there were no witnesses but the perpetrators and
                        the victim. Mr. Wheelock’s evidence was not before the judges, and there is,
                        therefore, every reason to believe that Sotillo’s alleged vindication rested
                        solely on his own testimony and that of his subordinate instruments.</p>
                <p>To denominate the proceedings against the officer Sotillo as a miscarriage of
                        justice, is the mildest form of denunciation that can be applied. The
                        sanction of the executive government of Venezuela imparts to them the
                        character of an absolute denial of justice. Were such an outrage as that
                        perpetrated by Sotillo on Mr. Wheelock possible—as fortunately it is not—in
                        the United States, and Venezuelan citizens were the subject of it, the
                        offending officer would be instantly dismissed from the public service and
                        handed over to the proper tribunals for trial, and, if found guilty,
                        subjected to the severest punishment denounced by the laws of the country
                        against an offense at once so abnormal and inhuman. It is unnecessary to
                        invoke the principles of the treaty of amity and friendship (1860) existing
                        between the United States and Venezuela, of the <pb facs="1144" n="1044" xml:id="pg_1044"/> 3d article of which these acts are in clear
                        contravention. It is no less an offense against the principles of public law
                        and the civilization of the age. This government would be wanting in that
                        duty which it owes to its citizens, and regardless of its own dignity, were
                        it lightly to pass over so flagrant an outrage.</p>
                <p>You will lose no time in bringing these views to the attention of Mr.
                        Saavedra, expressing at the same time the earnest wish entertained by the
                        President that the subject may receive the early and earnest tttmsid-eration
                        of the Venezuelan Government, and result in a speedy adjustment of Mr.
                        Wheelock’s claim for pecuniary indemnity. When the Government of Venezuela
                        shall signify its willingness to make such reparation the amount of that
                        indemnity may properly become a matter for further consideration by this
                        Department.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WM. M. EVARTS.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
