<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>130. Telegram From the Embassy in the Dominican Republic to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d130</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">130</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-09-03T15:27:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-09-03T15:27:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Internment</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="visas" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436" lcsh-match="exact">Passports</term>
                    <term ref="recy94pCDcRAr4voG" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="freedom-of-expression" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003012251" lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of speech</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-09-03T15:27:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-09-03T15:27:00-05:00" n="130"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d130">
                <head>130. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Dominican
                        Republic</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d130fn1">Source: <persName>Johnson</persName>
                        Library, National Security File, Country File, Dominican Republic, Vol. X,
                        8/65–9/65. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_EXDIS1">Exdis</gloss>.
                        Passed to the White House, DOM, and <gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                        >CIA</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Santo Domingo</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-09-03T20:27:00+00:00">September 3, 1965,
                        2027Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>616. Ref: <gloss target="#t_EMBTEL1">Embtel</gloss> 541.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d130fn2">In telegram 541 from Santo Domingo, August 27, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BE1">Bunker</persName> informed the Department that he and
                            <persName corresp="#p_GGH1">Garcia Godoy</persName> met on the evening
                        of August 26 to “further discuss the handling of the Communist problem” and
                        to review a draft of the memorandum of understanding which <persName
                            corresp="#p_GGH1">Godoy</persName> subsequently agreed to.
                        (Ibid.)</note> Following is copy of memorandum of understanding on handling
                    Communist problem as agreed on with <persName corresp="#p_GGH1">Garcia
                        Godoy</persName> this morning:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Begin Text</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>The Provisional Government will be anti-Communist and will associate
                            itself with the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> and the <gloss
                                target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Government in opposing <pb facs="0349"
                                n="314" xml:id="pg_314"/> communism on the basis of that doctrineʼs
                            incompatibility with representative democracy. The provisional
                            government will exercise all powers and resources at its disposal to
                            check the growth and eliminate the influence of communism and <persName
                                corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName>-communism in the Dominican
                            Republic. On taking office, the Provisional President will provide
                            instructions to the Minister of the Interior and the Director of the
                            National Department of Investigations regarding the general policy to be
                            followed in dealing with the Communist problem.</p>
                        <p>These instructions will follow consultation with the Ambassador of the
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The Provisional President will take all appropriate action to protect his
                        government, the Dominican nation, and friendly foreign governments from
                        Communist and <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName>-Communist
                        subversion. In the event of a real and present danger from Communist
                        subversive activities which cannot be coped with by existing law, he will
                        invoke emergency powers under the Institutional Act. (Articles 2 and 48.) If
                        necessary, he will order the internment of dangerous Communists and
                        Castroites.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>No Communists, Castroites or <persName corresp="#p_CR1"
                        >Castro</persName>-Communist sympathizers will hold critical positions in
                        the Provisional Government. If there is doubt with regard to a particular
                        individual being considered for an important post, information will be
                        supplied confidentially on the basis of which the Provisional President can
                        make his determination. Individuals who are known to be present members of
                        the <gloss target="#t_PCD1">PCD</gloss> of the <gloss target="#t_MPD1"
                            >MPD</gloss> will not be accepted into government service in any
                        capacity during the term of office of the Provisional Government. Some
                        flexibility is indicated with respect to the <gloss target="#t_APCJ1"
                            >APCJ</gloss> in view of the fact that certain non-Communist followers
                        (as opposed to the leadership) are anxious to break their ties to the
                        movement, and should be encouraged in this regard. Information regarding
                        members of those parties presently in government will be made available to
                        the Provisional President. He will take whatever action may be possible to
                        remove them from the government service.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The National Department of Investigations will be given the responsibility
                        for organizing and coordinating all anti-subversive intelligence and
                        operational activities. The best available man will be chosen to head the
                        department after appropriate consultations with representatives of the
                            <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Government, as will other key
                        officials of the organization. Appointments to the department will be made
                        on the sole basis of merit. In order to deal effectively with the Communist
                        problem, the department will require the close cooperation of the Minister
                        of Interior and Police. It is agreed that the man to head that Ministry must
                        be anti-Communist by conviction.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Government will provide appropriate
                        assistance to the Provisional Government in dealing with <persName
                            corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName>-Communist subversion. The form and
                        extent of this assistance will be the subject of consultations <pb
                            facs="0350" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> between the Provisional President
                        and the Ambassador of the United States or his designated
                        representative.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The National Department of Investigations will ensure that Communists,
                        Castroites and <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName>-Communist
                        sympathizers of Dominican nationality are kept under close observation.
                        Those found breaking the law will immediately be arrested and [brought to]
                        trial. The Provisional Government will take necessary steps to send out of
                        the country all Communists, Castroites and <persName corresp="#p_CR1"
                            >Castro</persName>-Communist sympathizers of foreign nationality.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The Provisional President will be furnished a list of Dominican Communists
                        and Castroites who have entered the country illegally after receiving
                        training in Communist countries. The Provisional President will take
                        appropriate action to submit these individuals to legal process and trial in
                        accordance with Articles 153, 154, and 155 of the penal code which apply to
                        the use of false or altered identification documents, or Article 439 of the
                        code dealing with the destruction of official documents, including
                        passports.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>On taking office, the Provisional President will issue a decree-law
                        providing heavy penalties for the illegal possession of weapons. Assistance
                        in drafting the law will be furnished if so desired. First priority in
                        enforcing the law will be given to apprehending Communists and other
                        subversives who may possess unregistered weapons.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Within thirty days of taking office, the Provisional President will issue
                        a decree-law implementing Article 27 or the Institutional Act with the
                        purpose of setting up procedures for identifying political parties which are
                        not eligible to participate in the elections because they are organized on
                        the basis of doctrines or goals not in accordance with the principles of
                        representative democracy, and with the purpose also of regulating and
                        controlling the activities of parties so identified. The Provisional
                        President and the Ambassador of the United States will consult on the scope
                        and form of this law. Suggested language will be provided if so
                        desired.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>On taking office, the Provisional President will issue a decree-law
                        creating a “Council of Information” to deal with abuses of freedom of speech
                        and the press. The council will be charged with formulating a code of
                        conduct for the press and radio consistent with Articles 30 and 31 of the
                        Institutional Act. The council will also report to the Provisional
                        Government on the advisability of promulgating laws designed to prevent use
                        of the radio and the press for slander and incitement to subversion.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>The Provisional President and the Ambassador of the United States will
                        periodically review the terms of this memorandum. Changes, modifications or
                        additions will be in accordance with these consultations. <hi rend="italic"
                            >End Text</hi>.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0351" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/>
                <p>With respect para. 1 of memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_GGH1">Garcia
                        Godoy</persName> prefers provide oral directives to Minister of Interior and
                    Director NDI, due his experience that anything in writing in this country has a
                    way of becoming public in short order. He states he has full confidence that
                    Castillo is anti-Communist by conviction and will serve reliably and effectively
                    as Minister of Interior. NDI Director not yet chosen, with selection subject of
                    consultation [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                        declassified</hi>].</p>
                <p>Re para 3: Department will note some flexibility is provided for in case <gloss
                        target="#t_APCJ1">APCJ</gloss>. This is in line <persName corresp="#p_GGH1"
                        >Garcia Godoy</persName>ʼs interest in enlarging political center and
                    providing alternatives for all non-Communist followers <gloss target="#t_APCJ1"
                        >APCJ</gloss> (<gloss target="#t_EMBTEL1">Embtel</gloss> 461).<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d130fn3">
                        <ref target="#d125">Document 125</ref>.</note> He agrees <persName
                        corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName>-Communist leadership of <gloss
                        target="#t_APCJ1">APCJ</gloss> now complete. He, however, cites cases of
                    individuals who have been active in <gloss target="#t_APCJ1">APCJ</gloss>, but
                    who are anxious to break away and have asked his help by way of jobs abroad or
                    some other means. He would like to assist such individuals to make the break and
                    we believe this in both Dominican and our interest.</p>
                <p>Re para 7: <persName corresp="#p_GGH1">Garcia Godoy</persName> continues have
                    reservations about reaching back to arrest former deportees who returned to
                    DomRep illegally. He argues number involved is small and he would be accused of
                    political persecution, a charge which would affect unfavorably his broader
                    effort against Communists. He agrees to necessity of keeping these and other
                    Communists under close observation and to intern them in event of clear and
                    present danger (para 2). We have recalled to him <persName corresp="#p_BJ4"
                        >Bosch</persName>ʼs consideration of Beata Island as secure internment site.
                    He says he is prepared detain Communists and Castroites who enter country
                    illegally from now on.</p>
                <p>Re para 9: <persName corresp="#p_GGH1">Garcia Godoy</persName> indicated his
                    understanding that law in effect prior to April 24 outlawing three Communist
                    parties will still be in effect. However, he is prepared issue decree law in
                    line that discussed para 10 <gloss target="#t_EMBTEL1">Embtel</gloss> 461. He
                    would be glad to have suggestions on this.</p>
                <p>Re para 10: <persName corresp="#p_GGH1">Garcia Godoy</persName> now believes
                    Council of Information should be primarily keyed to radio industry. He said
                    editors of three principal newspapers had agreed to self-regulation (he hopes
                    they will honor promise), but are opposed to joint press radio council. He
                    believes now it would be better to handle the two media separately.</p>
                <p>Throughout these conversations and consideration of memorandum, <persName
                        corresp="#p_GGH1">Garcia Godoy</persName> has shown sound, realistic
                    attitude on control of communism. He has indicated full awareness of problem and
                    readiness to act on it, at same time coupling controls with efforts to save
                    those frustrated youth who are salvageable. We are convinced he will exert his
                    best efforts in this vital field of security.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWTJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Bennett</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
