<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>235. Memorandum for the Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d235</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">235</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-02-07T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-02-07T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recfIX2Uumy8inHEq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85144526"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wages</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-02-07T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-02-07T17:00:00-05:00" n="235"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d235">
                <head>235. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d235fn1"
                        >Source: Central Intelligence Agency, DCI (<persName corresp="#p_MJA1"
                            >McCone</persName>) Files, Job 80–B01285A, Folder 7, DCI Meetings with
                        the President, Jan–Apr 1964. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_FD1"
                            >FitzGerald</persName> on February 8.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-02-07T17:00:00-05:00">February 07, 1964, 5:00 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Meeting at the White House 7 February 1964</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>At 5 p.m. the same group<note n="2" xml:id="d235fn2">No other record of
                            the informal meeting that immediately preceded the 5 p.m. meeting at the
                            White House has been found.</note> plus Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1"
                            >Ball</persName>, Mr. Nitze, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WD1">Donald
                            Wilson</persName>, <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>, and Mr.
                        Theodore Sorensen met with the President. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA1"
                            >McCone</persName> commenced with a briefing of the facts which had been
                        established as follows: First, Cuban public statements, press releases and
                        broadcasts have in the last ten days featured the Guantanamo issue. Second,
                        the Cuban ships were fishing in our territorial waters on February 2nd and
                        there were fish aboard of the type caught in these waters. Third, there was
                        no absolute evidence that the <pb facs="0619" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/>
                        ships were dispatched or directed to national waters as against having been
                        directed into traditional United States fishing grounds. Fourth, Cuban
                        authorities <hi rend="italic">were</hi> advised that the ships were in U.S.
                        national waters at the time they were seized. Fifth, it should be noted that
                            <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName>ʼs actions regarding the
                        Guantanamo water supply took place four days after the ships were
                        apprehended which raises some question as to whether Guantanamo was a part
                        of the original plan.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Mac Bundy</persName> stated that the easiest part
                        of the decision to be reached concerned the Florida legal problem. After
                        hearing Mekerʼs briefing, the President agreed that the matter should be
                        handled by the Florida courts as being in the nature of a first offense;
                        that the crews would be released under temporary custody of Immigration and
                        not fined; that the captains should be fined and that there should be no
                        forfeiture of the vessels.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>On the question of Guantanamo and measures to be taken in response to
                            <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName>ʼs act, Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BM1">Bundy</persName> said that the choices had narrowed
                        down to alternatives one and two as set forth in the proposed releases.<note
                            n="3" xml:id="d235fn3">At 6:30 p.m. <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                                >Johnson</persName> called Senator Russell to discuss the wording of
                            the statement to be issued that evening and the differences between the
                            Presidentʼs advisers over two different alternatives and proposed
                            releases. The President read virtually the entire statement to Russell
                            and noted that <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Bundy</persName>, <persName
                                corresp="#p_MJA1">McCone</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_CKM1"
                                >Kennedy</persName> had disagreed with him and suggested an
                            alternative statement which proposed that the President instruct the
                            Department of Defense to make the Base “wholly sufficient in fresh
                            water” and to prepare other measures to make it secure. <persName
                                corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> said, “but to do nothing about
                            it [the employees], you see, just to prepare.” Russell said “I much
                            prefer the first one, I think that the people will too.” The President
                            then said that <persName corresp="#p_MTC1">Mann</persName> thought that
                            the rest of the Hemisphere was watching “and if we get soft with them,
                            weʼll be soft with Panama and that everybody else will start kicking us
                            in the pants cause theyʼll think they can.”
                                (<persName>Johnson</persName> Library, Recordings and Transcripts,
                            Recording of conversation between President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                                >Johnson</persName> and Richard Russell, Tape F64.12, Side A, PNO
                            1)</note> The argument centered around the question of the Base
                        employees and the lines were quite clearly drawn. The Secretary of Defense
                        strongly favored the dismissal of employees on the ground that only by this
                        act could the Base be made “secure.” General Taylor on balance supported the
                        Secretary of Defense. Mr. Nitze on close balance favored not dismissing the
                        employees but did not re-state his position in the later stage of the
                        argument. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> suggested a
                        compromise which would put special emphasis on the dollar contribution to
                            <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName> made by the Base
                        wages.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Attorney General repeated his very strong objection to the dismissal
                        of the Base employees on the grounds that (a) it was an overreaction to
                            <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName>ʼs move and (b) it hurt the
                        wrong Cubans who by and large had been loyal Base employees, some for more
                        than a generation. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA1">McCone</persName> also
                        opposed the dismissal on these grounds plus the fact that other countries in
                        which we have bases might fear a similar <pb facs="0620" n="585"
                            xml:id="pg_585"/> action in the event of a disagreement with them. He
                        also pointed out that our annual rental for Guantanamo is $3,000. Without
                        the economic benefits of the Base salaries, this rental figure will stand
                        out and weaken our Guantanamo position. <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Mac
                            Bundy</persName> stated that from the point of view of domestic reaction
                        (which he said would be bad) there was little to choose between the two
                        alternatives and that he favored alternative two.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The President clearly showed that he leaned toward alternative one, mainly
                        on the ground of Base security. The argument went around again with
                            <persName corresp="#p_WD1">Wilson</persName> voting for alternative two
                        and the Secretary of State for alternative one with certain word changes.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Mac Bundy</persName> at this point made a
                        heated defense of alternative two.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Mr. Sorensen said that the course of the argument had indicated to him
                        that neither alternative was adequate under the circumstances.</item>
                    <label>(7.</label>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJA1">McCone</persName> pointed out that a
                        recent report had indicated that Cuban training in SAM operations has now
                        entered a new phase wherein Cuban trainees are regularly passing target
                        tracking information. It was agreed that, in view of the fact that this
                        might presage early Cuban control of the SAM installations, there should be
                        an early review of plans for military retaliation.)</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The President chose alternative one.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_FD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Desmond FitzGerald</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Chief, Special Affairs Staff</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
