<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-04-22T17:38:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-04-22T17:38:00-05:00" n="313" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d313">
                        <head>313. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Chile</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d313fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, POL CHILE–<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_NODIS1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted and approved by <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-04-22T17:38:00-05:00">April 22, 1967, 5:38
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>180698. Sugarcane. Eyes Only for the Ambassador from Secretary.</p>
                        <p>At Punta del Este Valdez<note n="2" xml:id="d313fn2">Gabriel Valdez
                                Subercaseaux, Chilean Foreign Minister.</note> spoke to me about
                            Cuba and seemed to think that there are now some differences of view in
                            Havana which might be open to probing. I told him what I had many months
                            ago told Carrillo Flores of Mexico. The attitude of the United States
                            remains that indicated by President <persName corresp="#p_CKM1">Kennedy</persName>, namely, that Cuba could find its way back to
                            the Hemisphere if it (a) stopped its interference in the affairs of
                            other American states by agents, arms and propaganda, and (b) severed
                            its military association with the Soviet Union. I said that the internal
                            organization of Cuba is not the crucial obstacle but that these two
                            primary external forces were fundamental. As you will recall, these have
                            been the two key points all along. I added to Valdez that we have seen
                            no real evidence that <persName corresp="#p_CR1">Castro</persName> is
                            prepared to change his attitude on either point. Indeed, he seems to be
                            differing with Moscow on the question of interference in other
                            countries. Nonetheless, I told Valdez I saw no objection to any most
                            secret probes which he might wish to undertake and that if he got
                            anything of interest coming back we would be glad to know about it. I
                            further said that we would set up this special channel between you and
                            me in order to assure maximum secrecy and that he could be entirely
                            frank in passing on to you, and to you alone, anything that
                                develops.<note n="3" xml:id="d313fn3">Dungan reported to <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>, in telegram 283 from Santiago,
                                July 26, that Valdez had said the previous day that “there had been
                                no developments significant enough to pass on to you.” Valdez stated
                                that the Cubans had been interested in knowing whether the Chilean
                                probe was being made with the knowledge of the U.S. Government and
                                that they were told that “this strictly Chilean initiative.” Dungan
                                concluded the telegram by stating that it was his impression “that
                                matter is not being pushed aggressively.” (National Archives and
                                Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, POL
                                    CHILE–<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Regards.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>