<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-11-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="335" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d335">
                        <head>335. Memorandum From the Director of the Office of Caribbean Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_CKM1" type="from">Crockett</persName>) to the
                            Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MTC1" type="to">Mann</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d335fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, POL 15–1 HAITI.
                                Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-11-23">November 23, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The Multiple Dilemma in Formulating U.S. Policy on Haiti</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0815" n="780" xml:id="pg_780"/>
                        <p rend="center">PREMISE</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Continuation of the brutal Duvalier dictatorship and maintenance
                                by the U.S. of even minimal relationships with it are
                                disadvantageous to the United States because: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>Continuing economic deterioration, moral decay and despair
                                        of another alternative work to the advantage of the
                                        communists. In addition, only the most clandestine
                                        opposition can hope to survive under Duvalier, a situation
                                        more suited to communist organization and tacts than to
                                        non-communist opposition.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>Haitian oppositionists, along with many of our own people
                                        and the people of the Hemisphere, are unwilling to concede
                                        that the U.S. interest is better served by the maintenance
                                        of even a minimal relationship with the Duvalier
                                        dictatorship as contrasted to the moral advantage to be
                                        gained by a complete U.S. withdrawal from Haiti.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>The maintenance of a U.S. presence in Haiti is in the U.S.
                                interest because: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>The U.S. must be in the best position possible to protect
                                        the lives and property of its citizens in Haiti.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>Haiti has a voice in international forums (<gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss>, UN, etc.) which can be
                                        used for or against U.S. interests. Direct access to
                                        Duvalier is necessary in order to get maximum advantage for
                                        the U.S. from Haitiʼs vote and voice in international
                                        forums.</item>
                                    <label>(c)</label>
                                    <item>We must be on the scene if we are to have maximum
                                        influence on the course of events in Haiti when Duvalier
                                        goes.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center">ALTERNATIVE COURSES OF ACTION</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Actively consort with Duvalierʼs opposition to
                                        overthrow him.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The better Haitians, who are all in opposition to Duvalier, would
                                    be greatly heartened. Their bitterness toward the U.S. for
                                    tolerating Duvalier would be blunted. We would garner support
                                    for such a policy from many of our own people and the people of
                                    the Hemisphere who abhor Duvalier. If the policy resulted in
                                    Duvalierʼs overthrow, it would open the prospect for
                                    establishment of a less repugnant successor government.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>To undertake an interventionist policy such as this would be to
                                    assume very grave responsibility for the consequences. In the
                                    final analysis we can ensure the establishment and continuation
                                    of a less repugnant post-Duvalier government only if we are
                                    prepared to install and control it with force of arms if
                                    necessary. To undertake an interventionist <pb facs="0816" n="781" xml:id="pg_781"/> policy in Haiti without being
                                    prepared to go the whole way to ensure its success would be to
                                    invite a double curse on our house, i.e., (a) to have
                                    intervened, and (b) to have failed.</p>
                                <p>An interventionist policy in Haiti would represent a major shift
                                    of U.S. policy in Latin America. Our enemies would exploit it to
                                    the fullest. Many of our friends would see in it a precedent
                                    involving much greater dangers to their interests than does
                                    Duvalierʼs continuation. We could expect major and continuing
                                    criticism.</p>
                                <p>Assuming we were prepared to bear the consequences in order to do
                                    something meaningful for the Haitian people, the needs are so
                                    monumental that even the unrestrained application of our
                                    resources could be expected to make only a modest impact for at
                                    least a generation. Thus, the initial and continuing foreign
                                    policy price would be great. The long-term cost to our economy
                                    would be very high. But demonstrable and real benefits would be
                                    quite small, at least through the mid-term.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Work closely and fully with Duvalier despite
                                        his shortcomings.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Substantial input of funds and technical assistance would
                                    alleviate the great suffering of Haitiʼs masses to some extent
                                    in the short run and would offer improved prospects for the
                                    countryʼs future. A substantial U.S. developmental effort might
                                    give us some leverage in softening Duvalierʼs brutal oppression
                                    of the Haitian people.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>All of the better elements of Haiti (who are in opposition to
                                    Duvalier) would decry such a policy as strengthening Duvalierʼs
                                    hand at home and abroad. Many of our own people and the people
                                    of the Hemisphere would denounce our support of a brutal
                                    dictatorship. Experience has demonstrated that Duvalier prefers
                                    to forego U.S. assistance unless he can get it on his terms and
                                    exploit it to his maximum advantage. This would minimize
                                    benefits accruing to the Haitian people while maximizing
                                    benefits to Duvalier and his supporters. Reactivation of an
                                    assistance program in Haiti would be taken as a sign of U.S.
                                    weakness by Duvalier and would probably provide little if any
                                    additional leverage in dealing with him.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Maintain a U.S. presence in Haiti but make
                                        clear by word and deed our distaste for the Duvalier
                                        dictatorship.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The U.S. position would be clear for all to see. We would satisfy
                                    most of those who criticize us for consorting with Duvalier. We
                                    would continue to enjoy a presence in Haiti.</p>
                                <pb facs="0817" n="782" xml:id="pg_782"/>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>It is unlikely that Duvalier would long tolerate a U.S. presence
                                    in Haiti under these circumstances, but would force a
                                    confrontation offering two alternatives: (a) a softening of the
                                    policy, or (b) the expulsion of our Ambassador and possibly our
                                    entire mission. At the very least, our ability to exploit our
                                    presence in Haiti would be greatly circumscribed.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Maintain a U.S. presence in Haiti on as normal
                                        a basis as conditions there permit, but deny Duvalier U.S.
                                        endorsement or economic assistance.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Maintenance of a U.S. presence in Haiti on as normal a basis as
                                    possible permits maximum application of our influence in
                                    attaining our policy objectives. We will be on the scene and in
                                    a position to take quick and effective counter measures should a
                                    communist takeover threaten or occur either before or after
                                    Duvalierʼs demise.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>Maintenance of even limited relationships with the Duvalier
                                    dictatorship places us in an ambiguous position, especially for
                                    those who find it simpler to see all things in black and white.
                                    Criticism and bitterness will be engendered, creating problems
                                    for the U.S. now and in the future. Elements of the Haitian
                                    opposition who offer the best hope for the countryʼs future are
                                    estranged by such a policy. It is a difficult policy to
                                    implement because it has few tangible benefits for Duvalier.
                                    Consequently, he is constantly tempted to force a confrontation
                                    which might deny him the limited benefits he now enjoys over the
                                    short run but offers prospects of more tangible returns as the
                                    price for a future rapprochement. To stay this temptation,
                                    Duvalier must be kept in doubt about future U.S. intentions and
                                    the value which the U.S. places on maintaining a presence in
                                    Haiti.</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center">CONCLUSION</p>
                        <p>Despite the disadvantages, Course of Action (4) is clearly the least
                            unattractive of the alternatives open to the U.S.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>