<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>342. Intelligence Memorandum</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d342</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">342</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-05-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-05-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HPZNpQil9Rnjj" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-civil-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026387"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil Service</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-05-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-05-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="342"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d342">
                <head>342. Intelligence Memorandum<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d342fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INRIL1">INR/IL</gloss> Historical
                        Files, 303 Committee Records. Secret. Prepared in the Office of Current
                        Intelligence of the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>. Secret; No Foreign
                        Dissem.; Controlled Dissem. A May 14 memorandum from <persName
                            corresp="#p_WMD1">Murat W. Williams</persName> (<gloss target="#t_INR1"
                            >INR</gloss>) to <persName corresp="#p_VJH1">Vaughn</persName> noted
                        that this memorandum was circulated at the May 13 meeting of the 303
                        Committee. The Committee agreed that “a small group of determined insurgents
                        could unseat Duvalier.” <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Bundy</persName> directed
                        that State and the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> “coordinate on
                        investigating alternative sources of political power in Haiti,” since
                        Duvalierʼs days might be numbered and the United States “should not be
                        caught short.” (Ibid., Country File, Haiti)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">OCI No. 1754/65</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-05-13">May 13, 1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">INSTABILITY IN HAITI</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Since Francois Duvalierʼs accession to power in 1957, he has attempted to
                        destroy every force which could possibly overthrow him. <pb facs="0827"
                            n="792" xml:id="pg_792"/> The military, which has been the traditional
                        kingmaker in Haiti, lost most of its power in 1958 when the National
                        Security Volunteers (VSN-Militia) and the secret police (Ton-Ton
                        Macoute-bogeymen) were created as counterforces. Since that time there have
                        been repeated purges within the military. Those who have been purged have
                        been replaced by Duvalier favorites who owe their positions to him. A civil
                        service does not exist. All government employees are hired on the basis of
                        their loyalty to Duvalier. Even cabinet officers are changed frequently to
                        prevent their building up any following. Discontent is believed to be
                        widespread, but opposition, both real and imagined, is ruthlessly and
                        immediately suppressed.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Over the years there have been numerous incursions by anti-Duvalier
                        Haitian exiles. In August and September 1963 several incursions took place
                        on the northern border area, the last with a force of over 100 men. These
                        expeditions met with failure, however, because Duvalier was alerted and
                        because of the poor leadership of the exile commander, Brig. Gen. Leon
                        Cantave. Cantave has since lost exile support.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>From June to September 1964 two separate groups invaded Haiti. One group
                        of about 30 came from the Dominican Republic and operated in the
                        southeastern portion of the southern peninsula for several weeks, then
                        crossed back into the neighboring republic where they were temporarily
                        interned by Dominican officials. The other group landed on the southwestern
                        portion and was comprised of 13 men. This group was probably the best
                        trained and equipped that has operated in Haiti. The Haitian military were
                        unable to engage them for several months, but the group was finally worn
                        down until all had been captured and killed. It is significant to note that
                        a force of only 13 men operating in the countryside were capable of running
                        the Haitian Armed forces (FAdH) ragged for several months. The FAdH was
                        demoralized at its inability to engage the enemy. There were complaints that
                        the army lacked good field support and sufficient supplies. Another
                        widespread complaint was that the VSN—Duvalierʼs favorite—was not up to the
                        task of fighting for the country.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The last two incursions were eventually beaten back, but only at great
                        cost to the economy. Haiti has been unable to recover fully and is now in
                        serious economic straits. Government employees are not paid for months on
                        end. The Duvalier government has repeatedly asked for <gloss target="#t_US1"
                            >US</gloss> economic aid. Following its vote in the <gloss
                            target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> to back the <gloss target="#t_US1"
                            >US</gloss> in its actions in the Dominican Republic Haiti may seek “its
                        reward.”</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Although Haitian exiles are agreed that Duvalier must be overthrown, they
                        are divided amongst themselves. The exile factions work singly without
                        overall direction and therefore are unable to put large groups in the field.
                        Last yearʼs defeats also have served to dampen exile spirits.</item>
                    <pb facs="0828" n="793" xml:id="pg_793"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>During the past several weeks we have had reports that some Haitian exiles
                        are fighting with the rebels in the Dominican Republic. These exiles are
                        probably led by Andre Riviere, a French soldier of fortune. He is reported
                        to have fought in Indochina, and is an expert in guerrilla tactics. In the
                        past several years Riviere has instructed anti-Duvalier exiles—numbering
                        about 70–100—in the Dominican Republic. Those Haitians presently fighting
                        with the rebels may be some of those which he has trained. One of the
                        exilesʼ perennial complaints was that they lacked arms; however, they may
                        have acquired some from the Dominicans. At present Riviere—who reportedly
                        has had Communist ties in the past—is a translator and military adviser to
                        Manuel Montes Arache—one of the leaders of the Dominican rebel
                        command.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">16 lines of source text not declassified</hi>] Radio
                        Havana has long been trying to incite the Haitian people to overthrow the
                        dictatorship. Recently these broadcasts, in the Creole language, have
                        included excerpts from “Che” Guevaraʼs guerrilla warfare book. [<hi
                            rend="italic">2½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>]</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Should exiles be able to mount an incursion on several fronts
                        simultaneously, with small, well-trained groups who could be resupplied, the
                        Duvalier regime could be overthrown. Depressed economic conditions in Haiti
                        limit the governmentʼs ability to finance protracted military
                        operations.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>This paper has the concurrence of WH/DDP and O/NE.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
