<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-05-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="354" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                        <head>354. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_BWG1" type="from">William
                                G. Bowdler</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            Presidentʼs Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d354fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Agency File, SIG,
                                6th Mtg., 4/19/66, Vol. I. Secret.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-05-02">May 2, 1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>SIG Meeting: Haitian Contingency Paper</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The situation in Haiti has “stabilized” itself again after the plotting
                            of three weeks ago. But conditions continue to be sufficiently unstable
                            to make a sudden upheaval a possibility at any time. Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_TBEL1">Timmons</persName> is coming from
                            Port-au-Prince today to give the SIG the latest estimate.</p>
                        <p>The contingency paper before the SIG is an incomplete and not very lucid
                                draft.<note n="2" xml:id="d354fn2">
                                <ref target="#d353">Document 353</ref>.</note> The most important
                            annexes (explained below) are missing. The paper itself was prepared
                            according to a pre-determined standard format dictated by an IBM
                            approach to problems and suffers from all the corresponding rigidities.
                            My efforts to have papers tailored to individual country situations have
                            foundered on bureaucratic requirements levied on <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> by higher authority.</p>
                        <p>The paperʼs principal value is that it identifies the various ways which
                            the ball might bounce if Duvalier falls or a serious effort to dislodge
                            him materializes. In trying to anticipate specific Latin American and
                            Communist reactions to various contingencies and prescribe fixed courses
                            of action, the paper is unrealistic, although there is some utility in
                            at least thinking through the possibilities. What we do in a given
                            situation will depend upon the circumstances prevailing at the time
                            which may be quite different from those anticipated in the paper.</p>
                        <p>In the <gloss target="#t_IRG1">IRG</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> review of this paper, I insisted on the preparation of
                            three annexes which should be kept up to date: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>list of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> personnel with
                                    Haitian expertise who could be used in Haiti or Washington in a
                                    crisis situation.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>list of acceptable Haitians in Haiti or in exile whom we could
                                    tap to man a provisional government.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>list of immediate economic measures which we could take
                                    following the fall of Duvalier to quiet unrest, buttress the
                                    provisional government and get the economy moving again.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0861" n="826" xml:id="pg_826"/>
                        <p>As you and I discussed earlier, these three lists, plus the military
                            contingency plans, are the guts of realistic planning in that they will
                            enable us to act with maximum speed in any situation.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_IRG1">IRG</gloss> agreed to include all three lists
                            as annexes. They are in various stages of preparation but none ready to
                            be included in the package which the SIG will consider tomorrow.</p>
                        <p>I recommend that at the SIG you take this position: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The SIG should take note of the paper as a useful planning
                                        document.<note n="3" xml:id="d354fn3">A Record of Agreements
                                        and Decisions of the SIG meeting of May 3 reported that the
                                        Group considered the draft contingency plans on Haiti and
                                        agreed that, if possible, the United States should avoid
                                        placing its forces in Haiti for any purpose other than rapid
                                        evacuation of U.S. and certain other citizens, and that the
                                        contingency plans should not be discussed with other members
                                        of the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss>. (Johnson
                                        Library, National Security File, Agency File, SIG, 6th Mtg.,
                                        4/19/66, Vol. I)</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The SIG should ask <gloss target="#t_IRG1">IRG</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> to: <list>
                                        <label>a)</label>
                                        <item>complete the annexes and keep them up to date as a
                                            matter of top priority.</item>
                                        <label>b)</label>
                                        <item>revise the paper to make explicit references to the
                                            annexes and relate them to the corresponding sections of
                                            the paper.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BWG1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">WGB</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>