<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>359. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d359</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">359</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-12-18T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recuvwbOC4H2MyRrN" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Amphibious force</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-12-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-12-18T18:00:00-05:00" n="359" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d359">
                <head>359. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>In November 1966 rumors began to circulate in Haiti and in Miami, Florida, that
                    an invasion of Haiti was imminent, with Miami and the Dominican Republic
                    mentioned as staging areas. In a November 11 memorandum from <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> to the President, also sent as an
                    unnumbered telegram to the LBJ Ranch, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1"
                        >Rostow</persName> reported that there was no “hard information of any
                    muscle” behind impending coup plans but that officials of the Central
                    Intelligence Agency and the Departments of Defense and State were meeting that
                    morning to review contingency plans and ensure that “the Caribbean Amphibious
                    Force is in position to react promptly in case of need.” (Johnson Library,
                    National <pb facs="0872" n="837" xml:id="pg_837"/> Security File, Country File,
                    Haiti, Vol. IV) <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName> reported to the
                    President the following day that Duvalier had dismissed or retired 17 Haitian
                    military officers without first arresting them, indicating that the dictator was
                    “sure of his ground.” (Ibid.)</p>
                <p>A November 14 memorandum from the Director of the Federal Bureau of
                    Investigation, sent by telegram to the President, the Secretary of State, and
                    the Directors of Central Intelligence and Defense Intelligence among others,
                    reported that Rolando Masferrer, an exiled former Cuban senator, had organized
                    an invasion force in the Miami area to overthrow Duvalier, and was attempting to
                    charter a boat capable of carrying 300 men. (Ibid.) In a November 17 note to
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BWG1"
                        >Bowdler</persName> reported that he had relayed the substance of the FBI
                    memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SRM1">Sayre</persName>, who reassured him
                    that the enforcement agencies had their own people inside the ranks of the
                    expeditionary group and would “move against Masferrer when the time is right.”
                    (Ibid.) Telegram 88010 to Santo Domingo and Port-au-Prince, November 18,
                    reported that a Department officer had told the Haitian Chargé that “the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> would not permit such activities on its soil”
                    and authorized the Ambassador to so inform Foreign Minister Chalmers. (National
                    Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964–66, POL 23–7
                    HAI)</p>
                <p>Telegram 1914 from Santo Domingo, December 16, reported <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJH1">Crimmins</persName>ʼ discussion with President <persName
                        corresp="#p_BJ1">Balaguer</persName> the previous day. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJH1">Crimmins</persName> said that U.S. policy toward Duvalier
                    was essentially passive, stating that “we are neither helping him stay in office
                    nor in any way abetting his overthrow.” <persName corresp="#p_BJ1"
                        >Balaguer</persName> replied that he “in effect could not care less about
                    Duvalier and Haiti.” Concerning invasion activity, <persName corresp="#p_BJ1"
                        >Balaguer</persName> said that Haitians and Cubans were still preparing
                    plans, bases, and supplies in the Dominican Republic, but that the Dominican
                    military had raided their Manzanillo camp, seized their arms cache, and were
                    deporting three Cuban “no-good adventurers.” (Ibid., POL 23–9 HAI) Telegrams
                    111362 and 112102 to Port-au-Prince, January 3 and 4, 1967, reported that U.S.
                    Customs Service agents arrested 75 persons from Masferrerʼs group during the
                    night of January 2, seized two boats, arms, and ammunition. (Both ibid.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
