<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Panama ( (Price))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1921v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1921-02-28T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1921-02-28T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-02-28T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-02-28T14:00:00-05:00" n="150"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">718.1915/296a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Panama</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Price</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-02-28T14:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 28, 1921—2 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>15. This Government views with concern the growing acuteness in the relations
                    between Panama and Costa Rica. The territorial question on which Costa Rica and
                    Panama are divided has twice been the subject of disinterested and judicial
                    examination upon the joint submission of both Governments.</p>
                <p>In the first instance, the matter was submitted to the President of the French
                    Republic, and after much time spent in its investigation, the so-called Loubet
                    award was made. When this award in turn gave rise to controversy as to its
                    intention and application, a new submission, after the lapse of several years,
                    was made to the Chief Justice of the United States Supreme Court. Again an
                    exhaustive examination was made of the whole controversy and an award made by
                    the highest judicial authority and in the most disinterested spirit, which has
                    not been accepted by Panama. It is difficult for us to see what can be gained by
                    a proffer of good offices or any other form of friendly interposition in the
                    present phase of this longstanding dispute. Such interposition could only point
                    to further examination of the matter in controversy and a third arbitral
                    decision of it. In view of the two instances in which this mode of adjustment
                    has been sought, it seems idle either to recommend it or to look upon it as a
                    method with any particular chance or promise of bringing the controversy to a
                    conclusion. It is the opinion of the Department that both Panama and Costa Rica
                    should desist from hostile demonstrations or armed activities, and thus afford
                    an opportunity for a discussion and agreement as to the manner in which the
                    terms of Chief Justice White’s decision shall be applied, paying due regard to
                    any contentions that may be advanced by either party bearing upon the
                    subject.</p>
                <p>We are communicating the substance of the above to our Legation at Costa Rica for
                    submission to the Costa Rican government, adding <pb facs="0300" n="176"
                        xml:id="pg_176"/> an expression of regret that Costa Rica should have seen
                    fit to act so precipitately and without notification of its intention and
                    suggesting the recall of her forces and complete avoidance of military action or
                    the threat of such action, pending adjustment as herein mentioned. The same
                    action should be taken simultaneously by Panama.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Colby</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
