<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-09-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-09-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="197" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d197">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/1328</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Fletcher</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-09-21"><hi rend="italic">September 21,
                                    1921</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The Chilean Ambassador called by appointment today, and gave me to read,
                            in confidence, a personal letter to him from the President of Chile, as
                            well as the original instruction from his Government on the subject of
                            the steps Chile is now ready to take for the solution of the Tacna–Arica
                            question. The instruction, after referring to what was said by the
                            President of Chile in his annual message to Congress on the subject of
                            the solution of this long-standing question, informed the Ambassador
                            that the Chilean Government intended to invite the Peruvian Government
                            to proceed to carry out the Treaty of Ancon by the holding of a
                            plebiscite on the bases provided for in the Huneeus–Valera Protocol<note n="45" xml:id="d197fn45">For negotiations relating to this protocol,
                                see <ref target="frus1913#pg_1222"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1913, pp. 1222</ref> ff.</note> (copy
                            attached), without prejudicing the consideration of such other bases as
                            Peru may suggest, provided that such bases should contemplate the
                            definitive settlement of the sovereignty by means of the plebiscite as
                            has been done by the various plebiscites celebrated under the Treaty of
                            Versailles. The instruction stated further that in view of the
                            possibility that Peru would refuse to accept the bases above mentioned,
                            the Ambassador should inform this Government unofficially of the
                            intention of the Chilean Government as above set forth, and suggest
                            also, unofficially, that in such case this Government should
                            spontaneously suggest to Peru and Chile the bases on which the
                            plebiscite should be held, which would be agreed upon before-hand
                            between the Governments of Chile and the United States.</p>
                        <p>After congratulating the Ambassador upon the decision of his Government
                            to initiate negotiations for the settlement of this longstanding
                            controversy, I asked him how his Government proposed to approach the
                            Peruvian Government, whether directly or through another Government. He
                            informed me that Mr. Carlos Castro Ruiz (who was Under Secretary of
                            Foreign. Affairs during my term of service in Chile, and later Consul
                            General in New York) had been appointed Counsellor of Embassy, and had
                            brought with him this instruction, as well as other verbal instructions
                            of his Government. He said that Mr. Castro had informed him that the
                            Chilean Government would probably extend its invitation to the Peruvian
                            Government through the President of Uruguay. I asked him whether he
                            believed that his Government would be prepared to modify the bases of
                            the Huneeus–Valera Protocol, and I referred <pb facs="0368" n="244" xml:id="pg_244"/> especially to the stipulation that the plebiscite
                            Commission should be presided over by the Chief Justice of the Supreme
                            Court of Chile. The Ambassador replied that he felt confident that his
                            Government would not insist on this feature, and, in his opinion, would
                            be willing to accept the Chief Justice of Uruguay, or some other
                            impartial country, if Peru should propose that as an alternative. The
                            Ambassador gave me the impression that his Government really desired to
                            come to terms with Peru on the plebiscite, and dispose of this
                            question.</p>
                        <p>I told the Ambassador that if he would give me a confidential memorandum
                            of the pertinent portions of the instruction which I had read, I would
                            be very glad to lay it before the Secretary of State, and to let him
                            know the result as soon as possible. The Ambassador promised to send me
                            this memorandum at once, and requested that the matter be held in the
                            strictest confidence.</p>
                        <closer>[No signature indicated]</closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Bases of Plebiscite as per Huneeus–Valera
                                    Protocol</hi></head>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">First</hi>. It was agreed to postpone the
                                    plebiscite until 1933.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Second</hi>. The plebiscite was to be taken
                                    under the jurisdiction of a mixed commission composed of two
                                    Peruvian delegates and two Chilean delegates and presided over
                                    by the President of the Supreme Court of Chile.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Third</hi>. Natives of Tacna and Arica and
                                    the Chileans and Peruvians who were not born there but who had
                                    resided three years in the territory were to be entitled to
                                    vote.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Fourth</hi>. Diplomatic relations were to be
                                    re-established by the appointment of Ministers in both
                                    countries.</item>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Fifth</hi>. The Government of Chile was to
                                    pay to the Government of Peru five hundred thousand pounds for
                                    the occupation of the disputed territory, extending over
                                    twenty-one years.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>