<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1921-07-19T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1921-07-19T16:00:00-05:00" n="626" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d626">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">818.6363 Am 6/90: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chargé in Costa Rica</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Thurston</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1921-07-19T17:00:00-04:00"><hi rend="italic">July 19,
                                        1921—5 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>36. Your 108, July 15, 10 a.m.</p>
                        <p>You may advise the Minister for Foreign Affairs that the statements made
                            by this Government to the British Government with respect to the Amory
                            concession can not be construed as granting the British Foreign Office
                                <hi rend="italic">carte blanche</hi> in negotiations with the
                            Government of Costa Rica regarding that concession in the sense that the
                            result would be in any way binding upon the United States. The
                            Department has advised the British Government that in its opinion the
                            holders of the concession have access to the courts of Costa Rica,
                            constitutionally set up, in which the matter in dispute may be made the
                            subject of appropriate judicial determination. The British Government
                            was further advised that this statement should not, however, be taken as
                            implying that the Government of the United States would oppose an
                            arbitration if that course should commend itself to the Costa Rican
                            authorities.</p>
                        <p>When this explanation of the negotiations between this Government and the
                            British Government has been made to the Minister for Foreign Affairs,
                            you should add that while this Government would not oppose arbitration
                            of the question if the Costa Rican <pb facs="0789" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/> authorities desire it, this Government and its
                            nationals could not consider themselves bound by any arbitral award
                            which might be rendered as they would not be parties to the
                            arbitration.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hughes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>