<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>152. Paper Prepared by the National Security Council Staff</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-08-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-08-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recNHstTN4mCmPSgR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011305"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Missile defense</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-08-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-08-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="152"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                <head>152. Paper Prepared by the National Security Council Staff<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d152fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H-Files), Box H–047,
                        Senior Review Group Meetings, Senior Review Group—Military Assistance to
                        Israel—Chile (97) 8/19/70. Secret; Nodis. The paper prepared by the <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Interdepartmental Group for the Near East,
                        “U.S. Arms Assistance to Israel: Military and Diplomatic Options,” undated,
                        which is summarized here, is attached. A cover memorandum by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SHH_1">Saunders</persName> is attached but not printed. All
                        brackets are in the original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-08-18">August 18, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">ANALYTICAL SUMMARY</p>
                <p rend="center">U.S. ARMS ASSISTANCE TO ISRAEL</p>
                <p rend="center">Military and Diplomatic Options</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">I.</hi> What the Paper Represents</p>
                <p>The paper at the next tab [“IG Paper”] was written in the following way:</p>
                <p>—A Defense Department task force, which has been working with the Israeli weapons
                    problem for the past seven weeks, identified a series of Israeli strategy
                    options for defending the Suez cease-fire line.</p>
                <p>—At Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>’s request,
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1">Hal Saunders</persName> put these options in
                    policy context in the cover memo at the next tab. This memo (1) states the pros
                    and cons of each military option, (2) identifies the next steps in a military
                    assistance scenario from now to November and (3) makes a preliminary effort to
                    relate those steps to the next steps in the diplomatic scenario.</p>
                <p>—Defense and State both made refinements and the full Defense study<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d152fn2">See <ref target="#d150fn2">footnote 2, Document
                        150</ref>.</note> is attached to the policy paper.</p>
                <p>—<persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName>’s Interdepartmental Group endorsed
                    the paper Monday.<note n="3" xml:id="d152fn3">August 17.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">II.</hi> A Preview of the Decisions Required</p>
                <p>It would be <hi rend="italic">desirable to reach conclusions on a general
                        framework within which our military assistance relationship with Israel can
                        proceed.</hi> These conclusions can be reported to the President for
                    decision after the meeting since major dissent does not seem likely. <hi
                        rend="italic">Three major points should be addressed:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>A. <hi rend="italic">What range of Israeli military strategies for defending the
                        Suez cease-fire line is the U.S. prepared to support if the cease-fire
                        breaks down?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The options are ranged in the next section of this summary with a view to setting
                    aside those which seem infeasible or undesirable. This <pb facs="0544" n="511"
                        xml:id="pg_511"/> process of elimination leaves a range of options which <hi
                        rend="italic">could</hi> be discussed with the Israelis if we wish for
                    political reasons to invite them into consultations on strategy. They <hi
                        rend="italic">should</hi> be discussed if any precise strategy is to be
                    chosen because there are questions which only the Israelis can answer.</p>
                <p>B. <hi rend="italic">Shall we invite Israeli military planners to consult with us
                        on a sensible equipment package within the range of strategies the U.S. is
                        prepared to support?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The basic answer is really stated above—YES. The issue is what limits to place.
                    Defense is wary of anything that smacks of formal joint planning but would go
                    along with some fairly detailed talks with Israeli military officials on the
                    reasoning behind the various options we have identified. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName> wants such detailed talks as a means of
                    bringing the Israelis to face the financial and military realities of their
                    present situation as well as to provide the general assurance of cooperation the
                    Israelis need. A decision is required on the limits to be imposed on these
                    talks.</p>
                <p>C. <hi rend="italic">How should this invitation be timed to relate to the
                        diplomatic scenario?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This is least clear because it is still uncertain how the diplomatic scenario
                    will play itself out. The invitation to discuss strategies should be issued
                    fairly soon so it is important to identify what we should seek in connection
                    with it since this is the main “carrot” we will have to offer in the next few
                    weeks.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">III.</hi> The Military Options</p>
                <p>For the sake of simplifying, the options are grouped below to facilitate the
                    process of narrowing and focusing. For the same reason, they are dealt with here
                    in reverse order.</p>
                <p>—The <hi rend="italic">options are described</hi> fully in the attached paper at
                    pp. II:3–7. A small tab marked “Options” identifies these pages.</p>
                <p>—An <hi rend="italic">equipment package for each</hi> option is in the annex
                    paper at a small tab marked “Packages.” You do not need to get into the
                    packages, but you may wish to take a quick look to see what is involved.</p>
                <p>—A full statement of <hi rend="italic">pros and cons</hi> appears in Section III
                    of the IG paper at the next tab; it is marked with a tab, “Pros and Cons.”</p>
                <p>A. <hi rend="italic">Options Most Quickly Set Aside</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Alternative 6: Prepare for full-scale U.S. intervention.</hi>
                    This option is included by Defense “only to show that beyond a certain point in
                    the Israeli capabilities described below U.S. involvement is probably the next
                    step.”</p>
                <pb facs="0545" n="512" xml:id="pg_512"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Alternative 5: Provide a surge capability for pre-emptive
                        strikes against deep Egyptian targets as a possible prelude to ground
                        invasion.</hi> The Israeli need to administer a serious blow is recognized,
                    and some would make the argument that the U.S. has an interest in showing the
                    USSR’s vulnerability. But no one-time Israeli strike seems likely to be decisive
                    in the longer perspective if the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is
                    committed to get Egyptian territory back, and the risk of Soviet retaliation
                    would be serious.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Alternative 4–B: Provide continuous forward SAM-attrition
                        capability.</hi> This was the Israeli strategy before the cease-fire of
                    seeking capability to <hi rend="italic">attack the missile sites
                        themselves.</hi> It is the judgment of the Pentagon task force that this is
                    militarily infeasible for these reasons:</p>
                <p>—The Soviet-UAR missile defense is denser, more sophisticated and better manned
                    than anything the <gloss target="#t_USAF_1">USAF</gloss> flew against in North
                    Vietnam, and the <gloss target="#t_USAF_1">USAF</gloss> adopted a strategy of
                    not attacking the sites but of trying to suppress them while attacking other
                    targets.</p>
                <p>—The Soviet capacity to replace sites is probably greater than Israeli capacity
                    to destroy them.</p>
                <p>—Israel probably cannot afford this strategy. Pentagon gaming suggests this
                    strategy would cost Israel $100 million a month. That would include losses of 12
                    Phantoms and 16 Skyhawks a month.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">NOTE:</hi> There is very little feeling in the Pentagon that
                    this is even a feasible strategy for Israel to consider. However, <hi
                        rend="italic">the following question should be asked: Is this strategy
                        infeasible only because the U.S. is not prepared to supply its most advanced
                        munitions for stand-off pinpoint bombing?</hi> [There are a few weapons
                    specialists who feel that this strategy might become feasible if the U.S. were
                    prepared to give Israel such things as laser bombs. The argument for using this
                    technology would be to demonstrate U.S. superiority.]</p>
                <p>B. <hi rend="italic">Options to be Most Seriously Argued</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The strategies outlined below are not necessarily mutually exclusive, and the
                    answer may be some combination of them. However, there does seem to be a special
                    choice between 3–B and some combination of the rest. The question is whether the
                    Israelis need the capability to attack Egyptian artillery sites badly enough to
                    warrant the cost.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Alternative 3–B: Provide continuous gun-attrition
                        capability.</hi> This would—by heavy jamming—permit continuous Israeli
                    attacks on front-line artillery positions in a 5–10 mile zone west of the Canal.
                    The main argument for this approach is that the Israelis have maintained they
                    could not sustain the losses from Egyptian artillery barrages. This is why they
                    began their steady air raids in July 1969. However, the Pentagon estimates this
                    strategy might cost the Israelis $70 million a month in munitions and lost
                    aircraft alone. Moreover, some in the Pentagon <pb facs="0546" n="513"
                        xml:id="pg_513"/> feel that Israel could hold its position on the Suez
                    cease-fire line with a much less costly strategy (see Alternatives 1 and 2
                    below).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Alternatives 3–A and 4–A: Provide a one-time surge capability
                        to silence guns (3–A) and forward <gloss target="#t_SAM_1">SAM</gloss> sites
                        (4–A) on the west bank to defeat a canal-crossing build-up.</hi> These two
                    alternatives differ more in numbers than in types of equipment. The equipment
                    involved would cost just under $15 million. These strategies by themselves would
                    probably not be sufficient because they do not provide means for coping with
                    day-to-day Egyptian firing across the Canal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Alternatives 1 and 2: Provide additional equipment for better
                        air defense and for defeating an armored invasion into the Sinai (2) and
                        equipment for infiltration control (1).</hi> This package would include more
                    armor and anti-aircraft weapons to a one-time total of about $95 million for the
                    heavy equipment and another $15 million for intelligence and anti-infiltration
                    equipment. Some of the tanks are already being provided.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">NOTE:</hi> The <hi rend="italic">question to be asked</hi>
                    about this alternative is whether the Israelis could stay on the Canal without
                    some capacity to bomb steadily across the Canal. Some Pentagon answers are that
                    the Israelis could further reduce the number of men on the Canal and rely on
                    sensors to identify raiding parties. A mobile force could then be moved rapidly
                    to meet any such group. Others in the Pentagon, however, feel that some Israeli
                    capacity to bomb Egyptian gun positions across the Canal (Alternative 3–B above)
                    would remain necessary.</p>
                <p>C. <hi rend="italic">Issues in Devising a Combination of Strategies</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Minimum.</hi> If deep raids and continuous attacks on the
                    SAM’s are ruled out, Alternatives 1, 2 and 3–A—4–A would seem to be a minimum.
                    This would give the Israelis the capability to defend the Sinai with insurance
                    in a one-strike capability to defeat a build-up on the west bank for a
                    canal-crossing. This could all be done for about $125 million.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">The issue</hi> is whether Alternative 3–B—the ability to
                    bomb the gun positions continuously is necessary. This is where costs mount—to
                    $70 million a month in expendable items alone. The decision depends on:</p>
                <p>—Whether the Israelis feel they can give up cross-Canal bombing <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi>
                </p>
                <p>—Whether it is in the U.S. interest to let the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1"
                        >USSR</gloss> establish the fact that its defense of the <gloss
                        target="#t_UAR_1">UAR</gloss> is invulnerable.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> The Central Political-Military Issue</p>
                <p>One of the central conclusions of the Pentagon study is that the military
                    situation across the Canal may finally have reached one of near balance—or
                    stand-off. The Egyptians still are unable to cross the Canal without direct
                    Soviet involvement. The Israelis are unable to fly across <pb facs="0547"
                        n="514" xml:id="pg_514"/> the Canal steadily without incurring expensive
                    losses which only the U.S. can replace or to cross the Canal in force without
                    risking Soviet retaliation.</p>
                <p>In some ways the situation has become more unstable because the Israelis in
                    increasing desperation may launch a ground attack against the Soviet system.</p>
                <p>In other ways, by strengthening Israel’s defensive position it is possible to
                    demonstrate to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> that only its own
                    direct involvement in a cross-canal attack will make such a crossing possible.
                    In other words, a stable, long-term stand-off might still be possible if the
                    Israelis could see their way clear to adopt it.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The central military issue, therefore, is whether the Israelis
                        could and would be willing to adopt a strategy that would not require them
                        to cross the Canal on a regular basis.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Ideally, the U.S. could have reason for wanting to see the continuing
                    ineffectiveness of the Soviet <gloss target="#t_SAM_1">SAM</gloss> system
                    demonstrated. However, a cost of $70 million monthly and up, may outweigh any
                    advantage.</p>
                <p>However, only the Israelis can factor out the relative costs and advantages in
                    this choice. That is why consultation is necessary to determine whether
                    Alternative 3–B should be added to Alternatives 1, 2 and 3–A—4–A.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">V.</hi> Should We Consult With Israel?</p>
                <p>For the reason described in the last section—we do not know all the factors
                    involved in Israel’s selection of strategy—and for the sake of giving Israel the
                    reassurance of continuing consultation, consultation on these strategy choices
                    seems necessary:</p>
                <p>—first, to establish with Israel that attacking the <gloss target="#t_SAM_1"
                        >SAM</gloss> sites (Alternative 4–B) is too costly;</p>
                <p>—second, to develop a combination of the remaining lesser options.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">main issue</hi> is to determine a format that would avoid
                    the over-commitment of formal joint planning and yet provide the framework for
                    necessary consultation. Defense should be asked for a scenario.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">VI.</hi> Diplomatic Scenario</p>
                <p>Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Sisco</persName> should be asked
                    to discuss this in greater detail. However, in very general terms, it seems
                    helpful to consider the military assistance and diplomatic scenarios in three
                    phases:</p>
                <pb facs="0548" n="515" xml:id="pg_515"/>
                <p>A. Phase I—between now and late September when the foreign ministers gather in
                    New York.<note n="4" xml:id="d152fn4">At the 25th session of the <gloss
                            target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> General Assembly, which convened on
                        September 15.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. The main <hi rend="italic">military</hi> move would be to offer full
                    consultations on strategy.</p>
                <p>2. The main <hi rend="italic">diplomatic</hi> move would be to persuade the
                    Israelis to advance negotiable positions in the early stages of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_JGV_1">Jarring</persName> talks.</p>
                <p>B. <hi rend="italic">Phase II</hi>—mid-September to November 5 when the
                    cease-fire expires.</p>
                <p>1. The main <hi rend="italic">military</hi> move would be U.S. approval for some
                    combination of Israeli strategies for defending the Suez cease-fire line if the
                    cease-fire breaks down or expires. The first deliveries of earmarked aircraft
                    are also due in this period.</p>
                <p>2. The main <hi rend="italic">diplomatic</hi> move is difficult to foresee.
                    However, while we might try to avoid a major crunch with Israel over withdrawal
                    in this period, we will have to produce enough Israeli movement to persuade the
                    Arabs that it is worthwhile renewing the cease-fire.</p>
                <p>C. <hi rend="italic">Phase III</hi>—after November 5.</p>
                <p>1. The main <hi rend="italic">military</hi> move would be approval of (a) some
                    $500 million in financial assistance and (b) a package that might make Israeli
                    withdrawal possible. [This should be the subject of the next phase of in-house
                    planning.]</p>
                <p>2. The main diplomatic move—should we be so lucky—would be an effort to gain
                    Israeli acceptance of the final peace agreement.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
