<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>159. Memorandum From Harold Saunders and and HoskinsonSamuelof the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Samuelof the National Security Council Staff to the President’s
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d159</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">159</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-09-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124537"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Atmospheric</term>
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                    <term ref="recr08QgEMEm1Bk04" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037035"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deployment</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-09-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="159"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d159">
                <head>159. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1">Harold Saunders</persName>
                    and <persName corresp="#p_HSM_1">Hoskinson</persName>Samuelof the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d159fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 656, Country
                        Files, Middle East, Mideast Ceasefire, Vol. II. Top Secret; Sensitive. Sent
                        for information. It was sent back to <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1"
                            >Saunders</persName> to answer <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>’s query; see <ref target="#d159fn2">footnote
                            2</ref> below. All brackets are in the original except those indicating
                        text that remains classified.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-09-08">September 8, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Intelligence on Egyptian and Soviet Cease-Fire Violations</item>
                </list>
                <p>You may well have had enough of the numbers game on Egyptian and Soviet
                    violations of the military standstill. However, we have been making a major
                    effort to reduce this complex intelligence problem to some simple propositions
                    the policy-maker can work from without at the same time losing sight of the
                    limitations involved. The following analysis includes the latest intelligence on
                    the SAMs but it does not reveal the response on the ground to our more recent
                    démarches in Cairo and Moscow. In other words, this memo brings the situation up
                    to the day on which those démarches were made and tries to bridge the gap
                    between the analysts’ problems and the policy-maker’s needs.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Intelligence Problems</p>
                <p>First of all, it is important to note the limitations and problems associated
                    with our intelligence on possible cease-fire violations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Photographic intelligence</hi> can tell us a great deal but,
                    despite all the technical sophistication that goes into this kind of analysis,
                    it is far from being a highly developed art and has some important limitations.
                    There are two main types of problems:</p>
                <pb facs="0567" n="534" xml:id="pg_534"/>
                <p>1. To cover adequately the Egyptian cease-fire zone it is necessary to have
                    photography taken with both high and low resolution cameras. The low resolution
                    photography is necessary to cover the whole area but it can only identify the
                    more general features of suspected <gloss target="#t_SAM_1">SAM</gloss> sites
                    and usually not the more specific details which reveal such important facts as
                    status (i.e. operational or not) and type of occupancy. High resolution
                    photography is therefore taken to make up for these inadequacies, but it covers
                    a much smaller area.</p>
                <p>2. Most of our photography is low resolution and taken at a wide angle from the
                    U–2s. In addition to the resolution limitation, the obliqueness of the U–2
                    coverage is another limitation since the farther away the target is the less
                    detail we are able to identify and even then not all the area can be adequately
                    covered in each flight. We can monitor most developments fairly well up to about
                    10 miles from the canal but beyond that the quality begins to taper off
                    significantly. We have begun using a new higher resolution camera with the U–2s
                    but again this presents the dilemma of being able to identify more detail but
                    covering less area. Many gaps can be at least partially filled by using a
                    combination of regular high and low resolution U–2 coverage supplemented by
                    periodic high and low resolution satellite coverage.</p>
                <p>3. There are a variety of other technical problems. These include such things as
                    weather near the ground, upper atmospheric conditions, terrain features and the
                    condition of the film and its development. The human analytical factor also
                    plays a big role since many of these points are highly debatable even for highly
                    trained photo interpreters.</p>
                <p>Our main source of information on the SAMs is photography, but [<hi rend="italic"
                        >less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] also play a role. So far, because
                    of our [<hi rend="italic">2 lines not declassified</hi>]. This appears to stem
                    as much from budgetary and bureaucratic reasons as from the state of the art and
                    an effort is being made to increase somewhat [<hi rend="italic">4 lines not
                        declassified</hi>]. As you know, however, [<hi rend="italic">2½ lines not
                        declassified</hi>].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Conventional clandestinely collected intelligence</hi> has so
                    far played a very limited role in detecting possible Egyptian and Soviet
                    cease-fire violations. It could, however, at some future point prove to be
                    important for confirming evidence from other sources and for revealing Egyptian
                    motives and intentions.</p>
                <p>There is <hi rend="italic">one major gap in our intelligence</hi> which prevents
                    us from being able to document all the violations since the cease-fire went in
                    effect on August 7. As you know, we can not be sure of what exactly happened
                    within the Egyptian cease-fire zone in the week or so before and in the two days
                    immediately after the cease-fire went into effect. We know that there was a
                    substantial movement of SAMs toward the canal during this period, but because of
                    the periodicity of our satellite missions we can not prove—even with the
                    evidence supplied by the Is<pb facs="0568" n="535" xml:id="pg_535"/>raelis—that
                    there were substantial violations. Therefore, for our own working purposes, we
                    have used the results of low resolution U–2 flights (August 9 and 11) plus good
                    quality low resolution satellite photography on August 10 to establish a data
                    base against which we can measure violations since then.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">What this adds up to is in substantive terms:</p>
                <p>1. Our evidence is best in documenting <hi rend="italic">construction of new
                            <gloss target="#t_SAM_1">SAM</gloss> sites.</hi> It is now possible to
                    say that there are some sites on ground where there was no sign of activity at
                    all before the ceasefire.<note n="2" xml:id="d159fn2">In the margin, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> wrote: “How many?”</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. It is harder to identify the <hi rend="italic">status of completed
                    sites</hi>—whether they are occupied or unoccupied or whether they are occupied
                    by dummy, SA–2 or SA–3 equipment. This means, for instance, that, even though we
                    have recently discovered SA–3 equipment in several SA–2 sites, we cannot say for
                    sure that this equipment was not at these sites on August 10.</p>
                <p>3. It is even more difficult to document the <hi rend="italic">net increase</hi>
                    of [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] <gloss
                        target="#t_SAM_1">SAM</gloss> battalions (particularly SA–2s). This means
                    that it is so far not possible to prove that the Egyptians have done more than
                    rotating units within the standstill zone without increasing their overall
                    equipment strength, although there are fairly good circumstantial indications
                    they have done more than this.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Intelligence Results</p>
                <p>One major source of considerable confusion since we began trying to identify
                    Egyptian and Soviet violations of the military standstill has been the <hi
                        rend="italic">difference between when we have discovered possible violations
                        and when they have actually occurred.</hi> This arises essentially from the
                    technical problem of differing quality and type of photographic coverage and the
                    delay required for careful analysis and re-evaluation of information. Sometimes
                    identification of activity in high resolution photographs of a given site makes
                    it possible to look back at earlier low resolution photos and “see” evidence of
                    activity that had not been noted in the earlier photos. What is most important
                    for diplomatic purposes is when possible violations actually occurred—not when
                    we discovered them. Therefore what follows is an effort to construct a “real
                    time” analysis under the five main categories that were used in making our
                    presentation to the Egyptians.<note n="3" xml:id="d159fn3">Presumably <persName
                            corresp="#p_BDC_1">Bergus</persName>’s presentation of “factual data” on
                        September 3. See <ref target="#d158">Document 158</ref> and <ref
                            target="#d158fn3">footnote 3</ref> thereto.</note> This will be a “real
                    time” picture of the situation the day we made that presentation worked out from
                    the photos taken that day:</p>
                <pb facs="0569" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">SA–2 sites built before the ceasefire but not occupied on
                        August 10.</hi> Counting from August 10 (our reliable data base), it appears
                    that—through September 3—13 or 14 SA–2 missile sites built before the cease-fire
                    were occupied. Two of these sites, however, were evacuated during this period so
                    there has only been a net increase of 11 or 12 pre-cease-fire sites occupied
                    with SA–2 equipment. We do not know how many of these occupied sites are truly
                        [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] and high
                    resolution photography of these sites have been inadequate to settle that point.
                    We also do not have sufficient [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>] whether there has been a net addition to the number of
                    Egyptian SA–2 battalions within the cease-fire zone since the military
                    standstill went into effect, as would be necessary if all the additionally
                    occupied sites had become [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>]. Our intelligence analysts, however, based on their
                    estimate of the amount of SA–2 equipment presently visible within the cease-fire
                    zone, believe that some of it must have been brought in since August 10 since we
                    do not know of any storage depots for SA–2 equipment within the zone. It is
                    conceded, of course, that some of the newly occupied sites may, as the Egyptians
                    claim, be filled with equipment relocated from previously occupied sites or from
                    unidentified excess equipment stocks, but since only two occupied sites have
                    been evacuated such relocation cannot account for the equipment visible at many
                    of the 13 or 14 newly occupied SA–2 sites. That is difficult to prove,
                    however.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">SA–2 sites which did not exist on August 10 and have since
                        been constructed and sites partly built by August 10 on which significant
                        construction has continued since.</hi> The Egyptians have also been
                    constructing and occupying new SA–2 sites within the cease-fire zone. We have
                    clear evidence of Egyptian construction work on twelve SA–2 sites. Work began on
                    six of these sites after August 10 (four since August 27), and, although
                    construction had begun on the other six sites apparently before the cease-fire,
                    they have been finished or nearly finished since August 10. Three of these sites
                    have been occupied.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">SA–2 battalions field deployed since August 10.</hi> Two
                    battalions have been field deployed.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">SA–3 battalions field deployed since August 10.</hi> As you
                    know, the Soviets are also involved in possible cease-fire violations. As of
                    August 10 we were able to identify five Soviet-manned and occupied SA–3 sites
                    within the cease-fire zone. We suspect that some or all of these may only have
                    been occupied after the cease-fire went into effect (on August 8 and 9) but we
                    cannot prove this. In addition to these suspected Soviet violations, we have
                    evidence of the deployment of two additional SA–3 units in what appears to be a
                    field unit configuration. Both of the deployments were completed after the
                    cease-fire (by August 18), although one of the deployments may have been
                    partially completed by <pb facs="0570" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> August 10 and
                    we cannot be sure whether this was actually begun before the cease-fire.</p>
                <p>We have also identified four SA–3 units occupying SA–2 configured sites. The SA–3
                    equipment was only discovered in high resolution photography in late August and
                    the sites were previously identified on the basis of low resolution photography
                    as occupied SA–2s. The SA–3 equipment may, however, have been in the sites since
                    the military standstill went into effect. At least we cannot prove
                    otherwise.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Standstill Violations</p>
                <p>As you know, there are considerably different Egyptian (and by inference Soviet)
                    and Israeli/U.S. interpretations of the military standstill provisions of the
                    cease-fire agreement. The official <gloss target="#t_UAR_1">UAR</gloss> position
                    is that they (and by inference, the Soviet forces in Egypt too) are permitted to
                    rotate and relocate <gloss target="#t_SAM_1">SAM</gloss> missiles and equipment
                    from site to site, as well as complete the construction of sites where work was
                    initiated prior to the cease-fire. We and the Israelis do not accept this loose
                    interpretation of the terms of the cease-fire and our views were clearly placed
                    on the record shortly after the cease-fire in both Cairo and Moscow. The
                    Israelis, of course, have pinned us down to a very strict interpretation of the
                    standstill.</p>
                <p>Most of the evidence of violations that we have acquired relates to the area of
                    difference between the Egyptian/Soviet and Israeli/U.S. interpretations. In
                    fact, <hi rend="italic">in only six instances do we have evidence of brand new
                        post-August 10 construction starts, all SA–2s. In addition, we have one
                        instance of the field deployment begun and completed since August 10 of an
                        SA–3 unit—an apparent Soviet violation.</hi> Presumably, this Egyptian and
                    Soviet activity would be a violation even by their definitions.</p>
                <p>The case against the Egyptians and Soviets is much more impressive, of course,
                    when viewed from our strict interpretation of the cease-fire agreement and based
                    on circumstantial evidence. But we cannot prove all of it sufficiently to make a
                    strong case on the specifics in Cairo and Moscow. All we can really use against
                    the Egyptian and Soviets, even using our interpretation of the cease-fire
                    agreement, are the following violations:</p>
                <p>—The Egyptian construction of twelve SA–2 sites, three of which have been
                    occupied. Six of these are the sites started since the cease-fire (three of
                    which have also been occupied) which are violations even by the Egyptian
                    definition. The other six were all begun before the cease-fire but construction
                    had been stopped probably because of Israeli bombing. The present construction
                    on these sites involves substantial improvements and clearly represents an
                    Egyptian effort to take advantage of the cease-fire.</p>
                <pb facs="0571" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/>
                <p>—Both of the Soviet field deployments of SA–3 units can be proved to be
                    violations. As mentioned above, one is even a violation in Egyptian/Soviet
                    terms. The other unit appears to have been partially deployed as of August 10
                    and then finished by August 18.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Conclusion</p>
                <p>Our information ideally could be better, but it seems very clear that the Soviets
                    and Egyptians have continued to erect their missile complex within the
                    cease-fire zone along the Egyptian side of the Canal. This is apparently a
                    continuation, albeit at much less intensity, of the big movement of the SAMs
                    toward the Canal in the days immediately before the cease-fire. We cannot
                    document all of the moves precisely but we have a very good idea, in gross
                    terms, what has happened.</p>
                <p>There are limitations to our intelligence but these are not likely to be resolved
                    by the information the Israelis pick up with their almost daily overflights of
                    the Egyptian cease-fire zone [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>]. The people at <gloss target="#t_DIA_1">DIA</gloss>, who
                    have worked most closely with the Israelis, have found that their intelligence
                    has not turned up anything important that we have not identified ourselves. In
                    fact, so far as we can determine, we have discovered more possible violations
                    than they have, especially concerning the Soviet-manned SA–3s. Our photography
                    is more precise than theirs.</p>
                <p>Because of the nature of this kind of intelligence, we can expect continuing
                    clarifications. This will be especially true when good quality high resolution
                    photography is acquired from satellite coverage. This means that the numbers
                    game will continue as we refine our knowledge of what has happened. We know
                    enough already, however, to be reasonably confident in our protests to the
                    Egyptians and Soviets. Our main interest now is in their response on the ground
                    to our démarches. Intelligence on this aspect should be available later this
                    week. U–2 missions were flown on September 6 and 8 and together—all other things
                    being equal—these may provide us with our first good indications of how the
                    Egyptians and Soviets are reacting. Because of the limitations in this kind of
                    intelligence, it may—if there are more violations of standstill—be a while
                    before we can construct a case good enough to call them on.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
