<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-09-09T14:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-09-09T14:50:00-05:00" n="308" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d308">
                        <head>308. Telegram From the President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HGAM_1">Haig</persName>) to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> at Camp David,
                                Maryland<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d308fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 609, Country Files, Middle East, Israel,
                                Vol. X. Secret; Sensitive. Stamped notations on the first page
                                indicate that the telegram was received at Camp David at 4:35 p.m.
                                and that the President saw it.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-09-09T19:50:00+00:00">September 9, 1972, 1950Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>WH27332. Memorandum for: The President. From: <persName corresp="#p_HGAM_1">Al Haig</persName>. Subject: Rising Tensions in
                            the Mid-East.</p>
                        <p>Pursuant to your instructions, I conveyed to Israeli Minister Idan (in
                            the absence of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RLGY_1">Rabin</persName>
                            who was en route to Israel) our strong concern for the retaliatory
                            action taken by the Government of Israel yesterday against refugee
                            terrorist camps.<note n="2" xml:id="d308fn2">On September 8, Israeli
                                fighter jets struck 10 Palestinian guerrilla bases deep in both
                                Lebanese and Syrian territory in retaliation for the killing of the
                                Israeli athletes in Munich on September 6. (<hi rend="italic">New
                                    York Times</hi>, September 9, 1972, p. 1)</note> I added that
                            this action was inconsistent with the assurances given by Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_RLGY_1">Rabin</persName> to Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> yesterday that Israel would
                            do nothing to upset the <pb facs="1079" n="1046" xml:id="pg_1046"/>
                            “trend of tranquility” in the Mid-East. Idan replied that Israel
                            intended to abide by the assurances given but that this did not mean
                            that Israel would stand by idly and not take some action against known
                            terrorist bases. He implied that the targets were precise and well
                            identified beforehand. He estimated that there may have been as many as
                            90 to 100 casualties inflicted.</p>
                        <p>Idan pointed out that today’s air action over the Golan Heights resulted
                            from efforts by the Syrian Air Force to bomb Israeli territory. During
                            these air battles, which involved as many as 90 aircraft, three Syrian
                            SU–7s were shot down and a fourth was damaged but landed safely. Idan
                            stated that today’s actions were purely defensive in nature and that he
                            did not foresee any change in the assessment given by <persName corresp="#p_RLGY_1">Rabin</persName> yesterday. I again reiterated
                            to him that you were concerned and hoped that Israel would not
                            jeopardize the good will built here as a result of the improving
                            situation in the Mid-East, and the sympathy for Israel which had been
                            engendered by the tragic events in Munich. It was made clear to Idan
                            that a continuation of clearly unprovoked military aggressiveness on the
                            part of Israel would not be understood nor condoned by the White
                                House.<note n="3" xml:id="d308fn3"><persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> wrote “good” next to these last two sentences.
                                In a September 11 memorandum, Butterfield informed <persName corresp="#p_HGAM_1">Haig</persName> that the President read this
                                telegram and “was especially pleased to note that you made it clear
                                to Minister Idan that a continuation of unprovoked military
                                aggression on the part of Israel would not be understood, or
                                condoned, at this end of the line.” (National Archives, Nixon
                                Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                                Box 609, Country Files, Middle East, Israel, Vol. X) On September
                                16, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> told Idan:
                                “But if you do not stop these actions—I must tell you, you are
                                running an enormous risk in your relations with the President. You
                                launched an action the day before I go to Moscow and you launch an
                                action the day after I come back at a time when we are taking an
                                all-out diplomatic position in your defense and are preventing—going
                                into actions. We cannot take this. Now there is no President who has
                                done more for you, and I can tell you, I have just come from the
                                President and he asked me to call you.” (Transcript of telephone
                                conversation, 1:28 p.m.; ibid., <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry
                                    Kissinger</persName> Telephone Conversation Transcripts, Box 15,
                                Chronological File)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>