<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>316. Telegram From the Embassy in Israel to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v23</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-11-09T05:25:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-11-09T05:25:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005651"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monitoring</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-11-09T05:25:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-11-09T05:25:00-05:00" n="316"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d316">
                <head>316. Telegram From the Embassy in Israel to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d316fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 658, Country
                        Files, Middle East, Middle East Nodis/Cedar/Plus, Vol. V. Secret; Nodis;
                        Cedar. Repeated to Cairo.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Tel Aviv</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1972-11-09T10:25:00+00:00">November 9, 1972,
                        1025Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>7357. Subject: US-Israel: <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> Visit to
                        Washington.<note n="2" xml:id="d316fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> visited New York and Washington
                        November 12–14. The memorandum of conversation of <persName
                            corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>’s meeting with Department of Defense
                        officials is Document 319.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary:</hi>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> is the one Israeli leader who
                    continues to focus on possibility of interim Suez Canal settlement and by all
                    indications to want it. We believe he should be encouraged. However, <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> like rest <pb facs="1101" n="1068"
                        xml:id="pg_1068"/> of <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> is probably
                    convinced that <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> in due course will
                    take his own initiative to bring about such settlement and that nothing should
                    be done meanwhile which might sidetrack him. <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Dayan</persName> also must be concerned about current unrealistic mood of
                    expectation in Cairo that US, with elections over, will help solve Egypt’s
                    problem with Israel. <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> for this reason may
                    charge <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> with making strong pitch in
                    Washington for <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> to do and say nothing about
                    Arab-Israeli problem in coming weeks. As for substantive questions involved in
                    interim settlement, it would not be surprising if <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Dayan</persName>’s authority to talk with Americans about such matters at
                    this juncture is severely limited; PriMin <persName corresp="#p_MG_1"
                        >Meir</persName> would not want to risk mistaken impression in Washington
                    that <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> is ready to send signals to <persName
                        corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>. <gloss target="#t_Dept_1">Dept</gloss>
                    might consider using occasion of <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>’s
                    visit rekindle his desire to start moving now toward Canal settlement—and to
                    strengthen his hand within <gloss target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> as leading
                    proponent of such move—by renewing assurances of US willingness to be helpful in
                    spheres of advance intelligence coordination monitoring and subsequent for any
                    Canal settlement, possible limited observer role in such settlement, and fending
                    off undesirable outside Middle East initiatives in meantime. <hi rend="italic"
                        >End summary.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> is the one Israeli leader who
                    from the fall of 1970 to the present day has wanted strongly to see a partial
                    Suez Canal settlement and who appears to remain convinced that one is
                    achievable. Presumably his strong interest in disengagement with Egypt arises
                    from <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>’s responsibility for military
                    situation at Canal, his appreciation of normalization of life in Israel made
                    possible by past two years of ceasefire at Canal, and his dread of unpredictable
                    situation to which renewed shooting could lead. <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Dayan</persName> therefore is the right Israeli leader for US to encourage
                    on subject of interim Canal settlement.</p>
                <p>2. There is no reason to think, however, that <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Dayan</persName> does not share conviction of rest of Israeli leadership
                    that <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> is being led inexorably by
                    flow of events toward taking an Egyptian initiative aimed at Israelis themselves
                    (and not US). While recognizing that disarray in Cairo’s relations with <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and Egypt’s internal unrest have weakened
                        <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> at the moment, making
                    initiative toward Israel harder for him to undertake, we suspect Israelis like
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> look upon <persName
                        corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>’s current troubles with his own military
                    and his Soviet allies as sealing once and for all, in <persName
                        corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>’s mind, notion that Egypt can afford to
                    delude itself that it has any military option against Israel for foreseeable
                    future.</p>
                <p>3. Israelis clearly have sensed mood of unrealistic anticipation in Cairo, which
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_GJN_1">Greene</persName> has so succinctly
                    reported (Cairo 2933),<note n="3" xml:id="d316fn3">Dated November 1. (National
                        Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, POL 27–14 ARAB–ISR)</note> that
                        <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> after elections may take major new
                    initiative in Middle East <pb facs="1102" n="1069" xml:id="pg_1069"/> entailing
                    pressure on Israel to bring about settlement acceptable to Egypt. Israelis
                    undoubtedly view such mood not only as regrettable sidetrack for gradual
                    evolution of Egyptian policy in realistic direction, but also as serious
                    potential danger because of instability to which Cairo’s inevitable
                    disappointment with US can lead. We therefore believe that if Israeli leadership
                    charges <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> with conveying any message
                    in Washington on November 14, it will be to emphasize need, as <gloss
                        target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss> sees it, for US in coming weeks to do and say
                    absolutely nothing concerning Arab-Israeli problem.</p>
                <p>4. As we are reporting separately, Israel’s pre-election campaign is now getting
                    underway, and <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> is involved. How
                    involved he is personally is hard to judge, since his numerous supporters have
                    been applying all their talents to do battle for him and may have to some extent
                    helped to create the emanations we are getting to effect that a sparring among
                    leading personalities is underway within Labor Party. Suffice it to say here, in
                    any case, that Washington should not be surprised if <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Dayan</persName>’s lips are tightly buttoned Nov 14 with respect to
                    substantive issues involved in any interim Canal settlement. Fact that <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> at first regretted and later accepted
                    Secretary’s invitation to come to Washington during his visit to US could
                    conceivably mean that <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>’s colleagues
                    in Cabinet have hammered out with him set of guidelines for his talks with US
                    officials. Given <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>’s propensity to
                    speak his mind on terms of an accommodation with Egypt and <gloss
                        target="#t_GOI_1">GOI</gloss>’s concern not to encourage US to say anything
                    on this subject because of Cairo’s current mood of expectation, one of
                    guidelines might well be injunction to stay off subject of Suez Canal.</p>
                <p>5. If <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> while in Washington cannot be
                    drawn out on substantive aspects of Canal settlement, and if as we expect he
                    takes view that US and Israel should do absolutely nothing at this time to prime
                    the Egyptian pump, US talks with <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>
                    Nov 14 can still be turned to good advantage, in our view, if they serve the
                    purpose of reviving and strengthening <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Dayan</persName>’s interest in seeing Canal settlement come to pass. <gloss
                        target="#t_Dept_1">Dept</gloss> might therefore consider renewing to
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> assurances of US readiness to:
                    A) Enter into detailed discussion with Israel at any time of intelligence
                    aspects of interim settlement, to give Israel added assurance that it can safely
                    carry out partial withdrawal; B) provide Israel with meaningful, ongoing
                    assistance in monitoring good performance on obligations undertaken by Egypt in
                    any Canal agreement, if desired; C) serve in limited supervisory or observer
                    capacity on ground as part of Canal settlement arrangements, if desired; and D)
                    assist Israel meanwhile in fending off any unhelpful outside initiatives on
                    Middle East arising in <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> or other contexts.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_BW_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BW_1">Barbour</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
