<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Embassy in France to the French Ministry for Foreign
                    Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recZPVvCSdB8G01JR" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaty negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="174"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.114 Liquor/771</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Embassy in France</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">French Ministry for Foreign Affairs</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="54" xml:id="d174fn54">Transmitted to the Department by the Ambassador
                        in France in his despatch No. 1198, September 11; received September
                        20.</note>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In a note of April 3, 1934,<note n="55" xml:id="d174fn55">Not printed.</note> the
                    Embassy recalled the existing discrimination against American exports to France
                    in the matter of the <pb facs="0299" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/> application of
                    the 2, 4 and 6 per cent import turnover tax which arises from the circumstance
                    that France has suppressed the higher rates of the tax in favor of Belgian and
                    Italian products and the products of certain other countries. While citing the
                    point of view of the American Government that the removal of this discrimination
                    should not depend upon the granting to France of what might be considered
                    compensating advantages the Embassy pointed out that in actual fact its
                    Government did accord to France as a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> for the
                    removal of the discriminatory tax on copper the elimination of the restrictions
                    on French samples of women’s wearing apparel entering the United States, this
                    advantage having been given without waiting for the French Government to make
                    the necessary adjustment with regard to copper which had orally been promised.
                    As the Ministry for Foreign Affairs is aware, the satisfaction sought by the
                    United States in regard to copper was never given.</p>
                <p>The Ministry for Foreign Affairs replied to the Embassy’s note in a note dated
                    May 7, 1934.<note n="56" xml:id="d174fn56">Not printed.</note> In the last
                    paragraph the Ministry stated that it might reexamine the whole question when
                    circumstances permit. It is believed that as stated somewhat further below,
                    conditions have now so shaped themselves as to render it advantageous to the
                    French Government to give further and serious consideration to the matter.</p>
                <p>It may be remembered that the Embassy, in a note of May 16, 1933,<note n="57"
                        xml:id="d174fn57">Note No. 2386 from the Chargé in France to the French
                        Minister for Foreign Affairs, <ref target="frus1933v02#pg_156">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1933, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 156</ref>.</note> asked the removal of
                    the discriminations inherent to the present application of the import turnover
                    tax as concerns all products imported from the United States. The Ministry for
                    Foreign Affairs responded under date of May 20, 1933,<note n="58"
                        xml:id="d174fn58">See telegram No. 234, May 22, 1933, 4 p.m., from the
                        Chargé in France, <ref target="frus1933v02#pg_157">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 157</ref>.</note> stating that a bill
                    had been laid before the French Chambers authorizing the French Government to
                    reduce the import turnover tax to 2% “en ce qui concerne tout ou partie des
                    produits originaires des divers pays étrangers dont la production est grevée de
                    charges fiscales équivalentes à celles que supporte la production françhise ou
                    qui auront conclu avec la France des arrangements spéciaux à cet effet”.<note
                        n="59" xml:id="d174fn59">Translation: “with regard to all or part of the
                        products of origin in the several foreign countries on the production of
                        which taxes are levied equivalent to those placed on French production, or
                        which will have concluded with France special arrangements to this
                        effect.”</note> The Ministry’s note continues, “Dès que cette loi sera votée
                    et mise en vigueur, ce qui ne saurait tarder, le Ministere des Affaires
                    Etrangeres se mettra en rapport avec l’Ambassade pour examiner la question avec
                        elle”.<note n="60" xml:id="d174fn60">Translation: “As soon as this law is
                        passed and put into effect, which will not be long, the Ministry for Foreign
                        Affairs will get in touch with the Embassy In order to examine the question
                        with it.”</note> (It is interesting to observe that <pb facs="0300" n="200"
                        xml:id="pg_200"/> the Ministry’s note coupled with this question the desire
                    of the French Government to secure protection in the United States for French
                    wines as regards the use of geographic names of origin.) While the bill cited by
                    the Ministry was not approved by Parliament last year an analogous law was later
                    approved by Parliament and signed by the President of the Republic on March 10,
                    1934. This law affords the French Government the authority, up to November 15,
                    1934, to effect by decree the reduction of the higher rates of the import
                    turnover tax in favor of the products of another country. It would appear
                    therefore that the French Government has at its disposal the means for affording
                    relief to American products as regards the import turnover tax.</p>
                <p>While the Embassy, in reply to the Ministry’s note of May 7, 1934, must reaffirm
                    that the American Government is still of the mind that the discriminations in
                    the application of the import turnover tax should be gratuitously removed and in
                    particular that the oral understanding relative to a reclassification of copper
                    should be fulfilled, it is at the same time mindful of the mutual interest of
                    both Governments in improving commercial relations. It therefore invites
                    attention to developments in the United States which may possibly be turned to
                    the advantage of France.</p>
                <p>The French Government has long sought protection of geographic names of origin of
                    French wines. On August 10, 1934 the Federal Alcohol Control Administration
                    promulgated regulations, which it is believed will prove satisfactory to foreign
                    interests, which would provide protection for geographic names employed for
                    distilled spirits. Of particular interest to France is the protection henceforth
                    afforded to brandy or cognac.</p>
                <p>The Embassy is now informed that hearings will very shortly be held regarding the
                    granting of analogous protection to geographic names of wines. It is, however,
                    learned that considerable opposition to the proposed wine regulations has
                    developed in the United States, notably among the wine growers in California,
                    New York and Ohio. Further, prior to the promulgation of the regulations
                    concerning geographic and distinctive designations of wines, the regulations
                    will be referred to the Department of State at Washington for consideration in
                    the light of their effect on American foreign commerce etcetera.</p>
                <p>The Embassy realizes that the French Government has for long considered that the
                    adoption of such regulations as those now contemplated is of the utmost
                    importance to the French wine trade. In fact protection of the nature was one of
                    the demands made by the French Government during the course of the commercial
                    treaty negotiations two years ago,<note n="61" xml:id="d174fn61">See <ref
                            target="frus1932v02#pg_195">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1932, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 195</ref> ff.</note> a declaration in
                    that regard having been suggested as an annex to the draft treaty. In
                    consequence, it is felt <pb facs="0301" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> that the
                    French Government will desire that everything possible be done to assure the
                    promulgation of the regulations in question.</p>
                <p>It therefore occurs to the Ambassador that through the cooperation of the
                    Ministry for Foreign Affairs and the Embassy, it may be practical to secure the
                    approval of the wine “name” regulations which the French Government has so long
                    sought and at the same time liquidate some of the problems which have proved
                    irksome to American producers.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador feels that it might weigh heavily in overcoming opposition in the
                    United States to the regulations now under study if American interests in
                    general could be assured of a substantial <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> in
                    return for the consideration given French geographic names of wine origin. Such
                    a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> would doubtless also tend favorably to
                    influence the Department of State in reviewing the effects of the regulations on
                    American foreign commerce.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador therefore proposes to the Ministry for Foreign Affairs to employ
                    his good offices before his Government to the end that adequate protection be
                    given geographic designations, upon the understanding that the Ministry
                    similarly will exercise its good offices in obtaining certain adjustments sought
                    by American trade. To be specific, there is suggested as possibly satisfactory
                    to the American Government the reduction of the import turnover tax to 2% as
                    concerns all products entering France from the United States and the granting to
                    the United States of <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> treatment, that is the
                    minimum tariff rate, on American rice (in this latter connection please see the
                    Embassy’s note No. 939 [<hi rend="italic">507</hi>] of March 29, 1934).<note
                        n="62" xml:id="d174fn62">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>If the Ministry for Foreign Affairs is in agreement with this procedure the
                    Ambassador hopes that immediate steps may be taken to reach an arrangement,
                    since not only does the special authority granted the French Government for free
                    negotiation on the import turnover tax shortly expire but it is important that
                    prior to the termination of the study of the regulations for wine names, now
                    going on in the United States, every effort be made to make them as advantageous
                    to France as the domestic situation shall permit.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-09-07">September 7,
                            1934</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
