<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-02-15T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-02-15T07:00:00-05:00" n="21" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d21">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">863.00/864: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Long</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-02-15T13:00:00+01:00">February 15, 1934—1
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 1:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>28. Your circular telegram February 14, 5 p.m.,<note n="14" xml:id="d21fn14">See footnote 11, <ref target="#pg_13">p.
                                        13</ref>.</note> and my 26, February 14, 7 p.m. According to
                                Suvich Italy considers it a very salutary movement in that it has
                                brought to a head a situation which has been hanging over Austria
                                for several years. He thinks that as long as it had to come it has
                                come at an opportune moment because if the movement of the Social
                                Democrats in opposition to Dollfuss had developed when the Nazis
                                were carrying on activities subversive of the Dollfuss regime it
                                would have resulted in the certain fall of Dollfuss. The situation
                                is thought to be well in hand by Dollfuss and Italy believes that he
                                will maintain his authority. Having done so he will have answered
                                the criticisms of the Nazis who have said that he was incapable of
                                being ruthless and strong and unable to maintain order; furthermore,
                                many of the Nazi ambitions are being realized through the
                                forcefulness of his actions and by his policies so that Italy thinks
                                there will be less Nazi opposition after this revolutionary movement
                                is put down partly because of the anti-climactic effect that
                                demonstration bombs and hand grenades will have after this bloody
                                show is over.</p>
                            <p>Mailed Vienna, Paris, London, Berlin, Geneva.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Long</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>