<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-01-22T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-01-22T16:00:00-05:00" n="277" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d277">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">862.51/3815a: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Chargé in Switzerland</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Riggs</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-01-22T16:00:00-05:00">January 22, 1934—4
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>9. The Swiss Government has taken the initiative in pressing upon the
                                German Government an agreement whereunder in return for so <pb facs="0441" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/> called extra purchases of
                                German goods the proceeds of these extra purchases should be applied
                                to the service of German bonds held in Switzerland over and above
                                the service which the German Government is permitting on the same
                                bonds held elsewhere.</p>
                            <p>The Dutch Government has made a similar agreement. The question of
                                renewal of these agreements has been under discussion and a meeting
                                is scheduled in Berlin on the 25th to deal with them. The British
                                and Swedish Governments have taken initiatives in Berlin in protest
                                against this more favorable treatment and are tending to take the
                                position that if these agreements are maintained they would have to
                                institute “clearing agreements” on German trade whereunder the
                                exchange arising from that trade would be segregated and applied to
                                supplement the service on the German securities held by their
                                nationals. They, however, do not want to introduce such arrangement
                                if discrimination is not practised against them.</p>
                            <p>The American Government was approached by the British Government to
                                support this position and it has done so vigorously both here and in
                                Berlin emphasizing the fact that discrimination against American
                                holders of German securities as compared with the holders of other
                                countries would be gravely resented. The President himself is
                                talking about it to Ambassador Luther this morning.</p>
                            <p>The Bondholders Protective Council, a disinterested American body
                                formed by private interests with the encouragement of this
                                Government, has sent a representative, Mr. Laird Bell, to Berlin to
                                protect the interests of American holders of German securities.</p>
                            <p>The Department believes it advisable to make known to the Swiss
                                Government the position it is taking in the matter. Will you please
                                therefore, before the 25th, see the proper Swiss authorities and
                                inform them orally of the position which this Government is taking
                                in the matter. You may find it advisable to emphasize the following
                                points:</p>
                            <p>(1) That the only government that seems to be pressing with
                                determination for special treatment is Switzerland; the Dutch
                                Government would probably be willing to forego its special agreement
                                if the Swiss Government would.</p>
                            <p>If the pressure of the Swiss Government succeeds, other governments
                                are certain to pursue the same means leading to a general diminution
                                of international trade.</p>
                            <p>(2) The Swiss position in this German debt situation may create a
                                whole new area of controversy. If carried on it would mean great
                                dissension among diverse creditors to their mutual injury in various
                                situations. You may point out that the United States has abstained
                                from taking any such position in various situations in which it
                                might have been able to press an advantage to the detriment of other
                                countries.</p>
                            <p>(3) A superficial argument may be made to the effect that the special
                                agreements are not discriminatory because the special payments arise
                                out of the application of exchange coming from extra purchases of
                                    <pb facs="0442" n="342" xml:id="pg_342"/> German goods. It is in
                                fact however, impossible to segregate a small segment of bilateral
                                trade from the rest of the international trade process and to claim
                                special debt payment on the basis of this small segment without
                                creating discriminations and without even further causing countries
                                to erect new trade barriers in order to gain still further
                                advantage.</p>
                            <p>(4) In fact you can add that the whole bilateral commodity trade
                                position in this Government’s view does not offer a sound basis for
                                differential debt terms even apart from the aspects of general
                                policy recited above; for the computations totally ignore the
                                invisible items of trade such as tourist traffic, shipping services,
                                and the rest, and they also ignore the fact that purchases in third
                                countries, e. g., American purchases in the Dutch East Indies,
                                create markets for other countries.</p>
                            <p>Please report the result of your interview.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>