<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-02-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="385" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d385">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">462.11W892/2420</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the German Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Luther</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-02-20">February 20, 1934</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I am informed by the American
                                Agent, Mixed Claims Commission, United States and Germany, that all
                                the evidence in <pb facs="0588" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/> the
                                sabotage cases that he desires to present has been filed with the
                                Commission and that complete copies have been furnished the German
                                Agent. Unless your Government expects to submit counter evidence,
                                the next step in order will be the submission of briefs by the two
                                Governments. I shall therefore be pleased if you will inform me as
                                early as possible (1) whether it is the intention of your Government
                                to file counter evidence, as it is permitted to do under the
                                decision of the Umpire of December 15, 1933, and (2) if it is not
                                the intention of your Government to file such evidence, the
                                approximate date on which your Agent will be prepared to exchange
                                briefs.</p>
                            <p>I may add, for your information, that the brief on the part of the
                                American Agency can be submitted within a very short time after the
                                receipt of advices that no evidence is to be submitted by your
                                Government, if such is to be the position of your Government.</p>
                            <p>Since, as has so often been stated, it is the desire of both
                                Governments to close the work of the Commission as early as
                                possible, I am sure that you will appreciate the importance of an
                                early understanding on these points.</p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Cordell Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>