<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Department of State to the German Embassy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d392</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">392</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-05-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-05-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-05-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-05-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="392"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d392">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">462.11W892/2475</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">German Embassy</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In view of the approaching close of the work of the Mixed Claims Commission,
                    United States and Germany, the time would seem to be propitious for a definite
                    statement by the German Government of its position regarding payments due the
                    United States under the Debt Settlement Agreement of June 23, 1930,<note n="98"
                        xml:id="d392fn98">See <ref target="frus1930v03#pg_106">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1930, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 106</ref> ff.</note> with respect to
                    awards of the Mixed Claims Commission.</p>
                <pb facs="0594" n="494" xml:id="pg_494"/>
                <p>It will be recalled that the Resolution of Congress approved July 2, 1921,<note
                        n="99" xml:id="d392fn99">42 Stat. 105.</note> provided, <hi rend="italic"
                        >inter alia</hi>, for the retention by the United States of all property of
                    German nationals that had come under the control of the United States during the
                    period of the war, “until such time as the Imperial German Government” or its
                    “successor or successors” shall have made— <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">“suitable provision for the satisfaction of all claims
                            against said [Government]<note n="1" xml:id="d392fn1">Brackets appear in
                                original memorandum; omissions also indicated in the original
                                memorandum.</note> …of all persons, wherever domiciled, who owe
                            permanent allegiance to the United States of America and who have
                            suffered, through the acts of the Imperial German Government, or its
                            agents … since July 31, 1914, loss, damage, or injury to their persons
                            or property, directly or indirectly, whether through the ownership of
                            shares of stock in German,… American, or other corporations, or in
                            consequence of hostilities or of any operations of war, or otherwise
                            …”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The above provisions of this Resolution were incorporated in the Treaty between
                    the United States and Germany, signed at Berlin, August 25, 1921,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d392fn2">For text of treaty, see <ref target="frus1921v02#pg_29">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1921, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 29</ref>.</note> Article I of which
                    stipulated that the United States should have and enjoy— <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">“all the rights, privileges, indemnities, reparations,
                            or advantages specified in the aforesaid Joint Resolution of the
                            Congress of the United States of July 2, 1921 …”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>By certain other treaty provisions the United States had the right to retain and
                    liquidate all property rights and interests in the United States of German
                    nationals or companies controlled by them. Notwithstanding these several treaty
                    provisions, practically eighty per cent, of the property belonging to German
                    nationals, held by the Alien Property Custodian, has been returned pursuant to
                    Acts of Congress. Specifically, Section 9 of the Trading with the Enemy Act<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d392fn3">40 Stat. 411, 419.</note> as amended by Section 14 of
                    the Settlement of War Claims Act of 1928<note n="4" xml:id="d392fn4">45 Stat.
                        254.</note> provided for the return of eighty per cent, of the property
                    belonging to German nationals held by the Alien Property Custodian upon their
                    agreeing to a temporary postponement of the return of an amount equal to twenty
                    per cent, of the value of such property. The same section provided that where
                    the value of the property to be returned was less than $2,000, the whole amount
                    should be returned.</p>
                <p>Pursuant to Section 3 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of the Settlement of War Claims
                    Act of 1928, an Arbiter was appointed by this Government to determine the fair
                    compensation to be paid by the United States to German <pb facs="0595" n="495"
                        xml:id="pg_495"/> nationals in respect of merchant vessels, radio stations,
                    and patents taken over by the United States during the war. Awards, in the
                    amount of $86,738,320.83, including interest to December 31, 1928, were rendered
                    by the War Claims Arbiter, and $43,368,211.71 have been paid thereon to the
                    German nationals out of appropriations made by Congress, in accordance with
                    provisions of the Act of 1928.</p>
                <p>On August 10, 1922, the two Governments signed an Agreement providing for the
                    establishment of a Mixed Claims Commission to adjudicate the claims of American
                    nationals against Germany. Awards in favor of American nationals, totaling
                    $170,000,000, including interest to January 1, 1928, and awards in favor of the
                    Government of the United States, totaling $61,000,000, including interest to
                    January 1, 1928, have thus far been made. On these awards the German Government
                    has paid $52,000,000.</p>
                <p>On June 23, 1930, the Governments of the United States and Germany signed an
                    Agreement whereby Germany undertook to pay to the United States an amount
                    sufficient to cover the awards entered and to be entered in favor of the United
                    States and its nationals by the Mixed Claims Commission, referred to above, and
                    also to reimburse the United States for the costs of its Army of Occupation. The
                    payments by Germany on account of the awards of the Mixed Claims Commission were
                    fixed at the rate of 40,800,000 reichsmarks per annum, a comparatively small
                    annual payment. Germany is now in arrears on these payments in an amount of
                    approximately $50,000,000.</p>
                <p>The United States accepted the full faith and credit of Germany as the security
                    and guaranty for the fulfillment of Germany’s obligations under the Agreement,
                    subject, however, to an express understanding that the Agreement did not require
                    the United States to release any German property it then held other than as
                    theretofore or thereafter authorized by the Congress of the United States.</p>
                <p>The facts recited above show the consistently liberal policy followed by the
                    United States toward Germany and German nationals and should leave no doubt as
                    to the obligation and duty of the German Government to make the payments
                    provided for in the Debt Settlement Agreement.</p>
                <p>The Government of the United States would, therefore, appreciate an early
                    statement by the German Government of its intentions with respect to payment of
                    the amount in arrears under the Agreement and of the further annual payments as
                    they fall due. It is important that this information should be received by the
                    Department of State at as early a date as possible, in order that the Congress
                    of the United States may be advised in the premises.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-05-07">May 7,
                            1934</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
