<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Austria ( (Messersmith) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-10-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-10-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="56"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">701.6263/26</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Austria</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 168</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-10-05">October 5,
                            1934</date>.<lb/>[Received October 17.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform the Department that
                    Herr von Papen, the German Minister to Austria arrived here on October 3, from
                    Budapest, in order to take up his duties in this capital.</p>
                <pb facs="0150" n="50" xml:id="pg_50"/>
                <p>As I have already informed the Department, Herr von Papen came to Vienna some
                    weeks ago and presented his letters of credence. He stayed in Vienna only two
                    days and returned to Germany. I saw the Foreign Minister a few days after Herr
                    von Papen had presented his letters and he told me at that time that Herr von
                    Papen had not indicated when he would return to Vienna to actually assume his
                    duties, but left the impression with the Minister that he was returning to
                    Germany until certain measures had been taken with respect to the Austrian
                    Legion and the Headquarters of the Austrian National Socialist Party at Munich,
                    which he felt were essential as preliminary to his assumption of duty. The
                    Foreign Minister at that time expressed to me the pessimistic attitude of the
                    Austrian Government with respect to the probable activities of Herr von
                    Papen.</p>
                <p>In the interval between the presentation of his letters and immediate departure
                    for Germany, and his arrival here on October 3, the activities of the new German
                    Minister have been the subject of considerable speculation here and elsewhere. I
                    am informed in official circles in Austria that Herr von Papen made a number of
                    ineffectual efforts to talk with Chancellor Hitler with the object of getting
                    the assurances and instructions which he wished to have before definitely taking
                    up his duties. Well informed persons here, and this is substantiated by press
                    despatches from Germany, state that he finally succeeded in seeing the
                    Chancellor about two weeks ago and had several long conversations with him.
                    After the finish of these conversations the press carried reports that Herr von
                    Papen was going to visit in Hungary a member of the Hungarian Parliament in
                    order to shoot on his estate, but that the visit was of an entirely private
                    character. This member of Parliament whom Herr von Papen was to visit is known
                    to be very favorably inclined towards the National Socialist Government in
                    Germany and has been actively involved in the conversations and visits which
                    have taken place in recent months between members of the Hungarian Government
                    and representatives of the National-Socialist Government in Germany.</p>
                <p>Herr von Papen went to Budapest by airplane from Germany about ten days ago, and
                    after a very brief stay in Budapest went to the estate of his friend, and later
                    returned to Budapest. On October 3, just before leaving Budapest by automobile
                    for Vienna he gave the following interview to the representatives of the Vienna
                        <hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse:</hi>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">“I found myself very happy in Hungary. I was especially
                            interested in the shooting which turned out wonderfully well. The finest
                            stag which I shot is to be sent to me to Vienna. I had the opportunity
                            while I was here to talk with Minister-President Goemboes, and in the
                            course of our conversation we touched on a number of general problems.
                                <pb facs="0151" n="51" xml:id="pg_51"/> Now I am going to Vienna to
                            again take up my work. I do not know when I shall be coming to Budapest
                            again, but Vienna is really so near, and I hope to come therefore to
                            Budapest again very soon.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I saw the Foreign Minister, Baron Berger-Waldenegg, this morning by appointment
                    made some days ago, in order to get his impressions of his stay in Geneva.
                    During the course of the conversation the Foreign Minister informed me that the
                    German Minister was coming to see him during the morning. It was obvious that he
                    was keenly interested in what Herr von Papen would have to say. He stated to me
                    that the Austrian Government had so far no indications whatever of the nature of
                    Herr von Papen’s instructions and what direction his conversation or activities
                    would take. It was quite clear, however, that the developments in Germany and in
                    Austria and in the general situation have in no sense increased the hopes of the
                    Austrian Government that anything to ameliorate the situation between Germany
                    and Austria can develop out of the new Minister’s activities here.</p>
                <p>The visit which Herr von Papen made to Budapest and the personal character of
                    which was so much emphasized, has not created a good impression here, and has
                    caused a good deal of speculation not only here, but in other capitals. It is
                    now quite clear that he made this trip to Hungary specifically for the purpose
                    of conferring with Minister-President Goemboes before the latter makes his visit
                    to Warsaw, and also to have the opportunity of meeting and talking with
                    Hungarians gathered at the shooting party for this specific purpose. That he
                    should have made this visit before taking up his duties here has not increased
                    the degree of personal or official confidence placed here in Herr von Papen and
                    has not in any way made more easy the obviously difficult task which he has
                    before him.</p>
                <p>The general impression in official circles in Vienna, so far as I am able to
                    learn it, is that the new German Minister comes with no specific promises or
                    assurances to the Austrian Government. It is felt here that German diplomatic
                    action will be increasingly exerted in Warsaw, Belgrade, Sofia, and Budapest
                    with the objective of making any French-Italian agreement impossible, and that
                    while this diplomatic action is in progress the German Minister here will mark
                    time and content himself with the assurances that the German Government is in no
                    sense interfering, and will not interfere, in internal matters in Austria.</p>
                <p>I will not fail to inform the Department of any developments in this connection
                    of which I may learn.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">George S. Messersmith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
