<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-06-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-06-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="632" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d632">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">360H.117/90</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Minister in Yugoslavia</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 59</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-06-11">June 11, 1934</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has received your
                                despatch No. 96 of April 3, 1934, relative to the law regarding
                                military service in the Kingdom <pb facs="0844" n="744" xml:id="pg_744"/> of Yugoslavia, and has carefully noted the
                                enclosures which accompanied your despatch. It appears that on
                                February 16, last, the Yugoslav Vice Consul, in New York City,
                                stated in a letter to an American citizen that a Yugoslav citizen
                                naturalized in a foreign country has a right to visit his homeland
                                three months every three years without being compelled to serve in
                                the army. It is noted that in the letter of March 19, 1934,
                                addressed to you by the American Consul at Belgrade, it is stated
                                that if such a right exists, the Ministry of War apparently is not
                                aware of the fact. It is noted that you placed this matter before
                                the Royal Ministry for Foreign Affairs and asked to be informed
                                whether or not the statement of the Royal Yugoslav Consulate General
                                may be taken as correct, and that in the Ministry’s reply of March
                                26, 1934, you are informed that in accordance with Article 45 of the
                                law of September 6, 1929, regarding the organization of the army and
                                navy, as amended by Article 28 of the law of October 28, 1931, such
                                persons have a right to visit their native land and remain there for
                                a period of six months every three years without being subject to
                                service in the Royal Army.</p>
                            <p>The Department notes the Legation’s opinion that instead of making it
                                possible for a naturalized American citizen to return to Yugoslavia
                                every three years for a short residence without molestation, the
                                amendment of Article 45 of the law of September 6, 1929 by Article
                                28 of the law of October 28, 1931, tends to tighten the regulations
                                regarding military service in Yugoslavia.</p>
                            <p>The Department has very carefully read the translation of the law as
                                amended and believes that the interpretation contained in the Note
                                of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs may be regarded as proper in the
                                cases of naturalized American citizens who have not regularized
                                their status under Article 45 of the law of September 6, 1929 as
                                amended by Article 28 of the law of October 28, 1931. Inasmuch,
                                however, as it appears from your despatch that the Yugoslav military
                                authorities do not administer the law in accordance with that
                                interpretation, the Department cannot advise American citizens in
                                the sense thereof. In this connection, the Department infers from
                                your despatch that so far as the administration of the law is
                                concerned, naturalized American citizens of Yugoslav origin who have
                                not complied with the provisions of the above law as amended are
                                inducted into military service without being allowed any period of
                                unmolested sojourn in Yugoslavia.</p>
                            <p>It is requested that you ask as discreetly as possible the Ministry
                                of Foreign Affairs to discuss this matter with the Ministry of War
                                so that the information furnished by the former and the practice of
                                the military authorities may be harmonized and in order that the
                                Department may be properly advised as to the rights and liabilities
                                of naturalized American citizens of Yugoslav origin while in
                                Yugoslavia. <pb facs="0845" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> Of course, you
                                will on every occasion present to the Yugoslav authorities the
                                Department’s view, based on Section 1999 of the Revised Statutes of
                                the United States, which freely recognizes the principle of the
                                right of expatriation, that a naturalized citizen of the United
                                States should not, upon his return to Yugoslavia, be obliged to
                                perform military or other obligations or be held liable for failure
                                to perform such obligations which had not actually accrued under
                                Yugoslav law, prior to his emigration to the United States.</p>
                            <p>It is desired that you request the Foreign Office to issue
                                appropriate instructions to the Consulate General in New York City
                                in order that the information which was given by that office in the
                                case above referred to may not be repeated, at least not while the
                                practice of the military authorities is known to be contrary to such
                                information.</p>
                            <p>The Department will await a report from you as to the result of your
                                action in this matter.</p>
                            <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                            <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wilbur J. Carr</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>