<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-11-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="807" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d807">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">867.113 Jones and Lamson Machine
                                Co./12</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Skinner</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 419</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Istanbul</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-11-05">November 5, 1934</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    December 1.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I refer to the Department’s
                                Instruction No. 131, dated October 4, 1934,<note n="76" xml:id="d807fn76">Not printed.</note> relative to the possible
                                sale to the Turkish Government of machinery for the manufacture of
                                munitions by the Jones and Lamson Machine Company of Springfield,
                                Vermont. It is noted that the Department deems that it would be
                                contrary to the policy of the United States to finance or otherwise
                                encourage the exportation of the machinery in question. Whether or
                                not the Jones and Lamson Machinery Company can get financial
                                assistance from our commercial banks, which would enable them to
                                obtain this contract, appears to be doubtful.</p>
                            <p>At the present time the Turkish Government is interested in the
                                purchase of a large number of caterpillar tractors for the army, and
                                there is a prospect that this order can be obtained for the United
                                States if facilities can be obtained from the Export-Import Bank,
                                and if the Department entertains no objection to the transaction. It
                                seems probable, having regard to the decision in the Jones and
                                Lamson Machine Company case that the same view would be taken of the
                                sale of tractors.</p>
                            <p>It is to be pointed out, as to both contemplated purchases, that
                                there is no question of what is popularly denominated “high-power
                                salesmanship” of the type recently much discussed in the press. On
                                the contrary, the Turkish Government itself has turned to the United
                                States and manifested a preference for American supplies. If we are
                                unwilling to approve these contracts, they will go to European
                                countries whose representatives are in Ankara doing their utmost to
                                prevent purchases in the United States. I gather from what I have
                                heard that from the purely credit point of view the Export-Import
                                Bank officials are disposed to give the required assistance.</p>
                            <p>As the principles involved in this question are likely to come up in
                                many future instances, both in Turkey and elsewhere, I offer the
                                suggestion that we define our policy with precision. War supplies
                                such as guns, explosives, bombs, cartridges, and the like, are
                                certainly within the purview of the Department’s policy which, it
                                may be hoped, will become an internationally accepted policy. But
                                there is an almost unlimited line of articles in common use which
                                may or may not be used for war purposes. Thus, for example, machine
                                tools needed in Turkey for the army can be used for peacetime
                                purposes, and it may be assumed that they will be so used
                                occasionally. Similarly, caterpillar <pb facs="1070" n="970" xml:id="pg_970"/> tractors, if purchased in the first instance
                                for the army, can be used in a variety of ways, all of them quite
                                innocent.</p>
                            <p>It is to be hoped that we can so formulate and apply our policy as to
                                prevent the loss to our manufacturers and working classes of orders
                                for goods in every-day use, where self-denial would only redound to
                                the advantage of European manufacturers.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Robert P.
                                Skinner</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>