<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Turkey ( (Skinner) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d809</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">809</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="809"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d809">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">767.68119/862</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Skinner</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 279</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Istanbul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-06-12">June 12,
                            1934</date>.<lb/>[Received July 17.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: A good deal has been said of late about Turkey’s
                    intention to seek some modification of the Straits régime at Geneva during the
                    recent attendance of the Foreign Minister, Tevfik Rüştü Bey, at the session of
                    the League of Nations, but the Minister has now returned to Turkey and no formal
                    steps of any kind appear to have been taken with <pb facs="1072" n="972"
                        xml:id="pg_972"/> regard to the Dardanelles. On the contrary, as he passed
                    through Bulgaria he took occasion to say that Turkey had not raised the issue
                    “because she was in a position to defend the Straits.” Again: “Even if some
                    restrictions exist, we are capable of defending the passage. Moreover, we need
                    the permission of nobody to do it.”</p>
                <p>Technically, the Foreign Minister was right. The Straits Convention,<note n="82"
                        xml:id="d809fn82">Signed at Lausanne, July 24, 1923, League of Nations
                        Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xxviii</hi>, p. 115.</note> Article
                    4, declares that the shores of the Dardanelles and the Bosphorus shall be
                    demilitarized, and that within the demilitarized zones no fortifications shall
                    be set up, but Turkey retains the right to send her armed forces through the
                    demilitarized zones and the Turkish fleet has the right to anchor in territorial
                    waters. In fact, in these days of long distance guns and other weapons, the
                    treaty provisions place small restraint upon Turkey in this matter. It is safe
                    to say that the people of this country are far less concerned over the
                    demilitarization of the Straits area than they are over the continued existence
                    of the Straits Commission, which is a thorn in the flesh that they would gladly
                    have removed.</p>
                <p>In a brief historical review the Deputy, Ahmet Sükrü, in his <hi rend="italic">La
                        Turquie</hi>, traces the main facts up to today. Until Russia reached the
                    Black Sea, that body of water was practically an Ottoman lake, the entrance to
                    which was opened and closed by the Sultans according to their pleasure. The
                    Sultans set up a rule that the Straits should be closed to war vessels and
                    obtained acceptance of this rule by all of the States with which the Porte
                    carried on relations. Thus matters continued until 1833 when the Sultan Mahmud
                    signed a treaty<note n="83" xml:id="d809fn83">
                        <hi rend="italic">British and Foreign State Papers</hi>, vol. <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">xx</hi>, p. 1176.</note> which guaranteed the opening
                    of the Straits in favor of the Russians in order that he might have the aid of
                    Tsar Nicholas against Mehmet Ali of Egypt. The British Government, disturbed by
                    this treaty, brought about an international engagement eight years later<note
                        n="84" xml:id="d809fn84">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xxix</hi>, p.
                        703.</note> under which the Straits were closed to ships of war. In this way
                    the opening or closing of the Straits ceased to be a purely Turkish matter and
                    in 1841 became international. Then came the demilitarization of the Black Sea in
                        1856,<note n="85" xml:id="d809fn85">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xlvi</hi>, p.
                        22.</note> followed in 1871 by the abrogation of the clauses concerning the
                    demilitarization of that Sea.<note n="86" xml:id="d809fn86">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">lxi</hi>, p.
                        7.</note> Furthermore the Sultanate obtained the right to open the Straits
                    whenever it desired “to ships of war of friendly States.” This régime continued
                    until the beginning of the Great War in 1914.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert P. Skinner</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
