<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-24T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-24T16:00:00-05:00" n="1139" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1139">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">124.60c/7–2445: Telegram</note>
                                <head>No. 1139<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Appointed Ambassador to
                                        Poland</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_LAB1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lane</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                        the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d1139fn1">Sent over
                                        the signature of <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Caffery</persName>. The same message was sent directly
                                        to the Office of the Political Adviser at Frankfurt for
                                        transmittal to the United States Delegation at
                                        Babelsberg.</note></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi></seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-24T23:00:00+02:00">July 24, 1945—11
                                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>4463. From <persName corresp="#p_LAB1">Lane</persName>.</p>
                                <p>In view delay obtaining for our Embassy to Poland Soviet
                                    clearance across Soviet occupied zone in Germany en route
                                    Warsaw, it is pertinent to summarize steps taken: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>July 6 I inquired of Ambassador <persName>Murphy
                                                Frankfort</persName> whether <persName corresp="#p_ZMSUGK1">Marshal Zhukov</persName> would
                                            clear passage of group provided information furnished re
                                            route to be traveled, names persons in party and numbers
                                            of passports. Arrangements with US military for three
                                            airplanes having been made July 18 Frankfort was
                                            requested that date to obtain Soviet clearance over
                                            Soviet controlled territory. Altho we understood
                                                <persName corresp="#p_ZMSUGK1">Zhukov</persName>’s
                                                <gloss target="#t_HQHQs1">HQs</gloss> had on July 21
                                            given <persName>Murphy</persName>’s office reason to
                                            anticipate receipt that same day of a note granting
                                            permission such permission was not <gloss target="#t_recd1">rec’d</gloss>. It was therefore
                                            necessary to cancel at 9 a.m. July 22 plans for
                                            departure on 23rd as US military authorities Berlin
                                            require 24 hours notice of flight Paris Berlin.</p>
                                        <p>Permission was then requested to cross Soviet controlled
                                            territory on July 26 which should have given sufficient
                                            additional time for action by Soviet authorities and
                                            would also have enabled advance notice to be given to
                                            Polish Govt for our reception in Warsaw and to US
                                            military to have our planes in readiness. Permission
                                            still not having been <gloss target="#t_recd1">rec’d</gloss> we have been obliged again to
                                            postpone departure for Warsaw and to set July 30 as
                                            tentative departure date.</p>
                                    </quote></p>
                                <p>Obstructionist Soviet tactics recall similar measures towards our
                                    missions in Rumania and Bulgaria and especially refusal for
                                    months to permit Embassy to <gloss target="#t_Zecho1">Zecho</gloss> to proceed thru Rumania on ground of military
                                    security. Even this fictional argument does not obtain in case
                                    of Embassy to Poland in view end European <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss>. Furthermore, Soviet Govt has
                                    direct obligation thru Yalta decision to permit American Embassy
                                    to report on conditions in Poland. Fact that <pb facs="1328" n="1132" xml:id="pg_1132"/> British Chargé already arrived
                                    Warsaw great interest in US re conditions Poland and
                                    specifically re holding elections will undoubtedly create
                                    unfavorable public reaction unless immediate steps taken to
                                    grant our request. It will be recalled that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName>, in his conversations
                                    with <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> last
                                        May,<note n="2" xml:id="d1139fn2">See <ref target="frus1945Berlinv01#pg_27">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 27</ref>.</note>
                                    emphasized deterioration of public opinion in US towards Soviet
                                    Union as result of Polish question and had explained that this
                                    was principal reason for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName> going to Moscow and that this was
                                    principal cause of anxiety at that time. (Sent <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>; <gloss target="#t_rptd1">rptd</gloss> Frankfort for Berlin as 53 for attention
                                    Secretary State and Moscow 207.)</p>
                                <p>I therefore recommend that the Secretary consider desirability of
                                    taking up this matter in Berlin on highest level.</p>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>