<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No. 1151
                    Proposal by the United States Delegation
                    Handed to Molotov July 29. See ante, p. 472.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1151</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1151</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="1151" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1151">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> Papers</note>
                <head>No. 1151<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Proposal by the United States Delegation</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d1151fn1">Handed to <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> July 29. See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_472">p. 472</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Babelsberg</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-29">July 29,
                            1945</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In conformity with the agreement on Poland reached at the Crimean Conference the
                    three Heads of Government have sought the opinion of the Polish Provisional
                    Government of National Unity in regard to the accession of territory in the
                    north and west which Poland should receive. The President of Poland and members
                    of the Polish Provisional Government of National Unity have been received at the
                    Conference and have fully presented their views. The three Heads of Government
                    reaffirm their opinion that the final delimitation of the western frontier of
                    Poland should await the peace settlement.</p>
                <p>The three Heads of Government agree that, pending the final determination of
                    Poland’s western frontier, the former German territories east of a line running
                    from the Baltic Sea through Swinemünde, to west of Stettin to the Oder and
                    thence along the Oder River to the confluence of the eastern Neisse River<note n="2" xml:id="d1151fn2">i. e., the Glatzer Neisse or Nysa Kłodzka. See the
                        map facing <ref target="#pg_1152">p. 1152</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note> and along the eastern Neisse to the Czechoslovak
                    frontier, including that portion of East Prussia not placed under the
                    administration of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in accordance with the
                    understanding reached at this conference and including the area of the former
                    free city of Danzig shall be under the administration of the Polish State and
                    for such purposes should not be considered as part of the Soviet zone of
                    occupation in Germany.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
