<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-17T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-17T04:00:00-05:00" n="1187" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1187">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.796/7–1745: Telegram</note>
                                <head>No. 1187<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United
                                        Kingdom</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WJG2" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d1187fn1">The gist of
                                        this message was included in telegram No. 65 of July 19 from
                                            <persName corresp="#p_GJC1">Grew</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName> (file No. 800.00
                                        Summaries/7–1945).</note></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-17T10:00:00+01:00">July 17, 1945—10
                                            a.m.</date></dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>7182. With reference to the Embassy’s telegrams<note n="2" xml:id="d1187fn2">Not printed.</note> reporting various
                                    efforts on the part of the British to have steps taken which
                                    would lead to a fairly early agreement on the commercial aspects
                                    of air transport with the United States, <persName corresp="#p_HSW1">Sir William Hildred</persName> informed
                                    the Civil Air Attaché<note n="3" xml:id="d1187fn3"><persName corresp="#p_SL1">Livingston
                                        Satterthwaite</persName>.</note> that he hoped and expected
                                    to be able to go to the United States between now and August 2
                                    (when the Civil Aviation Radio Conference opens) partly in
                                    connection with setting up of the Interim Council<note n="4" xml:id="d1187fn4">Of the Provisional International Civil
                                        Aviation Organization.</note> but primarily to discuss the
                                    Fifth Freedom<note n="5" xml:id="d1187fn5">See <ref target="frus1945Berlinv01#d547">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, document No.
                                        547</ref>.</note> with <persName corresp="#p_PLW1">Pogue</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_WE1">Warner</persName>. The Department will observe that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HSW1">Sir William</persName> made this
                                    statement a day or two after the closing of the Empire Aviation
                                    conference and that the suggestion is now not that <persName corresp="#p_PLW1">Pogue</persName> come to England but that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HSW1">Hildred</persName> go to the
                                    United States. He said frankly that he believed he would be more
                                    successful in obtaining <persName corresp="#p_SV1">Swinton</persName>’s approval for the trip, which he had
                                    been unable to do before, in view of the “progress in thinking”
                                    which the Empire Aviation Conference developed. He said he
                                    thought that the British Government would agree to an
                                    arrangement with the United States and with other countries
                                    which set forth the principle that (1) the more international
                                    air transportation the better for mankind[,] (2) all economic
                                    and other burdensome restrictions on civil aviation should be
                                    removed and (3) the principle of the Fifth Freedom in general
                                    was necessary to the successful development of air
                                    transportation. He felt that where it could be demonstrated that
                                    the unrestricted exercise of short-range pickup traffic by
                                    strong nations destroyed or seriously upset some regional
                                    airlines, the Interim Council should be able to rectify such
                                    obvious injustices. He thought that the major international
                                    airlines would recognize sufficiently the value to them of
                                    prosperous feeder line services along their routes so that they
                                    would be careful not to put them out of business. <persName corresp="#p_HSW1">Sir William</persName> stressed the
                                    necessity of keeping the foregoing strictly confidential.</p>
                                <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WJG2"><hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>