<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 1378Memorandum by the Executive Secretary of the Central Secretariat (
                    (Yost))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1378</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1378</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-08-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="1378"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1378">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 (Potsdam)/8–945</note>
                <head>No. 1378<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Executive Secretary of the Central
                        Secretariat</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_YCW1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Yost</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d1378fn1">Printed from the ribbon copy, which is
                        unsigned. For the minutes of the discussions summarized in this memorandum,
                        see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_256">pp. 256</ref>–<ref
                            target="#pg_258">258</ref>, <ref target="#pg_302">302</ref>–<ref
                            target="#pg_305">305</ref>, <ref target="#pg_365">365</ref>–<ref
                            target="#pg_367">367</ref>, <ref target="#pg_527">527</ref>, <ref
                            target="#pg_577">577</ref>–<ref target="#pg_578">578</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-08-09">August 9,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin Conference</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Turkey and the Black Sea Straits</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Soviet Policy</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Soviets presented a proposal<note n="2" xml:id="d1378fn2">
                        <ref target="#d1369">Document No. 1369</ref>.</note> providing for the
                    revision of the Montreux Convention, for the control of the Straits by the
                    Soviet Union and Turkey alone and for the establishment of Soviet bases on the
                    Straits. <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> said that they
                    considered the Montreux Convention to be inimical to Russia in that it left
                    Turkey free to block the Straits whenever she thought she was threatened. This
                    meant that a small state had a great state by the throat and was a situation
                    which would not be permitted by the United States in Panama or by Britain in the
                    Suez. It is essential that Soviet shipping be able to pass to and from the Black
                    Sea safely and Turkey was too weak to guarantee such passage in case
                    complications arose. If it was thought that Soviet naval bases in the Straits
                    would be unacceptable to the Turks, then the Soviets should have some other
                    nearby base where the Russian fleet could refuel and where in cooperation with
                    its allies it could protect the Straits. He did not consider a mere
                    international guarantee of the freedom of the Straits to be adequate and was not
                    sure that Turkey would accept such international control. The Soviets pointed
                    out that international control of this kind is not applied to the Suez Canal.
                    This phase of the matter is left undecided, the Protocol merely recording the
                    agreement of all three governments that the Montreux Convention should be
                    revised and stating that each of the three governments would have direct
                    conversations with the Turkish Government on the question.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d1378fn3">See <ref target="#d1383">document No. 1383</ref>, section
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">xvii</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">xvi</hi>).</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1638" n="1440" xml:id="pg_1440"/>
                <p>As to other phases of Soviet-Turkish relations, the Soviets maintained that the
                    Turks had taken the initiative in seeking a treaty of alliance since such a
                    treaty would involve a mutual guarantee of frontiers. The Soviets have replied
                    that they could not enter into such an alliance as long as Kars and Ardahan,
                    which had been snatched from the Soviet Union, remained a part of Turkey. They
                    would not have raised this territorial question if the Turks had not asked for a
                    treaty of alliance.</p>
                <p>They insisted that the Turks had no reason to be alarmed as to Soviet intentions.
                    They maintained that they had only 30,000 troops in Bulgaria which was far less
                    than the Turks had on their European frontier. The one point on which the
                    Soviets seemed to be adamant in connection with Turkey was for some arrangement
                    which would give them effective control of passage through the Straits in time
                    of <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss> or emergency.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">British Policy</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The British exhibited grave anxiety in regard to Soviet intentions vis-à-vis
                    Turkey. They first raised the question at the Conference and asked the Soviets
                    for a statement of their intentions. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1"
                        >Churchill</persName> expressed himself as quite willing to support a
                    revision of the Montreux Convention with the participation of all the parties to
                    that Convention except Japan. He stated that he felt it perfectly proper that
                    there should be free passage of the Straits for Russian as for all other ships
                    in time of <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss> as in time of peace. He attached
                    great importance to the President’s statement that the United States was
                    prepared to join in an international guarantee of the free and unrestricted use
                    of the Straits. He appeared to be strongly opposed to the establishment of
                    Soviet bases on the Straits, though he couched his argument chiefly in terms of
                    his belief that the Turks would never consent to such bases. He made it clear
                    that the British would support the Turks in the protection of their legitimate
                    rights. He urged strongly that the Soviets not take any action which would
                    frighten the Turks, pointing out that the recent conversations in Moscow coupled
                    with the presence of large numbers of Russian troops in Bulgaria had served to
                    frighten the Turks. He seemed willing to support some form of international
                    control of the Straits if that should prove to be a satisfactory means of
                    settling the difficulty. In response to a remark by <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> that there was no such international control of the Suez
                    Canal, <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> replied that the Suez
                    was open to all ships of all nations at all times and that protection was
                    maintained in accordance with a treaty freely concluded between Britain and
                    Egypt.</p>
                <p>There was little discussion of this question after the change in the British
                    Government but from such discussion as there was it appeared that the Labor
                    Ministers supported <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s
                    position.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
