<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Department of State Minutes</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d710a-72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">[Unnumbered document following Document 710
                    (#72)]</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-07-23T03:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-07-23T03:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recUInGVZ0Y3MeuOS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">International organizations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-23T03:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-23T03:30:00-05:00"
                n="[Unnumbered document following Document 710 (#72)]" subtype="historical-document"
                type="document" xml:id="d710a-72">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> Papers</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Department of State Minutes</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Potsdam</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1945-07-23T11:30:00+03:00">July 23, 1945, 11:30 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>The sixth session of Foreign Ministers opened at 11:30 a.m. on July 23, 1945. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> was in the Chair.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> first announced that he wished to state the questions which were up for
                    discussion. They were: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Reparations from Germany and Italy;</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Economic Principles Regarding Germany;</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Report of the Subcommittee on the Council of Foreign
                            Ministers;</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Trusteeships;</item>
                        <pb facs="0457" n="277" xml:id="pg_277"/>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The Directive to the Allied Commanders-in-Chief in Germany;</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Paper on Cooperation in Solving urgent European Economic
                            Problems;</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Perhaps Iran.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that Iran was on the Big Three agenda.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> agreed and suggested that it be passed over.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then suggested Tangier, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> agreed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then suggested the proposed text of the invitations to China and France
                    and added that the morning agenda would conclude with the preparation of an
                    agenda for the Big Three. He asked whether there were any other questions. If
                    so, they should be stated. He remarked that several questions now before
                    subcommittees were not yet ready for discussion. These included the questions of
                    Italy and Spain and several others.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Reparations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then brought up the matter of reparations and circulated a paper
                    containing the principal suggestions of the Soviet delegation on this matter.
                    The first paper was entitled “Plan for Reparations from Germany.”<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d710a-72fn1">
                        <ref target="#d920">Document No. 920</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> He then mentioned the draft considered by the Commission
                    regarding advance deliveries from Germany<note n="2" xml:id="d710a-72fn2">It has
                        not been determined what draft is here referred to.</note> and submitted a
                    Soviet draft.<note n="3" xml:id="d710a-72fn3">
                        <ref target="#d921">Document No. 921</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> He stated that there were other reparations questions
                    which could not be raised now. There was need for time to study them and
                    consideration could be postponed until tomorrow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> agreed that it was best to postpone consideration since documents had been
                    received only now and time would be needed to study them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> remarked that he was certainly not now prepared to comment on the Soviet
                    proposals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> accepted this position but asked whether informal conversations could not
                    be held on the matter in the present meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> asked that the Economic Subcommittee work at the drafts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> agreed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> agreed that the papers should not be considered during the present
                    meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> then asked about <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s
                    reference to informal conversations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that the question of reparations is linked with other economic
                    questions, such as <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss> booty, and it would be a
                        <pb facs="0458" n="278" xml:id="pg_278"/> good idea to have informal
                    exchanges of view. However, he is ready to accept any proposal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> then asked for postponement until tomorrow and that there should be no
                    informal conversations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> agreed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then stated that the second question concerned economic principles, which
                    was not finished yesterday. He stated his readiness to withdraw his amendment to
                    paragraph 13 and hoped that his colleagues could agree on 18.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d710a-72fn4">Cf. <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_233"
                            >pp. 233</ref>–<ref target="#pg_234">234</ref>. The paragraphs 13 and 18
                        referred to are in the attachment to <ref target="#d863">document No.
                            863</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post;</hi> paragraph 5 is in <ref
                            target="#d863">document No. 863</ref> proper.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> replied that it was the American position that paragraph 18 should remain
                    in the document.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> agreed and pointed out that paragraph 18 is linked with paragraph 5 of the
                    report of the Committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then made a statement regarding the paragraph mentioned by Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>. He maintained that the subcommittee report
                    was not accurate. The present Conference should not discuss how to deal with
                    German territory. He knew that the idea is to supply Germany as far as possible
                    from territories where supplies were drawn before the <gloss target="#t_War1"
                        >war</gloss>. However, heavy damage in some areas has radically changed the
                    situation. He did not believe that it was possible for the Conference to know
                    where conditions have changed and to what degree. This matter should be referred
                    to the Council. It was the affair of our representatives and should be referred
                    to them. They can deal with the questions specifically. He mentioned the
                    opposing views of <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> on this matter and therefore
                    concluded that nothing could be accepted as being generally binding. He wished
                    to decide these matters by means of our representatives in Germany who if they
                    did not agree could refer questions to their governments. If they attempted to
                    write a paper applicable to Germany as it was before the <gloss target="#t_War1"
                        >war</gloss>, the Soviet Union could not agree. He suggested that the
                    question in paragraph 18 should not be decided either way at this meeting. There
                    should be no binding decision taken at this time. It should be decided in
                    accordance with future developments in Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> doubted that it would help much to pass the question on to the Control
                    Council. There were already differences of opinion in the Council on temporary
                    problems on how to fuel Berlin. A temporary arrangement had been reached on this
                    matter in order to tide it over this Conference.<note n="5" xml:id="d710a-72fn5"
                        >See <ref target="frus1945Berlinv01#d433">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>,
                            document No. 433</ref>.</note> A common solution must now be found in
                    order to meet the situation adequately.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> insisted that if he did accept this suggestion, it would make no practical
                    difference since all disagreements would <pb facs="0459" n="279" xml:id="pg_279"
                    /> remain. He pointed out that there are no figures on how much coal, food and
                    other materials are available or are necessary. This must be decided by the
                    Control Council when data is available. The Control Council at that time will be
                    able to reach a common agreement or will refer the matter to their governments.
                    If this article is accepted there would still be no practical solution. The
                    question would still go back to the governments. He suggested that if agreement
                    could not be reached, the matter be referred to the Big Three.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> admitted the truth of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s
                    contention to the effect that agreement on this principle would not solve the
                    practical problems of coal and food. On the other hand, this principle would
                    constitute a good basis upon which the Control Council could make decisions;
                    otherwise, there would be no basis to guide them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> replied that the Soviet Union could not accept now because of differences
                    in conception of the German problem. He suggested that the question be studied
                    in a business-like fashion for several weeks or for several days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> inquired whether Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> would
                    object to a statement of general principles to the effect that in the absence of
                    a specific reason, supplies would as far as possible be drawn from the same
                    areas as before the <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss>. He pointed out that the
                    statement actually says “so far as practicable.” Such a statement would be a
                    guide to assist the Control Council in their determinations of such questions.
                    If we simply referred the matter to them Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1"
                        >Byrnes</persName> feared that they would be unable to decide and would only
                    send the question back to their governments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> replied that he could not agree now because he had no data. Time was
                    needed. When the study had been made the matter might be reconsidered. He
                    suggested reference to the Big Three, and all agreed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then raised the question of the relative priority of exports and
                    reparations. He asked for consideration of the Soviet draft<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d710a-72fn6">
                        <ref target="#d872">Document No. 872</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> which he distributed and inquired whether his suggestion
                    was clear.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> replied that the American position is clear. It is the position of the
                    United States that there will be no reparations until imports in the American
                    zone are paid for. There can be no discussion of this matter. We do not intend,
                    as we did after the last <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss>, to provide the
                    money for the payment of reparations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> gave an example of the sense of his suggestion. He supposed the
                    possibility that 2 million tons of coal would be produced, and the total
                    requirements for internal use, export and reparations would amount to 2,200,000
                    tons. In this case he suggested <pb facs="0460" n="280" xml:id="pg_280"/> that
                    exports and reparations be reduced 10 per cent to make up the difference. It
                    would mean that both exports and reparations would be little less and that over
                    a period of a year’s time the situation might be balanced. If during the whole
                    year there was still a shortage of 10 per cent, all three factors, including
                    internal consumption, would be reduced 10 per cent.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> considered this to be a simple and fair solution. He stated that if
                    production were increased over the figure set the reparations amount would not
                    change. This would mean a surplus either for internal use or for export as the
                    Control Council should decide. He asked whether this was not a fair
                    arrangement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> stated that it seemed to him that either imports should be a first charge
                    or reparations should be a first charge or that as now suggested they should
                    have an equal status. He considered it certain that if exports were not
                    sufficient to cover imports someone must make deliveries without payment
                    therefor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> replied that imports could be reduced.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that the Soviet Union had agreed to a minimum import program
                    which must be fulfilled and which cannot be cut to meet reparations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> thought that shortages in coal exports might be compensated by increased
                    exports of other commodities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> remarked that he had stated his position. Imports must be a first charge
                    and not a dollar will be paid on reparations until imports are paid for.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then made another suggestion. Such German exports as had been agreed to by
                    the Control Council should have a first priority. On other exports reparations
                    would have first priority. All exports approved by the Control Council would be
                    carried out in the first instance.<note n="7" xml:id="d710a-72fn7">Cf. <ref
                            target="#d873">document No. 873</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>. The
                            <hi rend="italic">Rapporteur’s</hi> report (<hi rend="italic">post</hi>,
                            <ref target="#pg_290">p. 290</ref>) indicates that <persName
                            corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> put forward as an alternative an
                        actual draft.</note> He suggested that if the Foreign Ministers were unable
                    to agree, that the matter be referred to the Big Three.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> asked for permission to clarify the situation. He pointed out that the
                    Control Council has agreed to a minimum export program. If this program is cut
                    in any way it can only be done at the expense of someone, say the miners who are
                    producing coal. In order to avoid such a situation someone must bring in
                    supplies without payment. Therefore, imports must be a first charge.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that this was not quite clear to him and asked Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> to repeat the statement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> did so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> stated that if we lessened food supplies we lessened production.</p>
                <pb facs="0461" n="281" xml:id="pg_281"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> suggested the possibility of cutting internal consumption.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> stated that we have started with a program of minimum import needs and it
                    was therefore impossible to reduce internal consumption in order to provide for
                    reparations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that he had made the suggestion that where the Control Council
                    had approved imports they would be a first charge although they might possibly
                    affect reparations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> stated that everything must be approved by the Control Council.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> gave another example of his meaning. Say the Control Council had decided
                    on the export of 500,000 tons of coal at a time when it was planned to produce
                    2,000,000 tons. Suppose the British then wanted to export 700,000 tons. His
                    suggestion would mean that the 500,000 tons would be a first charge and the
                    supplementary 200,000 tons would be subject to reparations needs. To summarize,
                    the exports approved by the Control Council for the payment of imports is to be
                    a first charge. In other cases reparations have priority. In the example cited
                    the 500,000 ton exports would have priority but the 200,000 additional would be
                    subject to a reparations priority. However, if the Control Council agreed that
                    the 200,000 tons should be exported in order to pay for imports then they would
                    also have priority over reparations. He again suggested reference of the matter
                    to the Big Three.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Council of Foreign Ministers</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that there was a final draft on the establishment of the Council of
                    Foreign Ministers.<note n="8" xml:id="d710a-72fn8">
                        <ref target="#d714">Document No. 714</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> He had no comment and after asking for comment asked that
                    the draft be considered as approved.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Trusteeship</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then raised the subject of trusteeship and asked for comments on the
                    Soviet draft.<note n="9" xml:id="d710a-72fn9">
                        <ref target="#d733">Document No. 733</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> He pointed out that the Soviet draft deals in the first
                    place with the Italian colonies and suggested that a definite determination be
                    made of the future status of these colonies. If they are to be separated from
                    Italy, a joint trusteeship under the United States, United Kingdom and the
                    Soviet Union should be established.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out there were two problems in regard to the Italian colonies. The
                    first problem is whether Italy lost the <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss> or
                    not. The British have said that Italy has no right to get her colonies back but
                    have not gone beyond that point. The British believe that this question should
                    be considered in connection with the settlement <pb facs="0462" n="282"
                        xml:id="pg_282"/> of a peace treaty by the Council of Foreign Ministers.
                    When our minds are made up whether colonies go back to Italy or not, then it is
                    probable that the United Nations organization would decide on the form of
                    trusteeship, if any.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that the American position had been stated by the President
                    yesterday afternoon.<note n="10" xml:id="d710a-72fn10">See <hi rend="italic"
                            >ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_253">pp. 253</ref>–<ref target="#pg_255"
                            >255</ref>.</note> At the President’s suggestion it was tentatively
                    agreed that the conclusion of the peace treaty with Italy would be the first
                    business of the Council of Foreign Ministers.<note n="11" xml:id="d710a-72fn11"
                        >See <ref target="#d714">document No. 714</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> As a result the Foreign Ministers and their governments
                    must determine the disposition of the colonies and the Trieste boundaries and
                    any other decisions in regard to Italian territory. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName> did not see how the Conference could
                    decide what territories should be taken from Italy and what trusteeships should
                    be established. It is true that the Charter<note n="12" xml:id="d710a-72fn12">Of
                        the United Nations (Treaty Series No. 993; 59 <gloss target="#t_Stat1"
                            >Stat</gloss>. (2) 1031).</note> provided that there can be an agreement
                    as to trusteeships. The colonies referred to by the Soviet Union are now in the
                    custody of the United Kingdom. If there was an agreement between them the matter
                    could be considered here; but there is no agreement and there can be no
                    disposition until peace is concluded. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1"
                        >Byrnes</persName> did not see how the conference could decide this
                    question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that he would like to make a statement. <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eden</persName> had publicly stated in Parliament several times the British
                        position.<note n="13" xml:id="d710a-72fn13">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>,
                            <ref target="#pg_239">p. 239, footnote 2</ref>.</note> Therefore their
                    position can be clearly seen; but it has not been disclosed to the Allies, The
                    colonies are now in the custody of the British Army. Under these conditions
                    there was ground to believe that the British might wish to express an opinion.
                    If they do not wish to do so now perhaps they will later. The trusteeship
                    question had been raised in San Francisco and even in Moscow by the United
                    States. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> had no doubt that the
                    American Government has considered this question. He hoped that the United
                    States Government would give an expression of its views to the Allies. The
                    Soviet Government will express their views. If the matter is not to be discussed
                    now, he would agree. That is why the Soviet Government had suggested discussion
                    in the Council of Foreign Ministers. The matter will be referred to the first
                    meeting in London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> stated that the United States had presented both at Dumbarton Oaks<note
                        n="14" xml:id="d710a-72fn14">Concerning the general nature of the Dumbarton
                        Oaks conversations referred to, see <persName corresp="#p_KHM1"
                            >Harley</persName> A. Notter, <hi rend="italic">Postwar Foreign Policy
                            Preparation, 1939–1945</hi> (Washington, Government Printing Office,
                        1949; Department of State publication No. 3580), p. 301. No provisions
                        regarding trusteeship were included in the proposals agreed upon at
                        Dumbarton Oaks; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., appendix 43, p. 611.</note>
                    and at San Francisco its general views on trusteeships. However, it did not
                    state its views on specific colonies. The <pb facs="0463" n="283"
                        xml:id="pg_283"/> Council of Foreign Ministers at its first meeting would
                    pass on this and must necessarily make a decision regarding the disposal of the
                    colonies. If it was determined that the colonies or some of them were to be
                    taken from Italy, it was proper and necessary to decide the question of
                    administration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> added that the British Government has not yet decided whether some or all
                    of the colonies should be taken from Italy. He agreed that this should be
                    discussed in the Council of Foreign Ministers in the London meeting at the time
                    they drew up the peace treaty with Italy. Until then it was not worth while to
                    talk about trusteeships. However, he thought that the new world organization
                    should decide this question.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> asked whether it was agreed that this question would not be disposed of
                    here.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then suggested that the Soviet memorandum be referred to the Council of
                    Foreign Ministers for consideration at its first meeting in London.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> remarked there was no point in referring the Soviet memorandum since the
                    first task of the Council will be the preparation of peace terms for Italy and
                    the matter would come up automatically.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that he of course fully agreed. However, the question of the
                    western frontiers of Poland was a question to be considered by the Council of
                    Foreign Ministers in their preparation of peace treaties. Despite this the
                    matter is being dealt with now. In any event, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> asked that note be taken of the fact that the matter
                    would be raised in the first meeting of the Council.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> stated that this is fully understood.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Directive to Allied Commanders-in-Chief in Germany</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that the next subject up for discussion was the proposed directive
                    to Allied Commanders-in-Chief in Germany.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> stated that this paper<note n="15" xml:id="d710a-72fn15">
                        <ref target="#d870">Document No. 870</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> was proposed because in the opinion of the American
                    representative on the Control Council<note n="16" xml:id="d710a-72fn16">General
                        of the <persName corresp="#p_EGADD1">Army Dwight D.
                        Eisenhower</persName>.</note> it was desirable to have such a directive
                    issued giving instructions to the Commanders in each zone to carry out whatever
                    agreement was reached at this Conference. Therefore, he suggested that the
                    matter be referred to a committee in order that the Soviet and British
                    Delegations could make any suggestions they desired regarding the proposal. The
                    directive would simply give the Commanders instructions from their Heads of
                    State and each Commander would have the same instructions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> stated that he was a little puzzled regarding the need for this directive.
                    He pointed out that they had had before them <pb facs="0464" n="284"
                        xml:id="pg_284"/> principles on [<hi rend="italic">of?</hi>] agreement in
                    the handling of Germany. The political principles had been approved.<note n="17"
                        xml:id="d710a-72fn17">
                        <ref target="#d856">Document No. 856</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> They were based on an American draft<note n="18"
                        xml:id="d710a-72fn18">
                        <ref target="#d852">Document No. 852</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> which he considered to be extremely well set up. He had
                    assumed that these principles would go to the British Commanders in order to
                    guide them. He thought that this would be enough. The proposed discussion [<hi
                        rend="italic">directive?</hi>] covers to some extent similar grounds [<hi
                        rend="italic">sic</hi>]. Some things are left out and some added. Some very
                    good things had been left out.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> stated that his purpose is to have the matter referred to a committee in
                    order that past and future agreements of the Conference could be put into a
                    directive from the Heads of States to the Commanders. We should transmit to each
                    Commander everything decided at this Conference. This should be done before the
                    Conference ends.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> believed that there was some point in Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eden</persName>’s remarks. The proposed directive repeats what has been
                    said in the document on political principles plus some economic. He asked
                    whether it was advisable to have two wordings on the same points a ad stated
                    that he did not know how to solve this difficulty. If the purpose is to give
                    additional direction, the Soviet Government might consider; but decisions have
                    already been taken on political directives and are to be taken on economic
                    matters. These would be sent to the Commanders and the advantage of the
                    directive is not clear.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> agreed that the language should be the same. His only idea was to make
                    certain that the Commanders would know what had been decided at this Conference.
                    He suggested the appointment of a committee to incorporate the language
                    previously approved plus any that may be approved in the future, into a
                    directive. Either we can do this or let the Commanders read about it in the
                    press or perhaps they could be sent a copy of the communiqué. Army people
                    generally want written directives and <persName corresp="#p_EGADD1">General
                        Eisenhower</persName> has asked for this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> thought <persName corresp="#p_EGADD1">General Eisenhower</persName> might
                    not have known that we had adopted a set of political principles based on the
                    draft submitted by the United States. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eden</persName> agreed entirely that the directives given to the Commanders
                    must be written and the British had intended to send their Commander all agreed
                    principles. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> suggested that before
                    agreements were communicated to the Commanders, France should be consulted in
                    order that the directive should be uniform in all four zones.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> agreed to this proposal and restated his desire for <pb facs="0465"
                        n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/> some machinery to send to the Commanders whatever
                    was decided at the Conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> asked whether consideration would be given to bringing France in line.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> agreed and inquired about the composition of the subcommittee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> named Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> and Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> named Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SSW1">[<hi rend="italic">Sir William</hi>]
                        Strang</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GCHA1"
                    >Harrison</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> named Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GFT1">Gusev</persName> and Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SAA1">Sobolev</persName>.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cooperation in Solving Urgent European Economic
                        Problems</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that the next question concerned cooperation in solving urgent
                    European economic problems.<note n="19" xml:id="d710a-72fn19">See <ref
                            target="#d1161">document No. 1161</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> He thought it advisable to establish a subcommittee to
                    consider this matter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> agreed that this was the best thing to do.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> named Mr. <persName corresp="#p_A3">Arutunian</persName> and Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_G9">Goroshenko</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> named Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BHTH1">Brand</persName> and Mr. Phillips
                        [<persName corresp="#p_CJE2">
                        <hi rend="italic">Coulson</hi>
                    </persName>].<note n="20" xml:id="d710a-72fn20">The <hi rend="italic"
                            >Rapporteur’s</hi> report (<hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref
                            target="#pg_291">pp. 291</ref> and <ref target="#pg_301">301</ref>)
                        names <persName corresp="#p_CJE2">Coulson</persName> as the second British
                        member. There was no Phillips on the British Delgation.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> suggested that the matter be referred to the Economic Committee [<hi
                        rend="italic">Subcommittee</hi>].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> replied that this committee was not suitable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> then named Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWL1">Clayton</persName> and Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PEW1">Pauley</persName>.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <persName corresp="#p_I1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Iran</hi>
                    </persName>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then raised the question of Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> stated that this would be considered at another time.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then brought up the question of Tangier.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> stated that there was to be a preliminary discussion of this matter in
                    Paris soon and that we would welcome Soviet participation in the
                        discussion.<note n="21" xml:id="d710a-72fn21">See <ref
                            target="frus1945Berlinv01#pg_980">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp.
                            980</ref>–<ref target="frus1945Berlinv01#pg_1009">1009</ref>, and <ref
                            target="#d1350">documents Nos. 1350</ref>, <ref target="#d1352"
                            >1352</ref>, <ref target="#d1353">1353</ref>, and <ref target="#d1357"
                            >1357</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note> He stated that he was
                    in entire agreement with the principles contained in paragraph 1 of the Soviet
                        draft<note n="22" xml:id="d710a-72fn22">
                        <ref target="#d1356">Document No. 1356</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note> to the effect that the Zone should remain international
                    and that steps should be taken to put an end to Spanish occupation. It was to
                    consider how best this could be done that the suggestion was made that the
                    meeting should be convened in Paris. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eden</persName> stated the hope that all governments signatory to the Act
                    of Algeciras<note n="23" xml:id="d710a-72fn23">Signed April 7, 1906. For text,
                        see Treaty Series No. 456; 34 <gloss target="#t_Stat1">Stat</gloss>. (3)
                        2905; <ref target="frus1906p2#pg_1495">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1906, pt. 2, p.
                        1495</ref>.</note> would meet before final decisions were taken. He did not
                    feel that the four powers could ignore the interests of the small powers. He
                    hoped that a full conference could meet before long. He did not think that it
                        <pb facs="0466" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/> was right for the Conference to
                    consider the subject since there was to be a meeting soon and the French have
                    considerable interest in the matter. The position of Spain would of course have
                    to be considered in the Paris meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> asked what was suggested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> replied that he suggested an early Paris meeting between the
                    representatives of the three powers here and the French.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> suggested the adoption of paragraph 1 and agreement that the four powers
                    would meet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> replied that he must say that he had told the French that the British
                    would not join in a settlement of the Tangier situation without the French.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> asked whether it was agreed that the four powers should work out an
                    agreement. He stated his assumption that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eden</persName> would prefer no publicity in the press.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> wondered whether such a paradise was possible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> then asked whether the Soviet Union wanted an announcement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> stated that it would be unwise to make an announcement that we are going
                    to the French capital in order to decide the Tangier question. Also, there were
                    the other signatories of the Act to be considered. It is enough that we here
                    agree to have conversations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that the Soviet Union would not insist on an announcement. He
                    suggested agreement among the Foreign Ministers without publicity that we accept
                    paragraph 1 of the Soviet paper and that we will meet in Paris.</p>
                <p>This was agreed to.<note n="24" xml:id="d710a-72fn24">See <ref target="#d1383"
                            >document No. 1383</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, section <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">xvi</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">xv</hi>).</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Invitations to China and France</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> brought up the subject of the proposed invitations to China and France. He
                    suggested that after the words “members of Council” there should be added the
                    words “by agreement between them.” After looking at Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>’ draft he agreed that it was all right
                    without this change.<note n="25" xml:id="d710a-72fn25">See <ref target="#d1383"
                            >document No. 1383</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, section <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">i</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Agenda for Big Three</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> then asked for consideration of an agenda for the Big Three.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> intervened to suggest that a time should be set for sending the
                    invitations to China and France. He remarked that if they were sent now they
                    might become known to the press. He suggested <pb facs="0467" n="287"
                        xml:id="pg_287"/> sending the invitations the day before the issuance of the
                    communiqué and the end of the Conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> thought that there should be a little more notice than one day in order to
                    give a chance for an answer to be received. He suggested 48-hour notice.</p>
                <p>This was agreed to.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Agenda for Big Three</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> again asked for the formulation of an agenda for the afternoon Big Three
                    meeting. He stated that there would be: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Turkey</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Koenigsberg</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Syria and the Levant</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Persia</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> mentioned the question of reparations from Germany and Italy, but it was
                    agreed that this should not go on the agenda but should be discussed in the next
                    day’s meeting of the Foreign Ministers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> also raised the question of economic principles but this was put over
                    until the next day.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> then brought up the fact that the question of the admission of Italy into
                    international organizations and the exclusion of Spain from them had been
                    referred to a committee,<note n="26" xml:id="d710a-72fn26">See <hi rend="italic"
                            >ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_150">pp. 150</ref>, <ref target="#pg_159"
                            >159</ref>.</note> which had not yet reported. He understood that part
                    of the paper had been agreed to and suggested that the committee report back if
                    it was unable to agree. There had been a suggestion that there would be two
                    separate papers and then a proposal that they be combined into one paper. At the
                    present time they were incorporated in one paper.<note n="27"
                        xml:id="d710a-72fn27">Presumably <ref target="#d729">document No. 729</ref>,
                            <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note> He thought that this matter might be
                    disposed of.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> asked what suggestions Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    had.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> replied that he suggested that the matter be acted on now and disposed of.
                    He understood that there was no difficulty about the matter except whether there
                    should be two papers or one. He was willing to take either.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> suggested the drafting committee have one more try and that otherwise the
                    matter would be considered tomorrow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> stated that it was not entirely a question of whether there should be one
                    or two documents.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> then asked for a report from the subcommittee either for or against the
                    paper tomorrow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> then circulated a note by the Prime Minister on the Greek situation.<note
                        n="28" xml:id="d710a-72fn28">
                        <ref target="#d1066">Document No. 1066</ref>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >post</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The meeting then adjourned.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
