<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-22T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-22T09:00:00-05:00" n="[Unnumbered document following Document 710 (#66)]" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d710a-66">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source"><persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> Papers</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_CBV1">Cohen</persName>
                                    Notes</hi></head>
                            <dateline>
                                <placeName>Potsdam</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-22T17:00:00+03:00">July 22,
                                    1945, 5 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: The withdrawal of Soviet troops from
                                the north Soviet zones in Vienna has begun, and should be completed
                                in a few days.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: The British government is pleased to
                                learn of this prompt action.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: So is the American government.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_EA1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Eden</hi></persName>:
                                (reads the report of the Foreign Secretaries).<note n="1" xml:id="d710a-66fn1"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_244">pp. 244</ref>–<ref target="#pg_246">246</ref>.</note></p>
                            <p>The paper of the American delegation on the southeastern European
                                satellite countries<note n="2" xml:id="d710a-66fn2">For the
                                    documents referred to in these notes, see the footnotes to the
                                        <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> minutes,
                                        <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> was presented to the
                                Foreign Secretaries. The British agreed with the paper, but the
                                Soviets were unable to agree with the provisions for the
                                reorganization of the government and the election.</p>
                            <p>The matter of the press and the control exercised by the control
                                commissions were referred to the subcommittee for discussions.</p>
                            <pb facs="0441" n="261" xml:id="pg_261"/>
                            <p>The Soviet delegation agreed to submit a memorandum on the
                                improvement of the control commission in Italy.</p>
                            <p>The Secretaries considered the economic committee’s report on German
                                economic problems. The United States asked postponement of disputed
                                issues for subsequent meeting. Foreign Secretaries agreed to discuss
                                only principles agreed to by the subcommittee. These agreed
                                principles were accepted, except for the wording of paragraph
                                13.</p>
                            <p>The discussions on paragraph 18 and annex to paragraph 16 were also
                                reserved.</p>
                            <p>The Foreign Secretaries also discussed the removal of Allied
                                industrial equipment in Kumania, on the ground that it was booty,
                                but no conclusions were reached.</p>
                            <p>The agenda for the Big Three Meeting was submitted. It included the
                                western frontier of Poland, trusteeships, the straits, the western
                                frontier of the Soviet Union, and Iran. It was suggested that
                                certain problems be referred by the Big Three to the Foreign
                                Secretaries for discussion, to save the time of the Big Three. These
                                problems included cooperation on European economic problems,
                                Tangier, and the problem of Syria and the Lebanon.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: I agree that we should submit these
                                problems to the Foreign Secretaries without further discussion
                                here.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: Syria and Lebanon affect us
                                specially. We want to withdraw from there as soon as possible, but
                                our immediate withdrawal would mean the massacre of the French. I
                                should like to hear more on this here. Possibly we can discuss it
                                here.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: The government of Syria has asked the
                                Soviet [Government] to intervene. We should like some information on
                                this matter. This might be discussed by the Foreign Secretaries. We
                                do not propose the removal of troops from any country.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: I suggest that this matter be deferred
                                until tomorrow and that the other questions go to the Foreign
                                Secretaries.</p>
                            <p>(This was agreed).</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: We now may discuss the western frontier
                                of Poland. I have already stated my views.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_MVM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi></persName>: (First brought up the question of
                                certain Soviet <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss> prisoners held in
                                Italy. He gave notice that he would like to say a few words on this
                                subject at the close of the meeting.)</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Have you seen the statement by the
                                Polish government on the frontiers?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName> and <persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName> both indicated that
                                they had.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: That means all the delegations maintain
                                their existing views, and the question remains in suspense.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: Next subject is trusteeships.</p>
                            <pb facs="0442" n="262" xml:id="pg_262"/>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: We must hope that the Polish
                                question will become ripe for discussion before we leave. It would
                                be unfortunate to have all these problems discussed in
                                Parliament.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Let us accept the Polish proposal.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: I am sorry we cannot. The matter, of
                                course, is for the peace table, but the Polish problem is not
                                advantageous for Poland. It destroys Germany’s economic integrity,
                                and puts an undue burden on the occupying powers. I have grave moral
                                scruples regarding great movements and transfers of populations.
                                Nine million people are involved. True, there is no agreement on the
                                population data. The Soviets say only a few million are left. We
                                should clear up the facts. I could give other reasons, but I won’t
                                burden you now.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: I have undertaken [<hi rend="italic">shall not undertake?</hi>]<note n="3" xml:id="d710a-66fn3">Cf.
                                    the <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> minutes,
                                        <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_248">p.
                                        248</ref>.</note> to oppose Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s views on all these points, but I will
                                deal here only with two. One, Germany will have resources in the
                                Ruhr and the Rhineland, so there is no great difficulty if Silesian
                                coal basin is taken from Germany. Two, the movement of population
                                does not present the difficulties Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> anticipates. There are neither eight nor
                                six nor three million Germans in this area. There have been several
                                call-ups of troops in this area. Few Germans remain. Our data can be
                                checked. Could we not arrange for representatives of the Polish
                                government to come here and be heard?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: I should hesitate to support that,
                                in view of the strong views of the President regarding hearing the
                                Yugoslavs.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Let the Foreign Ministers in London
                                call them and hear them.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: That is satisfactory.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: The Polish government must be heard in
                                answer to the Crimea decision. I continue to urge the meeting to
                                adopt the decision that the Foreign Ministers in London should hear
                                the Polish government on the western frontier.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: How can the frontier be discussed
                                that way? I regret that this grave matter should be adjourned to a
                                lesser body.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: We must not be accused of settling the
                                frontier without hearing the Poles.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: I cannot see the urgency. The question
                                can be settled only by the peace conference.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: There is urgency, Mr. President. The
                                local situation will be unremedied. The Poles who have been assigned
                                this large area will have digged [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]
                                themselves in. This process will continue and it will be more
                                difficult to settle or to revise as time passes. So I still hope
                                that some arrangement will be made here. The situation <pb facs="0443" n="263" xml:id="pg_263"/> will not be improved by
                                hearing the Poles when the great Allies are not agreed on
                                principles.</p>
                            <p>The burden falls on us, the British in particular. Our zone has the
                                smallest supply of food and the greatest density of population.
                                Suppose the Foreign Ministers, having heard the Poles, cannot agree.
                                Then there will be indefinite delay, at least until another meeting
                                of the heads of government. I am anxious to meet practical problems
                                due to the march of events which the Marshal referred to. We should
                                be prepared to consider a compromise solution to cover the period
                                between now and the peace settlement. We would be ready to suggest a
                                provisional line. The Poles west of that line would be working for
                                the Soviet occupying authority. I think Marshal <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> and I agree up to this
                                point, that the new Poland should advance to the Oder. But the
                                difficulty between the Marshal and me is that I do not go quite as
                                far as the Marshal. Is there no use for us to look at anything like
                                this suggested compromise, Mr. President? We should not despair of
                                solutions. We should seek a halfway house. Delay now might make it
                                impossible to alter the consolidated position of the Poles
                                later.</p>
                            <p>Berlin draws its coal from the Silesian mines, which have long been
                                worked by Polish miners. What is to happen to Berlin’s coal during
                                the winter?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Berlin draws her coal from Saxony. Let
                                the Ruhr give her coal. There are different opportunities for
                                supplying Berlin with coal.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: May I re-state my view point. The
                                eastern frontier should follow the <persName corresp="#p_C7">Curzon</persName> line, with slight digression in favor of
                                Poland. The Allies recognize that Poland must receive substantial
                                compensation in the north and west. They believe the new Polish
                                government should be heard, and the final settlement await the peace
                                conference. That was the agreement of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> with the Big Three at
                                Crimea. I am in complete accord with it; but Poland has in fact been
                                assigned a zone of occupation contrary to our agreement. We can
                                agree, if we wish to give the Poles an occupying zone, but I don’t
                                like the way the Poles have taken or been given their zone.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: I also proceed on the decision of the
                                Crimea Conference cited by the President. After the Government of
                                National Unity has been formed, we are bound to seek its opinion.
                                The Polish government have communicated their views. We have two
                                alternatives: one, to approve the Polish proposal; or, two, to hear
                                the Poles and settle the question.</p>
                            <p>I think it expedient to settle the question now. As we are not in
                                agreement with the Polish government, the Poles should be summoned
                                    <pb facs="0444" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/> here. But the view was
                                expressed by the President that the Poles cannot be heard here, so
                                we must remit the question to the Foreign Ministers.</p>
                            <p>At Crimea, the President and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> suggested the line should be along the
                                Oder until it joined the Neisse. I insisted on the western Neisse.
                                Under <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s plan,
                                Stettin and Breslau would remain German. The question to be settled
                                is the frontier, and not a temporary line. We can either settle the
                                question or ignore it.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: Or decide it without the Poles.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: If we disagree with the Poles we cannot
                                decide it without them. It has been said that a fifth country has
                                been brought into occupied Germany, and in a manner contrary to our
                                agreement. If anyone is to blame, circumstances as well as the
                                Russians are to blame.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: I withdraw my objection to the Poles
                                coming here and trying to work out arrangements pending the peace
                                conference.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: I have no objection to the Poles coming
                                here, and for the Foreign Secretaries to hear them.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: The Chairman should invite them.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: The matter of trusteeships is now
                                before us. We will hear the Soviet delegation.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> is our expert.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_MVM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi></persName>: The proposals of the Soviets are
                                submitted in writing. The principal question has been settled by the
                                San Francisco Charter. We have before us specific questions
                                regarding the assignments of territorial trusteeships. It is not
                                possible for us to give detailed answers to these questions, but
                                some progress can be made. First, we can discuss Italian possessions
                                in Africa. We can proceed in one of two ways. We suggest that the
                                matter go to the Foreign Secretaries, or we could consider the
                                questions here tomorrow. There is also the question of the mandated
                                territories.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_EA1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Eden</hi></persName>:
                                Do you want our mandates?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: There are other mandates. The question
                                deserves the attention of the Big Three. One point more, we could
                                exchange views on Korea.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: We can exchange views on any
                                subject, but at the end we have had only an interesting discussion.
                                The existing mandates were dealt with at San Francisco.</p>
                            <p>(<persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName> reads Articles 77 to 79 of the Charter.
                                He points out that mandated territory cannot be [placed under?]
                                trusteeship without the consent of the mandatory power. He assumes
                                that it is the territory detached from the present enemy powers that
                                the Soviets wish to discuss, and indicates that he is willing to
                                have the matter referred to the Foreign Secretaries.)</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: We have agreed to the San Francisco
                                draft, nothing <pb facs="0445" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/> more. As
                                this matter is in the hands of the world organization, I doubt that
                                this is a matter to be discussed around this table.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Teuman</hi>: Article 79 gives you complete
                                protection on your mandated territory.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> said Italy lost her colonies. Who gets
                                them?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: The British alone conquered the
                                Italian armies.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: Alone?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: But Berlin was taken by the Red
                                Army.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: I meant the Italian colonies, Mr.
                                President, were taken by us.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: No one denies. It is to the honor and
                                glory of Britain.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: We do not seek territorial
                                aggrandizement. We have suffered grievous losses, though not so
                                great in human life as has Russia. We come out of the <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss> a great debtor. We have no
                                possibility of regaining naval equality with the United States. Yet,
                                in spite of all these losses, we have made no territorial claims. We
                                have no Koenigsberg, nor Baltic States. We claim nothing. Having
                                acted with rectitude and complete disinterestedness, we approach the
                                question of the Italian colonies with good conscience.</p>
                            <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> made the statement in
                                Parliament that Italy had lost her colonies. That meant she had no
                                claim to them as a matter of right. That does not preclude the
                                return of certain colonies to her, if the peace conference so
                                decides. I do not say I favor the return of the colonies, but so far
                                as we are concerned, it is a question open for discussion. I have
                                seen the excellent reclamation work done by the Italians in Libya
                                and Cyrenaica. At present we hold these colonies. Who wants
                                them?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: We do not want them. We do not want a
                                trusteeship for them. We have enough “poor Italians” to feed in the
                                United States [<hi rend="italic">in Italy?</hi>].<note n="4" xml:id="d710a-66fn4">Cf. the <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> minutes, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>,
                                        <ref target="#pg_254">p. 254</ref>.</note></p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: We considered them for Jewish
                                settlement, but the Jews are not attracted to them. Of course, we
                                have great interest in the Mediterranean.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Our proposals are submitted in writing,
                                and we would like the conference to consider them.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: Does the Marshal wish to put forward
                                a claim to these colonies, or to a trusteeship for them?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Do we consider it necessary for Italy
                                to lose these colonies? If so, to what states do we propose to
                                entrust the trusteeships? If it is premature to deal with this
                                question, we can wait, but we will have to deal with it sooner or
                                later.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: I am frank to say I have not
                                considered the possibility of Russia claiming territory in the
                                Mediterranean.</p>
                            <pb facs="0446" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: The Soviet delegation stated at San
                                Francisco that we were anxious to receive mandates for certain
                                territories.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: I have a copy of the statement that Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> gave Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SERJ1">Stettinius</persName>.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: We have the right to take the
                                colonies from Italy, but to whom shall we give them? That belongs to
                                the discussion of the peace treaty. The administration of
                                trusteeships is for the world organization.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Is it your position that the present
                                conference is qualified to settle the question?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: Of course, if we three agree, it
                                facilitates settlement.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Of course the conference is qualified
                                to consider.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: I make no objection. I am prepared
                                to hear the Marshal’s views.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: The question has been submitted in
                                writing.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: Let the Foreign Secretaries consider
                                it.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: I have no objection, but we are
                                over-burdening the Foreign Secretaries. There are more urgent
                                problems. We are agreed that the Italian treaty should have priority
                                when the council of Foreign Ministers meets in September.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Let us submit the question to the
                                Ministers.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: Yes, if they have time after
                                considering more urgent questions.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: There should be no reservation.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: Let us turn to the British paper
                                regarding Turkey.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: This comes up because of the need to
                                modify the Montreux Conference [<hi rend="italic">Convention</hi>].
                                At Yalta, I told the Marshal we would favor the revision of the
                                Convention, but that can be done only with the consent of the
                                signatories, except Japan, with whom we are at <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss>. I have also expressed our
                                readiness to welcome the free movement of Russian ships, whether
                                    <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss> or merchant ships, in or out
                                of the Black Sea in time of peace or <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss>. So we start on a friendly basis.</p>
                            <p>Still, I wish to impress on the Marshal the importance of not
                                alarming Turkey. Undoubtedly Turkey is much alarmed, because of the
                                concentration of Russian and Bulgarian troops on her borders, by the
                                attacks on her by the Russian radio, and the course of the
                                conversation between the Turkish Ambassador and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>, at which a modification of
                                the Turkish eastern frontiers was mentioned. Also, a base in the
                                Straits. This led Turkey to fear for the integrity of her empire,
                                and the power to defend Constantinople. I understand that these were
                                not demands made on the Turkish government, but were stated as
                                conditions of alliance proposed by the Turks. I can see that in the
                                consideration of such alliance, the Russians <pb facs="0447" n="267" xml:id="pg_267"/> would state what improvements they desired in
                                the Turkish situation. But the Turks were under alarm. What I should
                                like to know is, what is the present Russian position on this
                                subject?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_MVM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi></persName>: I have now circulated the views of the
                                Soviet government as set forth in writing.</p>
                            <p>I should like to explain the origin of the question. This was brought
                                up by the Turkish government with our Ambassador, and later by the
                                Turkish Ambassador with me. Early in June I had two conversations
                                with the Turkish Ambassador. In reply to the Turkish proposal for an
                                alliance, I stated Russia had no objection, subject to certain
                                conditions. We should first settle mutual claims. I mentioned two
                                questions on our side. The treaty of alliance means we jointly
                                undertake to defend the frontiers of two states. I pointed out that
                                we could not undertake to defend certain sections of the frontier
                                which we considered unjust. In 1921 part of this territory was torn
                                from the Soviet Union—part of Armenia and part of Soviet Georgia. I
                                pointed out that these territories should be restored. We should
                                also have an alteration of our rights in the Straits. And a
                                base.</p>
                            <p>On behalf of the Soviets, I have put forward our claims in the paper
                                circulated. I pointed out to the Turks that if they were prepared to
                                settle the two questions, we were prepared to make an alliance and
                                settle any questions they wished to have settled. If the Turkish
                                government was not prepared, the Soviets were prepared to make an
                                agreement regarding the Straits only.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: May we have a moment to read your
                                statement?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_MVM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi></persName>: Yes.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: This is a very important document.
                                It goes far beyond any of our discussions. I presume “regular
                                procedure” in paragraph one means consultation with all signatories
                                but Japan. Quite a different question is raised when Russia asks for
                                a military base and asks that no powers be permitted to participate
                                in control of the Straits but Russia and Turkey. I am quite certain
                                Turkey will never agree to this.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Similar treaties existed between Turkey
                                and Russia at other times.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: What times do you refer to?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: In 1805 and 1833.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: These suggestions are wholly
                                different from our previous talks. I stand by my talk with the
                                Marshal when I promised to support revision of the Montreux
                                Convention, but I feel quite free as to these new proposals.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: You are quite free.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: I thank you.</p>
                            <pb facs="0448" n="268" xml:id="pg_268"/>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_MVM1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Molotov</hi></persName>: May we submit our proposals on
                                Koenigsberg to the President and the Prime Minister?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: Certainly, and the invitation to the
                                Poles to appear before the Foreign Secretaries has gone out.</p>
                            <p>Should we discuss the communiqué before it leaks out?</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: Yes.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_CWS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Churchill</hi></persName>: It is breaking the principle we have
                                followed.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_SGIV1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Stalin</hi></persName>: It is agreeable to me one way or the
                                other.</p>
                            <p><persName corresp="#p_THS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Truman</hi></persName>: We will drop it.</p>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>