<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Thompson Minutes</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d710a-49</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">710a-49</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-09-21T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-09-21T04:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="economic-affairs" lcsh-match="no_match">Economic questions</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="debt" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130" lcsh-match="exact">Debts</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" subject="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recqhvaPBazS2SPQl" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" subject="freedom-of-the-press" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051711" lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of the press</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="diplomatic-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="oil" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec1c8936cc6bb154a" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="yalta-agreement">Yalta Agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-09-21T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-09-21T04:00:00-05:00" n="[Unnumbered document following Document 710 (#49)]" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d710a-49">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_TSH1">Truman</persName> Papers</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_TLEJ1">Thompson</persName> Minutes</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Potsdam</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian" when="1945-09-21T12:00:00+03:00">July 21, 1945, noon</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>The meeting of Foreign Ministers began at 12 noon on Saturday, July 21, 1945.
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName> was in the Chair.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Date of Meeting for the Council of Foreign Ministers</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that the first item of business was the fixing of the date of the
                    meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers. He proposed not later than
                    September 1.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> inquired what day of the week this would be.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> replied that it was Sunday.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said he agreed.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that the Council of Foreign Ministers would meet at a date not
                    later than September 1.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> inquired in what composition would the Council of Foreign Ministers
                    meet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> replied that they had agreed first of all to meet in London and that they
                    would have a formal meeting there to set up the Council.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> inquired if this meant five members. He pointed out that the composition
                    of the Council would determine the type of questions to be discussed.</p>
                <pb facs="0367" n="187" xml:id="pg_187"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> replied that it would be five, because there was the question of
                    organizing the Council and deciding the procedure to be followed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that he did not wish to be grasping. It had been decided that
                    the Secretariat would be in London but the Council might wish to meet elsewhere.
                    He thought this might be said.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> thought they might rotate the meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> proposed that they approve the addition of language to state that the
                    Council should normally meet at London, which would be the seat of its
                    Secretariat, but that it might meet elsewhere by common agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said it was decided that they would communicate with France and China
                    before final announcement was made of the creation of the Council. He proposed
                    that they each appoint a representative to draft a telegram. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> named Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> named Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> named Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WJG1">Ward</persName>, for the purpose of
                    drafting a telegram.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Report of Subcommittee on German Economic Questions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that the Subcommittee on German Economic Questions had
                    presented its report.<note n="1" xml:id="d710a-49fn1">See <ref target="#d863">documents Nos. 863</ref> and <ref target="#d902">902</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that the Subcommittee had finished its work late at night and he had
                    had no time to get acquainted with its report. If possible, he would prefer that
                    this question be taken up as item 1 on the agenda of the Foreign Ministers’
                    meeting the next day.</p>
                <p>This was agreed to.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> inquired if they would have any agenda for the present meeting today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that they would first consider the questions submitted to them by the
                    Big Three. Then they would take up the reports of the subcommittees which they,
                    the Foreign Ministers, had appointed. Finally, they could consider the agenda
                    for the Big Three meeting.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Polish Question</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that papers on this subject had been submitted by the British and
                    Soviet delegations. These had been considered by a subcommittee, and he would
                    now call on the chairman of the subcommittee for his report.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_V7">Vyshinski</persName>
                    </hi> said that the subcommittee set up to deal with the Polish question had not
                    reached full agreement on their report.<note n="1a" xml:id="d710a-49fn1a">
                        <ref target="#d1129">Document No. 1129</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note> They had had three papers before them: (1) a British
                    paper of July 19, (2) <pb facs="0368" n="188" xml:id="pg_188"/> an amended text
                    of the British draft of July 19 which the British had submitted, (3) a Soviet
                    amended draft of the same British text.<note n="2" xml:id="d710a-49fn2">For the
                        British draft of July 19, see <ref target="#d1121">document No. 1121</ref>,
                            <hi rend="italic">post</hi>. The British redraft referred to has not
                        been found as a separate paper but can be largely reconstructed from <ref target="#d1129">document No. 1129</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.
                        For the “Soviet amended draft” referred to, see <ref target="#d1421">document No. 1421</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note> They were
                    guided in their discussions by the second draft submitted by the British. In
                    drafting the final text on this question there were five matters upon which no
                    agreement was reached. These were: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The first disagreement related to the question of the transfer of the
                            assets of the London Polish Government to the new Provisional
                            Government. The last sentence of paragraph 2 of the British draft was
                            not acceptable to the Soviet delegation, which thought that no
                            discussion of the question of liabilities of the Polish Government
                            should be included in the declaration. The Soviet delegation thought
                            that this was a matter of Polish-American and Polish-British relations.
                            The amount and character of the assets and debts was not known to the
                            Soviet delegation, and they thought that this question should be dealt
                            with separately.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The second difference related to the last sentence of paragraph 4 of
                            the British draft, which related to assurances for the return of Poles
                            to Poland. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_V7">Vyshinski</persName> pointed
                            out that there were three thoughts embodied in this sentence. The Soviet
                            delegation welcomed the last thought, namely, that the Poles who
                            returned to Poland should have equal rights with other Poles. With
                            respect to the other two thoughts, namely, the question of assurances to
                            Poles and the thought that as many Poles as possible should come home,
                            the Soviet delegation considered that it was not proper to include the
                            mention of these assurances, and they thought that it was already clear
                            that it was desired that as many Poles as possible return to Poland. The
                            Soviet delegation had therefore suggested a shorter sentence, to the
                            effect that the three Governments expect that those Poles that return
                            home will be accorded equal rights with all Polish citizens. The British
                            delegation did not agree with this proposal because of the word
                            “expect”. The British delegation thought that the Polish Government
                            should give assurances.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>This disagreement related to the proposal of the Soviet delegation
                            that the declaration include a statement to the effect that the British
                            Government would undertake not to arrest Poles who wanted to return
                            home.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>This related to the sentence to the effect that the three powers took
                            note that the Polish Government had undertaken to hold free and
                            unfettered elections, etc. The Soviet delegation agreed to this except
                            for the word “pledge”, which they objected to because the Crimea
                            decision had said “should pledge” and not “pledge”.<note n="3" xml:id="d710a-49fn3">The English text of the decision referred to
                                read: “This Polish Provisional Government of National Unity shall be
                                pledged to the holding of free and unfettered elections as soon as
                                possible on the basis of universal suffrage and secret ballot.” See
                                    <ref target="#d1417">document No. 1417</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, section <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>.</note> When
                            the new Polish Government was formed it had given this pledge. A
                            proposal had been made to state “It is the confident hope of the Three
                            Powers that the elections will be conducted in such a way as to make <pb facs="0369" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> it clear to the world that all
                            democratic and anti-Nazi sections of Polish opinion have been able to
                            express their views freely, and thus to play their full part in the
                            restoration of the country’s political life.” Mr. <persName corresp="#p_V7">Vyshinski</persName> said that if this meant that
                            all sections of public opinion in Poland, including Nazis, had been able
                            to express their views freely, it was not acceptable. If it meant
                            otherwise, the Soviet delegation proposed to avoid repetition by merely
                            adding to the first part of this paragraph a reference to democratic
                            parties fully participating in the country’s political life.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>This difference referred to the freedom of the press to report to the
                            world upon developments in Poland before and during the elections. This
                            wording was unlimited and meant that unrestricted freedom of the press
                            was proclaimed. Hostilities had just finished, and the Soviet delegation
                            thought that this would be difficult. They were of the opinion that the
                            press should have greater freedom now because conditions had changed,
                            but this was a Polish internal question and it was impossible to decide
                            it without the Poles.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">These five differences the Subcommittee had referred back to the
                    Foreign Ministers. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_V7">Vyshinski</persName> added that
                    he should mention that there had been other serious differences which had been
                    settled and, with the exception of the five points he had mentioned, the draft
                    had been unanimously agreed upon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> proposed that they discuss these points in order.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(1) <hi rend="italic">Liabilities and Assets of the Polish
                        Government</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that the chairman of the Subcommittee had suggested that the
                    liabilities of the Polish Provisional Government should not be mentioned,
                    because that was a question to be handled between the Polish and American and
                    the Polish and British Governments. He felt, however, that the same thing was
                    true of the question of Polish assets. The United States had recognized the
                    Provisional Polish Government. It had promptly taken steps to protect those
                    assets. He saw no reason to believe that the United States would not transfer
                    them to the government which it has recognized. He was sure that the Polish
                    Provisional Government had no doubt about the United States transferring to it
                    property which belonged to it. The United States was unwilling to make any
                    statement with respect to Polish assets without stating at the same time that we
                    would discuss the question of liabilities through diplomatic channels.
                    Otherwise, a statement with respect to Polish assets might deceive people in
                    Poland and elsewhere, because transfers of this kind must be made subject to any
                    liens under the laws of the United States. Secondly, he did not know what debts
                    might be due to the United States by the Provisional Government of Poland. The
                    Polish Government need have no doubt but that our attitude would be sympathetic,
                    because our attitude toward Poland had always been sympathetic. He disliked to
                    mention in a public statement that we would transfer property to the Polish
                    Government that belonged to them now that we had recognized that <pb facs="0370" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/> Government. That followed as a matter of course.
                    Since, however, his colleagues wanted a statement on this subject, the American
                    representative on the Subcommittee had proposed the following language: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The British and United States Governments have taken measures to protect
                            the interest of the Polish Provisional Government as the recognized
                            government of the Polish State in the property belonging to the Polish
                            State located on their territory and under their control, whatever the
                            form of this property may be. They have further taken measures to
                            prevent alienation to third parties of such property. All proper
                            facilities will be given to the Polish Provisional Government for the
                            exercise of the ordinary legal remedies for the recovery of any property
                            of the Polish State which may have been wrongfully alienated.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName> said that he
                    had already stated to the Conference<note n="4" xml:id="d710a-49fn4">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_104">p. 104</ref>.</note> that
                    on the day before the United States had recognized the Polish Provisional
                    Government, the United States Government had learned of a proposal to transfer
                    the Polish Embassy to a third party. The United States Government had intervened
                    and had been prepared to institute proceedings to recover the property had that
                    been necessary. The Polish Government knows this and needs no assurance that it
                    will be treated fairly under the law.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said he found it difficult to discuss this question without the
                    participation of the Polish Government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that this was also his position—namely, that the matter could only be
                    discussed with the Poles. He did not know what the debts were, but he would not
                    wish to tell the Poles that we would transfer assets and then find that there
                    were liabilities against these assets. In such a case we would be charged with
                    bad faith. He therefore proposed that they mention neither the transfer of
                    assets nor the payment of liabilities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> said that they also did not know the extent of the liabilities and debts.
                    They might be sure, however, that the British would not drive a hard bargain. He
                    added, however, that if you deal with the assets you must deal with debts. The
                    British also did not know the amount of the Polish assets. He could assure his
                    Soviet Allies, however, that the British would act in accordance with the
                    obligation they had undertaken by recognizing the Polish Provisional Government.
                    He thought it was best to drop this paragraph altogether.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that he did not agree that if they mentioned assets they must mention
                    liabilities. He drew the attention of his colleagues to the manner in which the
                    Polish question was being <pb facs="0371" n="191" xml:id="pg_191"/> discussed
                    here and the manner in which it had been discussed at the Crimea. Here the
                    question was a one-sided one. At the Crimea the question was whether or not the
                    British and American Governments would recognize the Polish Provisional
                    Government and not whether the Polish Government would recognize the British and
                    American Governments. He hoped that all these questions of liabilities would be
                    discussed by the parties. There was no need to say anything about it here. He
                    pointed out that the question which had been discussed at the Crimea was only
                    that of the transfer of property which was held by the London Polish
                    Government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said he recalled that Marshal <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> had raised the question of the transfer of property and
                    that President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> had said that of
                    course the property of the London Government would be transferred when the new
                    Polish Government was recognized.<note n="5" xml:id="d710a-49fn5">See <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_776">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conferences at Malta and
                            Yalta, 1945, p. 776</ref>.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName> said he could say the same thing of the Soviet
                    Government. When the Soviet Government recognized the Polish Government, he
                    assumed that it transferred the property of the Polish Government. He assumed
                    also that in making such transfer the Soviets were obliged to take account of
                    Soviet laws and of any liabilities against this property. He would not ask for a
                    declaration that the Soviet Government would comply with its own laws. He knew
                    that it would.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that all other questions could be decided by bi-lateral
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that so far as the United States is concerned they would be decided
                    at the earliest possible date. He did not think that any statement should be
                    made that pressure had to be brought on the United States Government to transfer
                    to the Polish Government property that belonged to that Government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that they had frozen Polish funds.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> suggested that the matter be referred to the Big Three.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> suggested that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> study
                    the American draft that had been presented during the meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said he had offered this substitute draft but he would not be frank if he
                    did not make clear that he would tell the President that, in his opinion, the
                    President should not be a party to a statement in the press that the United
                    States Government would give to Poland property which is rightfully the property
                    of the Polish Government, which it has recognized, without coupling such
                    statement by [<hi rend="italic">with?</hi>] a statement that the Polish
                    Government had never questioned that the United States would transfer to the
                    Polish Government the property that belongs to it.</p>
                <pb facs="0372" n="192" xml:id="pg_192"/>
                <p>Since Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> did not have the Russian
                    text of the new language which had been proposed, the matter was passed over, in
                    order that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> would have time to
                    consider it.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(2) <hi rend="italic">Return of Poles to Poland</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that there were two versions of this proposal: one submitted
                    by the Soviet delegation and one submitted by the British delegation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said he thought the general idea of both versions was essential and that
                    this general idea should be retained. All the rest was unnecessary and might be
                    offensive to the Poles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> remarked that he did not see what there was that would be offensive to the
                    Poles. Their object was to get Poles home. He was prepared to agree, however, to
                    some change in the drafting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said he did not see why this matter was insisted upon. The Soviet version
                    made clear that the Poles would not be persecuted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> said that if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> thought
                    the language was offensive, they would accept the Soviet version subject to a
                    minor drafting suggestion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that there was a change suggested by the Soviet
                    representative, in the last paragraph on page 2—namely, to substitute for the
                    words “is pledged” the words “in conformity with the Crimea decision has
                        agreed”.<note n="6" xml:id="d710a-49fn6">Cf. paragraph 4 of <ref target="#d1121">document No. 1121</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>,
                        and the fourth paragraph of <ref target="#d1131">document No. 1131</ref>,
                            <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>This was agreed to.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(3) <hi rend="italic">Arrest of Poles by British</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that the next question was the proposed undertaking that the British
                    Government would take steps on British territory and territory under British
                    control not to arrest Poles who wished to return home.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> said he could not accept in a declaration designed to assure the return of
                    Poles to Poland that they would undertake not to do the opposite. He pointed out
                    that the London Polish Government did not now have any power. Power had been
                    transferred to the new Polish Government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that there would probably be no more such acts and that they could
                    drop the paragraph.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that certain governments had been given rights on British
                    territory. The London Polish Government did not now have these rights.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that there had been some recent incidents.</p>
                <pb facs="0373" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> replied that there had been none since recognition of the new Polish
                    Government.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(4) <hi rend="italic">Polish Elections</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that the proposed sentence on the free expression of views in
                    the election had not been agreed to.<note n="7" xml:id="d710a-49fn7">See
                        paragraph 4 of <ref target="#d1121">document No. 1121</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that this sentence would be unpleasant for the Polish Government,
                    that all the thoughts had been expressed in the previous sentence. This sentence
                    would give the impression of mistrust.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> offered to leave out the first part of this sentence if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> would agree to include the last
                    sentence of the draft relating to freedom of the press.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_V7">Vyshinski</persName>
                    </hi> drew Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>’s attention to the
                    fact that in the Subcommittee the British representatives had made just the
                    opposite proposal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> said that he had not known this.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that at the meeting yesterday Marshal <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> [<persName corresp="#p_MVM1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Molotov</hi>
                    </persName>] expressed agreement in principle with the thought that the press
                    should be allowed to report freely on what went on in these countries.<note n="8" xml:id="d710a-49fn8">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_151">pp. 151</ref>–<ref target="#pg_153">153</ref>.</note>
                    Hostilities had ceased and the situation was changed. It would be of great
                    importance in the future relations of the Polish Provisional Government that
                    there be no question in regard to the freedom of the press.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> inquired if there were any complaints that the Allied press could not work
                    in Poland now.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> said it was one thing to let the press in but that it was another as to
                    whether they could say what they wished.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> inquired whether the correspondents who had visited Poland had
                    complained.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that his information was that for a long while no press
                    representatives had been permitted to visit in Poland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that there had been no government of national unity at that
                    time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> continued that a group of correspondents did visit Poland and that they
                    were not restricted. We did not, however, have any regularly appointed press
                    representatives in Poland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> inquired if there were any applications pending for American
                    correspondents to go to Poland.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said we did not know how these correspondents would be treated if they
                    went to Poland and we only wished to express the hope that they would have
                    freedom.</p>
                <pb facs="0374" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that this would make a bad impression.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> then proposed that the question be submitted to the Big Three along with
                    the other difficulties that had arisen.</p>
                <p>This was agreed to.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Yalta Declaration on Liberated Europe</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that they had not had time to have the document on this question<note n="9" xml:id="d710a-49fn9">
                        <ref target="#d748">Document No. 748</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note> translated into Russian.</p>
                <p>At his request it was agreed to pass over this question until he could study the
                    document.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Italian Declaration</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> observed that two papers had been submitted on this matter—one on Italy
                    and one on the other satellites.<note n="10" xml:id="d710a-49fn10">
                        <ref target="#d1092">Documents Nos. 1092</ref> and <ref target="#d805">805</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, respectively.</note> Marshal
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName> had suggested at the meeting
                    yesterday that they simultaneously settle these two questions,<note n="11" xml:id="d710a-49fn11">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_169">pp. 169</ref>, <ref target="#pg_175">175</ref>.</note> and it was Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s proposal that they consider
                    merging the two drafts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that at the meeting yesterday it had been recognized that
                    there was a difference between the situation of Italy and that of the other
                    satellites. Italy had signed more severe armistice terms<note n="12" xml:id="d710a-49fn12">See Treaties and Other International Acts Series No.
                        1604; 61 <gloss target="#t_Stat1">Stat</gloss>. (3) 2740.</note> than had
                    the other countries. He preferred two separate declarations rather than one.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> suggested that they could be merged in the drafting committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> suggested that the reason for separate texts was that the United States
                    had not recognized the Rumanian and Bulgarian Governments. Also, the United
                    States was not at <gloss target="#t_War1">war</gloss> with Finland. If it was
                    merely a question of drafting, he urged Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> to let them take up the matter in two separate
                    papers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> said that he was proceeding from the suggestion made yesterday by Marshal
                        <persName corresp="#p_SGIV1">Stalin</persName>. Both of these papers dealt
                    with armistice terms signed by these countries. He was fully aware of and
                    understood the difference between them. The subject of both documents was the
                    same. He could not give a final opinion as he had only had time to read them
                    once. The drafts contained good working material.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that the question was whether there should be one draft or two, and
                    he proposed to refer the matter to the Big Three.</p>
                <p>This was agreed to.</p>
                <pb facs="0375" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Agenda for the Big Three Meeting</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    </hi> observed that the Soviet delegation stuck to its suggestion for the
                    resumption of diplomatic relations with Rumania, Bulgaria, Finland, and
                    Hungary.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    </hi> said that he was circulating a paper on Persia,<note n="13" xml:id="d710a-49fn13">
                        <ref target="#d1330">Document No. 1330</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note> but he did not ask that it be taken up today.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">Byrnes</persName>
                    </hi> said that he wished to submit a paper which he thought should go to the
                    economic subcommittee. This paper dealt with the necessity of making available
                    increased supplies of oil from Rumania and the use of about 200 tankers to
                    transport this oil.<note n="14" xml:id="d710a-49fn14">
                        <ref target="#d1320">Document No. 1320</ref>, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It was agreed to refer this question to the economic subcommittee.</p>
                <p>The agenda of the Big Three meeting was drawn up as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The Polish question—Implementation of the Yalta Agreement and transfer
                            of the Property of the London Polish Government.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Declaration on Italy and Satellite States.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The Western Frontiers of Poland.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Trusteeships.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Turkey.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The meeting adjourned.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
