<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>No. 851
                    Memorandum by Major Harold
                            Zink, of the Political Division, United States Group, Control
                        Council, Germany
                    Printed from the final text as transmitted to the
                        Secretary of State by Murphy as an
                        enclosure to despatch No. 699, dated July 26. This text has only minor
                        variations from a draft forwarded by Murphy on July 17 to James W.
                            Riddleberger, Chief of the Division of Central European
                        Affairs, then at Babelsberg, for use in connection with the discussions
                        taking place at the Berlin Conference, except that the draft given to
                            Riddleberger (file No.
                        862.00/7–1745) did not contain paragraphs 21 and 22,</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945Berlinv02</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d851</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">851</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-07-16T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-07-26T15:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-26T15:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-16T16:00:00-05:00" n="851" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d851">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/7–2645</note>
                <head>No. 851<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by <persName corresp="#p_ZMH1">Major Harold
                            Zink</persName>, of the Political Division, United States Group, Control
                        Council, Germany</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d851fn1">Printed from the final text as transmitted to the
                        Secretary of State by <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> as an
                        enclosure to despatch No. 699, dated July 26. This text has only minor
                        variations from a draft forwarded by <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> on July 17 to <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">James W.
                            Riddleberger</persName>, Chief of the Division of Central European
                        Affairs, then at Babelsberg, for use in connection with the discussions
                        taking place at the Berlin Conference, except that the draft given to
                            <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName> (file No.
                        862.00/7–1745) did not contain paragraphs 21 and 22,</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1945-07-26T23:59:59+03:00" notBefore="1945-07-17T00:00:00+03:00">Undated</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">German Governmental Structure</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">section i. general policy</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>It is highly desirable that the process of reestablishing a German
                        governmental structure be undertaken with great care and after adequate
                        planning. The experience of American Military Government in Germany
                        following 1918 as officially set forth in the <persName corresp="#p_HCIL1">Hunt</persName> Report<note n="2" xml:id="d851fn2">
                            <hi rend="italic">American Military Government of Occupied Germany,
                                1918–1920: Report of the Officer in Charge of Civil Affairs, Third
                                Army and American Forces in Germany</hi> (Washington, Government
                            Printing Office, 1943).</note> clearly indicates the great peril of
                        proceeding on the basis of expediency and inadequate knowledge. <persName corresp="#p_HCIL1">Colonel Hunt</persName> concluded that the lack of a
                        policy founded on a thorough analysis of the complicated factors involved
                        resulted in many weaknesses which seriously and permanently vitiated the
                        effectiveness of American Military <pb facs="0961" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/>
                        Government in Germany and led to the playing of American, British, and
                        French occupation forces against each other by the Germans.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>During tactical operations military expediency must necessarily receive
                        high priority in military government; during the post-hostility period long
                        range objectives should determine action except in special emergencies. In
                        setting up a German governmental structure it would be short-sighted to
                        follow the line of least resistance or to be guided by such considerations
                        as a slight economy of military government personnel or the convenience of
                        dealing with a minimum number of German officials. The main objective is to
                        prevent a recurrence of such international menaces as German militarism and
                        National Socialism. The setting up of an adequate German governmental
                        structure has an important bearing on the above objective.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Steps taken to set up a German governmental system should be directed to
                        the maximum extent toward the establishment of a structure which will be
                        democratic in character and lasting in effect. Unless Military Government
                        can create a German governmental system which embodies democratic principles
                        and is so well founded that it will be retained by the Germans after the
                        occupation has ended it will have failed in its fundamental mission.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Though the setting up of a satisfactory German governmental structure
                        requires the elimination of Nazi agencies and ideology, it is not necessary
                        to ignore the system which has developed in Germany over several centuries.
                        The scrapping of all established machinery and units would in all
                        probability lead to a chaos which would not only enormously complicate the
                        problems of military government but defeat its primary objective. Insofar as
                        possible and unless there are compelling reasons otherwise the general
                        governmental system based on the <hi rend="italic">Gemeinde–Kreis–Regierungsbezirk–Land/Provinz</hi> and the existing
                        boundaries of the various units should be retained. In any country it is
                        dangerous to ignore the experience of the past; in Germany where even the
                        Nazis found it impossible to eradicate traditional governmental units such
                        as the <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi>, blind disregard of established
                        governmental units would lead to endless difficulties and serve no useful
                        purpose.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In those instances in which a change in boundaries of German governmental
                        units is contemplated, careful regard must be given to the cultural,
                        language, religious, geographical, economic, transportation, and related
                        factors involved. Disregard of these factors would lead to the setting up of
                        artificial units with little chance of permanent success. The subsequent
                        failure of such units might cause serious problems in the future, thus
                        jeopardizing the primary objective of Military Government.</item>
                    <pb facs="0962" n="768" xml:id="pg_768"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Many of the objectionable features of German government in the past have
                        been largely due to extreme centralization. The Nazis carried an already
                        highly centralized governmental system to a point where they controlled
                        virtually every aspect of human activity. The <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1067 series<note n="3" xml:id="d851fn3">“The <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1067 series” refers to a draft
                            directive to the Commander in Chief, United States Forces of Occupation
                            in Germany, regarding the military government of Germany circulated to
                            the Joint Chiefs of Staff as <gloss target="#t_JCS1">J. C. S.</gloss>
                            1067 (text in <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_143">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conferences at Malta
                                and Yalta, 1945, p. 143</ref>), and to subsequent drafts and papers
                            on this subject produced during the development of the directive as
                            finally issued in May 1945 (see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, p. 596).</note>
                        directs that the German governmental system be decentralized and that local
                        responsibility be developed. “Autonomy in regional, local and municipal
                        agencies of German administrative” [<hi rend="italic">administration</hi>]
                        is to be encouraged. The primary objective of Military Government depends in
                        no small measure on the carrying of this mandate into effect. The promotion
                        of democratic principles requires the restoration and even the strengthening
                        of the old self-government authority of the <hi rend="italic">Landkreise,
                            Stadtkreise</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Gemeinde</hi>. Vitality must be
                        reinfused into the <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi>. At the same time
                        decentralization must not be interpreted so literally that it renders
                        impossible reasonably effective provisions for public health, public safety,
                        public welfare, housing, collection of statistics, etc.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Though there are fundamental differences distinguishing the Germans of
                        Bavaria, Baden and Württemberg, for example, from their fellow-countrymen in
                        Westphalia, Hanover, Oldenburg, and Hamburg the overriding factors make for
                        a single German state rather than for separatism. Small groups on the
                        Czechoslovak, French, Dutch, and other borders favor separation from Germany
                        and union with the nearby countries. Other small groups desire to restore
                        dynasties to ruling authority. Certain individuals have placed themselves on
                        record as supporting the setting up of an independent Bavaria, Rhine
                        Republic, Saar State, etc. However, there is slight evidence at present of
                        any widespread support among the German population for the dividing up of
                        the <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> into a number of
                        independent countries. Nor is there any very compelling argument for
                        separatism from the long range Military Government viewpoint, though a case
                        can be made on the basis of possible expediency. In general, it does not
                        appear to be realistic to expect a separatist movement of large proportions
                        among the Germans. A separatism imposed by Military Government would bring
                        in its wake the lack of popular support, the probable impermanence, and the
                        many other difficulties usually attendant upon such artificial
                        creations.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>With decentralization mandatory and separatism unlikely to have wide
                        support, a federal type of German governmental structure seems to offer the
                        greatest promise of achieving the primary Military <pb facs="0963" n="769" xml:id="pg_769"/> Government objective. Under such a system functions
                        such as food supply, railroad administration, <gloss target="#t_PTT1">PTT</gloss>, issuance of currency and eventually the conduct of foreign
                        relations would be handled by a <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> government while the major part of governmental
                        authority would be exercised at the <hi rend="italic">Land/Provinz</hi>
                        level. The <hi rend="italic">Länder/Provinzen</hi> would in turn provide a
                        maximum of autonomy at the <hi rend="italic">Kreis-Gemeinde</hi> levels in
                        accordance with <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1067.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>In any federal system likely to prove effective certain basic
                        modifications in the <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi> must be undertaken. While
                        it is not essential or indeed desirable that all <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi> be uniform in area and population, it is of the highest
                        importance that Prussia be broken up into a number of smaller units. A
                        single <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> (Prussia) which contains more than half
                        of the area (321,787 sq. km.) and population (45,328, 118 in 1939) of the
                        entire German <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> cannot be fitted
                        into any vital federal system of government. On the other hand but
                        distinctly less important is the problem presented by very small <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi>, such as Schaumburg–Lippe with 53, 159
                        inhabitants in 1939, Lippe with a population of 187,220, and Anhalt with
                        431,422 people, which are too tiny to exercise in any very satisfactory
                        manner the functions of really effective <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi>.
                        Though <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1067 directs decentralization and
                        it is undesirable otherwise to engage in any considerable general fusion of
                            <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi>, there are strong arguments for
                        considering the possibility of eliminating the separate identity of <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi> with fewer than one million
                        inhabitants.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">section ii. governmental levels</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Reich</hi>
                        </persName>. Under the Nazi Regime virtually all governmental functions were
                        centralized at the <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> level. The
                        early military government planning was based on the assumption that the
                        machinery at this level would be in operation at least to some extent when
                        the Allies took over. Consequently plans were drawn for the continued
                        operation of agencies other than those to be scrapped as Nazi creations. The
                        fact that no central government agencies were functioning when Germany
                        capitulated makes it necessary to reconstitute those ministries which it is
                        desired to reestablish. While it is desirable to set up a fragmentary
                            <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> government at an early
                        date because of the pressing problems of food, coal, transportation, and
                        possibly a few other items, there seems no good reason to proceed
                        immediately to the establishment of an elaborate general system of <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> government. Executive and
                        legislative branches clearly must be delayed until the early period of
                        Military Government has passed. The setting up of administrative departments
                        should depend upon the needs as revealed by developments. The principle of
                        establishing ministries only after it has been decided that there are
                        necessary <pb facs="0964" n="770" xml:id="pg_770"/> functions to be
                        performed in the immediate future might well be followed. In setting up
                        ministries the same principle of functional necessity might wisely be
                        followed in the case of subdivisions. Any other course would not only
                        provide unnecessary machinery but complicate and even jeopardize the process
                        of substituting a federal system of government for the old highly
                        centralized machinery.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi>. Under a federal system substantial authority
                        will be vested in the <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi>, though this should not
                        go so far as to transfer to the <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi> the entire
                        body of power formerly exercised by the <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName>. Under the Nazis the <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi>
                        [became primarily administrative units of the <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> and their former machinery of government<note n="4" xml:id="d851fn4">The passage in brackets has been supplied from the
                            draft forwarded to Biddleberger by <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>.</note>] was deprived of any considerable
                        responsibility. It is of first-rate importance that the <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi> be restored to a position of vitality and influence. On the
                        other hand it is not desirable to give too far reaching authority to them,
                        since such a system, though easier to supervise and of great appeal to those
                        who are primarily impressed by immediate effectiveness, would prevent the
                        autonomy specified in <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1067 and make
                        impossible the local responsibility so necessary for educating the German
                        people in democratic techniques.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Provinzen</hi>. With Prussia broken up both because of the
                        zone lines and the necessity of ending its predominance, some provision must
                        be made for the <hi rend="italic">Provinzen</hi>. Most of them can be
                        transformed into <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi> with little difficulty.
                        Others can be joined together into <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi>.
                        Hessen–Nassau, the only Prussian area involved in the American Zone[,] has
                        already been given the status of a <hi rend="italic">Land.</hi>
                    </item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Regierungsbezirke</hi>. There has been some desire to
                        abolish these units of government which have recently functioned only in
                        Prussia and Bavaria. However, the experience of Military Government in
                        Bavaria as well as in certain <hi rend="italic">Provinzen</hi> indicates
                        that <hi rend="italic">Regierungsbezirke</hi> occupy a very necessary place
                        in the governmental system in those <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi> where the
                        population and area are large. In Bavaria with approximately 150 <hi rend="italic">Landkreise</hi> and more than 20 <hi rend="italic">Stadtkreise</hi> some intermediate unit is essential between the <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> government and the local governments. In those
                            <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi> with populations not exceeding two million
                        inhabitants, such a unit is probably not necessary inasmuch as such <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi> are themselves about the [same] size as <hi rend="italic">Regierungsbezirke</hi> in Bavaria and Prussia. The <hi rend="italic">Regierungsbezirke</hi> require the necessary authority to
                        carry out those services which cannot be handled at the local level, but
                        care should be taken that they do not assume complete control over the <hi rend="italic">Kreise</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gemeinden</hi>, thus
                        eliminating the very important self-government functions of the
                        latter.</item>
                    <pb facs="0965" n="771" xml:id="pg_771"/>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Local Governments</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">Landkreise,
                            Stadtkreise</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gemeinden</hi> have the closest
                        contacts with the people of Germany. Under the <persName corresp="#p_SBH1">Stein</persName> Reform<note n="5" xml:id="d851fn5">For details
                            concerning the “<persName corresp="#p_SBH1">Stein</persName> Reform”,
                            see <persName>J. R. Seeley</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Life and Times
                                of <persName corresp="#p_SBH1">Stein</persName>, or Germany and
                                Prussia in the Napoleonic Age</hi> (Cambridge, 1878), and Guy
                            Stanton Ford, <hi rend="italic">
                                <persName corresp="#p_SBH1">Stein</persName> and the Era of Reform
                                in Prussia, 1807–1815</hi> (Princeton, 1922).</note> they were to be
                        given a large measure of control over so-called “self-government functions”
                        and in many instances developed standards which were admired even outside of
                        Germany. Though a start was made in the direction of placing German local
                        government on a democratic basis the process was not permitted to continue
                        far. Under the Nazis the remaining vestiges of local freedom disappeared and
                        local government became very largely the creature of the <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName>. The <hi rend="italic">Landkreise,
                            Stadtkreise</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Gemeinden</hi> during recent
                        years have been little more than administrative units, though in theory the
                        sphere of “self government” authority has been maintained. A major objective
                        of Military Government calls for the reconstituting of German local
                        government on the basis of as much local autonomy as is consonant with a
                        reasonably effective handling of problems. The most promising method of
                        training the Germans in democracy is to give them a large measure of
                        responsibility in conducting their own local affairs. It is important that
                        the emphasis should not be solely on the most efficient system of controls,
                        the greatest economy of funds or personnel, the easiest way for <gloss target="#t_MG1">MG</gloss> officers to supervise (though these are of
                        course not to be disregarded), for these are immediate matters. Relative
                        inefficiency is tolerable, indeed desirable, if democratic experience can be
                        provided. On the other hand, it is unrealistic to believe that full local
                        autonomy is feasible in this age of complicated problems. Moreover, the
                        helplessness engendered by extreme centralization exhibited by many local
                        officials makes some measure of higher supervision essential, especially
                        during the immediate future. Food rationing, coal supply, public health, and
                        other related problems cannot possibly be left to the local units. However,
                        local public works, public safety, recreation, welfare, housing and
                        education are fields in which every effort should be made to promote local
                        responsibility and interest. Considerable leeway should be feasible in
                        administering local finances.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Special Districts</hi>. The Nazis gave great impetus to a
                        movement already underway in Germany which provided special districts for
                        the handling of various functions. Finance, labor, food rationing and
                        production, economic matters, <gloss target="#t_PTT1">PTT</gloss>,
                        transportation, and a number of other governmental functions were removed
                        from the traditional government units and administered on the basis of
                        special districts which were by no means unified in boundaries. The result
                        was an enormously complicated system which few citizens could be <pb facs="0966" n="772" xml:id="pg_772"/> expected to keep in mind.
                        Decentralization and the accompanying emphasis on the promotion of democracy
                        require the fusion of most of those special districts with the regular units
                        of government. Such a step will strengthen the <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi>
                        and local units of government, make it easier for the people to know their
                        governmental system, and obviate some of the duplication and waste which
                        naturally accompany such an elaborate structure. <gloss target="#t_PTT1">PTT</gloss> and railroad districts may be exceptions to the rule since
                        they depend upon transportation facilities which may have little relation to
                            <hi rend="italic">Länder</hi> boundaries. A case can obviously be made
                        for the maintenance of all of these special districts, but overall
                        considerations of simplification and democratization call for fusing them
                        into the <hi rend="italic">Land/Regierungsbezirk/Kreis</hi> system.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">[<hi rend="smallcaps">section</hi>] <hi rend="smallcaps">iii.
                        miscellaneous</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Executive Agency</hi>. Executives subject to strict <gloss target="#t_MG1">MG</gloss> control have in general been installed by
                        Military Government up to and including the <hi rend="italic">Land</hi>
                        level. Until the reconstituting process has been carefully observed and
                        found satisfactory in operation, including the establishment of such
                            <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> ministerial machinery as
                        is necessary, it is not intended that a <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> executive agency shall be set up. The Control Council
                        will act as an executive at the <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> level. In the past German executives have been
                        appointed, except in a few instances such as <hi rend="italic">Bürgermeister</hi> in Württemberg for a brief period. This system is in
                        general probably better adapted to Germany than an elective one, but a
                        provision under which <hi rend="italic">Bürgermeister</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Gemeinden, Oberbürgermeister</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Stadtkreise</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Landräte</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Landkreise</hi> would be popularly elected after elections
                        are permitted might contribute to the building up of local responsibility
                        for government. In any case the selection of anti-Fascists with adequate
                        professional qualifications, strong personal characteristics, and not too
                        advanced in years is of the greatest importance.</item>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Legislative Bodies</hi>. Legislative bodies either ceased
                        to exist entirely or became powerless under the Nazi system. During the
                        early period of Military Government no elected legislative bodies can be
                        permitted, but advisory bodies should be established at least on the local
                        level. When elections are authorized, legislative bodies should be first
                        organized in the <hi rend="italic">Kreise</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gemeinden</hi>. Then the provision should be extended to the <hi rend="italic">Regierungsbezirke</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lander</hi>.
                        Only after it has been decided that a general <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> government is desirable should a provision be made for
                        a national legislative body. In setting up legislative bodies every attempt
                        should be made to endow them with definite authority which will permit a
                        large measure of freedom in matters relating to their respective units of
                        government.</item>
                    <pb facs="0967" n="773" xml:id="pg_773"/>
                    <label>18.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Courts</hi>. Military Government plans call for the
                        reestablishment of German courts beginning with the <hi rend="italic">Amtsgerichte</hi> as soon as conditions permit and satisfactory
                        personnel are available. Numerous <hi rend="italic">Amtsgerichte</hi> have
                        already been reopened as well as a small number of <hi rend="italic">Landgerichte</hi>. Higher courts should be provided as rapidly as
                        conditions warrant. Lower administrative courts should be reconstituted as
                        soon as the necessary personnel can be screened. The numerous special courts
                        which under the Nazis made the German judicial system excessively
                        complicated should be eliminated in large measure from the court
                        system.</item>
                    <label>19.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Civil Service</hi>. The German Civil Service is probably
                        the oldest and one of the largest, if not the largest, in the world. During
                        the years 1933–1945 severe pressure led the majority of the civil servants
                        to become at least nominal members of the <gloss target="#t_NSDAP1">NSDAP</gloss>. Civil servants with Nazi allegiance will be removed and
                        disqualified insofar as they hold executive or policy-determining positions.
                        While wide attention has been given to the denazification of the Civil
                        Service, comparatively little has been heard of an equally serious problem
                        involving the bureaucratic and anti-democratic traditions of civil servants,
                        especially in the higher and middle classes. There is substantial evidence
                        that the attitude of the civil servants was an important contributing factor
                        in the scuttling of the Weimar Republic. Military government may have to
                        make immediate use of those civil servants who pass the Nazi vetting test
                        irrespective of their lack of sympathy with democratic traditions, but it
                        would be a very short-sighted policy to continue these civil servants in
                        position indefinitely on the basis of their technical qualifications, at
                        least insofar as they are employed in those departments having political
                        character, where the opportunities to sabotage the democratic achievements
                        of Allied Military Government at a critical moment are unsurpassed. Vigorous
                        effort should be made in the direction of setting up training programs for
                        new civil servants which will be free from the pernicious emphasis of
                        bureaucracy. Special titles and perquisites which set the civil servant
                        apart and serve as foundations of the bureaucratic system should be
                        eliminated. The civil service system which had been completely nationalized,
                        even to local government employees, should be reconstituted on a <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> basis, giving reasonable leeway to the local
                        units in handling their own personnel problems.</item>
                    <label>20.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Military Government Control</hi>. Allied Military
                        Government must assume responsibility for the supervision of German
                        government indefinitely. As and when this control is ended, it should follow
                        the procedure of giving full responsibility to the Germans on the <hi rend="italic">Kreise</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gemeinden</hi> levels
                        first. If that proves satisfactory, controls may be removed at the <hi rend="italic">Regierungsbezirk</hi> level. Military Government control
                            <pb facs="0968" n="774" xml:id="pg_774"/> at both the <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> and <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> levels must
                        be continued throughout the occupation.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>In exercising control Military Government should work primarily through a
                        single German official, i. e. Minister President of a <hi rend="italic">Land, Regierungsprdsident</hi> of a <hi rend="italic">Regierungsbezirk,
                            Landrat</hi> of a <hi rend="italic">Landkreis, Oberbürgermeister</hi> of
                        a <hi rend="italic">Stadtkreis</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Bürgermeister</hi>
                        of a <hi rend="italic">Gemeinde</hi>, holding this official strictly
                        responsible for the entire performance of the government unit concerned.
                        This does not mean that no contact can be had with other German officials,
                        but if control responsibility is subdivided it will inevitably lead to
                        evasion of final accountability by the Germans and thus cause confusion and
                        unsatisfactory performance.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>Military Government officials cannot expect to exercise adequate control
                        unless they spend much of their time in the field, observing at first hand
                        the operations of the German governments they supervise.</item>
                    <label>21.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Elections</hi>. Elections are not contemplated during the
                        initial period of Military Government. However, as soon as Military
                        Government experience at the <hi rend="italic">Gemeinde</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Kreis</hi> levels indicates that German government has
                        reached a point where elective councils can function to advantage local
                        elections should be authorized. Appointive advisory councils should in the
                        meantime precede such a step. As developments at the local level demonstrate
                        that the German people can properly be entrusted with responsibility, the
                        election process should be extended to <hi rend="italic">Regierungsbezirk</hi> councils and then to the <hi rend="italic">Landtage</hi>. National elections must be postponed until such a time
                        as it is decided to establish a full <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> government with executive and legislative
                        powers.</item>
                    <label>22.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Political Parties</hi>. The <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 1067 series provides that “no political activities of any
                        kind shall be countenanced unless authorized by” the Commanding General of
                        the U. S. Forces. This has properly been construed to ban political parties
                        during the initial period of occupation. There is fairly extensive evidence
                        of a desire on the part of a limited number of former Social Democrats,
                        Democrats, Centrists and other Middle and slightly Rightist groups to become
                        active as political parties. Communists are more insistent on their
                        resumption of political activity. Anti-fascist groups tending to be
                        dominated by Communists though including in their numbers representatives of
                        middle and left center ideologies are to be encountered in many urban
                        sections. A limited amount of freedom should be given to political parties,
                        especially on the local level, as soon as the German governmental system has
                        developed sufficient stability. If this arrangement works out greater leeway
                        should be given and activities should be permitted on a <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> level. Authorization of national political organizations
                        would depend upon the decision to authorize a <persName corresp="#p_GRMH1">Reich</persName> legislative body.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0969" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/>
                <p>It is highly desirable that the number of political parties be reduced sharply
                    below that which characterized the Weimar Republic, inasmuch as a multiplicity
                    of parties contributed in no small way to the weakness of that government and
                    would in all probability have a similar effect in the future. It would not be
                    feasible for Military Government to set an arbitrary limit on the number of
                    political parties in Germany, for any such provision would not only be difficult
                    to enforce but lead to an undesirable artificiality. However, encouragement
                    insofar as may be possible should be given by Military Government to a system
                    under which there would be two or three major political parties.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
