<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-04-29T17:58:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-04-29T17:58:00-05:00" n="16" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d16">
                        <head>16. Telegram 87526 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Argentina<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d16fn1">
                                <p><seg type="summary">Summary: In a meeting with Secretary
                                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>,
                                        Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> voiced his concern over the U.S.
                                        Government’s policy toward Cuba.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                        Foreign Policy File, P850027–1724. Confidential; Nodis.
                                        Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_DJW_1">Davis</persName> on
                                        April 26; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_LWH_2">Luers</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KJB_2">Kubisch</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ELS_1">Eagleburger</persName>, and Ortiz.</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-04-29T22:58:00+00:00">April 29, 1974,
                            2258Z</date>.</dateline>
                        <p>87526. Subject: Secretary’s Meeting With Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName>.</p>
                        <p>1. The Secretary met with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> on Tuesday, April 16, for approximately one hour.
                            Other participants were Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_OAJL_1">Orfila</persName>, Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KJB_2">Kubisch</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LS_1">Stephen
                                Low</persName> of the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staff and
                            an interpreter. There follows summary of the discussion:</p>
                        <p>2. Cuba and the <gloss target="#t_MFM_1">MFM</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said Argentina seriously
                            preoccupied by continuing isolation of Cuba. The situation presents a
                            spectacle which is not in accord with international atmosphere of
                            peaceful coexistence. There is a need for a solution. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said he would raise Cuba in the
                                <gloss target="#t_MFM_1">MFM</gloss> but would not propose a
                            specific solution. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said
                            that he thought solution could be found without compromising the US. The
                            Secretary responded by saying that organizing the <gloss target="#t_MFM_1">MFM</gloss> so soon after the Mexico meeting was a
                            mistake. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> agreed. The
                            Secretary said one right step would be to support the selection of
                            Buenos Aires as the site for the next meeting. The Secretary then said
                            that if friction developed over the Cuba question in Washington,
                            US-Latin American relations would be set back substantially and the
                            whole idea of periodic Foreign Ministers’ meetings could be jeopardized.
                            The Secretary said he thought that the <gloss target="#t_MFM_1">MFM</gloss> could set up working groups to prepare for the next
                            meeting in B.A. and to proceed in the spirit of Tlatelolco. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> agreed and stressed his
                            personal conviction of the importance of good relations between the US
                            and Argentina.</p>
                        <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said the Argentine
                            people would not understand if he did not speak out clearly on Cuba. He
                            said he thought he had <pb facs="0102" n="50" xml:id="pg_50"/> a formula
                            which would give satisfaction to the US and to Argentina. He would state
                            at the conference that the problem of Cuba is a problem for all the
                            Latin American countries and he believed the Foreign Ministers should
                            face it squarely. The Secretary asked if that was all he was going to
                            say. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said he intended to
                            say much more but that the fundamental point was that he was not going
                            to propose a specific solution. He would speak in general terms about
                            coexistence and the need for a solution to the problem. He would then
                            yield to Rabasa who would suggest that Cuba be invited to the next
                            meeting. The Secretary asked what would happen then. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said that he did not have a
                            crystal ball but that this procedure would give everybody eight months
                            and in that time the Secretary would be able to work out a solution. The
                            Secretary said that if the meeting proceeded in a constructive way, if
                            Cuba were the only controversial item, if there then were no clear cut
                            resolution on Cuba, with only Mexico and Argentina speaking on the
                            subject, then he thought we could live with it. He then asked if
                                <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> was going to make any
                            other proposals on this subject at the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> meeting. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName>
                            said he would not ask for the incorporation of Cuba in the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> but he could not give assurances that
                            the matter would not come up. He said if a vote on sanctions came up a
                            two-thirds majority would be required. In that case the US could
                            abstain, the vote would fall short and the Ministers would be rid of the
                            problem. The Secretary then asked if <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> was definitely planning on making this proposal
                            if the subject came up and he responded in the affirmative. The
                            Secretary said that such a move could not come at a worse possible
                            moment. He said that he personally believed that relations with Cuba
                            could be improved over time but that if the US is pressed into a rapid
                            solution it would lead to an explosion. The Secretary said that we could
                            live with some discussion in Washington but that bringing up Cuba in
                            Atlanta would be too much. He told <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> we were considering changing our position on
                                <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> voting procedures but we could
                            not do so if a vote on Cuba sanctions were to follow. This would give
                            the appearance of collusion and would be an impossible move for us.</p>
                        <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> responded by saying
                            that the Argentines were searching for a solution and that if Mexico
                            would propose that Cuba be invited to the next conference this proposal
                            would be accepted and that there would be no further argument. The
                            Secretary said that we could not accept this and the best solution would
                            be the one that gave us eight months time. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said that he could not ask the countries to wait
                            eight months and that the point he wanted to make was that all the
                            nations should study the problem and search for a solution. The
                            Secretary pointed out other countries such as Brazil, Chile, and Uruguay
                                <pb facs="0103" n="51" xml:id="pg_51"/> would not agree with the
                            Argentine approach and the US also could not agree. The Secretary
                            pointed out that the US could not be put in a position of having a
                            decision taken in Washington to invite Cuba to a Foreign Ministers’
                            meeting. If it reached that point the US would simply have to say that
                            it would not attend and would work to prevent it from happening.
                                <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> responded that he was
                            not advocating a vote and that he wanted a decision without a vote. The
                            Secretary said what the US could not have in Washington was a decision
                            to invite Cuba even if that decision were arrived at by silence.
                                <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said he understood
                            and proposed that instead of Rabasa saying that he wanted to invite Cuba
                            to the conference he would ask only for the formation of a working
                            group. The Secretary said we could consider that though, of course, we
                            couldn’t support it. (Further discussion concerning <gloss target="#t_MFM_1">MFM</gloss> tactics and the timing of the Buenos
                            Aires meeting followed. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName>
                            suggested March.) The Secretary then proposed that <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> make his statement, Rabasa
                            would then say he proposed to invite Cuba. The Secretary would then say
                            that he thought that <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> as
                            the host for the next conference should consult with all the governments
                            of the hemisphere about their views. The Secretary said that he would
                            not oppose or support the proposal but that would, in itself, be a
                            positive American approach. He would make our position clear and hope
                            that before March 1975 some progress could be made.</p>
                        <p>5. The Secretary said he hoped that he would be able to visit Buenos
                            Aires before that time. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName>
                            expressed pleasure and said he would so inform President <persName corresp="#p_PJD_1">Perón</persName>. The Secretary said that
                                <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> could count on his
                            visit because an understanding between Argentina and the US can be the
                            basis for Western Hemisphere policy.</p>
                        <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> then summarized his
                            proposal on Cuba and the Secretary agreed that the Argentines should
                            consult with the other countries about their views and ideas and the
                            wisdom of inviting Cuba but that no vote would be asked for at the
                                <gloss target="#t_MFM_1">MFM</gloss>. The Secretary then asked if
                            this procedure would enable the subject to be avoided at the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said he would have to touch on the matter but
                            that he would say that Argentina had found a solution it considered
                            viable. The Secretary then repeated that the US was considering the
                            possibility of agreeing on a change in the voting procedure on
                            sanctions. He reiterated that we would only be able to do this if there
                            was no vote in Atlanta because we could not have it appear as if we were
                            in collusion.</p>
                        <p>7. US subsidiaries—<persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName>, near
                            the end of the conversation, asked about the US subsidiaries and the
                            question of automobile sales. The Secretary said he thought he could get
                            a positive answer by Thursday, April 18. <persName corresp="#p_VAJ_2">Vignes</persName> said he wanted to be able to have an answer
                            before leaving Washington and that it would cover up the other aspects
                            of <pb facs="0104" n="52" xml:id="pg_52"/> the Cuba matter entirely in
                            the Argentine press. The Secretary said that if the Cuba question could
                            be handled properly in Washington and Atlanta he could get a decision on
                            the sales.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_RK_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Rush</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>