<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-03-05T16:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-03-05T16:30:00-05:00" n="266" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d266">
                        <head>266. Telegram 2128 From the Embassy in Colombia to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d266fn1">
                                <p><seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_VVP_1">Vaky</persName> reported that the outcome of the Quito
                                            <gloss target="#t_MFM_1">MFM</gloss>, the provisions of
                                        the U.S. Trade Act, and the U.S. Government’s handling of
                                        bilateral issues had caused the Colombian Government to
                                        doubt the sincerity and reliability of the United
                                        States.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                        Foreign Policy File, D750078–1057. Confidential; Priority;
                                        Limdis. The Quito Conference is discussed in <ref target="#d386">Documents 386</ref>, <ref target="#d389">389</ref>, and <ref target="#d396">396</ref>. In
                                        telegram 519 from Bogotá, January 17, <persName corresp="#p_VVP_1">Vaky</persName> reported on January
                                        14 conversations between U.S. and Colombian officials on
                                        textiles, stating that the Colombians sought to stabilize
                                        and increase their share of the U.S. market. (Ibid.) The
                                        Urrutia-Thomson Treaty of 1914 guaranteed Colombia’s right
                                        of access to the Panama Canal. <persName corresp="#p_LMA_1">López</persName>, in a conversation with <persName corresp="#p_MWS_1">Mailliard</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_VVP_1">Vaky</persName>, expressed concern
                                        that the current Panama Canal negotiations maintain
                                        Colombia’s rights under the Urrutia-Thomson Treaty. The U.S.
                                        officials assured him that Colombia would be consulted with
                                        regard to U.S. capacity to comply with the Treaty. (Telegram
                                        802 from Bogotá, January 27; RG 59, Central Foreign Policy
                                        File, D750031–0766) <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s March 1 speech is in the
                                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin,</hi> March
                                        24, 1975, pp. 361–369. In telegram 4902 from Bogotá, May 29,
                                            <persName corresp="#p_VVP_1">Vaky</persName> reported
                                        that a U.S.-Colombian agreement on textiles had been signed.
                                        (Ibid., D750189–1046)</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Bogota</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-03-05T21:30:00+00:00">March 5, 1975,
                                2130Z</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2128. Subject: The US and Colombia: The Problem of Linkages. For <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> Asst Sec <persName corresp="#p_RWD_1">Rogers</persName> from the Amb.</p>
                        <p>1. Summary. This cable is intended to give you a tentative overview of
                            the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>’s perception of US in the hope
                            that this may be helpful to you, particularly in the light of possible
                            forthcoming visits: A significant change is occurring in the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>’s perception and attitude toward US.
                            It appears to be increasingly one of doubt about the sincerity of our
                            interest or of our capacity to cooperate in the crunches, and a
                            corresponding conclusion that they cannot depend upon close ties with US
                            alone to defend their own interests. This perception is not new in
                            Colombia, but the readiness of the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>
                            to act systematically on it is. This perception is the result of the
                            linked impact of a variety of factors, especially the Quito conference,
                            the trade act and our response to a series of bilateral issues. It is
                            not that the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> is becoming hostile;
                            rather it is becoming more calculating and hard-headed, more willing to
                            offset US and to develop more leverage to deal with US. To some degree
                            this is understandable; but the point is that at the moment Colombia is
                            moving away from US, and the ultimate degree of friendship or
                            antagonism, warmth or coolness of our basic relationship is still to be
                            decided. A conscious awareness of how the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> “sees” US and of how linkages among the various things
                            we do reinforce each other would help optimize beneficial effects. End
                            summary.</p>
                        <p>2. More than most <gloss target="#t_LA_1">LA</gloss> countries, Colombia
                            has approached the whole question of a relationship with US with
                            understanding and moderation. Thus while Colombia shares the Latin
                            American fear of <pb facs="0763" n="711" xml:id="pg_711"/> the
                            interventionist tendencies of our power, it has also been more disposed
                            then most to appreciate the benefit side, to be cooperative and to “help
                            US out” (e.g. flowers and countervailing duties). More than most,
                            Colombians have understood what we had in mind when we talked of
                            mutuality, interdependence and dialogue.</p>
                        <p>3. Now, however, a subtle but significant change is in process in the
                                <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>’s perception of US. The image
                            of the US which increasingly appears to form the basis for the Lopez
                            administration’s attitude toward US may be described approximately as
                            follows: a) whatever the rhetoric, the US as a nation and a people are
                            basically indifferent to Latin America’s ordeal; at least they are
                            unwilling or unable to implement any special treatment for the region;
                            b) the US readily departs from its philosophy and rhetoric when it feels
                            its self interest requires, and it frequently “exports” its problems; in
                            particular the US does not hesitate to use its power as a sanction or to
                            “intervene” when it feels it must; c) all of this is understandable and
                            realistic, but what it means is that for Colombia to depend too much
                            upon close ties with US is to subject Colombian development and national
                            life to US-determined interest, priorities and perceptions and to US
                            domestic crises and swings.</p>
                        <p>4. This Colombian perception is the result of the linked impact of a
                            number of complex and long-range factors, such as basic changes in the
                            world structure; what they see as the impact on US of our recent and
                            current domestic economic, political and spiritual crises: The <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> “revelations”. But there are three
                            proximate sources for this “cooling” which it is important for US to
                            understand: a) the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>’s reaction to
                            Quito b) the image of US they saw revealed in the Trade Act and c) our
                            reaction to a series of bilateral issues.</p>
                        <p>5. Quito. President Lopez said to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MWS_1">Mailliard</persName> that the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>
                            had assumed that in agreeing to an <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>
                            meeting the US also implicitly agreed it should be a success. The <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> believes it was in our power to help
                            secure the requisite votes, and that therefore our decision not to do so
                            was a deliberate one that left it out on a limb. What it is particularly
                            important to understand is that their unhappiness rests basically on
                            personal dimensions. Colombians are intensely personalistic, and dignity
                            and self-esteem are extremely important. The Foreign Minister and the
                            President, and more abstractly all the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>, felt personally embarrassed by the results. Their
                            dignity and self-esteem were damaged, and they fastened on us as the
                            cause. One does not, in their view, treat a friend that way. That is why
                            the resentment has been deep and why logical arguments do not alleviate
                            it.</p>
                        <p>6. Trade Act. The Colombians consider that the Trade Act neither hurts
                            nor particularly benefits them. They understand the concepts behind it
                            and give us credit for them. To them however the conditions <pb facs="0764" n="712" xml:id="pg_712"/> in Title V are reminiscent of
                            the Hickenlooper amendment and are evidence that we are still prepared
                            to attach conditions to our assistance. To them import-sensitive
                            exceptions are deliberate departures from our stated philosophy when
                            adherence to it becomes difficult. To them there is little in the act
                            that shows any special consideration for Latin America. What they see
                            demonstrated, in short, is not so much our principles, but how readily
                            we depart from them under pressure when we think we have to. They
                            understand this as realistic and even inevitable, and they do not
                            condemn us for it (as some of their neighbors do). What they simply
                            conclude is that there is doubt as to how much access to markets they
                            really get.</p>
                        <p>7. Bilateral problems. Consider the Colombian perspective on some current
                            bilateral matters: although somewhat assuaged by the presidential
                            invitation, the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> still feels it is
                            not as highly regarded by US as some other nations. The Secretary’s
                            March 1 speech, for example, made clear to the world that his trip and
                            yours were important opening guns to grasp the “new opportunity”. Yet as
                            far as Colombian knew at the moment they are left out of both.</p>
                        <p>8. Textiles may be our most touchy current bilateral problem. The
                            Colombians understand our problems; yet their industry is vital to them,
                            too. And so they are waiting to see what treatment we offer them in the
                            light of all we have said about friendship, access to markets, a new
                            world order, etc. Whether they will agree to limit themselves
                            voluntarily depends upon whether they will think our offer reasonable in
                            terms of their own interests. But more than that, they think that what
                            is at stake here is a test case of the future—of the role of comparative
                            advantage in a new world trading system. What they are afraid of is that
                            we will handle it in terms of the domestic political pressures of the
                            moment, rather than as a problem of mutual interests in a new world
                            system as we talk about.</p>
                        <p>9. Colombia’s concern with the Urrutia-Thomson Treaty rests more on
                            concepts of dignity and sovereignty than on estimates of benefit alone.
                            What they see is a treaty right they enjoy [garble] although they have
                            periodically brought this subject up over the past year and a half to
                            ascertain our purpose and thoughts, all they have heard us say is,
                            “don’t call us, we’ll call you.”</p>
                        <p>10. Although Colombia has ratified the Quita Sueno Treaty, we have not.
                            The <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> can only conclude that the
                            matter is not very important to us.</p>
                        <p>11. Their efforts up to now to find out what we think about a new coffee
                            agreement have elicited no real answer. Because they have had no
                            indication we wanted a new agreement, Colombia stopped entering actively
                            into tech discussions in the ICO, feeling it pointless. We in turn
                            interpreted that as meaning Colombia had no interest. And so we <pb facs="0765" n="713" xml:id="pg_713"/> have danced around each other
                            waiting for evidence of each other’s good faith. What the Colombians
                            look for is private consultations and a meeting of the minds with
                            US.</p>
                        <p>12. In short, the Colombian perception of US is a total perception. All
                            of these—and other—factors reinforce each other, and it is their linked
                            impact that has added up to doubt a cumulative doubt of the sincerity of
                            our interest, of our willingness or capacity to be helpful in the
                            crunches (which is when they think they need our help the most), and
                            even of how much Colombia itself really wants to open up to US.</p>
                        <p>13. It is not that Colombia is becoming hostile, far from it. But it is
                            becoming hard-headed. It is less disposed to be cooperative to “help us
                            out”. It is more prepared to balance and offset us than to follow our
                            leadership. In short the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> seems to
                            be moving to a conception of a relationship with US that is based on a
                            calculation of their own interests and a toe-to-toe bargaining strategy,
                            even if it means risking our irritation, displeasure or opposition.</p>
                        <p>14. All of this is coupled with the growing conviction that the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> needs to create new relationships and
                            arrangements to advance Colombia’s interests and improve its leverage.
                            Thus Colombia is more disposed now than it ever has been to [garble]
                            into a dumb-bell pattern and to regional arrangements such as <gloss target="#t_SELA_1">SELA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>15. There is nothing particularly unique, extraordinary or surprising in
                            all of this. These perceptions are not particularly new. What is new is
                            that the Lopez admin is more prepared than its predecessors to act
                            systematically on these perceptions. The Lopez govt is a far different
                            thing than the <persName corresp="#p_PBME_1">Pastrana</persName> govt.
                            To some degree, too, Colombia’s desire to be master of its own fate is
                            understandable, even desirable. But the point is that Colombia is at the
                            moment moving away from US and it is not clear where it is going to
                            stop. The precise degree of warmth or coolness, alienation or
                            cooperation, irritation or politeness which the basic relationship will
                            ultimately exhibit is still very much in doubt. A subtle erosion in our
                            relationship is in process—some of it unavoidable—and it will take a
                            conscious effort to arrest it.</p>
                        <p>16. Like most <gloss target="#t_LA_1">LA</gloss>’s, Colombia judges the
                            value of cooperation with US, and the sincerity of our [garble] and it
                            decides how to deal with US—in short it “sees” US—in terms of how we
                            respond to their concrete problems, situations, interests and needs.
                            This egocentric attitude should neither irritate nor surprise US. <gloss target="#t_LA_1">LA</gloss>’s have no other way of conceiving a
                            relationship with US, given their long history of gravitation around our
                            power pole and their list of past grievances. “What have you done for me
                            lately?” is to the Latinos a perfectly legitimate question to ask. And
                            so when we talk of mutual adventures they first seek to test our good
                            faith, and the only way they know how to do that is to judge how we
                            relate to what they consider their major concerns and needs.</p>
                        <pb facs="0766" n="714" xml:id="pg_714"/>
                        <p>17. This situation is still with US. The Secy’s March 1 speech was
                            excellent. Cellos are more soothing than trumpets. But ultimately the
                            question will be the same: What does it mean for me? When the Secy says
                            commodities policy is essential, the Colombians will say, “fine, how
                            about coffee?” when we say access to markets is vital to the developing
                            world, the Colombians say, “we agree; how are you going to treat me on
                            textiles?”</p>
                        <p>18. None of this argues for simply catering to every Latin whim. It does
                            mean we have yet to win Latin America’s confidence. That in turn
                            underlines the importance of an accurate understanding of how the
                            Colombians “see” us and of a conscious awareness of linkages, i.e. how
                            separate issues reinforce or offset each other. Many of our problems
                            obviously maybe intractable, e.g. textiles. But our style and
                            responsiveness on others might be shaped differently were we aware of
                            the linkages, e.g. visits, and canal question.</p>
                        <p>19. Curiously we often forget about this linkage effect. Our bilateral
                            policies are often the prey of two interrelated circumstances a) the
                            domestic structure of our bureaucracy which means different experts
                            handle different problems with different perspectives and criteria, and
                            b) the absence of any consensus as to a fundamental purpose governing
                            our relations with <gloss target="#t_LA_1">LA</gloss> which can serve as
                            an arbiter when contradictory US sub-interests are involved. Neither the
                            “special relationship” nor any other concept of <gloss target="#t_LA_1">LA</gloss> importance has ever really received bureaucratic-wide
                            consensus or acceptance up to now. In the absence of such an accepted
                            over-arching concept or purpose, issues tend to become decided on tech,
                            parochial or individual bases, without particular regard to on-going
                            relations or to each other.</p>
                        <p>20. No matter how you slice it, Colombia is unique in the hemisphere and
                            uniquely positioned to be consecutive. It is, after all, large
                            enough—fourth in size, third in population—to be important, it is
                            democratic enough to be listened to with respect by the left;
                            non-ideological and pragmatic [enough] to work with the right; dynamic
                            and rich enough—the most industrialized country in the Andean Pact
                            including Venezuela—to be a force in economic integration; poor enough
                            to be a spokesman for the third world in any international forum; and
                            moderate and realistic enough to be willing to respond to us if we prove
                            ourselves willing to help them with their problems.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_VVP_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_VVP_1">Vaky</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>