<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-02-19T12:48:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-02-19T12:48:00-05:00" n="273" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d273">
                        <head>273. Telegram 40131 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Colombia<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d273fn1">
                                <p><seg type="summary">Summary: The Department informed the Embassy
                                        that it was willing to provide increased anti-narcotics
                                        funding if Colombia developed a realistic control program
                                        and implemented commodity assistance programs.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                        Foreign Policy File, [no film number]. Confidential;
                                        Immediate. Repeated to the Mission in Geneva. Drafted by
                                            <persName corresp="#p_EDH_1">Ernst</persName> and
                                        McLaughlin; cleared by Kranz, Grown, <persName corresp="#p_WME_1">Wampler</persName>, and Mantonelli;
                                        approved by <persName corresp="#p_EDH_1">Ernst</persName>.
                                        In telegram 1176 from Bogotá, February 3, the Embassy
                                        informed the Department that <persName corresp="#p_LMA_1">López</persName> had tapped the Ministry of Defense as
                                        the executive authority responsible for coordinating the
                                        drug enforcement effort in Colombia. (Ibid., D760043–0056)
                                        In telegram 1671 from Bogotá, February 13, the Embassy
                                        recommended specific levels and types of assistance to be
                                        offered to the Colombian Government to support its
                                        anti-narcotics efforts. (Ibid., D760058–0436)</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Bogota</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-02-19T17:48:00+00:00">February 19, 1976,
                                1748Z</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>40131. Bogota for Ambassador, Geneva for <persName corresp="#p_VSB_1">Vance</persName>. Subject: <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>
                            Narcotics Reorganization and Associated Assistance Request. Ref: (A)
                            Bogota 0981, (B) Bogota 1176, (C) Bogota 1414, (D) Bogota 1671, (E)
                            Bogota A–105, August 25, 1975.</p>
                        <p>1. Your reports of <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> plans to
                            reorganize its national narcotics control effort have been welcomed here
                            as indication of substantially increased <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> commitment to international narcotics control program.
                            While we are confident Embassy has not implied any commitment on
                            specific aspects of <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> request for
                            increased assistance, proposals outlined in Bogota 1671 underscore need
                            for cautious approach to entire assistance question. In sum, we are
                            prepared to provide increased narcotics-related assistance to <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> provided: (A) <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> develops a realistic control program which proposes to
                            attack specific problems in specific ways; (B) Successful implementation
                            requires commodity assistance using narcotics funds; and (C) Funds made
                            available by Congress. End summary.</p>
                        <p>2. We do regard Colombia as a high cocaine priority country and consider
                            it appropriate to augment our assistance considerably beyond prior
                            levels, if this is required to diminish its middleman role in the <pb facs="0786" n="734" xml:id="pg_734"/> substantial cocaine traffic
                            from Latin America to the United States, as noted in your NCAP (Ref. E).
                            We also welcome your assessment that a reorganization of the Colombian
                            effort as outlined in Refs A and C is appropriate to the situation and
                            that it augurs more effective efforts. We note your estimate of the
                            ability of the military to perform in this area. We understand the role
                            of the military for command and coordinating purposes as well as
                            maintaining and operating of aircraft, but assume the people doing most
                            of the actual gathering of intelligence, interdicting and enforcing
                            would essentially be national police, <gloss target="#t_DAS_1">DAS</gloss> and customs trained and experienced in those
                            functions.</p>
                        <p>3. With respect to further U.S. assistance, we regard the citation of an
                            overall dollar amount and specification of equipment (Ref D) to be
                            premature. A reasonable rationale for and justification of an enlarged
                            program must be based on a full analysis and definition of the nature,
                            scope and incidence of the narcotics traffic problem to be attacked,
                            together with carefully planned and described approaches to meet it at
                            the most feasible points at which suppression efforts could be applied.
                            While money is a function of program, and there is a “chicken and egg”
                            aspect as far as that goes, the program itself must be a function of
                            elaborated need.</p>
                        <p>4. Thus, while Ref D is a good summary of what we might rpt might do, we
                            would be hard pressed at this point to sell it to Congress. Much staff
                            work on both sides remains to be done if we and the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> are to develop a realistic outline of
                            a workable narcotics control effort. Once it has been agreed that
                            certain types of actions will be required (and that, if undertaken, they
                            have reasonable chance of success), we can then jointly determine what
                            equipment will be needed, how much of this need can be met from existing
                                <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> inventory, and how much and
                            what types should be provided under narcotics assistance rubric. At this
                            point, however, we do not wish in any way encourage unrealistic <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> expectations which, if not met, would
                            lead to a diminution of the Colombian effort.</p>
                        <p>5. FYI only: At this time we can plan rpt plan on a program in the range
                            of eight to ten million dollars, the maximum that would be available in
                            our <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 76 and <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 77 programs combined, assuming Congressional
                            appropriations for both years reach levels requested by executive
                            branch. End FYI.</p>
                        <p>6. Further, several considerations must bear heavily on our approach.
                            First, cocaine ranks after heroin in the prioritization of drugs of
                            abuse made in the domestic council white paper. Second, we have heavy
                            and increasing assistance commitments to other countries, certain of
                            which must be given higher priority. Third, our entire <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1976 narcotics assistance request is for
                            but 42.5 million dollars, and this has yet to be acted upon by the
                            Congress. Fourth, we must be absolutely assured <pb facs="0787" n="735" xml:id="pg_735"/> that equipment provided by assistance funds will
                            be used for narcotics control purposes and not diverted to general
                            support of military or general law enforcement entities. Should this
                            ever not be the case, our program would be placed in grave jeopardy in
                            the Congress.</p>
                        <p>7. We suggest it appropriate in the circumstances for a small number of
                            Washington-based specialists to join with key members of the Embassy’s
                            narcotics control committee, at a suitable time soon after the
                            Secretary’s visit, for an up-to-date analysis of the detailed nature of
                            the interdiction problem in Colombia. This would be followed by careful
                            development of a program with the Colombians into which can be fitted
                            appropriate amounts and types of available U.S. grant equipment. We have
                            in mind from Washington, for example, a representative of <gloss target="#t_SNM_1">S/NM</gloss> for overall programming, one each
                            specialists in aviation, communications and general drug enforcement. In
                            our approach we would give priority to developing and equipping units
                            having drug control as their specific charge over those that would have
                            it as one among other responsibilities.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_IRS_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_IRS_1">Ingersoll</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>