<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>283. Memorandum From Secretary of Defense Richardson to the President’s
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs ( to the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve11p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d283</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">283</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National Security Study Memorandum</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-04-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-04-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="283"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d283">
                <head>283. Memorandum From Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_RER_1"
                        >Richardson</persName> to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d283fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_RER_1"
                                    >Richardson</persName> recommended to <persName
                                    corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> that a <gloss
                                    target="#t_SRG_1">SRG</gloss> be convened to review U.S. policy
                                towards Peru.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Country
                                Files, Box 793, Latin America, Peru, Vol. 3, January 1972–December
                                31, 1973. Secret. On April 18, <persName corresp="#p_RER_1"
                                    >Richardson</persName> sent a copy of the memorandum to Rogers.
                                (Ibid., RG 59, Central Files, 1970–1973, <gloss target="#t_POL_1"
                                    >POL</gloss> PERU–US) <persName corresp="#p_BTG_1"
                                    >Belcher</persName>’s February 23 telegram is referred to in the
                                source note to <ref target="#d282">Document 282</ref>. On March 23,
                                in telegram 1894 from Lima, <persName corresp="#p_BTG_1"
                                    >Belcher</persName> informed the Department of Peru’s “probable
                                imminent decision” to purchase Soviet <gloss target="#t_MIG_1"
                                    >MIGs</gloss>. (Ibid., RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, [no
                                film number]) <gloss target="#t_NSDM_1">NSDM</gloss> 199, December
                                26, 1972, is <ref target="frus1969-76ve10#d640">Document 640</ref>
                                in <ref target="frus1969-76ve10">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1969–1976, vol. E–10,
                                    Documents on American Republics, 1969–1972</ref>. No <gloss
                                    target="#t_SRG_1">SRG</gloss> meeting on Peru was held.</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-04-18">April 18, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Deteriorating US-Peruvian Relations</item>
                </list>
                <p>I have become increasingly concerned by the rapid deterioration in US relations
                    with Peru over the past several months. This deterioration has been highlighted
                    by our Ambassador to Peru in messages of 232214Z Feb 73 and 232225Z Mar 73. The
                    immediate cause is the recent seizures of US fishing vessels. It appears that
                    these seizures were stimulated by the October 1972 revision of the Fisherman’s
                    Protective Act and subsequent public reaction in Peru.</p>
                <p>Since <gloss target="#t_FMS_1">FMS</gloss> to Peru have again been placed “under
                    review” following the December 1972 seizure, both the US Country Team and the
                    Peruvian Naval Attaché in Washington have expressed the extreme frustration and
                    dilemma of the Peruvian Navy created by the review. The major ships of Peru’s
                    Navy are obsolete, and Peru is currently exploring means and sources for their
                    replacement. The Peruvian Air <pb facs="0811" n="759" xml:id="pg_759"/> Force is
                    also deeply affected because of its desire to modernize with A–37B and F–5E
                    aircraft. The sale of these aircraft is contingent upon the ability of the US
                    Government to sell seat ejection cartridges and mini-gun barrels. Both of these
                    Services must look elsewhere if assured <gloss target="#t_FMS_1">FMS</gloss> are
                    not soon forthcoming from the United States. The Soviets have made continued
                    overtures toward Peru for the sale of military equipment with attractive credit
                    terms and have recently demonstrated new equipment (including MiGs) to the
                    Peruvian Joint Chiefs of Staff equivalent, both in the Soviet Union and in Cuba.
                    Should Peru purchase MIGs, the Chilean Air Force may accede to Soviet pressure
                    and also accept these aircraft. Intelligence reports indicate that Peru is also
                    considering the acquisition of Soviet T–54 tanks.</p>
                <p>Parallel to the problems caused by the seizure of US fishing boats, is the
                    equally frustrating matter of the 1968 Peruvian expropriation, without
                    compensation, of the International Petroleum Company (IPC). Following the most
                    recent review of US policy toward Peru (National Security Study Memorandum 158),
                    National Security Decision Memorandum (<gloss target="#t_NSDM_1">NSDM</gloss>)
                    199, dated 26 December 1972, stated that the Senior Review Group (<gloss
                        target="#t_SRG_1">SRG</gloss>) would reconsider the situation if, by the end
                    of February 1973, the initiation of talks with the Peruvians in the IPC case had
                    not proven feasible.</p>
                <p>The US Ambassador to Peru has identified a number of expected or possible actions
                    and reactions which could further raise the intensity of bilateral conflicts
                    within the next few months and has suggested that we should not go further into
                    this difficult period without some plan for management.</p>
                <p>In my view, the inability to make progress in resolving the IPC dispute, combined
                    with the deteriorating situation brought about by the fisheries problem, makes
                    it urgent that US policy toward Peru be reviewed. I therefore recommend an early
                    meeting of the <gloss target="#t_SRG_1">SRG</gloss> for this purpose.</p>
                <p rend="right">
                    <hi rend="strong">E.L.R.</hi>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
