<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-08-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="359" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d359">
                        <head>359. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                            Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SHW_1">Shlaudeman</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d359fn1">
                                <p><seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1">Shlaudeman</persName> discussed the questions raised by
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName>
                                        regarding the Condor démarche and recommended that <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> approach both
                                            <persName corresp="#p_BEJC_1">Blanco</persName> and
                                            <persName corresp="#p_VJC_1">Vadora</persName>, while a
                                        parallel approach was made by <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1">Shlaudeman</persName> to the Uruguayan Ambassador in
                                        Washington.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                        Foreign Policy File, P860084–1945. Secret; Nodis. Drafted by
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1">Shlaudeman</persName>;
                                        cleared by O’Donohue. The proposed cable from <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1">Shlaudeman</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> is attached but
                                        not printed. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                        Policy File, P860084–1948) No decision is recorded on the
                                        memorandum, but in telegram Secto 27128 from the Secretary’s
                                        Delegation in Lusaka, September 16, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> “declined to
                                        approve message to Montevideo and has instructed that no
                                        further action be taken on this matter.” (National Archives,
                                        RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D760350–0102) Tab 2 is
                                            <ref target="#d358">Document 358</ref>; Tab 3 is
                                        Document <ref target="#d241">241</ref>.</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-08-30">August 30, 1976</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="italic">Operation Condor</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>You raised a number of questions about <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName>’s reactions (Tab 2) to the instructions to him
                            on Condor (Tab 3). My comments on his cable follow.</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">2 lines not declassified</hi>] The <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line
                                not declassified</hi>] does not believe <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName>’s representations would unduly endanger him in
                            light of widespread talk about Condor and the assassination aspect among
                            officers of the security services of the southern cone. [<hi rend="italic">3½ lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>If we take this tack, the question is: should <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> also make representations? I
                            believe he should. Our approach as originally conceived is couched in
                            terms of a continuing exchange of information on the ground in
                            Montevideo. A proposal of that kind from <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> would offer the most constructive and effective
                            method of handling the problem. Dealing only with the Ambassador here
                            would foreclose establishing that kind of relationship.</p>
                        <p>We agree with <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> that, if
                            he does it in Montevideo, he should talk both to the military and to
                                <persName corresp="#p_BEJC_1">Blanco</persName>.</p>
                        <p>A parallel approach here, as <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> suggests, is acceptable to me and would help to
                            preserve his position with the government there. But it is not my sense
                            that this démarche is being made for domestic U.S. political
                            considerations. What we are trying to head off is a series of
                            international murders that could do serious damage to the international
                            status and reputation of the countries involved.</p>
                        <pb facs="1010" n="958" xml:id="pg_958"/>
                        <p>We agree with <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> that he
                            should add that the Condor targets have their own lists of Uruguayan
                            Government officials targeted for assassination. It is precisely for
                            that reason we propose to engage the Government of Uruguay in an
                            exchange of views on the security situation so that we can demonstrate
                            our appreciation of the problems they face.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Options:</p>
                        <p>We have three options in the Uruguayan case. We could do it:</p>
                        <p>—by <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> to General <persName corresp="#p_VJC_1">Vadora</persName> and to <persName corresp="#p_BEJC_1">Blanco</persName>, supported by a démarche to
                            the Ambassador here [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation:</p>
                        <p>That you authorize the attached telegram to <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> instructing him to talk to both <persName corresp="#p_BEJC_1">Blanco</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_VJC_1">Vadora</persName>, informing him of a parallel
                            approach by me here and referring to a communication he will receive
                                [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] on
                            additional protection for the source. (Tab 1) Phil <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName> has concurred in the attached
                            suggested telegram.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">ALTERNATIVELY</hi>, that we ask <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName> to have the message conveyed
                                [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] if in his
                            judgment that can be done.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">ALTERNATIVELY</hi>, that I make the démarche here,
                            with no action to be taken in Montevideo for the time being.</p>
                        <p>Attachments:</p>
                        <quote>
                            <p>Tab 1—Telegram to <persName corresp="#p_SEV_1">Siracusa</persName>
                            </p>
                            <p>Tab 2—Montevideo 3123</p>
                            <p>Tab 3—State 209192</p>
                        </quote>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>