<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>51. Telegram 4844 From the Embassy in Argentina to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve11p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1976-07-23T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-07-23T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Foreign nationals</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec7XCpI38AIhVpLJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional security</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-07-23T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-07-23T15:00:00-05:00" n="51"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                <head>51. Telegram 4844 From the Embassy in Argentina to the Department of
                        State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d51fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: The Embassy commented on a Bureau of
                                Intelligence and Research report on Southern Cone security
                                practices, suggesting that the report might have underestimated the
                                extent of cooperation between regional security forces.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D760285–0673. Secret. In telegram 178852 to all
                                American Republic diplomatic posts, July 20, the Department
                                transmitted <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss> Report No. 526, an
                                updated version of the June 4 report to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                                    >Kissinger</persName> on Southern Cone security practices that
                                is published as <ref target="#d46">Document 46</ref>. The report
                                concluded that “the evidence does not conclusively establish the
                                existence of formal, high-level coordination among Southern Cone
                                security forces for the express purpose of eliminating exiles,”
                                though it did suggest “that cooperation does occur on at least a
                                localized and opportunistic basis.” (National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Foreign Policy File, D760279–0200)</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Buenos Aires</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1976-07-23T20:00:00+00:00">July 23, 1976, 2000Z</date>.</dateline>
                <p>4844. Subject: South American Southern Cone Security Practices. Ref: State
                    178852. (Not releasable to foreign nationals/not releasable to contractors or
                    contractor-consultants/warning notice—sensitive intelligence sources and methods
                    involved)</p>
                <p>1. Embassy Buenos Aires offers following comments on <gloss target="#t_INR_1"
                        >INR</gloss> Report No. 526 of July 19, 1976, as transmitted in reftel:</p>
                <p>2. First, we agree with <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss> assessment that
                    present evidence does not rpt not confirm that Southern Cone security forces are
                    involved in well-organized conspiracy to eliminate exile leaders. It should be
                    emphasized, however, that local governments have motivation and opportunity to
                    do so, and it would be equally erroneous to conclude that such conspiracy is
                    unlikely.</p>
                <p>3. However, <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss> assessment underestimates degree
                    of cooperation between regional security forces, in our opinion. Report
                    recognizes that regional governments have organized to exchange information and
                    to cooperate in certain areas (Operation Condor). It does not appear to take
                    into consideration recent reports of the presence in Argentina of security
                    forces personnel from Uruguay and Chile, for example, who appear to be acting as
                    advisors to the Argentine forces in connection with nationals of their own
                    countries supposed to be involved in subversion. One recent report cited
                    Argentine Army source reference to a Uruguayan Army major assigned to the
                    Uruguayan military intelligence service “who has been in Buenos Aires for the
                    past several weeks cooperating with Argentine security forces in anti-terrorist
                    operations.” Another report, [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not
                        declassified</hi>] cited presence in Buenos Aires of Uruguayan defense
                    intelligence service personnel working in conjunction with Argentine security
                    service. <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss> should also note [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] which makes clear the
                    extensive interchange <pb facs="0201" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> of personnel and
                    active cooperation between Chile and Argentina on security matters. We consider
                    that the evidence is heavily weighted in favor of the conclusion that both
                    Chilean and Uruguayan security personnel are joining in operations of the
                    Argentine security forces against terrorists and subversives, both in Buenos
                    Aires and other parts of Argentina, although we cannot document the conclusion.
                    It is probable that Argentine security personnel in turn have traveled to
                    neighboring countries to cooperate with local security forces. Without question,
                    regional governments have recognized and responded in kind to “internalization”
                    of terrorist/subversive effort, represented in Southern Cone by the JCR.</p>
                <p>4. In addition, there appears also to be misunderstanding, to which we may have
                    contributed, as to composition of the various forces engaged in battle in
                    Argentina. In para 4 of reftel, <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss> refers to
                    “. . . tri-cornered battle among security personnel, leftists and right-wing
                    assassins.” This description implies that there are right-wing extremists
                    operating completely independently in Argentina. During period of Triple A under
                    last Peronist govt this was true as right-wing labor goons were probably as
                    active as off-duty security personnel in murdering and harassing leftists. In
                    our best judgment, the only “right-wing assassins” operating in Argentina at
                    this point, however, are members of the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss>
                    security forces. The battle is a two-sided affair, not tri-cornered. Only real
                    question is degree to which security forces personnel may be operating out of
                        <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> control.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>Chaplin</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
