<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>58. Telegram 262786 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                    Argentina</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve11p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">58</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1976-10-22T18:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-10-22T18:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134112"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Terrorism</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-10-22T18:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-10-22T18:45:00-05:00" n="58"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                <head>58. Telegram 262786 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                        Argentina<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d58fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1"
                                    >Shlaudeman</persName> assured <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1"
                                    >Hill</persName> that he and other U.S. officials had shared
                                human rights concerns with <persName corresp="#p_GCA_1"
                                    >Guzzetti</persName> during meetings in Washington, and he
                                stated that the Argentine Foreign Minister must have heard only what
                                he wanted to hear on this issue.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, [no film number]. Secret; Immediate; Nodis. Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1">Shlaudeman</persName> and approved
                                by <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName
                                    corresp="#p_RCW_1">Robinson</persName>. Telegram 6871 is <ref
                                    target="#d57">Document 57</ref>. In an October 20 draft of this
                                telegram, the concluding paragraph reads: “With respect to your
                                closing admonition about the futility of representations, we doubt
                                that the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> has all that many
                                illusions. It was obvious here that even <persName
                                    corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName> knew his country had a
                                problem. In any event, you and we have laid it out as best we could.
                                In the circumstances, I agree that the Argentines will have to make
                                their own decisions and that further exhortations or generalized
                                lectures from us would not be useful at this point.” (Department of
                                State, <gloss target="#t_FOIA_1">FOIA</gloss> Electronic Reading
                                Room, Argentina Declassification Project) In telegram 7062 from
                                Buenos Aires, October 27, <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1"
                                    >Hill</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1"
                                    >Shlaudeman</persName> that it was “reassuring to have chapter
                                and verse on what <persName corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName>
                                was told.” <persName corresp="#p_HRC_1">Hill</persName> added that
                                “we continue to believe many in <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss>
                                maintain their illusions <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> has no
                                serious human rights problems” and suggested that a protest by the
                                Department would reinforce the message delivered to <persName
                                    corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName>. (National Archives, RG
                                59, Central Foreign Policy File, P850108–2013, N760007–0818)</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1976-10-22T23:45:00+00:00">October 22, 1976, 2345Z</date>.</dateline>
                <p>262786. For Amb. only from Asst. Sec. <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1"
                        >Shlaudeman</persName>. Subject: <persName corresp="#p_GCA_1"
                        >Guzzetti</persName>’s Visit to the U.S. Ref: Buenos Aires 6871.</p>
                <p>1. As in other circumstances you have undoubtedly encountered in your diplomatic
                    career, <persName corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName> heard only what he
                    wanted to hear. He was told in detail how strongly opinion in this country has
                    reacted against reports of abuses by the security forces in Argentina and the
                    nature of the threat this poses to Argentine interests. An example of the filter
                    he employed (or perhaps a reflection of his poor grasp of English) is the
                    quotation ascribed to Ambassador Martin on “being careful” about the Catholic
                    church. What Ed said was that if priests <pb facs="0227" n="175" xml:id="pg_175"
                    /> were guilty of crimes, they should be arrested and tried—but if they simply
                    disappeared or were shot that could never be accepted in this country.</p>
                <p>2. As for the “consensus of the meeting,” on our side it was that <persName
                        corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName>’s assurances that a tranquil and
                    violence-free Argentina is coming soon must prove a reality if we are to avoid
                    serious problems between us. <persName corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName>’s
                    interpretation is strictly his own. With respect to “understanding” Argentina’s
                    problems, we did indeed take cognizance of the violent assault on Argentine
                    society from the other side and expressed the hope that we could continue to be
                    helpful in the task of restoring Argentina’s economy.</p>
                <p>3. On the <persName corresp="#p_HTR_1">Harkin</persName> problem, the Secretary
                    warned <persName corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName> that we would be forced
                    to vote against Argentine loans absent an improvement in conditions. We have
                    told the Argentines that we would not vote negatively at the moment in light of
                    our understanding of the current situation in the country, but might be forced
                    to abstain. (If our impression that counter-terrorism has declined recently is
                    ill-founded, please correct it.) The <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> has
                    postponed a $30 million industrial-credits loan, but not as <persName
                        corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName> indicated for several months. The
                    loan should come up again within a few weeks.</p>
                <p>4. Finally, with respect to <persName corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName>’s
                    “jubilation” and its effect, we doubt that the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1"
                        >GOA</gloss> has such illusions. It was obvious in our contacts that
                        <persName corresp="#p_GCA_1">Guzzetti</persName> knew his country has a
                    problem—one that requires a speedy solution. And we will continue to impress on
                    Argentine representatives here, as we expect you to do there, that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> regards most seriously Argentina’s
                    international commitments to protect and promote fundamental human rights. There
                    should be no mistake on that score. I recommend that you read and bring to the
                    attention of the <gloss target="#t_GOA_1">GOA</gloss> the Secretary’s speech of
                    October 19 before the Synagogue Council of America as a basic statement of our
                    policy of practical efforts to enhance respect for human rights—in Argentina or
                    elsewhere.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_KHA_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
