<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-08-07T11:10:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-08-07T11:10:00-05:00" n="64" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d64">
                        <head>64. Telegram 155286 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Bolivia<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d64fn1">
                                <p><seg type="summary">Summary: The Department sent the Embassy the
                                        text of a letter from <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> to Banzer concerning consultations
                                        with tin-producing nations over increased stockpile
                                        sales.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                        Foreign Policy File, [no film number]. Confidential;
                                        Immediate. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MDF_1">Meyers</persName> (text received from the <persName corresp="#p_WR_1">White</persName> House on August 6);
                                        cleared by <persName corresp="#p_FJW_1">Fisher</persName> in
                                        ARA/BC and by <persName corresp="#p_IJJ_1">John
                                            Ingersoll</persName> in <gloss target="#t_EBICD_1">EB/ICD</gloss>; approved by <persName corresp="#p_KJ_1">Katz</persName>. Repeated to London. <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>’s June 4 letter is
                                        ibid., Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 749,
                                        Presidential Correspondence, President Banzer, Bolivia,
                                        1971–1974. On September 7, the Department informed Bolivian
                                        Ambassador Valencia that the U.S. Government would begin
                                        sales on September 10. Valencia noted that the U.S.
                                        Government’s action seemed to reflect its sincere desire to
                                        avoid a deleterious impact on the economies of Bolivia and
                                        other tin-producing nations. (Telegram 179280 to La Paz,
                                        September 10; ibid., RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, [no
                                        film number])</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-08-07T16:10:00+00:00">August 7, 1973,
                            1610Z</date>.</dateline>
                        <p>155286. Subject: Letter From the President to President Banzer on Tin
                            Disposals.</p>
                        <p>1. Please pass following letter from the President to President
                            Banzer:</p>
                        <p>Quote August 6, 1973</p>
                        <p>Quote Dear Mr. President</p>
                        <p>Quote As you will recall from my letter of June 4, 1973, following
                            consultations with Bolivia and other tin producing countries I
                            authorized the sale of 1,500 tons of tin from the United States
                            strategic stockpile during the last month of fiscal year 1973 and the
                            sale of an additional 5,000 tons during the first six months of fiscal
                            year 1974. Demand for this tin has been almost unprecedented. The 1,500
                            tons sold without difficulty and the 5,000 tons, which we anticipated
                            selling over a six-month period, was disposed of within the first
                            fifteen days of July.</p>
                        <pb facs="0239" n="187" xml:id="pg_187"/>
                        <p>Quote Despite these prompt sales, tin market prices have continued to
                            rise, reaching record highs on both the London and New York markets.
                            Indeed, many observers believe prices at the current levels, if
                            sustained, will hasten the substitution of tin-free steel and other
                            metals for tinplate, a development that would threaten the interests of
                            producing countries.</p>
                        <p>Quote Because of these developments and because the United States has an
                            interest in market stability, I have directed the Department of State to
                            begin consultations with all tin producing countries regarding a further
                            increase in our disposal program for the current fiscal year. You may be
                            certain as I assured you in my earlier letter, that in directing this
                            undertaking I wish to avoid any undue disruption of the world market, as
                            well as any action that would harm Bolivian interests or damage
                            relations between our two countries. I can also assure you that we will
                            begin an immediate review of our revised disposal program, should tin
                            prices drop precipitously from their present record levels.</p>
                        <p>Quote I continue to look forward to meeting you and Mrs. Banzer in
                            Washington later this year.</p>
                        <p>Quote With warm personal regards, Sincerely, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Richard Nixon</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>Quote General <persName corresp="#p_BSH_1">Hugo Bánzer Suárez</persName>,
                            President of Bolivia, La Paz, Bolivia Unquote</p>
                        <p>2. Cable Immediate when message delivered as Dept intends begin
                            consultations with producer Embassy reps on Aug 8.</p>
                        <p>3. Original of President’s letter follows by pouch.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>Rogers</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>