<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-05-09T15:55:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-05-09T15:55:00-05:00" n="73" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                        <head>73. Telegram 3254 From the Embassy in Bolivia to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d73fn1">
                                <p><seg type="summary">Summary: President Banzer, Minister of the
                                        Interior Pereda, and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SWP_1">Stedman</persName> discussed threats to Bolivia’s
                                        external and internal security.</seg></p>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central
                                        Foreign Policy File, D750164–0238. Confidential. Repeated to
                                        Lima, Santiago, and <gloss target="#t_USCINCSO_1">USCINCSO</gloss>. The May 8 conversation between
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SWP_1">Stedman</persName> and
                                        Banzer is reported in telegram 3201 from La Paz, May 8.
                                        (Ibid.) On May 7, the Bolivian Cabinet required Gulf Oil
                                        Company to state if it had passed bribes to Bolivian
                                        officials between 1966 and 1972, and it requested a U.S.
                                        Government investigation. (Telegram 3191 from La Paz, May 8;
                                        ibid., D750162–0178) The September 1974 Banzer-<persName corresp="#p_RWB_1">Rosson</persName> conversation is
                                        summarized in <ref target="#d69">Document
                                    69</ref>.</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>La Paz</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-05-09T20:55:00+00:00">May 9, 1975,
                            2055Z</date>.</dateline>
                        <p>3254. Subj: Bolivian Concerns About Peruvian Arms Build-Up and Internal
                            Security Problems.</p>
                        <p>1. During conversation with President Banzer on May 8 about alleged Gulf
                            Oil Co. bribery, he said he wished to review a deep-seated concern about
                            Peruvian arms build-up and internal security problems affecting Bolivia.
                            Present during the conversation was the Minister of the Interior, who at
                            the moment was also acting Foreign Minister.</p>
                        <p>2. President Banzer said that he has received continuing reports of
                            sizeable quantities of military equipment arriving at the Port of
                            Matarani. He said that information is reaching him from highly reputable
                            officials of Bolivian state entities who have visited Matarani seeking
                            to expedite delayed shipments of needed materials for their operations
                            in Bolivia. These officials have stated that ships not carrying military
                            equipment are being delayed and that dock facilities are being
                            pre-empted for delivery of Soviet tanks, ammunition, and other military
                            equipment. President said that the Peruvian authorities in the Matarani
                            area are telling inquirers that much of this equipment is destined for
                            La Paz so as to reduce any Peruvian concerns about an arms build-up in
                            their own country.</p>
                        <p>3. President Banzer said that continuing reports of sizeable arms
                            delivery to Peru, particularly in the southern area, is a matter of
                            great concern to him. He is worried, he reported, about the possibility
                            of conflict between Peru and Chile and also about possible use of
                            military equipment across Bolivia’s borders. He said he would like to
                            turn to his other concern which involves the concentration of
                            extremists, terrorists, and Communist forces on Bolivia. He asked the
                            Minister of Interior to elaborate.</p>
                        <p>4. The Minister of Interior said that the recent successes of Communist
                            forces in Indo-China have inspired groups such as the <gloss target="#t_ERP_1">ERP</gloss> and the ELN to consider that they are
                            engaged in a winning cause. They <pb facs="0258" n="206" xml:id="pg_206"/> therefore are encouraged to take more aggressive action, especially
                            against countries like Bolivia which are calm but weak. He noted that
                            Bolivia has frontiers with five Latin American nations and is unable to
                            adequately cover those borders to prevent infiltration. The Minister
                            went on to note that a recent meeting in Lisbon of ELN type groups has
                            resulted in decisions to move against Bolivia and Paraguay. He said that
                            information received from Argentine intelligence sources is that some
                            fifty armed guerrillas are being prepared to penetrate into Bolivia. He
                            observed that another motivation for picking on Bolivia was the
                            continued bitterness in the extreme left forces about the liquidation of
                            Che Guevara here. The Minister said that the problem of Bolivia’s
                            internal security is or should be a concern for its neighbors and also
                            for the US. He expressed the hope that it might be possible to have
                            continuing conversations with us on these problems with the aim of
                            developing some form of common strategy.</p>
                        <p>5. President Banzer then said that the two concerns, i.e. Peru and
                            internal security, were constant preoccupations of his and referred me
                            back to the conversation in his office with <gloss target="#t_USCINCSO_1">USCINCSO</gloss> General <persName corresp="#p_RWB_1">Rosson</persName> in September 1974. He said that
                            the Bolivian population gives little or no support to extremist
                            elements, but with a new aggressiveness on the part of those hostile to
                            Bolivia, it is possible that inroads in some areas might be made. He
                            said that Bolivia needs either to increase its internal security
                            capability through delivery of military equipment or to accelerate
                            economic development activities. At one point he noted that possibly
                            both courses of action need to be pursued. He noted that the regime has
                            the full support of all elements of the Armed Forces and of the
                            population. He said that he had recently dispatched the chiefs of staff
                            of the three Armed Forces around the country and that their report
                            confirmed the solidarity of adherence to the Banzer regime. He said that
                            if it were in the interest of the US to help Chile, one way is to
                            provide assistance to Bolivia. For example, he said Bolivia’s production
                            of foodstuffs could be expanded greatly and thus Chile could be fed from
                            a neighboring country rather than having to import food from longer
                            distances as it does now. He also said that in relation to the arms
                            build-up in Peru some additional military assistance to Bolivia, which
                            is now more closely attuned to the ideology of Chile, would help keep
                            the relative strengths in nearer balance. While on the subject of Chile,
                            he said that while he is hoping that some progress can be made toward a
                            solution of the access to the sea, he can only state at the moment that
                            Chile has shown a disposition to discuss possibilities.</p>
                        <p>6. President concluded the talk by repeating what he had said earlier in
                            the discussion about the Gulf Oil Co. matter—that he considered the
                            bilateral relations between Bolivia and the US as excellent. He <pb facs="0259" n="207" xml:id="pg_207"/> said he even detected that
                            they had improved in recent months. While he did not clearly or
                            specifically ask me for anything, it is quite clear that he is repeating
                            his firmly held view that the US should seriously consider expanding
                            military and economic assistance here for the benefit of Bolivia, the
                            deterring of tension between Chile and Peru, and to avoid potential
                            build-up of hostile elements in what he considers to be a strategic
                            geographic area. I intend to dig further into the basis for the Minister
                            of Interior’s analysis, either directly or indirectly. It may be that we
                            can dispel some of the pessimistic attitudes by offering differing and
                            more profound analysis of currents in neighboring countries and within
                            terrorist groups. The conversation with the President and the Minister
                            of the Interior did reveal that both are seriously concerned but that
                            some of their preoccupation may be based upon their isolation,
                            frustration, and weakness. I have no recommendations for new or
                            different action by the US at this time and will report further if
                            additional information or observations are developed by me or members of
                            the Embassy staff.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_SWP_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_SWP_1">Stedman</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>