<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-07-11T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-07-11T11:00:00-05:00" n="170" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                        <head>170. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Jordan</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d170fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 785.00/7–1158. Top Secret; Priority. Repeated to Baghdad and
                                London.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Amman</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-07-11T18:00:00+02:00"><hi rend="italic">July 11,
                                        1958—6 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>65. Re Deptel 68.<note n="2" xml:id="d170fn2"><ref target="#d169"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi></ref>.</note> Following is Embassy
                                [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                declassified</hi>] Amman evaluation domestic security situation
                            after events described Embtel 47.<note n="3" xml:id="d170fn3">See <ref target="#d169fn2">footnote 2, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>.</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0330" n="298" xml:id="pg_298"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>A conspiracy exists in the army among group non-Beduin officers
                                sympathetic to aims of Baath party of Jordan. Although aims of the
                                conspiracy are reported as assassination of Hussein and creating
                                    pro-<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> Government, a number of
                                conspirators appear primarily interested in more limited objectives,
                                personal advancement. A cause of disaffection among these officers
                                is precedence given Beduin elements by loyal but not brilliant
                                    <gloss target="#t_CGS1">CGS</gloss> Habis Majali. Non-Beduins
                                have looked chiefly to <persName corresp="#p_SMGS1">Major General
                                    Sadiq Ash-Shara</persName> for leadership. With <persName corresp="#p_SMGS1">Shara</persName>’s rustication to assignment
                                in Baghdad, non-Beduin group has been left at least temporarily
                                without a patron. Embassy has not yet received conclusive evidence
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SMGS1">Shara</persName>’s complicity plot
                                overthrow monarchy.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>According to the military attaché, the army will remain loyal.
                                    <gloss target="#t_CGS1">CGS</gloss><persName corresp="#p_Majali1">Majali</persName> is faithful to Hussein,
                                has courage to take necessary steps insure royal control, and
                                principal weapon in army, the first armored brigade, is controlled
                                by Bani Sakhr tribe which strongly supports King. Dissident elements
                                in army unlikely to strike as long as armor not under their
                                control.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>In opinion [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                    declassified</hi>] military attaché political direction of
                                conspiracy comes from outside army and undoubtedly from <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, probably through Colonel Serra in
                                Syria. There does not yet appear to be organization in Jordan
                                capable of carrying out a coup d’etat on its own and without foreign
                                support and direction. Present regime’s policy of suppression
                                opposition elements by arrest, curfew, censorship and other
                                Draconian means has paid off to extent that opposition, including
                                subversives, not yet able organize.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In broader sense, however, situation is grave because Jordan more
                                susceptible now than at any other time in past year to threat of
                                internal disturbances brought on by <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. Condition results from prolonged crisis in Lebanon
                                which could easily produce sympathetic reaction in Jordan in form
                                extremist nationalist demonstrations, mob disturbances.
                                Psychological effect of possible defeat <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> discourages loyalists and, conversely, gives
                                extremists opposition elements first opportunity take heart since
                                April 1957.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>[<hi rend="italic">5½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>]
                                Most salient character Hussein is physical courage, of which he has
                                almost too much. With guidance shrewd heads, such as Rifai, Hussein
                                likely persevere against opponents.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_HKJ1">HKJ</gloss> should be urged proceed
                                quickly with investigation of conspiracy releasing those against
                                whom there is insufficient evidence and prosecuting guilty without
                                delay. Also, <gloss target="#t_HKJ1">HKJ</gloss> should be
                                encouraged reorganize intelligence and security services to insure
                                that responsible officials outside palace have accurate and timely
                                information on subversive activities. Provision of US economic aid
                                on spot basis, such as drought alleviation through surplus wheat
                                shipments, has important effect in minimizing threat to regime.
                                Machinery must be created for <pb facs="0331" n="299" xml:id="pg_299"/> rapid transmission aid to Jordan when
                                necessary (A) to overcome economic crisis and (B) give needed
                                support Jordan security force in terms its internal security
                                function.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Beyond this, however, there is little immediate action US can take other
                            than give moral support Hussein-RIFAI. Solution Lebanese (or better yet,
                            Palestine) situation would have more benign effect than any action we
                            could take inside Jordan.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WTK1"><hi rend="strong">Wright</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>