<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-03-18T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-03-18T09:00:00-05:00" n="376" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d376">
                        <head>376. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Lebanon</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d376fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 783A.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/3–1860.
                                Confidential; Priority.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Beirut</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-03-18T16:00:00+02:00"><hi rend="italic">March 18,
                                        1960—4 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>2947. Department pass Defense. This morning President <persName corresp="#p_CGF2">Chehab</persName> made a direct personal appeal
                            for affirmative action on Lebanon’s long-standing request for a modest
                            amount of military aid.</p>
                        <p>Country team telegrams are too numerous to cite but briefly a seven-man
                            survey team from US Army European Command arrived here May 8 last year
                            and completed its survey June 17, estimating what Lebanese Army actually
                            needed for spare parts, ammunition and vehicles which ARMA valued at $2,
                            300,000. Subsequently country team refined this figure to a
                            recommendation that hardware and an item of training for Lebanese
                            officers in European Theater of US be furnished in a total amount of $1,
                            440,000. This figure was later reduced by country team to an ultimate
                            bedrock request for $900, 000 including training.</p>
                        <p>Thus, for not quite a year Lebanese Army and President <persName corresp="#p_CGF2">Chehab</persName> have been hoping that as result
                            of ordnance team survey and country team recommendations some modest
                            military assistance for Lebanon would win approval in a Presidential
                            determination. Of course we have not divulged any figures to
                            Lebanese.</p>
                        <p>This morning President <persName corresp="#p_CGF2">Chehab</persName>, in
                            discussing political situation which country confronts when nation-wide
                            parliamentary elections are held in May, said “In such a country as this
                            with so many different factions and basic problem of Moslem-Christian
                            differences, Army is real ultimate guarantor of independence of this
                            republic.”</p>
                        <p>While President did not wish speeding of munitions, spare parts and
                            vehicles to assist Lebanese Army in maintaining internal security for
                            elections, he did make valid point that morale of armed forces would be
                            very much improved if they knew there were some aid forthcoming from
                            US.</p>
                        <p>President said that last week he had once more requested Chief of Staff
                            to inquire as to possibility of securing US radar (cf. <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>s 2661 and 2721). He said he would
                            welcome a training mission to assist Lebanese in learning to operate
                            this equipment as well as training of younger officers in US.</p>
                        <p>President emphasized defensive character not only of radar installations
                            but of whole philosophy of his army. As reported in a separate telegram,
                            he once more repeated what he had told me two weeks ago that, in event
                            of an Arab-Israeli war, Lebanon would not participate.</p>
                        <pb facs="0681" n="649" xml:id="pg_649"/>
                        <p>Service attachés and country team concur in this message. With all
                            respect, but with measured insistence, we request a favorable
                            Presidential determination.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_MCRM1"><hi rend="strong">McClintock</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>