<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>393. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and
                    South Asian Affairs (Rountree) to the ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recn8b1d7iCOsszeq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100445"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum products</term>
                    <term ref="receYZXmZSuptfeyg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">PL 480</term>
                    <term ref="recGxSKiAmmOVqBc0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90005695"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Drought</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recKkhgppZ5fwGQoV" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Development assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-03-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-03-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="393"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d393">
                <head>393. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and
                    South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWM1" type="from"
                    >Rountree</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d393fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Conference Files: Lot 64 D 560, CF 1223. Secret. Drafted in <gloss
                            target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss> by
                            <persName corresp="#p_LWC2">Lakeland</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_RSW1">Rockwell</persName> and cleared with <gloss
                            target="#t_E1">E</gloss>, W/MSC, <gloss target="#t_H1">H</gloss>,
                        Defense, and <gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss>. Sent to <persName
                            corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> through <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                            >Dillon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MRD2"
                        >Murphy</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-03-14">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 14, 1959</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Policy Line and Tactics in Discussions during Visit of King Hussein of
                        Jordan (March 23–26)<note n="2" xml:id="d393fn2">Following a State visit to
                                <persName>Taiwan</persName>, Hussein planned to spend 5 days in
                            Hawaii (March 17–21) and then proceed via San Francisco to Washington,
                            where he would remain from March 23 through 28. No official functions
                            were planned for the King after March 26. Thereafter he planned to tour
                            the United States for 3 weeks, departing from New York on April 17 for a
                            brief visit to England and the continent before returning to
                            Jordan.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0720" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/>
                <p>Although the forthcoming visit of King Hussein of Jordan is to be unofficial and
                    we have made it clear to the Jordanians that we shall not expect to engage in
                    formal negotiations on this occasion, the King and his Prime Minister,
                        <persName>Samir Rifa</persName>’i, have been assured that there would be an
                    opportunity for discussions with the President, you and other officials of the
                    Department while they are in Washington. The schedule for these discussions is
                    the subject of a separate memorandum,<note n="3" xml:id="d393fn3">Dated March
                        11. (Department of State, Central Files, 785.11/3–1159)</note> and
                    individual briefing papers on specific topics are being prepared. The coming
                    visit may well have a crucial effect on U.S.-Jordan relations, however, inasmuch
                    as we can anticipate a concerted effort by King Hussein and his adroit Prime
                    Minister to extract from the U.S. assurances that we are firmly committed to the
                    proposition that the continued existence of Jordan as presently constituted is
                    vital to the maintenance of the Western position in the Near East. Prime
                    Minister Rifa’i has on several occasions asserted to our Charge in Amman that he
                    views such an assurance from the U.S. Government as essential if he is to
                    continue at the head of the Government, and has made it clear that in his mind
                    such an assurance would mean a continuing commitment to Jordan of military and
                    financial assistance significantly above the present substantial level, as well
                    as political and diplomatic support for the present regime in its self-envisaged
                    role as the leader of an anti-Communist and anti-<persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> Arab nationalism.</p>
                <p>It is not possible for us to satisfy the desires and ambitions of the King and
                    Rifa’i, and it is important that we obviate any possible misunderstanding on
                    that score, while at the same time avoiding too great a disappointment to our
                    visitors (with a possibility of highly undesirable repercussions). <gloss
                        target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> therefore considers it of the utmost importance
                    that there be clear understanding within the Government of the line of policy to
                    be followed and agreement on the tactics to be pursued in the forthcoming talks
                    with the Jordanians. To this end, the following recommendations are offered for
                    your urgent consideration.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Our general objective in discussions with King Hussein and <persName>Samir
                            Rifa</persName>’i should be to encourage the ending of Jordan’s
                        isolation from its Arab neighbors and cautiously to explore possible means
                        of lessening its almost total financial and political dependence on the U.S.
                        (and, to some degree, the U.K.).</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Our tactics (to be reflected in position papers) should be designed to
                        further our general objective without provoking a reaction of desperation or
                        despair, which could possibly lead to the King’s abdicating without making
                        provision for an orderly change of regime, or, alternatively, to his
                        embarking on military adventures in Syria.</item>
                    <pb facs="0721" n="689" xml:id="pg_689"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In keeping with the foregoing, we should be prepared to employ the
                        following tactical line vis-à-vis Hussein and Rifa’i:<note n="4"
                            xml:id="d393fn4">
                            <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> initialed his approval of
                            recommendations 3a–g on March 17.</note>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>We should stress our continuing interest in the welfare of Jordan
                                and its people, pointing to the considerable aid we have already
                                extended as evidence of this.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>We should point out the legislative and constitutional situation
                                which prevents our making long-term aid commitments or giving
                                indefinite political undertakings. We are making a special and
                                    unique<note n="5" xml:id="d393fn5">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> inserted by hand
                                    the words “and unique.”</note> exception to established USG
                                practice by telling Jordan what we plan to provide in aid for <gloss
                                    target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1960, prior to Congressional
                                authorization of the necessary funds. This reveals our intention to
                                continue to be helpful to Jordan.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>We should firmly make clear that in our thinking about future
                                    assistance to Jordan we do not envisage the U.S. contribution as
                                    being substantially above the present level.* In U.S. <gloss
                                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1959 this is expected to amount
                                    to $38.23 million direct budgetary support, $1.9 million
                                    technical assistance, $5 million emergency assistance for
                                    procurement and delivery of petroleum products and related
                                    equipment, and $5.3 million PL 480 commodities (at market
                                    value). For U.S. <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 60 aid $40.5
                                    million for budgetary support and up to $5 million in PL 480
                                    commodities for drought relief have already been offered <gloss
                                        target="#t_HKJ1">HKJ</gloss>. In addition we plan to carry
                                    out a program of economic development and technical assistance
                                    in an amount to be determined following Congressional action on
                                    the U.S. <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 60 MSA program. We
                                    consider the level of U.S. <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 60
                                    budget, development and technical assistance generous, given our
                                    expectations of the likely level of U.S. <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                                        >FY</gloss> 60 <gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss> funds and
                                    world-wide demands upon these funds. It should be indicated to
                                    the Jordanians that in view of the magnitude of U.S. assistance
                                    it is important that prior consultations with U.S.
                                    representatives take place concerning Jordan’s annual budget
                                    levels. We would also expect to be consulted about any
                                    contemplated activities by the <gloss target="#t_HKJ1"
                                        >HKJ</gloss> which might materially affect the budget
                                    level.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> Figures given herein are for U.S.
                                    fiscal years. In detailed discussion with the Jordanians it is
                                    necessary to talk in terms of the Jordan fiscal year, which is
                                    from April 1 to March 31.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>We should say that, while we do not envisage any increase in our
                                    <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 60 planned special assistance
                                to Jordan for budget support and economic development, we are
                                prepared to give sympathetic consideration to additional PL 480
                                assistance, above that to which we are already committed, if
                                Jordan’s drought situation so requires. We should also be prepared
                                to be somewhat flexible, in view of Jordan’s acute budget problems,
                                as regards the division of available special assistance funds
                                between direct budget support and economic development (e.g., we
                                have already promised $40.5 million for budget assistance and would
                                be willing to consider making available an additional amount for
                                this purpose by transferring a portion of such economic development
                                funds as might be allocated to Jordan following <pb facs="0722"
                                    n="690" xml:id="pg_690"/> Congressional appropriations). We
                                cannot, of course, specify the amount of development assistance nor
                                of additional budget aid which may be anticipated.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>As our past aid activities indicate, we are interested in
                                furthering Jordan’s economic development. In this regard, the <gloss
                                    target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss> has received additional technical
                                data which it requested on the Jordan Phosphate Mines Co., and we
                                hope that this project<note n="7" xml:id="d393fn7">The text of
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>’s memorandum
                                    read at this point: “can be given sympathetic.” <persName
                                        corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> crossed out those words
                                    and wrote in: “will be ready for.”</note> will be ready for
                                consideration by the <gloss target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss> Board of
                                Directors in the very near future. The <gloss target="#t_DLF1"
                                    >DLF</gloss> is prepared to consider other applications which
                                meet <gloss target="#t_DLF1">DLF</gloss> criteria.</item>
                            <label>f.</label>
                            <item>We should state that we are prepared to implement the
                                recommendation of the Risden report, phasing the program over a
                                period of three years.<note n="8" xml:id="d393fn8">A marginal
                                    notation at this point, in <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1"
                                        >Herter</persName>’s hand, reads: “beginning in <gloss
                                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> ’60”.</note> (The Risden report
                                recommended a $12.8 million program of military aid, largely in the
                                form of new military equipment to be procured principally in the
                                U.K.) Our willingness to do this, would depend upon Jordan’s
                                willingness to accept the Risden assumptions regarding the
                                limitation of force levels and other measures, such as the
                                elimination of obsolete equipment, designed to hold recurring costs
                                to a minimum.</item>
                            <label>g.</label>
                            <item>As the discussions develop, we should seek to implant and
                                cultivate in the King’s mind the concept of a gradual and orderly
                                rapprochement with the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and other
                                Arab neighbors, making it clear that the U.S. is not thinking of
                                abandoning Jordan to <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s
                                tender mercies but would be prepared to help explore the
                                possibilities for an understanding with the <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                                    >UAR</gloss> which would serve Jordan’s interests.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
