<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-09-09T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-09-09T11:00:00-05:00" n="410" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d410">
                        <head>410. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Jordan</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d410fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, White House Office Files,
                                Project “Clean Up”, Jordan. Secret; Niact; [<hi rend="italic">distribution indicator not declassified</hi>]. Received at 4:56
                                p.m.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Amman</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-09-09T18:00:00+02:00"><hi rend="italic">September 9,
                                        1960—6 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>347. Reference Embtel 339. <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_JSC1">Johnston</persName> saw King Hussein
                            evening of eighth as planned. I have seen <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Ambassador’s report to <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> [<hi rend="italic">2½ lines of source text not
                                declassified</hi>]. Sir Charles’ impression was that King heard him
                            out but <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Ambassador not sure what
                            impression he had made at end of talk. Sir Charles told me that for
                            first time since he has been in Jordan he is “shaken” by present course
                            of events.</p>
                        <p>I obtained appointment with King 1:00 p.m. on ninth directly before
                                <persName>Spinelli</persName> also saw His Majesty. I told King I
                            had come to see him on matter of considerable concern not only to myself
                            personally but <pb facs="0769" n="737" xml:id="pg_737"/> also to my
                            Government. We had heard reports concerning extensive troop movements
                            from Jordan along Syrian frontier that appeared particularly disturbing
                            at this time. I had come to His Majesty personally without authorization
                            from my Government because USG had not had sufficient time to react to
                            news of border build-up, but I said we would appreciate any
                            clarification he could give us concerning present situation.</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (15 lines of source text) not
                                declassified</hi>] I said that in last 10 days I had had Jordan’s
                            problem constantly in mind. I had tried to visualize all possible
                            actions and solutions. Natural impulse was certainly to strike out in
                            fury. No one could blame Jordan for anger after series of incidents of
                            last ten days. At same time, if Jordan acted out of emotion in present
                            affair and tried to use forces across border, I personally could see
                            only blow-up of disastrous proportions ahead. [<hi rend="italic">5½
                                lines of source text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (10 lines of source text) not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>I continued that more I had thought about this problem the more it came
                            back to solution through channels of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.
                            Speaking personally I saw no helpful role for any individual third
                            country in this affair. Equitable solution required prestige of some
                            supra-national body and only organization which fitted this description
                            was <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. King indicated he had already
                            assured me Jordan would take no precipitate action before informing his
                            close friends US and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>. I said I very
                            much appreciated this reassurance, especially at this time and could His
                            Majesty assure me that Jordan would rely on <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action before taking matters into its own hands? He [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                            assured me that Jordan was moving “step by step” in complete
                            consultation with <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and he was shortly
                            going to see Ambassador <persName>Spinelli</persName> who, he supposed,
                            would be talking to him about same problem.<note n="2" xml:id="d410fn2">Spinelli subsequently indicated that his conversation with Hussein
                                had run along lines similar to the conversation which <persName corresp="#p_KE4">Kocher</persName> had with the King. <persName corresp="#p_KE4">Kocher</persName>,
                                    <persName>Spinelli</persName>, and U.K. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JSC1">Johnston</persName> agreed that the best
                                course to follow was to seek and use messages of concern from the
                                United States, the United Kingdom, and Secretary-General
                                Hammarskjöld in an effort to restrain military action on the part of
                                Jordan. (Telegram 348 from Amman, September 9; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>; included in <ref target="frus1958-60v11mSupp">the
                                    microfiche supplement</ref>)</note> In parting I again thanked
                            King for his reassurances.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Like <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                            Ambassador I am not sure what impression this démarche made on King. He
                            received my comments attentively but I could feel underneath a sense of
                            strain and tension. Since he remains highly emotional over whole series
                            of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>-inspired incidents, I would
                            imagine he has not been preceptive to pressures of those favoring across
                            border action.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KE4"><hi rend="strong">Kocher</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>