<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>9. Telegram From the Embassy in Lebanon to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-03-05T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-03-05T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recRS4Fh2wkyRhAa5" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87002273"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Sunni</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-03-05T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-03-05T11:00:00-05:00" n="9"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                <head>9. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Lebanon</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d9fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 783A.00/3–558. Top Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Beirut</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-03-05T18:00:00+02:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 5, 1958—6 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2964. Pursuant Deptel 3375<note n="2" xml:id="d9fn2">
                        <ref target="#d8">
                            <hi rend="italic">Supra.</hi>
                        </ref>
                    </note> I called on President <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> this
                    morning and made oral representation outlined paragraph 1 reference telegram. I
                    said I had personally listened to some hundred or more Lebanese personalities,
                    each with his own slant on presidential problem, but had kept my own counsel. My
                    government agreed time had now come to ask <persName corresp="#p_CC7"
                        >Chamoun</persName> himself for his estimate of situation.</p>
                <p>President said that, although he “had not quite yet made up his mind”, he felt on
                    balance he would have to stand for reelection.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> then went through process of
                    elimination, ticking off one by one potential candidates. He said, of those who
                    were outside Parliament, it was clear Joseph Hitti did not have sufficient
                    following to be considered as successful candidate, nor did Jawad Boulos, a
                    pleasant man with no political drawing power. General <persName
                        corresp="#p_CGF2">Chehab</persName> was possibility, but there were two
                    objections to him: (1) he did not want the office; (2) to bring military leader
                    to presidency would establish dangerous precedent and might involve Lebanese
                    army in politics in future. In fact, only candidate outside of Parliament who
                        <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> thought might have serious
                    chance as contender for presidency was Bechara El-Khoury. This he thought would
                    be disaster for country as <pb facs="0047" n="15" xml:id="pg_15"/> Bechara
                    El-Khoury had revealed during last term extent to which he and his family had
                    profited by corruption and, furthermore, he had given himself too much to
                    external forces outside Lebanon.</p>
                <p>Within Parliament, <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> discussed
                    prospects of two Edde brothers, Pierre and Raymond, indicating he thought
                    neither could muster sufficient strength in Chamber to get elected. Another
                    possibility was <persName>Selim Lahoud</persName> “but he had many enemies” and
                    clearly, in <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName>’s opinion, did not
                    have sufficient votes to muster majority.</p>
                <p>Ergo, by this he came to conclusion only politician who could lead country and
                    evaluate its present foreign policies was himself.</p>
                <p>I stressed our hope, because we wished to see Lebanon remain independent and
                    because new currents were swirling in Arab world, that whatever happened in
                    elections result would be to draw various elements in Lebanon into greater union
                    and not to emphasize divisive possibilities which were latent in Lebanon.</p>
                <p>President said his own estimate of his popular strength was 90 percent of
                    Christians, 60 percent of Sunni Moslems. If this estimate is correct, it would
                    mean his popular support would be 69 percent of population.</p>
                <p>I next inquired <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName>’s opinion re
                    chances of civil strife if he should succeed himself, recalling what had
                    happened to Bechara El-Khoury, who had also changed Constitution and had been
                    ousted from second term. <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> said
                    conditions were different. Bechara El-Khoury had been discredited because of
                    corruption, whereas his own regime could not be accused similarly. Although
                    there might be troubles, he was calmly confident any disturbances could be
                    handled, and seemed to have no fear of discord fomented from outside—e.g.,
                    Egyptian and Syrian.</p>
                <p>When I probed <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> re theory (cf. Embtel
                        2893)<note n="3" xml:id="d9fn3">In telegram 2893 from Beirut, February 27,
                            <persName corresp="#p_MCRM1">McClintock</persName> reported on British
                        Ambassador Middleton’s assessment of what he saw as the dangerous political
                        situation in Lebanon. Middleton suggested that a compromise solution to the
                        presidential problem might be to amend the constitution to extend <persName
                            corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName>’s term by 2 years, to afford time to
                        groom a suitable successor. <persName corresp="#p_MCRM1"
                            >McClintock</persName> observed that Middleton’s proposed solution was
                        based upon pragmatism rather than principle, but might mitigate the venom of
                        a presidential campaign. (Department of State, Central Files,
                        783A.00/2–2758)</note> some compromise might be found by limiting new
                    presidential term to 2 or 4 years, President was noncommital, but throughout our
                    conversation referred to reelection in terms of six years.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName>, already envisaging second term in
                    office, said he was quite prepared to be clement to opposition and he would be
                    willing early on to indicate readiness to bury hatchet. He explicitly said he
                    felt an opposition was essential to Lebanon and he would be glad to have members
                    of opposition in new government.</p>
                <pb facs="0048" n="16" xml:id="pg_16"/>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>] both
                        <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MC9"
                        >Malik</persName> might feel they could whistle up Sixth Fleet any time they
                    found themselves in trouble, I recalled assurances given as authorized Deptel
                        3000<note n="4" xml:id="d9fn4">See <ref target="#d5fn3">footnote 3, Document
                            5</ref>.</note> re assistance in preserving internal security and said I
                    had indicated to <persName corresp="#p_MC9">Malik</persName> my feeling means
                    must be tailored to ends. It was my belief if there were riots or civil strife
                    in Lebanon these should be put down by Lebanese themselves. It would be, in my
                    opinion, prejudicial to Lebanon’s own interest if we should be asked to land
                    Marines, as this would be portrayed in Arab world and elsewhere as subjection of
                    Lebanon to an outside power. <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName>
                    replied he was in complete agreement. He said only time he had discussed
                    possibility of deploying Sixth Fleet was when Jordan not Lebanon was in danger.
                    I am sure he got point I desired to make; namely, that US military strength in
                    Mediterranean should not be used in forthcoming Lebanese political turmoil.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusions:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> has decided to amend
                            constitution and succeed himself for second 6-year term.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName>, consummate politician
                            whose access to political intelligence is undoubtedly greater than that
                            of his rivals, is clearly confident of his popular support and of
                            consequent Parliamentary approval, both in amending constitution and in
                            his reelection.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> did not ask for US backing
                            but obviously expects that, if he succeeds himself and continues same
                            foreign policy, he will continue to receive US support.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Although <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName>’s estimate of
                            percentages his popularity is probably on high side, it is clear to us
                            he can in fact be reelected.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>I have not altered opinion expressed Embtel 2832<note n="5"
                                xml:id="d9fn5">
                                <ref target="#d7">Document 7</ref>.</note> that it would be best for
                                <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName>, Lebanon and US that
                            he step down for time being and permit compromise candidate to assume
                            Presidency and continue his policies. It is certain trouble will ensue
                            when he takes office for second term. On other hand, we cannot very well
                            dictate to <persName corresp="#p_CC7">Chamoun</persName> in this
                            situation, nor can we against this opposition elect another President.
                            In consequence,</item>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>US, given this problem in political arithmetic, can come to only one
                            answer: We should support <persName corresp="#p_CC7"
                            >Chamoun</persName>.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>If Department concurs this analysis, would appreciate early word in order garner
                    early kudos.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MCRM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">McClintock</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
