<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 180.Mr. Sargent to Mr. Frelinghuysen.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d180</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">180</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1883-02-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1883-02-26T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274" lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183" lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1883-02-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1883-02-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                <head>No. 180.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Sargent</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-02-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 26, 1883</date>.
                            (Received March 13.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 112.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The case of [Car] William Scheibert presents
                        such peculiar features that I beg to lay it before you, and to ask for
                        definite instructions in case you think it proper that I should further
                        intervene in it. That of the Staarbach brothers involves much the same
                        considerations, and I group them together.</p>
                <p>On the 20th of December, 1882, Mr. Julius Scheibert, father of William
                        Scheibert, called in person at the legation and stated that he himself
                        emigrated to the United States in 1856, and was there naturalized in 1864.
                        His said son was born in New York, December 22, 1856. The father returned to
                        Germany with his family, including this son, in 1869, where he has since
                        resided.</p>
                <p>The son returned to the United States after three years, and came back here
                        in 1879, and has since resided here. On the 19th of December the son was
                        impressed into the military service.</p>
                <p>Upon this statement, which was the apparent evidence of an extreme case, I
                        addressed a note the same date to Count Hatzfeldt, imperial secretary of
                        state for foreign affairs, in which, after stating the above facts, I
                        urgently requested him to have the case promptly investigated, and, if
                        possible, that the young man should be set free from military service and
                        allowed to return to his parents for the Christmas holidays, and until a
                        definite decision could be arrived at, as I believed him to be an American
                        citizen by virtue of both his birth and his father’s naturalization, and not
                        liable to military service in Germany; and that he had the right of any
                        native-born American citizen to remain quietly in this country.</p>
                <p>On the 28th of December I had a note from Dr. Busch, of the imperial foreign
                        office, in which he assured me that the proper authorities had been
                        instructed to expedite the matter, and the right was reserved to make
                        further answer.</p>
                <p>December 31 Julius Scheibert wrote to me that his son arrived at home on the
                        28th for a fourteen days’ furlough, and praying me to take steps for his
                        entire liberation. To this I replied that I had fully presented his son’s
                        case, and hoped for a speedy and favorable result, which should be at once
                        communicated to him.</p>
                <p>January 17 the father again wrote to me, stating that on the expiration of
                        the furlough the son had returned to his regiment, stating his <pb facs="0413" n="343" xml:id="pg_343"/> own extreme distress, and asking
                        that another furlough be demanded. An answer was sent to this, calculated to
                        soothe his feelings, and induce him to await with patience the somewhat
                        deliberate methods of the foreign office.</p>
                <p>January 28 he again wrote, urging diligent attention to the case.</p>
                <p>January 29 I addressed another note to Count Hatzfeldt, again calling his
                        attention to the fact that Scheibert is an American by birth, who has
                        resided twenty years of his life in America, and that his parents are
                        naturalized citizens of the United States. Inasmuch as I was not aware of
                        any case where a native-born American had been put into the German army
                        against his will, I stated that I could not understand why an exception
                        should be made in this case, or why the simple facts in the case should
                        require so long to investigate and decide upon. As the parents of the young
                        man were much disturbed by their son’s compulsory detention in the army, I
                        requested prompt decision, not doubting that it would result in Scheibert’s
                        release.</p>
                <p>On the 30th I informed the father of my second application to the foreign
                        office on his son’s behalf, and that I hoped soon for a favorable reply.
                        This letter the father misunderstood as an announcement that his son’s
                        release was already ordered, and then writes under date of February 8,
                        expressing his pain that its promise was not fulfilled, and reiterating the
                        reasons for the release.</p>
                <p>On the 9th I called at the foreign office and had an interview with Dr.
                        Busch, under secretary of state in the absence of Count Hatzfeldt, and made
                        urgent representations in the case, asking for speedy decision, and the same
                        day informed the father that I had done so, and that he had misunderstood my
                        previous letter in supposing that it announced his son’s release.</p>
                <p>On the 16th of February I received a note from Count Hatzfeldt requesting me
                        to call the next: day at the foreign office, which I did. Referring to the
                        Scheibert case, he said he wished to be agreeable to me, and do all possible
                        things, but the case presented difficulties.</p>
                <p>He then told me that the father became renaturalized as a Prussian when the
                        son was fifteen years old, and had then all his family in Prussia, and named
                        each of his sons, including [Carl] William, the eldest, in his written
                        application for renaturalization; that this son remained in Germany
                        thereafter until the time came to be of service in the army, when he
                        absented himself for some years, but had now been back for several years,
                        and had married and settled in Prussia and engaged in business here. He
                        thought the son was naturalized a German at the time of the renaturalization
                        of the father, and his acts tended to show that to be his understanding
                        also. He read to me the petition of the father and decree of the court for
                        naturalization, copies of which I inclose, with translations. I asked for
                        copies, and stated that I could say nothing decisive without reflection upon
                        these new facts; that neither I nor my Government wished to ask unreasonable
                        things, and I might refer the whole matter to you for instructions.</p>
                <p>I had, up to that time, acted upon this case upon the theory that Scheibert
                            <hi rend="italic">père</hi> had given me all the facts, and that his son
                        was unquestionably an American citizen, and I did not doubt the father was
                        one also. On the same date I caused the father to be informed that in answer
                        to my inquiries I was informed that his son, during his first visit to
                        Germany in 1869–’72, voluntarily and with the consent of his parents became
                        a German citizen; that he is married here, and to all appearances had taken
                        up his residence here, and wished to know if these statements were
                        correct.</p>
                <pb facs="0414" n="344" xml:id="pg_344"/>
                <p>The answer to this letter was dated on the 20th, and stated that when his son
                        was recently called before the authorities to ascertain his intentions, if
                        he intended to remain in Germany, he replied, “Not if he would have to
                        become a soldier.” He does not admit or deny his or his son’s naturalization
                        as a Prussian, but says the latter is not yet married, though engaged to be.
                        It is possible I misunderstood Count Hatzfeldt in that particular, as he
                        spoke in French. He insists that his son would not wish to remain here if he
                        had to be a soldier, and complains that the advice of the consul at Bremen
                        had deceived his son into security. The consuls are usually quite discreet
                        in turning over such questions to me, as out of their province. * * *</p>
                <p>On the 20th of February I received the accompanying legitimatization papers,
                        and wrote to the father that I had before me copies of the document
                        submitted by him January 20, 1870, to the magistracy of Nienberg, wherein he
                        applied for himself and family, naming each of his children, to be
                        readmitted to Prussian citizenship, stating that he had built a house, and
                        intended to settle down permanently with his family; also of the decree of
                        the magistracy granting the request. Although all my previous letters had
                        been promptly answered, he has never responded to this one.</p>
                <p>Copies of all this correspondence I inclose, that you may have the whole
                        record before you. My examination of cases does not show to me any one in
                        which the same question has arisen, and I respectfully ask your views upon
                        it.</p>
                <p>The following considerations present themselves to me:</p>
                <p>The Scheibert father gave up his American citizenship for himself and family
                        in 1870, naming this son, then sixteen years old, in the document, in which
                        he prayed to be admitted to German citizenship. This son was then with him
                        in Germany. By United States law it is held that where a German becomes
                        naturalized in the United States his minor children who are with him become
                        naturalized by the act also. I do not see how it can be claimed by the
                        United States that the naturalization of a German in the United States
                        naturalizes his minor children, and yet denied that the naturalization of an
                        American in Germany does not naturalize also his minor children here. If the
                        above consideration is not conclusive, as it may well be held to be, there
                        are circumstances of ratification by the son which tend to fortify the view
                        that this man is a German subject. Thus, being naturalized when sixteen
                        years old, he said here two years thereafter, and then went to the United
                        States when eighteen years old, and when twenty-three returned here, where
                        he has since remained four years, engaged himself to be married, and has
                        settled down permanently. When questioned by the authorities if he intended
                        to remain in Prussia permanently, he said he would if he did not have to
                        serve as a soldier. America he might use as a convenience to escape military
                        duty, but he was willing to keep this as his home, only not to render an
                        equivalent of service for the protection which he would receive here. His
                        casual absence in the United States after his naturalization here was not
                        for the purpose of regaining American citizenship, for he does not appear to
                        have taken any steps to that end, but probably to avoid military service,
                        which, as a Prussian, he was liable to. He has devoted himself for the past
                        four years to comfortably settling down here as a German, upon the theory
                        that he could at last do it without performing the duties of one, and if
                        worse came to worse, would plead that he was born elsewhere.</p>
                <p>These acts tend to create an <hi rend="italic">estoppel in pais;</hi> to
                        ratify the act of the father to justify the view of the imperial
                        Government.</p>
                <pb facs="0415" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/>
                <p>The father has two other sons, also born in America, who are serving in the
                        German army without question on his or their part. He suddenly takes
                        exception when this one is called on for that purpose, but conceals from me
                        the fact that he had applied for and obtained renaturalization for himself
                        and family.</p>
                <p>This case illustrates the difficulty that sometimes occurs in getting the
                        truth from the excited or secretive applicants. Like some suitors in law
                        courts who fear to tell their lawyers the truth, these claimants sometimes
                        conceal the essential points in their cases, and lead the legation upon a
                        mistaken track.</p>
                <p>Considering the peculiarities of this case, the strong reason there is for
                        holding young Scheibert a German subject, the little value he places on any
                        possible right from his birth by his avowed desire to live in Prussia if he
                        can escape military service; and believing that indiscriminate demands on
                        the imperial Government for all sorts of pretenders to Americanism should
                        not be insisted on, but only legal and judicious ones made, such as commend
                        themselves to our own judgment and conscience, I have informed Mr. Scheibert
                        that I can do nothing more in his son’s case until I have definite
                        instructions from the State Department, to which I would refer the whole
                        matter.</p>
                <p>The case of the Staarbach brothers involves much the same principles. The
                        young men were born in the United States in 1857 and 1859, respectively,
                        returned with the father to Alsace in 1871, where they have since lived, and
                        the father became renaturalized when the sons were fourteen and twelve years
                        old, respectively.</p>
                <p>The facts in this case were called to my attention by a letter of
                        Consul-General Vogeler at Frankfort, a copy of which is inclosed; and I
                        inclose a copy of my reply to him, wherein all the facts are stated, and the
                        considerations governing the case are fully discussed. In that case I beg to
                        direct attention to what I say about the additional element of difficulty,
                        inasmuch as the youths are residents of Alsace.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. A. SARGENT.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                112.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Count <persName type="from">Hatzfeldt</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Sargent</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign
                                        Office, Berlin</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-02-18">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 18,
                                    1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The undersigned has the honor, referring to the personal interview of
                            yesterday, to inclose herewith for the information of Mr. A. A. Sargent,
                            envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of the United States of
                            America, a copy [of] proceedings at Nienberg on the 20th of January,
                            1870, according to which the American citizen, Julius Scheibert, made
                            application to have Prussian citizenship conferred [on] himself and
                            family, among which was his son William, born December 22, 1856; also
                            the answer referring to the application dated February 3, 1870,
                            conferring the requested naturalization.</p>
                    <p>The undersigned, while remarking that the investigation into the
                            citizenship of “W. Scheibert has not yet been completed, and that
                            consequently he reserves to himself the honor of a further communication
                            as soon as a definite result shall have been reached, avails,
                            &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>HATZFELDT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0416" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                112.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">landmarschal of
                                    Hanover</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">magistrate of
                                    Nienberg</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Royal
                                        Prussian Landmarschal’s Office</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Hanover</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1870-01-31">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 31,
                                1870</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>In answer to the report of the 21st instant, we do hereby consent to the
                            reinstatement of Julius Scheibert, baker and confectioner, of New York,
                            as a Prussian subject, permission having already been given to the said
                            Scheibert to take up his residence in Nienberg by the magistrate. Said
                            Scheibert is to be informed of this in our name.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>LEIPZIGER.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Nienberg</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1870-02-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 3,
                                1870</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>A copy of the foregoing is herewith transmitted to you in lieu of any
                            special reply to your written application of the 20th of last month.</p>
                    <p>The magistrate:</p>
                    <closer>[Signature.]</closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>To Mr. Julius <hi rend="smallcaps">Scheibert</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Baker, Present</hi>.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                                112.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Application of J. Scheibert to become a German
                                citizen</hi>.</head>
                    <p>Done at the magistracy of Nienberg, January 20, 1870.</p>
                    <p>There appears before us Julius Scheibert, baker and confectioner, and
                            deposes upon proper examination as follows:</p>
                    <p>I am a son of August Scheibert, farmer, who is still living, of Broessow,
                            in the district of Prenzlau, in the jurisdiction of Potsdam, born on the
                            2d December, 1833, in Broessow. In the year 1856 I emigrated to America
                            and settled down in New York, where I lived until my return to Germany.
                            In New York I was married to Ernestine Denker, of Nienberg; from this
                            marriage there issued seven children: William, born December 22, 1856;
                            Henry, born December 19, 1858; John, born December 15, 1860; Francisca,
                            born January 8, 1862; Johanna, born December 31, 1864; Julius, born
                            October 19, 1866; Christian, born May 1, 1869.</p>
                    <p>I can prove these statements by certificates of baptism, or perhaps
                            correct any misstatements as to the proper dates by exhibiting— <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>A citizen paper, dated New York, June 8, 1864, which proves me
                                    to be a naturalized citizen of the United States of
                                    America.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>A passport of June 22, 1869, identifying me as an American
                                    citizen.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>[On the part of the magistracy, these statements, after a careful
                            examination of the papers, are pronounced to be correct.]</p>
                    <p>I left the Prussian Monarchy in the year 1856, without a permission to
                            emigrate; but I can prove by the exhibition of a certificate dated
                            Prenzlau, August 28, 1855, that I reported for duty and was placed in
                            the army reserves by the royal department of the Ersatz commission.</p>
                    <p>[On the part of the magistracy this is corroborated.]</p>
                    <p>If my withdrawal from the Prussian territory without permission to
                            emigrate be a punishable offense according to laws then in force, it has
                            ceased to be such now. At present I am building me a house here in
                            Nienberg, as is well known, for the purpose of carrying [on] the baker
                            business, and intend to settle here permanently with my family, and
                            desire to be again reinstated as a Prussian subject.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JULIUS SCHEIBERT</signed>.</closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <p rend="center">[Indorsement.]</p>
                        <p>Further necessary steps shall be taken.</p>
                        <p>Certified to.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>SCHWARZKOPFER.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0417" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 112.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Vogeler</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Sargent</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate-General of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Frankfort-on-the-Main.</hi>
                            </placeName> [<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1883-02-26T23:59:59+00:53" notBefore="1883-02-21T00:00:00+00:09">undated</date>].</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herein copy of
                            a letter addressed to me by L. Staarbach, of Strasburg, Alsace, dated
                            February 21, and two orders, inclosures to said letter, commanding
                            Rudolph Staarbach and Julius Staarbach, sons of L. Staarbach, to report
                            on the 26th instant in person to the military recruiting commission for
                            the district of Strasburg.</p>
                    <p>In transmitting the request of Mr. Staarbach, as expressed in his letter,
                            I beg to state the case of Rudolph and Julius Staarbach, as I understand
                            it from verbal statements heretofore made to me by Mr. Staarbach and
                            sundry written communications received from him.</p>
                    <p>Mr. L. Staarbach lived in the United States many years, and did business
                            there, and in due time became a naturalized citizen. His said sons were
                            born after his naturalization. While these sons were minors Mr.
                            Staarbach returned with them to Alsace.</p>
                    <p>This took place, I think, before the annexation of Alsace to Germany. Mr.
                            L. Staarbach, while his sons were still minors, surrendered his American
                            citizenship and elected to and did become a German subject. He is doing
                            business at Strasburg, his said sons, who have both passed the age of
                            majority, being associated with him. They have declared to the German
                            authorities that they intend to remain American citizens; also that they
                            intend to return to the United States for a permanent residence,’ but
                            being pressed by the authorities have failed to fix a time for their
                            return. The authorities have deferred action, but have from time to time
                            importuned them to fix a time for their departure. They now take a
                            definite step.</p>
                    <p>Pursuant to Mr. Staarbach’s request, and without exprssing any opinion in
                            the matter, I submit the case to your consideration, feeling confident
                            that you will take such action in the premises as the nature of the case
                            requires.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>FERDINAND VOGELER,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul-General.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5 in No.
                                112.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">L. Staarbach</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Vogeler</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Strasburg</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-02-21">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 21,
                                    1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Inclosed I beg leave to forward two military orders of the burgomaster of
                            this place, from which you will perceive that the local police
                            authorities have had the impudence to call upon two American-born
                            citizens for military duty, a proceeding which caused a general
                            indignation here. The two sons, Rudolph Staarbach, born in New York,
                            July 13, 1857, and Julius Staarbach, born in New York, November 6, 1859,
                            are not at all inclined to obey this illegal summons, nor even to leave
                            the city, as they have formerly repeatedly been importuned to do in this
                            matter, but they insist upon their American citizen rights; and are of
                            an age when they can certainly not be interfered with in their actions,
                            in spite of the opinion which seems to prevail here, that even those
                            children who are born in America must needs follow the nationality of
                            their father.</p>
                    <p>I would request you most urgently to bring this case before his
                            excellency Mr. A. A Sargent, the American ambassador in Berlin, and ask
                            his speedy help and protection.</p>
                    <p>I look forward to a kind answer as well as further advice how I am to
                            conduct myself in the matter.</p>
                    <p>With much respect,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>L. STAARBACH.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>As the examining commission meets next Monday, I beg you to ask Mr.
                                Sargent to take speedy measures to bar these proceedings.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0418" n="348" xml:id="pg_348"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6 in No. 112.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Sargent</persName> to
                                Consul-General <persName type="to">Vogeler</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-02-24">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 24,
                                    1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your esteemed letter concerning the case
                            of the Staarbach brothers is received. The young men were born in the
                            United States in 1857 and 1859 respectively, of a German-American
                            father; returned with him, sometime before 1871, to Alsace, where they
                            have since lived, they being then not over fourteen and twelve years
                            old. The father became renaturalized as a German citizen. The
                            authorities have summoned the sons to appear for military service, after
                            repeated inquiries of them as to their intentions about going to America
                            if they considered themselves as American citizens—the young men
                            responding that they claim to be American citizens, but declining to go,
                            or to fix any time for going there, and the authorities at last taking
                            the decisive action above stated.</p>
                    <p>The question raised in this case is now pending [in] the imperial foreign
                            office in another case, and I have referred it to the Department for
                            instructions. It is simply this: Does the naturalization of an American
                            citizen in Germany, by which he becomes a German subject, work the
                            naturalization of his family, including his minor sons who are then
                            present with him in Germany? For the purpose of this question a native
                            and a naturalized American may be held as on the same footing.</p>
                    <p>By American law and practice the minor sons of a German naturalized in
                            the United States, if then with him, become Americans. Do not the minor
                            sons of such an American who may be naturalized a German become German
                            subjects, if with him at the time in Germany? Can we insist on one
                            doctrine for ourselves and another for Germany? It seems to me not.</p>
                    <p>Had these youths promptly, on gaining their freedom at majority, gone to
                            the United States and assumed the duties and functions of American
                            citizenship, any defect in their title to this would probably have been
                            passed <hi rend="italic">sub silentio</hi>. Instead of so doing they
                            have settled down here, engaged in business, perhaps married and
                            ratified their father’s acts by their own except so far as indefinite
                            declarations go, which were made merely to avoid service to the country
                            whose protection they seek and enjoy.</p>
                    <p>Until corrected by the Department, I must hold the American citizenship
                            of these parties to be doubtful at least. The foreign office considers
                            such persons as naturalized with the father, according to the American
                            doctrine. I do not see how these young men can escape military service
                            if they remain in the country.</p>
                    <p>There is another complication in their case: The foreign office has not
                            yet formally admitted, and has heretofore denied, that Alsace-Lorraine
                            is covered by the naturalization treaties which were made with the
                            original separate States before the Empire and before the acquisition of
                            those provinces. If it should revive this consideration in this case,
                            the only ground on which it would consider it would be one of national
                            comity, which, of course, must be consistent with its own views of
                            justice to itself. As already said, it looks upon youths so
                            circumstanced as naturalized with the father; and its own rights and
                            interests are involved not to surrender to us those whom it considers as
                            its own subjects.</p>
                    <p>I may add that the United States has some right to be considered in this
                            matter, and to require that those who expect to rely upon its protection
                            in the sacred name of citizenship shall in some way, except by barren
                            declarations to foreign officials, show their fidelity to it.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. A. SARGENT.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
