<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 272.Mr. Frelinghuysen to Mr. West.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1882-11-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1882-11-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1882-11-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1882-11-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="272"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d272">
                <head>No. 272.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Frelinghuysen</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">West</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-11-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 28, 1882</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In 1878 and 1879 correspondence was had between
                    your legation and this Department touching the claim of the Colombian Government
                    that the custody of the papers of foreign vessels should lie with the local port
                    officers, and not with the consul of the vessel’s nation. As this Department has
                    advised your legation of the steps taken then and subsequently which led to the
                    abrogation of the obnoxious Colombia law on which the practice was founded, it
                    seems proper to now acquaint you with the circumstance that further
                    correspondence on this subject has taken place at Caracas, by reason of the
                    reported action of the authorities of Panama in continuing to require
                    shipmasters to procure, at great delay and expense, collateral certificates from
                    the various officers of the port that the vessel owes them nothing before
                    permitting her clearance to be granted. The result, so far, has been the
                    expression of the belief of the federal Government of Bogota that no local edict
                    of the State of Panama exists, or, if it exists, that it can have no effect
                    whatever at variance with the Colombian “law 109 of 1880.”</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>FRED’K T. FRELINGHUYSEN.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
