<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 305.Mr. Frelinghuysen to Mr. West.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d305</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">305</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1883-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1883-07-26T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183" lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249" lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856" lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1883-07-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1883-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="305" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d305">
                <head>No. 305.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Frelinghuysen</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">West</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-07-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 26,
                                1883</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to Mr. Saurin’s note of the
                            28th of February last, referring to previous correspondence and denying
                            the reports received by this Government to the effect that the Milk
                            River country was overrun with Canadian Indians and half-breeds, I now
                            have the honor to inclose herewith for the information of Her Majesty’s
                            Government a copy of a letter to this Department from the War Department
                            on the subject.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>FRED’K T. FRELISTGHUYSEN</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tweedale</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">War
                                            Department</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-07-13">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 13,
                                        1883</date>. (Received July 14.)</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your letter of March5 last, inclosing copy of a note from
                                the British legation at this capital, together with a copy of a
                                communication from the inspector of the northwestern mounted police,
                                commanding Wood Mountain post, on the subject of the movements of
                                the half-breeds and hostile Indians in the vicinity of Milk River,
                                Montana, in which communication the inspector asserts that the
                                reports that the Milk River country is overrun with Canadian
                                half-breeds are not correct.</p>
                    <p>In reply I beg to inform you that the matter was referred to the
                                commanding general of the Department of Dakota, who was instructed
                                to cause a careful statement to be made of the number of half-breeds
                                and Canadian Indians who have been <pb facs="0586" n="516" xml:id="pg_516"/> during the past autumn and winter, in the Milk
                                River country and on adjoining reservations in the Territory of
                                Montana.</p>
                    <p>I have now the honor to invite your attention to the inclosed copies
                                of the respective reports on this subject from the commanding
                                officers of the Department of Dakota, the District of Montana, and
                                the camp on Poplar River, Montana, and also to the inclosed
                                statement, marked A, compiled at the headquarters of the Department
                                of Dakota, from the best information that could be obtained.</p>
                    <p>Copies of the inclosed papers have been furnished the Department of
                                the Interior to-day.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN TWEEDALE,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Chief Cleric</hi>
                                        (<hi rend="italic">for the Secretary of War, in his
                                        absence</hi>).</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p>Copy of indorsements on (2445, Adjutant-General’s Office, 1883)
                                communication from Adjutant-General of March 9, 1883, furnishing,
                                for the information of the commanding general, Military Division of
                                the Missouri, copy of letter from State Department to Secretary of
                                War, inclosing copy of a note from the British legation on the
                                subject of the movements of half-breeds and hostile Indians in the
                                vicinity of Milk River, Montana, &amp;c.</p>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>[First indorsement.]</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters Military Division
                                                Missouri</hi>,<lb/>
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Chicago</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-03-14">
                                    <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 14, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Respectfully referred to the commanding general, Department of
                                    Dakota, for investigation and report, attention being invited to
                                    the statement contained in the letter of A. R. Macdonell,
                                    inspector, commanding mounted police Northwestern Territory,
                                    Wood Mountain.</p>
                        <p>The commanding general, Department of Dakota, will please cause a
                                    careful statement to be made of the number of half-breeds and
                                    Canadian Indians who have been in the Milk River country and on
                                    the reservation referred to, and return these papers with a full
                                    and detailed report as possible to these headquarters.</p>
                        <p>By command of Lieutenant-General Sheridan.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>R. WILLIAMS</signed>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Assistant Adjutant-General.</hi>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>[Second indorsement.]</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters Department of
                                                Dakota</hi>,<lb/>
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Fort
                                                Snelling, Minn.</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-06-08">
                                    <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 8, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Respectfully returned to the headquarters Military Division of
                                    the Missouri.</p>
                        <p>Attention invited to the inclosed reports of the commanding
                                    officer of the district of Montana, the commanding officer Camp
                                    Poplar River, Montana, and the inclosed statement marked A.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>SAMUEL BRECK</signed>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Assistant Adjutant-General,<lb/>In absence of the
                                        brigadier-general commanding.</hi>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>[Third indorsement.]</head>
                        <opener>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters Military Division of
                                        Missouri</hi>, <lb/>
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chicago</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-06-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 16, 1883</date>.</opener>
                        <p>Respectfully forwarded to the Adjutant-General of the Army for
                                    the information of the Secretary of War.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>P. H. SHERIDAN,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant-General, Commanding.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Captain <persName type="from">Read</persName> to
                                        <gloss type="to">assistant adjutant-general, Department of
                                        Dakota</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Camp Poplar River, Mont.</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-06">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 6, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In compliance with your indorsement of
                                March 19 on copies of correspondence relative to a movements of
                                half-breeds and hostile Indians in the vicinity of Milk River,
                                Montana, I have the honor to report as follows: On the 26th of
                                November I sent First Sergeant Neeland, Company B, Eleventh
                                Infantry, with a small party to the Milk River country to hunt for
                                the command and observe the movements of the <pb facs="0587" n="517" xml:id="pg_517"/> half-breeds and Indians. Immediately after his
                                arrival there he saw what he believed to be half-breeds running
                                buffalo. Following them up, he captured seven half-breeds, with
                                train of nine carts loaded with meat and robes, on their way north,
                                whom he permitted to go in consideration of information given him
                                regarding other parties. He then followed a party of twenty or
                                twenty-five half-breeds with thirty-nine carts, came in sight of
                                them, but was unable to overtake them before reaching the Canadian
                                line. He therefore turned back to strike another party of whom he
                                had been informed, and found them near Campbell’s Crossing of Milk
                                River. The party, consisting of thirty-three half-breeds and four or
                                five Cree Indians, abandoned their train and fled with their ponies,
                                leaving in Neeland’s hands fifty-eight carts, 200 robe hides, and
                                about 15,000 pounds of meat. He afterwards saw another party of five
                                half-breeds with seven carts, making in all about seventy-five
                                half-breeds and Cree Indians with ninety-three carts seen by this
                                party during an absence of thirteen days. A few days after Sergeant
                                Neeland’s return a party sent out by the Indian agent, with which
                                was a non-commissioned officer from this post on furlough, Corporal
                                Yesson, Company B, Eleventh Infantry, from whom I got my
                                information, captured a party of ten half-breeds, saw five other
                                half-breeds at one time, eight half-breeds and twenty-five or thirty
                                Indians at another, thirteen half-breeds at another, about sixty-six
                                in all, and also saw large numbers of half-breeds or Indians hunting
                                buffalo every day for ten days. Corporal Yesson was informed by
                                hunters that about one hundred half-breeds and Indians had gone up
                                Beaver Creek.</p>
                    <p>On the 28th of February, Scout Culbertson, with one white man and six
                                Indians, captured nine lodges of Crees (forty-seven Indians all
                                told, of whom eleven were bucks), near head of Beaver Creek, and
                                brought them to Timber Creek, where they were turned over to a
                                detachment sent to meet them, and afterwards sent across the line by
                                order of the department commander. These Indians were part of a camp
                                of thirty lodges that had been removed from the big bend of Milk
                                River, by troops from Fort Assinniboine a short time before, and
                                were moving towards Missouri River. They stated that the other
                                twenty-one lodges returned to their old camp after the troops had
                                left. A white man in the employ of the Indian bureau, and others
                                whom I know to be perfectly reliable, have informed me that about
                                fifty families of Canadian half-breeds have been all winter south of
                                the Missouri, within a few miles of Fort Peck. All of these people
                                mentioned were trespassing upon the Fort Peck Indian Reservation,
                                and all except those last named in what is known as the Milk River
                                country.</p>
                    <p>On the 21st of December, 1832, I left post myself and scouted that
                                section of country thoroughly, returning December 31. I found no
                                half-breeds or Indians, but the snow, which had fallen within two
                                weeks, was packed down by “jumpers” or half-breed sleighs into
                                well-beaten roads, the principal ones leading towards Wood Mountain,
                                with smaller trails running into them from the hills in every
                                direction. These trails showed conclusively that hundreds of
                                “jumpers” had passed over them since the snow fell, and confirmed
                                the report made to me that half-breeds in large numbers had been
                                there a few days before my arrival.</p>
                    <p>The numbers given above as having been seen are only such as have
                                been reported to me officially; many others have been reported by
                                outside parties, which I have no means of verifying. So far as I
                                know, no Canadian half-breeds have wintered on the reservation,
                                except those south of the Missouri, who have now left; but that the
                                reservation has been overrun by them and hostile Indiaus, as well as
                                by white hunters, to such an extent as to intimidate the reservation
                                Indians and keep them from their best hunting grounds, there is not
                                a shadow of a doubt. I use the term “hostile Indians” not only with
                                reference to the remnant of the Sioux in Canada, but the Crees as
                                well, who are numerous and hostile to the reservation Indians. The
                                fact that these people made their camps and left their families
                                north of the line does not materially diminish the number of men
                                hunting buffalo on this side.</p>
                    <p>Inspector Macdonell seems to have ascertained the number of white
                                hunters on the reservation with more accuracy than I have been able
                                to do, and the report he mentioned as having come from the “United
                                States authorities at Poplar River” is certainly incorrect. Every
                                white hunter I have been able to find has been removed, but when it
                                is considered that they are scattered over a large extent of country
                                in parties of from two to six, the difficulties in the way of
                                removing all of them are obvious.</p>
                    <p>As for Scout Culbertson, he has served under my immediate command
                                more than two years, has proved himself an excellent scout and
                                interpreter in every respect, and in every case where I have acted
                                on reports made by him they have been fully verified. His field
                                service the past winter has been mostly with detachments of troops
                                where the reports have been made by others.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>O. B. READ,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Captain Eleventh
                                        Infantry, Commanding Post.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0588" n="518" xml:id="pg_518"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Ruger</persName>
                                    to <gloss type="to">adjutant-general, Department of
                                        Dakota</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters District of Montana</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Helena, Mont.</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-24">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 24, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to forward herewith
                                report of the 8th instant by the commanding officer of Fort
                                Assinniboine, Mont., relative to raids recently made south of the
                                boundary line by Canadian Indians, principally Crees; also,
                                statements by Mr. John Young, United States Indian agent at the
                                Blackfeet Agency, and by Mr. William Rowe, deputy United States
                                marshal, living at Fort Benton, regarding the same general subject.
                                A summary of essential facts embraced in the papers is as follow
                                s</p>
                    <p>On the night of the 15th of March ultimo 111 ponies were stolen from
                                the Piegans at the Blackfeet Agency, but the thieves were not
                                overtaken. Their course was direct for the boundary line, and the
                                party were no doubt Crees.</p>
                    <p>About the 15th March last a party of Crees, under leadership of
                                “Cut-foot,” left the vicinity of Fort Walsh, crossed the boundary,
                                and, on the 18th and 19th, killed the work oxen belonging to Mr.
                                Clark Tingley, of Fort Benton, near Mr. Joseph Kipp’s ranch, which
                                is on the Marias River, about 80 miles from Benton, and stole from
                                Mr. Kipp forty-three horses, and from Mr. Guadupié, near there, five
                                horses; and from Mr. Solomon Abbott, at Willow Round,up the Marias
                                from Mr. Kipp’s ranch, twenty horses. Pursuit was made by a party of
                                agency Piegans, at the time near Mr. Kipp’s ranch, who overtook the
                                raiclers on the morning of the 19th and killed two, but the main
                                party of about fifteen remaining escaped across the line, and
                                arrived on the 21st, with the stolen horses, in the vicinity of Fort
                                Walsh. Of these horses, seven were afterwards recovered through the
                                efforts of officers of the northwest police at Fort Walsh.</p>
                    <p>On the night of April 1 a party of Cree Indians stole horses—reported
                                at sixty-seven—from the Gros Ventre camp on People’s Creek. Of
                                these, thirty-seven were recovered near the boundary by a pursuing
                                party, but the thieves escaped.</p>
                    <p>On the 17th instant seventeen horses were stolen by a party of Crees
                                from Mr. John Galbraith, about 28 miles from Fort Benton, on the
                                Teton River. Information of this was received on the 18th instant by
                                the commanding officer at Fort Assinniboine, who promptly dispatched
                                troop L, Second Cavalry, Captain Randolph Norwood, with Indian
                                scouts, to intercept the raiders.</p>
                    <p>A party of seventeen Crees, presumed to be the same, were overtaken
                                near White Horse Lake to the east of Sweet Grass Hills, making their
                                way with stolen horses for the boundary. These Crees fired on the
                                advanced party of scouts. One of the Indians was killed by return
                                fire, and, the troop coming up, one other was killed, the rest of
                                the Crees then making good their escape across the boundary in the
                                direction of Fort Walsh.</p>
                    <p>Special report has been made as to this affair.</p>
                    <p>On the 14th instant sixty-nine Cree Indians (men, women, and
                                children), who came from the vicinity of Fort Walsh, were found
                                south of the boundary near Fort Assinniboine. They said they came
                                south to get food, hunt and truck. , They have been sent north of
                                the line.</p>
                    <p>From-communications before received, and as appears by the letters
                                from Major Shurtleff, commanding at Fort Walsh, to the commanding
                                officer at Fort Assinniboine, attached to the report of Colonel
                                Ilges, the officers of the northwest police are anxious to put a
                                stop to these incursions, but, probably from lack of adequate force,
                                have not. Removal of the Crees to the North Saskatchewan, referred
                                to in the letter of the 6th instant by Major Shurtleff, would do
                                much to put a stop to their forays. The recent activity of these
                                Indians in horse-stealing south of the line, particularly by those
                                in the vicinity of Fort Walsh, may be due to expectation on their
                                part of having to move north soon. Presentation of the subject would
                                be incomplete were no reference made to conduct in like regard by
                                our Indians. Stealing parties of them have at times, no doubt, been
                                north of the border, but the evil resulting has been comparatively
                                small. A communication from Colonel Irvine, then commanding officer
                                at Fort Walsh, was received in November last by the commanding
                                officer at Fort Shaw, to the effect that a large number of horses
                                had been stolen from the vicinity of Fort Walsh and supposed to have
                                been taken to the agency on this side of the line. This matter was
                                inquired into, but no evidence found that the Indians of the
                                Blackfeet Agency or other Indians this side of the line were guilty.
                                A copy of the letter of Colonel Irvine, and a statement by United
                                States Indian Agent John Young, are attached. No other complaint of
                                like acts by our Indians has, so far as I have information, been
                                made within a year past.</p>
                    <p>The rumor mentioned by Mr. Young that ranchmen on the Teton, from
                                whom horses had been stolen, had been north of the boundary to make
                                good their losses by theft in return, I heard nothing of at the time
                                and do not credit.</p>
                    <p>Report has been made of the particular dispositions of troops
                                recently made and ordered with reference to raids by Canadian
                                Indians south of border, particularly to the region of the Marias
                                River.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>THOMAS H. RUGER,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Commanding
                                        District of Montana.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0589" n="519" xml:id="pg_519"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Ilges</persName>
                                    to <gloss type="to">acting assistant adjutant-general, District
                                        of Montana</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Fort Assinniboine, Mont.</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 8, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In obedience to telegraphic
                                instructions from your office, I have the honor to submit the
                                following report concerning the late raids of hostile Crees into the
                                United States territory, and their operations, as far as I have been
                                able to ascertain from reliable sources:</p>
                    <p>It appears that about the 15th ultimo one of the Cree chiefs named
                                Pie-a-pot informed Capt. A. Shurtleff, superintendent and commander
                                of the post of Fort Walsh, of the intention of a band of Cree
                                warriors, under the leadership of “Cut-foot,” to cross the boundary
                                line into United States territory for the purpose of stealing horses
                                and taking the war-path; that Pie-a-pot requested Captain Shurtleff
                                to prevent the raid; that thereupon Captain Shurtleff assembled the
                                leader, “Cut-foot,” and his young men in the post-trader’s store,
                                and advised them against the raid, as being contrary to law and
                                against his positive orders; that if they did cross the boundary
                                line with any hostile intent, which of course he could not prevent
                                with the forces available, they would be arrested and any stolen
                                stock taken away from them upon their return, if such should be
                                found in their possession. This conversation is reported to have
                                taken place in the presence of the trader, Mr. D. W. Marsh, Captain
                                Norman, the Indian agent, and several white men; that a day or two
                                after said conversation “Cut-foot” with fifteen other Cree warriors
                                (among them “The Head,” “The Man who speaks with his Friend,”
                                “Chocolate,” “Frying Around,” “Kernel,” “The Indian,” “The Medicine
                                Man,” “The Old Moccasin” and “The Lonesome Fellow”) crossed the
                                boundary line into United States territory, and on the night of the
                                19th ultimo, after having separated into two bands, raided the ranch
                                of Mr. Joe Kipp, at the crossing of the Marias, on the McLeod road,
                                and simultaneously the ranch of Mr. Sol. Abbott, at Willow Round,
                                stealing from the former fifty-six horses, and from the latter
                                twenty-one; that these Crees at once started to return across the
                                line in the direction of Fort Walsh; that they were followed by a
                                party of white men and Piegan Indians (American), who overtook and
                                killed three of the raiding party, among them a brother of the chief
                                “Pie-a-pot,” previously referred to in this communication; that on
                                the evening of the 21st ultimo the head man, “Cut-foot,” with his
                                surviving party and the stolen horses (about seventy in number),
                                arrived at Fort Walsh, Northwest Territory, and that the particulars
                                of this raid became at once known to the garrison, the surrounding
                                settlements and the Indians encamped near the post. On the 24th day
                                of March last I dispatched to the commanding officer at Fort Walsh,
                                Northwest Territory, a communication, giving him as full information
                                as was then in my possession, and soliciting his official assistance
                                to recover the stolen stock. The troops which had meanwhile been
                                sent out from this post for the purpose of intercepting the raiders,
                                if possible, and which had been delayed at crossing of Sage Creek by
                                a severe storm, were recalled at the same time.</p>
                    <p>The answer of Captain Shurtleff, commanding Fort Walsh, Northwest
                                Territory, to my communication above referred to, was received on
                                the 7th instant, and is attached hereto.</p>
                    <p>A citizen named J. C. Pickett (with two companions), who is, to my
                                personal knowledge, a man of high standing and respectability,
                                arrived at Fort Walsh as the agent of Messrs. Kipp and Abbott about
                                the 26th ultimo, for the purpose of recovering the stolen stock from
                                the Canadian authorities, in case the same or part had been
                                recovered. They saw Colonel Irvine, the officer commanding the
                                mounted police, in person, stated their errand, and were promised
                                all possible assistance. They passed through the post yesterday,
                                having in their possession seven of the stolen horses. Mr. Pickett
                                states that the balance of the stolen horses are cached by the Crees
                                in the hills, and that they refuse to give them up, although ordered
                                by the authorities to do so; that the Crees claim these horses as an
                                offset to the lives of the three warriors killed on the American
                                side during the raid. Mr. Pickett further states that he found two
                                of the stolen horses in the possession of the interpreter of Fort
                                Walsh, Northwest Territory; that he so informed Colonel Irvine and
                                the commanding officer of the post; that he repeatedly demanded
                                possession of the same, but that these horses were not returned to
                                him for some reason unknown, although the interpreter (La Vallet)
                                admitted that they were of the stolen number. On the 5th instant I
                                sent, by special courier, a communication to the commanding officer
                                at Fort Walsh, Northwest Territory, giving information about raid of
                                Crees upon Gros Ventre Indians encamped on Milk River, and in United
                                States territory; also asking for further information about the
                                former raid. This communication, together with answer are attached
                                hereto.</p>
                    <p>It appears from information received from Indian Agent Major Lincoln,
                                attached hereto, stationed at Fort Belknap, Mont., that a band of
                                Crees (leader unknown) raided a camp of Gros Ventres at People’s
                                Creek, stealing from the latter sixty-seven horses. This party was
                                followed by some of the Gros Ventre Indians, the trail leading
                                toward the boundary line. I have received no further particulars
                                except those contained in the communications above referred to. Not
                                being able to learn of these <pb facs="0590" n="520" xml:id="pg_520"/> raids to intercept and punish, I have been powerless to act
                                effectively. By the time information reaches me the marauders are in
                                safety across the boundary line. I respectfully suggest that the
                                remedy for recovery of the stolen stock lies with the Canadian
                                authorities, and the strongest effort of this Government should be
                                put forward to bring about the desired result.</p>
                    <p>A summer camp, consisting of one company of cavalry and one company
                                of infantry, established on the eastern slope of the Sweet Grass
                                Hills, where there is good water and plenty of grass and timber,
                                would, in my opinion, be of great advantage to prevent raids of
                                Canadian Indians into the settlements, and, if such are made, to
                                intercept and punish.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>GUIDO ILGES,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant-Colonel
                                        Eighteenth Infantry, Commanding.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Major <persName type="from">Shurtleff</persName>
                                    to Colonel <persName type="to">Ilges</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Northwest Mounted Police</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fort Walsh</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-05">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 5,
                                        1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your letter of the 24th of March, concerning the Cree
                                raid into Montana.</p>
                    <p>I have been doing all in my power to recover Kipp’s stock, but find
                                it very slow work, as they are cachéd in small numbers about the
                                hills and moved about every day. I will undoubtedly be able to
                                recover them, but it will take some time to get them all. The
                                Indians state that they left several of them on the road, played
                                out.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. SHURTLEFF,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Superintendent,
                                        Commanding Post.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Ilges</persName>
                                    to <gloss type="to">commanding officer, Fort
                                Walsh</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Fort Assinniboine, Mont.</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The inclosed communication has just
                                reached me from Belknap by courier:</p>
                    <p>“I respectfully request that you will take such measures as you may
                                deem necessary to effect a recovery of the stolen stock, or such
                                part of it as you may be able to find in the possession of the
                                marauding party. I will also thank you to furnish me such
                                information as you may have of the stock stolen from the Marias
                                River, and which I have been informed was taken to your post on the
                                21st of March. Any assistance rendered me by you in these matters
                                will be reciprocated as far as it is in my power to do so. I fully
                                concur in the view expressed by Colonel Irvine that this
                                horse-stealing should be stopped.”</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>GUIDO ILGES,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant-Colonel
                                        Eighteenth Infantry, Commanding.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Major <persName type="from">Shurtleff</persName>
                                    to Colonel <persName type="to">Ilges</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Northwest Mounted Police</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fort Walsh</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-06">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 6,
                                        1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your scout, Nicholson, has just
                                arrived with your communication concerning stolen horses from the
                                Gros Ventre Indians by a party of Crees, under the leadership of
                                “Break-through-the-ice.”</p>
                    <p>This party has not been in this vicinity during the past winter, and
                                has not come this way with the horses. It is probable that they have
                                crossed the line towards the east end of the mountains. I will at
                                once send a party in that direction to intercept them and recover
                                the horses, if possible. We expect to be able in a few weeks to send
                                all these Crees to their reservation on the North Saskatchewan,
                                which will prevent their raids in future.</p>
                    <p>I wrote you yesterday by mail concerning the recovery of Kipp’s
                                horses.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. SHURTLEFF,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Superintendent,
                                        Commanding Post.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0591" n="521" xml:id="pg_521"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lincoln</persName> to
                                    Colonel <persName type="to">Ilges</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Indian Service</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fort Belknap Agency</hi>
                            </placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 3,
                                1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am grieved to have to report to you
                                that the Cree Indians, fourteen in number, have raided the camp of
                                the Gros Ventres, now on People’s Creek, on the night of April 1,
                                and stole sixty-seven head of their horses. I am informed by one of
                                the pursuing party that they discovered the tracks of twelve head of
                                shod horses, which were evidently stolen from the white men on the
                                Missouri River. Those Crees’ trail led toward the camp of Crees
                                under the leadership of Break-through-the-ice, which is about 35
                                miles northeast of here and some few miles south of the forty-ninth
                                parallel, as I have already informed you through Scouts Nicholson
                                and Valentine. Will you kindly take steps to notify the Canadian
                                authorities in order to effect a recovery of the animals? A party of
                                my Indians are following up the trail.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>H. L. LINCOLN,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States
                                        Indian Agent.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Young</persName> to
                                    General <persName type="to">Ruger</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Indian Service</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Blackfeet Agency,
                                    Montana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 4,
                                        1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your telegram dated 26 th ultimo, asking statement of
                                facts regarding the recent raids on this reservation, &amp;c. On the
                                night of the 15th March 111 ponies were stolen from the vicinity of
                                this agency. Pursuit was made as promptly as possible. It took time
                                to get horses enough. As fixed ammunition is forbidden to the
                                Indians, there was delay in getting that. The trail was followed to
                                near the Canada line towards Cypress Mountain. Ten of the ponies
                                that had given out on the way were recovered, but died from the
                                fatigue; but the thieves were not overtaken. The leader of the
                                pursuing party was “Piegan-man”; he had five assistants.</p>
                    <p>From the articles picked up on the trail, moccasins, gun-covers,
                                &amp;c., the raiders are believed to have been Crees.</p>
                    <p>The ponies lost by this raid numbered 101. About the same date a raid
                                was made near Willow Round, and pursuit was given more promptly. The
                                raiders had taken 61 head of horses and had wantonly killed 10
                                work-steers belonging to freighters. The pursuing party, White Wolf,
                                Little Dog, Bird’s Tail, and Jack Miller, half-breed, overtook two
                                of the raiders, who showed fight and wounded Little Dog, Bird’s Tail
                                and Jack Miller, the two first severely, but were finally captured
                                and scalped. This ended the pursuit, the main party crossing into
                                Canada with the stolen property. No doubt exists as to the party
                                being Crees.</p>
                    <p>On the night of the 21st of March a raid was made on Birch Creek, the
                                southern boundary of the reservation, and forty-seven ponies were
                                stolen; in this case pursuit was prompt, and seventeen of the ponies
                                were recovered; the pursuers, weakened by those left in charge of
                                the recovered ponies, continued the chase, some on foot, taking the
                                trail to the Cardotte Pass, through which the thieves crossed the
                                mountains, escaping with thirty head of ponies. The raiders are
                                believed to be Pend d’Oreille Indians from the Flathead agency.</p>
                    <p>The pursuers returned, got fresh ponies and letters of protection,
                                and started again to follow all the way to the Flathead agency, if
                                necessary. Their names are, The Horn, Sleeping Wolf, and White
                                Bird’s Tail. No report from them at this date.</p>
                    <p>I have written to Colonel Irvine, commanding Fort Walsh, giving the
                                particulars of the two first raids, and requesting his efforts for
                                the recovery of the stolen property, and also to Major Ronan, of the
                                Flathead agency, with full particulars of the Pend d’Oreille raid,
                                and requesting his exertions for the recovery of the stolen
                                ponies.</p>
                    <p>The two severely wounded Indians are out of danger and on the fair
                                way of recovery.</p>
                    <p>While talking with some of the chiefs to-day about these raids, they
                                said, “We do go to war and steal ponies; but to wantonly kill,
                                without object, work-steers, no, never.”</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN YOUNG,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Indian
                                        Agent.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0592" n="522" xml:id="pg_522"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Rowe</persName> to
                                    General <persName type="to">Ruger</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Fort Benton, Mont.</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-03-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 23, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>E. X. Budlor having left town, I took the trouble to find out the
                                facts of the case, and have got the evidence of Mr. Tingley and Mr.
                                John Harris, both stockmen that are familiar with case. On the 18th
                                of March, 1883, in the morning, Mr. Tingley’s herder on the Marias,
                                about 5 miles below Joe Kipp’s ranch, rounded up his work oxen, and
                                in the afternoon of the same day he discovered that six of them had
                                been shot and butchered. He then started to Kipp’s ranch for help;
                                got Pickett, the herder, and some Piegan Indians, went to where the
                                cattle were butchered, and found that more had been killed.</p>
                    <p>The Indians returned to Kipp’s ranch, and Pickett and two others went
                                to look for their mules and horses; they found the mules and some of
                                the horses, and discovered the Indians with the balance of the
                                horses, about 40 head in number. Some shots were exchanged, and in
                                the excitement the Indians dropped the meat they had taken from the
                                oxen they had butchered. Later in the night a party of Piegans,
                                about 20 in number, started in pursuit, and about daylight on the
                                morning of the 19th they overtook the Crees and killed two of them;
                                also two Piegans were wounded in the fight, and a half-breed had his
                                horse shot from under him. Another mail arrived today, having left
                                Kipp’s yesterday and traveled all night, Indians having been seen
                                around Pend d’Oreille and at the Knees during the day.</p>
                    <p>The driver reports that the horses are stolen at the Willow Round and
                                at the Blackfeet agency; also some of J. G. Baker &amp; Co.’s work
                                oxen were killed.</p>
                    <p>The Indians, when last seen, were making for Fort Walsh. Joseph
                                Pickett and two other men have gone to Fort Walsh to try and recover
                                the horses, and to find out what Crees were engaged in the raid.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>WILLIAM HOWE,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Deputy United States
                                        Marshal.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Irvine</persName>
                                    to <gloss type="to">commanding officer, Fort
                                Shaw</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Northwest Mounted Police</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Headquarters, Fort Walsh</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-11-13">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 13, 1882</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that a
                                very serious raid has been made upon settlers’ horses in these
                                territories; a large number of horses were stolen, it is said, by
                                Indians from the United States. The impression here is that the
                                stolen horses have been taken to the Piegan Agency, Montana. I have
                                written to Mr. W. G. Conrad, of J. G. Baker &amp; Co., Fort Benton,
                                on the subject, requesting him to secure the services of the sheriff
                                of Benton in view of recovering the stolen horses. I shall be most
                                grateful for any assistance you can render Mr. Conrad or the sheriff
                                in the discharge of his duties. Mr. Conrad has a description of the
                                horses.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. G. IRVINE,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Commissioner,
                                        Northwest Mounted Police.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Young</persName> to
                                    General <persName type="to">Ruger</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Indian Service</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Blackfeet Agency,
                                    Montana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-11-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 28,
                                        1882</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your letter, dated November 23, giving me a copy of
                                Commissioner Irvine’s letter to you respecting a large number of
                                horses stolen from near Fort Walsh, and supposed to have been taken
                                to this agency. Stealing horses from each other by the tribes on
                                either side of the line is an ancient practice, and my efforts to
                                repress the usage have always been exerted, and the owner of stolen
                                property has uniformly been aided in getting it back. In April last
                                a party of Crees and half-breeds from the Canada side made a raid on
                                the settlement at Birch Creek, on this reservation, and stole 70
                                head of ponies, with which they succeeded in reaching Fort Walsh,
                                although closely pursued to the line. I promptly informed the police
                                authorities at Fort Walsh of this outrage, and requested their
                                exertions for the return of the ponies.</p>
                    <p>In reply, the arrival of the above number of ponies was acknowledged
                                at the time stated, accompanied by a promise of endeavor to recover
                                and return them. Until this date none of them have been
                                returned.</p>
                    <p>Small raiding parties from this side during the summer have made
                                reprisals, and about 20 ponies have in this way been recovered. Of
                                course I only know of these raids when they are accomplished. Along
                                with this number 12 ponies were brought <pb facs="0593" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/> that had never belonged to my Indians. These
                                were at once taken possession of by my police, and 6 of them
                                returned to Joseph Brown, the owner, and 6 are still here awaiting
                                claimants.</p>
                    <p>I have information quite recently of a band of 36 ponies, in charge
                                of northern Indians from the line near Fort Belknap, passing the
                                Sweet Grass Hills and then turning northward again; there is a
                                possibility of these being part of the “large number lost,” and
                                supposed to have been taken to this agency.</p>
                    <p>I called the leading men of these tribes together and made them aware
                                of your communication, and their reply was uniform and emphatic,
                                “that no large band of stolen horses had recently been brought on
                                this reservation.”</p>
                    <p>In any action toward the suppression of these thefts or the
                                punishment of the offenders I shall deem it my duty to heartily
                                concur.</p>
                    <p>During the summer a party of three half-breeds from north of the line
                                came here properly accredited, seeking stolen horses. They succeeded
                                by my help in getting 6, and in going back homeward through the
                                Teton Valley stole 17 head from the ranchmen there, and I hear that
                                those ranchmen have been north since, stealing in return.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN YOUNG,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Indian
                                        Agent</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Ilges</persName>
                                    to <gloss type="to">adjutant-general, District of
                                        Montana</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Fort Assinniboine, Mont.</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 19, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Just received the following letter from Major Shurtleff, commanding
                                officer Fort Walsh, per courier: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“I have to inform you that I have just learned that a war
                                        party of Crees left this vicinity three or four days ago for
                                        the purpose of stealing horses. I am told that they intend
                                        to go to the Piegan agency. In their raids on the agency and
                                        the Marias they generally go and return by way of the Sweet
                                        Grass Hills. You may be able to intercept them on their
                                        return.</p>
                            <p>“Dated Fort Walsh, April 18, 1883.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>I think this the same party Captain Norwood is after, and hope that
                                he will succeed in striking them.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ILGES,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant-Colonel,
                                        Commanding.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Note.</hi>—Information on which action was
                                    taken by the commanding officer at Fort Assinniboine was
                                    received by him from Fort Benton the day before reception of
                                    that from Major Shurtleff. His telegram is not specially
                                    referred to in my communication, but, being pertinent to the
                                    general subject, is forwarded.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>THOMA.S H. RUGER,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Colonel
                                            Eighteenth Infantry, Commanding District of
                                            Montana.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Ruger</persName>
                                    to <gloss type="to">adjutant-general, Department of
                                        Dakota</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters District of Montana</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Helena</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-04-25">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 25, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor, in response to
                                indorsement of March 19 last, from department headquarters, to
                                report concerning the presence of Canadian Indians and half-breeds
                                south of the boundary line, particularly in the Milk River region,
                                during the past winter and autumn, as follows:</p>
                    <p>From the first part of July last, when a force from Fort Assinniboine
                                established a camp on the big bend of Milk River, until the 4th day
                                of October, when the force was withdrawn, there were no camps,
                                properly so designated, of Canadian Indians or half-breeds south of
                                the boundary in that region. During that time several hunting
                                parties of such Indians and half-breeds were encountered on the
                                reservation by detachments from the Assinniboine force, and sent
                                north of the boundary. The largest of such parties consisted of
                                about forty Crees, on the 8th of July last, by a detachment from the
                                command of Captain Kellogg, Eighteenth Infantry, of which report was
                                made at the time.</p>
                    <p>Early in December last a hunting party of Crees and other Canadian
                                Indians of about fifty lodges were on Milk River near the mouth of
                                Frenchman’s Creek. This information was had from a chief of the
                                Belknap agency, Assinniboine, and also from an Assinniboine Indian,
                                who arrived at Belknap December 27 from Wolf Point.</p>
                    <p>This camp left in the latter part of December or early in January
                                last, and returned, it is presumed, across the line, as it was not
                                found by scouting parties from Poplar River and Assinniboine or
                                scout sent from Belknap, which traversed that particular <pb facs="0594" n="524" xml:id="pg_524"/> vicinity and the country
                                of the Milk River generally in January and February.</p>
                    <p>On February 3 last Lieutenant Hardin, Eighteenth Infantry, in command
                                of a detachment from Fort Assinniboine, found two camps of Canadian
                                Indians—Crees—one of four lodges and the other of forty lodges,
                                under Chief “Rosebud” or “The Hip “and “Frozen Nose,” south of the
                                boundary on Woody Island Creek, near the Milk River, whom he
                                compelled to move north. These Indians stated to Lieutenant Hardin
                                they had been all winter south of the boundary. Reports were made to
                                United States Indian Agent Lincoln that other parties of Canadian
                                Indians were on the Lower Beaver Creek in December last, but as to
                                this fact no information sufficiently definite and reliable to
                                enable me to report positively has been obtained. If such parties
                                were there and not connected with that at the mouth of Frenchman’s
                                Creek, their stay must have been short.</p>
                    <p>But few half-breeds were, I am confident, on the reservation during
                                the winter, and these small roving hunting parties. Some few, it is
                                reported, crossed the Missouri to the settlement in the Judith
                                Basin.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>THOMAS H. RUGER,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Colonel
                                        Eighteenth Infantry, Commanding District of
                                    Montana.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Reuger</persName>
                                    to <gloss type="to">adjutant-general, Department of
                                        Dakota</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters District of Montana</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Helena</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-05-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 28, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to say that the
                                accompanying report is as definite as I can make from reports and
                                statements obtained.</p>
                    <p>In the first report (of April 25, 1883) I did not state numbers, and
                                cannot now, except as inferred from the number of lodges in each
                                case. There is included in the report with this, and not embraced in
                                the former report, a Cree camp of about forty lodges under Chief
                                “Waterfall.” I did not then think the evidence as to this camp
                                sufficient for a positive statement, but now include it as reported
                                by Agent Lincoln. I had before no information of visits by a band of
                                Crees to the Belknap agency.</p>
                    <p>This information was given by Agent Lincoln in communication of the
                                21st instant, in part reply to inquiry by me for as full and
                                definite statement as practicable relative to presence south of the
                                boundary of Canadian Indians and half-breeds for a year past. I have
                                taken for granted that the trail, as to which inquiries and report
                                by me were desired in the indorsement of March 19 last, is that
                                referred to in the principal paper, and I have confined my report to
                                the past autumn and winter.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>THOMAS H. RUGER,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Colonel
                                        Eighteenth Infantry, Commanding District of
                                    Montana.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Ruger</persName>
                                    to <gloss type="to">adjutant-general, Department of
                                        Dakota</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters District of Montana</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Helena</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-05-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 28, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor, in response to
                                telegram of the 7th instant from the department headquarters, and
                                referring to indorsement of March 19 last and my reply of April 25,
                                to make further report and a statement of the number of Canadian
                                Indians and half-breeds who may have been south of the boundary and
                                on the Indian reservation, as follows:</p>
                    <p>There were in December last, near the mouth of Frenchman’s Creek, a
                                hunting party of about fifty lodges of Crees and half-breeds,
                                numbering, as estimated, three hundred and fifty persons.</p>
                    <p>During the months of November, December, and January last, and until
                                February 3 following, there were forty-four lodges of Crees camped
                                on Woody Island, near its junction with the Milk River, under chiefs
                                “Rosebud” or “The Hip,” and “Frozen Nose,” numbering about 308
                                persons.</p>
                    <p>These Indians were captured by a detachment from Fort Assinniboine,
                                under Lieut. Charles B. Hardin, Eighteenth Infantry, on February 3
                                last, and sent north across the boundary.</p>
                    <p>During the month of December, and until about the 10th instant, there
                                were camped near the mouth of the Muscleshell River a party of
                                Crees, numbering twelve. There were also, during part of last autumn
                                and during December last, camped, as reported <pb facs="0595" n="525" xml:id="pg_525"/> by Indian Agent Lincoln to the
                                commanding officer at Fort Assinniboine, about fifty lodges of
                                Crees, under Chief “Waterfall” or “The
                                Man-who-breaks-through-the-ice,” at a place in a northeasterly
                                direction from Fort Belknap and a few miles south of the boundary,
                                numbering about 280 persons.</p>
                    <p>A band of about twenty lodges of Crees were at the Belknap agency on
                                at least two different occasions during the winter. This band, I
                                estimate, numbered about 120 persons.</p>
                    <p>During the autumn and winter roving hunting parties of Canadian
                                Indians and half-breeds, not included above, were from time to time
                                south of the boundary in the Milk River region, but as to these I
                                have been unable to obtain information sufficiently definite for
                                statement of their numbers.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>THOMAS H. RUGER,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Colonel
                                        Eighteenth Infantry, Commanding District of
                                    Montana.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p rend="flushleft">A.—<hi rend="italic">Statement of the number of
                                    half-breeds and Canadian Indians who have been during the last
                                    past autumn and winter in the Milk River country and on
                                    adjoining reservations for Indians in the Territory of Montana.
                                    Compiled at headquarters Department of Dakota, from the best
                                    information that can be obtained.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="5" rows="15">
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Date.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Place
                                        where found or heard from.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Description and number of people.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top #border-right">Number.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom #border-top">Remarks.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">December, 1882</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Near mouth of Frenchman’s
                                        Creek.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Crees and half-breeds.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">350</cell>
                            <cell>Fifty lodges estimated at number given.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">November and December, 1882;
                                        January and February, 1883.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Woody Island Creek, near its
                                        junction with Milk River, Montana Territory.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Crees under Chief “Rosebud” or
                                        “The Hip” and “Frozen Nose.”</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">308</cell>
                            <cell>Forty-four lodges, estimated at number given, captured by
                                        a detachment under lieutenant Hardin, Eighteenth Infantry,
                                        February 3, and sent across the Canadian boundary
                                        line.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">December, 1882; January,
                                        February, March, April and May. 1883.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Near mouth of Muscleshell River,
                                        Montana Territory.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Crees</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">12</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Autumn of 1882</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Northeast from Fort Belknap, a
                                        few miles south of the Canadian boundary line.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Crees under Chief “Waterfall” or
                                        “The-Man-who breaks-through the-ice.”</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">280</cell>
                            <cell>Forty lodges estimated at number given.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Winter of 1882 and 1883.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">At Belknap agency, Montana
                                        Territory.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Crees</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">120</cell>
                            <cell>Twenty lodges estimated at number given.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Autumn of 1882 and winter of
                                        1882 and 1883.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Milk River region.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Other Canadian Indians and
                                        half-breeds in roving bands and hunting narties.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                            <cell>No definite data as regards numbers obtainable.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">From November 26, 1882, to
                                        December 9, 1882.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Eastern portion of Milk River
                                        country.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Half-breeds, first party
                                        seen.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">7</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Half-breeds, second party
                                        seen.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right" rows="3">
                                <table>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell rendition="#top" role="num">20</cell>
                                        <cell role="brace" rows="3">{</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell role="num">37</cell>
                                    </row>
                                    <row>
                                        <cell rendition="#bottom" role="num">5</cell>
                                    </row>
                                </table>
                            </cell>
                            <cell rows="3">This party, when about to be overtaken, abandoned
                                        58 carts, 200 robe hides, and about 1,500 pounds of meat,
                                        and fled with their ponies.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Half-breeds and a few Crees,
                                        third party seen.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Half-breeds, fourth party
                                        seen.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">December, 1882, dates later than
                                        above.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Same</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Several parties of half-breeds,
                                        in all.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">36</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">February 26, 1883</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Near head of Beaver Creek,
                                        Montana Territory.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Crees</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">47</cell>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Winter of 1882–’83</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">South of Missouri River, near
                                        Fort Peck.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right">Half-breeds</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right" role="num">200</cell>
                            <cell>Fifty families, estimated at two hundred persons, camped
                                        for hunting purposes on the north or the Missouri
                                        River.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom"/>
                            <cell rendition="#border-right #border-bottom">Total</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#top #border-right #border-top #border-bottom" role="num">1,422</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#border-bottom"/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters
                                        Department of Dakota</hi>,<lb/>
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Fort Snelling, Minn.</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-06-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 8, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
