<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1883-02-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1883-02-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="317" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d317">
                    <head>No. 316.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Schuyler</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-02-10"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 10, 1883</date>.
                            (Received March 5.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 8.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I received a few days ago a circular of the
                        minister of the interior, dated January 23, 1883, addressed to the
                        provincial authorities of the Kingdom and to the bureau of health of
                        Piraeus, with reference to the importation of cattle from various eastern
                        countries. The second paragraph, however, of the circular renewed the
                        prohibition against the importation of hams, sausages, and lard coming from
                        America, either directly or indirectly. I inclose a copy and translation of
                        this circular.</p>
                    <p>On his first reception day I inquired of Mr. Tricoupis whether the Government
                        had any additional reasons for prohibiting the importation of hams, &amp;c.,
                        from the United States, adding that I thought that the results of the
                        investigations undertaken by the order of our Government had sufficiently
                        proved that there was no danger to be expected from such importations. Mr.
                        Tricoupis said that he was ignorant of the causes which had led to the
                        insertion of the paragraph referred to, as in his capacity of minister of
                        the interior he had simply published a circular prepared by the sanitary
                        authorities of his department; that if he had noticed the passage he would
                        have inquired, because he remembered that Mr. Botassi, the Greek
                        consul-general at New York, had made a report in which he stated that the
                        reports about disease of swine, &amp;c., in America had been greatly
                        exaggerated. He promised me, therefore, to make further inquiries, and,
                        without binding himself, gave me to understand that if the result of his
                        inquiries proved satisfactory the prohibition would be withdrawn.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>EUGENE SCHUYLER.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No.
                            8.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">circular prohibiting importation of american
                                pork.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-01-11"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 11,
                                1883</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">The ministry of the interior to the
                                nomarchs and eparchs of the Kingdom and to the bureau of health of
                                Pirœus:</hi></p>
                        <p>According to the orders which you have already received, cows and
                            buffaloes coming from Russia, Asia Minor, Syria, Egypt, Thrace, Valona,
                            and Rahova in Roumania, on account of the epizoöty raging in those
                            countries, are only allowed to be imported by way of Syra, Corfu, and
                            Piraeus, and after a previous quarantine. With regard to raw cow and
                            buffalo hides of the same origin, their importation is only permitted by
                            Syra and Corfu, and with all the prescribed sanitary precautions, while
                            the importation of other products of these animals, such as bones,
                            intestines, &amp;c., is absolutely forbidden.</p>
                        <pb facs="0607" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/>
                        <p>By the present circular we renew to yon these orders, and also those
                            concerning the prohibition to import into Greece hams, sausages, lard,
                            &amp;c., coming directly or indirectly from America, and we order you to
                            see that these orders are strictly executed by the sanitary authorities
                            of your jurisdiction.</p>
                        <p>On the recommendation of the medical counsel, and in view of the epizoōty
                            existing in Thrace and at Valona, we also forbid the importation of cows
                            and buffaloes coming from any part of Turkey in Europe, by any other way
                            than Syra, Corfu, and PiraBus, and until after a previous quarantine of
                            nine days, including the days of the passage. We also forbid the
                            importation into Greece of raw cow-hides of the same origin, except by
                            way of Syra or Corfu, and after the observance of the sanitary measures
                            per-gcribed by the regulations. The importation of dried and salted
                            cow-hides is not prohibited.</p>
                        <p>You will communicate the contents of this circular to the sanitary
                            authorities of your jurisdiction.</p>
                        <p>The minister:</p>
                        <closer><signed>CH. TRICOUPIS.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>