<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1882-10-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1882-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="34" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                    <head>No. 34.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Logan</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Santiago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1882-10-31"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 31, 1882</date>.
                            (Received December 16.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 17.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to inform you that the sale of
                        1,000,000 tons of guano by the Chilian Government, advertised to take place
                        last August, but postponed until the 18th of the present month, came off in
                        this city upon the latter date.</p>
                    <p>There were nine bids in all, one of which came from the American firm of
                        Grace &amp; Co. The Chilian Government had adopted the standard <pb facs="0150" n="80" xml:id="pg_80"/> rate of the English market as the
                        basis of price. This standard relates to a unit founded upon the percentage
                        of nitrogen and phosphorus which different samples yield upon chemical
                        analysis. The; rate is 21 shillings for the unit of nitrogen, and 4½
                        shillings for the unit of phosphorus. The price of the guano per ton being
                        fixed, therefore, the real bidding took place upon what is called the <hi rend="italic">forfait</hi>, or the cost of removing it from its place of
                        deposit to the European market, which includes digging, shipping, bags,
                        insurance, landing charges, storage, porterage, commission, interest on
                        money, &amp;c. The effect of this was, of course, that the lowest bid for
                            <hi rend="italic">forfait</hi> left the Chilian Government the largest
                        price for the guano per ton delivered in Europe, at the foregoing
                        established rates.</p>
                    <p>The bidding upon the <hi rend="italic">forfait</hi> ranged from £5 10<hi rend="italic">s</hi>. to £2 19s. 10<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. per ton.
                        This latter bid was made by Miguel Baillie, of Paris, secured by an
                        indorser, and a deposit of $500,000 forfeit money in a Valparaiso bank.
                        Being far below all other bids, the contract was awarded to M. Baillie.</p>
                    <p>The impression of some here is that the bid is made by Dreyfus. All, however,
                        agree in the statement that the contractor can make no money out of it, but
                        upon the contrary must lose a considerable sum.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>C. A. LOGAN.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>