<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 347.Mr. Frelinghuysen to Mr. Carter.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d348</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">348</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1883-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1883-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1883-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1883-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="348"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d348">
                <head>No. 347.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Frelinghuysen</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Carter</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-12-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 6, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have had the honor to receive your note of the
                    18th of October last, inclosing a signed protest on the part of the Hawaiian
                    Government against the annexation of archipelagoes and islands of Polynesia by
                    foreign powers, and especially by Great Britain, in behalf of which protest the
                    sympathies of this Government are asked.</p>
                <p>It is unnecessary to assure you that the sympathies of this Government and the
                    people of this country are always in favor of good self-government by the
                    independent communities of the world.</p>
                <p>While we could not, therefore, view with complacency any movement tending to the
                    extinction of the national life of the intimately connected commonwealths of the
                    Northern Pacific, the attitude of this Government towards the distant outlying
                    groups of Polynesia is necessarily different.</p>
                <p>It is understood that the agitation to which the protest refers as now existing
                    in Australia contemplates the immediate protection and eventual annexation of
                    the New Hebrides, the Solomon Islands, and the immediately adjacent groups to
                    the Australian colonial system. <pb facs="0646" n="576" xml:id="pg_576"/> These
                    islands are geographically allied to Australasia rather than to Polynesia. At no
                    time have they go asserted and maintained a separate national life as to entitle
                    them to entrance, by treaty stipulations and established forms of competent
                    self-government, into the family of nations, as Hawaii and Samoa have done.
                    Their material development has been largely due to their intercourse with the
                    great Australian system, near which they lie, and this Government would not feel
                    called upon to view with concern any further strengthening of such intercourse,
                    when neither the sympathies of our people are touched nor their direct political
                    or commercial relations with those scattered communities threatened by the
                    proposed change.</p>
                <p>The President, before whom the protest has been brought, moved by these
                    considerations, does not regard the matter as one calling for the interposition
                    of the United States, either to oppose or support the suggested measure.</p>
                <p>Accept, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>FRED’K T. FRELINGHUYSEN.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
