<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 509.Mr. Foster
                            to Mr. Frelinghuysen.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d508</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">508</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1883-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1883-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="economic-sanctions" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665" lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558" lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807" lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1883-11-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1883-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="508" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d508">
                <head>No. 509.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-11-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 15, 1883</date>.
                            (Received December 3.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 102.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I transmit herewith a copy and translation of
                        a note dated the 8th instant, and received on the evening of the 13th, from
                        the minister <pb facs="0867" n="797" xml:id="pg_797"/> of state, in partial
                        reply to my several notes of July 2 and 3 last, relative to the claims of
                        American citizens on account of the embargo of their estates in Cuba. The
                        minister says that my notes have been transmitted to the minister of
                        ultramar for explanations of each one of the cases, and that I can
                        understand that the sums claimed and the verification of the allegations of
                        the claimants will necessarily delay the answer which is due to my notes,
                        but he assures me that the cases will be treated with justice and
                        equity.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>It will be noticed that he refers to the cases as “new claims “presented by
                        me, and as the character of the examination indicated in his note seems to
                        be upon that hypothesis, I have deemed it proper to correct any such
                        misapprehension, and I have accordingly sent to him a note of which I
                        inclose a copy.</p>
                <p>In a visit which I made to the ministry of state to-day I called the
                        minister’s attention to the note which I had sent him and urged the
                        importance of the early consideration of the cases. He promised to read my
                        note with care and to give the matter as early examination as was
                        possible.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                102.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Gomez</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of
                                    State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <placeName type="venue">
                                <hi rend="italic">Palace</hi>
                            </placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-11-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 8, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have informed myself of the notes
                            which your excellency was pleased to address to my predecessor, the
                            Marquis de la Vega de Armijo, at the time minister of state, under dates
                            of the 2d and 3d of July last, claiming in the name of the Government of
                            the Union the return to various American citizens of the property which
                            they possessed in Cuba, embargoed in consequence of certain judicial and
                            gubernative dispositions adopted on account of the insurrection which
                            took place in that island in 1869, and whose return was ordered by the
                            Spanish Government by the decrees of the 12th of July, 1873, and 20th
                            October, 1877.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency will understand that the importance of the amount claimed
                            in those notes, as well as the necessity to verify its exactness and to
                            ascertain if the claimants, treated in the present case in the same
                            manner as His Majesty’s subjects, have made use of all the measures
                            which Spanish legislation concedes to them for the defense of their
                            interests, and if they have been in fact injured by the authorities in
                            Cuba, against which the interested parties prefer certain charges which
                            the Government can only repel. Meanwhile that they are not justified,
                            all these circumstances tend necessarily to delay the answer due to the
                            notes of your excellency referred to, which have been transmitted by
                            this ministry to that of ultramar, in order that it may be pleased to
                            make the necessary explanations of each one of the cases cited in
                            them.</p>
                    <p>The Government of His Majesty, which has already paid $1,093,858 on
                            account of the decisions of the commission of arbitration, and which
                            will soon pay $494,860 on account of the late awards of the said
                            commission agreed upon before adjourning, all this in the space of
                            twelve or fourteen years, will examine with equal spirit of rectitude
                            and of justice the new claims presented by your excellency, and will not
                            fail at the same time to treat them with that justness and equity which
                            their importance and proportions may exact after careful
                            examination.</p>
                    <p>This is all I am able at the moment to state to your excellency, to whom
                            I renew, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>SERVANDO RUIZ GOMEZ.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0868" n="798" xml:id="pg_798"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 102.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Gomez</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-11-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 14,
                                    1883</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your excellency’s note of the 8th instant, relating to the
                            claim of various American citizens arising out of the embargo of their
                            estates in Cuba, and which claims were the subject of my notes of the 2d
                            and 3d of July last.</p>
                    <p>It is very gratifying to recognize the friendly spirit in which your
                            excellency’s note is couched and to receive the assurance that these
                            claims will be re-examined with rectitude and justice, and that they
                            will be treated with that justness and equity which their importance and
                            proportions may require. From the high spirit of equity and intelligence
                            which has always marked the long and distinguished public service of
                            your excellency, and from the friendly relations which have existed and
                            ever ought to exist between the Governments of Spain and the United
                            States, a no less favorable answer could have been expected; and I
                            congratulate myself that in the discharge of the urgent instructions
                            which I have received from the President of the United States on this
                            subject, I can count upon the conscientious co-operation of your
                            excellency in seeking a fair and early settlement of the questions
                            involved.</p>
                    <p>But in acknowledging the receipt of the note of the 8th instant I deem it
                            important to call attention without delay to what seems to be some
                            serious misapprehension in said note respecting these claims. They are
                            referred to by your excellency as “new claims” presented by me, and it
                            is to be supposed that, under this impression, it has been thought
                            necessary to refer them to the ministry of ultramar for the
                            investigation specified in the note of the 8th instant. But so far from
                            these being “new claims,” presented by me for the first time, the
                            records of your excellency’s department will show that they have been
                            the subject of frequent and voluminous correspondence between the two
                            Governments for fourteen years past, that the facts and principles
                            involved have been fully and carefully examined and decided in favor of
                            the claimants, and that almost all of them have by name and in detail
                            been considered and favorably adjudged in cabinet councils and made the
                            subject of royal decrees. In my note of July 3 citation is made of the
                            correspondence with your excellency’s department, of the examination
                            had, and of the royal decrees in favor of the claimants. Omitting a
                            reiteration of these notes, I desire to direct attention to some
                            historical facts not therein alluded to, of great importance in
                            connection with these claims, which will convince your excellency that
                            they were not only long since presented to the Spanish Government, but
                            were by it fully examined and definitely decided in favor of the
                            claimants.</p>
                    <p>As is well known they had their origin in 1869 in the unlawful embargo by
                            the military authorities during the revolution in Cuba. After six years
                            of effort on the part of the Government at Washington and of this
                            legation to bring the cases to a satisfactory settlement, the President
                            of the United States determined that some decided steps should be taken
                            to secure American citizens a prompt restoration of their estates in
                            Cuba and of their property and proceeds appropriated by military force.
                            In accordance with this determination the then Secretary of State, Mr.
                            Fish, addressed an instruction to the minister of the United States in
                            Madrid, dated November 5, 1876, in which he reviewed at length the
                            grievances of his Government against Spain growing out of the Cuban
                            insurrection, prominent among which were the embargoed claims now
                            pending and referred to in your excellency’s note. Mr. Fish, after
                            citing the royal decree of July 12, 1873, and the orders of the Spanish
                            Government, in which a return of the embargoed estates had been
                            directed, and after stating that the question had then been pending for
                            more than six years, used the following language: “The promises made and
                            repeated, the assurances given from time to time that something should
                            be done, the admission of the justice of the demands of this country, at
                            least to the extent of expressing regret for the wrongs, and promising
                            redress, followed, as they have been, by absolutely no performance and
                            no practical steps whatever towards performance, need no extended
                            comment.” Continuing a recital of the injuries which American citizens
                            had suffered from the Cuban insurrection, he says: “It becomes a serious
                            question how long such a condition of things can or should be allowed to
                            exist, and compels us to inquire whether the point has not been reached
                            when longer endurance ceases to be possible.* * * It is absolutely
                            necessary to the maintenance of our relations with Spain, eveu on their
                            present footing, that our just demands for the return to citizens of the
                            United States of their estates in Cuba unincumbered* * * should be
                            complied with.” He then directs the minister to communicate to the
                            Spanish Government the resolution of the President to bring the subject
                            of the Cuban revolution in its relation to the <pb facs="0869" n="799" xml:id="pg_799"/> United States to some definite attitude, “in the
                            firm conviction that the period has at last arrived when no other course
                            remains for this Government.”</p>
                    <p>A copy of this highly important instruction was also sent to the American
                            ministers in London, Paris, Berlin, St. Petersburg and Vienna, for
                            notification to the respective Governments of the intervention which the
                            President had decided to assume in the Cuban affairs.</p>
                    <p>While the instruction of November 5 was on its way, and before its
                            receipt, the Spanish minister of state sent to this legation a note
                            dated on the 15th of the same month, which, in response to the repeated
                            and urgent efforts of the minister, Mr. Cushing, seemed to consider, in
                            substance, all that the Government of the United States had contended
                            for in regard to these claims. In order to bring this note with all
                            possible dispatch to the notice of the Secretary of State at Washington,
                            Mr. Cushing sent a full abstract by telegraph and a copy of the same by
                            a special messenger, and advised delay in the contemplated action of the
                            President.</p>
                    <p>On the 30th of November, 1875, Mr. Cushing had an interview with the
                            minister of state, Señor Calderon y Collantes, in which he handed to him
                            a copy of Mr. Fish’s instruction of November 5, above cited, and
                            explained to him the modification or suspension of the President’s
                            action in Cuban affairs, which had been occasioned upon his (Mr.
                            Cushing’s) recommendation, by the favorable promises made in Señor
                            Calderon y Collantes’s note of November 15, 1875, and upon the
                            understanding that the grievances of the United; States would be
                            promptly redressed; and on the 4th of December following, Mr. Cushing
                            telegraphed to Washington that he had again seen the Spanish minister of
                            state; that Mr. Calderon y Collantes had carefully read Mr. Fish’s note
                            of November 5, and said he “admits our grievances; is opposed in
                            principle to sequestration of property of foreigners; condemns the
                            delays; will take up and promptly settle each case.”</p>
                    <p>Upon these repeated and positive assurances of a speedy examination and
                            satisfactory settlement of the embargoed estate claims and grievances
                            growing out of the Cuban revolution, the President desisted from the
                            action indicated in Mr. Fish’s instruction of November 5. Thereupon the
                            minister of the United States entered, with Señor Calderon y Collantes,
                            upon an examination of such of the claims as had not already been passed
                            upon. By reference to Mr. Cushing’s memorandum of January 31, 1876, his
                            note of February 6, and Señor Calderon y Collantes’s note of February 9,
                            1876, it will be seen that two of the most important cases referred to
                            in my note of July 3 last were then examined and finally settled (as it
                            was then supposed) by the royal decree of February 9, 1876. Without
                            extending the limits of this note by further citations (which are set
                            forth in full in my notes of July 3 last), reference to the records of
                            your excellency’s department will show that all these cases have been
                            examined and determined in favor of the claimants years ago, but that
                            the commands of His Majesty the King have been disobeyed and obstructed
                            by the authorities of Cuba.</p>
                    <p>I flatter myself that the foregoing narration will satisfy your
                            excellency that so far from these cases being “new claims” presented by
                            me, they have been of long standing, that their justness has been
                            affirmed in the most positive manner and under the most solemn
                            circumstances by the highest authority in Spain. It would seem,
                            therefore, that if any delay is now necessary for further examination,
                            it should only be to ascertain why the authorities of Cuba persist in
                            disobeying the King’s decrees, and what further injury has thereby been
                            occasioned to claimants. I am sure that my Government will not consider
                            it a satisfactory answer to my notes of July 2 and 3 last to be informed
                            at the end of four months that the cases have been referred to the
                            ministry of ultramar for examination, if that examination is to relate
                            to the merits of the claims and open up decisions long since settled,
                            and for the execution of which the faith of the Spanish Government has
                            been repeatedly pledged.</p>
                    <p>If, therefore, a misapprehension has occurred in the ministry of state in
                            supposing the cases in question to be “new claims,” and for this reason
                            a reference of them has been made to the ministry of ultramar, I beg
                            that your excellency will cause that mistake to be corrected. During the
                            fourteen years that these claims have been pending, they have been
                            repeatedly referred to the ministry of ultramar for information and
                            examination, and there doubtless exists in the ministry of state
                            voluminous data respecting them. As stated in my notes of July 2 and 3,
                            the President of the United States has specially charged me to press an
                            early settlement of this long-standing business upon the Spanish
                            Government, and I deem it my duty to again ask that the consideration of
                            the subject may be brought as rapidly as possible to a final and
                            satisfactory conclusion.</p>
                    <p>With this new opportunity it is pleasant, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
