<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 580.Mr. Frelinghuysen to Mr. Baker.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d579</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">579</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1883-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1883-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1883-01-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1883-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="579"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d579">
                <head>No. 580.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Frelinghuysen</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Baker</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-01-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 16, 1883</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 196.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the Department instruction of the
                    27th of September last, No. 183, relative to the claim of Mr. John E. Wheelock
                    against the Government of Venezuela, and to your dispatch of the 7th ultimo in
                    reply to that instruction, I desire to bring the subject again to your
                    attention. The facts and circumstances which gave rise to this claim were
                    brought to your notice in detail by the instruction of my predecessor, Mr.
                    Evarts, of the 15th of October, 1880, No. 91, and it is unnecessary to do more
                    than refer you to that instruction in regard to them. I fully concur in its
                    suggestion, and, in view of the facts as they are before the Department and
                    before your legation, find myself at no loss to account for the earnestness and
                    urgency of the claimant in regard to its settlement. In a case like this,
                    presenting, as it does, the clearest evidences of unusual cruelty and outrage to
                    a citizen of the United States by a civil officer of the Venezuelan Government,
                    in regard to which the Department has expressed itself so clearly, it is
                    expected that you will, in the spirit of the instructions which you have
                    received, exert your efforts with earnestness and energy to secure for the claim
                    a prompt hearing and a reasonably speedy adjustment. You are the representative
                    of this Government to that of Venezuela. Your residence at the capital of that
                    republic affords you opportunities of almost daily intercourse with the minister
                    of foreign relations. Opportune moments may be taken advantage of by you for
                    calling his attention to the unusual and what may seem unnecessary delays in
                    responding to your communications in matters intrusted to your care and
                    attention by your own Government.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>It is desired that you will give such attention to this claim as will secure for
                    it an early adjustment and settlement by the Government of Venezuela.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>FRED’K T. FRELINGHUYSEN.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
