<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 598.Mr. Baker to Mr. Frelinghuysen.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d597</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">597</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1883-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1883-09-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1883-09-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1883-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="597"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d597">
                <head>No. 598.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Baker</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-09-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 19, 1883</date>. (Received October
                        2.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 750]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to make a very succinct
                    statement respecting the honors given in Venezuela to Bolivar, one hundred years
                    after his birth.</p>
                <p>Bolivar was born in Caracas on the 24th of July, 1783. Venezuela celebrates the
                    centennial of his birth by certain ceremonies and by an exhibition.</p>
                <p>The principal of the ceremonies were those which took place on the 24th of July,
                    the birthday of Bolivar, and on the 31st of July, when a statue of Washington
                    was erected in Caracas.</p>
                <p>I give here a word to the first.</p>
                <p>Venezuela has a Pantheon, not dedicated, as in ancient Rome, to all the gods, but
                    to the deceased men of the country who are regarded as great. One can see in
                    this difference the great modification which time has wrought.</p>
                <p>Bolivar occupies a supreme place in the Pantheon of Venezuela. His remains are
                    there; his statue is there, at the end of the principal aisle of the
                    edifice.</p>
                <p>On the morning of the 24th of July, one hundred years after his birth, <pb
                        facs="0997" n="927" xml:id="pg_927"/> all the officiality of Caracas, and
                    that of foreign countries here present, followed by an imposing concourse of
                    people, moved in stately procession to the Pantheon. Then, after some words by
                    the President, many beautiful crowns or garlands, all of artificial flowers,
                    were placed on the pedestal of the monument of Bolivar, the President being the
                    first to deposit his offering; then the gentlemen in various representative
                    capacities, and finally the ladies.</p>
                <p>The procession then moved to the Plaza Bolivar, where stands an equestrian statue
                    of Bolivar, and on the base of this many floral offerings, artificial and
                    natural, were deposited.</p>
                <p>For my part, I deposited two crowns or garlands at the Pantheon and one in the
                    Plaza Bolivar. In depositing the last the President accompanied me, indicating
                    the place where the crown of immortelles which I bore in my hand should be
                    deposited, and saying, “Venezuela and the United States,” extended his hand to
                    mine at the base of the statue of Bolivar.</p>
                <p>So much for the morning act of the 24th of July.</p>
                <p>The night of the same day witnessed what is here termed the “apotheosis of
                    Bolivar,” the real meaning of the “apotheosis “being as much changed from its
                    ancient import as that of the word “pantheon.”</p>
                <p>The large new theater of Caracas, brilliantly illuminated, and filled in all its
                    circles, was the scene of this act, and presented, truth to say, a really
                    magnificent spectale. The act consisted principally of music and of floral
                    offerings to Bolivar. As at the pantheon, the President first presented his
                    offering, advancing to the stage and laying it before a bust of Bolivar. Then
                    followed various floral offerings in various representative character, until
                    this part of the ceremony was finished (except as to the United States). For the
                    rest I translate from the account of the act as given by the Opinion National of
                    the 6th ultimo, an account which, though containing some erroneous details, is
                    correct as to the general spirit of the scene: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>After this, agreeable surprise and profound commotion was caused in all
                            the surroundings upon seeing the commodore of the American squadron
                            anchored at La Guayra, Mr. G. H. Cooper, in full uniform, accompanied by
                            the minister resident of the United States, Mr. Baker, and Mrs. Baker,
                            and by the several naval officials of that friendly nation, advance to
                            the proscenium, carrying a beautiful garland. Once there, they separated
                            into two wings and offered a passage to the honorable minister and his
                            worthy wife, who were to place the offering at the pedestal of the bust
                            along with the others, by which they generously evinced their admiration
                            of our liberator and hero. The public could not restrain the vivid
                            emotions caused by this eloquent mark of sympathy, and broke forth into
                            loud and prolonged applause, as much at the approach as at the return of
                            the amiable and distinguished guests; and in all the boxes and on all
                            the sofas the ladies also applauded with the greatest enthusiasm in
                            order to signify to our brothers of the North in what high estimation we
                            hold the kind proofs of their most valuable friendship and the cordial
                            relations which exist between Venezuela and the Great Republic. General
                            Guzman Blanco, standing in his box, led the applause in the ovation.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JEHU BAKER.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
