<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 75.Mr. Young to Mr. Frelinghuysen..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1883</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1883-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1883-01-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recg3iRrscBAKUZil" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="narcotics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85095095"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Opium</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85086967"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monopoly</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recSGyPwUYTaLPhEi" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038182"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Consular service</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recuY33deeMLOZJV6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123713"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Smuggling</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recbfb6dc62c599a48" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recOAfZ9FRSJKK76a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Income tax</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recBTfVgprHsl1J9K" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85047074"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Famine</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1883-01-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1883-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="75"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d75">
                <head>No. 75.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Young</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Frelinghuysen</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1883-01-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 29, 1883</date>. (Received March
                        26.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 115.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As a further reference to the subject of my
                    dispatch, No. 34, I have the honor to inclose you a copy of a letter addressed
                    to the legation by the Rev. Dr. Hopper, an American missionary long resident in
                    Canton, discussing with clearness and ability many phases of the opium question.
                    I commend the views of Dr. Hopper to the Department, as a part of the history of
                    this agitation. I inclose also several extracts from recent Indian newspapers,
                    giving some arguments on the other side, arguments in favor of the opium trade,
                    as held by the official Indian class.</p>
                <p>While the opium trade does not materially concern the United States, we cannot
                    look without interest and sympathy upon the movement to suppress it. This
                    movement received a marked impulse from the anti-opium clause in our recent
                    convention with China. I never see the viceroy Li without his bringing up the
                    question. I always say to the viceroy, and others who refer to the opium trade,
                    that everything is to be expected from the humanity, justice and magnanimity of
                    a Christian people like the people of England. When they come to realize the
                    scope and volume of the degredation imposed upon China by the use of opium, they
                    will suppress it, even if the Indian revenue were twenty times as large. In my
                    latest conversation with the viceroy, I recalled the agitation against slavery
                    in the West Indies, and the victory which came to a good cause after so many
                    years of earnest and disheartening <pb facs="0252" n="182" xml:id="pg_182"/>
                    effort on the part of Wilberforce and his allies. Powerful, also, as the opium
                    interest appeared to be now, it was not as strong as slavery in my own country
                    twenty-five years ago. Public opinion in the end destroyed slavery, public
                    opinion would destroy, opium, only remained for China to keep her cause steadily
                    before the world, and for the rulers to show the sincerity of their protests by
                    suppressing the growth of the poppy, and throwing were possible municipal
                    restriction round the opium shops.</p>
                <p>The calamity to be feared is that the opium habit will take so strong a hold of
                    China that any successful effort to suppress it would be beyond even the power
                    the Emperor. * * *</p>
                <p>The suggestion of Dr. Hopper that a special embassy should be sent from China to
                    England, to negotiate, or I might say, intercede as to opium, is I am informed;
                    under consideration by the cabinet.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JNO. RUSSELL YOUNG.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 115.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Substance of Dr. <persName type="from">Hopper</persName>’s
                            letter to Mr. <persName type="to">Young</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>There has arisen lately a class of writers who consider the use of opium as a
                        harmless luxury, and some even as a healthful tonic and preservative against
                        malaria. This arises because of $40,000,000 of revenue which India derives
                        from the monopoly of the growth in its own territory and the transit dues
                        which it levies on that which has to pass through its territory to a seaport
                        for shipment to China. All the opium grown in Indian territory is grown for
                        the Indian Government, which has the entire monopoly of its sale, paying the
                        cultivators less actually for growing it than they would realize by the
                        growth of other crops, the Government realizing the whole of the profits. On
                        that grown by the native states Of Malva, which have no seaport, the Indian
                        Government levies a transit duty of more than $300 a chest. The Government
                        of India levies just as much as the commodity will bear and not stop its
                        growth. It having been represented that the amount levied for several years
                        past was stopping its growth, it has lowered the amount from 650 rupees a
                        chest to 600 rupees. Yet the same Government which exacts such an enormous
                        transit revenue refuses to allow China to levy transit duty on the
                        same-commodity into different ports of China, lest it should operate by the
                        enhanced cost of it to the consumer against the sale of the present quantity
                        of the drug.</p>
                    <p>There are some points in the discussion as now conducted that need your
                        careful consideration.</p>
                    <p>1. Sir Thomas Wade, for a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi>, agreed in the
                        state paper called “the Chefoo Convention” to permit the Chinese to levy
                        transit duty <hi rend="italic">ad libitum</hi> (called here “<hi
                            rend="italic">lekin</hi> tax”). The English have been in possession of
                        what they obtained, but have to this time not given the Chinese what was
                        promised in that convention. Last year Sir Thomas Wade was in conference
                        with his excellency Li Hung Chang for months in this matter of opium, his
                        excellency Li wishing to levy an import of 150 taels per chest, Sir Thomas
                        only consenting to 90 or 100. Sir Thomas was called home to give information
                        to the home Government on this point mainly.</p>
                    <p>2. The Chinese Government, failing to effect any cessation of its import from
                        India, is trying a most dangerous and ineffectual plan, viz, permitting the
                        native growth, in hopes thereby to supplant the India-grown drug. This
                        scheme has failed in its purpose, the Indian drug continuing to come in the
                        same quantity and to be sold at the same prices, whilst all the native
                        growth is consumed by the multiplication of new victims in the ports where
                        the native drug is grown. Sir Robert Hart, in the preface to the customs
                        pamphlet on opium, estimated the native growth at 100,000 chests, the same
                        as the imported quantity. Mr. Donald Spence, of the English consular service
                        at Ichang, presents facts showing the growth of opium in the west provinces
                        to be 224,000 chests.</p>
                    <p>Sir Robert Hart fixed upon three <hi rend="italic">mace</hi> a day as the
                        average daily consumption of smokers, and thus concluded that there were
                        2,000,000 opium smokers in China. In a paper on “The number of opium smokers
                        in China,” I challenged the daily average of three <hi rend="italic"
                            >mace</hi> as too large, and argued for one <hi rend="italic">mace</hi>.
                        In this estimate Dr. Dudgeon has concurred, as also Mr. Spence. I argued
                        that the facts of the case as presented by travelers and others would lead
                        to the inference that the number of smokers was <pb facs="0253" n="183"
                            xml:id="pg_183"/> at least from ten to twelve millions. On the estimate
                        of 100,000 chests of native growth, there was drug enough to supply that
                        number of smokers, but the amount of native drug as reported by Mr. Spence
                        supplies more than sufficient of the drug for that number, and the number of
                        smokers now cannot be much short of 15,000,000.</p>
                    <p>3. It is known to you that China has inserted a clause in the treaty with the
                        United States forbidding United States citizens to engage in this trade. A
                        similar clause has been introduced into the treaty with Russia and also with
                        Braizil. The Chinese Government evidently wished in this way to bring public
                        opinion to bear upon England. But England seeks to insure to India the
                        export of the drug to China, and thereby hold the large revenue that she has
                        from that source. To do this the English Government has to secure, the
                        entrance of this drug into China, and also has to quiet the agitation that
                        is now going on in England in regard to the morality of the opium trade as
                        now conducted. As to China, England refuses to permit China to discourage
                        this drug by levying a larger duty on it, either as import duty or <hi
                            rend="italic">lekin</hi> tax, thus curtailing China’s right as a
                        sovereign power in her own territory. In England there is a combined effort
                        to misrepresent the evils of the use of opium, and also to misrepresent
                        England’s responsibility for the introduction of the vice into China, and
                        for forcing the trade upon the latter country. A strong point which the
                        English, will now urge at home is that the quantity imported is small as
                        compared with that which is grown, and, therefore, the stopping of the
                        import would not arrest the consumption of opium, but would only stimulate
                        the Chinese to a more extensive growth to supply the deficiency occasioned
                        by the withdrawal of the Indian drug. To quiet the anti-opium agitation in
                        England the British Government is directing great efforts. Sir Thomas Wade
                        has been called home to give information. Mr. Baker, who has spent some four
                        years in West China collecting facts on native growth, on his way to England
                        visited the governor-general of India, at Simla, with the object, I have no
                        doubt, of putting the Indian Government in possession of all the facts about
                        native growth. When Sir Thomas went home he called Mr. Spence (who has been
                        in West China since Mr. Baker left) from his station at once, and took him
                        home to England, although Mr. Spence told some of his, colleagues in the
                        service that he was called from West China to go to some other port Putting
                        these three things together, I think a strong effort is to be made to quiet
                        this opium agitation in England as entirely uncalled for, on the ground that
                        the India-grown drug is small as compared with that grown in China.</p>
                    <p>4. I know full well that the Chinese Government has stated again and again
                        that they only permit the growth of opium temporarily in order to stop
                        import from India, and I believe that so far as his excellency, Li Hung
                        Chang is concerned, it has been done sincerely with that view. But his
                        excellency needs to be shown that it has entirely, or nearly entirely,
                        failed to effect anything in that way, and that it is affecting two most
                        serious results: First, it is causing many of China’s friends to doubt his
                        own sincerity in his expressed desire to stop the opium trade, and it
                        affords the defenders of English complicity in the evil the apparently just
                        grounds to say that, his great desire to stop the Indian import is that the
                        Chinese Government may derive the whole profit from the native grown opium.
                        This conviction, if allowed to spread, will quiet the agitation in England
                        and settle the evils of the Indian import <hi rend="italic">en
                            permanence</hi>. The second evil of permitting the native growth is that
                        it is getting so rooted in the country and raising up such a vast army of
                        opium-smokers in all the provinces that the Government will be no longer
                        able to arrest its growth, even if it should try. The high officials need to
                        have their minds awakened to this matter. This enormous production of the
                        native drug has nearly all come to pass within the last, fifteen years.</p>
                    <p>The American Government having entered into treaty agreeing to forbid its
                        citizens to engage in the import or selling of opium, has a right to
                        remonstrate against such an increase of a trade from which its citizens are
                        excluded by treaty, the United States Government only acceding to such a
                        stipulation on the implied understanding that China was desirous to stop the
                        trade, both external and internal, entirely. But instead of taking any
                        effective measures to stop the native growth it is increasing enormously
                        yearly, with the knowledge of the Chinese Government, and, of course, with
                        its consent.</p>
                    <p>The Chinese have tried various means to get control of the foreign drug. Last
                        year it was proposed to form a syndicate with twenty millions of dollars
                        capital, which would take the whole of the India-grown drug and pay the
                        Chinese Government 150 taels duty, thus having the monopoly of the sale of
                        it and relieving the Chinese Government of all responsibility for the
                        prevention of smuggling. This was with the condition that 10,000 femer
                        chests should be supplied each year, and thus in ten years the whole import
                        should cease. Sir Thomas refused to agree, aud so it fell through.</p>
                    <p>I have in various ways presented to the Chinese Government that it can only
                        get rid of the opium trade by sending a special embassy to England to
                        represent the evils which China suffers from the opium trade—as the United
                        States sent a special embassy to China to represent the evils it suffered
                        from coolie emigration, and authorize this <pb facs="0254" n="184"
                            xml:id="pg_184"/> embassy to enter into a convention or mutual
                        stipulation that, while England diminishes the amount of opium produced in
                        India for the Chinese market year by year, say, ten or fifteen or twenty
                        thousand chests, China should stop the native growth <hi rend="italic"
                            >instanter</hi> and give England the right to examine as to the
                        fulfillment of this stipulation by the former country.</p>
                    <p>I hold that if such an embassy were sent to England for such a purpose, the
                        moral sentiment of the world would be so expressed in the newspapers and
                        other ways of expressing public opinion as virtually to force England to
                        accede and agree to such a proposal. But China is so inexperienced in the
                        ways of western diplomacy that she shrinks from proposing such a thing lest
                        she should fail, and thus experience a humiliation before the eyes of many
                        people. But in the present state of the general conscience on this subject
                        at present, such an embassy would be in no danger of failing in effecting
                        such a convention between the two nations. * * * Russia and Brazil, as well
                        as the United States, would be bound by their treaties with China to express
                        sentiments at the court of London favorable to such a convention. All
                        nations are interested in it commercially, because now China expends the
                        whole of the value of the tea and silk she exports in paying for the
                        imported opium from India, and hence has little money to pay for other kinds
                        of imports. But there is every reason to believe that if she could save the
                        money now expended on Indian opium she would purchase to that amount at
                        least of other kinds of imports.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 115.—Extract from an Indian
                            newspaper.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">opium and the indian revenue</hi>.</head>
                    <p>“Would the extinction of £5,000,000 Indian revenue this very day involve
                        either national insolvency or the imposition of new taxation amounting to
                        cruelty?” This is the question which the Anti-Opium Association has
                        addressed to Major Baring in reply to his budget speech. Of course the
                        association answers its own question in the negative, and it quotes in
                        support of its view the authority of the brothers Strackey:</p>
                    <p>“It would undoubtedly be possible to increase largely the income of the state
                        without serious injury to the industry of the country, and without political
                        danger, in the event of great financial emergency, such, for instance, as
                        might conceivably, though not improbably, arise if we were suddenly to lose
                        the greater part of our opium revenue, or if the difficulties caused by the
                        fall in the value of silver in relation to gold should attain to very
                        alarming dimensions.”</p>
                    <p>Before going further we would state the figures of the problem with more
                        exactness. The net opium revenue for 1878–’79 was about six and a half
                        millions sterling, and though the Anti-Opium Association, to suit their own
                        purposes, desire to show the revenue as low as possible, and give therefore
                        only the figures for Bengal, yet they do in fact want us to suppress the
                        export from India altogether. This would entail not only the loss of the
                        whole net revenue above stated, but a very large outlay in prevention of
                        export and in compensation to the Malua states. Let us, however, state the
                        loss with which India is threatened by the great anti-opium movement at home
                        (which will, we fear, eventually succeed, unless the Indian Government
                        encounters it much more vigorously than at present) at 6,000,000 net; it
                        will then be but common prudence to consider beforehand how such a loss can
                        be met, whether it befalls us suddenly, at the hands of the imperial
                        Parliament, or whether it comes upon us gradually from the action of the
                        Chinese. The probability is that both causes will act together. We may
                        expect that under popular pressure the home Government will abolish the
                        Bengal monopoly, and will encourage the Chinese Government to raise the
                        tariff duty on opium and to levy the <hi rend="italic">lekin</hi>, or local
                        transit thereon under the provisions of the Chefoo convention. Also that the
                        Chinese Government, thus assured of British sympathy, will gladly adopt this
                        means of obtaining an enhanced customs revenue, and will at the same time
                        vigorously push on the domestic cultivation to which, of course, the
                        enhanced price of the foreign drug will give a natural impulse. Thus it
                        appears to us certain that, in no long period of time, the Indian revenues
                        must suffer a loss in the substitution of a duty for the Bengal monopoly.
                        The amount realized by China on the opium imports under the present tariff
                        rate is about two millions sterling. Enhancement of the tariff duty and
                        imposition of <hi rend="italic">lekin</hi> will probably more than double
                        this: and, as most of what is gained to the Chinese Government will probably
                        be loss to that of India, we arrive at the loss stated under the Chefoo
                        convention. Again, the Bengal production, on an average of twenty years
                        past, has been 50,000 chests, which, by a duty of 600 rupees per chest,
                        would yield only three crores. Thus the loss in this measure (allowing for
                        that already reckoned under the Chefoo convention, which would affect the
                        present income under <pb facs="0255" n="185" xml:id="pg_185"/> the monopoly)
                        would he about one and one-half crores of rupees. It is thus a very safe and
                        sober calculation to estimate the probable diminution of the Indian revenues
                        in the matter of opium under the combined action of the home and Chinese
                        Governments at 3,000,000 sterling. From what source is this sum to be made
                        good?</p>
                    <p>The brothers Strackey have suggested the following possible sources of
                        increased revenue:</p>
                    <p>Income and license taxes, £1,500,000; registration, £500,000; tobacco tax,
                        £3,000,000 to £4,000,000; sugar, £1,000,000; railway traffic, £500,000.</p>
                    <p>Of these, however, the principal ones (tobacco and sugar) are condemned by
                        them “as impracticable, except under the pressure of some financial
                        catastrophe so great that it would justify almost any experiment.” The
                        license tax already yields eighty-six lacs net, and an income tax yielding
                        one and one-half crores additional is hardly conceivable. A tax on railway
                        traffic would practically come out of the railway returns which depend upon
                        the cheapening of traffic rates, so nothing would really be gained by that.
                        The supposed half million from registration is purely speculative and may be
                        dismissed from consideration. Where then are the three millions sterling to
                        be made up with the loss of which the Indian revenue is threatened? We have
                        answered the question many times before: it is in the pockets of the Bengal
                        zemindars.</p>
                    <p>The admitted rental of the Bengal zemindars is 18,000,000 sterling, but as
                        estimated by Sir George Campbell, when lieutenant-governor of Bengal, it was
                        “probably more than 20,000,000 sterling.” Now, in 1793, when Lord Cornwallis
                        took the tax collectors or publicans of the day and created them
                        proprietors, each in his own circle of collection, their aggregate income or
                        share of the government revenue retained by them in payment for collection
                        must have been far below one-half million. Mr. justice Cunningham, in his
                        “British India and its Rulers,” says: “The revenue in 1793 was about
                        3,000,000, and as the zemindar’s share was fixed at a tenth of the revenue
                        (so fixed from the time of the Moguls), it cannot have been more than
                        between £300,000 and £400,000.” No wonder then than Sir George Campbell said
                        of these Bengal land-holders that “we have created in their favor an
                        enormous property which never existed before * * * a property utterly
                        unknown to any native government”— or indeed to our own English system
                        either. And what have we had for it? Nothing. Mr. O’Kinealy, in his note on
                        Enhancement, attached to the report of the Bengal Rent Law Commission,
                        computes that these “descendants of Calcutta money dealers or of native
                        officials,” who, as Mill says, “live as useless drones on the soil which has
                        been given up to them,” extract from the ryots a sum which, if capitalized,
                        “represents 165,000,000 sterling taken out of the pockets of the poor and
                        put in the pockets of the rich, and do nothing for them or the country in
                        return.” (Cunningham’s British India, page 302.) No wonder then that Mill
                        says, “Whatever the Government has given up of its pecuniary claims for the
                        creation of such a class has at the best been wasted.”</p>
                    <p>Though the admitted rental of the Bengal zemindars is stated at thirteen
                        millions, Mr. Cunningham considers that the amount really taken by them from
                        the ryots is at least double that figure. Adding expenses, illegal
                        exactions, the expenses of litigation, and a share of the expenditure on
                        police, the total payments, he considers, do not fall short of twenty-five
                        or thirty millions sterling, and he speaks practically, with the authority
                        of the famine commission. This estimate tallies with Sir George Campbell’s,
                        and would show that Bengal ought, at the revenue rates of other provinces,
                        to yield to the imperial treasury eight or nine millions more of land
                        revenue than it does now under the permanent settlement, and what have we in
                        return for the surrender of this vast sum? Mr. Cunningham tells us we have
                        “the creation of a body of landlords who are described as not particularly
                        prosperous, and of whom their warmest advocate can scarcely venture to
                        affirm that they perform any one of the public duties which attach to the
                        corresponding class in England, and of a corresponding class of tenantry
                        whose unsatisfactory condition forces itself with increasing vehemence year
                        by year on the public attention.”</p>
                    <p>Not only is this so, but there has been another remarkable result.</p>
                    <p>Bengal has nearly one-third of the population of British India, and in wealth
                        and prosperity it represents very much more than one-third, of the Empire,
                        hut evidently with a land revenue fixed on a scale of ninety years ago, it
                        cannot and does not bear one-third of the public burdens, though it appears
                        to do so, because most of the revenue of opium and customs is credited in
                        Ben gal. So far, however, from really bearing its share of the general
                        burden, “the richest province in India has been to a large extent defended,
                        administered, educated, supplied with roads, barracks, hospitals, railways
                        and canals, and relieved in the famine at the expense of the rest of the
                        community. Ryots have been toiling in Madras and starving in the Deccan, in
                        order that gentlemen like the rajahs of Durbhunga and Burduan may enjoy
                        incomes of several hundred thousand pounds a year free from the rude contact
                        of the tax collector’s hand.”</p>
                    <p>Of course it is quite out of the question that the whole eight or nine
                        millions of short payment due from the zemindars of Bengal can ever be
                        entirely made good in <pb facs="0256" n="186" xml:id="pg_186"/> future, any
                        more than it can he recovered for the past; but nevertheless a portion
                        may.</p>
                    <p>There is no other reasonable proposition for making good a loss of opium
                        revenue, and such a loss can and must therefore be met by a revision of the
                        permanent settlement.</p>
                    <p>The sooner legislation declares that settlement liable to revision, the
                        earlier will it be possible to begin, recouping opium Josses, thereby. It
                        must be a very slow process, a long date will have to be given from the time
                        of the act, before reassessment shall be lawful; and after that date, when
                        reassessment may require to be made, it will have to be very gradual. The
                        doubling of the present Bengal land revenue, of three and a half millions,
                        which is the utmost increment that can be hoped for, will necessarily be a
                        very slow and cautious process, extending over a long period of years,
                        probally over a full generation.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 115.–Extract from the Pioneer
                            Mail, an Indian newspaper.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the opium question in china.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>We suppose that in due course of time the falsehoods published throughout
                        England on the subject of the Indian opium trade to China will be
                        discredited by their own virulence; but meanwhile, that they should meet any
                        credence at all is little to the credit of our countrymen’s common sense. A
                        Mr. Turner, among others, has published a book in which he typifies the
                        conduct of England, as follows: “The strong man knocks down the weak one,
                        sets his foot upon his chest, and demands, ‘Will you give me the liberty to
                        knock at your front door and supply your children with poison <hi
                            rend="italic">ad libitum</hi>?’”</p>
                    <p>It is fortunate that the Anti-Opium League are thus overdoing it, for thus we
                        may hope that they will defeat themselves. The British public and the London
                        journals, even the Spectator, must ere long begin to understand that no one
                        forces opium on China, and that no one wants to or does prevent China from
                        taxing opium; Then they will further comprehend that the fanatic’s object is
                        to deprive China of Indian opium, whether she wishes it or not; that they
                        not only wish the Indian Government to abandon a most profitable manufacture
                        and export on its own account, but also (as they know that this will only
                        increase the opium supply) they want the manufacture and export forcibly put
                        down altogether, and even the import into China forcibly prevented. And all
                        this at the cost of the Indian taxpayer.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 115.—Extract from the Shanghai
                            Courier.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">the opium trade.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>As to the way in which the contraband trade in foreign opium was carried on
                        in China fifty years ago, the Englishman says it at once shows how little
                        would be the gain to morality if the views of the anti-opium agitators were
                        carried out, and explains the dissatisfaction with which the mandarin class
                        regard a system under which the importation of the drug into China is
                        legalized.</p>
                    <p>The effect of laws which prohibited the importation of opium under pain of
                        death was not to prevent the trade, but to fill the pockets of the local
                        officials who winked at it for a consideration. The demoralizing effects of
                        an irresistible temptation to corruption were thus superadded to whatever
                        evil may have resulted from the consumption of the drug. This temptation
                        would certainly be none the less effective, now that the habit of opium
                        smoking is fifty years older and the number of the population addicted to it
                        has enormously increased. Even if the Government of India were induced to
                        play into the hands of the mandarins by preventing the export of the drug,
                        or the cultivation of the plant itself, the effect would be only a temporary
                        diminution of the supply. Not only would an immense expansion of the
                        cultivation of the plant in China ensue, to the great advantage of the local
                        officials and the detriment of consumers throughout the country, but a
                        powerful stimulus would be given to opium growing in various other countries
                        where climate conditions are quite as favorable to it as in India. Thus,
                        while in China, the cause of morality would suffer rather than gain, the
                        Government and people of India would be impoverished to the extent of
                        several millions sterling annually for the sake of a chimera. The trade
                        checked, it may be for a time, to the advantage of no one except the corrupt
                        Chinese official and to the great distress of many, would, in the end, pass
                        into the hands of less <pb facs="0257" n="187" xml:id="pg_187"/> scrupulous
                        or more practical rivals. The peasantry of India would groan under
                        insuperable burdens, public works would be stopped, and the services would
                        be starved for want of funds and all progress, except ail the road to ruin,
                        would be at an end. In the mean time the superfine moralists of Exeter Hall
                        would have the satisfaction of knowing that, however much evil might
                        flourish in-China, the British nation at least had no concern in it, and
                        however much misery might have been increased in India, it was amply
                        compensated for by a sense of the virtue of self-denial.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
