<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Director General of the United Nations Relief
                    and Rehabilitation Administration ( (Lehman))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d261</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">261</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-11-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="261"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d261">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">512.4A1A1/10–444</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Director General of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation
                        Administration</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lehman</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-13">November 13,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I acknowledge the receipt of your note of October
                    4, 1944 in which you submitted to this Government for its comments the English
                    texts of the draft Sanitary Conventions which were approved in principle by the
                    Council at its Second Session in Montreal.</p>
                <p>The appropriate officers of this Government have now completed their review of
                    the English texts. I wish to advise you that the draft Conventions are, in
                    general, acceptable to this Government.</p>
                <p>There are numerous places in the drafts where in our opinion the wording or
                    drafting style could be improved upon but we do not consider it necessary to
                    insist that any changes of this nature be made. However, for your convenience I
                    am attaching a memorandum<note n="38" xml:id="d261fn38">Not printed.</note>
                    calling attention to certain instances in which, in our opinion, some such
                    changes might be made. The Department will be pleased to put at your disposal an
                    officer of the Treaty Section of the Division of Research and Publication to
                    collaborate with your staff in the editorial work of preparing the Conventions
                    in final form.</p>
                <pb facs="0361" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/>
                <p>The French texts submitted with your note of October 19, 1944<note n="39"
                        xml:id="d261fn39">Not printed.</note> have been examined by the Central
                    Translating Division of this Department and I am attaching a memorandum<note
                        n="39" xml:id="d261fn40">Not printed.</note> containing certain suggestions
                    of relatively minor importance for improving the wording of these texts.</p>
                <p>As I advised you in my letter of August 26, 1944, it is the view of this
                    Government that the proposed Conventions should be submitted to the United
                    States Senate for its advice and consent before the Conventions are brought into
                    force as to the United States. Accordingly, it may be necessary for the United
                    States Government to delay its signature of the Conventions until after their
                    consideration by the Senate.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
