<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="455" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d455">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">800.796–1244</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Berle</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Delegate of the French Committee of National Liberation</hi>
                            (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hoppenot</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-19">September 19,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Hoppenot</hi>: I have received your letter
                        of September 12, 1944,<note n="81" xml:id="d455fn81">Not printed.</note>
                        replying to our invitation to the French Delegation to hold exploratory
                        talks on the subject of post-war civil aviation and note that for reasons
                        which are quite understandable, it has been impossible for the Delegation to
                        enter upon these discussions up to this time.</p>
                    <p>In the meantime, as you no doubt are aware, on September 11, 1944, the United
                        States Government issued an invitation to a large number of nations to
                        attend a Conference on International Civil Aviation to be held in the United
                        States beginning November 1st next. Such an invitation was extended to the
                        French Delegation and we sincerely hope that France will be represented at
                        that Conference. In the light of these developments, it is probably of less
                        importance that the preliminary exploratory talks be held. However, if you
                        are able to assemble in Washington, in advance of the Conference, the people
                        whom you would like to have explore informally some of these questions with
                        us, we shall be glad to confer with them along the lines of our original
                        suggestion.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Berle, Jr</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>