<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The New Zealand Prime Minister ( (Fraser) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d460</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">460</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="air-safety"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recIT3Pf4nhjHnc6Z" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003759"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Innocent passage</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="460"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d460">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.796/10–2644</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The New Zealand Prime Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Fraser</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="89" xml:id="d460fn89">Transmitted to the Department by the New Zealand
                        Legation in covering memorandum dated October 26, 1944.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Wellington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-27">27 September,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Secretary of State</hi>: I have to refer to the
                    discussions which took place during my visit to Washington in July last with Mr.
                    Grew, Mr. Berle and other representatives of the United States Government
                    concerning the future development of Civil Aviation, and to the copy which was
                    then handed to me of the summary dated 24th March of objectives favoured by the
                    United States of America with respect to post-war civil air transport. To this
                    was attached a copy of a draft form of bilateral agreement relating to the
                    operation of international air transport services.</p>
                <p>I informed Mr. Grew and the other representatives of the United States Government
                    at this meeting that the summary of objectives would be considered and that I
                    would later inform you in writing of my views.</p>
                <p>The New Zealand Government have given careful consideration to the basis on which
                    air services on international routes should be operated and their conclusions
                    are, as I stated during the course of the meeting in Washington, as defined in
                    the agreement made at Canberra in January of this year between the Australian
                    and New Zealand Governments. As a first principle, the New Zealand Government
                    hold the view that air services on international air trunk routes should be
                    operated by an international air transport authority, which would own the
                    aircraft employed on these services and ancillary equipment. It has become
                    evident in the period which has elapsed since the publication of this agreement
                    that the principle of international operation of trunk air routes may not prove
                    wholly acceptable and as an alternative the New Zealand Government support a
                    system whereby air services on international trunk routes would be developed and
                    operated under the control of an international authority which should be
                    established as soon as possible. This authority should possess regulatory powers
                    in the technical and economic fields. Within the framework of such an authority,
                    the <pb facs="0558" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/> New Zealand Government would be
                    willing to subscribe to the grant to all signatory powers of the four following
                    freedoms of the air:— <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The right to innocent passage.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The right to land for emergency, refueling, etc.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The right to disembark passengers, etc. from the aircraft’s own
                            country of origin.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The right to embark passengers, etc. for the aircraft’s own country of
                            origin.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>A system of international co-operation on the lines suggested above would afford
                    equal opportunity to the air carriers of all nations, in accordance with some
                    such principle as traffic interest, and ensure that with full recognition of the
                    needs of security, air services were operated with appropriate regard to the
                    national interests and needs of all States.</p>
                <p>Subject to the principles outlined, the New Zealand Government find themselves in
                    agreement with many of the objectives stated in the paper dated 24th March
                    submitted by your delegation. The forthcoming conference to be held in the
                    United States of America commencing on the 1st November next, will afford
                    opportunity for consideration in detail of the objectives favoured by the United
                    States and other interested Governments and the New Zealand delegation to this
                    Conference will be in a position to state and discuss the views of the New
                    Zealand Government.</p>
                <p>I should like to say in conclusion how much I valued the opportunity which my
                    visit to America gave me for discussions on the subject of civil aviation and I
                    am hopeful that the forthcoming conference to be held in your country will yield
                    an agreement which will ensure that air services on international trunk routes
                    are operated on an orderly and equitable basis.</p>
                <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>P. <hi rend="smallcaps">Fraser</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
