<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d517</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">517</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recDV1FNGQhoilizZ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90000897"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconstitution</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="517"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d517">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50/8–2344</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In H.M. Embassy’s memorandum of 17th August on the handling of requirements for
                    reconstruction in Europe, reference was made to the possible establishment of a
                    European Economic Committee in London. H.M. Government have been giving further
                    and urgent consideration to this question and feel that an amplification of
                    their views might be of interest to the U.S. Government.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Just as, in matters of relief and rehabilitation, the basic principle of
                        the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration is to help the
                        liberated countries to help themselves, so in H.M. Government’s view should
                        this principle guide the approach to the problems of reconstruction. The
                        Anglo-American supply machinery is already strained for the prosecution of
                        the war and the maintenance of the civilian economies of the countries from
                        which supplies are drawn. It is therefore essential that every possible
                        resource in Europe should be utilized to the full before further demands are
                        made on the overseas sources. From this it would follow that the liberated
                        countries of Europe should first formulate and attempt to harmonize their
                        policies in the economic field and to define what may be needed from outside
                        the Continent of Europe before demands for these needs are placed on outside
                        resources. Only after such consideration should the Anglo-U.S. supply
                        machinery be called in to assist.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>If however the principle which has been enunciated above is to be put into
                        effect there must be established an organisation in Europe through which the
                        necessary consultation between European Allied countries can be achieved. It
                        was with this in mind that H.M. Government put forward the proposal for a
                        European Economic Committee. In such a Committee representatives of the
                        European Allies under the joint guidance of the United States, the Union of
                        Soviet Socialist Republics and of the United Kingdom could discuss such
                        matters as their several intentions in the matter of economic policy, the
                        manner in which they propose to help one another and the extent of their
                        initial commercial intercourse with neutrals. The Committee <pb facs="0629"
                            n="619" xml:id="pg_619"/> would, for example, consider such matters of
                        common concern as the national agricultural and industrial policies of the
                        various European countries and their effects on their neighbours. They would
                        discuss the respective claims of countries represented on the Committee to
                        materials and goods in short supply. In support of their request for help
                        from outside Europe the countries will wish to, and indeed should,
                        demonstrate that they can and will institute all proper safeguards to ensure
                        not only that maximum use is made of resources available in each
                        domestically but also that what is received through the offices of
                        Anglo-U.S. supply machinery is used to fullest advantage. The Committee
                        would exchange views and information accordingly on the measures which each
                        contemplated within its boundaries in such matters as rationing,
                        distribution, grain collection and dehoarding, black market, and kindred
                        measures necessary for the orderly reconstitution of their economies.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>It would then be necessary to consider, in the light of knowledge of the
                        intentions, proposed policies and denned needs of the European countries and
                        in the light of the views expressed by the American, British and Russian
                        representatives on the European Committee, to what extent it was desirable
                        to meet European countries’ requests through the agency of Combined Supply
                        machinery, and on what terms. One of the terms of help would naturally be
                        that the applicant countries should undertake to make their purchases from
                        sources, in quantities, and according to methods, acceptable to the
                        governments represented on the Combined Boards and, where desired, should
                        find for the Boards raw materials, finished goods, capacity and even
                        manpower from resources at their disposal. These matters could best be
                        discussed in Washington through the media of the consultative bodies already
                        established by the U.S. Government and H.M. Government, in which in some
                        cases the Government of Canada participates.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Some steps have already been taken which might assist in the evolution of
                        the proposed Committee. Economic Liaison Groups for France and Belgium
                        respectively have been set up in London with the assistance of the U.S.
                        Government in conjunction with both the French authorities and the Belgian
                        Government. The purpose of each of these two Groups has been to afford a
                        means for free discussion of economic questions affecting French and Belgian
                        interests. They have formed a most useful means for full and informal
                        discussion of problems both relating to the overseas empires of these two
                        countries and to the general economic problems likely to be faced after
                        liberation of metropolitan France and Belgium. It has always been understood
                        in these Committees, however, that major questions of policy relating to the
                        work of the Combined Boards would be resolved <pb facs="0630" n="620"
                            xml:id="pg_620"/> in Washington and formal tripartite bodies were
                        established in Washington for this purpose.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>H.M. Government has had under consideration the establishment of similar
                        Economic Liaison Groups with the Dutch and Norwegian Governments. Once these
                        two additional groups were established, these Economic Liaison Groups could
                        rapidly be developed into a pluripartite organisation which might become the
                        nucleus of a European Economic Committee. The march of military events in
                        Europe makes it, in the view of H.M. Government, a matter of extreme urgency
                        to press forward with every step that may be of assistance to the end of
                        establishing the widest possible form of collaboration on economic matters
                        between European countries. There may be considerable areas or even whole
                        countries in which there will be no military period as it has been
                        understood in the past. These would be hiatus areas for which, apart from
                        procurement undertaken under Plan A,<note n="6" xml:id="d517fn6">Plan A
                            represented a set of figures with respect to a program of supplies (for
                            all the areas of Europe to be liberated) which was produced by a working
                            party of representatives of the Department of State, the Foreign
                            Economic Administration, and the International Division of the Army,
                            which was given official approval by the Combined Civil Affairs
                            Committee on February 17, 1944; for further information on this subject,
                            see an article entitled “Supplies for Liberated Areas”, in the
                            Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, May 20, 1944, p.
                            469.</note> no one has any defined responsibilities. In view of military
                        developments H.M. Government considers that the establishment of these two
                        further groups should be undertaken as a matter of urgency.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>If the U.S. Government should agree with the setting up of Economic
                        Liaison Groups for the Dutch and Norwegian Governments with a view to their
                        early amalgamation with the existing Groups, H.M. Government would propose
                        forthwith to invite the Norwegian and Dutch Governments to participate.
                        Simultaneously H.M. Government would suggest that the U.S. Government should
                        join with them in proposing the formation of the European Economic Committee
                        to the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>It would moreover seem to be desirable to make arrangements for informal
                        consultation between the United States, United Kingdom and Soviet
                        representatives on the proposed economic committee so that there might be a
                        full exchange of views between these three Governments as to the best advice
                        and guidance to be given to the other European countries represented on the
                        Committee on economic matters. Subject to the agreement of the U.S.
                        Government, H.M. Government would therefore suggest that: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>the Soviet Government be consulted as soon as possible about the
                                establishment of the European Economic Committee</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>the Soviet Government be informed of the desire of the U.S.
                                Government and H.M. Government to arrange for informal consultation
                                between the three Governments on subjects within the terms of
                                reference of the European Economic Committee, and</item>
                            <pb facs="0631" n="621" xml:id="pg_621"/>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>the Soviet Government be further informed that the U.S. Government
                                and H.M. Government have already taken steps to set up a Combined
                                Liberated Areas Committee<note n="7" xml:id="d517fn7">For
                                    documentation on this subject, see <ref target="#pg_301">pp.
                                        301</ref> ff.</note> whose primary task will be to
                                coordinate Anglo-U.S. action for making available the combined
                                supply machinery in meeting where they can the needs of European
                                countries.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-23">23 August,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
