<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Winant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d57</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">57</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-09-18T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-09-18T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-18T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-18T23:00:00-05:00" n="57"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d57">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50/8–344: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="87" xml:id="d57fn87">Text of this telegram quoted to the
                        Ambassador in Canada in airgram A–142, September 27, 5:55 p.m., with
                        instructions to report information obtainable regarding questions asked of
                        London and to send the information and reports requested in last paragraph
                        of the telegram quoted.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-19T00:00:00-04:00"
                            >September 19, 1944—midnight</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>7647. Reurtel 5766, July 20, and 6179, August 3, reurdes 17268, August 3.<note
                        n="88" xml:id="d57fn88">Despatch 17268 not printed; it transmitted text of
                        British Foreign Office note summarized in telegram 6179, August 3, from
                        London, <ref target="#pg_64">p. 64</ref>.</note> Despite British view that
                    need of insuring adequate supplies of scarce foodstuffs at stable, reasonable
                    prices justifies long-term bulk-purchase contracts, and despite understandable
                    desire of Dominions for dependable markets, and even though products of
                    substantial immediate interest to American exporters or importers may not now be
                    covered by the contracts, we remain concerned over possibility <pb facs="0088"
                        n="78" xml:id="pg_78"/> that they run counter to the principles of Article
                    VIII of the Trade Agreement.</p>
                <p>To extent shortages of certain products may actually exist after the war, meat
                    and dairy-products importing countries desiring to obtain adequate supplies at
                    stable reasonable prices may feel that the British contracts conflict with their
                    interests.</p>
                <p>The possibility if not the probability that the duration of the British bulk
                    purchases will extend beyond the periods of short supply for many, at least, of
                    the products involved causes us special concern. Government bulk purchases, in
                    times of commodity abundance, could become far more discriminatory than tariff
                    or quota preferences. The reported contemplated minimum purchases of bacon from
                    Canada are at three times the rate of United Kingdom pre-war bacon imports from
                    Canada, and the purchases reported in your 6239, August 4,<note n="89"
                        xml:id="d57fn89">Not printed; it reported a 4-year agreement for purchase by
                        the United Kingdom from New Zealand of surplus dairy and meat
                        products.</note> seem to be tantamount to long-term freezing of a position
                    for New Zealand in the United Kingdom market regardless of the possible
                    development of lower cost production elsewhere. In a telegram dated September 1
                    from Buenos Aires it is stated that <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Embassy has just received reliable report to effect that large British
                            house here received cable from home office London stating British
                            Ministry Food informed it that 4-year meat contract would be signed
                            shortly. Local representative Ministry of Food doubts accuracy of report
                            but Department may wish investigate.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">The existence of such long-term contracts might present a
                    substantial handicap to other countries with equally or more efficient
                    production attempting to regain their pre-war position in the United Kingdom
                    market.</p>
                <p>In expressing concern with regard to this matter we do not consider that we are
                    reflecting a doctrinaire attitude of opposition to necessary governmental
                    intervention in economic matters, or lack of sympathy with the British
                    Government in meeting the vital problem of British food needs. It seems clear to
                    us, however, that inelastic, long-term government purchase contracts for large
                    quantities are likely in the end to do more to retard than to advance
                    achievement of our two governments’ underlying objectives, set forth in Article
                    VII of the mutual-aid agreement, of expanded world trade on a non-discriminatory
                    basis.</p>
                <p>Your 5766, July 20, paragraph 10, states that there is no reason to believe that
                    the measures under negotiation concerning meat and dairy products have any
                    relation to or constitute any precedent for United Kingdom policy on raw
                    materials. In this connection <hi rend="italic">Business Week</hi> for July 15
                    states that <pb facs="0089" n="79" xml:id="pg_79"/>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Ottawa has revealed that British government representatives have
                            arranged with private Canadian interests for the purchase of
                            2,500,000,000 bd. ft. of lumber to be delivered during the first 2 years
                            after the defeat of Germany. Contracts will soon be signed in
                            London.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Please inform appropriate officials that we hope that the subject of state
                    trading can be thoroughly explored with the British delegation when Article VII
                    talks are resumed, and convey to them the sense of the foregoing so that they
                    may understand that our opinions on state trading in general and on the criteria
                    for state-trading contracts have not changed in principle from those held during
                    the talks last year. We would appreciate an early report on their reactions.</p>
                <p>We are still uninformed regarding many features of the contracts and we should
                    like a report on the following questions: (1) What provision exists in the
                    contracts for their termination or for alteration in the quantities or prices
                    involved in case any product comes into long supply and other countries are in a
                    position to sell on a competitive basis? (2) What is the exact definition of
                    exportable surplus in the agreements? (3) What control, if any, over the use of
                    sterling resulting from the bulk purchases is contemplated in the
                    agreements?</p>
                <p>Please send available information on the reported lumber contract with Canada and
                    the reported meat contract with the Argentine referred to above. Also, send by
                    mail copies of any of the long-term contracts which may be available. In general
                    please follow and report promptly all developments in connection with individual
                    bulk purchases or with over-all policy concerning them.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
