<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Winant) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d613</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">613</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-10-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-10-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="613"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d613">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">103.9164: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-10-24">October 24,
                            1944</date>.<lb/>[Received October 24—10:28 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>9156. To Land, WSA, for Morse and Chubb from Reed, Brown and O’Boyle.
                    Supplementing our 9130, October 24.<note n="11" xml:id="d613fn11">Not
                        printed.</note> Have discussed agenda for first UMEB meeting with Weston who
                    agrees that following items mentioned Chubb’s memorandum to the Administrator
                    October 13th<note n="12" xml:id="d613fn12">Not found in Department files.</note>
                    and in Planning Committee discussions should be included.</p>
                <pb facs="0728" n="718" xml:id="pg_718"/>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Adoption of Planning Committee report.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Report of subcommittees on coastal and short sea trades.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Consideration of paragraph 6 of Planning Committee report.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Question of currencies and brokerage.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Position of USSR, Brazil, Yugoslavia, France, Denmark, Dominions, et
                        cetera.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Personnel requirements.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Weston suggests that the above items should be circulated to Allies before
                    meeting as being major items likely to be discussed. Detailed agenda might be
                    prepared when he arrives in Washington not later than November 12th.</p>
                <p>Weston agrees that matter of agency arrangements on vessels allocated to berth
                    services should be discussed but wants to talk this over with us in advance and
                    therefore suggests it be omitted from main agenda. His feeling is that while it
                    would be desirable to invite Allies to selected meetings of committees such as
                    SEPC’s at early date for educational purposes actual establishment of UMEB
                    freight rate and voyage charter committees should be deferred as long as
                    possible. This should not, however, preclude early Anglo-American discussions on
                    rate questions.</p>
                <p>Weston also agrees that Allies should be given general idea of tonnage situation
                    but feels this might more appropriately be done in SEPC rather than UMEB. He
                    suggests omitting it from main agenda.</p>
                <p>We are not clear as to what questions of allocations policy you had in mind in
                    paragraph 1 of Chubb’s memorandum of October 13th to the Administrator. Can you
                    elucidate?</p>
                <p>Please advise if foregoing meets with your approval.</p>
                <p>Speekenbrink is leaving with Nicholson’s party.</p>
                <p>Samuelson advised today that Carlsson<note n="13" xml:id="d613fn13">Gunnar
                        Carlsson, Chairman of Swedish Shipowners Association.</note> and Boheman,
                    chief permanent civil servant in Swedish Foreign Office, are arriving here
                    November 6th to discuss UMA. We told him that Weston is leaving November 8th for
                    Washington meeting and urged that they come several days earlier. Assume you
                    wish us to meet them with Weston? Please instruct. [Reed, Brown, and
                    O’Boyle.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
