<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Winant) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d652</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">652</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-08-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-08-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="652"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d652">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50/8–1944: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-08-19">August 19,
                            1944</date>.<lb/>[Received August 19—5:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6733. For Berle, Hooker and Radius.<note n="14" xml:id="d652fn14">Radius had
                        departed from London on August 16.</note> The proposed text of the joint
                    communication to Moscow concerning EITO follows: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The Governments of the United Kingdom and the United States are
                            impressed with the increasing urgency of the need for establishing a
                            European Inland Transport Organization. In view of the progress of
                            military operations in Europe, the military authorities are concerned
                            that there should be set up at an early date a central organization
                            capable of coordinating control of transport in all the liberated areas.
                            Moreover, the other Allied Governments concerned are expressing anxiety
                            at the absence of indications of progress in this field. As the success
                            of the plans under consideration depends on effective cooperation by the
                            European Allies, the United Kingdom and United States Governments feel
                            that early consultation with them can no longer be delayed.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The two Governments, therefore, feel it essential to set a date for
                            the convocation of a conference to consider the draft agreement and
                            consider this date should be not later than September 25th. It seems
                            desirable that the European Allies should have an opportunity of
                            considering the draft agreement well in advance of this date and it is
                            therefore proposed to communicate it to them on September 1st. They
                            would at the same time be invited to attend the proposed conference in
                            London on September 25th. The United States and United Kingdom
                            Governments earnestly hope that the Soviet Government will be by then in
                            a position to join in the invitation. If not, however, the United States
                            and United Kingdom Governments consider that the preparatory work for
                            the conference on September 25th could, nevertheless, be put in hand and
                            they would propose to communicate, the draft agreement to the Allies on
                            September 1st indicating that it is the intention to hold a conference
                            toward the end of September. The United States and United Kingdom
                            Governments propose also to indicate to the Allies that the draft
                            agreement has their general approval and that the Soviet Government has
                            stated that it attaches <pb facs="0786" n="776" xml:id="pg_776"/> great
                            importance to the early creation of a special organization of the United
                            Nations for the restoration and coordination of European inland
                            transport in the period following the end of hostilities on the European
                            Continent and that the Soviet Government has been kept fully informed of
                            the discussions leading to the draft agreement on which, however, it is
                            not yet in a position to indicate its attitude. At the time of the
                            communication of the draft agreement to the Allied Governments, it would
                            be indicated to them that the draft is based to a large extent on the
                            work done by their experts on the Technical Advisory Committee on Inland
                            Transport. The Allied Governments would also be informed that their
                            comment on the draft agreement would be welcomed and that any inquiries
                            they might wish to make on the subject would be discussed with them
                            informally.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>In view of the increasing tempo of military operations, the United
                            Kingdom and United States Governments feel that the establishment of the
                            proposed Interim Commission should not be further delayed. The United
                            Kingdom and United States Governments hope that the Soviet Government
                            will be ready to participate in this Commission by early September. In
                            the event of its preparations not being complete, the Soviet Government
                            might consider appointing an observer to the Interim Commission until
                            such time as they are ready to designate a full commissioner.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>In the first communication made to them, the Allied Governments would
                            be informed of the imminent establishment of the Interim Commission and
                            invited to designate a member to serve on an Advisory Committee to the
                            Commission.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
