<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-13T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-13T07:00:00-05:00" n="732" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d732">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.70/11–1344: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gallman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-13T13:00:00+01:00">November 13,
                                1944—1 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received November 13—9:40 a.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>9884. ReEmbs 9807, November 10, 9 p.m. The Embassy has received a written
                        communication from Ronald recapitulating what <pb facs="0875" n="865" xml:id="pg_865"/> we were told orally Friday evening<note n="85" xml:id="d732fn85">November 10.</note> with regard to the British desire
                        for an early indication of the Department’s attitude toward the Soviet note
                        regarding Polish representation at the EITO Conference.</p>
                    <p>Ronald points out that pending a reply from the State Department to the
                        Foreign Office’s telegram of November 1, in which it gave the text of its
                        proposed replies to the Russians, the British and American [De]legations
                        have worked out a redraft of the projected agreement attempting to reconcile
                        as far as possible the draft put in by the Soviet Delegation with those put
                        in by other delegations. He states that consideration is now being given to
                        showing this redraft to the French Delegation as the sponsors of the point
                            [<hi rend="italic">joint?</hi>] draft put in by the Continental Allies
                        covering their desiderata. Ronald states that, “meanwhile an awkward
                        situation is developing here as a result of the failure of the United States
                        Government to let us know their views on the proper answer to the Soviet
                        note of October 28”. He states that until the reply of the United States
                        Government has been received it is impossible for the two Delegations in
                        London to make definite suggestions as to the procedure to be followed after
                        the contemplated consultation with the French Delegation.</p>
                    <p>This morning Ronald informed us by telephone that in his opinion the British
                        Government can delay no longer in giving a written reply to the Russian
                        Ambassador. He intends to recommend to the Foreign Secretary that such a
                        reply be given Gousev unilaterally in which the oral statements made by
                        Eden, as outlined in the Embassy’s 9807, will be confirmed. We have informed
                        Ronald that if such unilateral action is taken it will place us in a very
                        embarrassing position.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gallman</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>