<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-11-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="742" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d742">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.70/10–2844</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the Soviet Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Gromyko</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-11-22">November 22,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        receipt of Your Excellency’s note of October 28, 1944 relative to the desire
                        of the Polish Committee of National Liberation to send a delegation to the
                        European Inland Transportation Organization Conference which is now taking
                        place in London.</p>
                    <p>The European Inland Transportation Conference was called for the sole purpose
                        of coordinating technical questions relating to European transport in order
                        to expedite the prosecution of the war against the common enemy and
                        synchronize these efforts during the immediate post-hostilities period. In
                        view of the technical character of the matters under discussion and the
                        importance attached to the successful conclusion of the questions being
                        considered by the conference, the United States Government does not feel
                        that political questions of such a far-reaching nature as those raised by
                        the Polish Committee of National Liberation should be introduced into a
                        conference of this kind. Moreover, it is the understanding of the United
                        States Government that the negotiations initiated recently in Moscow by
                        Premier Mikolajczyk have not been concluded.<note n="94" xml:id="d742fn94">See <ref target="frus1944v03#pg_1321">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1321</ref>–<ref target="frus1944v03#pg_1335">1335</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>For these reasons the United States Government cannot entertain the request
                        of the Polish Committee of National Liberation contained in your note under
                        reference.</p>
                    <p>The United States Government hopes that the Soviet Government, after giving
                        consideration to the above aspects of the question, will not permit the
                        request of the Polish Committee to stand in the way of continued Soviet
                        participation in the Allied discussion on the problems of European inland
                        transport.</p>
                    <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>E. R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Stettinius, Jr</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>