<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-05-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-05-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="811" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d811">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">800.6176/502</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. William T. Phillips of
                            the Commodities Division</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-05-04">May 4, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. R. Keith Jopson—Commercial Secretary,
                                British Embassy</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. B. F. Haley, CD</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. W. T. Phillips, CD</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>On May 4 Mr. Haley and I called on Mr. Jopson at the British Embassy to
                        inform him of the present state of affairs relating to our internal
                        negotiations regarding the proposed rubber agreement.</p>
                    <p>We informed Mr. Jopson fully of the opposition which has developed toward
                        United States participation in the proposed rubber agreement. It was pointed
                        out to him that the industrial representatives of United States rubber
                        interests have a feeling that they have not been taken fully into the
                        confidence of the Department and also that they are still apprehensive
                        regarding the motives lying behind the invitation for United States
                        participation in the proposed international rubber agreement.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Jopson suggested that several Department representatives accompanied by
                        one or more industry representatives might profitably arrange a trip to
                        London to discuss informally with the British and Dutch the type of problems
                        with which the proposed international rubber committee would concern itself.
                        Mr. Haley and I agreed with Mr. Jopson that it would dispel much of the
                        apprehension of the rubber industry concerning any underlying motives behind
                        the invitation for United States participation if such a delegation were to
                        sit down with the British and Dutch and discuss the problem informally. It
                        might also indicate to the industry that the Department does intend to keep
                        the industry informed and intends to consult with representatives of the
                        rubber industry in order to obtain their individual views. Mr. Jopson
                        indicated that it would be impossible to exclude the Dutch from such
                        discussions since they have been informed of all negotiations and have
                        worked closely with the British on this matter.</p>
                    <p>It was proposed that a cable be prepared for transmission to the American
                        Embassy in London describing the present state of affairs and that Mr.
                        Jopson send a similar cable to his Government so that both sides might be
                        fully aware of all developments and the reasons for our delay in answering
                        the British proposal of January 14, 1944.<note n="21" xml:id="d811fn21">See
                            despatch 13,301, January 14, from London, <ref target="#pg_952">p.
                                952</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The participants plan to meet again on May 5 since Mr. Jopson wishes us to
                        review the cable which he plans to transmit to his Government.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>