<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-18T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-18T11:00:00-05:00" n="855" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d855">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">561.35E1A/7–1844: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-18T18:00:00+02:00">July 18,
                                1944—6 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received July 18—3:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>5668. From Delegate to Sugar Council. Westermann, Dutch Delegate and Vice
                        Chairman of Sugar Council, called today to discuss <pb facs="1009" n="999" xml:id="pg_999"/> draft protocol for extension of Sugar Agreement, copy
                        of which he had received from Foreign Office. He explained that he was
                        trying to decide how to advise his Government regarding this proposal for
                        extension. He said that he had two objections: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                        that article 2 removed all restraint upon participating countries—in
                        particular upon production policies, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) took
                        away all the Council’s important powers. He also voiced Dutch resentment, as
                        a major sugar producer, at being confronted with what he thought was, to all
                        intents and purposes, a <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> on a matter of
                        major concern to his country. I explained to him, as much as seemed
                        appropriate, the American attitude and said that, although the draft
                        protocol might not be everything we would like it to be, we felt it
                        accomplished the main immediate objective, namely, maintenance of existing
                        machinery. It was therefore preferable to letting the agreement expire as
                        seemed to be the only alternative.</p>
                    <p>Westermann seemed to accept the necessity of concessions to the British point
                        of view and although he avoided any statement as to what his Government’s
                        attitude would be toward extension he indicated that acceptance would be
                        materially eased if the American and British Governments were able even
                        informally to give some assurances at the next meeting of the Council when
                        the proposal presumably would come up that it was not the intention as a
                        consequence of article 2 to permit countries which had expanded production
                        during the war to reap unfair advantage from such expansion in the post-war
                        period.</p>
                    <p>It seems advisable to give Westermann some further information about the
                        American attitude in which connection the Department’s instructions would be
                        appreciated. [Steere.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>