<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-10-13T16:36:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-10-13T16:36:00-05:00" n="1048" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1048">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.00/9184.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Chargé
                                    d’Affaires</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram—Paraphrase.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-10-13T15:00:00-06:36">
                                    <hi rend="italic">October 13, 1913—3 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>549. By special decree President Huerta, in view of the dissolution of
                            Congress, assumes the powers granted the Congress in the Departments of
                            Gobernación, Finance and War. The judiciary power still remains with
                            full powers so long as not in conflict with the decrees <pb facs="0943" n="839" xml:id="pg_839"/> of the Executive. The President made his
                            intentions plain in a decree published under date of October 10 [11], as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Victoriano Huerta, Constitutional President ad interim of the
                                    United Mexican States, to its inhabitants makes known that the
                                    Chamber of Deputies and Senators of the Twenty-sixth Legislature
                                    having been dissolved and inhabilitated from exercising their
                                    functions, and until the people elect new magistrates who shall
                                    take over the legislative powers, and in the belief that the
                                    Government should count on all the necessary faculties to face
                                    the situation and to reestablish the constitutional order of
                                    things in the shortest possible time, as is its purpose, since
                                    October 26 has been set as a date for elections for Deputies and
                                    Senators, has seen fit to decree that— <list>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1. The judicial power
                                            of the Federation shall continue in its functions within
                                            the limits set by the Constitution of the Republic and
                                            the decree of the Executive of October 10 of this month
                                            and such others as shall be issued by him.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. The Executive Power of
                                            the Union conserves the powers conferred upon him by the
                                            Constitution and assumes furthermore the Departments of
                                            Gobernación, Hacienda, and War only for the time
                                            absolutely necessary for the reestablishment of the
                                            legislative power. In the meantime the Executive takes
                                            upon himself the powers granted the legislative power by
                                            the Constitution in the aforementioned Departments and
                                            will make use of them by issuing decrees which shall be
                                            observed generally and which he may deem expedient for
                                            the public welfare.</item>
                                        <item>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 3. The Executive of the
                                            Union will render an account to the legislative power of
                                            the use which he makes of the powers which he assumes by
                                            means of this decree as soon as this is in
                                            function.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>Wherefore I order that this be printed, published, and given due
                                    fulfillment.</p>
                                <p>Given at the National Palace of Mexico October 11, 1913.</p>
                                <p rend="right">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">V. Huerta</hi>.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>The exemption from arrest which the members of Congress have enjoyed had
                            been declared invalid by President Huerta in view of the recent
                            dissolution of Congress. A decree to that effect was distributed last
                            night. Text of the decree: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Victoriano Huerta, Constitutional President ad interim of the
                                    United Mexican States, to its inhabitants makes known that in
                                    view of the fact that the Chambers of Deputies and Senators of
                                    the Congress of the Union have been dissolved and inhabilitated
                                    to perform their functions, and in view of the powers which I
                                    hold in the Department of Gobernación according to the decree of
                                    October 11 of this year, I have seen fit to decree that—</p>
                                <p>Article 1. The constitutional exemption from arrest and judicial
                                    action which the citizens which formed the Twenty-sixth Congress
                                    of the Union enjoyed in view of their functions, is hereby
                                    repealed, and consequently they are subject to the jurisdiction
                                    of the tribunals corresponding to the case in the event that
                                    they are guilty of any crime or offense.</p>
                                <p>Wherefore I order that this be printed, published, and duly
                                    fulfilled.</p>
                                <p>Given at the National Palace in Mexico October 11, 1913.</p>
                                <p rend="right">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">V. Huerta</hi>.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Nelson O’Shaughnessy</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>