<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Secretary of the Navy.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1913</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1084</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1084</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1913-10-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1913-10-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Domestic politics</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-10-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-10-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="1084"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1084">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.00/9487.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of the Navy</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-10-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 28, 1913</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your letter<note n="1" xml:id="d1084fn1">Not printed.</note> of this date
                    transmitting a copy of a telegram received by you from Admiral Fletcher, at Vera
                    Cruz, with reference to the action of the U. S. S. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Wheeling</hi> in taking on board General Díaz and two friends, and
                    Williams, American correspondent of the New York Herald.</p>
                <pb facs="0959" n="855" xml:id="pg_855"/>
                <p>In this connection I beg to advise that, while the rule governing such cases is
                    that it is the duty of American men of war to protect American citizens, it is,
                    as a general rule, against the policy of this Government to grant asylum in its
                    ships to the citizens of foreign countries engaged in political activity,
                    especially when such asylum is for the purpose of furthering their political
                    plans. Temporary shelter to such persons, when they are seeking to leave their
                    country, has sometimes been conceded on grounds of humanity, but even this is
                    done with great circumspection lest advantage be taken of it to further the
                    political fortunes of individuals with the result of involving us in the
                    domestic politics of foreign countries.</p>
                <p>In this case you will please direct the commander of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Wheeling</hi> to furnish Williams, the American correspondent of the New
                    York Herald, who, we take it for granted, is not a citizen of Mexico, asylum on
                    the American ship until he can secure passage to the United States. In the case
                    of General Díaz and his two friends, you will give them temporary asylum until
                    they can find a ship to take them away from Mexico, it being taken for granted
                    that they do not desire to remain in Mexico. They will, of course, understand
                    that while they are on an American ship they can not use it as a basis for
                    political activity.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. J. Bryan</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
