<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-09-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-09-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="1345" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1345">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 817.51/565.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister of Nicaragua and the
                                    Minister of the Treasury of Nicaragua</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Not a translation.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Nicaragua</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-09-01">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Sept. 1, 1913.</hi>
                                </date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: Having in a general way pointed
                            out the pressing immediate needs of our country, we wish to add that
                            there is but one bank in the Republic of Nicaragua, that it has an
                            insignificant capital, so little that it can not extend loans to even a
                            small percentage of those worthy of credit. The current rates of
                            interest are from 18% to 24% for loans in general, even for those with
                            which to move the crops. We need a bank with more capital, and an
                            experienced man who understands dealing with our people at its head.</p>
                        <p>Very shortly the former “billetes” of our country cease to be legal
                            tender. We need money now to supply in their stead the new standard
                            “córdoba,” which is the equivalent of your American dollar.</p>
                        <p>The Mixed Claims Commission, created at your country’s suggestion, sorely
                            needs money to begin to pay off the awards it has made. Already there is
                            evidenced a tendency to endeavor to effect settlements direct with
                            Nicaragua because the creditors have so far seen no practical evidence
                            of finality in matters the Commission has taken up.</p>
                        <p>The original suggestions of Mr. Jarvis, a man who has in dealing with
                            Latin America succeeded largely in Cuba, that he could arrange a loan
                            for us of from two million to two million and a half dollars in gold,
                            and could put up a million of it himself, on terms better than those of
                            the present bankers, met with our approval and immediately Mr. Jarvis
                            delivers this amount to the Department of State in Washington, or to
                            whomsoever it shall designate, approximately 711,000 of which shall be
                            used for liquidating our obligation and thus cancelling our contract
                            with the present bankers, and the balance placed at the disposition of
                            Nicaragua, we, having the authority of the President of Nicaragua to do
                            so, will definitely appoint Samuel Miller Jarvis as Finance
                            Commissioner, the appointment to be according to the terms of the
                            agreement copy of which is attached to this letter, and have the
                            appointment confirmed by our Congress now in session at home.</p>
                        <p>This offer is made in the belief that Mr. Jarvis can raise money in any
                            reasonable quantity in the near future and that instead of two and a
                            half millions the loan might be for as much as four millions, and at
                            long instead of short time, with precisely the same guaranties as the
                            present bankers have except the option on the Railroad stock.</p>
                        <p>After great reflection it occurs to us that any plan which did not
                            comprehend liquidating with the present bankers prior to definitive
                            naming of a Finance Commissioner might give rise to differences the
                            effect of which might reflect little credit on the foresight of our <pb facs="1155" n="1051" xml:id="pg_1051"/> country, or possibly even
                            give rise to question as to our fair intention towards those who have
                            had business with our Republic.</p>
                        <p>We have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <list>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Emiliano Chamorro.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Pedro Raf. Cuadra</hi>.</item>
                                </list>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure—Not a translation.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Agreement between the Republic of
                                    Nicaragua and Samuel M. Jarvis, which becomes effective on
                                    compliance with terms of letter dated September 1, 1913.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The Republic of Nicaragua shall through its Congress create
                                    the office of Finance Commissioner, who shall attend to the
                                    international financial affairs of the Republic; and he shall
                                    cooperate with the Minister of Finance in Nicaragua under the
                                    advice of the Secretary of State at Washington. It shall be the
                                    duty of the Finance Commissioner, and he shall be required, at
                                    all times to furnish to the Minister of Finance of Nicaragua and
                                    to the Secretary of State at Washington any information which
                                    either may request as to the financial affairs of the Republic;
                                    and he shall make to the Minister of Finance of Nicaragua
                                    quarterly reports of such affairs. He shall in no case be
                                    interested in any concessions from the Government, except that
                                    mentioned in Clause 7, referring to Banco Nacional de
                                    Nicaragua.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The office of Finance Commissioner shall be filled by the
                                    appointment by the President of Nicaragua of Samuel Miller
                                    Jarvis of New York. And he shall continue to hold this office
                                    during the existence of the present loan and of all loans
                                    negotiated by him for Nicaragua, if approved and accepted by the
                                    latter. His appointment shall be officially certified to the
                                    Department of State at Washington.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Said Jarvis shall do everything in his power to arrange for
                                    meeting the present financial needs of Nicaragua and shall have
                                    authority to secure funds for the conversion of currency, the
                                    refunding of all loans in a proper and economical manner on the
                                    best terms obtainable by him, all contracts to be subject to the
                                    approval of the Department of State at Washington, D. C., and
                                    ratification by the Nicaraguan Government, and for the placing
                                    of the finances of Nicaragua on a sound basis. All expenditures
                                    of the loans to Nicaragua shall be made through the National
                                    Bank of Nicaragua; and the books of the bank shall at all times
                                    be open to the inspection of the Minister of Finance of
                                    Nicaragua and of the Secretary of State at Washington.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Said Jarvis shall have at all times the active cooperation of
                                    the Government of Nicaragua. He may also have the right to refer
                                    for advice to the Department of State at Washington, independent
                                    of the Minister of Finance of Nicaragua.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Said Samuel Miller Jarvis shall be empowered at once by
                                    Nicaragua to investigate and report upon the financial and
                                    economic condition of Nicaraguan financial affairs. And to
                                    authorize and to have executed and carried out such action,
                                    legal or otherwise, as shall be necessary to properly protect
                                    and conserve the interest and welfare of Nicaragua; and to
                                    recover whatever may be properly due her on any account or from
                                    any source. And for this purpose he shall have the right to
                                    investigate records and accounts, demand accountings, employ
                                    auditors and legal and other services wherever necessary to
                                    carry out the purposes of this article.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Said Samuel Miller Jarvis shall have proper compensation for
                                    the services performed in pursuance of the duties devolving upon
                                    him under this instrument And shall have reimbursement for all
                                    his proper expenses incident to said work. Said expenses to be
                                    determined and allowed from time 10 time as the same are
                                    incurred. The compensation for services in connection with loans
                                    shall be one per cent upon amount negotiated and approved by the
                                    Department of State at Washington and accepted by Nicaragua. All
                                    compensation for services in all other matters to be agreed upon
                                    between the Government of Nicaragua and said Samuel Miller
                                    Jarvis, and approved by the Department of State at Washington,
                                    D. C.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Samuel M. Jarvis shall have the right to purchase a
                                    controlling interest in the shares of the National Bank of
                                    Nicaragua within a reasonable time to be determined by the
                                    Secretary of State at a price to be agreed upon by the <pb facs="1156" n="1052" xml:id="pg_1052"/> Minister of Finance
                                    of Nicaragua and said Jarvis, and in case they should be unable
                                    to agree, to be fixed by a person to be designated by the
                                    Secretary of State of the United States.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>It is understood that the purpose of this transfer of the shares of
                                the bank is to assure its development as an institution whose
                                importance, strength and solidity shall comport with the dignity of
                                the Republic.</p>
                            <closer><dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-09-01"><hi rend="italic">September 1, 1913</hi></date>.</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>