<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-01-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="140" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d140">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.51/1220.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">American Chargé d’Affaires at
                                London</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram—Paraphrase.]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-01-09">
                                    <hi rend="italic">January 9, 1913</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Chinese loans; your telegram January 7. The Belgian railway concession
                            was taken up last October with the French Embassy here, with the
                            intimation that this was business which, under the inter-group
                            agreement, should be offered for participation by the six groups because
                            of the identity of the French interests concerned. The French
                            representative appeared to take this as a matter of course. The Legation
                            at Peking at the same time advised the Department that the local
                            representative of the Russian group, with which it is understood the
                            Belgian concessionaires are affiliated, had given out that the Belgian
                            contract would result in no conflict with the six groups, but on the
                            contrary all interests would be taken into the new venture. The
                            Department is not aware that any independent American capital is
                            interested in this loan and considers it extremely unlikely that any
                            will be. It therefore prefers to reserve its opinion as to the
                            understanding proposed by the British Government until the two powers
                            still more directly interested have expressed themselves.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Knox</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>