<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Embassy of Brazil to the Department of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1913</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1511</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1511</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1913-07-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1913-07-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recPwjhmSWu0ZTtDD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112953"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Reproduction</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-07-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-07-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="1511"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1511">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 722.2315/595.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Embassy of Brazil</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>.</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d1511fn1">Left with the Counselor of the Department of State
                        by the Chargé d’Affaires of Brazil on July 22, 1913.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1913-07-22">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Memorandum—Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>The Peruvian Government, owing to the request of the mediator nations and wishing
                    to avoid every motive that would prevent the solution of the boundary litigation
                    with Ecuador, is disposed to order that the District of Loreto keep in charge in
                    Morona only police agents to protect the civilized inhabitants of that region
                    against the fresh attacks of Indians and to avoid by so doing the reproduction
                    there of the events that took place on the Putumaio. The recall of the troops
                    would not amount to very much if the two countries would not mutually yield in
                    some of their demands. It will be the continuation indefinitely of the status
                    quo which could only create new inconveniences and complications. For that
                    reason the Brazilian Legation at Quito has been instructed to impress upon the
                    Government of Ecuador the importance of it also making some concessions to show
                    a desire to settle this disagreeable question, pointing out the advantage of
                    submitting the question to arbitration, which we always thought the only way to
                    solve it, as it is evident that it is impossible for the two countries to reach
                    a direct agreement. As it is possible that Ecuador will continue to refuse The
                    Hague Tribunal, we suggest the choice of the President of the United States, or,
                    in case he also is rejected, to submit the question to a tribunal that would
                    meet in Washington or some other capital, composed of Peruvian and Ecuadorian
                    judges and presided over by a judge of another nationality, which [sic] could be
                    selected later. This would be the practical way to combine the solution by
                    arbitration, <pb facs="1259" n="1155" xml:id="pg_1155"/> which is desired by
                    Peru, as well as by direct accord, which Ecuador wishes. The Minister for
                    Foreign Affairs of Argentina is in full accord with this plan and finds the idea
                    of a mixed tribunal excellent. It is necessary now to know the opinion of the
                    American Government on the subject so that the combined mutual action of the
                    three mediator nations will be agreed upon in the presentation of the proposal
                    to the two countries in litigation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
