<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Group to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1913</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d188</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">188</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1913-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1913-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="188"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.51/1360.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Group</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-03-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 19, 1913</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: We beg to confirm our telephone conversation of
                    today in which the Department advised us that the statement of yesterday issued
                    to the press by the President in regard to Chinese loan negotiations was to be
                    considered as the Government’s reply to the request of the American group in our
                    letter of March 5th that the Department indicate its desire as to our future
                    conduct in this matter.</p>
                <p>We beg to enclose herewith a copy of the telegram which we have today despatched
                    to the groups with whom we have been associated, and to our representative in
                    Peking for communication to the Chinese Government, announcing our intention to
                    withdraw from the six-group agreement and to give notification of our withdrawal
                    from the four-group agreement in June next, in accordance with the provisions of
                    article 14 thereof.</p>
                <p>We would, however, call to the Department’s attention the fact that, as shown by
                    your records, we are now committed to certain transactions entered into by us
                    with the Chinese Government at the instance of the Department, notably the
                    Hukuang Railway loan agreement; <pb facs="0276" n="172" xml:id="pg_172"/> our
                    one-fourth share in the £400,000 advance made on May 23rd, 1911, under the
                    currency-loan agreement, signed on April 15th of that year; and our one-sixth
                    share in the advances made to the Chinese Government on February 28, March 9,
                    May 17, June 12 and June 18, 1912, for which we now hold Treasury bills, and
                    which China intended to repay from the proceeds of the proposed reorganization
                    loan.</p>
                <p>In this connection we would beg to call to your attention the fact that the
                    Chinese Government has not as yet redeemed the Treasury bills held by the six
                    groups falling due on February 28 and March 9 respectively, of which the
                    American group’s share is— <list>
                        <item>Bills due February 28, 1913, $237,894.13.</item>
                        <item>Bills due March 9, 1913, $128,828.84.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The telegram proposed by Mr. Addis, contained in Messrs. Morgan, Grenfell &amp;
                    Company’s communication of the 13th of March, a copy of which was transmitted to
                    the Department with our letter of the same date,<note n="1" xml:id="d188fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> was on that date forwarded to Peking.</p>
                <p>As is shown by telegram received by us to-day from Messrs. Morgan, Grenfell &amp;
                    Co., copy of which is enclosed,<note n="1" xml:id="d188fn2">Not printed.</note>
                    the representatives of the six groups in Peking have officially addressed the
                    Minister of Finance reminding him of obligations due February 28 and March 9,
                    and asking for early information as to arrangements made for payment. In reply,
                    the Minister of Finance has stated his inability to pay owing to non-conclusion
                    of the reorganization loan, and has requested an extension of six months or one
                    year at 7½% interest per annum.</p>
                <p>The Peking representatives add that as the reply from the Minister of Finance
                    fails to give definite information as to the arrangements for repayment, they
                    have notified the Legations in accordance with their instructions contained in
                    the telegram of March 13 above referred to, that the Chinese Government is in
                    default, and requested the Legations formally to notify the Chinese Government
                    that its obligations are overdue.</p>
                <p>We beg to request that the Department may be pleased to instruct the American
                    Minister in Peking to cooperate with his colleagues in making such
                    representations to the Chinese Government as may be necessary to secure an early
                    adjustment of this matter.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Willard Straight</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Group</gloss> to <gloss
                                type="to">Morgan, Grenfell and Company</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-03-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 19, 1913</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Please communicate the following to [naming the representatives of the
                        British, Russian, Japanese, French and German groups of bankers]:</p>
                    <p>“The President of the United States has issued to the press [a] statement as
                        follows:</p>
                    <p>[Here follows the statement quoted in the telegram of March 19 from the
                        Acting Secretary of State to certain diplomatic officers; see ante.]</p>
                    <p>In view of foregoing the American group is with great regret obliged to
                        announce to the other groups its complete withdrawal from negotiations for
                        the <pb facs="0277" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/> reorganization loan. We
                        sincerely trust that our action will in no wise prejudice the position of
                        the other groups. We shall gladly consider any suggestions other groups may
                        be pleased to make as to action they desire us to take in order that our
                        withdrawal may cause them least possible embarrassment. We shall delegate
                        International Banking Corporation to carry on such routine business as may
                        be necessary in view of the commitments already undertaken. We trust that
                        you will appreciate the circumstances which have made our action imperative,
                        and that you will realize our regret at severing our associations with the
                        combination which we, like yourselves, believe to have been in the best
                        interests of China and of the investing public in our respective
                        markets.</p>
                    <p>In communicating with British, French and German groups please add
                        following:</p>
                    <p>“The International Banking Corporation will act for us as regards the Hukuang
                        agreement and the currency loan. We presume, in view of amended
                        reorganization loan agreement, currency loan will be merged therewith, but
                        if other groups wish proceed independently we shall gladly do everything in
                        our power be of assistance. We would further notify you that as at present
                        advised we shall in June give notification of our intention withdrawing also
                        from four-group agreement in accordance with article fourteen thereof.”</p>
                    <closer>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. P. Morgan</hi> &amp; Co.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2—Telegram.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Group</gloss> to its
                                <gloss type="to">Representative at Peking</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-03-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 19, 1913</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>We are today sending following telegram to other groups.</p>
                    <p>[Here follows Inclosure 1.]</p>
                    <p>Communicate to your colleagues and officially advise Chinese Government of
                        our withdrawal from negotiations for reorganization loan.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. P. Morgan</hi> &amp; Co.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
