<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-07-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-07-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="569" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d569">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 822.5048.</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American
                                Minister</gloss>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 3.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-07-21">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July 21, 1913</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department encloses herewith a copy
                            of a note dated July 5, 1913, from the British Embassy, with reference
                            to a despatch dated May 14, 1913, a copy of which is also enclosed,<note n="1" xml:id="d569fn1">Not printed.</note> from the British
                            representative at Quito regarding labor conditions in certain parts of
                            Ecuador.</p>
                        <p>You are instructed to forward all information obtainable at Quito as to
                            the condition of the indigenes in the Ecuadorean Province of Oriente,
                            and to furnish your views as to the advisability of the United States
                            joining with Great Britain in the friendly invitation to the Ecuadorean
                            Government alluded to in the note from the British Embassy.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. B. Moore</hi>.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Ambassador</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 183.]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">British Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Dublin N. H.</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1913-07-05">
                                        <hi rend="italic">July 5, 1913</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honour to refer to Mr.
                                Huntington Wilson’s note<note n="1" xml:id="d569fn2">Not
                                    printed.</note> to my predecessor, No. 1714 of December 26th
                                last, in which it is stated, in answer to enquiries on the subject
                                on the part of His Majesty’s Government that the United States
                                Government would be prepared, in specific cases of the maltreatment
                                of South American natives, to use its influence with the Government
                                concerned to ensure steps being taken to better the condition of the
                                native inhabitants.</p>
                            <p>In this connection I have now the honour, under instruction from my
                                Government, to bring to your notice unofficially the enclosed copy
                                of a despatch from His Majesty’s Chargé d’ Affaires at Quito and to
                                enquire whether, in view of the above-mentioned note, the United
                                States Government would be disposed to join with His Majesty’s
                                Government in a friendly invitation to the Ecuadorean Government
                                thoroughly to investigate the circumstances and, should a traffic in
                                slaves between Ecuador and Peru be found to exist, to cooperate with
                                the Peruvian Government in suppressing it.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>(Not signed.) [<signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cecil Arthur
                                Spring-Rice</hi>.</signed>]</closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>