<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-07-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="706" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d706">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">By the President of the United States of
                                America.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p rend="center">A PROCLAMATION.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi> a Treaty between the United States of
                            America and the Kingdom of Italy amendatory of Article III of the Treaty
                            of Commerce and Navigation of February 26, 1871, was concluded and
                            signed by their respective Plenipotentiaries at Washington, on the
                            twenty-fifth day of February, one thousand nine hundred and thirteen,
                            the original of which Treaty, being in the English and Italian
                            languages, is word for word as follows:</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Treaty between the United States of America and His
                                Majesty the King of Italy, amending the Treaty of Commerce and
                                Navigation concluded February 26, 1871, between the same High
                                Contracting Parties.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The United States of America and His Majesty the King of Italy, desiring
                            to define more accurately the rights of their respective citizens in the
                            territories of the other, have for that purpose determined to conclude a
                            treaty amendatory of Article III of the Treaty of Commerce and
                            Navigation of February 26, 1871, between the two countries and have
                            named as their respective Plenipotentiaries:</p>
                        <p>The President of the United States of America: Philander C. Knox,
                            Secretary of State of the United States of America;</p>
                        <pb facs="0716" n="612" xml:id="pg_612"/>
                        <p>His Majesty the King of Italy: The Marquis Cusani Confalonieri, Commander
                            of the Order of Saint Maurice and Saint Lazarus, Grand Cordon of the
                            Order of the Crown of Italy, etc., etc., His Ambassador Extraordinary
                            and Plenipotentiary at Washington:</p>
                        <p>And the said Plenipotentiaries having exhibited, each to the other, their
                            full powers, found to be in good and due form, have concluded and signed
                            the following articles:</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.</p>
                        <p>It is agreed between the High Contracting Parties that the first
                            paragraph of Article III of the Treaty of Commerce and Navigation of
                            February 26, 1871, between the United States and Italy shall be replaced
                            by the following provision:</p>
                        <p>The citizens of each of the High Contracting Parties shall receive in the
                            States and Territories of the other the most constant security and
                            protection for their persons and property and for their rights,
                            including that form of protection granted by any State or national law
                            which establishes a civil responsibility for injuries or for death
                            caused by negligence or fault and gives to relatives or heirs of the
                            injured party a right of action, which right shall not be restricted on
                            account of the nationality of said relatives or heirs; and shall enjoy
                            in this respect the same rights and privileges as are or shall be
                            granted to nationals, provided that they submit themselves to the
                            conditions imposed on the latter.</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.</p>
                        <p>The present Treaty shall be ratified by the President of the United
                            States, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate thereof, and by
                            His Majesty the King of Italy, in accordance with the constitutional
                            forms of that Kingdom, and shall go into operation upon the exchange of
                            the ratifications thereof, which shall be effected at Washington as soon
                            as practicable.</p>
                        <p>In faith whereof the Plenipotentiaries of the High Contracting Parties
                            have signed the present Treaty in duplicate in the English and Italian
                            languages, and have affixed thereto their respective seals.</p>
                        <p>Done at Washington this 25th day of February in the year of our Lord one
                            thousand nine hundred and thirteen.</p>
                        <table cols="2" rows="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Philander C Knox</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cusani</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>And whereas the said Treaty has been duly ratified on both parts and the
                            ratifications of the two Governments were exchanged in the City of
                            Washington, on the third day of July, one thousand nine hundred and
                            thirteen;</p>
                        <p>Now, therefore, be it known that I, Woodrow Wilson, President of the
                            United States of America, have caused the said Treaty to be made public,
                            to the end that the same and every article and clause thereof may be
                            observed and fulfilled with good faith by the United States and the
                            citizens thereof.</p>
                        <pb facs="0717" n="613" xml:id="pg_613"/>
                        <p>In testimony whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and caused the seal of
                            the United States to be affixed.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <seg type="margin">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>]</seg> Done at
                                the city of <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian us-republic" when="1913-07-03">this third
                                    day of July in the year of our Lord one thousand nine hundred
                                    and thirteen, and of the Independence of the United States of
                                    America the one hundred and thirty-seventh</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Woodrow Wilson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>By the President: <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">W. J. Bryan</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>