<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Minister to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1913</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1912-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1912-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1912-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1912-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 893.00/1505.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Minister</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 671.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1912-11-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 12, 1912</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that as far as outward
                    appearances go, the political situation here is one of gradual improvement. It
                    is still far from ideal, and no great promise for the future is present, but,
                    upon the whole, the political outlook is better than it was a few months
                    ago.</p>
                <p>This improvement is largely evidenced by the single fact that Yuan Shih-kai is
                    slowly but steadily increasing his hold upon the country. * * * By common
                    consent all hopes for the future are largely centered in this one man.
                    Unfortunately he is aging fast, and the fear is often expressed that he may
                    break down, and the wonder is, what will happen if such a misfortune occurs;
                    there is no man in sight to take his place. * * *</p>
                <p>It may be said that the improvement I have noticed is largely superficial. That
                    no constructive work of any great importance has been done and none is under
                    way. That the fundamental question as to the relation of the central government
                    to the provinces remains in determined. * * * This important question will
                    probably not be settled until the permanent constitution is adopted. * * *</p>
                <p>I think the over-shadowing fact remains that the country has settled down to the
                    new order of things. The people, so far as they know anything about it, have
                    accepted the Republic as an established fact. For a time I was afraid that there
                    would be a great struggle for control, between the north and south, at the
                    coming election, and that all kinds of trouble would ensue. But now that the
                    opposition to Yuan has so largely disappeared, he may be regarded as the
                    accepted leader, for the time at least. The crops this year have been uniformly
                    good, except perhaps in a few districts subjected to unusual floods. This fact
                    helps the situation very much; it brings not only comfort but confidence to the
                    people; confidence, because the good crops show that Heaven was not so much
                    displeased, after all, by the removal of the Emperor, and therefore, they may
                    accept the new order with the assurance that it is all right from a religious as
                    well as a political standpoint.</p>
                <p>The difficult, the delicate and the dangerous problem with which the President is
                    confronted, is how to get rid of the independent tutus or provincial governors,
                    and also the military chiefs who defy all civil authority. Only one or the other
                    of two ways is possible for the solution of this problem. The President must
                    fight these men with armed <pb facs="0192" n="88" xml:id="pg_88"/> force and
                    thereby in all probability bring on a civil war, or he must buy them off with
                    money. He doubtless thinks the latter course is the easiest and the cheapest. *
                    * *</p>
                <p>It is not meant that it shall be implied that there is no legitimate or other
                    need for money aside from the specific purpose above named. The disbandment of
                    the troops is the most prominent need, but the arrearages of the indemnity and
                    other liabilities, and the supply of the actual expenses of the Government in
                    many legitimate ways, require the borrowing of money to bridge the country over
                    until the disrupted revenues resume their normal returns. Without considerable
                    money the new Government cannot get on its feet, so to speak. The query in every
                    one’s mind is how long the present condition of affairs will last; it cannot, in
                    the very nature of things, last indefinitely. If Yuan is not supported, he will
                    fail, anarchy will result, and armed foreign intervention, with all its
                    complications and unforeseen consequences will surely follow.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. J. Calhoun</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
