<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Statement made by the Secretary of State on April 24, 1913, on presenting the
                    President’s Peace Plan to the Representatives, some thirty-six in number, of the
                    Foreign Governments, who constitute the Diplomatic Circle at Washington.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1913</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d8</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">8</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1913-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1913-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1913-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1913-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="8"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d8">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 711.0012/64.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Statement made by the Secretary of State on April 24, 1913, on
                        presenting the President’s Peace Plan to the Representatives, some
                        thirty-six in number, of the Foreign Governments, who constitute the
                        Diplomatic Circle at Washington.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1913-04-24">April 24, 1913</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellencies</hi>: I have called you together in order
                    that I may present to you all, simultaneously, a plan for the promotion of peace
                    which I am directed by the President to submit. It reads as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The parties hereto agree that all questions of whatever character and
                            nature, in dispute between them, shall, when diplomatic efforts fail, be
                            submitted for investigation and report to an international commission
                            (the composition to be agreed upon); and the contracting parties agree
                            not to declare war or begin hostilities until such investigation is made
                            and report submitted.</p>
                        <p>The investigation shall be conducted as a matter of course upon the
                            initiative of the commission, without the formality of a request from
                            either party; the report shall be submitted within (time to be agreed
                            upon) from the date of the submission of the dispute, but the parties
                            hereto reserve the right to act independently on the subject matter in
                            dispute after the report is submitted.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>You will notice that it is very brief and deals only with the principles
                    involved, not with the details which must be considered in embodying the
                    principles in diplomatic form. The President’s object is to hasten universal
                    peace. All arbitration treaties contain certain exceptions—that is, certain
                    questions are not to be submitted to arbitration, and, as these questions are of
                    the highest importance, they are likely to become themselves a cause of war.</p>
                <p>The plan proposed by the President, through you, to the nations which you
                    represent, is intended to supplement the arbitration treaties now ill existence
                    and those which may be hereafter made. It is intended to subject to
                    investigation those disputes which have not up to this time been considered fit
                    subjects for arbitration. It is based upon the belief that we have now reached a
                    point in the progress of civilization when nations cannot afford to engage in
                    war before the cause of the war is impartially investigated and openly declared
                    to the world. It is believed that the period of investigation—a time to be fixed
                    by agreement, and which may be different in different agreements—will enable the
                    parties to the controversy to separate questions of fact from questions of
                    national honor and reach some amicable adjustment of their differences. The
                    period of investigation will also allow passion to subside and the great forces
                    that work for peace to assert themselves. When men are excited they talk about
                    what they can do; when they are calm and capable of deliberation they talk about
                    what they ought to do. And this is true of nations as well as of individuals.
                    Public opinion is an increasing force in the world, and the time provided for
                    investigation permits the formation and expression of public opinion.</p>
                <p>You will note that while the proposed plan provides for the investigation of all
                    questions which do not yield to diplomatic treatment, it reserves to each of the
                    contracting nations the right to act independently after the investigation is
                    concluded. If, after the time <pb facs="0113" n="9" xml:id="pg_9"/> specified
                    elapses and after the results of the investigation are made known, the nations
                    still desire war, they are at liberty to settle their differences with the
                    sword, but it is believed that this will seldom be the case and it is hoped that
                    this agreement when entered into will make war between the contracting parties a
                    remote possibility.</p>
                <p>The plan as outlined does not prescribe the method by which the commission will
                    be created. This is a matter of detail which is left for discussion. It may
                    differ in the different agreements entered into, but it is desired that the
                    commission shall be permanent in character, in order that the investigation may
                    be made by the commission, upon its own initiative, without the formality of a
                    request from either party. This is suggested because of the fear that in times
                    of excitement neither party might be willing to ask for investigation lest such
                    a request be regarded as an evidence of weakness.</p>
                <p>In the original draft, as presented to the Foreign Relations Committee of the
                    Senate, a suggestion was made that the period of investigation should not be
                    utilized for a change in the naval program of the contracting nations, but this
                    is a detail which has been omitted from the plan as proposed because it was
                    feared that different nations might look upon it from different standpoints.</p>
                <p>The plan has been made as simple as possible and everything has been eliminated
                    except the things which seem essential to its success, and this Government
                    stands ready to discuss with those Governments which are willing to enter into
                    such an agreement such details as it may be necessary to consider.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, let me assure you that I am very much gratified to be the medium
                    through which the President presents this plan to the nations represented here,
                    and I esteem myself fortunate to occupy the office with which the President has
                    honored me at the time when the step is taken in the interest of peace. Our
                    nation desires to use its influence for the promotion of the world’s peace, and
                    this plan is offered by the President with the hope that its acceptance by the
                    nations will exert a large influence in this direction.</p>
                <p>I thank you for your courtesy in coming at this time and giving me your
                    attention. I hand to each one of you a copy of the plan as outlined, and on
                    behalf of the President, I respectfully invite your cooperation in putting it
                    into effect.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
