<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Iran ( (Wiley), ), to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-07-04T02:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-07-04T02:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-07-04T02:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-07-04T02:30:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">761.91/7–448: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wiley</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   us urgent</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">
                            <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-07-04T11:00:00+03:30"
                            >July 4, 1948—11 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>770. Saw Prime Minister for nearly hour last evening. Most important topic
                    discussed was his interview with Sadtchikov, Soviet Ambassador, which interview
                    took place Friday and lasted two hours. Prime Minister stated that it was clear
                    Sadtchikov talked only on basis of specific instructions from Moscow.</p>
                <p>Prime Minister, who, I understand, speaks excellent Russian, told Sadtchikov of
                    his earnest desire to improve relations with Soviet <pb facs="0167" n="153"
                        xml:id="pg_153"/> Union. Then Prime Minister referred to Iranian Gold held
                    by Russia, to Iranian customs claims against USSR, and other economic matters at
                    issue. Sadtchikov complained over “contingents” of Russian imports into Iran
                    held by Iranian customs. Prime Minister replied that it would be easy to find
                    prompt formula for release of their “contingents” provided that Soviet Union
                    would not insist on selling to Iran at ten times pre-war price level while at
                    same time refusing to pay more than twice pre-war price level for Iranian
                    exports to USSR. All USSR had to do was to be reasonable.</p>
                <p>Sadtchikov answered that all this was irrelevant. There was not one question,
                    including that of the gold, between Iran and Soviet Union which could not be
                    immediately and satisfactorily settled provided that Iran changed its
                    “inadmissable” policy of political and military “unity” with US. Sadtchikov then
                    sounded off with old theme song, namely, that US, with Iranian complicity, was
                    constructing subterranean deposits of aviation fuel and building secret
                    airfields.</p>
                <p>Prime Minister replied that this was untrue. Where, he answered, were the secret
                    airfields? There was, he insisted, no subterranean fuel storage. Prime Minister
                    asked why should Iran or anyone else be interested in such activities. Iran
                    Government would under no conceivable circumstances ever dedicate itself to
                    Communist revolution. Therefore should war break out, Iran would be on side of
                    allies (meaning of course, US and UK). Abadan, Prime Minister added, was in
                    British hands. Who needed, therefore, secret subterranean fuel deposits?</p>
                <p>Sadtchikov continued his charges against US activities in Iran, reminding Prime
                    Minister of Soviet offer to furnish, without charge, planes, arms, munitions, et
                    cetera, as well as number of Soviet military instructors, likewise on gratis
                    basis. Sadtchikov expressed resentment that instead of accepting Soviet
                    generosity, Iran should have turned to US. Prime Minister replied that after all
                    Iran was an independent and sovereign nation, and felt itself free to turn
                    wherever it wished.</p>
                <p>Sadtchikov then complained against publicity which had been given to frontier
                    incidents. Stories about frontier incidents, Sadtchikov declared, were largely
                    invented, publicity given to subject had been unnecessary and hostile to USSR.
                    Prime Minister replied by asking whether Soviet incursions and frontier
                    incidents should be considered a normal and continuing state of affairs between
                    two countries with a common frontier. Sadtchikov, whose instructions perhaps did
                    not cover this query, sidestepped, replying that any publicity which agitated
                    Majlis and aroused public opinion should be avoided. He was apparently very firm
                    on this point.</p>
                <p>Soviet Ambassador—I think this is rather significant—raised question of Soviet
                    oil concession in north, which was defeated in Majlis. <pb facs="0168" n="154"
                        xml:id="pg_154"/> He gave Prime Minister to understand that rejection of
                    concession by Iran was something that USSR could not stomach. He was not
                    speaking, Sadtchikov said, because of material considerations involved. It was
                    more serious than that. Soviet prestige throughout entire world had been
                    seriously damaged by Iran Government—the situation had to be remedied.</p>
                <p>Prime Minister concluded our conversation by asking my advice. He had obviously
                    taken conversation with Sadtchikov very serious[ly] indeed. He said that his
                    Government had to choose between two courses of action: (1) That Iranian policy
                    was fixed, clear and definite and would be followed. Soviet Union could, for its
                    part, adopt whatever policy it desired, or (2) Iran Government could leave door
                    half open—I interrupted him to ask “To permit the Russian foot to be
                    interjected?” Prime Minister replied “No”. He said that what he meant by leaving
                    door half open was merely to talk in order to stall for time. I told him that I
                    would like to think it over.</p>
                <p>My feeling is that I should tell Prime Minister that conversations just to gain
                    time would not deceive Russians for a moment. They could produce
                    misunderstanding, even confusion. This might facilitate Russian designs.
                    Iranians should not pursue such a policy but ought to protest again against the
                    notes which Soviet Union has addressed to Iran Government; utterly false Soviet
                    charges should be withdrawn; incursions into Iran should be stopped at once, and
                    “clandestine” radio activities likewise should be discontinued.</p>
                <p>I would therefore, greatly appreciate Department’s guidance before Tuesday, when
                    I shall have my next interview with Prime Minister, I shall also see Shah on
                    Tuesday.</p>
                <p>British Chargé called upon me last evening. Following my interview with Prime
                    Minister, Creswell was received by Hajir for half hour’s talk. Prime Minister
                    went over pretty much same ground with Creswell as he did with me. Creswell, I
                    believe, is sending only a brief telegram to Foreign Office and regards
                    Sadtchikov’s representations with serene composure.</p>
                <p>Sent Department, repeated London 60. Department pass Moscow 38.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wiley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
