<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-09T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-09T09:00:00-05:00" n="169" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d169">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">890F.7962/2–948: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Saudi Arabia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Childs</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret   most immediate</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">
                                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Jidda</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-09T17:00:00+03:00">February 9, 1948—5 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>56. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 33, February 8<note n="1" xml:id="d169fn1">Not printed, but see footnote 2,
                                    above.</note> received in time enable me ask Foreign Office
                                suspend for time being my request for audience with King.</p>
                            <p>Action proposed by Department <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 32, February 6, believed in general very
                                satisfactory. I believe <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> will
                                welcome comments proposed re Anglo-Saudi treaty and particularly
                                point 3.</p>
                            <pb facs="0235" n="221" xml:id="pg_221"/>
                            <p>I think it unwise raise at this time question assignment Military
                                Attaché Legation Jidda. We should be satisfied if <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> can be induced assignment Military
                                Attaché for Air. While King has disapproved such assignment “at
                                present” (see Legtel 55 of February 9<note n="2" xml:id="d169fn2">Not printed.</note>) I have not abandoned hope King may be
                                persuaded change decision in light arguments I may use based on
                                general ways we propose assist him, as outlined <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 32. <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss>’s suggestion of difficulty reaching decision at
                                present time will make it easier to point out our own
                                difficulties.</p>
                            <p>If our support Palestine partition were not the excessive incubus it
                                is in all our dealings with <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss>, I
                                would feel very hopeful in being able persuade King to request us to
                                remain at Dhahran after March 1949. King, however, as Department
                                aware, is under heavy attack in Arab world for what is regarded
                                already as his excessive leniency toward US interests, in view of
                                what is regarded as our hostility to Arab world by our Palestine
                                policy. Even if he desired us remain Dhahran, as he probably does,
                                after that date he is likely find it particularly difficult make
                                such request at this extremely unpropitious moment.</p>
                            <p>I see no reason, however, why subject should not be explored with
                                him. It is entirely possible he may feel question of extension
                                should remain in abeyance for some months until Palestine issue has
                                become clearer and our own relation to Arab world better defined in
                                Arab eyes. I think it important that we make plain our interest in
                                assisting him to the extent of spending considerable sums Dhahran
                                and, as such expenditure obviously cannot be made if our occupancy
                                at Dhahran is to be terminated next year, it seems desirable from
                                point of view of indicating to King our willingness assist him, that
                                question of airport agreement be raised.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Childs</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>