<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Saudi Arabia ( (Childs) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d183</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">183</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recLVtmipNOLIF0A1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="reciuru9i20NCuS5s" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="183"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d183">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890F.5151/5–648</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Saudi Arabia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Childs</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jidda</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-06">May 6,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">No. 129</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my telegrams No. 206
                    of April 14 and No. 209 of April 17, 1948,<note n="1" xml:id="d183fn1">Neither
                        printed.</note> and to report that Mr. Judd Polk, United States Treasury
                    Representative attached to the American Embassy in Cairo, arrived in Jidda on
                    April 20, 1948, and remained in Jidda until May 2, 1948, for an investigation of
                    the particular situation created by the payment of Arabian American Oil Company
                    oil royalties to the Saudi Arabian Government in gold sovereigns,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d183fn2">The “gold pound controversy” between <gloss
                            target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> and the Saudi Arabian Government was
                        of some two years’ duration and concerned the computing of royalties due to
                        the Government and offsets based on dollar advances made by the company to
                        the Government against future royalties. <p>Final negotiations between Saudi
                            Arabian officials and <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss>
                            representatives began in February 1948 and were brought to a successful
                            conclusion before the end of March. Royalties were fixed at four gold
                            shillings per ton of oil, payable in British gold sovereigns. Should
                                <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> be unable to obtain gold
                            sovereigns, it was to make payment in dollars at the rate of $12 per
                            sovereign. It was the contention of <gloss target="#t_Aramco1"
                                >Aramco</gloss>, during the negotiations, that dollar payments
                            should be calculated at the selling price of the gold sovereigns in the
                            United States, i.e., $8.24. The Saudi Arabian negotiators insisted on
                            payments at the rate of the sovereigns at Jidda, which fluctuated
                            between 16 and 20 dollars. The company finally presented the controversy
                            to King Ibn Saud, after which agreement was reached at the $12 level
                            (despatch 95, April 3, from Jidda, 890F.51/4–348). Past accounts up to
                            February 29, 1948, were liquidated by payment of 184,549 gold sovereigns
                            by <gloss target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> to the Saudi Arabian
                            Government (despatch 98, April 6, from Jidda, 890F.5151/4–648).</p>
                        <p>The “particular situation” as reported by Minister Childs on April 13,
                            flowed from the payment of royalties in gold sovereigns. An acute dollar
                            shortage resulted, together with a fall in the local price of sovereigns
                            to $12 and of the riyal to 20 cents, less than its bullion value. These
                            monetary developments were said to threaten a cessation of Saudi Arabian
                            trade with the United States (telegram 204 from Jidda,
                            890F.5151/4–1348).</p>
                    </note> as well as the general financial situation of the Saudi Arabian
                    Government.</p>
                <p>Immediately upon Mr. Polkas arrival Shaikh Abdullah as-Sulaiman, Minister of
                    Finance, was informed of his presence by the Legation and it was stated that Mr.
                    Polk was at the disposition of the Minister of Finance and of his advisers for
                    any discussions which they might care to have with him concerning their
                    particular problems. I have reason to believe that both the Minister of Finance
                    as well as His Majesty, were extremely gratified by the promptness with which
                    Mr. Polk made his services available and, as I had anticipated, the peculiar
                    nature of the problems confronting the Saudi Arabian Government as a result of
                    an influx of gold sovereigns made the Minister of Finance peculiarly receptive
                    to a discussion of Saudi Arabian financial problems with Mr. Polk. Mr. Polk had
                    several initial conversations with: the Minister of Finance and his principal
                    assistant, <pb facs="0253" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/> Shaikh Mohammed Suroor, at
                    which Second Secretary Donald C. Bergus and Third Secretary T. Andrew Galambos
                    were present. Mr. Polk requested certain information of the Government to enable
                    him to pursue his inquiries, and Mr. Polk informed me that he was very much
                    encouraged by the very sincere effort made by the Government to supply him with
                    the information which he desired.</p>
                <p>Toward the close of his visit Mr. Polk consulted with me concerning a draft
                    communication to Shaikh Mohammed Suroor embodying certain personal suggestions
                    which he felt it would be desirable to offer the Saudi Arabian Government in
                    meeting its financial problems. It was both my view and Mr. Polk’s that these
                    suggestions should be made in the most informal manner and that every appearance
                    should be avoided of pressing the Saudi Arabian Government to adopt any
                    particular course of action or to employ financial experts or counselors of
                    American nationality. It was felt that the more disinterested our informal
                    advice was framed, the more likely the chances of such advice being given
                    serious consideration. Local considerations regarding the need for presenting
                    currently unpalatable advice in a manner which might leave the Ministry of
                    Finance in a receptive mood for further patient exposition by their own advisors
                    of the need for future implementing measures largely indicated the form in which
                    the memorandum was cast.</p>
                <p>I enclose a copy of the suggestions as finally framed by Mr. Polk, which were
                    communicated to Shaikh Mohammed Suroor on April 30, 1948.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d183fn3">Not printed.</note> It will be observed from the enclosed
                    memorandum that Mr. Polk has made an analysis of prospective revenues of the
                    Saudi Arabian Government for the ensuing four years, from which it appears that
                    dollar revenues alone may total in 1948 56 million dollars, in 1949 70 million
                    dollars, in 1950 100 million dollars, and in 1951 120 million dollars. Mr. Polk
                    next analyzes the present losses of the Saudi Arabian Government through its
                    currency and exchange operations and he makes certain suggestions for avoiding
                    these losses, including the giving of consideration to the reduction of the
                    silver content of the riyal and the eventual introduction of a paper currency.
                    Mr. Polk also recommends the employment of carefully chosen foreign experts who
                    might prove exceedingly useful in setting up operating and accounting
                    procedures. Finally, Mr. Polk points out the desirability of the employment by
                    the Saudi Arabian Government of one or more foreign consultants who might advise
                    the Saudi Arabian Government concerning its monetary problems.</p>
                <p>On May 1, 1948, Mr. Polk, in company of Mr. Donald Bergus and Mr. T. Andrew
                    Galambos, presented his memorandum to Shaikh <pb facs="0254" n="240"
                        xml:id="pg_240"/> Mohammed Suroor. At this conference Shaikh Mohammed Suroor
                    indicated his general agreement with the points made by Mr. Polk in his
                    memorandum but expressed disappointment that it did not deal with the specific
                    problem of dollars which Shaikh Abdullah Sulaiman had raised originally with me.
                    I had anticipated that this would be the first point raised by the Saudi
                    financial authorities and Mr. Polk pointed out that the monetary problem arising
                    from a decline in the premium rate on sovereigns was not a genuine dollar
                    problem of the Government. Mr. Polk emphasized that Saudi Arabia’s dollar
                    problem was not really a problem of needing credit, but rather a problem of the
                    effective and wise use of the Saudi Arabian Government’s very rapidly growing
                    dollar revenues.</p>
                <p>On May 2, 1948, Mr. Polk in company with Mr. Galambos called on Shaikh Abdullah
                    Sulaiman to discuss the memorandum previously presented by Mr. Polk to Shaikh
                    Mohammed Suroor. At this conference the Minister of Finance expressed a desire
                    for Mr. Polk’s opinion on how the Saudi Arabian Government could best market its
                    sovereigns. Mr. Polk replied that he was incompetent to advise him on this point
                    but expressed willingness to refer his question to the Chase National Bank
                    representative for the Middle East in Cairo.</p>
                <p>Shaikh Abdullah Sulaiman then outlined his general plans for handling Saudi
                    Arabian finances. He stated that it was the Government’s purpose to establish a
                    central bank in which the Saudi Arabian Government would deposit 214 million
                    paper riyals, an amount equivalent to the recently published budgetary
                    expenditures of the Government. The Government would draw on these riyals
                    against the deposit of gold sovereigns at the rate of 65 riyals per
                    sovereign.</p>
                <p>Mr. Polk stated that he was gratified at the direction of Shaikh Abdullah’s
                    thinking, but that he was worried over the notion of stabilizing the riyal in
                    terms of the sovereign, inasmuch as the sovereign itself has a fluctuating
                    value. Shaikh Abdullah stated that he would in any event make no decision
                    without first obtaining the advice of competent experts. The Minister of Finance
                    added that the Government proposed to obtain Egyptian advisers, and Mr. Polk
                    mentioned as a suitable candidate Darwish Bey. Shaikh Abdullah asked Mr. Polk if
                    he would approach Darwish Bey to ascertain whether he would be interested in the
                    post of consultant.</p>
                <p>In concluding the interview the Minister of Finance stated he had great respect
                    for American financial opinion and knew our advice was disinterested. He
                    reminded Mr. Polk he had first turned to the “friendly American Government” when
                    he needed advice on financial problems, and he assured Mr. Polk he would again
                    turn to the “friendly American Government” for its comments on such advice as
                    the consultants whom he might employ would have to give him. I <pb facs="0255"
                        n="241" xml:id="pg_241"/> enclose for the record memoranda of Mr. Polk’s
                    conversations of May 1 and 2, 1948.<note n="4" xml:id="d183fn4">Neither
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I believe a very useful start has been made in the turning of the thoughts of the
                    Saudi Arabian Government seriously to a consideration of the modernization of
                    its currency and financial problems. I wish to express my great appreciation of
                    the extremely valuable services rendered by Mr. Polk to the Legation in this
                    instance. I have expressed to Mr. Polk the hope that in the event the wish
                    should be expressed at any time by the Saudi Arabian Government for his presence
                    in Jidda for consultation he make every effort to accede to such desire. I feel
                    strongly we have an exceptional opportunity presented to us at the present time
                    and that if we are prompt in taking advantage of it and prudent in our approach
                    to the Saudi Arabian authorities we may accomplish a great deal in the way of
                    assisting the Saudi Arabian Government to the effective solution of its monetary
                    and financial problems.<note n="5" xml:id="d183fn5">Mr. Polk made a second
                        report on Saudi Arabia’s financial situation on May 31. A copy was
                        transmitted to the Department by Jidda in despatch 160, June 5
                        (890F.5151/6–548). The report, as quoted in the despatch, stated in part:
                        “Saudi Arabia’s financial problem is how to convert the revenues from oil
                        into lasting production gains. The problem is dramatic because of the size
                        of prospective aggregate earnings—at least $2½ billion and possibly as much
                        as $15 billion. The problem is sobering because of the very real
                        difficulties in finding promising lines of economic development in so barren
                        a land. The problem is urgent because oil is a depletable resource—its
                        benefits will accrue for perhaps 25 to 50 years. As far as it is now known,
                        there is nothing to take oil’s place once it is gone. So the problem may be
                        more definitely stated as how to translate $2½–$15 billion into as big a
                        gain in production as possible, and to do so within a generation or
                        two.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Rives Childs</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
