<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the United States Representative at the
                    United, Nations ( (Austin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d206</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">206</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-01-01T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-01-01T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-01-01T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-01T14:00:00-05:00" n="206"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">745.45F/12–3047: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the United States Representative at the United, Nations</hi> (<persName
                        type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-01T14:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 1, 1948—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1. Allen of Brit Emb called at Dept at noon yesterday to discuss late
                    developments in Kashmir situation. Among other things he said <gloss
                        target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> had sent instructions that US be informed
                    of immediate action Cadogan<note n="1" xml:id="d206fn1">Sir Alexander Cadogan,
                        United Kingdom Permanent Representative on the United Nations Security
                        Council.</note> had been instructed to take in event India files appeal to
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    <pb facs="0281" n="267" xml:id="pg_267"/> against Pakistan. As soon as Cadogan
                    knows of actual filing of such an appeal by India, he is to take steps to assure
                    that <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> considers matter as soon as possible
                    (retel 6668 from London, Dec, 30 Par. 12<note n="2" xml:id="d206fn2">
                        <ref target="frus1947v03#pg_188">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1947, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 188</ref>.</note>) (Allen has today
                    told us that <gloss target="#t_UKDel1">UKDel</gloss> in New York has already
                    made an informal approach to UN Secretariat on intermediate level to assure
                    early consideration of case).</p>
                <p>Allen then said his Govt was inviting attention of US to possibility of taking
                    similar steps and that Cadogan had been apprised of this also.</p>
                <p>Dept. informed Allen later in day that while US agrees Indian appeal should be
                    heard as expeditiously as possible, we believe this can be accomplished by
                    informal methods rather than by any formal approach such as a letter to <gloss
                        target="#t_SecGen1">Sec. Gen.</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    President. We observed further that since Belgian is now <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss> President, it should be possible to approach him informally and
                    accomplish the desired result with no difficulty.</p>
                <p>Dept does not believe it desirable or wise at outset of this case to make
                    political issue of time or speed with which <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    should deal with matter. We are, however, willing to support informal methods of
                    obtaining immediate <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> consideration of the case.
                    We recognize that after <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> commences such
                    consideration Pakistan may desire stay in proceedings pending completion of
                    preparation of case or arrival of additional personnel. In such an eventuality
                    we believe <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> should adhere to well-established
                    practice of permitting parties reasonable period of time to make such
                    arrangements as are clearly necessary for a proper handling of the case.</p>
                <p>Sent New York, repeated to London, New Delhi and Karachi.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
