<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-28T01:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-28T01:30:00-05:00" n="241" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d241">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">745.45F/2–2848: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grady</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   most immediate</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-28T12:00:00+05:30">February 28, 1948—noon</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>170. Your 124 February 25. During past few days in addition to
                                Abdullah have talked with Jaya Prakash Narayan,<note n="1" xml:id="d241fn1">Leader of left-wing elements of India’s
                                    Congress Party.</note> Symon acting British High Commissioner,
                                and Kearney Canadian High Commissioner and have several general
                                impressions. First, a feeling which seems to be growing that <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> have taken side of Pakistan. Thursday night
                                Ayyangar publicly accused both governments and the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> of bias and cited statement of
                                Senator Austin with reference to the necessity of satisfying the
                                tribal invaders in connection with any solution of the Kashmir
                                    problem.<note n="2" xml:id="d241fn2">Statement by Austin not
                                    identified.</note> He said to his “astonishment” British
                                delegates concurred in statement of Senator Austin. Nehru likewise
                                has bitterly criticized <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> without
                                singling out <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>. On other hand, <hi rend="italic">Dawn</hi> newspaper frequently indicates belief in successful
                                outcome for Pakistan of Kashmir dispute at UN. Kearney returned on
                                plane recently with Pakistan official who had been at Lake Success
                                and who indicated growing confidence of Pakistan victory before
                                    <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> feel their case badly handled
                                and there is some tendency criticism <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> circles of Ayyangar. Also public criticism <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> for <pb facs="0323" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/> submitting question to <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. Nehru says privately as justification for
                                submission he felt case so strong there could be no doubt of
                                outcome. <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> feel matter a simple
                                one of invasion with the demonstrable assistance of Pakistan and
                                that <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> should only have considered
                                evidence this point and enjoined Pakistan to desist its aid to
                                tribesmen and make every effort to get them out of Kashmir. Kearney
                                feels that a defeat for Nehru before <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> might well lead to fall his government and I agree.
                                Plebiscite defeat would not have this effect. As
                                indicating-possibility Pakistan being effective in helping keep law
                                and order in Kashmir, Abdullah stated his belief tribesmen would
                                shortly be returning home for the sowing their spring crops. Once
                                they leave, problem of keeping them out, especially if Pakistan made
                                clear to them it would not continue assistance from West Punjab,
                                would be greatly simplified.</p>
                            <p>Referring your suggestions 1 to 8 inclusive, would stress the
                                importance from standpoint <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> of
                                maintaining strictly constitutional procedure. As you know, <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> case based primarily on legal
                                grounds. I have little doubt <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> can
                                control Maharaja<note n="3" xml:id="d241fn3">H. H. Maharaja Sir
                                    Harisingh.</note> and Abdullah and they will accept whatever
                                program <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> agrees to. They would
                                wish the appointment of administrator and his assistants to be
                                formally made by emergency coalition government. I am convinced
                                    <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> will continue to insist
                                Abdullah remain head of any coalition government that might be set
                                up. General feeling here is Abdullah has the confidence of people of
                                Kashmir as no other Kashmiri could possibly have. I believe if
                                authority of administrator and staffs is entirely confined to the
                                plebiscite and matters directly connected with the plebiscite and
                                the absolute authority of the emergency coalition government is
                                recognized, that <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> might accept
                                your suggestions.</p>
                            <p>Drawing analogy Greek situation, I believe coalition government would
                                have every reason to wish to have favorable verdict rendered as to
                                fairness of the elections by the UN Commission and therefore be
                                meticulous in its conduct. This should be reassurance to Pakistan. I
                                believe your plan the basis upon which a solution may be worked out
                                keeping in mind the points I have made in my endeavor to appraise
                                the situation.</p>
                            <p>Ayyangar leaving for Lake Success end of first week in March. Will
                                cable exact date when definite. Abdullah not returning with him.</p>
                            <p>Sent Department 170, repeated Karachi 58.<note n="4" xml:id="d241fn4">Commenting on this cable, Ambassador Alling in Pakistan
                                    informed the Department in telegram No. 128 of March 2, not
                                    printed, that he seriously doubted whether India would have the
                                    slightest confidence in the fairness of a plebiscite as long as
                                    Abdullah remained head of the Kashmir Government
                                    (745.45F/3–248).</note> Department please repeat London 50, and
                                New York.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Grady</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>