<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                            Embassy in India</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p1</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d250</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">250</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-29T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="250" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d250">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">845.00/3–1048: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in India</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-29">March 29,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–40. Urdes No. 218, Mar 10, 1948<note n="1" xml:id="d250fn1">Not printed.</note>
                    entitled “Comments of Secretary of Ministry of States on Hyderabad Negotiations”
                    which requested views of Department of treatment to be accorded Agent General of
                    Hyderabad should such an officer be sent US.</p>
                <p>In view India-Hyderabad standstill agreement of Nov 29, 1947 under terms of which
                    foreign affairs, defense, and communications will continue on same basis as
                    before Aug 15, 1947, US Government in its treatment of representative of
                    Hyderabad will avoid any act which might be interpreted as a recognition of
                    Hyderabad’s sovereignty or of right to conduct external affairs independently of
                        <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>. While the treatment accorded Hyderabad
                    Agent-General will depend on terms <pb facs="0336" n="322" xml:id="pg_322"/>
                    under which he conies to US as well as on arrangements made between Hyderabad
                    and <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> for coordinating his activities with
                    Embassy of India and/or Indian Consulate New York, he will probably be regarded
                    as having status analogous to that of trade commissioner. It is likely that he
                    would not be permitted to communicate direct with Department, but, like Consular
                    Representative or foreign trade mission, would be obliged to use regularly
                    established diplomatic mission, that is, Embassy of India, as channel for
                    correspondence with US Government.</p>
                <p>US policy re princely states remains unchanged, and Department will avoid
                    encouraging aspirations of princely states for independence and the further
                    political division of the Indian sub-continent. All matters of political or
                    diplomatic nature or questions with political overtones which concern princely
                    states which have associated themselves with Dominion of India will continue to
                    be dealt with by Department through Embassy of India in Washington or US
                    Embassy, New Delhi.</p>
                <p>A copy of this airgram is being sent the Embassy at London, with the request that
                    London also inform Department re treatment accorded the Nizam’s representative
                    in the United Kingdom.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
