<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Iran ( (Wiley) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-10-19T02:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-19T02:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recqDYPNCT9Q6HQio" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039557"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Drilling</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-19T02:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-19T02:30:00-05:00" n="33"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d33">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">890.0145/10–1948: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wiley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-19T11:00:00+03:30"
                            >October 19, 1948—11 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1207. British Ambassador told me today that Persian Gulf sheiks will in about
                    three weeks be given draft proclamation for claiming <pb facs="0064" n="50"
                        xml:id="pg_50"/> jurisdiction of sub-sea resources out to median line. They
                    will be given fortnight to think it over and then when they make statement
                    Iranian Government and other interested governments will be notified.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d33fn1">Tehran, on October 20, reported information from the British
                        Embassy that the correct timetable called for the sheikhdoms to be given
                        three weeks after receipt of the proposals before they would be free to make
                        any announcements; and that Iraq and Iran would be informed a fortnight
                        after the first communication to the sheikhs and the Saudi Arabian
                        Government. Tehran concluded that “Giving Iran week to consider matter
                        before any proclamations are issued will not soften reaction here very much
                        in my opinion. Iran Government might rush to make some absurd claim to
                        waters around Bahrein.” (telegram 1216, 890.0145/10–2048)</note>
                </p>
                <p>In my opinion this procedure is very close to previous plan of presenting Iran
                    with “fait accompli” against which Department argued so forcefully. Iran is to
                    be presented with Anglo-American “suggestion” which involves establishing 900
                    mile boundary line for Iran. Iran is by all odds the riparian state most
                    concerned in division of Gulf but she is apparently not going to be asked to
                    agree plan or even to present her views. Simultaneously, other riparian states
                    all of whom are subject to direct or indirect influence of UK–US Governments
                    will make declaration implementing suggested plan.</p>
                <p>It is my considered opinion that Iranians will regard this course of action as
                    US–UK “imperialism”. At the minimum it will create most unpleasant situation
                    which will certainly not be helpful in our current negotiation for renewing
                    military mission contract. It could even undermine present political orientation
                    of Iran. It will surely be excellent grist for Soviet propaganda mill. As
                    Department is aware Iranians are highly sensitive to their rights in Persian
                    Gulf and Bahrein issue has been foremost in Iranian nationalistic agitation.</p>
                <p>Am afraid that question of sub-sea resources in Gulf will be handled in a manner
                    that may seriously prejudice our broader interests here. <gloss target="#t_SAG1"
                        >SAG</gloss> has apparently agreed to award off-shore rights to <gloss
                        target="#t_Aramco1">Aramco</gloss> (<hi rend="italic">Current Economic
                        Developments</hi> September 27). Iran cannot grant concession for another
                    four years by virtue law October 22, 1947. American Independent has presumably
                    obtained off-shore rights Kuwait half neutral zone. Iraq only possesses few
                    miles frontage on Gulf and this is heavily silted. This leaves only
                    sheikdoms/Surely British are in position to resolve disputes between them and to
                    suggest concession areas covering shallow waters which are of interest to oil
                    companies circumscribed so as to give minimum offense to Iran. Concessions could
                    delineate limited areas open to immediate drilling and provide for later
                    inclusion waters over which sheikdoms may <pb facs="0065" n="51" xml:id="pg_51"
                    /> eventually have jurisdiction. This should satisfy oil companies as I
                    understand they are not immediately interested in water deeper than 100 feet. As
                    need for overall division Gulf waters becomes more evident Iran could be invited
                    to participate in proceedings on equal footing she deserves.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 1207; repeated London 104.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wiley</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
