<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="52" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d52">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">890G.6113/3–2948</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in Iraq</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Wadsworth</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-29">March 29,
                                    1948</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">No. 17</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has considered with
                                care your report and recommendations concerning a proposed program
                                for irrigation and other economic development projects in Iraq, as
                                outlined in your memorandum of November 13, 1947 addressed to the
                                Director of the Office of Near Eastern and African Affairs. For your
                                convenience there is attached a copy of this memorandum, and of the
                                letter of November 7, 1947, addressed to the Foreign Minister of
                                Iraq by the Vice President of the International Bank for
                                Reconstruction and Development,<note n="1" xml:id="d52fn1">Neither
                                    printed.</note> referred to under Point 13 of your
                                memorandum.</p>
                            <p>Particular note has been taken of your report that in several
                                important conversations which you had in Baghdad with the Iraqi
                                Prime Minister prior to your return to the United States last
                                September, you were informed of the Iraqi Government’s desire for
                                broad collaboration with the British and American Governments in the
                                formulation of a comprehensive and integrated overall plan for
                                development in Iraq and for its earliest possible realization. In
                                subsequent discussions in Washington participated in by important
                                officials of the Iraqi Government as well as by yourself, including
                                a meeting with the President and Vice President of the International
                                Bank, the establishment of an Iraq Development Planning Board, with
                                appropriate participation by British, American and International
                                Bank experts was envisaged as the appropriate vehicle through which
                                such collaboration might be afforded. It is noted in this connection
                                that, as stated in the letter of November 7 by the Vice President of
                                the International Bank, while the Bank could not consistently with
                                its policy <pb facs="0092" n="78" xml:id="pg_78"/> permit a member
                                of its staff to serve actively on such a Board, “thereby becoming a
                                party to the decisions of a body which would subsequently approach
                                the Bank with a request for finance”, the Bank would be prepared, at
                                its expense “from time to time to make available one or more
                                members” of the Bank’s staff “for consultation at the board’s
                                headquarters or at such other places as may be mutually
                                agreeable”.</p>
                            <p>The question raised by your report and recommendations in these
                                circumstances relates therefore to the readiness of the Government
                                of the United States to participate at the request of the Government
                                of Iraq and in collaboration with the Government of the United
                                Kingdom, in aiding in the formulation and realization of an overall
                                economic development program for Iraq through representation by
                                American experts on the proposed Iraq Development Planning Board. In
                                this connection it may be observed, as noted in your memorandum of
                                November 13, that the British Government’s interest in economic
                                development in Iraq and a favorable inclination toward
                                Anglo-American cooperation in reference thereto, has been expressed
                                more than once, notably in a memorandum winch the British Foreign
                                Minister transmitted to the Secretary of State on March 20,
                                    1947.<note n="2" xml:id="d52fn2">
                                    <ref target="frus1947v05#pg_503">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1947, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 503</ref> and footnote
                                    33.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>With a view to the formulation of an appropriate instruction to you
                                based on a broad consideration of the subject, the Department has
                                consulted other interested agencies of this Government through the
                                Cabinet Food Committee. On the basis of this consultation the
                                Department is now able to advise you as follows: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The Government of the United States views with sympathetic
                                        interest and approval the desire of the Government of Iraq
                                        to formulate, and proceed to the realization of, an overall
                                        plan for economic development centered upon irrigation and
                                        other agricultural projects in the area of the Tigris and
                                        Euphrates Rivers, designed to expand food production,
                                        control floods, and in other ways contribute to improvement
                                        in the standard of living of the people of Iraq.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>This Government would accordingly be prepared to give
                                        favorable consideration, at the Iraq Government’s request,
                                        to such measures of assistance for this purpose as may be
                                        practicable and appropriate. Specifically, it would be
                                        willing to consider the nomination of an American expert or
                                        experts, subject to such expert or experts being available,
                                        for service with an Iraq Development Planning Board as
                                        proposed. More precise determination of the American
                                        participation of this nature which would be found
                                        practicable and appropriate would of course have to await a
                                        specific request from the Iraq Government. It is assumed in
                                        this connection that timely consideration will also be given
                                        to enlisting, in appropriate circumstances, the assistance
                                        or advice of suitable international organizations such as
                                        the Food and Agriculture Organization.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>It would be understood that the nomination of such
                                        American expert or experts could not imply approval in
                                        advance by this Government <pb facs="0093" n="79" xml:id="pg_79"/> of whatever plans and program the
                                        proposed Iraq Development Planning Board might evolve. Such
                                        approval by this Government as might prove requisite for the
                                        support by it of any Iraq loan application to the
                                        International Bank would necessarily depend upon study and
                                        approval by the United States of technical and financial
                                        details of such final plans as may be presented.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>It is the Department’s desire that you should, in such manner and on
                                such occasion as you find appropriate, express to the Iraqi
                                authorities the views of this Government as above outlined in
                                continuation of the conversations you have had with Iraqi officials
                                in Baghdad and Washington. In view however of the interest already
                                expressed to this Government by the British Government in this
                                general subject, in view further of the Iraq Government’s desire for
                                Anglo-American collaboration with it in the formulation of its
                                development program, and in view of this Government’s general policy
                                of maintaining the maximum harmony of action and fullest interchange
                                of views with the British Government in connection with Middle
                                Eastern affairs, the Department considers it important that there
                                should be a further exchange of views with the British Government
                                prior to your communicating this Government’s views to the Iraq
                                authorities.</p>
                            <p>Accordingly a copy of this instruction, together with its enclosures,
                                is being communicated to the American Ambassador in London, with the
                                request that he discuss the subject further with the appropriate
                                authorities of the British Government and explore with them the
                                desirability of similar and synchronized action on their part. It is
                                anticipated that the British Government will welcome such procedure
                                and instruct its representative in Iraq accordingly.<note n="3" xml:id="d52fn3">The Department, on March 29, transmitted a copy
                                    of instruction 17 and its enclosures to “Ambassador Douglas in
                                    instruction 121, noting that: <p>“The particular action
                                        envisaged in the attached instruction to Baghdad was
                                        informally discussed with that official (Mr. Greenhill), and
                                        it was then thought desirable that the action proposed
                                        should await the completion of the so-called Haigh survey of
                                        Iraq irrigation possibilities outlined in the attachment to
                                        Mr. Bevin’s memorandum (of March 20, 1947)
                                        above-mentioned.</p>
                                    <p>“In view, however, of the return of Ambassador Wadsworth to
                                        his post in Baghdad, it is felt that authorization to him to
                                        make appropriate response should not be further delayed. It
                                        is believed, in the light of the earlier discussions
                                        above-referred to that the Foreign Office will welcome the
                                        opportunity for harmonious and synchronized British and
                                        American action in the circumstances. Accordingly, it is
                                        requested that the subject be discussed with the appropriate
                                        officials of the Foreign Office. By this means, it is
                                        desired to afford the Foreign Office opportunity to cause
                                        such instructions as may be deemed desirable, to be sent to
                                        the British representative in Baghdad with a view to
                                        discussion of the subject with Mr. Wadsworth and the taking
                                        of such synchronized action as may be found useful and
                                        appropriate.” (890G.6113/3–2948)</p>
                                    <p>London, on May 26, transmitted to the Department, British
                                        Foreign Office note <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss>
                                        4512/153/93 of May 16 to the American Embassy. The note
                                        deemed it “useless” to press the “care-taker” Government of
                                        Iraq to undertake development plans and considered that “The
                                        present crisis of affairs in Palestine would also render
                                        such action untimely.” The Foreign Office, however, welcomed
                                        joint United States-United Kingdom action to press the Iraqi
                                        Government to resume activity concerning development plans
                                        when a new and more stable government would be formed
                                        (despatch 1228, 890G.6113/5–2648).</p>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="0094" n="80" xml:id="pg_80"/>
                            <p>You should therefore prior to communicating to the Iraq Government
                                the sense of this instruction, consult fully with your British
                                colleague with a view to synchronizing your action with such
                                harmonious action as he may be instructed to take. Should question
                                or difficulty arise as to such synchronization or harmony of action
                                you should communicate with the Department prior to taking the
                                action authorized by this instruction. The Department will
                                communicate to you such further instructions as may be necessary
                                when a report is received from London in response to its parallel
                                instruction to the American Ambassador in that city, a copy of which
                                is enclosed for your information.</p>
                            <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                            <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Willard</hi> L. <hi rend="smallcaps">Thorp</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>