<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Shanghai (
                        Cabot
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d184</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">184</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-05-16T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-16T21:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-16T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-16T21:00:00-05:00" n="184" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d184">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/5–1748: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-17T11:00:00+09:00">May 17, 1948—11 a. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 10:21 p. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1083. Local Chinese, close and intelligent observer of political arena from
                    Chungking days, expresses opinion that despite current headlines about current
                    fracas over Legislative Yuan seats, eyes should be on actions of Kmt cliques and
                    outside groupings. Renegade Kmt members of Yuan may hold key to future. He is
                    inclined, as are most observers, to minimize minority parties as political
                    factor.</p>
                <p>Apparent increased post-election willingness by parties and cliques to bolt Kmt
                    guidance is, in his opinion, a recognition of the fact that Li’s election and
                    his increased stature have suddenly and unexpectedly produced a possible
                    alternative to Generalissimo’s leadership and that a hastening of Kmt
                    disintegration would not now as formerly lead to a leaderless chaos. Alignments
                    behind Li are generally recognized as only seeking of port in storm for many
                    anti-CC factions but that such grouping will outlive CC power though
                    briefly.</p>
                <p>He believes quickest and best but least likely way to obtain political order out
                    of current intra- and inter-party confusion would be Generalissimo’s assumption
                    of supra party position dissolution of Kmt as unsuited to new constitution[al
                    era] and regrouping of political forces in keeping with individual preferences
                    from far left to far right. Idea was explored in Chungking days but
                    discarded.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 1083, repeated Nanking 850.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cabot</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
