<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d201</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">201</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-05-25T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-25T21:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-25T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-25T21:00:00-05:00" n="201" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d201">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/5–2648: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-26T11:00:00+09:00">May 26, 1948—11 a. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 11:03 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>947. It is our opinion that emergence of Marshal Li Chi-shen as leader of
                    Government would probably be widely welcomed in National China by all elements
                    except those most closely associated with Generalissimo, Deptel 744, May 18. As
                    we have previously reported, there exists among politically conscious
                    individuals general apprehension that the present Government’s lack of effective
                    leadership <pb facs="0268" n="258" xml:id="pg_258"/> facilitates rapid spread of
                    Communism. Communist military successes, growing economic distress and unrest in
                    National China, Generalissimo’s maneuvers in installation of constitutional
                    government, his current difficulties in finding acceptable Premier and his
                    selection of political nonentity to this post all contribute to and reenforce
                    this fear. Among less politically minded masses, suffering from
                    maladministration and inadequate leadership blame for plight is, to increasing
                    degree, placed on Generalissimo and associates. Generalissimo has lost much
                    prestige of late. In this situation, change in Government leadership would be
                    welcomed by a steadily increasing number provided new leaders could attract
                    popular confidence and advance popular policies. Inspired leadership is
                    desperately needed. Marshal Li Chi-shen is generally recognized as competent
                    administrator whose patriotism and personal integrity are above question. He
                    would probably gain confidence of politically minded elements and his policy of
                    mediated end to civil war would attract support from all those who have lost
                    faith in ability of present Government to force favorable military decision.
                    Given these factors, given his military connections and fact that he is senior
                    military commander in China after Generalissimo, and considering his close
                    relations with provincial political leaders, we believe it entirely possible
                    that his movement may prove the rallying point for dissident elements in Kmt
                    and, should it move from Hong Kong to national territory, may attract
                    sufficiently strong support to enable it to offer effective government.</p>
                <p>As to question of relative effectiveness present Government and hypothetical
                    government under Marshal Li in halting spread Communism, Department will
                    appreciate that too many factors are involved to permit firm prediction.
                    However, it remains our belief that the present Government lacks capability to
                    halt spread communism and will continue to lack this capability unless, as seems
                    unlikely, it can find the inspired leadership needed to rally the people and
                    restore to national armies a will to fight. The Generalissimo cannot be expected
                    to provide that leadership as he seems incapable of change and gives every
                    evidence of an intention to persist in the personal rule which has resulted in
                    present sad state of affairs. Unless, therefore, we are willing to become
                    dangerously involved in responsibility for governing China and directing the
                    civil war, which we do not recommend, we look for further disintegration of the
                    Government’s position until it is replaced by revolution from within, such as
                    that sponsored by Li, or until it is replaced by the Communists. At this stage
                    it is impossible to forecast positively that government under Marshal Li could
                    be more effective and efficient than present Government in utilizing national,
                    political, military and economic resources against Communists. Nevertheless,
                    such government would have greater measure of public support and confidence and
                    broader <pb facs="0269" n="259" xml:id="pg_259"/> base and might be expected to
                    attract and use more talents than present regime. Whether this would be
                    sufficient to task at hand is not susceptible to prior determination. However,
                    the record of Li Chi-shen, Pai Chung-hsi and Li Tsung-jen in the days when the
                    Liang Kuang<note n="71" xml:id="d201fn71">Two Kuang provinces (Kuangtung and
                        Kuangsi).</note> were models of provincial government gives cause for
                    encouragement.</p>
                <p>In present government, role of General Li Tsung-jen is strictly limited by
                    constitution to presidential succession in event president loses office. Even
                    this right of succession is only implicit. As previously reported,
                    vice-presidential office gives General Li no more than platform publicize views.
                    His support in National Assembly would lend authority these views if this
                    support could be organized. However, far as we are aware General Li has not
                    organized his support. He is despondent, stating he can see no way to effect
                    changes in Government since Generalissimo controls finances and army. Thus,
                    emergence of General Li’s effective political influence is probably dependent on
                    outside factors such as Marshal Li’s Kmt reform party. Circumstances in which
                    this group would come into power would determine ultimate leadership, but
                    General Li would probably be subordinate to Marshal Li. Also on basis their past
                    relations and present association, it is probable that they would cooperate
                    closely and with Pai Chung-hsi it is likely that they would accept subordinate
                    role.</p>
                <p>Those present at interview were Marshal Li, Li Tso-hsien, associate of Marshal
                    Li, Vice Consul Richard Service and Frederic Schultheis, Embassy Attaché.
                    Marshal Li was aware of presence of Embassy officer in Hong Kong and requested
                    interview to describe his views. Interview took place at home Li Tso-hsien,
                    whose relation with Marshal Li are described in Hong Kong unnumbered despatch of
                    April 5.<note n="72" xml:id="d201fn72">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_182">p. 182</ref>.</note>
                    Marshal Li requested that knowledge of meeting be kept from other dissident
                    groups Hong Kong.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
