<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Shanghai (
                        Cabot
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d205</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">205</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-05-28T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-28T04:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="guerrilla" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-28T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-28T04:00:00-05:00" n="205" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d205">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/5–2848: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-28T18:00:00+09:00">May 28, 1948—6 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received May 28—8:50 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1207. Chase,<note n="77" xml:id="d205fn77">Augustus S. Chase, Consul at
                        Shanghai.</note> returned from 8-day Fukien trip, reports by way of
                    preliminary summary following outstanding impressions of Fukien Chinese
                    political attitudes based on opinions expressed to him by <pb facs="0274" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/> numerous missionaries, other foreigners in daily
                    contact with natives and on his own personal talks with many officials and other
                    Chinese: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Evidence overwhelming great majority people believe Nanking regime as
                            hitherto constituted is utterly hopeless and no alleviation of nation’s
                            ills can be expected until Generalissimo and his reactionary politicians
                            are ousted and until war is ended. Unpopularity of Generalissimo is
                            everywhere apparent and need for riddance of “whole Soong dynasty” was
                            frequently expressed.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Testimony without exception indicated general popularity of Li
                            Tsung-jen and strong approval by public and most officials of his
                            election, though some voiced fears he lacks sufficient power to lead
                            accomplishment of needed reforms. Wong Wen-hao’s appointment also very
                            popular. (Some sympathy for Li Chi-shen, with hope of his reaching
                            understanding with Li Tsung-jen, was sensed, though not conclusively
                            established.)</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Re Communism, most significant factor is not what can be seen of
                            tangible Communist achievements such as guerrilla penetration and
                            student agitation, which seem markedly less advanced than in Yangtze
                            area, but what might be described as nonresistibility to Communism. This
                            characteristic attributable to economic misery, disgust with present
                            regime, susceptibility to Communist propaganda and conviction in
                            superior strength of Communists, appears to have significantly affected
                            thinking among all groups of population from peasants to intellectual
                            and even official circles.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>There is universal hatred of military conscription and intense desire
                            to end war which is regarded as doomed to failure and cause of country’s
                            entire economic plight.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Resultant prevalent mood of province does not yet seem of dynamic
                            character threatening positive action toward overthrow present
                            government. In keeping with province’s traditional overseas orientation
                            and relative isolation from interest in national affairs, it appears to
                            be more a negative and defeatist attitude, which, while not seeking to
                            aid or embrace Communism, feels it perhaps worth trying as offering at
                            least as much as present regime and in any case not alarming enough to
                            justify risk of actively opposing it. This attitude is believed to
                            account for apparent disinterest of officials in facing Communist issue
                            squarely and would probably result in province offering no more
                            resistance than it did to Japs in event of Communist push across
                            Yangtze.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Despite disgust with Nanking and war and susceptibility to Communism
                            thought, anti-foreignism is less evidenced than at Shanghai and feeling
                            toward America generally very friendly though many seem to hope for
                            renewed American help in negotiating peace with Communists and/or
                            US–USSR <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Local officials, while friendly, are generally characterized as colorless,
                    ineffectual and unusually corrupt. Noteworthy exception is governor, whom
                    foreigners regard as able administrator. Influence of CC clique and Kmt
                    generally is much less than at Shanghai.</p>
                <p>Sent Nanking 962, repeated Department 1207, pouched Canton and Hong Kong.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cabot</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
