<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Canton (
                        Ludden
                    ) to the Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    )Copy transmitted to the Department by
                        the Consul General in his despatch No. 194, August 10; received August
                        31.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d313</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">313</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="313" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d313">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/8–1048</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Canton</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ludden</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="44" xml:id="d313fn44">Copy transmitted to the Department by
                        the Consul General in his despatch No. 194, August 10; received August
                        31.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 44</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Canton</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-10">August 10,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to previous despatches
                    on the same subject and to enclose a Memorandum<note n="45" xml:id="d313fn45">Not printed.</note> of further Conversation with General Sun Pao Kang, an
                    official of the Democratic Socialist Party.</p>
                <p>The Embassy will observe that General Sun, in common with most other observers,
                    believes that the position of the Central Government is continuing to
                    deteriorate and that the power and prestige of the Generalissimo is at low ebb
                    and that conversely the power and influence of the Chinese Communists and their
                    supporters is rising.</p>
                <p>General Sun’s idea of a coalition of non-Communist groups is not a new idea and
                    General Sun, in common with others who have previously expressed the same
                    thought, is likewise unable to define the leadership of such a group. Although
                    General Sun, in this particular conversation, did not specifically so state,
                    there was a clear implication, as in previous conversations, that in final
                    analysis he considers it will be necessary for the United States to express an
                    interest in such a coalition and thus endow it with the breath of life.</p>
                <p>It will also be noted that General Sun, as previously, continues to play down the
                    importance of Marshal Li Chi-sen and accuses him of having no political program
                    other than that which is dictated by the Communists or his neo-Communist
                    followers. Sun continues to maintain that Li is motivated largely by his hatred
                    of the Generalissimo.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Raymond</hi> P. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ludden</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
