<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d354</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">354</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-09-14T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-09-14T02:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-14T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-14T02:00:00-05:00" n="354" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/9–1448: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-14T16:00:00+09:00">September 14, 1948—4 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received September 15—1:06 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1680. During first week of September North Shensi news agency broadcasts reported
                    in detail on achievements of North China Provisional People’s Representative
                    Congress and hailed inauguration of North China People’s Government as milestone
                    in China’s democratic revolution.</p>
                <p>While admitting that Congress was only provisional in nature and limited to North
                    China, much stress was placed on importance of undertaking political, economic
                    and cultural construction that area. Emphasis was placed on idea that people
                    were masters of their own destinies and that Congress was a truly democratic
                    [one] and devoid of any discrimination of race, creed or sex with members of all
                    classes and groups represented in Presidium. In further attempt to prove this
                    point it was argued that U. S. while claiming to be most democratic state
                    subjected Negro population to numerous racial and political discriminations.</p>
                <p>Accomplishments of past 2 years by governments of two border regions were
                    reported on in detail. In work of supporting front main stress placed on great
                    number enlistments in Army and high political consciousness of peasants.
                    Progress in land reform, agricultural and industrial production and economic
                    reconstruction were highlighted.</p>
                <p>Kmt currency reform measures came under attack as “unprecedented fraud” and
                    attempted despoliation of people’s wealth engineered by Chiang Kai-shek and four
                    families. It was maintained that measures were last desperate attempt of “Chiang
                    Kai-shek’s gang” to swindle people of all gold, silver and foreign exchange and
                    amass wealth of country in Central Bank, allegedly “treasury of four families”
                    in preparation for their flight abroad before final defeat.</p>
                <pb facs="0469" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"/>
                <p>Gold yuan note was ridiculed as lacking reserves and being unredeemable for gold
                    or foreign currency. While admitting that “Kmt suppression and deception and
                    American imperialist material aid” might have temporary dulling effect, it was
                    predicted that currency reform would accelerate economic bankruptcy skyrocketing
                    prices, revival of blackmarket and speculation and outcome would be final
                    collapse of Kmt “reactionary rule”.</p>
                <p>Founding of All Chinese Federation of Labor was hailed as most significant
                    achievement of Sixth All China Labor Congress. According to one report, two most
                    important provisions of program were for direct participation of workers in
                    management of all public enterprises through “democratically elected factory
                    administration committees” and direct workers representative conferences.
                    Emphasis was placed on cooperative pooling of workers’ knowledge and experience,
                    establishment of minimum scales of wages, hours and conditions, system of
                    graduated wages based on skill, output and technique, equal pay for women,
                    safety provisions, education and technical training. All technicians and experts
                    from Kmt areas were invited to join people in “industrial construction of
                    liberated areas”.</p>
                <p>In broadcast to All Overseas Chinese, Labor Congress appealed to industrialists
                    and businessmen to unite with people of China and join fight for freedom from
                    Kmt rule. Kmt regime flayed for attempting convert China into colony of American
                    imperialism and plunge whole Chinese people at home and abroad further into life
                    of slavery.</p>
                <p>War communiqués continued to play up Kmt losses on all fighting fronts with
                    occasional reference to capture of Japanese soldiers fighting with Kmt troops.
                    Reference was also made to continued bombing and strafing of Yellow River dyke
                    workers by “American-made planes”.</p>
                <p>Sent Department as 1680, repeated to Moscow.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
