<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-19T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-19T21:00:00-05:00" n="360" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d360">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/9–2048: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Tsingtao</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Turner</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tsingtao</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-20T11:00:00+09:00">September
                                    20, 1948—11 a. m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received September 21—1:56 a. m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>142. Reference Tsinan battle, Commies reported within 2 miles of city
                            wall to East, meaning they are inside main defense line that area. On
                            South, Commies have captured hill which enables them infiltrate and fire
                            on old and new airfields. CAT<note n="14" xml:id="d360fn14">Civil Air
                                Transport.</note> withdrew planes to Tsingtao morning September 18,
                            continues render support to them. Last CAT flight left Tsinan morning
                            September 18 under small arms fire.</p>
                        <p>That there has been real fighting is witnessed by long lines wounded and
                            trucks bearing dead seen returning to city. Disorganization apparent
                            among National forces on first 2 days now claimed overcome. CAT native
                            staff Tsinan asserts population believes Commie victory inevitable, thus
                            hope will come soon and without destruction. Up to 8 Commie columns in
                            attacking force with perhaps 2 in reserve. Few grounds for optimism
                            unless Wang Yao-wu<note n="15" xml:id="d360fn15">Commander of the Second
                                Pacification Area and Governor of Shantung.</note> assumes
                            offensive. This should be possible view ample supply ammunition and
                            minor disparity in strengths of defending and attacking. Nationalists
                            have 2d, 73d and 84th Divisions and 19th and 57th Brigades, totaling
                            around 80,000 men, plus 40 to 50,000 local troops in very restricted
                            perimeter. Commies probably numerically superior by only one-third.</p>
                        <p>Sudden cessation air service Tsinan prevents departure of the few foreign
                            residents desirous of leaving. Americans number eight. List names
                            follows in separate message,<note n="16" xml:id="d360fn16">Not found in
                                Department files.</note> Presume Embassy has seen ComNavWesPacs<note n="17" xml:id="d360fn17">Commander in Chief, U. S. Naval Forces,
                                Western Pacific.</note> conference 190631Z.<note n="18" xml:id="d360fn18">Not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0475" n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/>
                        <p>Sent Nanking 269; repeated Department 142.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Turner</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>