<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-15T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-15T23:00:00-05:00" n="391" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d391">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/10–1648: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-16T12:00:00+08:00">October
                                    16, 1948—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received October 16—6:34 a.
                                m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1922. Hong Kong ConGen reports receipt letter from Marshal Li Chi-shen
                            for Ambassador. Letter delivered by close associate of Marshal, who
                            states letter appeals to US to cease support present Chinese Government,
                            predicts it will fall by end of year, pledges support future
                            Sino-American cooperation, promises KmtRC will not tolerate one-party
                            control of government and states our withdrawal support from
                            Generalissimo will be followed by PCC coalition government and peace,
                            and so will be act of great friendship toward Chinese people.</p>
                        <pb facs="0506" n="496" xml:id="pg_496"/>
                        <p>Marshal’s spokesman also stated Li Chi-shen will be president coalition
                            government with Mao Tse-tung as vice president. Feng Yu-hsiang was to
                            have been head of army with Chu Teh as deputy. No replacement yet found.
                            Li Tsung-jen<note n="72" xml:id="d391fn72">Vice President of the
                                Republic of China.</note> to occupy only minor role since he failed
                            cooperate actively with KmtRC after election. Owing rapid deterioration
                            Government military and economic position, Marshal has abandoned plans
                            set up southwest China provisional government.</p>
                        <p>While veracity of Marshal’s statement and claims difficult to assess, it
                            is possible that facts are substantially as he represents them. At
                            present time Communists appear to be gaining military ascendancy
                            rapidly. However, they are faced with serious internal political and
                            economic problems. These problems will increase many fold as they
                            increase territorial holdings by military operations. Communists’
                            principal difficulty in solution these problems is lack sufficient
                            administrative personnel and technicians. Bulk of persons in
                            non-Communist China with such qualifications are either members Kmt or
                            are employees present Kmt-dominated Government. Thus it would be greatly
                            to Communist advantage if they could replace present Kmt leadership with
                            KmtRC and associate this reformed party with new coalition government.
                            This maneuver would provide them with administration over which they
                            might gradually secure control, and at same time would create government
                            with multi-party façade and democratic appearance, and so would appear
                            to be reasonable and likely course of action for them to adopt.</p>
                        <p>There is still no evidence that present Kmt leaders contemplate
                            relinquishing office voluntarily, nor does there yet appear to be any
                            active movement on Nationalist side for their expulsion. However, there
                            is now almost no hope among Nationalist civil and military officials
                            that Communist tide can be stayed, and it is freely admitted that
                            another break in either military or economic front will be “the end”.
                            Thus there are not many who continue with conviction to support the
                            Generalissimo except his immediate followers and certain ranking
                            military officers. There are increasing signs that this group now holds
                            together more from fear of its fate, should Communists win, than from
                            deep loyalty to Nationalist cause and at least one of its most prominent
                            members, General Chang Chih-chung,<note n="73" xml:id="d391fn73">Chief
                                of the Northwest Authority (in Lanchow).</note> freely advocates
                            immediately negotiated end to civil war. Those whose faith in, and
                            allegiance to, Generalissimo is lukewarm or nonexistent and who will not
                            espouse Communist cause, have no leader to whom they can turn. Should
                            Communists convoke PCC and form new government with participation in
                            KmtRC, as seems to be their purpose, <pb facs="0507" n="497" xml:id="pg_497"/> there are very many on Nationalist side prepared
                            to admit that mandate for party leadership has passed from Generalissimo
                            to Marshal Li or another. Under these conditions, particularly as
                            further military and economic reverses continue to reduce his influence,
                            the Generalissimo may well be forced from power by his erstwhile
                            supporters and persuaded to accept retirement.</p>
                        <p>We do not, at present moment, regard this development as certain,
                            although we think it highly possible. Among other alternatives open to
                            Generalissimo are fight to finish in Nanking, or flight with leading
                            members his Government to other location in China. First alternative
                            appears unlikely, for it is improbable that Generalissimo could
                            associate many with himself in such endeavor. Also, flight would be
                            construed throughout country as admission of defeat. He would find
                            himself with very small following should he attempt move Government to
                            new location. Revolutionary conditions are too far advanced and present
                            Government in too great discredit with body politic for long survival
                            after transplantation, and it seems most unlikely that it would ever
                            become rallying point for effective counterrevolution whether in exile
                            abroad or moved elsewhere in China.</p>
                        <p>As Department is aware, we have long said that appearance of coalition
                            government in China under Communist auspices was highly likely unless we
                            were able to intervene with sufficient force and control to change
                            trend.</p>
                        <p>That opportunity now may have passed. It is difficult to see at this late
                            date how any efforts on our part short of armed intervention on very
                            large scale can avert further military disaster, with likelihood
                            coalition in some form will result. There is complete unwillingness on
                            part of Nationalist troops to fight and in many instances they are
                            succumbing to Communist propaganda and defecting at first
                            opportunity.</p>
                        <p>As a result Government, but especially Generalissimo, is more unpopular
                            than ever and is increasingly denounced. Objection is not to Government
                            and to Generalissimo as such but against their inability to provide
                            protection and tolerable living conditions. Indeed our present policy of
                            support to Nationalist Government is but little better liked on
                            Nationalist side than on Communist. We are criticized for prolonging
                            suffering of Chinese people by supporting continuation of civil war
                            without giving Government means to victory, Chinese people of all walks
                            of life are war-weary and it is safe to say that coalition government is
                            now fairly generally regarded as inevitable and as preferable to
                            prolongation of civil war and that we are blamed as authors of political
                            and military stalemate wherein entire country suffers. We are by no
                            means sanguine over prospect of our influencing coalition government so
                            as to prevent its development into familiar patterns of gradual
                            domination by Communists. Nevertheless we <pb facs="0508" n="498" xml:id="pg_498"/> are at loss for means to avert coalition. It may
                            be therefore that we have reached point where present leadership of
                            Nationalist China is no longer effective medium for our efforts in
                            stemming spread of Communism in China. If this is so, we should consider
                            carefully our attitude toward coalition particularly while it is in its
                            formative period. We do not advocate abandoning Generalissimo at this
                            time. However, little good and much harm will ensue if we continue to
                            support him after he has been rejected by all except small group for
                            which, by reason of its past, no dealings with any element in coalition
                            government would be possible.</p>
                        <p>As we look at picture therefore we must envisage some typical Chinese
                            arrangement whereunder Generalissimo will retire and a coalition
                            government will be formed. It is entirely possible that in the
                            beginning, the northwest under Chang Chi-chung and the Mas,<note n="74" xml:id="d391fn74">The five so-called Ma generals of the Northwest:
                                Ma Hung-kwei, Governor of Ningsia; Ma Pu-fang, Governor of Tsinghai;
                                Ma Pu-ching, Deputy Commander in Chief Fortieth Group Army; Ma
                                Hung-pin, military commander Tsinghai; and Ma Chang-hsiang, leader
                                of Tsinghai Fifth Cavalry Army.</note> and Szechwan, Yunnan and
                            Kweichow under respective provincial leaders,<note n="75" xml:id="d391fn75">Wang Ling-chi, Lu Han, and Ku Cheng-Inn, Governors
                                of the Provinces of Szechwan, Yunnan, and Kweichow,
                                respectively.</note> will remain aloof and unmolested by Communists.
                            Likewise, T. V. Soong<note n="76" xml:id="d391fn76">Governor of
                                Kwangtung.</note> in the south may have a breathing spell while
                            Communists consolidate their gains in the north under coalition. During
                            that time we must retain a very flexible policy. China, under whatever
                            regime, needs external aid and US is only source available at this
                            stage. Accordingly, we have ammunition which we can use in our interests
                            as developing situation makes more clear exactly where our interests
                            lie.</p>
                        <p>Sent Department, pouched all Consulates, China.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>