<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d462</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">462</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-11-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-11-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="462" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d462">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/9–2048</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 230</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-11-13">November 13,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Acting Secretary of State refers to the Embassy’s despatch no. 396, September
                    20, 1948,<note n="85" xml:id="d462fn85">Not printed.</note> and in particular to
                    the following sentence: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“(5) <hi rend="italic">Coalition Government</hi>. The reversal of
                            American policy in regard to this issue becomes a rather academic
                            question in view of the <hi rend="italic">intransigeant</hi> attitude of
                            both the Kuomintang and the Communist Party.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>A review and careful examination of all recent instructions to the Embassy has
                    been undertaken in an attempt to ascertain the possible occasion for any such
                    concept of a reversal of American policy. This search revealed that the only
                    recent instruction which dealt with the question of a coalition was the
                    Department’s Top Secret telegram no. 1164 of August 12, 1948. This telegram was
                    occasioned by the following statement in the Ambassador’s despatch no. 287 of
                    June 30, 1948: <pb facs="0577" n="567" xml:id="pg_567"/>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“They [the Chinese Communist Party]<note n="86" xml:id="d462fn86">Brackets appear in the original instruction.</note> hint that if we
                            Americans are sincere in wanting peace, we should demonstrate this by
                            withdrawing all of our armed forces from China, which is only one of
                            several indications that they continue to think in terms of our
                            mediation. I am maintaining an attitude of friendly but passive interest
                            while assuring them that the door is still open if they care to take
                            advantage of it.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Telegraphic instruction no. 1164 of August 12, 1948, was sent as indicated
                    therein so that there should be no misunderstanding since it was considered that
                    the above-quoted statement was not constant with the instructions set forth in
                    telegram 90664 of January 27, 1947,<note n="87" xml:id="d462fn87">
                        <ref target="frus1946v10#pg_709">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">x</hi>, p. 709</ref>.</note> which was despatched
                    by the Secretary of State to the Ambassador through Colonel Underwood<note n="88" xml:id="d462fn88">Officer in charge of the Embassy Liaison Office,
                        successor to General Marshall’s office in China.</note> at Nanking, the
                    third paragraph of which is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The foregoing decision [i. e., the withdrawal of the Executive
                                Headquarters]<note n="89" xml:id="d462fn89">Brackets appear in the
                                original instruction. A press release issued by the Department on
                                January 29, 1947, indicated that the United States Government had
                                decided “to terminate its connection with Executive Headquarters
                                which was established in Peiping by the Committee of Three for the
                                purpose of supervising, in the field, the execution of “the
                                agreements for the cessation of hostilities and the demobilization
                                and reorganization of the Armed Forces in China.”</note> should not
                            operate to interfere with assistance by you if either side initiates
                            appeal to you, in your normal functioning as American Ambassador, for
                            assistance in the various problems peculiar to the Chinese situation.
                            The above does however spell conclusion to negotiations which were
                            initiated by me in December 1945. Should a decision be reached to reopen
                            negotiations they of course would probably take a new shape and you
                            would be duly advised as to whether or not it is desirable for the
                            Embassy to participate.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Accordingly, it will be appreciated that assurances that “the door is still open”
                    were misleading and unauthorized. So far as the U.S. Government was concerned,
                    the door was not open and, therefore, the assertion quoted in the first
                    paragraph of this instruction is not in conformity with the facts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
