<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-08-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-08-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="663" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d663">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">693.0031 Tibet/8–3148</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Chief of the
                            Division of Chinese Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Freeman</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-08-31">August 31, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging"> Tsepon Shakabpa, Leader of the Tibetan Trade
                                Mission</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Rinshi Pangdatshang, Member of the Tibetan
                                Trade Mission</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Ratna, Interpreter of the Tibetan Trade
                                Mission</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Benninghoff, FE</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Freeman, CA</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The above-named three members of the Tibetan Trade Mission called this
                        morning by appointment on Mr. Benninghoff. As on previous occasions, Mr.
                        Shakabpa spoke for the Mission through the interpreter.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Shakabpa opened the conversation by expressing appreciation for the offer
                        to sell 50,000 ounces of gold to Tibet for purposes of currency
                        stabilization and requesting a temporary loan to Tibet of $2 million in
                        order that the gold purchase might be arranged immediately. (The details of
                        Mr. Shakabpa’s proposal are embodied in the attached letter to the Secretary
                        dated August 31, 1948,<note n="21" xml:id="d663fn21">
                            <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>.</note> which was handed to Mr. Benninghoff
                        at the close of the conversation.) Mr. Shakabpa explained that the
                        Government of Tibet had sufficient rupee exchange in banks in India which
                        could serve as collateral for the loan. In reply to the pertinent question,
                        Mr. Shakabpa stated that the amount of rupee exchange was in excess of the
                        $2 million requested, computed at the official rate of exchange.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Shakabpa emphasized the temporary nature of the loan requested, and
                        stated that it could in all probability be repaid shortly after the
                        Mission’s return to Tibet. He said that, if the loan were granted, it would
                        strengthen Tibet’s bargaining position in current discussions with India
                        looking toward a revision of the “old treaty” between Tibet and British
                        India, and he indicated that the commercial and financial aspects at issue
                        might then be resolved in Tibet’s favor.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Shakabpa also brought up the question of the possibility of American
                        businessmen, tourists, newspaper men, etc. and official American
                        representatives visiting Tibet. He stated that his Mission was concerned
                        with purely commercial and financial matters, but that he wished to report
                        to his Government the views of the U. S. Government in this regard. He
                        explained that the Mission had received many informal requests from various
                        Americans for permission <pb facs="0793" n="783" xml:id="pg_783"/> to visit
                        Tibet and he indicated that the Mission heartily approved of the idea. (Both
                        Mr. Benninghoff and myself received the impression, however, that such
                        permission might be conditional upon the granting of the $2 million
                        loan.)</p>
                    <p>Mr. Benninghoff replied that he felt that it would be advantageous to both
                        Tibet and the U. S. if there were more interchange of businessmen, students,
                        newspaper men, etc., but that under present conditions travel to Tibet by
                        foreigners was apparently not permitted by the Tibetan Government. With
                        regard to official American representatives, Mr. Benninghoff inquired of Mr.
                        Shakabpa what the attitude of the Tibetan Government would be if the U. S.
                        Government should request authorization to send an American Consul into
                        Tibet. I explained that, if such a decision were perchance made, it would in
                        no way constitute an alteration of our traditional recognition of China’s
                            <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> sovereignty over Tibet. Mr. Shakabpa
                        stated that he was not in a position to speak for his Government in this
                        regard, but that he was of the opinion that such a request might be regarded
                        with favor.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Benninghoff stated that the question of the $2 million loan would be
                        discussed with the appropriate officers of the Government and that the
                        Mission would be informed in the premises as soon as possible. Mr. Shakabpa
                        stated that the Mission would return to New York on September 1 and
                        requested that the Department’s reply be forwarded to the Mission in care of
                        the Hotel Commodore, New York City.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>