<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-11-02T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-11-02T23:00:00-05:00" n="693" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d693">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">125.351/11–348: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-11-03T12:00:00+08:00">November 3,
                                1948—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received November 3—8:42 a. m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>2073. We believe recent Communist victories in Manchuria have highlighted
                        present value and considerably increased potential value of our Consulate in
                        Dairen. In final paragraph of his telegram October 1, sent Nanking 62,
                        repeated Department 160, Paddock urged that Dairen Consulate not be closed
                        simply because of delay in reestablishing courier service. We are inclined
                        to reconsider our recommendation made in penultimate paragraph Embtel 1607,
                        August 31 that Dairen Consulate be closed with full publicity if Soviets
                        after a month still refuse to agree to our re-establishment of a courier
                        service and now to recommend further and more emphatic approach to Foreign
                        Office in Moscow to permit us to service Dairen.</p>
                    <p>More than month has now passed since Moscow Embassy on September 30th first
                        sent letter to Soviet Foreign Office requesting prompt approval of proposed
                        re-establishment of courier service and, as far as we have learned, Soviet
                        Foreign Office has not yet shown courtesy of reply. This inaction clearly
                        portends Soviet intention to allow our Dairen Consulate simply to die on the
                        vine through lack of courier service bringing in currency, codes and vital
                        supplies. We believe the longer this Soviet inaction continues, the more set
                        it will become.</p>
                    <p>More emphatic representations Moscow might consist of flat statement to
                        Soviets that, if they continue to obstruct our legitimate courier service to
                        Dairen, we shall have no recourse but to reconsider the policy of
                        cooperation which we have always followed in assisting Soviet courier
                        services out of Washington to such lateral points as Ottawa, Mexico City,
                        Havana, and even Australia. We believe it very probable that Soviets would
                        quickly realize danger of jeopardizing their lateral courier runs under our
                        control which are certainly more important to them than ours to us.
                        Furthermore, given Soviet custom of making their reprisals in kind, we think
                        there is little danger that Soviets would try to retaliate to this display
                        of force in some other unrelated fields (which have already been quite well
                        covered anyway).</p>
                    <pb facs="0809" n="799" xml:id="pg_799"/>
                    <p>Unless we are prepared to force this issue to logical and justifiable
                        conclusion, we hold as academic question raised in Paddock’s despatch No.
                        31, July 25 to Embassy (copy to Department<note n="22" xml:id="d693fn22">Not
                            printed.</note>) concerning his recommendations about periodic
                        assignments of Russian and Chinese speaking FSOS to Dairen and Moscow’s and
                        Peiping’s approval thereof (see Moscow airgram 892, September 13 to
                            Department<note n="22" xml:id="d693fn23">Not printed.</note>) and
                        Peiping despatch No. 69, August 21, sent Nanking with copy to
                            Department.<note n="22" xml:id="d693fn24">Not printed.</note>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>