<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in China (
                        Stuart
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v07</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d723</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">723</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-05-26T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-05-26T21:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-26T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-26T21:00:00-05:00" n="723" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d723">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">125.633/5–2748: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-27T11:00:00+09:00">May 27, 1948—11 a. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received May 27—9:45 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>958. Re Mukden’s 266, May 18 [<hi rend="italic">8</hi>]<note n="22" xml:id="d723fn22">Sent to the Department as telegram No. 197, <ref target="#pg_815">p. 815</ref>.</note> and previous exchange of telegrams
                    between Nanking, Mukden and Department on size of staff in Mukden in event of
                    Communist occupation, Embassy while fully recognizing considerations which led
                    ConGen Mukden belief that staff in Mukden should, if anything, be increased in
                    event of Communist occupation, feels compelled to disagree. As we have
                    oftentimes repeated, it is our conviction that US Government in any area where
                    it has an established office must stand its ground in the event of Communist
                    occupation. The entire position of American interests in China could well be
                    seriously compromised should we at every point recede. It is fully realized that
                    a certain element of physical risk is involved for those concerned and an even
                    higher possibility of grave unpleasantness or even physical discomfort and it is
                    our conviction that all possible should be done for such American personnel as
                    remain in the event of Communist occupation.</p>
                <p>There are, however, in our opinion, certain factors which counsel against the
                    increase in staff as recommended by Mukden. The cold fact is that we simply do
                    not know with any degree of assurance what the reaction of occupying Communist
                    forces would be to the presence of American officials. We must, therefore,
                    proceed on assumption there may be fairly considerable possibility of physical
                    danger until it is proven to the contrary. On this assumption the risk of an
                    incident which would precipitate unfortunate consequences for all concerned
                    increases in direct ratio to the number of individuals concerned. Furthermore,
                    since communications between Communist and National territory will most
                    assuredly be extremely difficult, the problem of supporting those who remain
                    also increases in direct ratio the numbers involved. It is therefore our
                    considered opinion that the size of the staff should be conditioned by the
                    volume of work possible. Our evidence at present suggests that the current <pb facs="0830" n="820" xml:id="pg_820"/> staff is more [than?] adequate for the
                    work [that?] can be done in Mukden today and since this volume of work would
                    doubtless be reduced under the Communists, an even smaller staff under
                    occupation would be adequate.</p>
                <p>Embassy is fully cognizant of and sympathetic to problems of morale which are
                    raised by ConGen Mukden. We are in full agreement that all possible should be
                    done to maintain that morale. We would, at the same time, point out that service
                    in Mukden is on a voluntary basis. We would also point out that there are many
                    posts in Foreign Service today where living conditions are anything but ideal;
                    and thirdly, we would point out that association with Foreign Service implies on
                    part of those who enter it a readiness undergo certain hardships and certain
                    disabilities which are not expected of other people. If we read current trend of
                    world affairs correctly, Foreign Service officers and employees can, for a
                    number of years to come, expect only hardship and discomfort in a number of
                    areas of the world. We say this with all sympathetic understanding of problems
                    with which Mukden may be confronted and with assurance we will, of course, do
                    all within our power to be helpful. But we must state our opinion that in the
                    interests not only of the US itself but also of individuals concerned the
                    indicated course of action should be a gradual reduction in size of the Mukden
                    staff to a number more commensurate with work possible to be accomplished under
                    existing and anticipated conditions.</p>
                <p>Sent Department, repeated Mukden 101.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
