<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-03-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="177" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d177">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72119/1740</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Report of the Special Agent at Cairo</hi> (<persName>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Yale</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">Report No. 17</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-03-04">
                                        <hi rend="italic">March 4, 1918</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received May 28.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">The Growing Discontent among the Arabs; Reasons
                                    for this Discontent</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>In 1915 <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Emir Faisal</persName>, the son of
                                the King of the Hedjaz who is now leading the Arab forces at Akabah,
                                was in Damascus. He was in constant communication with the Moslem
                                Arab leaders in Damascus, who were bitterly opposed to the Turks and
                                wished to free themselves from the Ottoman yoke. Arab leaders and
                                sheikhs from the important tribes and groups in Syria from the East
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SJH2">Jordan</persName>, Hauran and other
                                regions secretly visited <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Emir
                                    Faisal</persName> and the Damascus leaders, and pledged
                                themselves to aid and support an Arab revolt, if such should be
                                started by the Cherif of Mecca.</p>
                            <pb facs="0334" n="242" xml:id="pg_242"/>
                            <p>At this time the Arabs affirm that they received a telegram (a copy
                                and translation of which it is hoped will later be obtained) from
                                Cherif Houssain stating that he had received the requisite supply of
                                rifles, cannon, ammunition, provisions and gold and that the Arabs
                                had been promised their independence if they joined in with the
                                Allies. On the strength of this telegram the Arab leaders in Syria
                                were pledged to the cause of the Cherif; and <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Emir Faisal</persName> with several of the
                                Damascus leaders fled to the Hedjaz. On June 5, 1916, the revolt of
                                the Arabs against the Turks began under the leadership of the Cherif
                                of Mecca and his four sons.</p>
                            <p>Many of the Arabian sheikhs were won over to the cause of the Cherif,
                                Syrian officers and soldiers offered their services to the King of
                                the Hedjaz, and through prisoners of the British taken from the
                                Turks they were organized and trained to cooperate with the forces
                                of the Cherif and his four sons. A propaganda in favor of the Arabs
                                was spread among the Arab tribes in the East <persName corresp="#p_SJH2">Jordan</persName> regions, in the Hauran, in
                                the Irak and among the Arabs of Syria.</p>
                            <p>Up to this time no public announcement was made of the policy of the
                                Allies towards the Arabs; but the Arabs were fighting for the
                                deliverance of their people from the Turks and with the hope [of]
                                independence, partial or entire, in their hearts.</p>
                            <p>During the summer of 1917 the secret treaties between England, Russia
                                and France were found and published at Petrogad.<note n="1" xml:id="d177fn1">See <ref target="frus1917Supp02v01#pg_493">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1917, Supplement
                                        2, vol. I, pp. 493</ref>–<ref target="frus1917Supp02v01#pg_507">507</ref>.</note> And it
                                became known that by these agreements France was to be given Syria,
                                Palestine was to be made international, and Great Britain was to
                                have Mesopotamia and the Irak and to hold the Syrian ports of Haifa
                                and Acre.</p>
                            <p>British and French statesmen made no definite statements about the
                                future of Syria, Mesopotamia and the Arabs; but public declarations
                                were made to the effect that neither Great Britain nor France was
                                waging a war of conquest and annexation, and that they endorsed the
                                principle of the right of small nationalities to an existence of
                                their own.</p>
                            <p>The Turks began to change their policy; Djemal Pasha visited Berlin
                                and returned to Syria, Abbas Hilmi, ex-Khedive of Egypt, was brought
                                to Syria, and a pro-Arab, Pan-Islamic propaganda was inaugurated.
                                (See Report No. 11 of January 21.<note n="2" xml:id="d177fn2">Not
                                    printed.</note>)</p>
                            <p>On November 11, 1917, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAJ1">Balfour</persName> made his now famous declaration to the
                                Zionists, and shortly afterwards the southern part of Palestine and
                                the city of Jerusalem fell into the hands of the British. This
                                supplied the Turks with more material for their propaganda, by which
                                they are trying to stir up the Arabs in Mesopotamia, in the Irak, in
                                Syria, the Hauran and East <persName corresp="#p_SJH2">Jordan</persName> regions, and even <pb facs="0335" n="243" xml:id="pg_243"/> in Arabia. (See Report No. 11: Letters of
                                Djemal Pasha to <persName corresp="#p_FE1">Emir Faisal</persName>
                                and Cherif Houssain.<note n="1" xml:id="d177fn3">Not
                                printed.</note>) The Turks point out that the first step taken by
                                the Allies after conquering southern Palestine was to give it, an
                                Arab country, to the Jews; and they, the Turks, insist that England
                                and France are fighting Turkey only to seize Mesopotamia and Syria
                                for themselves and not for the Arabs.</p>
                            <p>On December 23, 1917, Sir <persName>Mark Sykes</persName>, a special
                                delegate of the British Government (whose activities have been
                                mentioned in several previous reports), made the following
                                statements in a speech delivered before the Central Syrian Committee
                                at Paris: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Great Britain and France are at one in their politics in
                                        regard to all that concerns the non-Turkish elements of the
                                        Ottoman Empire.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>There exists no divergence or dispute between the two
                                        countries.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Jerusalem, Bagdad, Bassorah have been delivered from the
                                        Turks, and if the Turks are unable to retake them by force
                                        of arms they shall never have them by treaty.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The Arabs have brought to a successful conclusion the
                                        independence of the Hedjaz, and the least that can be said
                                        is that they are able to maintain their position. …<note n="2" xml:id="d177fn4">Punctuation as in the
                                            original.</note>
                                    </item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item>Point 4, the independence of the Hedjaz, is also of real
                                        importance; the accomplished fact of the independence of the
                                        Hedjaz renders it almost impossible that an effective and
                                        real autonomy should be refused to Syria. …<note n="2" xml:id="d177fn5">Punctuation as in the original.</note>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The Turks are still the masters of Syria.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The Syrians are not united. Make no mistake, Europe will not
                                    continue the war for the sole purpose of giving Syria her
                                    independence. And by this I wish to say that if when the war
                                    ends the Turks are still in Damascus and Beyrouth and you
                                    Syrians being still divided among yourselves into many parties
                                    following your ancient races and religions, I would despair of
                                    obtaining for you more than reforms on paper. …<note n="2" xml:id="d177fn6">Punctuation as in the original.</note>
                                </item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>Get together, unite, and you will become a powerful political
                                    force and if you desire a program, I would not know how to
                                    dictate it to you, it is the circumstances which will write
                                    it.</item>
                            </list>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>First of all it is necessary to do away absolutely with the
                                    negative Turkish regime: that which by unanimous opinion is
                                    intolerable in Armenia, is equally intolerable in Syria.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>You must desire that France give you her indispensable
                                    assistance, which a people for long time oppressed has need of
                                    before it can walk alone; you must demand guarantees of the
                                    civilized powers of the world that you be not again submitted to
                                    Turkish domination, which has reduced you to poverty and
                                    discord.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>A translation from the French of the entire speech<note n="1" xml:id="d177fn7">Not printed.</note> of Sir <persName>Mark
                                    Sykes</persName> is attached to this report.</p>
                            <p>
                                <persName>M. Jean Gout</persName>, Minister Plenipotentiary,
                                representing the French Minister of Foreign Affairs, made a speech
                                after Sir <persName>Mark Sykes</persName>, from which the following
                                is quoted: <pb facs="0336" n="244" xml:id="pg_244"/>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>Putting aside all idea of colonial domination, the two Allies
                                        are resolved, each in its sphere of action, to guide the
                                        population which speaks Arabic, and those who speak all
                                        other languages, who inhabit the region which extends from
                                        the Anatolian mountains to the Indian Ocean (the sea of the
                                        Indies) towards a regime of autonomy and civilized
                                        development, in a mutual respect of the religious beliefs
                                        and nationalities. A guide towards a better future, an
                                        arbitrator between religious and ethnical groups, a friendly
                                        advisor of civilization; such is the role that France and
                                        Great Britain are ready to assume, one in the north, the
                                        other in the south.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>The entire text of the speech of <persName>M. Jean
                                    Gout</persName><note n="1" xml:id="d177fn8">Not printed.</note>
                                is attached to this report.</p>
                            <p>Not only are the Syrian Arabs in Egypt greatly upset by this news and
                                declare that it means the division of the Arab provinces between
                                France and Great Britain, but they claim that the Arabs of Syria,
                                east of the <persName corresp="#p_SJH2">Jordan</persName>, in the
                                Hauran and throughout Syria, worked upon by the Turks, who it is
                                reported have promised the Arab provinces autonomy and are returning
                                Arab exiles to Syria, are losing faith in the Allies and are
                                unwilling to cooperate with them.</p>
                            <p>They claim that, unless a clearer, less ambiguous statement be made
                                by the Allies in regard to the future of Syria and Mesopotamia, the
                                Arab tribes of the Irak and the Arabs of Syria as well as many of
                                the tribes in Arabia will be lost to the cause of the Allies and of
                                the King of the Hedjaz.</p>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William Yale</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>