<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-01-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="33" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d33">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72119/1184</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Switzerland</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WHR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-01-27">
                                        <hi rend="italic">January 27, 1918</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received January 28, 7.24
                                    a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2513. German press comment on Chancellor’s speech.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Berliner Tageblatt</hi>, 25th: Despite emphatic
                                warning of Pan-Germans, Chancellor discussed <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s peace programme in detail.
                                Extremely doubtful, however, whether this discussion will lead to
                                general peace. His statement that Belgium not to be annexed is
                                highly welcome, but regrettable that he modified it by declaring
                                details of question can only be arranged at peace negotiations. His
                                attitude on this question still too hesitating and not sufficiently
                                unequivocal. <persName corresp="#p_CvCCO1">Czernin</persName>’s
                                    speech<note n="1" xml:id="d33fn1">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_54">p.
                                    54</ref>.</note> undoubtedly great event which perhaps may lead
                                to still more important events. Declarations of <persName corresp="#p_CvCCO1">Czernin</persName> that no opposition of
                                interests between Austria and America and his belief that peace
                                between Vienna and Washington is easiest, lead to conviction that
                                these statements have been made in conjunction with Berlin. Many
                                signs show that especially in the last weeks the desire for war in
                                America has abated; want of coal has caused large retrenchments and
                                prevented equipment of army. <persName corresp="#p_CvCCO1">Czernin</persName> speech [will] strengthen opponents of
                                warlike policy and increase atmosphere of peace. <persName corresp="#p_HCGFv1">Hertling</persName>’s speech alone will
                                scarcely conjure up peace, but possible that <persName corresp="#p_CvCCO1">Czernin</persName> may yet lead <persName corresp="#p_HCGFv1">Hertling</persName> thereto.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vorwärts</hi>, January 25: Speech of Chancellor
                                might have been world-freeing act if it had clearly stated that
                                behind German expressions of peace desires there lay concealed no
                                egotistic ambitions for power. It has not done this and
                                unfortunately in parts was calculated to increase the enemies’
                                distrust in sincerity of German peace declaration. This is
                                especially true of statements regarding treatment of Poland and
                                Belgium. Right of Russia to have a voice regarding Poland actually
                                recognized in Brest Litovsk negotiations. Lasting <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName> peace can only come if the
                                whole situation is taken as basis and any changes based on general
                                sanction. Regarding Belgium, Chancellor does not even meet desires
                                radical English peace advocates who demand unconditional return. The
                                conditions under which evacuation of occupied French territory is
                                granted will awaken suspicion in enemy; he might at least have
                                declared that no aspirations to annex Longwy and Briey existed.
                                Speech of Chancellor masterwork in finding elastic formulas in which
                                journalists can read what they want, but of such we have had enough.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SP1">Scheidemann</persName> criticism
                                pointed out our mistakes and weakness of speech and millions of the
                                people support him. <pb facs="0140" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/> When
                                enemies are ready for true democratic peace, a permanent peace
                                neither shameful for us or for them, they can count on immense
                                majority of German people which, though it will continue to fight
                                for its rights, wants nothing save peace and what was theirs before
                                war. The existing current must become strong enough to make
                                resistance to it on the part of those in power impossible.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</hi>, 25th: Speeches of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HCGFv1">Hertling</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CvCCO1">Czernin</persName> leave impression that way
                                to peace is open. However, speech of Chancellor has not brought
                                clarity necessary to thwart reports of annexionistic politicians. We
                                greatly regret this because attempts to force Government into policy
                                of senseless annexations rob us of internal quiet for necessary
                                reorganization at home and support doubts of enemies as to good
                                faith of our peace desires. <persName corresp="#p_HCGFv1">Hertling</persName> preserves hope that it is possible to lead
                                as one all parties of German people and to postpone moment of
                                separation. This is a fatal illusion as he will soon learn. The fact
                                that the German Chancellor and his German [<hi rend="italic">Austrian</hi>] colleague in Vienna have discussed and found
                                acceptable part of <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s
                                programme and have invited a reconsideration of terms will alienate
                                Military Party. Therefore it would have been better to have taken
                                the inevitable step and clearly broken away from this party.
                                Chancellor summarized in three words what Germany expects to gain
                                from the war as a basis of a lasting peace: integrity of the German
                                Empire, security for our vital interests and the honor of our
                                Fatherland. We would have wished that he had spoken more clearly
                                relative to Belgium and occupied portion of France and still more
                                categorically closed door to possibility of annexations. However,
                                our opponents have it in their power to settle once and for all
                                Belgian problem by guaranteeing integrity of territory of Central
                                Powers.</p>
                            <p>We hope that what Chancellor has said relative Germany’s aims will be
                                still more clearly defined in following speeches. The fact remains,
                                however, that the Chancellor holds to a peace of reconciliation.
                                What statesman would have the courage to be responsible for the
                                continuation of the war for possible military success who can obtain
                                a good peace through negotiation? Such a peace we believe to be
                                possible. The two speeches of Thursday strengthen us in this
                                conviction and we believe that after some delay same conviction will
                                be reached in Washington and London.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Volksstimme</hi>, Mannheim, 25th: Chancellor
                                failed absolutely in two main objects required: first, to counteract
                                excellent impression left on neutrals, English and Entente peoples
                                by speeches of <persName corresp="#p_LGD1">Lloyd George</persName>;
                                second, to make that clear declaration regarding Central Powers’ war
                                aims absolutely essential for successful defense. <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName> against Entente’s propaganda
                                    [<hi rend="italic">programme?</hi>], and necessary to remove <pb facs="0141" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> hindrances to early
                                reconciliation. While speech neither Pan-German nor annexationists,
                                nor destructive all bridges for possible reconciliation, it is
                                generally weak, and although will scarcely cause muck damage it will
                                hardly prove beneficial. <persName corresp="#p_HCGFv1">Hertling</persName> should have briefly and emphatically
                                declared Germany still holds to Reichstag war objects resolution
                                and, while unable accept all of <persName corresp="#p_LGD1">Lloyd
                                    George</persName>’s and <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s proposals, finds them sufficient basis for
                                immediate peace negotiations. Such declaration would have forced
                                Entente to peace and caused excellent impression upon German and
                                Austrian people. Such impression not created by <persName corresp="#p_HCGFv1">Hertling</persName>’s speech and therefore
                                Social Democrats cannot support Chancellor’s policy.</p>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Münchner Neueste Nachrichten</hi>, 25th, states
                                full clarity and precision so necessary after late occurrences
                                Berlin sadly missing in speech. It omits all mention of two opposite
                                camps Germany and gives only idea of official peace policy but all
                                indications point to existence unofficial peace policy with unknown
                                aims. <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s speech gives
                                better handle for serious discussion than <persName corresp="#p_LGD1">Lloyd George</persName>’s, and Chancellor has
                                not closed door for reconciliation if honest desire therefor really
                                exists other side of ocean. Same paper, 26th: <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s message showed desire to
                                discover basis for agreement. Chancellor should have formulated
                                answer clearly and promptly. This he has not actually succeeded in
                                accomplishing. The indefiniteness in many of the most important
                                parts of the speech is understandable in view of its antecedents
                                which forced upon it character of compromise as in case of so many
                                earlier official declarations of Chancellors concerning
                                non-annexation Belgium and France. [Omission] <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName> encouraging and we welcome it
                                especially as it will infuriate Pan-German press. However, speech
                                contains no positive statement of war aims or regarding Belgium’s
                                future and relations to Germany. Any statesman who would allow such
                                indefiniteness regarding Belgium to shatter peace prospects would
                                undertake more serious responsibility, assuming that Germany’s other
                                vital interests are secured.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WHR1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>