<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-10-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="332" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d332">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72119/2335</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Netherlands</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BRW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bliss</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Hague</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-10-24">
                                        <hi rend="italic">October 24, 1918</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received October 25.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>4882. <hi rend="italic">Norddeutsche Allgemeine Zeitung</hi>, 23d.
                                Text of <persName corresp="#p_BPMo1">Prince Max</persName>’s
                                    speech:<note n="2" xml:id="d332fn2">Before the Reichstag, Oct.
                                    22.</note>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>Gentlemen: Since I spoke to you last time further steps have
                                        been taken by both sides in prosecution of the peace action
                                        initiated by [my] Government when I entered office.<note n="3" xml:id="d332fn3">For the text of <persName corresp="#p_BPMo1">Prince Max</persName>’s note and
                                            the notes mentioned in the two sentences here following,
                                            see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_338">pp. 338</ref>, <ref target="#pg_343">343</ref>,
                                                <ref target="#pg_357">357</ref>, <ref target="#pg_358">358</ref>, and <ref target="#pg_380">380</ref>.</note> First came
                                        President <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s
                                        counter question. Our frank reply in the affirmative led to
                                        another question by the President; our reply to that was
                                        published yesterday. Gentlemen, the whole German people is
                                        waiting to hear what prospects the Government thinks it can
                                        see for the success of [its] peace work. You will readily
                                        understand that I can express myself on this point only with
                                        the greatest reserve. I know that the parties also wish to
                                        have debate limited in accordance with the gravity of the
                                        hour. The German people have been addressed by President
                                            <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>. This fact
                                        gives increased weight to the statements of the
                                        representatives of all parties.</p>
                                    <p>Regarding the international situation I should like to say
                                        only one thing today. The first reply of the President to
                                        the peace step of the German Government has brought the
                                        conflict of opinions in all countries concerning the
                                        question of a peace of right or a peace of force to a
                                        climax. This is the conflict of ideas which is being
                                        publicly fought out in every country, as it should be fought
                                        out with us also in the same situation. On the one side,
                                        those raise their voices louder than ever who imagine the
                                        time is near when they can satisfy their accumulated emotion
                                        of hate and revenge on the soil of our German home; on the
                                        other side, sincere advocates of a league of nations are
                                        absolutely clear on the point that the fundamental idea of
                                        the new faith is today undergoing its decisive test. This
                                        fundamental idea is as follows: Before any single power or
                                        group of <pb facs="0479" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> powers
                                        undertakes to use compulsion of force to assert the right
                                        which it represents against another nation the attempt must
                                        be made with all thoroughness and honesty to preserve the
                                        peace by means of voluntary agreement, or, applied to the
                                        present international situation, to attain the peace. This
                                        conflict of opinions is still undecided.</p>
                                    <p>We can name the spiritual forces which confront each other,
                                        but cannot estimate their relative strength. The last note
                                        of President <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>
                                        has not made it clear to the German people what the issue of
                                        the public dispute of opinions will be. Perhaps the new
                                        reply of the President will bring final certainty. Until
                                        then, gentlemen, [all our] thoughts and all our acts must
                                        rest upon two possibilities. [The first is] that the enemy
                                        governments want war and we have no choice but to defend
                                        ourselves with all the strength of a people driven to the
                                        extreme. In the event of this necessity I have no doubt that
                                        the German Government will be permitted to issue an appeal
                                        for the national defense in the name of the German people,
                                        just as it was privileged to speak in the name of the German
                                        people when it took action for peace. Whoever sincerely
                                        takes the position of a peace of right assumes at the same
                                        time the obligation not to yield to a peace of force without
                                        a fight. A government void of appreciation of this would be
                                        exposed to the contempt of the fighting and working people
                                        and would be swept away by the wrath of public opinion.</p>
                                    <p>But, gentlemen, we must also contemplate the second
                                        possibility today in its full significance. The German
                                        people must [not] be led blindfold to the conference table.
                                        The Nation has the right to ask today what it means for our
                                        life and future if peace is arranged on the basis of
                                            <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s
                                        conditions. Our reply to the President’s questions has, to
                                        judge from the echo of public opinion, awakened the
                                        consciousness of the German people to what is at stake; now
                                        the people want clarity.</p>
                                    <p>Yes, gentlemen, it is a decision of tremendous importance.
                                        Not what we ourselves consider right but what is recognized
                                        as right in free conversation with our adversaries is to
                                        apply in future to our position as a power. [This is a]
                                        difficult victory over oneself for a proud people accustomed
                                        to victory. For the question of right does not halt at our
                                        frontiers which we would never voluntarily open to force:
                                        the principles which we have accepted as applicable to us
                                        affect also problems within the territory of the Empire.</p>
                                    <p>Gentlemen, it has been held up to me from many sides that
                                        acceptance of <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s
                                        conditions would mean subjection to a tribunal hostile to
                                        Germany which would decide the question of right solely from
                                        the viewpoint of selfish interests. If that were the case
                                        why should the extreme-might politicians of the Entente be
                                        the very ones to shun the tribunal like guilty persons? The
                                        pith of <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>’s whole
                                        program is the League of Nations; it cannot ever be
                                        established unless all nations rise to a height of national
                                        self-control Realization of the community of right demands
                                        surrender of a part of that absolute independence which was
                                        hitherto the sign of sovereignty with us, as well as others.
                                        It will be of decisive importance for our whole future, in
                                        what spirit we follow this necessary development. If we are
                                        tenacious inwardly of the basis of national egotism which
                                        was the ruling force in the life of the nations until a
                                        short time ago, then, gentlemen, there can be no
                                        reconstruction and renovation for us, then there would
                                        remain a feeling of bitterness which <pb facs="0480" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/> would cripple us for generations. But
                                        when we have recognized that the meaning of this terrible
                                        war is above all else victory of the idea of right, and when
                                        we subject ourselves to this idea, not with reluctance, not
                                        with internal reservations, but with all frankness, then we
                                        shall find in it a healing for the wounds of the present and
                                        a task for the forces of the future. The German people must
                                        cooperate in this task with all the real seriousness and
                                        conscientiousness which we inherit.</p>
                                    <p>Gentlemen, we need only go back two generations to find all
                                        the necessary moral incentives for the new development. If
                                        these aims of mankind are once ours the cooperation of the
                                        nations becomes the great task of liberation for us. I
                                        should like to quote my words of February 19: “The mere
                                        fight for existence standing alone leaves great sources of
                                        human power unexplored. We must take up the happiness and
                                        right of other nations in our national will.”</p>
                                    <p>If I depict the idea of the League of Nations to our people
                                        today, at this critical hour, as a source of consolation and
                                        new strength, I will not attempt to deceive you for one
                                        moment as to the tremendous resistances which must still be
                                        overcome before the idea can become a reality. No human
                                        being can say whether this will take place quickly or
                                        slowly. Whether the next few days or weeks may summon us to
                                        further battle, or whether the road to peace [may] be
                                        opened, there can be no doubt that we can only cope with the
                                        duties of war or peace by carrying out the program of the
                                        Government and resolutely turning aside from the old
                                        system.</p>
                                    <p>I now arrive, gentlemen, at questions of internal policy
                                        regarding which I owe an accounting to the German popular
                                        representative body. On October 5 I set forth to you the
                                        general principles according to which I intended to conduct
                                        my office as Chancellor and discussed the program of the
                                        Majority parties,<note n="1" xml:id="d332fn1">For text of
                                            speech, see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_346">pp. 346</ref>–<ref target="#pg_351">351</ref>.</note> whose confidence permitted me to
                                        enter this office. Guided by those principles I have taken
                                        steps with my collaborators which are intended to establish
                                        liberal conditions in the interior of Germany and regarding
                                        which I must now report to you.</p>
                                    <p>Through the praiseworthy accommodation of the parties to the
                                        proposals of the Government, reform of the franchise in
                                        Prussia has progressed so far that the introduction of
                                        general, equal, direct and secret suffrage is assured there.
                                        Two drafts of laws have been submitted to the Reichstag
                                        which are to free our new form of government from the
                                        constitutional obstacles which are still in its way. The
                                        first measure intends to create the possibility for members
                                        of this High House to enter the Government without losing
                                        their Reichstag seats. This is indispensable if the
                                        connection between Parliament and the highest authorities of
                                        the Empire is to remain as firm as is called for by their
                                        joint labors and mutual confidence. The measure further
                                        proposes a change of the law relative to representation of
                                        the Imperial Chancellor. Heretofore only the chiefs of the
                                        highest departments of the Empire could become Vice
                                        Chancellor; in future, members of the Reichstag are to
                                        participate in the direction of Imperial policy and must be
                                        able to stand for the Chancellor although not having a
                                        department under them. <pb facs="0481" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/> This opens the new way to arrive at
                                        the responsible conduct of affairs of the Empire. It is the
                                        parliamentary way. We are convinced that it will prove a
                                        feeder of valuable popular forces heretofore unused, not
                                        merely for the Government, but indirectly for Parliament
                                        also. The rise of born leaders from other free vocations is
                                        not obstructed by it.</p>
                                    <p>In connection with this are preliminary measures for legal
                                        enlargements of the political responsibility of the Imperial
                                        Chancellor which should be insured by the establishment of a
                                        state tribunal. It might be doubted whether a state tribunal
                                        is needed to enforce the responsibility of the Chancellor,
                                        since no Chancellor or Secretary of State can remain in
                                        office if he has lost the confidence of the Majority of this
                                        House. I nevertheless consider it useful to have the new
                                        political institutions of the German Government reforms
                                        sanctioned and safeguarded by such a new instrumentality of
                                        public law, and I hope soon to be able to submit to the
                                        Reichstag the result of the preliminary study.</p>
                                    <p>The new system of Imperial Government has had a new form of
                                        government in the Reichsland as a natural consequence. An
                                        Alsatian has assumed the [governor-generalship] of
                                        Alsace-Lorraine and an Alsatian has become Secretary of
                                        State. Further, leading men from the Second Chamber of the
                                        Diet will enter the Government of the country. I assume that
                                        the new governor general will set up a program for his
                                        Government with the party leaders and publicly explain
                                        it.</p>
                                    <p>Gentlemen, the second measure which looks to the amendment of
                                        article 11 of the Imperial Constitution contains the
                                        compulsory establishment of the fundamental idea of the new
                                        nature of the Government; it intends that the Reichstag as
                                        the chosen representative of the people shall have the full
                                        right of determination in deciding the most important vital
                                        questions of the whole Nation, the questions of war and
                                        peace. This constitutes a guarantee for the peaceable
                                        further evolution of the Empire and its relations with other
                                        powers. The guarantees could be strengthened [if] treaties
                                        of alliance were also made subject to the new provisions.
                                        The Imperial Government will gladly lend its hand for such
                                        extension of the people’s rights when the League of Nations
                                        assumes practicable shape. As long as no world law prevails
                                        on the point Germany would be at a disadvantage by binding
                                        herself alone, but when the League of Nations has abolished
                                        all secret separate alliances and privy agreements, article
                                        11 can be extended in this direction also.</p>
                                    <p>Gentlemen, the state of war has resulted in irksome
                                        restrictions of civic liberty in all countries. Peace will
                                        bring its complete restoration. The extraordinary powers of
                                        wartimes are [as] yet indispensable, but now they can only
                                        be exercised in agreement with the Imperial Chancellor, who
                                        is responsible for their application. Unreasonable hardships
                                        are to be avoided in this way. Orders of His Majesty the
                                        Emperor, which I announced October 5, have been issued
                                        meanwhile and include not alone measures in the province of
                                        censorship, right of association and meeting, and
                                        restriction of personal liberty, but extend also to the full
                                        activity of the executive, even in the field of economic and
                                        social policy. If local military commanders cannot agree
                                        with the administrative authorities on <pb facs="0482" n="390" xml:id="pg_390"/> these points, the decision of
                                        the superior military commander must be sought, and he can
                                        make no decision and issue no order to which I, or my
                                        representative, have not assented. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_GH2">Groeber</persName> is my
                                        representative. Since the superior military commander has
                                        also received authority to establish general principles with
                                        my approval, provision has been made so that the act
                                        relative to the state of siege will be applied in the spirit
                                        in which I assumed direction of the affairs of the Empire
                                        and in which I am determined to carry them out.</p>
                                    <p>Gentlemen, the pardoning of persons sentenced for political
                                        crimes or offences, especially in connection with strikes,
                                        street demonstrations, or similar occurrences, was part of
                                        my program of October 5. An extensive amnesty of this sort
                                        has been suggested to the Emperor and all federated
                                        governments [and] is being put into effect. A large number
                                        of those thus sentenced have already regained their liberty.
                                        The Government has arranged pardon for many of them only
                                        after overcoming serious patriotic apprehension. The
                                        conviction of the healing qualities of a policy of
                                        confidence was decisive.</p>
                                    <p>Gentlemen, all constitutional [authorities] have agreed to
                                        all the steps on the new course which I [have] recited to
                                        you; they accordingly took the ground of the form of
                                        government represented by me and my collaborators. If you
                                        also, gentlemen, agree to these measures, and I have no
                                        doubt on this point, then government of the people will be
                                        firmly anchored in the laws of the Empire.</p>
                                    <p>I know, gentlemen, that a review of the internal political
                                        harvest of the memorable three weeks of October produces
                                        feelings of different natures among you. To some it will
                                        appear as a description of an ill-considered course on the
                                        downward path leading to the overthrow of the existing
                                        regime, to others it will appear like an uncertain, hesitant
                                        feeling of the way towards a new form of government. Both
                                        feelings may find their expression; that is the right and
                                        duty of the opposition which we need for the independence of
                                        Parliament. Those free from any responsibility may freely
                                        criticize. To both I would state for the Government of the
                                        Reichstag Majority that my colleagues and I are in complete
                                        agreement as regards both the object and the means of
                                        reaching it. The [object is] the political majority of the
                                        German people. It stands before our eyes as an immovable
                                        guiding star. The various members of the Government
                                        proceeded from different positions originally, but they
                                        follow the common object with equal loyalty and for this
                                        reason their roads have continually approached each
                                        other.</p>
                                    <p>The German people has been in the saddle for a long time; now
                                        it must ride. Our people had for a long time a number of
                                        rights which many politically mature neighbors envied it;
                                        German communal administration was a model in many respects,
                                        the Reichstag suffrage was for a long time the most liberal
                                        franchise of the world, and the Reichstag thus freely
                                        elected always had a strong political influence through its
                                        ability to refuse the budget. But the German people made no
                                        use of its power in decisive points.</p>
                                    <pb facs="0483" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/>
                                    <p>It is not enough to make a master violin player to make [him
                                        a] present of a fine violin. The player must be willing to
                                        try his capacity. The German people never tried to play its
                                        instrument with full force because it gladly trusted the
                                        efficient constituted powers; its main strength was deployed
                                        in great isolated achievements outside of [politics]. It was
                                        not the arbitrariness of the constituted powers but the lack
                                        of political will among the people that preserved Germany so
                                        long as a magistral state. Since July 1917 the resolve for
                                        political responsibility has been maturing; now at the end
                                        of September it has forced its way through and through. Thus
                                        everything has become new, gentlemen; in this lies the
                                        guarantee for the maintenance and enlargement of the new
                                        system. It came [about] through a decisive turn in the
                                        development of the character of the German people which had
                                        become inevitable after all the deeds and sacrifices of this
                                        war. This affords a more substantial guarantee than any
                                        legal paragraph. I see in [it] the roots of the power of the
                                        new Government. The result is for me a fixed line of march
                                        for all our measures. Not for the sake of foreign countries,
                                        nor in order to master the distress of the moment, must we
                                        resort to forms of government not backed by our inmost
                                        convictions and not expressive of our peculiar character and
                                        history, otherwise we should act insincerely and would
                                        deprive the new system, which is now passing through its
                                        first test, of the stamp of irrevocability with which we
                                        cannot dispense. Gentlemen, the great appeal addressed by
                                        Fichte to the Germans in time of need is heard by all of us:
                                        “Now preserve yourselves as a nation for those duties in the
                                        world which you alone can perform. Every nation has a duty
                                        of its own.” There are still great treasures in the depths
                                        of our people which can only be brought to light by the new
                                        freedom. Those hours in the life of the German Nation which
                                        seem to crush it down have always been the hours of the
                                        birth of new spiritual forces.</p>
                                    <p>But in order to develop the quality of our peculiar nature we
                                        must be able to insist on our domiciliary right. The enemy
                                        stands at our gates; our first and last thoughts belong to
                                        [those] brave men who are defending us against superior
                                        forces and [whom] we must protect against unjust
                                        accusations. Gentlemen, it must not be believed that our
                                        army can be insulted without affecting the honor of our
                                        people. Isolated evil acts and measures have occurred in
                                        every army, but the fundamental will of the people’s army
                                        rejects them. When the words were spoken that the spirit of
                                        the Red Cross was just as appropriate for a true army as the
                                        spirit of attack, overwhelming approval came from the
                                        circles of the army and confirmation came from Christian
                                        soldiers in enemy countries who fought against the
                                        Germans.</p>
                                    <p>Gentlemen, our soldiers have a terribly difficult task today;
                                        they are fighting with care for their country, they are
                                        fighting with the idea of peace and still hold fast. We
                                        thank them, we trust in them, we call to them: The country
                                        will not leave you in the lurch; whatever you need and
                                        whatever it can furnish in men, material and courage shall
                                        be sent you.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BRW1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bliss</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>