<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Sofia ( (Murphy) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Supp01v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">397</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-10-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-10-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-10-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="397"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d397">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/12170</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Sofia</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MDI1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 270</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sofia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-10-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 10, 1918</hi>
                        </date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received November 7.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that at 7.30 p.m.
                    Wednesday, the 25th of September, Mr. <persName>Liaptcheff</persName>, Bulgarian
                    Minister of Finance, called upon me to say that the Cabinet had just decided to
                    break with Germany—and that all the members united in the request that I should
                    accompany to the Macedonian front the delegates who had been selected to open
                    negotiations for an immediate armistice as a preliminary to peace with the
                    Entente.</p>
                <pb facs="0569" n="477" xml:id="pg_477"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Liaptcheff</persName> spoke freely of the situation in which
                    Bulgaria found herself—a situation with which I had already become perfectly
                    familiar. He reminded me of the long-existing dissatisfaction which had become
                    intensified and had developed into such a universal hatred that the army at the
                    front had become exceedingly discontented—three entire divisions refusing to
                    fight longer on the German side.</p>
                <p>I informed Mr. <persName>Liaptcheff</persName> that I had no instructions to
                    guide me in such an emergency—but that if he could positively assure me that
                    Tsar <persName corresp="#p_F1">Ferdinand</persName> assented to the step about
                    [to be] taken, I would accompany the delegates to the front and immediately
                    notify the Department of my action. I was assured that the Tsar was fully in
                    accord with the Cabinet and had accepted its decision without question.</p>
                <p>I then sent a telegram to the Department advising of the situation and of my
                    intention to leave for the front with the Bulgarian delegates. At 9.15 p.m. of
                    the 25th, Mr. <persName>Liaptcheff</persName>, Minister of Finance, Mr.
                        <persName>Radeff</persName>, Minister Plenipotentiary, Mr.
                        <persName>Vassileff</persName>, a distinguished lawyer of Sofia, Mr.
                        <persName>Walker</persName> and I left the city—the three first named going
                    in one automobile, Mr. <persName>Walker</persName>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d397fn1">For other activities of Mr.
                            <persName>Walker</persName> in connection with the Bulgarian armistice
                        negotiations, see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_329">p.
                            329</ref>.</note> and I in the other. We travelled at full speed all
                    night without stopping,— except once or twice when halted by patrols—and at 5
                    o’clock on the morning of the 26th we arrived at the headquarters of the general
                    in chief of the Bulgarian forces.</p>
                <p>The reason for the violent haste of the journey was to get to the front and open
                    negotiations with the Entente commander in chief so quickly as to forestall
                    action by the Germans and Austrians. And here it is proper to say that by the
                    convention between Germany and Bulgaria, entered into in September 1915, it was
                    provided that in case the latter should find herself in danger of invasion from
                    the Entente forces, Germany would, upon receiving notice, immediately send six
                    full divisions to aid the Bulgarians. Austria-Hungary likewise solemnly agreed
                    that in such a contingency, she would despatch six other divisions. Two months
                    ago, the new Government notified Germany that help was needed as the Entente
                    pressure on the Macedonian front was too heavy to be borne long—but the answer
                    was: “No troops can be spared.” The last request made on the 12th of August
                    last, by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Malinoff</persName>, Prime Minister, was
                    answered by General <persName corresp="#p_HFMPvBuv1">Hindenburg</persName>, in
                    effect, that as German forces were engaged in the decisive battle on the western
                    front, no men could be sent—but that a corps would be ordered to Bulgaria from
                    Sebastopol. Translation of the <persName corresp="#p_HFMPvBuv1"
                        >Hindenburg</persName> letter will be found herewith.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d397fn2">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0570" n="478" xml:id="pg_478"/>
                <p>This <persName corresp="#p_HFMPvBuv1">Hindenburg</persName> letter was the “last
                    straw”. At once the Cabinet was called together—the session lasting all night.
                    The unanimous verdict was that as Germany had violated her solemn compact with
                    Bulgaria, the moment had come for a severance of relations. Hence Mr.
                        <persName>Liaptcheff</persName>’s visit to me—and hence my journey to the
                    front.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">What Happened at the Front</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Arriving at headquarters on the Strouma front, a Bulgarian captain was sent
                    across the lines under flag of truce to General <persName corresp="#p_MSGF1"
                        >Milne</persName>, the British commander of the Salonica forces. The captain
                    not returning, it was thought proper to send Mr. <persName>Walker</persName>
                    over under another flag of truce early on Friday morning. Mr.
                        <persName>Walker</persName> carried to General <persName corresp="#p_MSGF1"
                        >Milne</persName> a letter from me introducing the Bulgarian delegates and
                    asking his good offices in putting them in touch with the commander in chief of
                    the Army of the Orient with as little delay as practicable. As Mr.
                        <persName>Walker</persName> had not returned by midnight Saturday, the 28th,
                    I determined to return to Sofia,—the delegates having passed over the lines
                    early that morning. On Sunday morning at 6 o’clock I started, accompanied by the
                    adjutant of the Bulgarian commander in chief, a guard and a chauffeur.</p>
                <p>It was subsequently learned that it was necessary for Mr.
                        <persName>Walker</persName> to go to Salonica which place he left on the
                    30th.</p>
                <p>On the return journey, in making a sharp turn in a narow defile, we found
                    ourselves in the midst of a German division of artillery in full retreat. We
                    went about four miles through their lines until there was a block caused by a
                    broken bridge. The damage was repaired in an hour—but in the meantime nine
                    British aviators attacked the German column—inflicting considerable loss. None
                    of my party were injured—nor was the automobile damaged—although the bombardment
                    by bombs and rapid gun fire was terrific, lasting about twenty-five minutes.</p>
                <p>Forty minutes later there was another attack—lasting twenty minutes—and again
                    none of the party were hurt. It should be said that the adjutant, when
                    questioned about me by the officer in command of the German division, answered
                    him that I was a Swiss writer who had been to the front. We were four hours
                    working our way through the enemy’s lines—and it was early Monday morning, the
                    30th September, before I reached Sofia.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Walker</persName> had an experience also, as he was passing through
                    Dupnitza, in the evening of the same day. At this place, the Bolsheviks, as they
                    are now called—Bulgarian divisions which refused to fight longer—established a
                    republic. A crowd gathered about the automobile in which Mr.
                        <persName>Walker</persName> was returning and hurled rocks and stones—their
                    purpose being to kill the officer who accompanied <pb facs="0571" n="479"
                        xml:id="pg_479"/> him. A large piece of rock struck Mr.
                        <persName>Walker</persName> on the right side of the head, inflicting a
                    severe wound from which he is now but recovering. The ridiculous “Republic of
                    Dupnitza” lasted for the whole of forty-eight hours, when it disappeared from
                    “the family of nations.”</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">What Happened in Sofia</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As soon as news was received that an armistice had been declared, there was great
                    rejoicing in Sofia—but it was soon learned that the three retreating divisions
                    of the Bulgarian Army were marching on the city with the avowed purpose of
                    taking the heads of Tsar <persName corresp="#p_F1">Ferdinand</persName> and
                    former Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_RV1">Radoslavoff</persName>—the two
                    men, more than any others, being held responsible for the alliance with Germany
                    and the evil days that had fallen upon Bulgaria in consequence.</p>
                <p>A battle was fought on the outskirts of Sofia lasting three whole days, many
                    being killed and wounded on both sides, but the victory was with the Government.
                    Then followed the abdication of the Tsar, the enthronement of the Crown Prince,
                        <persName corresp="#p_BBA2">Boris III</persName>, the Germans ordered to
                    leave Bulgaria within eight days, the establishment of order in the country, and
                    more than all the decisive blow given to German hegemony in the east and the
                    weakening of the Central Powers by the defection of Bulgaria. And as was said in
                    a recent telegram,<note n="1" xml:id="d397fn3">Not printed.</note> Bulgaria, if
                    needed, will fight on the side of the Entente. To-day again, I have had the
                    assurance from an authoritative source that Bulgaria is ready at the word of
                    invitation, to join forces with the Entente and the United States.</p>
                <p>If it is at all possible, American troops should be sent to Bulgaria. They will
                    be royally welcomed by the people—and their coming will mean that American
                    influence in the Balkans will be permanent. Munro in his book <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bulgaria and Her People</hi> well said—“Bulgaria is the only country in
                    Europe in which the United States has played an important <hi rend="italic"
                        >rôle</hi> in the development of a state … and the Bulgarians gratefully
                    recognize their obligation.”</p>
                <p>A large Red Cross contingent should also be sent to Bulgaria with ample supplies,
                    for there is widespread suffering and much sickness. There is likewise a most
                    lamentable lack of food as well as medicines and surgical supplies.</p>
                <p>In conclusion I have to state that the Germans in evacuating Bulgaria are playing
                    their usual <hi rend="italic">rôle</hi> of violence and robbery. They are
                    carrying off everything they can put hands to—robbing people of food, clothing
                    and about everything they possess. At Nish they robbed the Bulgarian officers of
                    all their belongings leaving them to get to their homes as best they could with
                    nothing but underclothing, <pb facs="0572" n="480" xml:id="pg_480"/> shoes and
                    pantaloons. Here in Sofia, they have been sullen and impudent, refusing to leave
                    the hotels until they were ready. In consequence, I am forced to entertain the
                    French and English officers—with their eight chauffeurs. The Legation, which has
                    been a decided centre of activity, is crowded—every room being occupied.</p>
                <p>The English and French military officers are very well received—Bulgarians,
                    without exception, being rejoiced that peace has been made with the Entente. My
                    particular regret at this time is that no American officers are here.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MDI1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">D. I. Murphy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
