<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-02-13T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-02-13T13:00:00-05:00" n="60" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72119/1276</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PTN1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Page</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-02-13T19:00:00+01:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">February 13, 1918, 7 p.m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received February 5.30
                                    a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1415. President’s address published this morning. Rome papers
                                received so far most favorably as important contribution to Allied
                                cause. The <hi rend="italic">Messaggero</hi>, independent
                                interventist, says: President proclaims more strongly than ever
                                sanctity of the rights of the people to justice and freedom; that
                                message if disseminated in Germany would have greater effect upon
                                people than a military defeat; that Italy now feels her aspirations
                                will be fairly considered by the most solid mind among the idealists
                                in political life. The <hi rend="italic">Giornale d’Italia</hi>,
                                afternoon semiofficial, while commending generally says the message
                                not an adequate reply to <persName corresp="#p_CvCCO1">Czernin</persName>’s speech which it thinks the President has
                                been deceived into considering different in intention from <persName corresp="#p_HCGFv1">Hertling</persName>’s, whereas only the tone
                                was different, the two <pb facs="0206" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/>
                                being fundamentally in agreement. With this exception it praises
                                warmly the President’s address.</p>
                            <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_OVE1">Orlando</persName> spoke for
                                Government yesterday on reopening of Chamber declaring plainly the
                                question of peace or war no longer one of choice but of necessity, a
                                question of life or death based on instincts of self-preservation.
                                Having referred to lesson from German-Russian peace negotiations as
                                tending to dishonor, he said Italy’s war aims are the same now as
                                when she entered upon struggle and added that now as then, Italy
                                does not want more and will not accept less than the completion of
                                her national unity and the security of her boundaries on land and
                                sea. He then argued that Italy has no imperialistic claims and
                                proclaimed that no doubt could exist between Italy’s aspirations and
                                the rights of other oppressed peoples. The military situation he
                                declared good with every prospect of improving.</p>
                            <p>Italians apprehend great German-Austrian push on Italian front very
                                soon. British, however, think chances of this are decreasing.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PTN1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nelson Page</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>