<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Switzerland ( (Wilson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Supp01v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-02-21T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-02-21T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-02-21T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-02-21T03:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72119/8185</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Switzerland</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WHR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-02-21T09:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 21, 1918, 9 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received February 22, 2.03 a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2694. Department’s 1500, February 15, 11 p.m.,<note n="1" xml:id="d77fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_119">p. 119</ref>.</note> was
                    decoded personally by me.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_LH1">Lammasch</persName> has no agent in Switzerland and I
                    hesitated to confide this message to any neutral. It was therefore imperative to
                    confide it only to a person of confidence who could deliver the message
                    secretly, orally and unofficially to <persName corresp="#p_LH1"
                        >Lammasch</persName> in Vienna. I therefore summoned
                        <persName>York-Steiner</persName>, an Austrian who often calls at the
                    Legation in connection with the sale of the vessels of the Austro-American Line
                    to Phelps Brothers. He is a close friend and warm admirer of <persName
                        corresp="#p_LH1">Lammasch</persName> and a disciple of his in political
                    matters. He is known personally to <persName corresp="#p_GJC1">Grew</persName>
                    in the Department and has always been found worthy of confidence both by the
                    former Embassy at Vienna and this Legation; furthermore he is an ardent admirer
                    of President <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wilson</persName>, an opponent of German
                    domination in Austria, and has come to Switzerland to devote himself to
                    furtherance of mutual understanding between Austria and the United States.</p>
                <p>I asked him whether he could proceed to Vienna on a confidential mission of
                    benefit to his country. He replied that he could proceed as soon as the
                    necessary three days of passport formalities had elapsed. I told him to obtain
                    the necessary visé and then return to me. He returned on the 19th instant,
                    having obtained permission to visit Vienna on the ground of his desire to bring
                    his daughter back to Switzerland, a reason which really exists and a mission
                    which he will accomplish.</p>
                <p>I then delivered your message which he repeated to me in exact wording. He
                    expressed himself as profoundly moved by this opportunity to be of service to
                    his country and assured me that having <pb facs="0222" n="130" xml:id="pg_130"/>
                    delivered his message he would wipe it from his memory. He has arranged to
                    inform me by a harmless telegram to his wife on Tuesday, who will know nothing
                    of its import, when message has been delivered.<note n="1" xml:id="d77fn3">In
                        his telegram No. 2722, Feb. 25, noon, the Chargé reported: “The telegram
                        agreed upon has been received, indicating that message has been delivered to
                            <persName corresp="#p_LH1">Lammasch</persName>.” (File No.
                        763.72119/8172.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Dulles</persName>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d77fn2">
                        <persName>Allen W. Dulles</persName>, Second Secretary of the
                        Legation.</note> and I are ciphering this message and matter is known to no
                    one else.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WHR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
