<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes of a Meeting of the Heads of Delegations of the Five Great Powers Held
                    in the Chateau of Saint Germain-en-Laye, on Wednesday, 10 September, 1919, at
                    11:15 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-09-10T05:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-09-10T05:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-09-10T05:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-09-10T05:15:00-05:00" n="10"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 180.03501/51</note>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">HD–51</note>
                <head>Notes of a Meeting of the Heads of Delegations of the Five Great Powers Held
                    in the Chateau of Saint Germain-en-Laye, on Wednesday, 10 September, 1919, at
                    11:15 a.m.</head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1919-09-10T11:15:00+01:00">September 10, 1919, 11:15 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States of America</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Hon. F. L. Polk.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Mr. L. Harrison.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Rt. Hon. A. J. Balfour.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretaries</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>Mr. H. Norman.</item>
                                    <item>Mr. P. Kerr.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Clemenceau.</item>
                                    <item>M. Pichon.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretaries</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Dutasta.</item>
                                    <item>M. Berthelot.</item>
                                    <item>M. de Saint-Quentin.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Tittoni.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretaries</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Paterno.</item>
                                    <item>M. Barone Russo.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Japan</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Matsui.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>M. Kawai.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <table cols="2" rend="width: 70%;" rendition="#center-block" rows="6">
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Joint Secretariat</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States of America</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Captain Chapin.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Lt-Commander Bell.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>M. de Percin.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Captain Rossi.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Interpreter</hi>—M. Camerlynck</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The following also attended for the items with which they were concerned: <list
                        type="participants">
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States of America</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Dr. J. Brown Scott.</item>
                                <item>Mr. Woolsey.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">British Empire</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Brig-General Seely.</item>
                                <item>Mr. Hurst.</item>
                                <item>Brig-General Groves.</item>
                                <item>Lt-Colonel Kisch.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>M. Tardieu.</item>
                                <item>M. Cambon.</item>
                                <item>M. Fromageot.</item>
                                <item>General Le Rond.</item>
                                <item>Captain Ropert.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Colonel Castoldi.</item>
                                <item>M. Ricci-Busatti.</item>
                                <item>M. Brambilla.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Japan</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>M. Nagaoka.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0183" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/>
                <p>1. The Council took note of the following draft resolution with regard to the Air
                    Convention:— <seg type="margin">Air Convention</seg>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“That the Air Convention shall be signed with the least possible delay by
                            the Contracting States, it being understood that it shall remain open
                            for a period of six months for signature by such of those States as are
                            not at present in a position to sign it.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi> drew the attention of the Council to the fact
                    that he was unable to sign the Air Convention on behalf of the United States at
                    the moment. It was even possible that the United States might not be able to
                    give its adherence to the Convention, should the American Government maintain
                    the reservations made by the American Delegates to the clauses relating to
                    patents and customs duties.</p>
                <p>(The draft resolution on the subject of the Air Convention was agreed to, subject
                    to the reservation formulated by Mr. Polk, on behalf of the United States.)</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that he had closely considered the
                    question left over at the last meeting of the Council. He had prepared a draft
                    note for transmission to the German Government, but was not wholly satisfied
                    with it. The conclusion was rather long and not decisive. Mr. Hurst had devised
                    another plan, which seemed more effective than the mere despatch of a note.
                    After reading his own draft Note (Appendix “A”) he called upon Mr. Hurst to
                    explain his plan. <seg type="margin">Violation of the Peace Treaty of Versailles
                        by Virtue of Certain Articles in the German Constitution. (See HD–50, Minute
                            1)<note n="1" xml:id="d10fn1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_155">p. 155</ref>.</note>
                    </seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hurst</hi> said that he had not been able to prepare
                    any document which could be submitted to the Council. He had, on the previous
                    day, made out a very rough draft, and had shown it to Dr. Scott. At the previous
                    meeting he had been aware that the desire of the Council had been to formulate
                    some plan of action, which would combine two separate ideas. Firstly, the two
                    separate violations of the Peace Treaty should be drawn attention to. Secondly,
                    whatever note, or communication, were sent to the Germans, they should be
                    compelled to reply immediately. In addition to this, whatever line of action
                    were adopted it should be of such a nature as to avoid adverse criticism in
                    neutral countries. The solution that had seemed best to him was, to collect
                    together all the admissions made by the Germans in their letter; to draw them up
                    in the form of a protocol, which should be presented to the Germans for
                    signature. When this had been done, their admissions would be given legal force,
                    and be binding upon them. The Germans had admitted that the Peace Treaty and the
                    Constitution were not in agreement. If, when presented with this admission in
                    proper legal form, either the German <pb facs="0184" n="174" xml:id="pg_174"/>
                    Government, or the Reichsrat, refused to ratify it, then the intentions of the
                    Germans would be made clear. The Drafting Committee had agreed, generally, to
                    this proposal, at their meeting. The manner in which the protocol and the note
                    by which it was to be transmitted were to be drafted, was doubtful, and, before
                    proceeding to work, it was necessary that his main idea should be approved.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said that he understood that the
                    Japanese Representative on the Drafting Committee had a proposal of his own to
                    make.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Nagaoka</hi> then read his draft proposal. (See Appendix
                    B.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Tittoni</hi> said that he had understood, on the
                    previous day, that the Council wished to force the German Government to make a
                    special enactment, cancelling the Articles in their Constitution that were
                    objected to. He understood M. Nagaoka’s proposal to consist in demanding a
                    declaration of nullification of the Articles in question, with the addition,
                    that the Reichsrat should itself confirm the declaration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that the Japanese proposal effected
                    no more than what the Germans alleged to result naturally from Article 178 of
                    their Constitution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said that he agreed with Mr. Hurst’s
                    proposal, which he considered to be the best solution of the difficulty. He
                    proposed that the Drafting Committee should bring a draft legal instrument
                    before the Council on the following day, of such a nature as to oblige the
                    German Government to sign, in the form of a protocol, whatever they had admitted
                    in their letter of the 5th September. The advantage of Mr. Hurst’s proposal was,
                    that the Germans would be unable to enter into lengthy negotiations. The
                    measures proposed, therefore, seemed to him to be the wisest and the most
                    effective possible.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi> said that he approved of Mr. Hurst’s proposal
                    also.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Tardieu</hi> said that the draft protocol to be prepared
                    by Mr. Hurst and the Drafting Committee, would have to be sent under the cover
                    of a letter. He thought that some of Mr. Balfour’s arguments and phrases might
                    be put into the covering letter with great advantage.</p>
                <p>(It was decided that the Drafting Committee should prepare a draft protocol,
                    giving legal force to the admissions of the German Government in their letter of
                    5th September, and should present it to the Council at its meeting on the
                    following day, together with a draft letter under cover of which, the aforesaid
                    protocol should be transmitted to the German Government.)</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Cambon</hi> reported the decision of the Joint Polish
                    and Czechoslovak Committees on the subject of the demarcation line to be <pb
                        facs="0185" n="175" xml:id="pg_175"/> adopted in the Teschen area, with the
                    aid of a map. He said that the Polish Delegates had provisionally approved of
                    the line proposed, which was ethnographically correct. <seg type="margin"
                        >Teschen</seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Tittoni</hi> said that he had received a visit from M.
                    Benes, who had admitted the justice of the new line, from an ethnographic point
                    of view. He, (M. Benes) had, however, argued, that if a strict ethnographic line
                    were to be adopted in the Teschen area, it seemed hardly fair, conjointly with
                    such a decision, to put four millions of Ruthenes in Eastern Galicia under
                    Polish jurisdiction. A solution might consist in making concessions to the
                    Czecho-Slovaks in the Teschen area, to balance the very great political and
                    economic advantages that were being conferred on the Poles by virtue of the
                    Galician decision.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that he could not consider the
                    analogy between the Galician and Teschen situations as very relevant, for two
                    reasons; (1) the solution proposed for Eastern Galicia was provisional only, and
                    was not intended to be a permanent settlement, and (2) the decision on the
                    subject of Galicia had been arrived at because the Ruthenian population in that
                    country could not stand alone. It was inevitable that the Ruthenians should
                    eventually be placed under the rule of a non-Ruthenian State. Nothing parallel,
                    or similar, to those considerations arose in the Teschen problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said that the Council proposed to
                    discuss the Teschen question, which was quite difficult enough, without the
                    Galician problem being added to it.</p>
                <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Polk</hi> said that M. Benes had proposed to him a line
                    of demarcation following the river Vistula. The line in question would, however,
                    be quite unacceptable to the Poles; although M. Benes considered that, in
                    proposing it, he was making concessions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Pichon</hi> said that the Council had heard the point of
                    view of the Polish and Czecho-Slovak Delegations.<note n="2" xml:id="d10fn2">See
                        HD–47, minute 5, and HD–48, minute 3, <ref target="#pg_102">pp. 102</ref>
                        and <ref target="#pg_118">118</ref>.</note> The Czech Delegates had insisted
                    that their interest in the Teschen area was centered on the coal that it
                    contained; the Poles had asserted that their interest in Teschen was on a
                    political basis, and was purely concerned with the Polish population in the
                    disputed districts. It was therefore clear that the Poles were asking for
                    population, and the Czechs for coal. A solution might be found by giving the
                    whole of the Karwin district to the Czechs, and the indisputably Polish
                    districts, in the remainder of the area, to the Poles. He did not think that the
                    line proposed by the Joint Polish and Czecho-Slovak Committees could be
                    upheld.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi> said that, if such a line as that proposed by
                    M. Pichon were adopted, it would separate the people working in the mines from
                    their own homes, by a national frontier.</p>
                <pb facs="0186" n="176" xml:id="pg_176"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said that a situation similar to that
                    foreseen by Mr. Polk existed in Northern France, Belgium and the Saar Basin. It
                    had not given rise to any serious difficulties.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that the Poles regarded the Karwin
                    Basin as a Polish district, as indeed it was. There was no serious objection to
                    cutting the coal-field into two halves, because geological formations in other
                    portions of the world were frequently divided politically. He was quite sure
                    that the French frontier did not follow the geological structure of that
                    country, in the northern districts, where the coal strata ran over into Belgium
                    and into Germany. This fact did not, however, give rise to serious difficulties,
                    but M. Pichon’s proposal involved cutting off a Polish population from the place
                    where it worked, and this constituted a grave danger for the future. His
                    conviction on this point was not only that of the Expert Committees of the Peace
                    Conference, but also that of the International Commission in Teschen, who had
                    studied the question locally. It was very dangerous to try to improvise another
                    solution, more particularly as the line proposed by the Joint Polish and
                    Czecho-Slovak Committees was really favourable to the Czechs, to whom it granted
                    60 per cent, of the coal produced, and 40 per cent, to the Poles. It could not
                    possibly be said that, under such a solution, the Czechs were being deprived of
                    coal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Tardieu</hi> said that it should not be forgotten, that
                    the Poles contended, that they could not count on the Silesian coal-fields until
                    the plebiscite in that country had been taken. This argument was ingenious, but
                    it was none the less certain that the Poles would eventually obtain possession
                    of the greater part of the Silesian coal-fields.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Pichon</hi> said that the Poles had repeatedly asserted
                    that they did not care about coal.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi> said that M. Benes had stated to him, that
                    either the line proposed by him (M. Benes) should be adopted, or a plebiscite
                    should be held in the area.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Berthelot</hi> said that M. Benes had stated to him,
                    that the situation in Bohemia was now so grave that it would be preferable to
                    the Czecho-Slovaks to risk a plebiscite, rather than to consent to a solution
                    which they regarded as so hopelessly unfavourable to them, and equivalent, in
                    their opinion, to a refusal of all their demands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Tittoni</hi> said that, if a plebiscite were to be held,
                    the area would have to be divided into two portions, as he had proposed for
                    Kadkersburg and Marburg, when these areas were under discussion.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Berthelot</hi> said that the Czech contention was that,
                    if they could not possess the coal, they would be dependent upon their
                    neighbours for it, and might be cut off from their necessary supplies at a time
                    of diplomatic tension. M. Pichon’s solution gave them the coal, and the rest of
                    the Polish population to the Poles. By adopting it, the present <pb facs="0187"
                        n="177" xml:id="pg_177"/> state of affairs would not be altered, since the
                    coal areas were now occupied by the Czechs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi> said that the difficulty was that, under M.
                    Pichon’s proposal, a proportion of the Polish Teschen districts would be ceded
                    to Czecho-Slovakia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Berthelot</hi> said that the Karwin coal district could
                    more properly be compared to the Lens, than to the Belgian, coal district, for
                    it was concentrated in a narrow area as in the case of Lens. The original
                    proposals of the Joint Committees had been most favourable to the Czechs, but
                    the proposals in question had now been withdrawn. Even by accepting M. Pichon’s
                    proposal, the Poles would be given far more than they had hoped for in the first
                    instance. If, as he now thought possible, M. Benes could persuade his countrymen
                    to consent to the new proposal, it was surely worth consideration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi> said that M. Pichon’s line would place 60,000
                    Poles under the administration of the Czechs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that it should not be forgotten that
                    even the line proposed by the Joint Committees gave a considerable number of
                    Poles to the Czechs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Berthelot</hi> said that M. Benes had based a good many
                    of his arguments on the solution to the Galician problem, contemplated by the
                    Council. The proposed decision was very favourable to the Poles, and the
                    impression left upon the Czechs was that, although the Council was ready to
                    place 4 million Ruthenes under Polish jurisdiction, they were not prepared to
                    make a concession far smaller, from an ethnographical point of view, in favour
                    of the Czecho-Slovak State. This would, in consequence produce a very bad
                    impression. M. Benes’ attitude had been extremely moderate and conciliatory, and
                    it would be a great misfortune if he found himself compelled to resign his post,
                    on account of what he considered an unconciliatory attitude of the Conference.
                    M. Benes’ resignation would be a political consideration, not entirely relevant
                    to the Teschen problem, but the possibility of it could not be disregarded, and
                    ought to be duly considered.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that he understood that the line
                    described to the Council by M. Cambon had been adopted unanimously in the Joint
                    Committees. As M. Berthelot had not been a member of either Committee, he
                    regarded his proposals as interesting, but not of sufficient authority to
                    outweigh a unanimous proposal by an Expert Committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Berthelot</hi> agreed with Mr. Balfour and said that the
                    Committees had been unanimous, but it should not be forgotten that their
                    unanimous opinion, for the first six months, had been to adopt a solution far
                    more favourable to the Czechs than any now proposed. They had subsequently
                    altered their opinion, and this, when made known, would cause a bad impression
                    in Czecho-Slovakia. The Committees <pb facs="0188" n="178" xml:id="pg_178"/> had
                    studied the problem from its ethnographical and economical sides, leaving out
                    political considerations, which seemed to be for the Council to decide. The
                    French representatives on the Joint Committee had originally objected strongly
                    to the line reported on by M. Cambon that morning, but they gave their assent to
                    it finally, in order to facilitate a solution of some sort. The consent of the
                    French representatives had only been given on the understanding that the Poles
                    should be obliged, by some means or another, to grant special facilities to the
                    Czechs with regard to the coal and to the railways.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Tittoni</hi> said that he understood that the line
                    described by M. Cambon would not be adopted without a special convention,
                    assuring to the Czechs the special economic facilities described by M.
                    Berthelot.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi> said that he had understood that the Joint
                    Committees had been unanimous. If they had not been, the question ought
                    obviously to be referred back to them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Berthelot</hi> said that the Report of the Joint
                    Committees had only been unanimous because the French representatives had given
                    their consent, so as not to isolate themselves from their colleagues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said that he did not understand the
                    reasons that had prompted the French representatives on the Joint Committee to
                    give their assent to a proposal of which they did not approve. He retained
                    opinions independently of whether they were shared by others or not. He had
                    thought M. Pichon’s proposal a very good one, and had hoped that it might have
                    been adopted.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Balfour</hi> said that he saw grave objections to the
                    adoption of M. Pichon’s solution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said that, whilst agreeing with Mr.
                    Balfour, he was convinced that the coal question in Teschen was the outstanding
                    problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Cambon</hi> said it should not be forgotten that, in the
                    Karwin Basin, which M. Pichon proposed to cede to Czecho-Slovakia, there were
                    nearly 70,000 Poles.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Clemenceau</hi> said that Mr. Balfour could not agree
                    with M. Pichon. He, himself, could not agree with the Committee’s proposals. He
                    therefore proposed to refer the whole question back to the Joint Committees,
                    who, as they had already changed their minds several times, could certainly do
                    so again, and present another report. He would never accept a line cutting a
                    coal basin into two, for such a solution would be like placing a man on one side
                    of a frontier, his wife upon the other, and dividing the children up between the
                    two.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Cambon</hi> said that he admitted M. Clemenceau’s
                    objection, but drew the attention of the Council to the fact that it was just as
                    unwise to devise a line giving the surface of the land to one country and the
                        <pb facs="0189" n="179" xml:id="pg_179"/> subterranean deposits to another,
                    and this seemed to be what was required of him [and?] the Joint Committees.</p>
                <p>(It was agreed that the Teschen question should be referred back to the joint
                    Polish and Czecho-Slovak Committees for report on the following day.)</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi> drew the attention of the Council to the
                    fact that the Bulgarian Delegation was objecting to having the Peace Terms
                    presented to them without a formal diplomatic ceremony. <seg type="margin"
                        >Presentation of the Bulgarian Peace Terms</seg>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">M. Dutasta</hi> further called attention to the fact, that
                    the Bulgarians were asking for a period of thirty days, after the presentation
                    of the Peace Terms, in which they might be allowed to draft their replies. Their
                    request was based upon the plea that it would be necessary for them to take the
                    terms to Sofia, and discuss them in the Bulgarian Sobranie.</p>
                <p>(After some discussion, it was agreed that the Peace Terms to the Bulgarians
                    should be formally presented to them at the Quai d’Orsay at a date which should
                    be decided upon later.</p>
                <p>It was further decided that the Bulgarian Delegation should be given a period of
                    25 days after the presentation of the Peace Terms, for the preparation of their
                    replies.)</p>
                <p>The Meeting then adjourned.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hotel Astoria</hi>, <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-09-10">10 September,
                            1919</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Appendix A to HD–51</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">British Delegation, <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                            </hi>[, <date
                                ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                                calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1919-09-10T11:15:00+01:00"
                                notBefore="1919-09-05T00:00:00+01:00">undated</date>].</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">[<hi rend="italic">Draft Reply to the German Note of September
                            5</hi>,<note n="3" xml:id="d10fn3">Appendix B to HD–49, <ref
                                target="#pg_138">p. 138</ref>.</note>
                        <hi rend="italic">Prepared by Mr. Balfour</hi>]</p>
                    <p>The Conference have brought to the notice of the German Government a clause
                        in the new German Constitution respecting German relations with Austria
                        which is in direct contradiction with the provisions of the Treaty of Peace
                        relating to the same subject. The German Government in effect reply that no
                        clause, whatever be its plain grammatical meaning, can really be in
                        contradiction with the Treaty of Peace because there is another clause in
                        the Constitution which says that nothing the Constitution contains can
                        affect the Treaty. By this ingenious device the German Constitution could
                        evidently be so amended as formally to contradict every provision which the
                        Treaty of Peace contains. It might for example enact that a German army of
                        ten million men was to be maintained by conscription; and when the <pb
                            facs="0190" n="180" xml:id="pg_180"/> Associated Powers pointed out that
                        this was not in conformity with a Treaty which narrowly limited the Army and
                        forbad conscription, the German Government could reply that, if so, the
                        Constitution itself in Article 178 provided a sufficient remedy for the evil
                        by laying it down that nothing in the Treaty could be affected by the
                        Constitution.</p>
                    <p>This case is imaginary. But it is not more extravagant than a similar
                        experiment in legislation contained in the 112th Clause of the German
                        Constitution. This enacts that no German citizen may be surrendered for
                        trial before a foreign tribunal. The Treaty on the other hand lays it down
                        that certain persons charged with grave offences against the principles of
                        humanity and the Laws of War <hi rend="underline">are</hi> to be surrendered
                        and <hi rend="underline">are</hi> to be tried by a foreign tribunal. Here
                        then is a second case of contradiction between the Constitution and the
                        Treaty: and presumably it will be excused in the same fashion as the
                        first.</p>
                    <p>The German Note suggests that Article 61 was introduced in order to avoid
                        “all possible contradictions between the Provisions of the Constitution and
                        the conditions of peace in the Peace Treaty.” The intention is excellent if
                        it relates to those doubtful and accidental contradictions which the
                        ingenuity of lawyers may detect in the language of two long and complicated
                        documents. But we are not dealing with doubtful and accidental
                        contradictions. Those of which we make complaint are assuredly open and
                        manifest, and can hardly be other than deliberate. No one can believe that
                        the framers of the German Constitution when they drew up Article 61 (and
                        Article 112) were not aware that both were absolutely inconsistent with the
                        engagements into which Germany had solemnly entered only a few weeks
                        before.</p>
                    <p>This condition of things cannot be allowed to endure. If, as the Germans
                        themselves proclaim when the Constitution and the Treaty clash, the
                        Constitution must give way, it is their evident duty to bring these two
                        great instruments into harmony by modifying the Constitution: and the
                        Conference must insist that this duty be fulfilled.</p>
                    <p>Since, however, the legislative machinery for effecting this object is
                        difficult to set in motion owing to the adjournment of the Reichstag, and
                        since the further examination of the Constitution shows that Article 110
                        must be amended as well as Article 61, the Conference are prepared to extend
                        the period allowed for the amendments till the expiry of the first fortnight
                        after the Treaty has been ratified. This will have two advantages. It will
                        in the first place meet a technical objection raised by the German
                        Government, based on the fact that the Treaty, though signed, is not yet in
                        force. It will in the second place put to the proof the sincerity of the
                        German arguments <pb facs="0191" n="181" xml:id="pg_181"/> based on Article
                        61. When the Treaty is ratified the Associated Powers will, in accordance
                        with its provisions, demand the surrender of certain accused persons, to be
                        tried in foreign courts. Unless the Constitution is amended, we shall then
                        have a test case by which to determine the mode in which the German
                        Government interpret the provisions of their Constitution when these are in
                        conflict with their treaty obligations. If Article 61 be honestly
                        interpreted, the substantive provisions of Article 110 [<hi rend="italic"
                            >112</hi>] will have to be abandoned. If Article 110 [<hi rend="italic"
                            >112</hi>] be acted upon, the Treaty of Peace will be violated in the
                        eyes of all the world. The first alternative would discredit the
                        Constitution: the second would bring about an immediate breach with the
                        Associated Powers. Neither alternative can be good for Germany: and the
                        Associated Powers are acting in her interests as well as in their own when
                        they insist that a speedy end shall be put to ambiguities and
                        inconsistencies which seem to be designed for no other purpose than to
                        weaken the force of the most solemn and binding obligation.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Appendix B to HD–51</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation<note n="4" xml:id="d10fn4">Translation
                                from the French supplied by the editors.</note>]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">[<hi rend="italic">Draft Reply to the German Note of September
                            5, Prepared by M. Nagaoha</hi>]</p>
                    <p>The German Government, recognizing that the provision in article 61 of the
                        constitutional law of August 11, 1919, is in contradiction to the terms of
                        article 80 of the Treaty of Peace of June 28, 1919, and that the maintenance
                        of the said provision of article 61 before an appropriate assent has been
                        given by the Council of the League of Nations, might give rise to
                        misunderstandings, in spite of the provisions of article 178 of the said
                        constitutional law, declares, after approval by the Reichstag, that article
                        61, as well as all stipulations contrary to the Treaty of Peace, are null
                        and void.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
