<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>144. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Mission in
                    Geneva</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d144</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">144</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-08-23T13:10:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-08-23T13:10:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1Gk59BaIROJJML" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85116922"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Salvage</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recieOBiY284bnHpv" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances">Western alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-08-23T13:10:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-08-23T13:10:00-05:00" n="144"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d144">
                <head>144. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Mission in Geneva</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d144fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL 27 CYP. Secret; Flash; Nodis-<gloss target="#t_TAG1">TAG</gloss>.
                        Drafted and approved by <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>.
                        Repeated to Athens, Ankara, and London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-08-23T14:10:00-04:00">August 23, 1964, 2:10 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>479. Geneva for <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName>. For Ambassadors.
                    After a long telecon with Ray Hare early this morning<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d144fn2">Initiated at 4 a.m. on August 23. (Ibid., <persName
                            corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> Papers: Lot 74 D 272, Telephone
                        Conversations, Cyprus Situation)</note> and the dubious result of his
                    subsequent final try with Inonu,<note n="3" xml:id="d144fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d140">Document 140</ref>.</note> I have reluctantly concluded
                    that Geneva, as originally conceived, has run its course.</p>
                <p>In order to salvage remaining possibilities, I ask your comments on the following
                    new proposed course of action: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>In Athens <persName corresp="#p_LHR1">Labouisse</persName> would say
                            to the <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> that it has proved impossible
                            to persuade the Turks to accept anything less than the Karpas Peninsula
                            Base and even that is doubtful on a leasehold basis.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>However, we are not prepared to let conditions drift to the point
                            where Cyprus becomes another Cuba, as will almost certainly be the case
                            if the <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> regime continues
                            in control of an independent GOC.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>We are, therefore, considering saying to the <gloss target="#t_GOG1"
                                >GOG</gloss> that they should go forward with their plans to bring
                            about enosis and that we will undertake to see that, if they bring it
                            off with reasonable promptness, neither the Turks nor any outside power
                            will intervene with military force.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The conditions of this offer are: <list>
                                <label>(a)</label>
                                <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> must undertake, once
                                    enosis is concluded, to negotiate promptly and in good faith
                                    with the <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> regarding the
                                    mutual recision of the Treaties of Guarantee and
                                    Alliance.</item>
                                <label>(b)</label>
                                <item>In the course of this negotiation, the <gloss target="#t_GOG1"
                                        >GOG</gloss> must undertake as a minimum to offer the Turks,
                                    in exchange for the abrogation of those treaties, two major
                                    concessions.</item>
                                <label>(c)</label>
                                <item>The first is the assurance of minority rights to the Turk
                                    Cypriot population in the form developed by <persName
                                        corresp="#p_AD1">Dean Acheson</persName>.</item>
                                <label>(d)</label>
                                <item>The second is an undertaking by the <gloss target="#t_GOG1"
                                        >GOG</gloss> to grant to the <gloss target="#t_GOT1"
                                        >GOT</gloss> a 50-year lease for a suitable area to be
                                    mutually agreed on with the advice of <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1"
                                        >SHAPE</gloss>.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>While the <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> may be reluctant to
                            agree now to negotiate these concessions in the absence of a
                            simultaneous Turkish agreement, we can point out to them that without an
                            understanding with the <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> a post-enosis
                            Cyprus will face sticky problems. For example, it will be confronted
                            with the presence of a Turkish garrison which the Turkish <pb
                                facs="0325" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/> Government will no doubt
                            insist on maintaining under the Treaty of Alliance unless the juridical
                            situation can be sorted out by agreement. The garrison, the rights
                            claimed under Article 4 of the Treaty of Guarantee, and the unresolved
                            status of other Treaty provisions can make relations very difficult.
                            This is true even though the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> General
                            Assembly might pass a resolution calling upon the Turks to relinquish
                            these rights and get out.<note n="4" xml:id="d144fn4">In telegram 387
                                from Athens, August 24, <persName corresp="#p_LHR1"
                                    >Labouisse</persName> endorsed <persName corresp="#p_AD1"
                                    >Acheson</persName>’s proposal and stated that in order for
                                Papandreou to carry out enosis successfully, he would have to be
                                able to limit the commitments he had already made to Turkey.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, POL 27 CYP)</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In Ankara we would propose to take the following actions: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Hare would say to <persName corresp="#p_II1">Inonu</persName> that he
                            regrets that the <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> has not accepted
                            our proposal and that Turkey will probably never be able to obtain as
                            good a deal again.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>, however, is not prepared to
                            let Cyprus become another Cuba.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>We are advising the <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss>, therefore,
                            that we are encouraging the <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> to bring
                            about enosis and propose to tell them that we will assure that this is
                            achieved without outside intervention from any quarter.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>At the same time we are insisting, as a condition of this assurance to
                            the <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss>, that the Greek Government must
                            agree as outlined in paragraph 4 above.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The advantage of this course of action from the point of view of the <gloss
                        target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> is that it does not require the Turkish
                    Government to agree to anything. It would merely accept notice of our statement
                    that we expect it to stand down on Cyprus and that we propose again to
                    concentrate on the great issues that bind Turkey to the Western Alliance. We
                    should get some sense of the risks involved in giving the Greeks an assurance of
                    Turkish standdown through General Porter’s visit to Ankara in the next two or
                    three days. I would like particularly to have Ray <persName corresp="#p_HRA1"
                        >Hare</persName>’s comments on this.<note n="5" xml:id="d144fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HRA1">Hare</persName>’s comments are in telegram 370
                        from Ankara, August 24. (Ibid.) In telegram 379 from Ankara, August 24,
                        Porter reported that he would make an effort to convince the Turkish General
                        Staff that the Karpas Peninsula was militarily sound for a base.
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>In order to share these risks and at the same time give a firmer underpinning to
                    the proposal, we might consider trying to associate the UKG as well as Germany
                    and Italy with our action.</p>
                <p>If we get an affirmative reply from the Greeks and implicit acquiescence from the
                    Turks, you might wish to stop off in Rome, Bonn and London on your return to the
                    US to try to get them on board.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, both <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Dean Rusk</persName> and I feel that
                    it would be helpful if you could stay on in Geneva for some days more until we
                    fully explore the possibilities of trying to work out an arrangement along the
                    above lines. This would minimize the possibilities of a sudden sense of alarm
                    resulting <pb facs="0326" n="288" xml:id="pg_288"/> from the conspicuous
                    termination of the Geneva talks. Moreover, your departure at this point from
                    Geneva might well encourage <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> and
                    the Greeks to take a more obstructionist stand. Your continued presence, on the
                    other hand, could reinforce the general situation while both the Greeks and
                    Turks are sorting out their final arrangements.<note n="6" xml:id="d144fn6">In
                        telegram 467 from Geneva, August 23, <persName corresp="#p_AD1"
                            >Acheson</persName> stated his readiness to stay as long as necessary to
                        carry forward <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>’s proposals.
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>In preparing the above suggestions we have obviously taken into account the
                    Papandreou letter to <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName> (Athens 153
                    to Geneva)<note n="7" xml:id="d144fn7">Papandreou’s letter was transmitted in
                        telegram 381 from Athens (repeated to</note> which gives some encouragement
                    to the course of action proposed.</p>
                <p>Geneva as 153), August 23. (Ibid.)</p>
                <p>I would greatly appreciate a reaction from all addressee posts regarding this
                        proposal.<note n="8" xml:id="d144fn8">In telegram 911 from London, August
                        24, <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName> registered his “deep
                        misgivings” about <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>’s proposals.
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
