<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>152. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Greece</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-09-03T19:37:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-09-03T19:37:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recGPO6TEVZ9esQhG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general">Fishing rights</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recfBXf5mApMtKJKj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peacekeeping-forces" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002546" lcsh-match="exact">Peacekeeping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-09-03T19:37:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-09-03T19:37:00-05:00" n="152"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                <head>152. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Greece</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d152fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL 27 CYP. Secret; Immediate; Limdis. Drafted and approved by
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> and cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName>. Also sent to Ankara, Paris for
                            <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss>, Nicosia, and London to deliver to
                            <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName> at breakfast. <persName
                            corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName> left Geneva on September 2, stopped
                        in London September 2–4, and returned to Washington on September 4.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-09-03T20:37:00-04:00">September 3, 1964, 8:37 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>432. While we are continuing to seek a permanent solution of the Cyprus problem
                    we have been giving further study as to how we can: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>prevent deterioration in the relations between Greece and Turkey that
                            may lead to a dangerous explosion;</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>create a climate in which we can prosecute a productive search for a
                            permanent settlement; and</item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>widen the scope of negotiations in order to get the discussion off
                            dead center.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The first order of urgency is to bring about the relaxation of tensions on the
                    Island and restore a more stable—if still uneasy—relation between the two
                    communities.</p>
                <p>The second is to prevent the Turks, Greeks, or Cypriots from setting in train a
                    chain reaction of retaliation and counter-retaliation.</p>
                <p>With these objectives in mind we are considering the floating of a possible
                    arrangement between the <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss>, aimed at a wide range of Greek-Turkish issues.
                    Each side would explicitly recognize this arrangement as an effort to prepare
                    the conditions in which a final settlement may be possible. Each side would
                    agree to continue to search for such a settlement urgently and in good
                    faith.</p>
                <p>There would be several advantages to such an arrangement if it could be
                    negotiated. If both sides complied, it could reduce the probability of an
                    explosion. If the arrangement broke down because one side or the other proved
                    unwilling or unable to carry out its share of the commitments, we would at least
                    have isolated responsibility and made it easier to handle a major row in the
                    Security Council.</p>
                <p rend="center">Assumptions</p>
                <p>The assumptions upon which we are suggesting the general lines of an arrangement
                    are the following: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> has sufficient military force
                            under its control on the Island to enable it to assure that the peace is
                            kept—if it has the will to do so. There are in the neighborhood of
                            10,000 Greek troops on the Island and in addition the 30,000 Greek
                            Cypriot National Guard has been placed under the command of Greek
                            officers.</item>
                        <pb facs="0339" n="301" xml:id="pg_301"/>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> would genuinely like to narrow
                            the engagement of its own military forces in relation to the Cyprus
                            problem. At the same time it would like assurance that the <gloss
                                target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> will not intervene capriciously.
                            (Support for this assumption implied in <persName corresp="#p_CKS1"
                                >Costopoulos</persName>’ suggestion to <persName corresp="#p_LHR1"
                                >Labouisse</persName>, reported in Athens 470 [<hi rend="italic"
                                >471</hi>] to Department.)<note n="2" xml:id="d152fn2">
                                <ref target="#d151">Document 151</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> would like to avoid the
                            creation of a situation in which it feels compelled to intervene with
                            military force. It would, therefore, welcome an arrangement that
                            contributed to the quieting down of the Island and the improvement of
                            the welfare and safety of the Turk-Cypriot population.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">Main Lines of Arrangement</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Commitments by <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss>:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> would use its best efforts to
                            assure that the GOC did not interfere with the rights reserved to the
                                <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> by the Treaties of Guarantee,
                            Alliance and Establishment, including the right of the <gloss
                                target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> [<hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss>
                            </hi>] to rotate its garrison.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> would undertake to assist the
                            restoration of more normal conditions on the Island. It would use its
                            best efforts to prevent the GOC from interfering with aid to
                            Turk-Cypriots from outside organizations and agencies. It would assist
                            in the rehabilitation and resettlement of Turk-Cypriot refugees. It
                            would endeavor to end the economic blockade, etc.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> would undertake not to provide
                            military support to the GOC against Turkish action, except in case of an
                            unprovoked attack by Turkey.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> would undertake to prevent the
                            GOC from seeking or obtaining military equipment or personnel or any
                            other form of military assistance, from any nation not a party to the
                            London-Zurich Agreements.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> would refrain from any acts of
                            discrimination or harassment against Turkish nationals living in Greek
                            territory, including Western Thrace.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Commitments by Turkey:</hi>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> would extend for at least an
                            additional six months the special privileges granted to Greek nationals
                            under the 1930 Treaty of Establishment, Commerce, and Navigation<note
                                n="3" xml:id="d152fn3">For text, see 124 LTS 371.</note> and would
                            undertake not to engage in any acts of discrimination or harassment
                            against Greek nationals living in Turkey.</item>
                        <pb facs="0340" n="302" xml:id="pg_302"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> would undertake not to
                            exercise its rights of military intervention under Article 4 of the
                            Treaty of Guarantee unless the GOC were acting in such a manner as (a)
                            to deprive the <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> of substantial rights
                            accorded it under the London-Zurich arrangements or (b) to endanger the
                            lives or welfare of the Turk-Cypriot population.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> would use its best efforts to
                            prevent the Turkish Cypriots from engaging in any provocatory
                            acts.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> would avoid any provocation
                            against the Government of Greece, including interference with fishing
                            rights, etc.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">Method of Procedure</p>
                <p>Obviously the points included above are merely suggestive of the general scope of
                    an arrangement. Each point would necessarily have to be articulated and expanded
                    through negotiation. Some points might have to be excluded and additional points
                    added.</p>
                <p>The development of such an arrangement could be approached through several
                    possible ways. We might ask <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Brosio</persName> to
                    undertake this through <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> channels since what
                    is contemplated is an arrangement between two <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> members. Alternatively we might undertake the negotiation by
                    asking the GOC and <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> to send representatives
                    to meet with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName> in Washington—or
                    possibly Rome. Or we might have Embassy Athens first put the proposition to the
                    GOG and—if that yielded promising results—have <persName corresp="#p_HRA1"
                        >Hare</persName> follow through in Ankara.</p>
                <p>In any event we are faced with a tight time schedule since several prospective
                    actions are scheduled for the middle of the month. The termination of the
                    special privileges accorded Greek nationals under the Treaty of Establishment
                    will take place on September 17. The Security Council discussion of the
                    extension of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Peacekeeping Force is
                    scheduled for the second week in September. At the same time the Turkish
                    Government has indicated that it may wish a Security Council review of the
                    economic blockade.</p>
                <p>Each of these actions may contribute to a deterioration in Greek-Turkish
                    relations. Taken together their cumulative effect could be serious.</p>
                <p>We would appreciate your prompt reactions to these very preliminary suggestions.
                    We shall look forward to reviewing them with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AD1"
                        >Acheson</persName> upon his return to Washington.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d152fn4">In telegram 475 from Ankara, September 5, <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRA1">Hare</persName> commented that the suggested proposals
                        would help get through a difficult situation “while a permanent solution
                        being sought,” and offered some specific revisions. (Department of State,
                        Central Files, POL 27 CYP)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
