<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-11-30T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-11-30T09:00:00-05:00" n="166" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                        <head>166. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Turkey</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d166fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, POL 27 CYP. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>. Repeated to Nicosia, Athens, Paris for <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss>, London, <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, and Moscow.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Ankara</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-11-30T16:00:00+02:00">November 30, 1964, 4
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>872. <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 860.<note n="2" xml:id="d166fn2">Telegram 860, November 26, suggested delaying a
                                U.S. response to questions raised by Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erkin</persName>. (Ibid.)</note> Although our
                            Cyprus policy as recently re-stated by Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Talbot</persName> (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 630),<note n="3" xml:id="d166fn3">Dated November 21.
                                (Ibid.)</note> has been not to favor particular solution but rather
                            to lend support to any proposal that had prospect of acceptance, in fact
                            our thinking and efforts during and even after Geneva discussions were
                            oriented toward modified form of enosis as solution which held out best
                            hope being definitive and of avoiding continuing trouble. However,
                            review of recent developments in Cyprus situation indicates changes in
                            several important factors which were previously determinants in our
                            policy thinking.</p>
                        <p>First and most important is that both <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss>
                            and <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> have in fact given
                            up idea of “instant enosis”, at least for the time being. Thus, while
                            enosis with sufficient compensations for Turkey may still remain
                            preferred US solution it retains little value as working concept in
                            shorter run.</p>
                        <p>Furthermore, experience has shown us that no matter how much Papandreou
                            continues talk about building up <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss>
                            position on island, <pb facs="0371" n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/> he has
                            failed put <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> in position force enosis
                            on <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> or even accelerate
                            pace of events. It now clear that on Greek side, <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> alone will call tune as to
                            timing and nature of any significant steps toward enosis. This has
                            obvious implications for our long-standing assumption that nub of
                            problem was to get <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> talking, so that hopefully they could
                            reach compromise agreement which <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> would have no choice but accept. What has
                            emerged, actually, is coincidence of <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss>
                            and GOC interest (though for different reasons and perhaps for short
                            term only) in maintaining Cyprus’ independence. Logically, this should
                            lead Turks and Greek Cypriots talk together but neither side seems ready
                            yet recognize this as tolerable alternative to present course of mutual
                            hostility (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 642).<note n="4" xml:id="d166fn4">Dated November 25. (Ibid.)</note> In meanwhile,
                            earlier open-mindedness of Turks to idea of modified enosis has changed.
                            Unhappy denouement of Geneva talks and their aftermath have made even
                            more acute feeling of Turks that they have been suffering unacceptable
                            losses to their position and their prestige. As consequence enosis has
                            again become dirty word for them, their whole attitude has stiffened and
                            they have reverted to original position of federation, with partition
                            relegated to automatic reaction if any overture made toward unilateral
                            enosis.</p>
                        <p>Another change in policy background has to do with Soviets’ role and
                            influence. Will be recalled one of principal reasons for seeking
                            urgently obtain agreement last summer on modified enosis formula was to
                            abort growing Soviet influence in and over Cyprus and specifically to
                            forestall Greek Cypriot mission to Moscow. In interval not only Greek
                            Cypriots but Turks have been to Moscow. Although Russians may not have
                            intended Moscow discussions give as much encouragement to Turks as
                            latter reflect in conversations with US and others, nevertheless
                            discussions and joint communiqué, at a minimum, created new element of
                            uncertainty for Greeks and expectations for Turks. Thus, although does
                            not appear have been any change in basic Soviet position, Soviets can
                            now win kudos from both Greek Cypriots and Turks by taking public stance
                            in favor of independence which per se no longer appears, in Turkish eyes
                            at least, as pro-Makarios position.</p>
                        <p>Then, there is experience of Mediator himself. Despite Galo Plaza’s
                            inveterate optimism and political virtuosity, including close rapport
                            with <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>, his multiple
                            conversations with all parties concerned have not resulted in any
                            narrowing of gap (as Acheson’s did) but instead have served reveal that
                            gap greater than was thought. Measure of bleakness Galo Plaza’s
                            prospects is his decision defer submission his final report until after
                                <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> discussion of Cyprus item.</p>
                        <pb facs="0372" n="334" xml:id="pg_334"/>
                        <p>In addition all of foregoing we constrained adduce one parochial but
                            nonetheless important consideration, which is continuing erosion of US
                            political stock in Turkey. Given fact we have had no choice but sail on
                            more or less straight line between Greek Scylla and Turk Charybdis, we
                            had to expect growing disillusionment and despair on part of Turkish
                            friends for our failure support them in position which they consider
                            right and honorable. This mood has gradually given way to one of
                            adapting themselves realistically to changed conditions but at same time
                            seeking opportunities make them as favorable as possible to Turkey’s
                            needs, e.g., <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erkin</persName>’s Moscow visit
                            and federation pitch made to Galo Plaza.</p>
                        <p>Put in summary form, the Cyprus question, as far as <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> is concerned, has changed greatly in
                            almost all of its aspects since we became actively concerned with
                            it.</p>
                        <p>First, problem itself has changed as our immediate objective of
                            preventing war between Greece and Turkey has essentially been
                            accomplished. It is true that Turks still talk grimly of war with Greece
                            if enosis should be carried out as a unilateral act but, as prospect of
                            such action fades due to Greek second thoughts and <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> having other ideas,
                            likelihood of an armed clash recedes.</p>
                        <p>But unfortunately this does not get us out of woods since original major
                            problem has now been replaced by series of others, which are perhaps of
                            lesser magnitude individually but taken as a whole are not only
                            immediately troublesome but could have important long term effects in
                            the area and on our position in it. Turkey and Greece, on whose past
                            cooperation so much depended, are now at daggers drawn and prospects are
                            for further deterioration. Greece and Turkey who were model members of
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, are now unhappy critics of
                            that organization and partisans of non-alignment are raising voices.
                                <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> is under severe criticism in
                            Nicosia, Athens and Ankara, which is unpleasant but bearable in its
                            spleenish aspect but has serious implications as regards our specific
                            national interests in Greece and Turkey which tend run parallel
                            qualitatively but are considerably greater in Turkey quantitatively.
                            Result is that problem which started out as primarily affecting others
                            has now become one in which our own interests are directly involved and
                            fact that war threat has receded should not leave us in doubt as to real
                            situation.</p>
                        <p>In circumstances it would seem this time for re-evaluation in order
                            determine whether policy evolved under other circumstances still holds
                            good. If so, it should be consciously revalidated in terms which are
                            explicable in light of present realities. If not, we should see what
                            could be done by way of modification or substitution. In this
                            re-examination cognizance should first be taken of fact that range of
                            possibilities for settlement has been greatly reduced by exclusion of
                            idea of early enosis, whether in unilateral, conditional or double form.
                            This means scrapping Geneva concept and leaves independence, even though
                            non-permanent, as <pb facs="0373" n="335" xml:id="pg_335"/> single
                            remaining solution with only question being determination of what kind
                            of independence. As matters stand <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> and Galo Plaza appear in agreement in principle
                            if not in detail on an independent, unaligned, demilitarized Cyprus with
                            certain minority right provisions for Turk Cypriots, and Papandreou’s
                            having pretty much chucked in his hand, is now taking position that
                            anything that suits <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>
                            will go for him. This also would seem to be what Sovs would like since
                            it would lead to pressure on British to give up their base rights and
                            leave Turkey and Greece estranged and good for troubled waters fishing.
                            This also coincides with Turkish policy to extent that it would block
                            enosis but it leaves sharp cleavage on form which independence would
                            take and it is on this narrowed but clearly defined gap that all the
                            asperity and emotionalism which have characterized this problem in past
                            are now concentrated in situation where both sides remain as deeply
                            entrenched as ever in their positions with result that hope for agreed
                            solution remains perhaps even more remote than before. In fact,
                            Papandreou has categorically gone back to his original position of
                            excluding all talks with Turks and there is no indication that <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>, still confident of success
                            without compromises will be any more flexible in future than in
                            past.</p>
                        <p>It is for this reason that policy of advocating agreed solution, although
                            having possible tactical advantages in situation where we (and also
                            British) are at wits end act positively, is, following Geneva
                            break-down, dead-end street as far as Turks concerned and leads them
                            endeavor induce US break log-jam by coming out in support of what they
                            profess believe type of independence adapted to realities of situation.
                            Unfortunately their nerves are pretty raw these days and they sometimes
                            put their arguments in heavy handed form which is aggravating but this
                            should not obscure fact that, regardless of form of presentation or our
                            ability do something about it, this is normal approach in situation
                            where Turks still deeply feel that something needs be done to redress
                            imbalance but repeatedly stress that they would be open to compromise if
                            real dialogue could be initiated.</p>
                        <p>This then is situation in which we find ourselves and in light of which
                            review would seem in order. Should decision emerge from such study to
                            give some form of support to principles of federation, we should realize
                            that we might be backing horse that would never get far down track
                            (Nicosia’s 775 to Dept).<note n="5" xml:id="d166fn5">Telegram 775 from
                                Nicosia, November 27, reported that a Cypriot federation could only
                                be imposed by force. (Ibid.)</note> On other hand, there would be
                            certain equity in making attempt since it would amount to giving Turk
                            solution fair try as we did with enosis this past summer. It is
                            foreseen, however, that it would be difficult to give type of general
                            pig-in-poke endorsement of federation which Turks suggest. Furthermore,
                            it would seem to be <pb facs="0374" n="336" xml:id="pg_336"/> wishful
                            thinking on part of Turks to assume that a word from US would cause Galo
                            Plaza to retrim his sails and still more improbable that Soviets would
                            fall in line (although, unlikely as it may be, sight should not be lost
                            of possibility that they might take initiative themselves if this suited
                            their purposes. After all in terms Soviet geopolitics Turkey easily
                            remains at top of priority list). However, this does not alter fact that
                            real imbalance exists, that <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> has upper hand and that some concession by him
                            is essential if matter is to be directed on more hopeful course. This
                            observation is made in knowledge that current GOC policy is antithesis
                            of this and that they too urging US abandon policy of neutrality
                            (Nicosia’s 789 to Dept),<note n="6" xml:id="d166fn6">This reference is
                                incorrect; the correct telegram has not been identified.</note>
                            which natural as far as GOC concerned but would make shambles of our
                            relations here for simple reason that it would be directed to solution
                            of greater rather than lesser imbalance in situation where our influence
                            should presumably be directed to latter not only as matter simple
                            justice but also in our own over-all interests. If <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>, hopefully with assistance of Galo
                            Plaza, could use influence to persuade GOC to undertake negotiations in
                            spirit of sincere compromise there might be some hope. If not, all doors
                            for helpful action prior <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> would
                            seem tightly shut since obvious <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss>
                            unable take initiative in absence some favorable indications in Nicosia
                            or Athens.</p>
                        <p>Question currently posed, therefore, is whether we see any useful purpose
                            could be served by putting renewed pressure on GOC primarily and <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> secondarily to take first step toward
                            compromise solution and mutatis mutandis advise Turks as discreetly as
                            possible of our views. In so doing, would be important make clear we not
                            washing hands of Cyprus, that any limitations on our action are result
                            of careful re-examination of facts and that we shall do our best be
                            helpful as situation develops, especially in <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Incidentally, British Amb tells me <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erkin</persName> approached him last Thursday in much same sense he
                            had talked to me two days before (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 856)<note n="7" xml:id="d166fn7">Dated November 25.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, POL 27 CYP)</note> except that
                            he included <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> along with US, Soviets and
                            Mediator in array which could push federation over goal line and
                            focussed approach on immediately following visit of Mediator in London.
                            German Amb told me he was also approached on same day by <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bayulken</persName> and German support solicited on
                            assumption that Galo Plaza left Ankara sympathetically disposed to
                            federation idea.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HRA1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Hare</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>