<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-10-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-10-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="210" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d210">
                        <head>210. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Turkey</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d210fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, POL 27 CYP. Confidential; Priority. Repeated to Athens,
                                Nicosia, London, <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, The Hague,
                                Paris for <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss>, Istanbul, Izmir,
                                and Adana. There is no time of transmission on the source text; the
                                telegram was received at 9:46 a.m.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Ankara</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-10-22">October 22, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>472. Refs: <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>s 416, 452, 454;
                                <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>s 278, 279; Nicosia’s 172
                            to Dept.<note n="2" xml:id="d210fn2">Telegram 416 from Ankara, October
                                9, reported on a conversation with <persName corresp="#p_IH1">Isik</persName>. (Ibid.) Telegram 452 from Ankara has not been
                                found. Telegram 454 from Ankara is summarized in <ref target="#d209fn2">footnote 2, Document 209</ref>. Regarding
                                telegrams 278 and 279 to Ankara, see <ref target="#d209fn3">footnote
                                    3, Document 209</ref>. Telegram 172 from Nicosia is summarized
                                in <ref target="#d209fn6">footnote 6, Document 209</ref>.</note>
                            Proposals re Cyprus Issue.</p>
                        <pb facs="0481" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/>
                        <p>Embassy has reviewed Cyprus question in context of <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Demirel</persName>’s victory,<note n="3" xml:id="d210fn3">In the October 1965 elections, <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Demirel</persName>’s Justice Party won 52.9
                                percent of the popular vote and 240 seats in the Grand National
                                Assembly.</note> FonMin <persName corresp="#p_IH1">Isik</persName>’s
                            earlier discussion in US re Cyprus, and remarks of Turkish officials
                            during Ambassador’s initial calls. We have also taken into account
                            helpful suggestions contained in Nicosia’s 172 to Dept and attitude of
                            Greek Government as reported by Embassy Athens. Against this background,
                            it seems to us that major elements in current situation are following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>It is improbable that bilateral Greek-Turkish talks will be
                                    resumed before <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> Cyprus
                                    debate despite Turkish efforts to renew discussions.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Turks believe they have commitment from us to support
                                    procedural resolution at <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. Even
                                    assuming US as well as possible Soviet support, Turks are
                                    concerned that majority of GA will approve substantive
                                    resolution, perhaps including reference to “self determination”
                                    for endorsement of Galo Plaza report.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Looking beyond <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> vote,
                                    over which Turks have limited control, indications are that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Demirel</persName> is anxious to
                                    try to achieve early resolution of Cyprus question so that he
                                    can devote his attention to Turkey’s domestic problems. Compared
                                    with predecessor coalition government, he will head strongest
                                    Turkish Government since 1950’s and thus will possess somewhat
                                    greater margin of flexibility. However, area of maneuver open to
                                        <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Demirel</persName> will remain
                                    small because he perforce will operate within familiar framework
                                    of Turkish national interests and also be ever sensitive to
                                    question of Turkey’s prestige.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>In contrast to greater political stability in Turkey,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Stephanopoulos</persName>
                                    government’s future seems doubtful. From our perspective, in
                                    view heightened Greek-Turkish tension which will probably
                                    intensify during <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> debate,
                                    it seems probable that in immediate future no Greek Government
                                    will be able to consider new initiatives re Cyprus which would
                                    require any concession. Consequently, enosis-Greek territorial
                                    compensation formula appears shelved.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>On Cyprus itself, <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>’ internal position apparently remains
                                    strong despite possibly weaker international position as
                                    reflected in August UNSC action and Soviet shift in direction of
                                    Turkey. Archbishop appears even less subject to Athens’
                                    influence than before, fact which Turks would now be willing to
                                    concede, and he remains determined to block any externally
                                    imposed solution.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Given political situation in three countries directly
                                    involved, and prospect of residual bitterness after <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> vote, US initiative probably
                                    will be required to move Cyprus issue off dead center.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0482" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/>
                        <p>On basis <persName corresp="#p_IH1">Isik</persName>’s conversations in
                            Washington and Ambassador’s discussions here with <persName corresp="#p_IH1">Isik</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BH1">Bayulken</persName>, it is clear that Turks are still anxious to
                            engage us in some type of joint planning, although they have no specific
                            proposals in mind.</p>
                        <p>In order partially to meet Turkish desire without actually becoming
                            involved in joint planning, they believe some merit in our exchanging
                            views with <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> on informal basis. We
                            might begin by reviewing with Turks various alternative proposals,
                            including those which have been considered before, with objective of
                            determining parameters of Turkish position. To create atmosphere of
                            mutual confidence it would be advisable to hold talks in secrecy while
                            making clear to Turks that no commitments on our part were involved
                            during preliminary exchanges.</p>
                        <p>In this connection, we believe conversations with Turks should begin by
                            explaining alternatives rather than on basis of US-drafted general
                            outline of reasonable proposal (Nicosia’s 172 to Dept), but we should be
                            prepared put forward such an outline if talks evolve in fruitful
                            direction. Talks should begin in Ankara on bilateral basis because it is
                            highly unlikely that Turks would be willing to agree to Nicosia as focus
                            of talks involving Archbishop, <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss>, Greek, Turkish and US
                            Embassies. In addition to Turkish belief that Cyprus issue should be
                            resolved primarily between Ankara and Athens, Turks would fear their
                            interests would not be properly protected in Nicosia where they would be
                            represented only by charge, who would be operating in Greek-Cypriot
                            dominated environment, subject to influence by unreliable
                            Turkish-Cypriot community, and out of direct control of Ankara.</p>
                        <p>Parallel with informal talks in Ankara, we might wish to consider similar
                            noncommittal bilateral exchanges in Athens and Nicosia, informing all
                            three governments that we were carrying on informal exploratory talks in
                            other capitals but that US did not view its role as mediatory one.
                            Instead, our task would be to try to determine whether there was any
                            possibility of forward motion on Cyprus issue by talking independently
                            to parties involved.</p>
                        <p>Depending on progress made in talks in Ankara (and possibly Athens and
                            Nicosia), we could decide whether there was any prospect for direct
                            negotiation between interested governments in light of prevailing
                            circumstances. It might, for instance, be desirable to encourage
                            resumption of Athens-Ankara dialogue building upon conversations which
                            US had previously undertaken with two governments. At that point, it
                            could also be decided how and when <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> might be brought into picture. We are inclined
                            to agree with Embassy Nicosia’s view that <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> should be brought into discussions in early
                            stage so that he does not remain aloof only to sabotage ultimate
                            solution. Turks would remain skittish about including Archbishop in any
                            discussions but their final attitude would hinge upon prospects of
                            satisfactory settlement, <pb facs="0483" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/>
                            rather than upon principle involved, and they might be willing to
                            include <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> if apparent
                            that weak Greek Government could not deliver. Throughout proposed
                            preliminary discussions with Turks (and possibly with others), we would
                            remain alert to desirability of injecting third party into discussions
                            at appropriate time. This could be done by again calling for <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> intervention. Despite Turks’ unhappy
                            experience with Galo Plaza, or possibly through Acheson type
                            arrangement.</p>
                        <p>Comments requested.</p>
                        <p>Foregoing thoughts are put forward on tentative basis to elicit reaction
                            of Department and other interested posts. During stopover in Athens as
                            well as at The Hague, Ambassador plans to discuss some of these ideas
                            with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Talbot</persName>. If
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Belcher</persName> or Department
                            have any preliminary reactions, their comments could be forwarded to The
                                Hague.<note n="4" xml:id="d210fn4">In telegram 209 from Nicosia,
                                October 25, <persName corresp="#p_BT1">Belcher</persName> endorsed
                                the approach outlined by <persName corresp="#p_HPT1">Hart</persName>, adding that the United States needed to begin
                                planning for its role in negotiations, and that a role had to be
                                found for <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, POL 27 CYP)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Foregoing drafted prior to receipt of <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 342.<note n="5" xml:id="d210fn5">Telegram 457 to
                                Athens (<ref target="#d209">Document 209</ref>) was also sent to
                                Ankara as telegram 342.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HPT1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Hart</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>