<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-09-15T09:55:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-09-15T09:55:00-05:00" n="237" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d237">
                        <head>237. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Greece</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d237fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, POL 27 CYP. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>.
                                Repeated to Ankara and Nicosia.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Athens</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-09-15T14:55:00+00:00">September 15, 1966,
                                    1455Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>1343. Following on my talks with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HPT1">Hart</persName> last week and private luncheon Tuesday with Greek
                            Prime Minister I have following comments on Greek-Turkish dialogue and
                            possible U.S. involvement: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Comparison of <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Stephanopoulos</persName> report to me of <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> positions (Athens 1293)<note n="2" xml:id="d237fn2">Telegram 1293 from Athens, September 13,
                                        reported <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Stephanopoulos</persName>’ belief that dialogue with
                                        Turkey had reached a point that might require U.S.
                                        mediation. (Ibid.)</note> with that given the Secretary by
                                    Caglayangil would indicate that, unless Turks still not
                                    revealing their full hand to us, either (1) Greeks are confused
                                    as to substance of <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> position
                                    or (2) to encourage U.S. involvement they are deliberately
                                    portraying gap in positions as narrower than it really is. I
                                    believe it would be helpful to probe further in September 17
                                    meeting with Toumbas for confirmation Turks are actually
                                    considering enosis, even though “loose” as reported in para 3 of
                                    Athens 1293.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>First task may be to clarify communication between two sides
                                    rather than more direct participation, particularly if
                                    Caglayangil’s statement in para 1 State 46636<note n="3" xml:id="d237fn3">Telegram 46636, September 13, reported on
                                        talks between <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and
                                        Caglayangil on Cyprus. (Ibid., POL TUR–US)</note> implies
                                    Turkey intends to view U.S. support for Turkish position as
                                    touchstone U.S.-Turkish relations. Further discussions while
                                        <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>s at <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> might elucidate this.</item>
                                <pb facs="0542" n="504" xml:id="pg_504"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Revelations volunteered so far give inadequate basis for
                                    judging utility of U.S. re-entry into negotiations along lines
                                        <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> is about to propose. My
                                    net impression, however, is that Greece and Turkey have not yet
                                    exhausted their maneuvering room in current dialogue. It would
                                    follow that they should be pushed to try harder to reach a
                                    settlement. Our basket is already pretty full and they have at
                                    least as much interest as we in peace in Eastern Mediterranean.
                                    In any event U.S. ability to exert influence toward settlement
                                    would depend on what U.S. would be prepared to do or not to do
                                    to bring Turkish position nearer to conditions that could be
                                    imposed on Greece and Greek Cypriots.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>However, since demise of <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Stephanopoulos</persName> government could bring
                                    Greek-Turkish negotiations to grinding halt, we have interest in
                                    seeing dialogue move as rapidly as possible. It may be long time
                                    before we again see combination as constructively committed to
                                    resolution of Greek-Turkish difficulties as are <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Demirel</persName>-Caglayangil and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Stephanopoulos</persName>-Toumbas. Also, it would be brash to
                                    forecast how much longer extraordinary secrecy so far maintained
                                    in dialogue can continue. When leaks start, public reactions
                                    could build up rapidly. For these reasons, I hope we can be in
                                    position to offer assistance such as Ambassador Bunker’s
                                    services on very short notice if two parties demonstrate
                                    willingness to take his suggestions seriously.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>I gather Caglayangil may involve U.S. assistance for interim
                                    solution. In considering whether there would be opportunity for
                                    constructive U.S. action along this line, we should keep in mind
                                    several factors: (1) status quo (including presence <gloss target="#t_UNFICYP1">UNFICYP</gloss>) is almost impossible
                                    to freeze precisely. Negotiating interim solution would
                                    therefore involve some of same compromises regarding internal
                                    structure as would permanent settlement; (2) unless basic
                                    revisions of Zurich-London could be agreed upon as basis of
                                    interim solution, which seems unlikely, Treaty of Guarantee and
                                    possibility of Turkish intervention under Article IV would
                                    continue to exacerbate Greek-Turkish relations; (3) under
                                    interim solution Cyprus would presumably remain independ-ent, in
                                    which case Greeks are convinced Ankara would have to address
                                    itself to Nicosia rather than Athens and negotiate with
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>. <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> considers interim solution just
                                    as difficult to negotiate as permanent one. I would tend to
                                    agree.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Nor am I sanguine about peaceful prospects of solution of
                                    “unfettered” independence. In that event, Cyprus would seem
                                    likely immediately to become cockpit of international struggle.
                                    Soviets and non-aligneds would develop sudden vested interest in
                                    preserving Cyprus as uncommitted country outside <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> area. Simultaneously Greeks
                                    (with or without government inspiration or support) would
                                    undoubtedly mount strident, intensive campaign for quick
                                    referendum to bring enosis. Presumably Turks would regard such
                                    Greek actions as <pb facs="0543" n="505" xml:id="pg_505"/>
                                    betrayal of understanding, and might reserve right to
                                    counteract. In one case we could be confronted with serious
                                    derogation of Western interests in Cyprus area; in other, with
                                    sharpened bitterness between Turkey and Greece. “Unfettered”
                                    independence with prior implicit Turkish acquiescence in enosis
                                    campaign would be a different thing, and might be workable
                                    compromise.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <p>With reference to <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Stephanopoulos</persName> report that Greeks and Turks
                                        are discussing disposition of Dhekelia base area, this at
                                        least is progress over 1964 Karpas Peninsula debate which if
                                        raised now would in my opinion be non-starter. Question of
                                        nature of Turkish rights in base area would be closely
                                        related to issue of demilitarization of Cyprus along
                                        Dodecanese lines. A Turkish military base on a demilitarized
                                        island would seem anomalous, though Turks would presumably
                                        find restriction to Dhekelia less attractive if rest of
                                        island were within Greek active border defense zone. It may
                                        be that Dhekelia issue can be resolved only within context
                                        of an Acheson-style Greek-Turkish defense board, a device by
                                        which defense needs of Cyprus could be reduced to proper
                                        proportions.</p>
                                    <p>As to form of enosis, we here have been pondering idea of
                                        commonwealth along Puerto Rican line. From Greek (and U.S.)
                                        point of view this would have serious deficiency of leaving
                                            <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> in
                                        saddle internally while making Greece responsible to Turks
                                        and rest of world for policy pursued in Cyprus. Nonetheless,
                                        if idea of enosis is still shocker to Turks, commonwealth
                                        theme might be worth examining by both parties despite Greek
                                        resistance to getting committed to anything short of full
                                        enosis.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>I advance these random thoughts at this time on assumption
                                    Department will in immediate future be intensively considering
                                    next steps.<note n="4" xml:id="d237fn4">In telegram 48821,
                                        September 16, the Department of State commented that while
                                        the Turkish Government might not have totally ruled out a
                                        dialogue on enosis, the Greek Government should avoid
                                        raising the issue. (Ibid., POL 27 CYP)</note>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Talbot</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>