<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>28. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Cyprus</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-03-28T14:54:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-03-28T14:54:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rechzLHEN4lWkdlwk" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">PermRep</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recGiqhGF0E6qdj5q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019102796"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Boycott</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-03-28T14:54:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-03-28T14:54:00-05:00" n="28"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <head>28. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Cyprus</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d28fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL 23–8 CYP. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_KGD1"
                            >Gordon D. King</persName>; cleared by <gloss target="#t_NEA1"
                            >NEA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>, and <gloss
                            target="#t_BNA1">BNA</gloss>; and approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName>. Also sent to Ankara and repeated
                        to Athens, London, and <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-03-28T14:54:00-05:00">March 28, 1964, 2:54 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>699. Ankara’s 1254 to Dept; Nicosia’s 1035 to Dept; Nicosia’s 1039 to Dept.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d28fn2">Telegram 1254 from Ankara, March 27, reported Turkish
                        press reaction to <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>’ refusal
                        to permit Denktash to return to Cyprus. (Ibid.) Telegram 1035 from Nicosia,
                        March 27, reported that <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>’
                        appointment of “temporary” ministers appeared to avoid violation of the
                        Cypriot Constitution. (Ibid., POL 15 CYP) Telegram 1039 from Nicosia, March
                        28, reported negative Turkish Cypriot reaction to <persName
                            corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>’ actions. (Ibid.)</note> Agree
                    with Embassy Nicosia’s conclusion reftel that <persName corresp="#p_MIII1"
                        >Makarios</persName>’ action in appointing acting ministers to replace Turks
                    designed underscore Turk non-participation and strengthen formal GOC control
                    Turkish-allocated ministries. This connection, Cyprus <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> PermRep Rossides has informed <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    President that civil servants who “deliberately refuse report to office” could
                    not expect “continue indefinitely be paid out of public funds”.</p>
                <p>Timing these Greek-Cypriot tactics is interesting. <persName corresp="#p_MIII1"
                        >Makarios</persName> apparently fully understands that (1) Turk-Cypriots
                    could strengthen their case and weaken his by participation, (2) that such
                    participation was not likely while security forces were primarily GOC and
                    British, and (3) that formal establishment <gloss target="#t_UNFICYP1"
                        >UNFICYP</gloss> is strategic moment for Kutchuk to insist on participation.
                    He appears to have made moves re Denktash and acting minister appointments to
                    goad Turks into frittering away energies in protests and legal arguments until
                    opportunity has passed. <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>’
                    tactics will probably succeed if Turk-Cypriots continue to sit on hands and feel
                    sorry for themselves.</p>
                <p>If Kutchuk would return to his office because of <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> presence, he could be serious embarrassment to <persName
                        corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>. Even if <persName corresp="#p_MIII1"
                        >Makarios</persName> could insist successfully that all measures of GOC
                    taken during Kutchuk’s absence are legal and not subject to Vice-President’s
                    veto, he would have difficulty not forwarding future bills or measures to
                    Kutchuk as required by constitution. His only effective alternatives would
                    appear to be: (1) to maintain that Kutchuk was rebel who tried to set up
                    separate Turk-Cypriot administration and therefore had lost authority in
                    government (difficult argument to sustain if GOC has, as it claims, been sending
                    invitations to Kutchuk and other Turk-Cypriot officials to attend scheduled
                    meetings) or (2) to maneuver Turk-Cypriots into holding back from participation
                    until too late.</p>
                <p>He appears to be operating under second alternative. With each passing day that
                    his tactics perpetuate Turk-Cypriots boycott of government, <pb facs="0095"
                        n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/> he increases general acceptance GOC as presently
                    constituted, strengthens his contention that Turk-Cypriots are insurgents and
                    weakens ability <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> to remain neutral between two
                    communities.</p>
                <p>In this connection, British Embassy informs us <gloss target="#t_GOT1"
                        >GOT</gloss> has asked HMG to intercede with <persName corresp="#p_MIII1"
                        >Makarios</persName> and protest to UNSYG on behalf Denktash. HMG has
                    informed <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> British forces Cyprus part of
                        <gloss target="#t_UNFICYP1">UNFICYP</gloss> and they cannot make independent
                    intercessions with GOC. (FYI. UKUN, however, has been instructed to call
                    Denktash problem to attention <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> on
                    humanitarian grounds. End FYI.) Turk Embassy informed Dept of GOT concern re
                    Denktash but made no request for <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> action
                    and Dept plans none.</p>
                <p>For Nicosia: Explore problem with <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> and in your discretion reiterate points
                    made in Deptel 668<note n="3" xml:id="d28fn3">Telegram 668 to Nicosia, March 18,
                        stressed the need to get Turkish Cypriot support for <gloss
                            target="#t_UNFICYP1">UNFICYP</gloss>. (Ibid., POL 23–8 CYP)</note> to
                    Kutchuk and Turk-Cypriot leaders as to advantage renewed participation
                    government. Re Rossides claim regarding payments, would appreciate clarification
                    on situation since other reports indicate Turks paying relief because no
                    salaries paid by GOC to absentee Turk-Cypriots.<note n="4" xml:id="d28fn4">In
                        telegram 1051 from Nicosia, April 1, the Embassy reported the British
                        believed that Turkish Cypriot leaders preferred partition as a solution and
                        would avoid returning to the Cabinet. It also reported that Turkish Cypriot
                        civil servants who failed to report to work were not being paid.
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>For Ankara: In your discretion, discuss Turk-Cypriot non-participation further
                    with <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss>. We would be interested any indications
                        <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> is planning or willing actively push
                    Turk-Cypriot leadership into participation.<note n="5" xml:id="d28fn5">In
                        telegram 1278 from Ankara, the Embassy reported Turkish assurances that they
                        were urging Turkish Cypriot Ministers to rejoin meetings of the <persName
                            corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> government. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
