<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>286. Telegram From the Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and
                    European Regional Organizations to the to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">286</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-05-09T15:18:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-05-09T15:18:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recHROZWmaF1AEYg7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military Assistance Program</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="detainees" subject="detained">detained</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-05-09T15:18:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-05-09T15:18:00-05:00" n="286"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d286">
                <head>286. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty
                        Organization and European Regional Organizations</gloss> to the <gloss
                        type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d286fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL GREECE–US. Confidential; Priority. Repeated to Athens, USCINCEUR,
                        and EUCOM for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-05-09T20:18:00+00:00">May 9, 1967, 2018Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>17886. NATUS. Subject: Sec <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>’s
                    talk with General Spandidakis. Following is memcon, still subject to clearance
                    with SecDef: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Minister of Defense Spandidakis, accompanied by Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_PCC1">Palamas</persName> and an interpreter, called on
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> in his <gloss
                                target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss> office at 1630 immediately following
                            conclusion of the Defense Ministers meeting. Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_CH1">Cleveland</persName> and Assistant Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_MNJT1">McNaughton</persName> were present.
                            Spandidakis initiated the conversation by saying he assumed <persName
                                corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> wanted to know why the
                            military acted in Greece. He then talked through the interpreter for 15
                            minutes.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>He said that from 1964 things had been deteriorating in Greece, that
                            the political parties had been corrupted, that there were a number of
                            liaisons with the Communists, and that there was a Communist build-up
                            everywhere including the army. It was clear the country was going to
                            fall in Communist hands, so the army, to prevent this, took over on
                            April 21 despite the Constitution. Spandidakis referred at this point to
                            the need to prevent a return to guerrilla warfare (“another Vietnam”) in
                            Greece. He said the ease with which the revolution was carried off in a
                            few hours proves it was accepted by the Greek people. He said there were
                            no “victims” (he would not count as victims the two people who were
                            killed in violating the curfew). He pointed out that peace reigned in
                            Greece two days after the action. He said the population, except for a
                            Communist small (12–15 percent) minority, accepts the action.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Spandidakis said the attacks on the Greek action are mainly from
                            foreign countries, by Communist governments or by groups associated with
                            the Communists. He referred also to false rumors such as the alleged
                            kidnapping of the King’s daughter to put pressure on the King, and the
                            rumors about the regime’s intentions to execute <persName
                                corresp="#p_PA2">Andreas Papandreou</persName> and Communist leader
                            Glazes. But he said the “greatest bitterness is in the rumor that the US
                            would revise its assistance to Greece.” He said this made no sense
                            because the alternative was to surrender to Communism. He said that, as
                            it is, the ties between Greece and <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            are stronger now than before.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>He said it is true that some people have been detained, including
                            George Papandreou—who, he says, is now being treated better than he <pb
                                facs="0643" n="605" xml:id="pg_605"/> would be in his own house. He
                            referred to others being kept in hotels, in comfortable circumstances as
                            the press could see for itself. He said such detentions were necessary
                            to stop their stirring up trouble.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Spandidakis said the government had a four-point program: (1) to
                            reorganize the government mechanism, (2) to establish economic control,
                            (3) to revise the Constitution to “bring it up to date”, and (4) to
                            “return the country to a constitutional order.” He said no one knows how
                            long the program would take, that it depends on the depth of the
                            preexisting disorganization. He said, “All of us are of a democratic
                            point of view; we are not going to establish a Fascist regime in
                            Greece”. He added that today there is no Parliament but, except for
                            that, there is more democracy today than before April 21; he said they
                            had anarchy at that time. He pointed to the interest taken by the new
                            government in the farmers and low income groups, who have expressed
                            their appreciation.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said he was
                            grateful for the explanation and for Spandidakis’ frankness (which
                            frankness, together with sincerity, Spandidakis had emphasized on three
                            occasions). <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said he
                            would likewise be frank. He said it was unnecessary to tell a Greek of
                            the admiration that the American people have for the Greek people: we
                            have had a very close relationship with them over the past two decades;
                            and our civilization is based upon theirs, dating back 2500 years. He
                            said it is completely natural for our young people to expect to travel
                            in Greece; indeed, his daughter had spent the last year there and is
                            still there. He said it concerns us greatly that Greece has moved away
                            from constitutional processes.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said it would be
                            unbecoming of him to comment on Greek internal affairs, but that it was
                            not inappropriate for him to comment on US internal affairs. He then
                            said that the American people could never understand a statement that
                            there is more democracy today than before April 21—with the press
                            suppressed, assembly prevented, people restrained, no free speech, and
                            other constitutional guarantees suspended. Also, important to the view
                            by the American people was the absence of any schedule for resumption of
                            constitutional processes. These, he said, are strong feelings of most of
                            the people in the US, and he and other government officials are servants
                            of the people. He said it would be extraordinarily difficult to maintain
                            the Greek military assist-ance program without modification if there is
                            no acceptable time schedule for the resumption of constitutional
                            processes.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that he believed
                            Spandidakis’ statement that he opposed a Fascist government, but that
                            the American view would be greatly affected by the degree to which the
                            Greeks indicate (a) a desire to make the change, (b) a schedule for the
                            change, and (c) actions toward the change. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                                >McNamara</persName> said the US would be willing to try to
                            help—e.g., by avoiding any public denunciation. But he said, the Greeks
                            should not <pb facs="0644" n="606" xml:id="pg_606"/> underestimate the
                            concern of the US and the strong hopes for movement back toward
                            constitutional processes.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Spandidakis at this point said, “Then you must explain the facts to
                            the American people”. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                            responded that, unfortunately, the facts seemed to be as stated
                            earlier—people detained, constitutional processes suspended, etc. He
                            said that the US looks to the future with hope along the lines he had
                            described.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Spandidakis said that a revision of the Military Assistance Program
                            would be dangerous, spelling out the Greek reliance on US aid. <persName
                                corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said that the whole Greek
                            situation is dangerous, and that, until action is taken to remedy it,
                            the dangerous situation will continue. He hoped the Greeks could see a
                            path for return to constitutional government which would make progress
                            in that direction obvious to outsiders. He added his view that the
                            greatest deterrent to the Soviets and the thing most likely to encourage
                            support from the US would be a demonstration by the Greeks that they can
                            return to constitutional processes.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Spandidakis said that continuation of <gloss target="#t_MAP1"
                                >MAP</gloss> will shorten the time required. <persName
                                corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> answered that, as Greek plans
                            along the lines he had described became firmer, we can be informed of
                            the progress, and public support for <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>
                            in our country will grow.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>Spandidakis asked what if the election had taken place and Greece had
                            gone Communist. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> said he
                            would not speculate but did not believe Greece would vote the Communists
                            into power. After Spandidakis explained that only 12–15 percent of the
                            population are Communist, but that more than 50 percent of the people
                            were going to make the mistake of following them, <persName
                                corresp="#p_PCC1">Palamas</persName> said that the political parties
                            had been behaving in such a way as to let the Communists take over.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> repeated that the
                            important thing was to lay out a course of action to return to the
                            constitutional processes.</item>
                        <label>13.</label>
                        <item>The conversation was concluded at 1720 with a short exchange on
                            reliability of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> as an ally of
                            Greece in trouble—both Spandidakis and <persName corresp="#p_PCC1"
                                >Palamas</persName> suggesting that <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                                >NATO</gloss> was in such disarray that it could not be counted on
                            to come to Greece’s aid. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1"
                                >McNamara</persName> said that, in his view, <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is in much better condition today
                            than it was a year ago, pointing to a year of “tremendous
                            accomplishment” in both the political and military sense, pointing to
                            the way the Allies had successfully survived the French withdrawal and
                            eviction, and to the birth and apparent good start of the NPG. He added
                            that we need (and will, in his view, be doing) more <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> planning in support of defensive
                            actions on the flanks.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CH1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Cleveland</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
