<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-05-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-05-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="46" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d46">
                        <head>46. Letter From the Ambassador to Cyprus (<persName corresp="#p_BT1" type="from">Belcher</persName>) to the Deputy Assistant Secretary of
                            State for Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_JJD1" type="to">Jernegan</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d46fn1">Source: Department of State, Cyprus
                                Desk Files: Lot 67 D 412, Letters from Post—1964. Secret;
                                Official-Informal.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Nicosia</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-05-21">May 21, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Dear <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Jack</persName>:</p>
                        <p>The Greek Cypriot leaders have made clear they intend to use the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> as a forum to press their case both in
                            the Security Council in June and in the General Assembly in the autumn,
                            by which time they expect <persName corresp="#p_TSS1">Tuomioja</persName>’s mediation efforts will have failed. They
                            expect to have adequate support not only to get the item on the agenda
                            but also to secure endorsement of the general principles they espouse:
                            an independent, unitary state; majority control; minority safeguards;
                            right of self-determination. If this is secured, they will proceed, with
                            or without Turkish Cypriot cooperation, to draw up a new constitution,
                            have it endorsed by plebiscite, and implement it.</p>
                        <p>The Cyprus problem would remain, but in an altered state. The Greek
                            Cypriots would have international moral endorsement of their efforts
                            along the above lines, and conversely, justification for continued
                            Turkish Cypriot legalistic opposition to these efforts would be thrown
                            into doubt, particularly if convincing security guarantees were
                            provided.</p>
                        <p>It appears inevitable that the GOC will seek General Assembly endorsement
                            of the above principles, which underlie our own system and which command
                            the obvious dedication of the overwhelming majority of the Cyprus
                            population. The vote on some such resolution will obviously pose a
                            difficult problem for the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>. The
                            Soviet Union and East Europeans will have no such scruples as we and can
                            pose as the “true supporters of democracy” unless we can find some way
                            to appear <pb facs="0135" n="97" xml:id="pg_97"/> on the positive side
                            of the debate and the vote. While recognizing the very difficult problem
                            this may pose vis-à-vis Ankara, we believe it would be harmful to our
                            overall interests here and elsewhere for the US to oppose such a
                            resolution or abstain. To prepare for this likely eventuality, we
                            believe the United States should commence now to plan a policy evolution
                            which would permit positive endorsement rather than awkward abstention.
                            It might be well for us to coordinate such an effort with the British,
                            who will presumably be in a similar position at the General Assembly
                            because of the need to protect their Sovereign Base Areas.</p>
                        <p>I realize this will have to be undertaken with considerable finesse in
                            view of the assurances given <persName corresp="#p_EFC1">Erkin</persName> that the United States will exert maximum effort
                            in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and among the parties concerned
                            to see that justice is done and that Turkey does not suffer humiliation.
                            The obvious problem here is the interpretation of what constitutes
                            “humiliation.” The <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> can be expected
                            to interpret this as broadly as possible. For our part, I believe we
                            should from the first make clear that the key word is justice, and in
                            our view a just solution must accord with the political facts of the
                            situation in Cyprus. In this context, we should exert our maximum
                            efforts to see that the wording, specific details and manner of
                            presentation of any specific proposals are such as to avoid offense or
                            humiliation to the <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss>. Aside from the
                            proceedings at an early Security Council meeting, I have in mind of
                            course, the probability that Tuomioja will, as a minimum, make a report
                            of his views on settlement to U Thant. As suggested in my tel 1235 to
                            the Department,<note n="2" xml:id="d46fn2">Telegram 1235 from Nicosia,
                                May 14, reported Tuomoija’s views of the likely contents of his
                                report to the Secretary-General. (Ibid.)</note> the use of his
                            report by SYG is something we would want to influence.</p>
                        <p>Aside from considerations of face, the principal fears of both the <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> and the Turkish Cypriot Community
                            appear to revolve around the question of security. To win even reluctant
                            Turkish acquiescence to a Cyprus solution, some promise of security must
                            be held out to Turkish Cypriots and Turks alike. Specific discussion of
                            ways to cope with Turkish Cypriot and <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> security problems would demonstrate our appreciation of
                            their legitimate concern in this area and should at the same time lead
                            their thinking into more productive and realistic examination of
                            practical problems rather than the present immobilism of extreme and
                            adamant positions which ignore the political, economic and arithmetical
                            realities of this Island.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName>
                                    <hi rend="strong">Toby</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>