<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>129. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v38p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-03-13T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-03-13T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="receuSgBSWw1dxuqH" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Cultural affairs</term>
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">International organizations</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-03-13T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-03-13T16:00:00-05:00" n="129"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                <head>129. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d129fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, General
                        Administrative Correspondence Files of the Deputy Under Secretary for
                        Management, 1968–75: Lot 78 D 295, <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                        1972–1974. Unclassified. Drafted by Mary Dell Palazzolo (<gloss
                            target="#t_DGPER_1">DG/PER</gloss>) on March 27. The meeting was held in
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s office at the
                        Department of State.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1974-03-13T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >March 13, 1974, 5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The Secretary’s Meeting with Representatives of the Women’s Action
                        Organization</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mrs. Dorothy Stansbury, <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Miss Barbara Good, <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mrs. Donna Oglesby, <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Dr. Dorothy Sampas, <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Nathaniel Davis</persName>, Director
                        General</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <head>OBSERVER</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BTD_1">Thomas Boyatt</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_AFSA_1">AFSA</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <head>REPORTER</head>
                    <item>M. Dell Palazzolo, <gloss target="#t_MDG_1">M/DG</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>—The representatives of <gloss target="#t_WAO_1"
                        >WAO</gloss> praised the accomplishments of the foreign affairs agencies in
                    the area of equal opportunities for women in the past few years, but expressed
                    dismay that there are still few women occupying top level positions in the
                    Department and overseas and that women are very under-represented in a number of
                    offices and bureaus in the Department. <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                    asked the Secretary to make two statements, one public and one “in-house”,
                    supporting equal opportunities for women and to explore the possibility of
                    developing in State a program similar to the one Director Keogh has initiated at
                        <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> to involve his senior staff in equal
                    opportunity programs. <hi rend="italic">End of Summary</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mrs. Stansbury opened the meeting by introducing herself and the other
                    representatives of <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss> by giving some
                    background on each one. Mrs. Stansbury said that the foreign affairs agencies
                    have taken a lead in promoting equal opportunities for women. She outlined the
                    accomplishments of the last few years including the policies on spouses, on
                    non-discrimination in assignments, reappointment of former Foreign Service wives
                    who had been forced to resign, and the upgrading of status for secretaries. The
                    Secretary inquired as to the exact meaning of <pb facs="0495" n="448"
                        xml:id="pg_448"/> “professional status for secretaries” and as to what the
                    problem was. Miss Good outlined the frustrations of secretaries including the
                    fact that there was a ceiling beyond which secretaries could not be promoted and
                    that they were expected to take a full share of the work while not being treated
                    as equals or given equal privileges. Furthermore, secretaries are the only
                    category in the Staff Corps without professional status. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Davis</persName> commented that measures were being taken
                    to correct this situation, that he hoped to institute FSRU appointments for
                    secretaries in the near future and that the next step in this program was
                    consultation with <gloss target="#t_AFSA_1">AFSA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Stansbury stated that the Department had indeed taken steps to overcome
                    discrimination and that what <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss> would like to
                    see would be a reaffirmation by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> of these policies of the recent past. Miss Good added
                    that one question of the constituents of <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                    was: where did Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> stand
                    on the professional status of women in the foreign affairs agencies. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> replied that he believed
                    women should compete on an equal basis with men, that he was not in favor of
                    quotas nor did he sanction reverse discrimination and that a woman should
                    neither be excluded from a job nor given an assignment purely because she was a
                    woman. He added that because of the long history of discrimination on the basis
                    of sex and its pervasive nature it would take a while to redress the
                    discrimination that had occurred in the past. He acknowledged that measures
                    might have to be taken to redress historical wrongs.</p>
                <p>Miss Good spoke of the under-representation of women in certain areas in the
                    Department. The Secretary asked Director General <persName corresp="#p_DN_1"
                        >Davis</persName> if we were taking more women into the Foreign Service now.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Davis</persName> reported that well over
                    25 percent of the people who took the last Foreign Service examination were
                    women, a much better percentage than in the past.</p>
                <p>Dr. Sampas commented that although there was no lack of good will on the part of
                    Management, a problem existed in the middle and senior levels of the Foreign
                    Service, exacerbated by the fact that those assignments with the best
                    opportunities for advancement usually do not go to women. She mentioned the fact
                    that there are no country directors, just one woman executive director in a
                    functional bureau and no office directors in <gloss target="#t_INR_1"
                        >INR</gloss> who are women. She also pointed out that there were no women in
                    top jobs in <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_SCI_1"
                        >SCI</gloss> or in the population office in the Department and cited such
                    prestige areas as <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> and the <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> as being especially weak on the distaff side.
                    Miss Good also mentioned that there was a dearth of women assigned to
                    delegations and in the top echelons of <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>, even
                    though educational and cultural affairs were considered a traditional women’s
                    area. Also in the area of delegates to International Organizations the U.S. has
                    a very small<pb facs="0496" n="449" xml:id="pg_449"/>of women. The U.S. has 7.2%
                    women in the <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss> Corps, while developing
                    countries have 10 to 50 percent women. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> replied that he was unable to judge whether this
                    problem was due to the fact that there were no qualified women for these jobs or
                    if real bias did exist. He added that he would not, for example, want an
                    unqualified woman as a country director. The <gloss target="#t_WAO_1"
                        >WAO</gloss> representatives agreed that women should be qualified for the
                    positions to which they are assigned. Dr. Sampas pointed out, however, that a
                    systematic search could and should regularly be made throughout the Foreign
                    Service for qualified women who would not otherwise be considered if top
                    assignments are made principally on the basis of personal acquaintance.</p>
                <p>Director General <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Davis</persName> mentioned that a
                    highly qualified and competent senior woman officer was currently heading up a
                    major division in personnel<note n="2" xml:id="d129fn2">Mary S. Olmsted was
                        Deputy Director of Personnel for Policy, Classification, and
                        Evaluation.</note> and that every effort had been made, for example, to
                    assure that women were placed on selection boards to the extent, in fact, that
                    senior women officers had complained of being over-burdened. Mrs. Stansbury, in
                    turn, cited examples of outstanding senior women who had been discriminated
                    against in terms of assignment because the offices had their “token” woman or
                    women, and one case of a woman whose outstanding ability had been considered
                    almost secondary to her race and sex in the question of a promotion.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> stated that he
                    certainly had no argument with the objectives stated by the <gloss
                        target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss> representatives, that he agreed with these
                    objectives, but that the problem was implementation. He stated he would like to
                    see more women on delegations and that systematic search should be made for
                    women from within and without the Department to serve on delegations. (Miss Good
                    interrupted here with a word of caution against tokenism or bringing in lateral
                    entrants to do jobs <gloss target="#t_FSO_1">FSO</gloss>’s could fill.)
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> also said that we
                    should make sure that more women are brought into the Service as junior officers
                    and that women are represented in all the bureaus. He expressed amazement that
                    there was not a single country director who was a woman.</p>
                <p>The Secretary added that one problem was that, while he could meet with groups
                    such as the <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>, he did not then have the
                    opportunity closely to oversee the follow-up. Director General <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Davis</persName> stated he would take responsibility for
                    implementation with the help of Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_RG_1">Gladys
                        Rogers</persName>, head of the Office of Women’s Affairs.</p>
                <p>Dr. Sampas indicated that the Department could provide the Secretary in the
                    future with econometric studies which would show the degree of past Department
                    bias toward women, whether the situation <pb facs="0497" n="450" xml:id="pg_450"
                    /> vis-à-vis women was improving, the identity of particular women who seemed to
                    have been victims of marked discrimination and who could be targeted for
                    promotion. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> then
                    asked whether the group honestly believed that there were enough qualified women
                    in the Department to be assigned to any sizeable number of jobs in the
                    substantive bureaus. Dr. Sampas replied by stating that the Department could
                    have done much better in this regard and she cited percentages which showed a
                    miniscule increase in the numbers of women at the senior levels and only a small
                    increase overall. Dr. Sampas also stated that she believed a comparative study
                    of the qualifications of women at a particular grade versus those of men at the
                    same grade would show most interesting results. Mrs. Stansbury said that with
                    the aid of Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_RG_1">Rogers</persName> and Mrs. Marcy of
                        <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> she had compiled a list of women in
                    the foreign affairs agencies who were qualified to be ambassadors or to be
                    assigned to top positions in the Department and overseas. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> said he would be most interested in
                    seeing this list and suggested that a copy also be given to Director General
                        <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Davis</persName>.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Stansbury urged that the Secretary make a public statement containing the
                    views on equal opportunities for women that he had expressed to the <gloss
                        target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss> representatives. He agreed to do so. Mrs.
                    Stansbury also urged that the Secretary make a second “in-house” statement
                    reaffirming the four existing major policy statements (on wives, secretaries,
                    non-discrimination in assignments, and equal opportunity).<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d129fn3">To mark the observation of Women’s Week, August 26–30,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> released a statement
                        affirming the Department’s commitment to women in foreign policymaking:
                        “Equality of opportunity and reward for merit are essential if the foreign
                        affairs agencies are to respond creatively to the challenges of contemporary
                        diplomacy. For this reason, I want to underscore my personal commitment to
                        the role women must play in the formulation and presentation of U.S. foreign
                        policy.” Moreover, he urged all senior officers to make “professional
                        equality for women a reality” and to make “tangible progress toward that
                        objective” by 1975, the United Nations International Women’s Year (<gloss
                            target="#t_IWY_1">IWY</gloss>). For the complete text, see the
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Newsletter,</hi> September 1974, p.
                        28.</note> Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    agreed to consider this request sympathetically, but stated that he first wished
                    to read the four statements. The <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                    representatives were able to provide three of the statements at the meeting and
                    indicated they would send Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    a copy of the fourth statement. Miss Good pointed out that a reaffirmation of
                    policies by Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> would be
                    particularly appropriate now in view of the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                    resolution designating 1975 as International Women’s Year (<gloss
                        target="#t_IWY_1">IWY</gloss>). She also described the goals of
                    International Women’s Year and its themes of equality, development and peace. A
                    paper enlarging upon <pb facs="0498" n="451" xml:id="pg_451"/> these points was
                    given to the Secretary.<note n="4" xml:id="d129fn4">Not found.</note> The
                    Secretary expressed his feeling that the Department should be doing something
                    about <gloss target="#t_IWY_1">IWY</gloss>.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss> indicated that much of the problem in
                    career development of women stemmed from attitudes of senior management. In this
                    regard Mrs. Oglesby stated that there was a third action that Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> could personally
                    undertake. She explained the program through which Director Keogh at <gloss
                        target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> was trying personally to involve his senior
                    staff in equal opportunity programs. First, Keogh had ordered a statistical
                    profile of the agency to demonstrate areas in which women and minorities were
                    concentrated or were not. After the study was done, Keogh held a ninety minute
                    discussion with the senior officers at the Agency about the study and its
                    implications. This is to be followed by three further seminars on this subject
                    in the spring. Every supervisor is encouraged to attend one of the three full
                    day sessions. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> said
                    that the programs initiated by Director Keogh sounded good and that a similar
                    program should be explored for possible use in the Department of State.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> said the major step
                    is to take action, to assure that there is follow-up. He asked Director General
                        <persName corresp="#p_DN_1">Davis</persName> what had been accomplished as
                    the result of the meeting with the Black Caucus.<note n="5" xml:id="d129fn5">See
                            <ref target="#d124">Document 124</ref>.</note> The Director General
                    mentioned several areas of progress. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> also pointed out that <persName corresp="#p_BTD_1">Tom
                        Boyatt</persName> in his <gloss target="#t_AFSA_1">AFSA</gloss> capacity
                    sits in on these meetings.<note n="6" xml:id="d129fn6">WAO’s legal counsel had
                        indicated that there was no need for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BTD_1"
                            >Boyatt</persName> to sit in on the meeting and <gloss target="#t_WAO_1"
                            >WAO</gloss> had disagreed strongly with the fact that an invitation had
                        been extended to him. <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss> does not regard
                        Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BTD_1">Boyatt</persName>’s presence as setting a
                        precedent for any future meeting between it and any managerial officials of
                        the foreign affairs agency. [Footnote in the original.]</note> Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> reiterated his amazement
                    that there was no country director who was a woman. He said he would be
                    interested to find out why this was. Director General <persName
                        corresp="#p_DN_1">Davis</persName> stated he would look into the situation
                    and would make an effort to get qualified women assigned as country
                    directors.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Oglesby stated that it would be interesting to find out how many women were
                    staff assistants, that she thought they were few in number. Dr. Sampas added
                    that the individuals who are assigned to difficult and demanding jobs early in
                    their careers are the ones who are forced to grow and stretch and, thereafter,
                    reach the top echelons of their professions. She added that over 40 percent of
                    the women junior officers were consular officers and that the reason so many
                    women are found in the consular and administrative cones is not because they
                    necessarily lack qualifications for substantive work, but because of traditional
                    pressures and bias that forces them into these areas. Secretary <pb facs="0499"
                        n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> replied that he thought all
                    Foreign Service Officers should have broad experience. A brief discussion of
                    cones followed.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> indicated that he
                    would be meeting with <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss> representatives on
                    occasions in the future, and expected <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss>
                    members to be blunt with him on such occasions concerning where progress was
                    being made and where there was none.</p>
                <p>The meeting ended with the participants expressing pleasure with having had the
                    opportunity to discuss equal opportunities for women in the foreign affairs
                    agencies. The representatives of <gloss target="#t_WAO_1">WAO</gloss> indicated
                    they would supply the Secretary with some of the material that had been
                    discussed during the meeting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
