<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-11-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="221" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d221">
                        <head>221. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d221fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Transition Records of the Executive Secretariat,
                                1959–1977, Entry 5338, Box 1, Transition/Admin. No classification
                                marking. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BPS_1">Bridges</persName>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-11-24">November 24, 1976</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Meeting with <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName>
                                Transition Officials</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Anthony Lake</persName> and Richard
                            Moose called at 1700 today on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName>, who was accompanied by Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_OFV_1">Ortiz</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BPS_1">Bridges</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName> gave Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> the following four papers, copies attached:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>1. List of “Coordination Officers for Transition”<note n="2" xml:id="d221fn2">The list is attached but not printed.</note>
                            </item>
                            <item>2. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> Memorandum dated November 24,
                                subject “Request for Information Memoranda/Organization”</item>
                            <item>3. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> Memorandum dated November 24,
                                subject “Request for Information Memoranda/Issues”</item>
                            <item>4. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> Memorandum dated November 24,
                                subject “List of Interview Requests”<note n="3" xml:id="d221fn3">This memorandum is attached but not printed.</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Reviewing the list of issue papers requested, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> said that some Assistant
                            Secretaries had told him that they hoped to be able to have a look at
                            the list of papers required before the list was put into concrete.
                            Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName> and Moose agreed
                            that it might be profitable to have a preliminary exchange with bureaus
                            on just what the scope and context of the papers should be. In response
                            to a question, Mr. Moose confirmed that they had decided it would not be
                            advisable to ask for the different bureaus to suggest possible different
                            policy options.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Moose asked if the papers could be ready for them by close of
                            business Friday, December 3. They would like to receive the papers as
                            they are done rather than have <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss> hold
                            them for presentation all at the same time. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> said that he thought December 3
                            was a reasonable deadline, but that he was not sure if we could produce
                            all the papers by then, given the Secretary’s particular interest in
                            some subjects.<note n="4" xml:id="d221fn4">On November 30, <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName> sent to the Department a
                                revised list of requested transition papers, broken down into first,
                                second, and third priorities. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Transition Records of the
                                Executive Secretariat, 1959–1977, Entry 5338, Box 1,
                                Transition/Admin) In a Cherokee channel telegram to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> in Mexico City, November
                                30, <persName corresp="#p_ELS_1">Eagleburger</persName> recommended
                                authorizing him to “go ahead with tasking the bureaus to respond to
                                the category one priority list without committing ourselves to the
                                transition team on a delivery date.” (Department of State, Files of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ELS_1">Lawrence S. Eagleburger</persName>:
                                Lot 84 D 204, Chron—November 1976) On December 3, Executive
                                Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">C. Arthur Borg</persName>
                                forwarded the second and third priority lists to all regional and
                                functional bureaus with instructions to complete second priority
                                papers by December 20 and third priority papers by January 3.
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Records
                                of the Policy Planning Staff, Director’s Files (<persName corresp="#p_LW_1">Winston Lord</persName>), 1969–77, Entry 5027,
                                Box 364, Dec. 1–15, 1976)</note> We <pb facs="0791" n="744" xml:id="pg_744"/> would, in any case, give <gloss target="#t_SCL_1">S/CL</gloss> the papers as they were completed, and we could put
                            them all together into a book later.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Moose raised the question of <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>,
                            noting that he hoped to see Birnbaum<note n="5" xml:id="d221fn5">Philip
                                Birnbaum was the Assistant Administrator of the Bureau for Program
                                and Policy Coordination, <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>.</note> in <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> on
                            Friday, November 26, especially to discuss the definition of <gloss target="#t_ODA_1">ODA</gloss> (Official Developmental Assistance).
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> noted that the <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> papers could raise some sensitive
                            issues on which <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> might disagree with
                            geographic bureaus. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName>
                            said that he would want to talk to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName> about this. We thought that the <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> papers<note n="6" xml:id="d221fn6">Not
                                further identified.</note> might best be folded in with the others,
                            but he hoped that Mr. Moose would let him know if he got any contrary
                            signals from <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> raised the question of
                            Mr. Peter Bourne’s<note n="7" xml:id="d221fn7">Special Assistant to
                                President-elect <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName>.</note> contacts with <gloss target="#t_SNM_1">S/NM</gloss> on narcotics. Bourne had asked for a briefing. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_ELS_1">Eagleburger</persName> had indicated
                            that this presented no problem. However, we understood that Mr. Bourne
                            might want to take part in the <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>
                            Regional Narcotics Conference. This was fine by us, but if Bourne was to
                            take part, it would be important to ensure that he had a full security
                            clearance before hand.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Moose said that he would suggest to <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Tony
                                Lake</persName> (who had left the room to take a call from Jody
                                Powell)<note n="8" xml:id="d221fn8">Press Secretary for
                                President-elect <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName>.</note> that <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName> should have a talk with Bourne.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>, returning to the room,
                            asked if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> knew of any
                            contact between “you and us” on the question of Soviet agrément for
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TM_1">Toon</persName>. There had been
                            press inquiries. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> said
                            he knew of none.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName> said that he assumed the
                            future Secretary of State would have a general knowledge of foreign
                            policy, so that we would not need to explain why a policy was what it
                            was, but would rather just have to present the facts of what it was. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName> said that we would
                            quickly convey to the bureaus what <gloss target="#t_SCL_1">S/CL</gloss>
                            wanted. Mr. Moose suggested, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName> agreed, that it might then be useful to have a
                            session at which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName> could
                            meet with all the bureau coordinators. It was agreed to do this. In
                            response to a question from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName>
                            said that he would of course make sure that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName> had a look at the list of
                            desired papers.</p>
                        <pb facs="0792" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/>
                        <p>The meeting ended after a discussion of the cable to be sent to <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss> about appointments for <gloss target="#t_SCL_1">S/CL</gloss> members in New York.<note n="9" xml:id="d221fn9">In telegram 288644 to <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss>, November 25, the Department informed the Mission
                                that Charles William Maynes, a member of the <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> Liaison Office, wished to
                                meet with officials of the Mission in New York on November 26.
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Foreign Policy Files, 1976)</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BPS_1">Peter S. Bridges</persName><note n="10" xml:id="d221fn10">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BPS_1">Bridges</persName> initialed “PSB”
                                    above this typed signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                            <hi rend="italic">Deputy Executive Secretary</hi>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment 2</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="strong">Memorandum From the Head of the Department of
                                    State Liaison Office for President-Elect <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> (<persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>) to the Executive
                                    Secretary of the Department of State (<persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName>)</hi><note n="11" xml:id="d221fn11">No classification marking.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-12-24">November 24,
                                1976</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECT</head>
                                <item>Request for Information Memoranda/Organization</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>We would appreciate receiving, from each bureau or office listed
                                below, a succinct description of that unit. These memoranda will be
                                for the use of the Secretary-designate and his senior appointees.
                                These memoranda should include:</p>
                            <p>1. A narrative description of the functions and responsibilities of
                                the unit and each of its senior positions. Please attach current job
                                descriptions.</p>
                            <p>2. A description of its internal organization and paper flow system;
                                an organization chart; and a list of key personnel, at least through
                                Office Director level, with notations as to their status
                                (career/noncareer, end-of-tour date). How are personnel assignments
                                made within the unit?</p>
                            <p>3. A description of its relationships to other units. To whom does it
                                report? How does it receive assignments? How does it relate to other
                                bureaus and offices in the Department, including the Policy Planning
                                Staff, <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss> and the Legal Advisor’s
                                office? In what intra-departmental and inter-agency groups does it
                                participate? Which does it chair? Who are the liaison officers who
                                handle day-to-day coordination with offices in other agencies? Who
                                are their primary points of contact in those agencies?</p>
                            <pb facs="0793" n="746" xml:id="pg_746"/>
                            <p>4. A description of how relations with the Congress and press are
                                handled. Who are the congressional members, committees and
                                subcommittees, and staff members most interested in the work of the
                                unit?</p>
                            <p>5. A list of the key public individuals and groups most interested in
                                the work of the unit. How are relations with them maintained?</p>
                            <p>6. A summary description of any recent proposals for organizational
                                changes specific to that unit, and the Department’s reaction.</p>
                            <p>7. A list and brief description of any legislation of which the
                                bureau has cognizance which will or may have to be submitted prior
                                to June 1977, including major budgetary items.<note n="12" xml:id="d221fn12">The transition papers produced by the bureaus
                                    for the <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> transition
                                    team are in the Library of Congress, Manuscript Division,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Papers,
                                    Boxes CL 327–329, Department of State, <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter, Jimmy</persName> Transition
                                    Papers, Briefing Books, Series I–III, 6 volumes.</note>
                            </p>
                            <table>
                                <head>Bureaus and Offices:</head>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>M/<gloss target="#t_DG_1">DG</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_AF_1">AF</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_MFSI_1">M/FSI</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>A</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_DBFS_1">D/BFS</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>M/MD</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_DHA_1">D/HA</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_OES_1">OES</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_DLOS_1">D/LOS</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_PA_1">PA</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_EA_1">EA</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_EB_1">EB</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_SCPR_1">S/CPR</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_SCA_1">SCA</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>H</cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_SIL_1">S/IL</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_IGA_1">IGA</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>S/NM</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>S/P</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <gloss target="#t_IO_1">IO</gloss>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>S/PRS</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>L</cell>
                                    <cell>T</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>M/CT</cell>
                                    <cell/>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0794" n="747" xml:id="pg_747"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment 3</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="strong">Memorandum From the Head of the Department of
                                    State Liaison Office for President-Elect <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName> (<persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>) to the Executive
                                    Secretary of the Department of State (<persName corresp="#p_BAC_1">Borg</persName>)<note n="13" xml:id="d221fn13">No classification marking.</note>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-12-24">November 24,
                                1976</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <list type="subject">
                                <head>SUBJECT</head>
                                <item>Request for Information Memoranda/Issues</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>The November 18 briefing book provides a useful overview of the major
                                issues facing the new Administration.<note n="14" xml:id="d221fn14">Not found. Possibly a reference to the briefing papers prepared
                                    for <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> before his
                                    November 20 meeting with <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Carter</persName>. See <ref target="#d218fn2">footnote 2,
                                        Document 218</ref>.</note> To provide necessary details for
                                the Secretary designate and his senior appointees, we would
                                appreciate receiving individual information memoranda of <hi rend="italic">no more than ten single spaced</hi> pages, and
                                preferably less, on the issues listed below.<note n="15" xml:id="d221fn15">The list is attached but not printed. The
                                    issues were: Foreign Policy and Defense Posture; Arms Control;
                                    the Middle East; Asia; Europe; Africa; Latin America;
                                    International Economic Policy; Development Assistance; United
                                    Nations; the Oceans, Environment and Science; Global Issues
                                    (e.g., terrorism); and Organizational Issues. See footnote 4
                                    above.</note> It is important that these memoranda be as factual
                                and specific as possible, including all relevant and sensitive
                                material, which will be handled appropriately. Recommendations for
                                revisions and additions to this list would be appreciated. Each
                                memorandum would usefully include:</p>
                            <p>—A very brief description of the current state of the issue—e.g., the
                                situation on the ground, status of any negotiations, principal
                                actors involved—together with some analysis of underlying causes and
                                factors. Some of these issues may raise organizational questions
                                that should be addressed. <hi rend="italic">Particular attention
                                    should be paid to action forcing events and opportunities during
                                    January 20–July 31, 1977, with specific dates where
                                    possible—e.g., a scheduled negotiation, a congressional
                                    deadline.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>—A statement of current U.S. policy on that issue, including any
                                current contingency plans.</p>
                            <p>—A succinct history of that policy, including any commitments that
                                may have been made.</p>
                            <p>—A statement of the relationship between this issue and human rights
                                concerns.</p>
                            <p>—A summary of congressional action and opinion on the issue.</p>
                            <pb facs="0795" n="748" xml:id="pg_748"/>
                            <p>—A very brief summary of any recent and relevant studies and
                                recommendations made to the Department by consultants or others, and
                                the reaction of the Department.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>