<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>95. Briefing Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Educational
                    and Cultural Affairs (Richardson) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State
                    Kissinger</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v38p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97000533"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Enrichment</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rechJJ62r5nmf4KiI" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046227"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cultural exchange</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133456"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Television</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="95"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d95">
                <head>95. Briefing Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Educational
                    and Cultural Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RJ_1">Richardson</persName>) to
                    Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d95fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                        Center, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Records of the Bureau of
                        Educational and Cultural Affairs, Office of Policy and Plans, Subject Files,
                        1961–1977, FRC 306–81–24, <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>—Monthly Report
                        to the Secretary. No classification marking. Drafted by Neil A. Boyer
                            (<gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>/OPP) and <persName corresp="#p_RJ_1"
                            >Richardson</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_PTR_1"
                            >Pickering</persName> sent a memorandum on November 6 notifying all
                        Assistant Secretaries and Office Directors that <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> had asked them to submit monthly reports “covering
                        significant items and analyzing trends in the bureau or office’s area of
                        interest.” <persName corresp="#p_PTR_1">Pickering</persName>’s memorandum
                        and <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>’s monthly reports are ibid.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-11-30">November 30, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">Monthly Report for November</p>
                <p>We believe we can effectively pursue your intention to promote an increased sense
                    of public participation in the foreign policy process by, inter alia, extending
                    our reach into the intellectual community. The variety of relationships we in
                        <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss> now have with that community are
                    especially active, constructive, and for all practical purposes undisturbed by
                    any problem of confidence.</p>
                <p>While we are far from the Department’s only available instrument (<gloss
                        target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss>, FSI, <gloss target="#t_PA_1">PA</gloss>, the
                    regional bureaus and others have their own direct linkages), we do believe that
                    26 years of experience with educational and cultural programming has built a
                    network of fruitful relationships that can readily be further developed. It is a
                    task we intend to pursue with emphasis in the future.</p>
                <p>As you know, State has since 1947 engaged the academic community in direct
                    international exchanges of “<persName corresp="#p_FJW_1">Fulbright</persName>”
                    scholars and graduate students for periods of a year or more. There are now some
                    38,000 former <persName corresp="#p_FJW_1">Fulbright</persName> participants in
                    this country and some 375 American scholars currently participate in the grantee
                    selection process. Also, <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss> support and
                    encouragement of programs of counselling, orientation and enrichment for foreign
                    students not sponsored by <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> agencies—now
                    numbering more than 150,000—help to bring very large numbers of American
                    professors and educational administrators into a constructive, although often
                    indirect, relationship with us. Our arrangements for outstanding short-term
                    visitors to this Country (some 3,000 per year) also bring Department sponsorship
                    to the attention of American experts in a wide range of disciplines and
                    professions—including especially those with competence on problem areas of
                    common international concern. In the arts we have enjoyed a cooperative
                    relationship for many years in the selection and support of tours abroad by
                    outstanding performing groups. Finally, there is a smaller but important <pb
                        facs="0381" n="334" xml:id="pg_334"/> flow abroad of American intellectual
                    and professional leaders selected for their capacity to engage influential
                    groups in useful dialogue.</p>
                <p>Other specific projects in which we are currently engaged with elements of the
                    U.S. academic/intellectual community are the following:</p>
                <p>1. The development, with Steve Bailey of the American Council on Education, of
                    five new joint task forces to enhance liaison between the government and the
                    academic community on questions related to international education and research.
                    (I serve as chairman of the government participants.) The five task force
                    assignment areas are:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—The government-academic interface in international studies;</item>
                    <item>—Transnational research collaboration;</item>
                    <item>—The diffusion of the product of international studies;</item>
                    <item>—Language skill reserves; and,</item>
                    <item>—Mid-career travel funds for area experts.</item>
                </list>
                <p>2. Continuing attention to the controversial question of <gloss target="#t_HEW_1"
                        >HEW</gloss> funding for foreign area and language studies centers around
                    the country, under Title VI of the National Defense Education Act. (Apparently
                    as a result of cumulative pressures from you and numerous others, Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_WCW_1">Weinberger</persName> has written in a letter
                    dated November 12, 1973 to Professor Lyle Nelson of Stanford—Chairman of <gloss
                        target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>’s Presidentially-appointed Board of Foreign
                    Scholarships—that <gloss target="#t_HEW_1">HEW</gloss> will reconsider funding
                    NDEA Title VI programs in its <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1975
                    budget.)</p>
                <p>3. Increasing support of programs aimed at stimulating American black college
                    involvement in internationally-oriented activities.</p>
                <p>4. A <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> initiated November seminar in Europe
                    which brought together American and West European scholars, journalists and
                    creative writers to evaluate cultural exchange with the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>5. Subsidizing foreign participation in the programs of the Aspen Institute for
                    Humanistic Studies.</p>
                <p>6. Stimulation of the process which led to the outstanding conference in Venice
                    last month on the Crisis in the Universities. The leading American scholars who
                    participated joined in the decision by their colleagues from 14 nations to
                    broaden the scope of the effort (re-named as the International Council on the
                    University Emergency) and make it permanent.</p>
                <p>7. A continuing dialogue with a variety of American scholars and professionals
                    concerned with China, centering in the Committee on Scholarly Communications
                    with the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> and the National Committee on
                    U.S.–China Relations.</p>
                <p>8. An elaborate system of privately managed but officially coordinated
                    U.S.-Japanese consultations and exchanges in a steadily growing <pb facs="0382"
                        n="335" xml:id="pg_335"/> number of fields ranging from television
                    documentaries to museum exhibitions and from newspaper editors to reciprocal
                    image studies.</p>
                <p>9. A dialogue with a variety of other intellectuals to obtain ideas useful in
                    developing an over-all U.S. cultural policy concept.</p>
                <p>10. A new Bicentennial-oriented effort which Professor Robin Winks (Yale) is
                    helping us organize to reform and strengthen “American Studies” worldwide. We
                    expect this project will be funded in part by the Humanities Endowment and the
                        <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName> Foundation.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d95fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RJ_1">Richardson</persName>’s April 1974 monthly
                        report to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> details <gloss
                            target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>’s “expansion and reinvigoration of American
                        Studies programs in other nations” as part of its contribution to the public
                        diplomacy component of the national commemoration of the Bicentennial of the
                        American Revolution. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>All these activities combine to provide an effective window on the academic world
                    and offer a good base on which to build broader relations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
