<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>1. Briefing Paper Prepared in the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-04-30T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-05-31T22:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recDVvXJiNa7eCFyj" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89000875"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor market</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="reclnawDbQgAFDvnc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85101098"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Phosphates</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" subject="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="petroleum-and-natural-gas" lcsh-match="no_match">Natural gas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-05-31T22:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-04-30T23:00:00-05:00" n="1"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1">
                <head>1. Briefing Paper Prepared in the Department of State<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d1fn0">Source: Department of State, Conference Files: Lot 66 D 110.
                        Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RJF2">Root</persName>;
                        cleared by Valdes, McBride, and <persName corresp="#p_WW3"
                        >Witman</persName>; and approved by Collopy. This paper was part of the
                        Briefing Book prepared for the President’s visit to France May 31-June 2,
                        1961.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            notAfter="1961-05-31T23:59:59-04:00"
                            notBefore="1961-05-01T00:00:00-04:00">undated</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">MOROCCO AND TUNISIA</p>
                <p>In giving Morocco and Tunisia their independence in 1956, France expected to
                    remain in very close association with them. “Independence within
                    interdependence” was the phrase coined to describe the hoped-for relationship.
                    France, it was thought, would continue to support the two North African nations
                    financially and in return would keep its military bases and obtain special
                    guarantees for its citizens and investments. In recognition of France’s
                    paramount role, the U.S. at the time said that any aid we might give Morocco or
                    Tunisia was intended to supplement (not supplant) French efforts.</p>
                <p>Events soon belied these hopes. The nationalistic prejudices aroused in Morocco
                    and Tunisia clashed with French short-sightedness (and short temper)—over bases,
                    over French privileges, over disputed territory and over the other sequels of
                    French colonization in North Africa. The Algerian war made it certain that a
                    stable relationship was for the time impossible. Morocco and Tunisia were bound
                    to support the <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss> and the French were bound to
                    resent such support. The <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss> depended heavily on
                    the sanctuary of Tunisian and Moroccan territory. Border transgressions by both
                    the French Army and the <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss> exacerbated the
                    tensions between France and its former protectorates to the point of
                    rupture.</p>
                <p>The remarkable fact is that French influence still counts for so much in Morocco
                    and Tunisia. This testifies to the underlying importance of the French-North
                    African interrelationship. Some 200,000 French nationals (of 350-400,000 before
                    independence) still live in Morocco and some 50-60,000 (of 150-200,000 before
                    independence) still live in Tunisia. Morocco continues to rely on some 15,000
                    French advisers, technicians and teachers and Tunisia, while it is much less
                    dependent on such help than Morocco, still employs several thousand French
                    teachers and other experts. France continues to provide a protected market for
                    Moroccan and Tunisian exports and French investments, particularly in Morocco,
                        <pb facs="0030" n="2" xml:id="pg_2"/> still account for most of the modern
                    sector of the North African economies. In both countries French is the second
                    language of all educated persons and the French liberal press and French culture
                    exert a powerful influence.</p>
                <p>On the governmental level, nevertheless, France, because of the obduracy of
                    Morocco and Tunisia in post-independence negotiations, suspended virtually all
                    direct financial aid to these two countries. This left a void which we have felt
                    it necessary to fill both for the sake of our own national interests and to
                    preserve some position for the West. In both countries the U.S. has become the
                    principal source of direct foreign economic aid. In Morocco, U.S. aid has
                    reached an annual level of $40 to $50 million, in Tunisia $20 to $25 million—two
                    of our largest aid programs in Africa. We also entered into modest military
                    supply programs when it appeared that Morocco and Tunisia, in desperation, would
                    seek arms from the Soviet bloc. France has not been happy about the expansion of
                    U.S. military and economic aid, but has acquiesced in it while trying to insure
                    that we consult France in advance of any new steps and showing great sensitivity
                    over an indication that we might permanently undermine the French position. As
                    elsewhere in Africa, the French have been especially pained by our
                    English-language teaching programs which they see as a permanent danger to the
                    predominance of French culture.</p>
                <p>We have taken great pains to persuade France that we are not seeking a
                    predominant role in North Africa and that we hope France will play a greater
                    role there when the Algerian war is over. We have argued, at the same time, that
                    so long as we have important interests in the area, such as our bases in
                    Morocco, and that so long as the controversies separating France and North
                    Africa endanger the Western position generally in the area, the U.S. does not
                    feel it can abandon Morocco and Tunisia.</p>
                <p>One of the most hopeful auguries for the future of the Maghreb (Morocco, Algeria
                    and Tunisia) lies in the interrelationships between the economies of France and
                    that area. France is an important labor market for North African workers and
                    provides outlets for North African grain, wine, phosphates, edible oil and
                    petroleum. The great reservoirs of natural gas developed by French enterprise in
                    Algeria can no doubt provide all of North Africa with a cheap source of power on
                    which to base an expanding industry, and with cheap power it may even become
                    possible to desalinize water profitably and thus to bring vast new desert areas
                    under cultivation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
