<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>179. Telegram From the Embassy in Benghazi, Libya to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">179</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-10-20T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-10-20T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-10-20T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-10-20T10:00:00-05:00" n="179"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                <head>179. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Benghazi, Libya</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d179fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 110.15-WI/10-2061. Confidential. Repeated to Tunis, Paris, and
                        Khartoum for <persName corresp="#p_WGM1">Williams</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Benghazi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-10-20T17:00:00+02:00">October 20, 1961, 5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>72. From <persName corresp="#p_WGM1">Williams</persName>.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d179fn1">Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WGM1"
                            >Williams</persName>, who was on his third trip to Africa September
                        29-October 26, visited Tunisia October 15-18. He was in Khartoum, Sudan,
                        October 21-24.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>During Tunis visit I was struck by warmth shown by both Tunisian
                        Government and people. I could detect few signs US position on Bizerte had
                        seriously harmed US-Tunisian friendship.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Outwardly at least I could also see little evidence Tunisian public any
                        longer much aroused by Bizerte issue. This impression no doubt had limited
                        significance however for pullback French forces just being completed<note
                            n="2" xml:id="d179fn2">On September 29, a <persName corresp="#p_FB2"
                                >Franco</persName>-Tunisian agreement was signed at Bizerte, whereby
                            French forces withdrew October 1-3, 1961, to positions held before
                            fighting broke out in Bizerte on July 19.</note> and public not yet
                        aware negative French reply to <persName corresp="#p_BH6"
                            >Bourguiba</persName> request for negotiations on evacuation.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Foregoing notwithstanding, I was made feel aware deep impact of Bizerte
                        episode and President <persName corresp="#p_BH6">Bourguiba</persName> spent
                        most my 75-minute meeting with him dwelling vividly on repercussions which
                        Bizerte has had and will continue to have so long as French refuse negotiate
                        for total evacuation. Come what may, he insisted, Tunisia would push
                        “decolonization” to end. Decolonization and dignity: West had to realize
                        these were for new nations primary goals to which everything else
                        subordinate. Tunisia had resisted aggression on its own soil and had
                        suffered terrible massacre. Report international jurists attested to
                        atrocities. (<persName corresp="#p_BH6">Bourguiba</persName> indulged in
                        impressive histrionics at this point.)</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I think he was particularly depressed by French reply he had just received
                        through Swiss. He apparently found no shred of encouragement in it. “French
                        seem to have understood nothing,” he said.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Second way in which Bizerte impact could be measured was in serious
                        problems created by departure French teachers, professional people and
                        technicians. I was told Tunisian Jews as well as French and Italians
                        apprehensive and many wanting to get out. Basis confidence on which previous
                            <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_GOF1">GOF</gloss>
                        cooperation depended badly shattered by Bizerte and unlikely be restored in
                        foreseeable future. <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> will certainly look
                        elsewhere to fill gaps and additional problems this will create for us can
                        be readily imagined.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Our group was made rather conscious of dogmatic, paternalistic even
                        authoritarian way in which <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> directs
                        Tunisian society, politically <pb facs="0297" n="269" xml:id="pg_269"/> and
                        economically. Seen in small way, for example, in obvious organization behind
                        public welcome for foreign visitors. More serious, there is growing malaise
                        and dissatisfaction among important elements Tunisian elite. However, there
                        seem to be considerable difference of opinion and discussion on different
                        points by policy makers.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>In field economic development we wondered whether <gloss target="#t_GOT1"
                            >GOT</gloss> really had capacity carry out all its fine plans. There is
                        self-satisfaction here bordering on smugness. I am also apprehensive
                        Tunisian planners giving insufficient consideration to role private
                        enterprise and I took occasion tell <persName corresp="#p_BH6"
                            >Bourguiba</persName> so. He assured me there would be much for private
                        enterprise to do. (Ben Salah tends to slight this role but in contrast
                        representative government banking institutions I met with appear consider it
                        very important.)</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Despite these misgivings, I am still impressed by Tunisia’s great
                        possibilities. I think US is presented opportunities with few parallels in
                        Africa. <gloss target="#t_GOT1">GOT</gloss> has energy, buoyancy, drive and
                        intelligence. In experience and trained manpower Tunisia is years ahead of
                        countries we have just visited south of Sahara. I think most important
                        consideration of all is influence which Tunisia, small in itself, can have,
                        we hope, in greater Maghreb context. No telling what problems we will face
                        in future Algeria and we will need all restraint, moderation and influence
                        Tunisia, as friend of West, can bring to bear. If Tunisia is not proof,
                        politically and economically, of advantages close cooperation with West, we
                        will certainly have hard time making headway in Algeria. In short, I counsel
                        continued emphasis on Tunisia for itself and especially for Maghreb
                        context.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Last but by no means least I wish to report I was deeply heartened by
                            <persName corresp="#p_BH6">Bourguiba</persName>’s emphatic and what I
                        took to be quite genuine reassurances about his basic affinity for West and
                        especially US. He said this was matter of conviction which nothing not even
                        Bizerte could change. This because we had same fundamental values, same
                        conception of life and liberty. He felt same way we did about danger in
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> desire extend hegemony over world.
                        In showdown Tunisia, so long as he was its leader, would be at our
                        side.</item>
                </list>
                <p>As I was first high-level Washington official he has had chance to talk with
                    since Bizerte, I took these assurances as special effort impress on us his
                    friendship and goodwill.</p>
                <p>Embassy Tunis comments this telegram would be welcome.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d179fn3">On October 26, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WWNJ1"
                            >Walmsley</persName> reported that he supported <persName
                            corresp="#p_WGM1">Williams</persName>’ observations and conclusions.
                        (Telegram 601 from Tunis, October 26; Department of State, Central Files,
                        110.15-WI/10-2661)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Dorman</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
