<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>324. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Mission to the
                    United Nations</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d324</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">324</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-01-11T19:56:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-01-11T19:56:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recSWpZOc8YpkYHHD" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-01-11T19:56:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-01-11T19:56:00-05:00" n="324"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d324">
                <head>324. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Mission to the United Nations</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d324fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 745C.00/1-1062. Confidential. Drafted by Simms; cleared by Reis,
                        Kellermann, <persName corresp="#p_DOH1">Deming</persName>, Sweeney, and Acly
                        (ODA); and approved by Wallner. Repeated to Salisbury.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-01-11T19:56:00-05:00">January 11, 1962, 7:56 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1819. US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Talks: Southern Rhodesia. Your
                        2364.<note n="1" xml:id="d324fn1">In telegram 2364 from <gloss
                            target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, January 10, Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_YCW1">Yost</persName> reported serious misgivings on the
                        part of the delegation about some aspects of a proposed Department of State
                        position paper on Southern Rhodesia. (Ibid.)</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> believes there are essential differences
                    between Southern Rhodesia case and case of Portuguese territories. In latter,
                    Administering Authority unwilling recognize its responsibilities under Chapter
                    XI, while <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> on contrary, clearly striving carry
                    out its responsibilities. Re argument contained last sentence your reftel that
                    because info re status Southern Rhodesia not submitted to <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> we unable judge whether or not territory is self-governing,
                        <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> satisfied that Southern Rhodesia is
                    self-governing.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> did not propose suggest British that they
                    try avoid vote on draft res by threat withhold cooperation from Committee of 17,
                    merely noted its view this likely in fact be only possibility preventing
                    vote.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> agrees there would be advantages from our
                    standpoint for Committee on Info, rather than Committee of 17, consider question
                        <pb facs="0541" n="513" xml:id="pg_513"/> Southern Rhodesia’s status, but
                    does not agree it would be more logical and doubts Afro-Asians be willing refer
                    question to Committee on Info.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> notes <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>’s
                    intention not make its case for self-governing character Southern Rhodesia
                    before Fourth Committee and will seek in US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                    talks convince British wisdom contrary course of action.</p>
                <p>Present Southern Rhodesian Government making earnest effort promote multi-racial
                    society, outlaw discrimination and substantially increase African participation
                    in government and public affairs. At same time, Federation Rhodesia Nyasaland in
                    midst important constitutional crisis which could result in independent
                    Nyasaland and possibly Southern Rhodesia in year or two. If US Government denies
                    or ignores fact of full internal self-government, position of Southern Rhodesian
                    Government would be undermined, tendency toward disorder in Central Africa would
                    be increased, and US relations with <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and
                    Southern Rhodesian authorities would be complicated. <gloss target="#t_Dept1"
                        >Dept</gloss> continues believe, therefore, USGADel should vote against
                    resolution, not merely abstain.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
