<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>61. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs
                    (Williams) to the Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs () to the Under
                    Secretary of State for Political Affairs (McGhee))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d61</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">61</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="61"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d61">
                <head>61. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_WGM1" type="from">Williams</persName>) to the Under
                    Secretary of State for Political Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MGGC2" type="to"
                        >McGhee</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d61fn0">Source:
                        Department of State, Central Files, 033.51S11/3-1362. Confidential. Drafted
                        by <persName corresp="#p_HPJ2">Hooper</persName> on March 12.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-03-13">March 13, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Authority to Receive <gloss target="#t_PAG1">PAG</gloss> Representative in
                        the Department after Algerian Cease Fire</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It has been agreed, as you know, that following the Algerian cease fire, the
                    Department should receive representatives of the <gloss target="#t_PAG1"
                        >PAG</gloss> informally <pb facs="0118" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/> at an
                    appropriate high level. The occasion of the official announcement of a cease
                    fire agreement would in itself present an opportunity which I believe would be
                    particularly useful for us to exploit in this connection.</p>
                <p>I should appreciate an early chance to talk to Mr. Chanderli, the <gloss
                        target="#t_PAG1">PAG</gloss> representative in New York, who up to now has
                    been limited in Departmental contacts to occasional informal discussions with
                    officers of <gloss target="#t_AFN1">AFN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_WE1"
                        >WE</gloss> outside the Department. Mr. Chanderli has been quite forthcoming
                    in these discussions and informal talks he has had with Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_SAEII1">Stevenson</persName> and other <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                        >USUN</gloss> officers.</p>
                <p>On an informal basis I should like to arrange to have a discussion with him as
                    promptly as possible after the cease fire announcement during which I would
                    propose to inform him of the substance of the President’s message and the
                    additional points which Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WWNJ1"
                        >Walmsley</persName> will have been authorized to pass to Ben Khedda.</p>
                <p>This would serve two useful purposes. First, it would be very gratifying to
                    Chanderli who has been sensitive about not being informed about past initiatives
                    of the Department concerning the <gloss target="#t_PAG1">PAG</gloss>. Secondly,
                    it would provide a natural pretext for holding such an interview and changing
                    our policy of banning reception of <gloss target="#t_PAG1">PAG</gloss>
                    representatives in the Department under circumstances and at a time which could
                    hardly be seriously objectionable to the French.</p>
                <p>Mr. Chanderli is a likely choice for the post of first Algerian representative to
                    the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and possibly also Ambassador to the United
                    States. Recent conversations he has had with <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                        >USUN</gloss> indicate that he is well informed about Algerian plans
                    concerning inter-African cooperation and that he is destined to play a
                    significant part in Algerian representation at future African conferences such
                    as the Conference of Independent African States scheduled to take place at Tunis
                    later this year. I feel that this move to establish a basis for informal
                    discussions in the Department would help us considerably in obtaining a flow of
                    useful information about prospective internal and external policies of the
                        <gloss target="#t_FLN1">FLN</gloss>.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommended Action:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That AF be authorized to arrange informally through <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                        >USUN</gloss> after the cease fire for Mr. Chanderli to visit the Department
                    for purposes of holding discussions along the lines indicated above.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d61fn1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">McGhee</persName> initialed his approval on
                        March 14. A cease-fire agreement was concluded at Evian-les-Bains on March
                        18. On March 26, Chanderli was received at the Department of State by
                            <persName corresp="#p_WGM1">Williams</persName>. The visit was preceded
                        by a small informal luncheon outside the Department hosted by Deputy
                        Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_THJ1">Tasca</persName>. The
                        conversation was recorded in two memoranda of conversation (ibid.,
                        751S.00/3-2662) and reported to the Embassy in Paris on March 26 in telegram
                        5251, which asked the Embassy not to emphasize the fact that this was the
                        first time any <gloss target="#t_PAG1">PAG</gloss> representative had been
                        received in the Department of State. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
