<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-08-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-08-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="70" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d70">
                        <head>70. Letter From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                            International Security Affairs (<persName type="from">Sloan</persName>)
                            to <persName type="to">William R. Polk</persName> of the Policy Planning
                                Council<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d70fn0">Source: Washington
                                National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss>
                                    330,<gloss target="#t_OASDISA1">OASD/ISA</gloss> Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 65 A 3501, Algeria 000.1-121, 1962.
                                Secret. Drafted by Colonel Junkermann.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-08-23">August 23,
                                    1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Bill</hi>: I want to thank you for supplying me
                            with a copy of your memorandum concerning the possibility of providing
                            military assistance to Algeria which you sent to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>.<note n="1" xml:id="d70fn1">Polk’s memorandum discussed several potential sources of military
                                equipment for Algeria, noting that the most disadvantageous to the
                                United States would be for the Soviet Bloc to provide military
                                equipment and instruction directly to the Algerians, which would
                                have a profoundly dislocating effect on the U.S. strategic position
                                in Africa. On the other hand, potential damage to French-U.S.
                                relations placed direct provision of U.S. military equipment near
                                the bottom of the scale of desired actions. The best arrangement
                                would be to have France supply such equipment, but current French
                                attitudes made this unlikely. Better from the U.S. point of view
                                would be to have a friendly Muslim country or another European
                                country act as a source of supply. (Ibid.)</note> Advance
                            information of <pb facs="0129" n="101" xml:id="pg_101"/> this type is
                            extremely helpful. A review of this subject is both timely and important
                            if we are to take the initiative rather than waiting to react to Soviet
                            efforts.</p>
                        <p>If it is decided to form an interagency working group on this or similar
                            African policy problems, it would be useful if <gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> could be represented. In this particular case, I would
                            designate Colonel Howard C. Junkermann and Colonel Joe Whitfield to
                            represent my office.</p>
                        <p>I have several comments concerning the memorandum which you may find
                            helpful in your deliberations.</p>
                        <p>I question the concept of any alternative which envisions the probable
                            use of an Arab country acting as an agent for the Soviet Bloc to furnish
                            aid to Algeria. Further, the furnishing of U.S. equipment through a
                            friendly power such as Pakistan would be such a thin subterfuge as to be
                            practically worthless. For example, we were accused of being a party
                            with the French in the Algerian rebellion because the French used U.S.
                            manufactured equipment. The idea of incorporating other friendly powers
                            such as Sweden, U.K., Italy, Japan, etc., which have an industrial base
                            capable of supporting either partially or in toto the required armaments
                            for training, has considerable merit. However, in such cases, it would
                            be appropriate for the U.S to be disassociated with the effort. Of
                            course, France is the logical choice to furnish such assistance but she
                            may be unwilling to meet the needs in a forthright fashion.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, I believe that the time has come, if we are unsuccessful
                            after exploring the problem with friendly industrial nations, for the
                            U.S. to speak firmly and clearly to the French about the matter,
                            indicating we are prepared to offer Algeria military assistance if they
                            do not. In this case it would be better for the U.S. to act directly
                            than through a third party.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Frank K.
                                    Sloan</hi></persName><note n="2" xml:id="d70fn2">Printed from a
                                    copy that indicates that Sloan signed the
                                original.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>