<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>71. Memorandum From Robert W. Komer of the National Security Council Staff to
                    President of the National Security Council Staff to President Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d71</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">71</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="rectswnul2C5uzE9Y" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092233"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Non-alignment</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec0a544f0318c9793" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">Food relief</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec26FVg4SV48wXxH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124118"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Socialism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="71"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                <head>71. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_KRW2" type="from">Robert W.
                        Komer</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to President
                        <persName corresp="#p_KJF2" type="to">Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d71fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_KJF2"
                            >Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security Files, Countries Series,
                        Algeria, 9/1/62-10/15/62. Secret. A handwritten covering note from <persName
                            corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_BMG2"
                            >Bundy</persName> reads: “This is long, but State briefing book is lousy
                        so I summed up their 30pp. in my three. I also wanted to clue <gloss
                            target="#t_JFK1">JFK</gloss> on State/<gloss target="#t_AID1"
                            >AID</gloss> hassle over aid to Algeria. Only he can decide it, in last
                        analysis, and now is best time to educate him.” Department of State briefing
                        material for Ben Bella’s visit in October 1962 is in Department of State,
                        Conference Files: Lot 65 D 533, CF 2176.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-10-13">October 13, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>While the chief purpose in receiving Ben Bella<note n="1" xml:id="d71fn1">The
                        National Assembly of Algeria, which was elected on September 20, designated
                            <persName>Ben Bella</persName> as Prime Minister of Algeria on September
                        26. On September 29, the Assembly approved his list of cabinet officers and
                        the United States formally recognized the “newly established Government of
                        the Republic of Algeria.” For texts of the statement issued by the
                        Department of State and messages from the Secretary and President to
                            <persName>Ben Bella</persName> and Foreign Minister Khemisti, see
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October 15, 1962, p.
                        560. The Embassy in Algiers was established on September 29 with Porter as
                        Charge d’Affaires ad interim. On October 4, the President formally invited
                        the new Prime Minister to visit the White House when he came to the United
                        States for the admission of Algeria to the United States. (Letter from
                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> to Ben Bella, October 4;
                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> Library, President’s
                        Office Files, Countries, Algeria)</note> is to get acquainted and to offset
                    any misapprehensions he may have about “neo-colonialist” U.S. policies, we also
                    have a chance to: (1) lay the groundwork for U.S. influence on him; (2)
                    underline the importance of close cooperation with France.</p>
                <p>This 46 year old comes with great personal respect for you, dating from your 1957
                    Senate speech (you could give him a copy of Strategy for Peace). He still clings
                    to a lot of naive ideas and thinks in terms of a melange of revolutionary
                    cliches from Marx, Mao, Nasser and Che Guevara. Basically, however, he’s much
                    more pragmatic than doctrinaire.</p>
                <p>Therefore, it should be possible to impress him with our general support of
                    self-determination and social change, our respect for honest non-alignment, and
                    even of our legitimate concern over the Communist threat to new nations (Sekou
                    Toure’s experience is relevant here). He understands why we couldn’t back his
                    rebellion; indeed your 1957 speech gives you credentials to argue that you
                    didn’t oppose it.</p>
                <p>The best tactic, however, might be to handle him in low key, asking him questions
                    and responding to his sallies. You might want to query him first about his own
                    plans for Algeria. This could lead naturally to an airing of the outlook for the
                    Evian Accords. We emphatically want France to shoulder the main burden in
                    Algeria (the bill will be immense, and we don’t have the money—at least this
                    year). But too direct an affirmation of the need for close French-Algerian ties
                    might arouse suspicion. Instead you might ask him what he thinks he can get from
                    the <pb facs="0131" n="103" xml:id="pg_103"/> French, how many technicians and
                    teachers he thinks he can woo back, whether he can get Paris to continue the
                    Constantine Plan, etc.</p>
                <p>Ben Bella recognizes the need for extensive French help, and that Algeria’s
                    natural economic links are with Europe. But as a neutralist he’s going to tap
                    other counterbalancing sources, both east and west. While State believes he has
                    no shopping list in his pocket, he undoubtedly wonders how generally forthcoming
                    we’re likely to be.</p>
                <p>We’ve given a lot of relief help already—350,000 tons of food since 1956 through
                    voluntary agencies, a medical team and supplies, ten mobile clinics as an
                    independence gift—and have already approved $40 million more in <gloss
                        target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 63 food relief (see Tab C).<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d71fn2">None of the tabs is attached to the source text.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Beyond this, however, we have no real aid program for Algeria. In <hi
                        rend="italic">fact State and <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> differ
                        sharply on this issue</hi>. <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> believes we
                    should leave Algeria to France. They fear that aggressively seeking ways to help
                        <persName>Ben Bella</persName> over his economic hump would make us
                    frontrunner, whereas we want to leave France in the driver’s seat. They plan to
                    continue emergency feeding and food-for-work projects through the winter. But
                    they are reluctant to volunteer other aid—even in principle—for fear of arousing
                    Algerian hopes of extensive technical assistance or development lending. They
                    claim they can’t round up enough French and Arabic speaking technicians for such
                    a program and don’t have loan money.</p>
                <p>State agrees that France must shoulder the chief load, but argues for a U.S.
                    program to support <persName>Ben Bella</persName> indirectly against an army
                    takeover and to influence development planning as it matures. They feel that the
                    Evian Accords might break down, or at least be greatly modified, and that the
                    Bloc will be all too willing to jump in. They would prefer <persName>Ben
                        Bella</persName> to turn to us for help if he looks anywhere but in Europe.
                    As for <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>’s argument about shortage of funds,
                    they argue that a country as important as Algeria should be near the top of the
                    list for what funds we do have.</p>
                <p>While recognizing how we’re strapped, I think State is right. Here we have a
                    chance (albeit a potentially costly one) to buy in on the ground floor in one of
                    the few really important new nations in Africa. Given a $180 million three-year
                    commitment to Tunisia and $40 million yearly to Morocco (plus $12 million <gloss
                        target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 63), it
                    doesn’t make sense for <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> to program only $2
                    million (plus food) for Algeria in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 63. Agreed
                    that we don’t want the French to unload Algeria on us. But we need some kind of
                    an independent presence, if only on preclusive grounds. Unless <gloss
                        target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> settles down to imaginative planning, we’ll be
                    in no position to respond quickly to Algerian needs, to identify those sectors
                    where concentrating <pb facs="0132" n="104" xml:id="pg_104"/> our resources will
                    best further our interests, or to face the contingency of a breakdown in
                    Franco-Algerian cooperation.</p>
                <p>I don’t know whether either you or <persName>Ben Bella</persName> will want to
                    bring up Cuba (he still seems to be going there).<note n="3" xml:id="d71fn3">On
                        October 6, following instructions from Washington, <persName
                            corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName> told Khemisti that the U.S.
                        Government was deeply disturbed by press reports that <persName>Ben
                            Bella</persName> planned to visit Cuba immediately after being received
                        by President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> in Washington.
                        (Department of State, Central Files, 033.51S11/10-662)</note> But he’s now
                    heard from many sources how sensitive we are on this issue. His entourage in New
                    York says he is going to Cuba to satisfy the leftists at home, perhaps with some
                    vague notion of healing the U.S.-Cuban rift. He professes to believe that Castro
                    is a “madman.” He excluded Communists from the National Assembly, and even
                    Colonel Boumedienne recently said that the “Communists never sincerely aided the
                    Algerian rebellion.”</p>
                <p>On the other hand, many Algerians still seem to look at Castro through
                    rose-colored glasses. So Cuba may provide a good text to get across the risk of
                    Communist capture of indigenous national revolutions (I’ve attached a <gloss
                        target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> summary).</p>
                <p>Finally, you might want to congratulate <persName>Ben Bella</persName> on his
                    formation of a government and dedication to the principles of parliamentary
                    democracy. He’s allowed an opposition in the new Assembly; almost a third of it
                    has opposed him on one issue or another. Whether or not <persName>Ben
                        Bella</persName> reverts to one-party government, he’s a better bet than the
                    army (Major Slimane, whom you’ll see at luncheon is along as the Army’s man).
                    Although our ability to influence the outcome of Ben Bella’s struggle to retain
                    power is negligible, we lose nothing by encouraging him along his current
                    moderate course.</p>
                <p>We propose an innocuous joint communique after our talk, in order to limit Ben
                    Bella’s opportunities to free-wheel with the press (Draft at Tab III-B). You
                    should also skim Scope and Talking Papers and Tab III-D rounding up recent
                        <persName>Ben Bella</persName> statements on his attitude toward the US, the
                    Evian Accords, socialism, etc. It gives a good feel for the man.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">
                            <hi rend="strong">R.W. Komer</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d71fn4">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
