<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-11-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-11-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="90" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                        <head>90. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d90fn0">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, Job 79 R
                                01012A, Box 242. Secret. According to a note on the cover sheet, the
                                estimate was prepared by the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and
                                the intelligence organizations of the Departments of State, Defense,
                                the Army, the Navy, the Air Force, and NSA. All members of the U.S.
                                Intelligence Board concurred in this estimate on November 27 except
                                the Atomic Energy Commission Representative and the Assistant
                                Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, who abstained
                                because the subject was outside their jurisdiction.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 62-63</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-11-27">November 27,
                                1963</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">ALGERIA</p>
                        <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>The sum of the political and economic difficulties facing Algeria
                                make the achievement of real political stability an uncertain
                                prospect for <pb facs="0162" n="134" xml:id="pg_134"/> some time to
                                come. For the present, however, <persName>Ben Bella</persName>
                                clearly remains the political personality with the widest popular
                                appeal and he appears to have a fairly firm grip on such
                                governmental institutions as exist in Algeria. His recent
                                negotiations with the Kayble dissidents and other opponents seem
                                likely to contain further threats of armed revolt for the time
                                being. Over time, the greatest danger to him would arise from an
                                erosion of his popular support as a consequence of continued
                                economic misery or of military reverses on the Moroccan border
                                conflict. (Paras 29-36)</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>No early improvement in the country’s serious economic condition
                                is likely. European colonization gave independent Algeria an
                                impressive physical plant in terms of industries and transportation
                                links, but the exodus left it with only a tiny fragment of trained
                                people necessary to run it. At best, Algeria will probably make only
                                modest progress in putting idle industrial capacity to work, with
                                the result that massive unemployment will continue for some time to
                                plague the three million Algerians in the cities. We think it likley
                                that the nationalized agricultural properties will experience
                                considerable trouble in maintaining a minimum level of subsistence
                                in rural areas. However, Algeria will need to import food for many
                                years to come. (Paras. 2-4, 24-28)</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>For a number of years foreign aid will play a critical role in
                                keeping Algeria from financial collapse and in feeding the country.
                                France will almost certainly continue to provide a substantial level
                                of developmental and budgetary assistance for at least the next two
                                years or so. Nevertheless, the Franco-Algerian relationship will be
                                delicate and there will almost certainly be strains, perhaps arising
                                from the use of the Saharan test sites or disagreements over oil
                                revenues, which could threaten the flow of French aid. (Paras. 21,
                                46-48)</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>In the absence of a Franco-Algerian rupture, the Soviet Union is
                                unlikely to play a major role in Algeria. If relations with France
                                deteriorate, Algiers would probably try to obtain more aid from both
                                the US and the Soviet Bloc. Under present circumstances, the Soviets
                                seem to realize that they cannot compete with France and are content
                                to establish a presence, get into the military field where possible,
                                and take advantage of any opportunities which may occur. (Paras.
                                44-45, 49)</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item>Algeria’s general foreign policy will continue to be governed by
                                the desire of its leaders to align themselves broadly with the
                                neutralist bloc and to oppose “imperialism”. This general attitude
                                will from time to time bring frictions not only with France but with
                                the US and other Western Powers as well. One major source of such
                                frictions will be Algeria’s effort to play a prominent role in
                                encouraging revolutionary independ-ence movements in Africa, a
                                policy to which the regime seems fairly well committed. Links to the
                                eastern Arab world are unlikely to be of major importance to
                                Algeria’s policy, but <persName>Ben Bella</persName> will probably
                                continue <pb facs="0163" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/> to look to Cairo
                                for assistance and will cooperate with Nasser on an ad hoc basis.
                                (Paras. 37, 42-43, 49)</item>
                            <label>F.</label>
                            <item>Prospects for a final settlement of the Moroccan border conflict
                                are not promising. Incidents in the disputed border areas are likely
                                to be endemic and could lead to outbreaks of larger scale fighting.
                                If this occurs or if an arms buildup continues because no political
                                settlement can be reached, there may be increasing pressure on the
                                great powers to declare themselves and to give material support. On
                                the whole, however, we believe that if the US preserves a generally
                                neutral stance the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> will be
                                disposed to limit its intervention. The effort of the other African
                                states to find a solution through the Organization for African Unity
                                    (<gloss target="#t_OAU1">OAU</gloss>) will also help to insulate
                                the struggle from the wider issues of the cold war. (Paras.
                                40-41)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>[Here follows the Discussion section of the estimate.]</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>