<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-09-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-09-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="120" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d120">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Adams</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1086.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-09-16"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 16, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> An absence of two weeks from the capital
                            has delayed this acknowledgment of the receipt of your despatch of the
                            25th of August, No. 766.</p>
                        <p>I have read with much interest your remarks upon the sectarian riots at
                            Belfast. It seems to me that the parliamentary orators, who seek to
                            excite a national controversy with us on the ground of Irish emigration,
                            might profitably study the ecclesiastical system of their own country.
                            Religion is a concern of deep interest for all the people of every
                            nation, and for a very large proportion of every people it has an
                            interest paramount even to the affairs of civil government. From Turkey
                            quite round the world to Japan, including all the European states and
                            all American countries, except the United States, spiritual
                            controversies are a permanent fountain of political and even
                            revolutionary conflicts. The reformers of Great Britain dwell much upon
                            what they regard as defects <pb facs="0320" n="300" xml:id="pg_300"/> of
                            their political system, but I do not believe any political amendment
                            whatever will avail to arrest the depopulation of Ireland. Nothing, I
                            think, can do that but an adoption of our own great principle of an
                            absolute divorce between the church and the state. It is not true that,
                            as is so often asserted, the Irish religious sectarians are as
                            discontented and contentious after they arrive in America as they were
                            in their native country. Some few of them, indeed, retain a disputatious
                            character for a time, but, speaking in a practical sense, the great mass
                            are speedily absorbed and become a loyal and effective portion of the
                            American people.</p>
                        <p>I have read Lord Palmerston’s speech to his constituents at Tiverton, and
                            have noticed with regret that he thought proper to defer so much to the
                            enemies of the United States as to express an expectation of a time when
                            foreign influence may be exercised to reconcile us to a dissolution of
                            the Union. I think I can perceive that his opinions are based upon the
                            interested reports of some of his countrymen, who, being domiciled among
                            us, work indefatigably in the supposed interest of the governing class
                            in Great Britain. It does not surprise me that these persons are
                            deceived by the intemperate demonstrations of factions here, which allow
                            their partisan zeal to carry them into disloyal courses. But that a
                            statesman so astute and having so much experience as Lord Palmerston
                            should suffer himself to fall into the error I have mentioned does
                            surprise me, and I can account for it upon no other ground than that,
                            like most European politicians, he has not allowed himself to become
                            personally acquainted with our country and with the American people.
                            Certainly I do not expect the British nation in any case to receive,
                            much less to invite, American advice concerning its political affairs.
                            Under no circumstances could I be induced to intrude advice upon them;
                            yet a contingency in which foreign advice shall be accepted by Great
                            Britain is, in my judgment, just as probable as the speculations
                            concerning American affairs are with which Lord Palmerston favored his
                            reverential audience at Tiverton. Great Britain has, during my connexion
                            with this government, been successively represented by three sagacious
                            ministers— Sir John F. Crampton, Lord Napier, and Lord Lyons. I do not
                            know their opinions on the subject, but I vehemently doubt whether
                            either of them would represent the American people to his government as
                            likely in any case to accept foreign intervention, or in any event to
                            submit to a subversion of the Constitution, or a dissolution of the
                            Union.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>