<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1864-11-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1864-11-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-11-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-11-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="168"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d168">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 817.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-11-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 18, 1864.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have received from Lord Wharncliffe, the
                    chairman of the British association organized to give aid and comfort to the
                    rebel cause, a note, a copy of which is transmitted herewith. I append a copy of
                    my reply.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wortley Hall, Sheffield,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-11-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 12, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: A bazaar has been held in St.
                        George’s Hall, Liverpool, to provide a fund for the relief of southern
                        prisoners of war; it has produced a clear sum of about £17,000. In
                        preference to any attempt to reach the intended object by circuitous means,
                        a committee of English gentlemen has been formed to address you on the
                        subject.</p>
                    <p>As chairman of this committee, I venture to ask your excellency to request
                        the permission of your government that an accredited agent may be sent out
                        to visit the military prisons within the northern States, and minister to
                        the comfort of those for whom this fund is intended, under such supervision
                        as your government may direct.</p>
                    <pb facs="0375" n="355" xml:id="pg_355"/>
                    <p>Permit me to state that no political end is aimed at by this movement. It has
                        received support from many Who were opposed to the political action of the
                        south. Nor is it intended to impute that the confederate prisoners are
                        denied such attentions as the ordinary rules enjoin. But these rules are
                        narrow and stern. Winter is at hand, and the clothing which may satisfy the
                        rules of war will not protect the natives of a warm climate from the severe
                        cold of the north.</p>
                    <p>Sir, the issue of this great contest will not be determined by individual
                        suffering, be it greater or less, and you, whose family name is interwoven
                        with American history, cannot view with indifference the sufferings of
                        American citizens, whatever their state or their opinions.</p>
                    <p>On more than one occasion, aid has been proffered by the people of one
                        country to special classes under great affliction in another. May it not be
                        permitted to us to follow these examples, especially when those we desire to
                        solace are beyond the reach of their immediate kinsmen. I trust that these
                        precedents and the voice of humanity may plead with your excellency, and
                        induce you to prefer to the government of the United States the request
                        which I have the honor to submit.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, your obedient, humble servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>WHARNCLIFFE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">C. F. Adams,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Lord
                            Wharncliffe</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-11-18">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 18, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the
                        reception of your letter of the 12th instant, asking me to submit to the
                        consideration of my government a request of certain English gentlemen, made
                        through your lordship, to send out an accredited agent to visit the military
                        prisoners held by the United States, and afford them such aid, additional to
                        that extended by the ordinary rules of war, as may be provided by the fund
                        which has been raised here for the purpose.</p>
                    <p>I am very sure that it has never been the desire of my government to treat
                        with unnecessary or vindictive severity any of the misguided individuals,
                        parties in this deplorable rebellion, who have fallen into their hands in
                        the regular course of war. I should greatly rejoice were the effects of your
                        sympathy extended to the ministering to the mental ailment, not less than
                        the bodily sufferings of these unfortunate persons, thus contributing to put
                        an end to a struggle which otherwise is too likely to be only procrastinated
                        by your labors.</p>
                    <p>Be this as it may, I shall be happy to promote any humane endeavors to
                        alleviate the horrors of this strife, and in that sense shall very
                        cheerfully comply with you lordship’s desire, so far as to transmit, by the
                        earliest opportunity, to my government, a copy of the application which has
                        been addressed to me.</p>
                    <p>I beg your lordship to receive the assurance of my distinguished
                        consideration.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Wharncliffe,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
