<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-04-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="333" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d333">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Lord Lyons</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-04-06"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 6, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: Recurring to your communication of the
                            24th ultimo in relation to the imprisonment in Fort Warren of Mr. Cory
                            the master, and Mr. Perries the chief officer, and three of the crew of
                            the British steamer Don, I have now the honor to enclose, in reply, a
                            copy of a letter of the 1st instant from the Secretary of the Navy,
                            stating that their release has been ordered, and that measures are being
                            taken for the discharge of all <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> foreign
                            subjects captured in neutral vessels seized for breach of blockade,
                            where there is no other charge against them warranting their detention,
                            and they are not needed as witnesses.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, with high consideration, my lord, your obedient
                            servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Right Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Lyons</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Welles</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Navy
                                        Department</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-04-01"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your letter of the 29th ultimo, enclosing a note from
                                Lord Lyons in reference to the detention and imprisonment in Fort.
                                Warren of the master, mate and three of the crew of the
                                blockade-running, steamer Don, who claim to be British subjects.</p>
                            <p>Orders have been given for the release of the persons referred to,
                                and measures are being taken for the discharge of all <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> foreign subjects captured in
                                neutral vessels seized for breach of blockade, where there is no
                                other charge against them warranting their detention, and they are
                                not needed as witnesses.</p>
                            <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>GIDEON WELLES, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the
                                    Navy.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>