<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lord Lyons to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d348</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">348</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1864-04-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1864-04-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-04-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-04-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="348"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d348">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Lord Lyons</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-04-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 21, 1864.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In obedience to instructions which I have
                    received from her Majesty’s principal secretary of state for foreign affairs, I
                    have the honor to submit to you <pb facs="0613" n="593" xml:id="pg_593"/> a copy
                    of a protest made by the master, mate, and one of the seamen of the British
                    wrecking schooner Dart, against the proceedings of a United States
                    steamer-of-war, supposed to be the Vanderbilt.</p>
                <p>Her Majesty’s government having considered this protest, are of opinion that if
                    the statements made in it be well founded, her Majesty’s territorial rights have
                    been intentionally violated, and injury inflicted upon her Majesty’s subjects
                    within her Majesty’s territory by a cruiser of the United States. Her Majesty’s
                    government have accordingly directed me to call the attention of the government
                    of the United States to those statements, and to request that an investigation
                    may be made respecting them.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your most obedient,
                    humble servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>LYONS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Protest of the master, mate, and one of the seamen of the
                            Dart.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bahama Islands</hi>, <hi rend="italic">New Providence
                            :</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Know all men by these presents: That on this 9th day of January, in the year
                        of our Lord 1864, before me, Bruce Lockhart Burnside, a notary public, by
                        lawful authority appointed, duly admitted and sworn, residing and practicing
                        in the city of Nassau, in the island of New Providence, personally came and
                        a ppeared George H. Pearce, the master, James Harris, the mate, and William
                        H. Bethel, seaman, of and belonging to the Bahama wrecking schooner Dart,
                        who, of their own free will and voluntary accord, did declare, (such
                        declaration being made in pursuance of the laws of the Bahamas for
                        substituting a declaration in lieu of an oath in certain cases,) that they
                        sailed in and on board the Bahama wrecking schooner Dart, in the capacities
                        above set forth, on Wednesday, the 6th day of this instant, January, from
                        the bluff in the island of Eleuthera, one of the Bahama islands, bound on a
                        voyage to the port of Key West, Florida. On arriving off Egg island, about
                        nine in the morning, these declarants observed a vessel-of-war in chase of a
                        merchant steamer, the latter of which approached to within two miles of Egg
                        island, and the declarants then observed that her deck load, consisting of
                        bales of cotton, was being thrown overboard. That the said schooner Dart was
                        then taken through the Egg island cut, and these declarants, with the rest
                        of the crew, commenced to save the cotton which was drifting about on
                        soundings, and within a distance of three miles from the land. That they had
                        succeeded in saving twelve bales of cotton when the vessel-of-war abandoned
                        the chase and proceeded towards the Dart, and approached within hailing
                        distance, she having at the time her licensed wrecking flag flying from the
                        main-topmast head. That this declarant, the said George H. Pearce, then
                        hailed the war vessel, and stated that the Dart was a licensed wrecking
                        vessel; that the cotton was in British waters, and that he considered he had
                        a right to save it. Two of the crew of the Dart, James Carry and the
                        declarant, William H. Bethel, were then in one of the Dart’s boats, and had
                        succeeded in securing a bale of cotton which they were about to take in,
                        when an officer from the deck of the war vessel presented a pistol at them
                        and declared that if they attempted to take it in he would shoot them. A
                        boat was then lowered from the war vessel, the parties in her drove the
                        wreckers away from the cotton and took it. The crew of the war vessel in her
                        boats then proceeded to save the rest of the cotton which was adrift. And
                        these declarants further declare that the said vessel-of-war had no flag
                        flying at this time, although when in chase of the merchant ship she had the
                        American ensign flying. That one of the crew of the Dart hailed and asked
                            <pb facs="0614" n="594" xml:id="pg_594"/> what the name of that vessel
                        was, but no reply was given; an officer from the deck of the ship
                        threatening to run into the Dart and sink her if they attempted to cross the
                        bows of the war vessel.</p>
                    <p>And these declarants lastly declare that the said war vessel was a side-wheel
                        steamer of between 1,500 and 2,000 tons burden, brig-rigged, drawing twenty
                        feet forward, with two walking beams above decks; these declarants believing
                        her to be the United States vessel-of-war Vanderbilt.</p>
                    <p rend="right">GEORGE H. PEARCE,</p>
                    <p rend="right">JOHN M. HARRIS,</p>
                    <p rend="right">WILLIAM H. BETHEL.</p>
                    <p>Declared to this 9th day of January, A. D. 1864, before me.</p>
                    <p>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l.s</hi>.]</p>
                    <p rend="right">B. L. BURNSIDE, <hi rend="italic">Notary Public, Bahamas.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bahama Islands</hi>, <hi rend="italic">New
                            Providence:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>To all to whom these presents shall come: I, Bruce Lockhart Burnside, a
                        notary public, by lawful authority appointed, duly admitted and sworn,
                        residing and practicing in the city of Nassau, in the island of New
                        Providence, do hereby certify the foregoing to be a true copy of a notarial
                        declaration duly made before me by the parties therein named, as the same
                        remains of record in my official notarial record book, page 243 to page
                        245.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">[l. s.]</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In faith and testimony whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and affixed my
                        seal of office, at Nassau, in the island of New Providence, this 9th day of
                        January, A. D. 1864.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>B. L. BURNSIDE, <hi rend="italic">Notary Public.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
