<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lord Lyons to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1864-06-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1864-06-29T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="immigration" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274" lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077" lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="elections" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557" lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-06-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-06-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="412" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d412">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Lord Lyons</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-06-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 29, 1864.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I am informed that in the department of
                            the gulf the following oath is exacted from foreigners:</p>
                <p rend="center">“<hi rend="smallcaps">United States of America, Department
                                of the Gulf,</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="right">
                    <hi rend="italic">“Office Provost Marshal General.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">New Orleans</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ss</hi> :</p>
                <p>“I, __________, do solemnly swear that I am a subject of __________; that
                            Ihave never become or been a citizen of the United States by
                            naturalization or <pb facs="0663" n="643" xml:id="pg_643"/> otherwise,
                            nor have I declared my intention to become such citizen, nor voted at
                            any political election in the United States, nor done any act in
                            derogation of my allegiance to — .</p>
                <p>“I do further solemnly swear that, so long as my government remains at
                            peace with the United States, I will do no act, nor aid, advise, or
                            consent that any be done, nor conceal any act done, or to be done, that
                            shall aid, assist, or comfort any of the enemies or opposers of the
                            United States, or the authority or government theleof.</p>
                <p>It appears that this oath is exacted even from British subjects belonging
                            to the crews of British merchant vessels, and even in cases in which
                            they arrive at and depart from New Orleans on board the same vessel.</p>
                <p>The oath, if it is to be construed literally, imposes upon subjects of
                            her Majesty obligations following them beyond the jurisdiction of the
                            United States; and, such being the case, is objectionable in several
                            particulars.</p>
                <p>I beg you to take into consideration the accompanying copies of a
                            correspondence on the subject which has taken place between Major
                            General Banks and the acting British consul at New Orleans, and I trust
                            that if it shall still be deemed necessary to exact an oath from
                            foreigners, measures will be taken to substitute at once, for that in
                            use in the department of the gulf, one unobjectionable in its terms.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your most
                            obedient, humble servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>LYONS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Major General Banks</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Coppell</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters Department of the
                                            Gulf,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">New Orleans,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-05-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 28, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Will you please suggest to me what
                                change you desire in the neutral oath to which you alluded
                                yesterday, and in what respect it conflicts with the rights of
                                seamen or any other class of British subjects.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>N. P. BANKS, <hi rend="italic">Major General
                                        Commanding.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">G. Coppell,</hi> Esq.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Coppell</persName> to <persName type="to">Major General Banks</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">British Consulate,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">New Orleans,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-05-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 30, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have to acknowledge the receipt of
                                the communication of the 28th current, which you have done me the
                                honor to address to me, respecting the aeutral oath, the subject of
                                my remarks on the previous day, and, conformably with the desire
                                expressed, I offer for your consideration the following
                                considerations</p>
                    <p>After a British vessel has been cleared for sea by the authorities,
                                it is required that the crew, whether the same that arrived with the
                                vessel or those shipped lere, shall subscribe the neutral oath (<hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> if they are aliens) before the vessel s
                                allowed to depart the port. British subjects, properly registered as
                                such, are also required to subscribe the oath when obtaining a pass
                                to leave this department for the north or for a foreign country.</p>
                    <pb facs="0664" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/>
                    <p>In referring to the oath as now administered, it will be seen that in
                                the first port the alien swears to the already proved fact of being
                                a foreigner; for, before subscribing, the applicant has to show a
                                foreign passport or a consular certificate. The second part of the
                                oath would seem to impose upon the neutral obligations binding when
                                beyond the jurisdiction of the United States, an obligation which,
                                if expected or intended, can scarcely be considered as consistent
                                with the rights which the United States government has with regard
                                to neutrals, nor the neutral British subject with his own sovereign.
                                I would, therefore, beg to suggest for your consideration that in
                                the case of the crews of British vessels, and where the crew is the
                                same as when the vessel arrived in port, the oath be dispensed with;
                                and with regard to that class of British subjects arriving at or
                                departing from New Orleans by sea, that the oath be somewhat
                                modified in the points I have named. I take the liberty of enclosing
                                a copy of a neutral oath which is imposed in one of the military
                                departments (the Mississippi, I think) of the United States,
                                believing that it may be considered as covering all the groun ds of
                                a neutral obligation.</p>
                    <p>I desire it to be understood, general, that I offer these remarks in
                                behalf of neutral British subjects only, particularly those whose
                                interests may call them to this department transiently, and in no
                                way to interpose for any who, in contempt of her Majesty’s
                                proclamation, may violate the neutrality imposed upon all classes of
                                her subjects.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself of this opportunity to renew my thanks for the prompt
                                consideration and action always accorded the many and important
                                matters I have had occasion to bring to your notice in the discharge
                                of my official duties.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>GEORGE COPPELL.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Major General <hi rend="smallcaps">N. P. Banks,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Army.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Major General Banks</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Coppell</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters Department of the
                                            Gulp,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">New Orleans,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-06-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 8, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to inform you that
                                there are difficulties connected with the modification of the
                                neutral oath suggested by you, which deters me from adopting it at
                                present.</p>
                    <p>There are many American citizens in this department, born of English
                                and French parents, who, to escape conscription, claim foreign
                                protection under the belief that the descendants of a subject do not
                                lose the nationality of their ancestry. Such persons have not only
                                participated in the elections of this country, but have availed
                                themselves of all the privileges of natural-born citizens. It seems
                                but just that those who claim the privilege of neutrality should be
                                required to make the declaration that they have not exercised the
                                privileges of citizens of the United States.</p>
                    <p>Without undertaking to decide the question of neutrality in cases
                                where such declaration cannot be made, and which may be reserved for
                                special consideration, the interests of the government seem to
                                demand that the general rule adopted in this department should be
                                observed. If there be just cause for changing the practice in regard
                                to seamen who ship from this port upon the same vessels in which
                                they arrive, I shall very gladly make the change upon a proper
                                representation of the facts.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>N. P. BANKS, <hi rend="italic">Major General,
                                        Commanding.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">G. Coppell,</hi> Esq</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
