<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lord Lyons to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d438</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">438</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1864-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1864-07-30T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-07-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="438" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d438">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Lord Lyons</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-07-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 30, 1864.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to transmit to you a copy
                            of a despatch from the acting British consul at New York, and a copy of
                            a protest, addressed to the collector of customs at that port, by
                            Messrs. Darrell &amp; Nash.</p>
                <pb facs="0683" n="663" xml:id="pg_663"/>
                <p>It appears from these papers that Messrs. Darrell &amp; Nash are British
                            merchants, and that they have been refused the clearance of certain
                            merchandise shipped by them to Nassau, in the Bahama islands.</p>
                <p>I beg you to call the attention of the proper authority to this matter,
                            in order that relief may be given to these merchants.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your most
                            obedient, humble servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>LYONS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Edwards</persName> to <persName type="to">Lord Lyons</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-07-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 23, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: I have been solicited to bring to
                                your lordship’s notice the case of certain merchandise shipped by
                                Messrs. Darrell &amp; Nash (British merchants doing business, here)
                                upon British account, for Nassau, N. P., on board the British
                                schooner Electric, which has been refused a clearance by the customs
                                authorities upon the plea that certain goods shipped in May last, by
                                the same firm, were subsequently transshipped to Nassau.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to transmit herewith, enclosed lor your lordship’s
                                information, a copy of a protest which has been served upon the
                                collector of customs, by Messrs. Darrell &amp; Nash, in reference to
                                the case.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>P. EDWARDS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Lyons,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>Protest of Darrell and Nash.</head>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">To the</hi>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Collector</hi> of the port of New York
                                    :</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The undersigned are commissioned
                                    merchants, established and conducting business at the port of
                                    New York. They have lately, at the said port, purchased and
                                    shipped On board the schooner Electric a cargo of goods and
                                    merchandise, the same having been purchased and shipped by order
                                    and per account of certain parties residing in Nassau, New
                                    Providence, a British port. Manifests of the said cargo have
                                    been prepared, and application for the clearance for the same
                                    made at the custom-house. The customs officer having the first
                                    charge or direction of such clearances, has passed and approved
                                    the said manifests, and the articles comprised therein, and has
                                    marked the same as proper to be bonded upon export, according to
                                    the customs regulations in such cases made and provided. The
                                    customs officer having the further charge and direction of such
                                    clearances, and the taking and approving such bonds, has, upon
                                    application, refused to allow the said goods and merchandise to
                                    be bonded, and has refused to grant or complete the clearances
                                    of the same. The undersigned, at the time of applying to the
                                    said last-mentioned officer for the said clearances, presented
                                    and offered good and sufficient bondsmen to execute the bonds
                                    required, and to justify in the manner usual in such cases. But
                                    the said officer refused to accept or allow the execution and
                                    perfecting of such bonds, not from any objection he had to the
                                    said bondsmen, or their sufficiency, but on the ground solely
                                    that he declined to grant clearance for the said goods and
                                    merchandise. The reason stated and assigned by the said officer
                                    for his refusal to grant clearance for the same is this, namely,
                                    that certain other goods and merchandize shipped by the
                                    undersigned in May, 1964, on board another vessel, and consigned
                                    to other parties, <pb facs="0684" n="664" xml:id="pg_664"/> than
                                    the consignees per Electric, and conveyed to another port than
                                    Nassau, to wit, the port of Turk’s Islands, another British
                                    port, were, after being landed and delivered at the said Turk’s
                                    Islands, thence transported and conveyed to the said port of
                                    Nassau.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned, by reason of the refusal of the officers of the
                                    customs to grant the clearance applied for as aforesaid of the
                                    goods and merchandise now laden on board the said schooner
                                    Electric, will be unable to forward the same to their
                                    destination, and will be obliged to discharge, unload, and
                                    receive the same from the said vessel, thereby incurring and
                                    suffering great and serious loss, damage, and expense.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned, upon the above facts, hereby protest against the
                                    acts of the customs officers at the port of New York in refusing
                                    to grant them clearance of, and for the goods and merchandise
                                    shipped as aforesaid on board the said Electric. Prepared as
                                    they are and have been to comply with all the regulations
                                    established and published with reference to such clearances,
                                    they claim to be entitled to have and receive the same, and they
                                    protest against the refusal of the clearance of the said goods
                                    and merchandise upon the grounds stated and sssigned, or upon
                                    any other grounds. For themselves, as shippers and con-aignors
                                    of said goods and merchandise, as well as for the consignees
                                    thereof, and for the owners of the vessel and all parties
                                    interested in the said vessel or cargo, the undersigned protest
                                    as aforesaid; and they hereby give notice that they will hold
                                    you responsible for and endeavor to collect from you or the
                                    United States, or any other officer thereof, as they shall be
                                    advised, the expenses, loss and damages which the undersigned or
                                    the said consignees or owners, or either of them, may suffer or
                                    incur by reason of the discharging and receiving the said cargo,
                                    or the delay and failure in -forwarding and receiving the said
                                    goods and merchandise, or that may be in other way occasioned by
                                    the refusal to grant and have the clearance or clearances as
                                    aforesaid.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">Dated <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">New York,</hi>
                                </placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-07-23">
                                    <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 23, 1864</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed>DARRELL &amp; NASH.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
