<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-10-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="520" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d520">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Burnley</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-10-05"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 5, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> Her Majesty’s government have had under
                            their consideration the note which you were good enough to address to
                            Lord Lyons, on the 13th July, in reply to the one which his lordship had
                            the honor of addressing to you, under instructions from her Majesty’s
                            principal secretary of state for foreign affairs, on the 13th June last,
                            relative to the imprisonment in the Old Capitol prison at this place of
                            the late Mr. James Hardcastle, and his death in consequence of a shot
                            fired by a sentry at that prison.</p>
                        <p>I am now instructed to state, that her Majesty’s government have learned
                            with much regret the view taken of Mr. Hardcastle’s case by the United
                            States government, and their refusal to offer compensation to the
                            relatives of this unfortunate person. After a further and careful
                            consideration of all the circumstances connected with this case, her
                            Majesty’s government see no reason to modify their opinion with respect
                            to it, as expressed in Lord Lyons’s notes of the 13th August, 1863,<note n="*" xml:id="d520fn1">38th Congress, 1st session, Ex. Doc. No. 1,
                                page 690.</note> and 13th June, 1864. I can, therefore, only repeat
                            that her Majesty’s government considers that Mr. Hardcastle’s life was
                            sacrificed by the carelessness of subordinate officers of the United
                            States government, and by the bad regulations of the prison in which he
                            was improperly confined.</p>
                        <p>Her Majesty’s government further consider that there are some portions of
                            the report of the United States Judge Advocate General to the Secretary
                            of War which ought not to be left wholly unnoticed.</p>
                        <p>If the construction which that officer places upon the meaning and effect
                            of a safe conduct under a flag of truce is to prevail, it should be
                            widely and generally known, for in substance it amounts to this—that the
                            United States regard a flag of truce, when used for the purpose of
                            soliciting and obtaining permission for a particular individual to pass
                            and remain within their lines, as imparting no protection whatever to
                            the person who may come under it into their territory. As thus
                            interpreted it means, merely, that persons who bring it are not to be
                            fired upon while they pass the space which intervenes between the lines
                            of the enemies, and while the flag itself is exhibited; but that, as
                            soon as they are within the lines of the United States, they may be
                            treated in exactly the same manner as if they had been made prisoners of
                            war. Her Majesty’s government affirm such a doctrine to be utterly at
                            variance with international law, with the usages of all civilized
                            states, and with the reason and justice upon which both are founded.
                            Good faith, in matters of this kind, is a question of substance, and not
                            (as international authorities seem to be interpreted by the Judge
                            Advocate General of the United States) one of form. Whether the form be
                            a written safe conduct, or a permission given (without writing) for the
                            safe passage of an individual within the lines of a belligerent, the
                            promise of safety is in substance the same; and the effect of such
                            promise must continue (unless a limit was originally fixed to its
                            duration) until it is revoked, after such a notice as may at least give
                            the person relying upon it the opportunity of returning without
                            molestation <pb facs="0753" n="733" xml:id="pg_733"/> from the same
                            belligerent to the place from which he came, or some other place of
                            security. The necessary use of a flag of truce to obtain such a
                            permission does not imply that the permission itself is to be nugatory
                            as soon as that flag is withdrawn.</p>
                        <p>As regards the passage brought forward by the Judge Advocate General, in
                            support of his views, from Vattel, cap. 17, I am instructed to state
                            that the passage does not appear in any way to support the doctrine for
                            the confirmation of which it is cited. That author is there not speaking
                            of the protection afforded by a flag of truce to a person who is
                            admitted under it to enter and remain in the enemy’s lines, but of a
                            general suspension of hostilities for a limited period, after the lapse
                            of which period, he rightly says, in the absence of any special
                            condition, the enemy found in the territories of either belligerent is
                            subject to the laws of war.</p>
                        <p>Her Majesty’s government do not dispute, that if Mr. Hardcastle had
                            misconducted himself after he had been so received into the territory of
                            the United States, he was liable to be arrested or imprisoned; but her
                            Majesty’s government are of opinion that Mr. Hardcastle’s arrest and
                            imprisonment, upon no ground whatever except upon vague suspicions as to
                            his previous acts and history, derived from the very fact of his coming
                            from the enemy’s lines, and from the papers produced at the time of his
                            admission under promise of safe conduct, (for it is admitted that this
                            expression was used, and it is vainly attempted to explain away its
                            force,) was a plain violation of the good faith pledged to him, for
                            which her Majesty’s government see no justification in any alleged
                            necessities of the belligerent.</p>
                        <p>Under these circumstances, I am instructed to state that her Majesty’s
                            government feel bound to reserve to themselves the right of renewing
                            their application to the United States government for compensation to
                            Mr. Hardcastle’s relatives, should they, at a future period, consider it
                            to be their duty to do so.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your most
                            obedient, humble servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>J. HUME BURNLEY.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>