<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-07-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="63" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 738.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">London,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-07-07"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 7, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In answer to the representation made by me
                            to Lord Russell, concerning the fitting out of the steamer Hawk, as
                            reported in my despatch No. 729, of the 23d of June, I have now the
                            honor to transmit a copy of his lordship’s note of the 4th instant.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward.</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Earl Russell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Adams</persName>.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-07-04"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 4, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> With reference to my note of the 20th
                                ultimo, I have the honor to inform you that it appears from further
                                inquiries which have been made by the <pb facs="0222" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/> board of customs with respect to the Hawk,
                                that vessel left the Victoria docks on the 13th ultimo, and is
                                stated to have passed Gravesend on the following day, cleared for
                                Bermuda.</p>
                            <p>The commissioners of customs report that the cargo of the Hawk
                                consisted of iron, iron bar, bar steel, and divers articles of
                                merchandise; that some of the packages were examined by their
                                officers, but that nothing of a suspicious nature was found
                                therein.</p>
                            <p>The commissioners add that they are informed that their officers had
                                no difficulty in going over every part of the ship, and that in so
                                doing they saw nothing whatever to arouse any suspicion of the
                                vessel; that she appeared to be a very fast merchant ship, and that
                                the general opinion seems to have been that she was not fitted for
                                war purposes, her iron plates being so thin and light.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your
                                most obedient, humble servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>RUSSELL.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>C. F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Adams,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>