<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1983-09-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1983-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="100" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                        <head>100. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of
                            State (<persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Hill</persName>) to the President’s
                            Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clark</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d100fn1">Source:
                                Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Robert Lilac</persName>
                                Files, Arms Transfer, Subject File/1981–84, AT (Arms Transfers):
                                [Korean Airlines] <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss> [09/10/1983];
                                NLR–332–14–35–1–4. Secret. A covering memorandum dated September 10
                                to <persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clark</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_LR_2">Lilac</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RR_2">Robinson</persName> indicates the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> received this set of
                                papers.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1983-09-07">September 7, 1983</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Transmission of Implementation Strategy for <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> on the U.S. Response to the
                                Soviet Destruction of the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss>
                                Airliner</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>We are attaching an implementation strategy for the <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> on the U.S. response to the Soviet
                            destruction of the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss> airliner.<note n="2" xml:id="d100fn2">See <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss>
                                102, <ref target="#d95">Document 95</ref>.</note> Several of the
                            steps have already been taken or are already in process. This study
                            reflects the input of the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss>
                            interagency group and the papers prepared by its working groups which
                            are attached.<note n="3" xml:id="d100fn3">Attached but not printed are
                                the following papers, which were also incorporated into the strategy
                                paper: “Private Boycott of Soviet Aviation;” “Claims;” “10
                                Strategies for Dealing with the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss>
                                Incident;” “Isolation of the Soviet Union in Aviation (A Strategy
                                for the U.S.);” a memorandum on “Strategy for Dealing with Congress
                                on the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss> Incident;” “<gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Public Affairs Followup
                                regarding the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss> Plane Incident;”
                                and “Proposed Public Posture and International Public Diplomacy
                                Strategy.”</note> The paper has not been cleared by the <gloss target="#t_IG_1">IG</gloss> but it has been distributed to the
                            member <pb facs="0386" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/> agencies. Should we
                            receive substantive comments from them, these will be reported to the
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> staff.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_HMC_1"><hi rend="strong">Charles
                                    Hill</hi></persName><note n="4" xml:id="d100fn4">Deputy
                                    Executive Secretary Covey signed for <persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Hill</persName> above <persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Hill</persName>’s typed
                                signature.</note></signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline"><hi rend="strong">Tab 1</hi></note>
                            <head><hi rend="strong">Strategy Paper Prepared in the Department of
                                    State</hi><note n="5" xml:id="d100fn5">Secret.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian">undated</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Strategy Paper for Implementation of
                                        <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> on the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss> Incident</hi></p>
                            <p>The Soviet attack on an unarmed Korean passenger airplane is a clear
                                violation of international law and a threat to international civil
                                aviation security. While the immediate threat is particularly in or
                                near the Soviet Union, the Soviet action raises serious questions
                                regarding the system as a whole. The <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> defines the measures the United States will take
                                with the international community to promote our objectives of
                                seeking justice, demonstrating resistance to intimidation, and
                                advancing understanding of the contrast between Soviet words and
                                deeds. The strategy for implementing these specific measures
                                including diplomatic, public diplomacy and congressional approaches
                                as developed by the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_IG_1">IG</gloss> follows below. Also described are
                                issues for future decision. The detailed papers prepared by the
                                various <gloss target="#t_IG_1">IG</gloss> working groups are
                                attached at the annex.</p>
                            <p>The <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> sets out specific actions
                                for seeking justice in five areas:</p>
                            <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Full Accounting</hi>. Even though the Soviets
                                have now admitted downing the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss>
                                aircraft, our most immediate requirement remains pressing the
                                Soviets for a full accounting of the incident, including access to
                                the crash site, recovery of the victims, technical equipment (black
                                box), wreckage and other material such as personal property and a
                                thorough and impartial investigation of what happened. We have
                                already made these demands forcefully, both in diplomatic channels
                                and publicly. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> will be making these points at the highest
                                level with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> in Madrid on September 8 and the issue will
                                be pursued through vigorous intervention in the appropriate
                                international organizations.</p>
                            <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Develop Omnibus U.S. Claim</hi>. A draft United
                                States claim for reparation, in the form of a diplomatic note, has
                                been prepared and <pb facs="0387" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                                circulated to other interested governments whose nationals perished
                                in the tragedy, with a request that they take similar action. The
                                note is a concise statement that we consider the Soviet action as
                                wrongful under international law, giving rise to a Soviet obligation
                                to make reparation. After responses from other governments, we will
                                present the Soviet Chargé with the diplomatic note on September
                                    12.<note n="6" xml:id="d100fn6">Acting Assistant Secretary of
                                    State <persName corresp="#p_KJH_1">Kelly</persName> presented
                                    the note to <persName corresp="#p_SO_1">Sokolov</persName> on
                                    September 12. For the statement issued at the time and the note,
                                    as well as a note presented on behalf of the Korean Government,
                                    see the Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                                    October 1983, pp. 14–15.</note> This claim will be supplemented
                                with details and documentation after consultations with the families
                                of the victims. We have invited those family members who will be in
                                Washington for the memorial service to a briefing on the claim at
                                4:00 p.m. on Friday, September 9.</p>
                            <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Measures Against Aeroflot.</hi> The <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> calls for the United States to
                                work with and help to lead other members of the international
                                community in formulating and implementing measures that will
                                “adversely affect” Aeroflot’s operations. Unilaterally, we have
                                already:</p>
                            <quote><p>—reiterated the existing sanction suspending
                                    regularly-scheduled Aeroflot service to the U.S.;</p>
                                <p>—notified the Soviets we will not renew our bilateral
                                    transportation cooperation agreement, nor proceed with
                                    discussions on consulates in Kiev and New York and on a new
                                    cultural exchanges agreement;</p>
                                <p>—the Department of State is sending a letter for the President’s
                                    signature requesting the <gloss target="#t_CAB_1">CAB</gloss> to
                                    initiate action to suspend relations between U.S. carriers and
                                    Aeroflot as well as Aeroflot’s remaining commercial activities
                                    in the United States;</p>
                                <p>—begun to undertake the necessary steps prior to informing the
                                    Soviets of the closure of the Aeroflot offices in New York and
                                    Washington.</p></quote>
                            <p>Multilaterally, we are seeking the isolation of the Soviet Union in
                                world aviation until it provides a satisfactory response to our
                                collective concerns for aviation safety. Specifically we have
                                proposed that for an initial period of 60–90 days:</p>
                            <quote><p>—that other governments suspend Aeroflot’s operations to and
                                    from their territories;</p>
                                <p>—that they suspend interline arrangements between their
                                    respective carriers and Aeroflot, and other commercial
                                    opportunities for Aeroflot, such as sale of tickets;</p>
                                <p>—that they investigate other possible restrictions on support
                                    services.</p></quote>
                            <p>A crucial ingredient in this strategy is that the U.S. not be seen to
                                be ahead in its reaction and that it consult fully with its friends
                                and allies in developing a coordinated, coherent and sustained
                                international <pb facs="0388" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/> reaction.
                                Thus, while we should continue to discuss our proposed measures
                                publicly in general terms, we should continue now to avoid specifics
                                so that the ongoing consultative process can reach agreement on
                                specific steps. We are urging the key European countries to
                                coordinate their actions and not undercut one another.</p>
                            <p>The key element in the diplomatic strategy is Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>’ participation at the
                                Madrid conference, where he will have intense consultations with
                                five of the countries (Italy, <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>,
                                France, U.K. and Canada) whose cooperation is essential. Japan, not
                                present in Madrid, will be handled bilaterally. His speech to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> plenary on September 9
                                will include a full statement of U.S. condemnation and the
                                implications for East-West relations. We have encouraged other
                                ministers to do the same, and the response has been excellent.</p>
                            <p>Multilaterally, the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Allies,
                                Japan, Korea, <gloss target="#t_ASEAN_1">ASEAN</gloss>, ANZUS and
                                other key countries of Europe and the third world have been briefed
                                in Washington. This approach has been reinforced in capitals. We
                                have forwarded to the White House letters from the President to the
                                heads of government of the U.K., <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>, Japan, Thailand, Malaysia, Singapore and Canada.
                                Letters are under preparation to other leaders, including France,
                                Italy, Ireland and Australia. Secretary Dole has sent messages to
                                her counterparts in the key <gloss target="#t_ICAO_1">ICAO</gloss>
                                Council member countries to ask their support in <gloss target="#t_ICAO_1">ICAO</gloss>, and also in adopting the
                                proposed civil aviation measures against Aeroflot.</p>
                            <p>Our top priority will be to monitor this diplomatic offensive and
                                apply the necessary measures to follow up the <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss>.</p>
                            <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Private boycott.</hi> A worldwide aviation
                                industry response would help isolate Soviet aviation and promote a
                                satisfactory Soviet response to aviation safety concerns. The
                                decision by the International Federation of Airline Pilot’s
                                Associations to institute a 60-day boycott of flights to and from
                                the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> is very encouraging. To
                                be effective, any boycott must remain a private, not a <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>, initiative. Our strategy should
                                be to maintain contact with U.S. pilot and other groups through one
                                or two key representatives to keep up to date on actions being taken
                                by the aviation industry. We will use these contacts to give them a
                                signal: that we favor all efforts consistent with U.S. law and
                                policy to isolate Soviet aviation in order to elicit satisfactory
                                Soviet response to the case and the safety concerns it raises.</p>
                            <p>5. <hi rend="italic">International Organizations.</hi> We will
                                sustain the efforts to obtain appropriate action in appropriate
                                international organizations. Our objectives are the broadest
                                condemnation of the Soviet Union, an investigation, and remedial
                                actions to enhance flight safety and prevent a recurrence of this
                                tragedy. Tactically, we should keep Japan, Korea and others in front
                                while mobilizing broad support for constructive remedies.
                                Specifically, in the international organizations, we should:</p>
                            <pb facs="0389" n="348" xml:id="pg_348"/>
                            <quote><p>—seek a strong resolution at the September 15 <gloss target="#t_ICAO_1">ICAO</gloss> Council meeting, in which we
                                    would seek to condemn this Soviet violation of international
                                    law, express shock and outrage at the Soviet Union’s callous
                                    disregard for human life and its refusal to cooperate in search
                                    and rescue as well as investigation efforts, and direct the
                                        <gloss target="#t_ICAO_1">ICAO</gloss> Secretary-General to
                                    conduct an immediate investigation. We have the votes for a
                                    resolution along such lines;</p>
                                <p>—seek a tough UNSC resolution equally critical of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, but not as detailed as the
                                        <gloss target="#t_ICAO_1">ICAO</gloss> resolution seeking
                                    many cosponsors;</p>
                                <p>—seek no emergency special session of the General Assembly, but
                                    seek a new agenda item for the plenary, or as a second choice,
                                    committee consideration. We will raise the issue under existing
                                    agenda items in committees, consulting with allied and friendly
                                    delegations;</p>
                                <p>—work for a good resolution at the New Delhi conference of the
                                    World Tourism Organization in early October;</p>
                                <p>—raise the issue in the UNESCO Executive Board, IPU and
                                    Subcommission on Human Rights.</p></quote>
                            <p>International Court of Justice direct adversary proceedings would
                                have only symbolic value since the Soviets have not accepted the
                                ICJ’s mandatory jurisdiction. We may, however, wish to demand that
                                the Soviets enter into a special agreement with us for referral of
                                this case to Court if only to have the Soviets publicly reject
                                impartial scrutiny of their action. An advisory opinion proceeding
                                is also possible but has many disadvantages for <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> interests.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Demonstrate and Encourage Resistance to
                                Soviet Intimidation</p>
                            <p>The <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> cites the objective of
                                bolstering the confidence of our Asian friends. Central to any
                                effort to support NE Asian nations in their resistance to Soviet
                                intimidation will be the necessity to demonstrate consistency and
                                steadiness in U.S. diplomatic policies and security presence within
                                the region. In large part, this would represent a continuation of
                                policies and programs already in train, though these could be
                                highlighted as locally appropriate by specific U.S. statements and
                                actions. We should bear in mind, however, that regional anti-Soviet
                                sentiment could be undercut by too explicit or vigorous U.S.
                                encouragement.</p>
                            <quote><p>—A basic theme of the President’s visit to the East Asian
                                    region later this fall will be a reaffirmation of the American
                                    commitment to the peace and stability of the region. The <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss> incident will inevitably
                                    increase the force and importance of the President’s
                                    statements.</p>
                                <p>—In Japan, we must continue close consultations with the <gloss target="#t_GOJ_1">GOJ</gloss>—both on immediate questions
                                    related to the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss> incident as
                                    well on the longer-term coordination of our national policies
                                    towards the Soviet Union, letting the <persName corresp="#p_NY_1">Nakasone</persName> government take the
                                    lead in any capitalizing on domestic anti-Soviet feelings.</p>
                                <p>—With the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>, we should follow
                                    through with the Secretary of Defense’s visit and the easing of
                                    technology transfer requirements, but, <pb facs="0390" n="349" xml:id="pg_349"/> given China’s own strong condemnation, we
                                    do not need to underscore for Beijing the implications of Soviet
                                    behaviour in the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss>
                                    incident.</p>
                                <p>—With the ROK, our short-term requirement will be to continue
                                    close consultations with Seoul, while over the longer-term we
                                    will need to provide continuing assurances of the firmness of
                                    our security commitment, including our readiness to support
                                    Korea’s considerable defense efforts and our intention to
                                    maintain the U.S. troop presence in Korea.</p></quote>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Confidence-Building Measures.</p>
                            <p>Since the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss> incident was one in
                                which improved communications channels could well have been used, we
                                should:</p>
                            <quote><p>—Renew through diplomatic channels at a high-level our
                                    proposals to the Soviets for consideration at a Washington
                                    follow-on meeting of communications improvements beyond solely
                                    the Hotline upgrade; and</p>
                                <p>—Simultaneously publicize our call to the Soviets for expanded
                                    communications for the prevention of such incidents,
                                    specifically citing the <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss>
                                    tragedy, underscoring the U.S. flexibility in exploring various
                                    proposals, and noting previous Soviet assertions that such
                                    measures were unnecessary.</p></quote>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Public Diplomacy.</hi> In addition to the extensive
                                media coverage and public affairs support for the U.S. position
                                given to date by <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>, the Agency
                                plans several steps in the immediate future:</p>
                            <quote><p>—<gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> will maintain an
                                    intensified broadcast schedule to the Soviet Union in several
                                    languages;</p>
                                <p>—the incident will continue to be a prominent item for all <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> language services;</p>
                                <p>—public affairs guidances reflecting and supporting
                                    Administration policy have been and will be sent to <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> posts;</p>
                                <p>—Agency foreign press centers in Washington and New York will
                                    continue to arrange interviews, press backgrounders, or
                                    on-the-record briefings for the foreign press on the
                                    incident.</p>
                                <p>—We must bear in mind the sensitivities and perceptions of our
                                    Asian allies, particularly Japan. This should include
                                    consultation with our allies, not only to keep them informed,
                                    but to offer an opportunity for them to join in our
                                efforts.</p></quote>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Congressional Strategy.</hi> We are working on a
                                draft text of a joint Congressional resolution. We do not anticipate
                                any difficulty in passage when Congress returns September 12. The
                                effort already begun to keep Congress fully informed through
                                briefings will continue, but with an expanded focus to include those
                                committees of both Houses dealing with tourism and aviation as well
                                as foreign affairs, armed services, and intelligence. The State
                                Department is continuing its briefings of key staffers prior to the
                                reconvening of Congress. Once Congress reconvenes on September 12,
                                we will offer formal briefings for members on the event itself and
                                on the actions we are taking and considering.</p>
                            <pb facs="0391" n="350" xml:id="pg_350"/>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Outstanding Issues.</hi> The <gloss target="#t_KAL_1">KAL</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_IG_1">IG</gloss> has surfaced two issues for
                                future decisions:</p>
                            <quote><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Abrogation of the bilateral <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> Civil Aviation Agreement.</hi> Those who
                                    argue for abrogation believe it is a small but necessary step to
                                    demonstrate our revulsion, particularly in view of the actions
                                    we are asking other countries to take. Further, if the U.S. ever
                                    decides to initiate service, termination of the bilateral would
                                    not pose a further substantial obstacle to restoring service.
                                    Others prefer to keep the Agreement in place as a basis for
                                    reestablishing a more normal civair relationship if conditions
                                    should permit. These argue that abrogation could be portrayed as
                                    going farther than other countries (those that suspended
                                    operations temporarily, for example) and could be used as an
                                    indication that the U.S. was intent upon a confrontation with
                                    the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>.</p>
                                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Whether a subsequent <gloss target="#t_CAB_1">CAB</gloss> order should suspend a)
                                        relations of foreign carriers with Aeroflot, even within the
                                        U.S. or b) carrier relations with Aeroflot wholly outside
                                        the territory of the U.S.</hi> Some argue that we should
                                    refrain from any punitive action against foreign carriers at
                                    least as long as there is some basis to hope that these
                                    carriers, or their national governments, will take these actions
                                    on their own. Such action at this point could seriously
                                    compromise our chances of obtaining the cooperation of our key
                                    Allies in measures against Aeroflot. Others believe that this is
                                    a necessary step, and that failure to face it would make us look
                                    weak.</p></quote>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Future Action</hi>. The <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> states that the duration of punitive action is
                                dependent upon Soviet willingness “to honor essential standards of
                                aviation safety,” and directs work to achieve censure in <gloss target="#t_ICAO_1">ICAO</gloss> “with reinforcing measures at
                                    <gloss target="#t_ICAO_1">ICAO</gloss> to be pursued.” We are
                                now examining existing <gloss target="#t_ICAO_1">ICAO</gloss>
                                commitments to determine how they can be strengthened, and develop
                                appropriate recommendations. If the existing measures are adequate
                                and the problem is enforcement, we should also examine whether it is
                                in our interest to propose new arrangements providing for
                                international punitive sanctions in the event a state fails to meet
                                its obligations under the existing Convention.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>