<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-03-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-03-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="202" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d202">
                        <head>202. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RR_1">Reagan</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d202fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>, Sensitive and Super Sensitive Documents, Lot
                                92D52, March 1–30, 1984. Secret; Sensitive. In a March 26 covering
                                memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HJT_1">Howe</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KJH_1">Kelly</persName> wrote: “In accordance with
                                your instructions, we have reworked both versions of the memorandum
                                to the President on arms control. The major difference between them
                                is that the first version at Tab A addresses <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> alone, while the version at Tab B briefly mentions
                                other areas of arms control as well. The argument for the latter is
                                that the Soviets have indicated that movement in other areas could
                                help with resumption of nuclear arms control talks.” <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> signed the memorandum at
                                Tab B, which was sent by special courier to the White House on March
                                27 at 7:30 a.m. in preparation for the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meeting that afternoon.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1984-03-27">March 27, 1984</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Arms Control in 1984</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>This is a critical year for arms control. In the United States, voters
                            will choose between two very different visions of how to conduct the
                            process. In the Soviet Union a new leadership faces a choice between
                            continuing to stress propaganda aspects of arms control or returning to
                            the more serious and confidential discussions of an earlier period. It
                            will be an important year for our European Allies, who are just emerging
                            from the trauma of <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> deployment, who
                            face major uncertainties about the future policies of both Moscow and
                            Washington, and who must respond to strong demands from their own
                            publics to revitalize the East-West dialogue.</p>
                        <p>Thus far, the Soviets have maintained a tough line on the central nuclear
                            arms control issues, continuing to assert that a resumption of <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> negotiations is impossible without major U.S.
                            concessions. They have expressed skepticism over your call for a more
                            constructive dialogue. Their reaction is dictated by a number of
                            factors. First, they have taken a self-acknowledged political defeat on
                                <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>, which will take time to
                            absorb. Second, their leadership situation, uncertain for half a decade
                            as <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> weakened, only to be
                            replaced by an ill <persName corresp="#p_AY_1">Andropov</persName> and
                            now by <persName corresp="#p_CK_1">Chernenko</persName>, still seems to
                            be evolving. Finally, the Soviets must balance their probable preference
                            for a Democratic victory in November against their clear incentives to
                            negotiate seriously before the elections in view of the likelihood that
                            they will be dealing with you for four more years.</p>
                        <p>Suspicious of our motives, <persName corresp="#p_CK_1">Chernenko</persName> in his letters to you has nonetheless
                            expressed a cautious interest in testing our seriousness about arms
                            control dialogue. Thus, while stonewalling on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>/<pb facs="0777" n="736" xml:id="pg_736"/><gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>, the Soviets have indicated a
                            willingness to move ahead bilaterally on several lesser matters,
                            underscoring their interest in <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss>,
                                <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_TTBT_1">TTBT</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ASAT_1">ASAT</gloss> and hinting at
                            a compromise between our respective positions at the Stockholm <gloss target="#t_CDE_1">CDE</gloss> conference. They have stressed various
                            possible declaratory measures as well. In doing so, they have suggested
                            that progress on these issues could lead them to initiate a substantive
                            dialogue on the more basic problems, including nuclear arms control.</p>
                        <p>Some of these Soviet offers (such as a no-first-use of nuclear weapons
                            pledge) would clearly be to our disadvantage and are non-starters. In
                            other areas, the development of new Western proposals are already
                            underway; we should be in a position to present initiatives to the
                            Soviets in the Vienna <gloss target="#t_MBFR_1">MBFR</gloss> talks and
                            the Geneva <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> negotiations in the coming
                            weeks. We have interagency groups examining questions related to outer
                            space arms control and the limited nuclear testing bans and expect to
                            continue our bilateral exchanges with the Soviets on the fringes of the
                                <gloss target="#t_CDE_1">CDE</gloss> in Stockholm. Specific
                            opportunities for progress in some of the fields may become
                            possible.</p>
                        <p>We should clearly recognize the difficulties involved and not put
                            ourselves in the position of rewarding Soviet intransigence. We do not
                            see the likelihood of a major breakthrough in either <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> in the near future. Nonetheless, as <persName corresp="#p_HAA_1">Art Hartman</persName> has noted, the leadership
                            situation in Moscow and accompanying Soviet policy decisions has not yet
                            been finalized. It is possible, for instance, that we may see a more
                            activist <persName corresp="#p_CK_1">Chernenko</persName> if he is
                            elected to the Chairmanship of the Presidium later this spring. Because
                            we cannot predict the course of Soviet action with any certainty, it
                            would be a mistake to build our strategy solely on the likelihood of the
                            Soviets adopting a more positive approach. It would be equally
                            self-defeating for us to assume in the current situation that the
                            Soviets will make no move at all this year. We need to be prepared to
                            deal quickly and effectively with either prospect.</p>
                        <p>If we find that the Soviets are not disposed to take more than minor
                            steps forward with us this year, you ultimately may want to move beyond
                            our current emphasis on confidential diplomacy to enunciate publicly a
                            vision of U.S. arms control policy for your second term. Such a
                            declaration, which might contain new initiatives, would be an effective
                            response to the political pressures which inactivity on nuclear arms
                            control will inevitably engender as the year progresses. At the same
                            time, such a statement would set the Western agenda for 1985 and could
                            pave the way for a resumption of nuclear negotiations in the new year,
                            both in perception and reality.</p>
                        <p>In sum, we must be ready to engage in serious, substantive arms control
                            discussions whenever—and indeed whether—the Soviets signal they are
                            ready to resume business. I know there are those who feel that our best
                            tactic with the Soviets, with our Allies, and with our <pb facs="0778" n="737" xml:id="pg_737"/> public is to rest upon our arms control
                            record of the past three years, call upon the Soviets to return to
                            Geneva, and emphasize non-compliance and the difficulties of
                            verification. They would argue we should refrain from putting forward,
                            or even looking internally at, any new steps until the Soviets do so.
                            There is logic to this approach—why should we negotiate with ourselves
                            when our arms control objectives are correct and our arms control
                            principles are sound? There is also a certain emotional appeal—the
                            Soviets walked out; why should we make concessions to bring them back? I
                            subscribe to the logic and reject any notion that we should—or need
                            to—compromise any of our basic goals. At the same time, however, one
                            must examine the effect of this approach upon the three audiences we
                            must seek to influence.</p>
                        <p>For the Soviets, this is the most convenient U.S. strategy, the one that
                            plays best to the strengths of their own position, and which puts the
                            least pressure upon them for change. Under such an approach the Soviets
                            would not be forced to react to new U.S. initiatives, their
                            inflexibility would not be revealed anew, and their accusations of U.S.
                            inflexibility would, over time, be given added weight by some.</p>
                        <p>For our Allies, this approach creates the greatest incentive for
                            uncoordinated initiatives on their part to build bridges to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, and to suggest ways to get the
                            nuclear negotiations back on track. Europe’s Foreign Ministers (<gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>
                            and Portugal) and heads of state (France) are already booking their
                            reservations in Moscow. The flurry of such visits throughout 1984 will
                            create its own momentum for new initiatives.</p>
                        <p>Finally, such a stand pat approach, if it is to work, requires that we
                            persuade our public throughout the balance of this year that the Soviets
                            will accept in this Administration’s second four-year term those arms
                            control arrangements which they refused to adopt in the first. This will
                            be a difficult case to make. The Soviets will not give us any help.</p>
                        <p>The evolution through 1984 of our arms control strategy obviously must
                            depend upon a number of factors, including Congressional pressures on
                            the defense budget and strategic modernization program, Allied actions,
                            and the Soviet response to our current overtures. It will require that
                            our approach retain a degree of flexibility, that we continue our quiet
                            exploration of possible new steps in <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>, and that we
                            look closely at possible areas for movement on selected secondary issues
                            as well.</p>
                        <p>We need not make a decision on the details of any new approach at this
                            time. I feel strongly, however, that we should not, by ceasing our
                            preparations now, rob you of the ability to make such a decision at some
                            appropriate moment in the future.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>