<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-04-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="208" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d208">
                        <head>208. Information Memorandum From the Acting Assistant Secretary of
                            State for European and Canadian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KJH_1">Kelly</persName>) and the Director of the Bureau of
                            Politico-Military Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HJT_1">Howe</persName>)
                            to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d208fn1">Source:
                                Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George
                                    Shultz</persName> Papers, Box 2A, 1984 Arms and Arms Control,
                                Mar.–May. Secret; Sensitive. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_DC_1">Dunkerley</persName>; cleared by Gordon, Dobbins, and Dean.
                                Brackets are in the original.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1984-04-05">April 5, 1984</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss>–137: U.S. Nuclear Arms
                                Control Strategy for 1984</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The White House has issued an <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss><note n="2" xml:id="d208fn2">See <ref target="#d206">Document
                                206</ref>.</note> (attached) setting out the President’s decisions
                            on our nuclear arms control strategy based on the March 27 <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> discussion.<note n="3" xml:id="d208fn3">See <ref target="#d203">Document 203</ref>.</note>
                            On the whole, the thrust of the <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss>
                            is favorable to us and can be used to support our continuing efforts to
                            move forward on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and other arms
                            control issues.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Continuing Approaches to the Soviets:</hi> In an
                            apparent bow to <gloss target="#t_OSD_1">OSD</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> cites several times the virtues of
                            our current positions and states: “we will not compromise our principles
                            by chasing expedient agreement.” At the same time, however, it also
                            notes that we should “use every appropriate avenue to explore ways . . .
                            to bridge the distance between the requirements of our principled
                            positions and the legitimate concerns of the Soviet Union,” specifically
                            citing trade-offs.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Priority Study of <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>
                                Options:</hi> To that end, the <gloss target="#t_SACPG_1">SACPG</gloss> is directed not only to flesh out our current
                            proposal, but to complete its evaluation of “options that could under
                            certain conditions bridge [U.S.-Soviet] differences” by May 5. In this
                            connection, the <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> notes that while
                            the previous arms control mistakes should not be repeated, “if elements
                            of previous agreements put in the right context meet our needs, we
                            should not ignore them”—an implicit rejection of the <gloss target="#t_OSD_1">OSD</gloss> argument that the Framework concepts
                            of State, <gloss target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss> are too similar to <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> II.<note n="4" xml:id="d208fn4">See
                                    <ref target="#d185">Document 185</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_CK_1">Chernenko</persName>
                                Letter:</hi> A draft letter is requested for Presidential review by
                            April 7; it is tasked in general terms to cite again the flexibility of
                            our position, express our readiness to explore trade-offs, and replay
                            our readiness for constructive dialogue on <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss>.</p>
                        <pb facs="0797" n="756" xml:id="pg_756"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Other Arms Control Items:</hi> The <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> states the draft <gloss target="#t_CW_1">CW</gloss> treaty will be tabled before the end of
                            the current <gloss target="#t_CD_1">CD</gloss> round. It states ongoing
                            work on nuclear testing, space-related issues and additional <gloss target="#t_CBM_1">CBMs</gloss> should be “brought to a timely
                            conclusion.”</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Protecting Against Disclosure:</hi> The <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> emphasizes the need to protect the
                            ongoing <gloss target="#t_SACPG_1">SACPG</gloss> work from unauthorized
                            disclosure, and, in this regard, states that Congressional testimony,
                            consultations with our Allies, background statements to the press and
                            public statements are to be cleared in advance through <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">Bud McFarlane</persName>.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Public Affairs Handling:</hi> The President calls for
                            intensified efforts to explain publicly the U.S. arms control record,
                            setting an April 14 deadline for a detailed plan to do so (we would note
                            in this regard, State already has underway a special arms control
                            speakers’ course at FSI; you are, moreover, scheduled to give a major
                            arms control address to the League of Women Voters in early June).</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Coordination of the Administration Position:</hi>
                            Finally, citing the need for “clarity and coherence,” you are designated
                            as “the Administration’s chief spokesman on arms control.” Testimony and
                            all major statements are to be cleared through <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>