<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>223. Letter From Soviet General Secretary Chernenko to President to President
                    Reagan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1984-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1984-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Strategic arms</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Strategic balance</term>
                    <term ref="recqaxqBsfTYVWHfR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034367"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cruise missiles</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="recNHstTN4mCmPSgR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011305"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Missile defense</term>
                    <term ref="rec5leqjXNtlx0kjy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85096156"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Outer space</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="rec3U9TKkW5rS0s3i" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">Freedom of navigation</term>
                    <term ref="rectadvRz4QZmc1z7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="chemical-and-bacteriological-warfare"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007509"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemical weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recszCCT27rtvcYPJ" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009004888"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Search and rescue</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="223"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                <head>223. Letter From Soviet General Secretary <persName corresp="#p_CK_1"
                        >Chernenko</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RR_1"
                        >Reagan</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d223fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Executive Secretariat, Head of State File,
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>: General Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_CK_1">Chernenko</persName> (8490695) (2 of 2). Secret;
                        Sensitive. <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> presented
                            <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> with this letter and the
                        attached talking points during their June 12 meeting (see <ref
                            target="#d224">Documents 224</ref> and <ref target="#d225">225</ref>). A
                        routing slip indicates <persName corresp="#p_RR_1">Reagan</persName> was
                        given this package during his June 14 daily briefing.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1984-06-06"
                            >June 6, 1984</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Mr. President,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p>In connection with your letter<note n="2" xml:id="d223fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d211">Document 211</ref>.</note> I would like to express some
                    thoughts in continuation of our exchange of views with you.</p>
                <p>I, of course, took note of the pledge of commitment to the lessening of tensions
                    between our countries made by you in the handwritten addition to your letter. In
                    turn, I can affirm once again what I wrote in my first letter to you—namely,
                    that it has been and continues to be our wish that there be a turn toward
                    steady, good relations between the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and
                    the <gloss target="#t_USA_1">USA</gloss>.<note n="3" xml:id="d223fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d183">Document 183</ref>.</note> As a matter of fact, the
                    numerous specific proposals submitted by our side, including those proposals put
                    forward in my letters to you, have been aimed at reaching that very
                    objective.</p>
                <p>As regards interpreting a certain period in the history of our relations, about
                    which you had already written once before, here our views differ. We have
                    presented our point of view in this regard, so I will not repeat myself. I will
                    note, however, that one side’s having military superiority or seeking such
                    superiority cannot be perceived by the other side as an indication of good
                    intentions. There can be only one indication—a willingness to conduct affairs as
                    equals, a willingness reflected in practical policies. The position of the
                    Soviet Union in this regard is clear and precise: we are not seeking
                    superiority, but we will not allow superiority over us. I do not see anything
                    here that should be unacceptable to the United States, if one wants stability
                    and a lessening of tensions. It is from a position of equality that it is
                    possible to agree on really mutually-acceptable solutions, when neither side can
                    have reason to believe that it is making unilateral concessions.</p>
                <p>I thought it necessary to point this out, having in mind the way in which the
                    intentions of the Soviet Union are interpreted in your letter. I cannot agree
                    with this. This has already been stated on our side in the past. But since you
                    return again to the question of intentions and how they can be perceived, I will
                    express a few opinions, illustrating them with specific examples.</p>
                <pb facs="0850" n="809" xml:id="pg_809"/>
                <p>If one is to sum up what on many occasions has been publicly stated by you and
                    other representatives of the Administration, one concludes that the only
                    situation that would be acceptable to the United States would be one in which it
                    was militarily ahead of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>. The fact of
                    the matter, however, is that such a situation has not been and is not acceptable
                    to us. In this respect we have experience—bitter experience. The history of our
                    relations, especially in the postwar period, has seen quite a few complications
                    too. Quite a few attempts have been made to exert political, economic, and even
                    military pressure on us.</p>
                <p>Let us take the current situation. There is, it seems, an American idiom “to turn
                    the table.” Try to look at the realities of the international situation from our
                    end. And at once one will see distinctly that the Soviet Union is encircled by a
                    chain of American military bases. These bases are full of nuclear weapons. Their
                    mission is well known—they are targeted on us. Nothing like it can be found
                    around your country.</p>
                <p>And what about the fact that entire regions of the globe have been proclaimed
                    spheres of American vital interests? And not only proclaimed, but made the
                    object of a U.S. military presence. And this is done, among other places, at our
                    very doorstep. And again we, for our part, are not doing anything like it. What
                    conclusions should we draw from this as to the intentions of the U.S.? I believe
                    the conclusions readily present themselves. Such an approach is nothing other
                    then a hypertrophied idea of one’s interests in which the legitimate interests
                    of others are completely ignored, an effort to gain, to put it mildly, positions
                    of privilege at the expense of the other side. This approach is not compatible
                    with the objective of ensuring stability. On the contrary, such an approach as a
                    matter of policy objectively helps to create and sustain tensions.</p>
                <p>Or let us take strategic arms. Here, too, no claims can be directed toward the
                    Soviet Union. The fact that there is rough parity between the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_USA_1">USA</gloss>
                    and, in a wider sense, between the Warsaw Pact and <gloss target="#t_NATO_1"
                        >NATO</gloss>, can be disputed by no expert familiar with the situation. The
                        <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>–2 Treaty was a reflection of this
                    fact. It was not the end of the road, and we did not consider it as such. But
                    the merit of the treaty was, among other things, that it established, I would
                    say, with mathematical precision the strategic balance that has evolved.</p>
                <p>Your military experts can tell you that the Soviet Union has done nothing to
                    upset this balance. At the same time we see what kind of attitude is displayed
                    toward the Treaty by the other side. Is it not the criterion by which to judge
                    its intentions?</p>
                <p>The same applies as well to medium-range nuclear forces in Europe. I will recall
                    only that it was we who offered to reduce their number to the minimum on the
                    side of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NATO_1"
                        >NATO</gloss>. In response, “Pershings” and cruise missiles are appearing
                    near our bor<pb facs="0851" n="810" xml:id="pg_810"/>ders. How would you regard
                    it, Mr. President, had something similar happened with respect to the U.S.? I
                    believe that your assessment of the intentions of the other side under the
                    circumstances could only be one—as regards both the other side’s approach to
                    negotiations and the essence of its intentions.</p>
                <p>But even under these circumstances we have displayed and continue to display
                    utmost restraint. The response we were forced to take, in terms of its scope and
                    character, has not gone beyond the limits necessary to neutralize the threat
                    posed to us and our allies. Moreover, we propose to return to the initial
                    situation and, instead of further unleashing an arms race, to address ourselves
                    in a decisive fashion to curbing the arms race, and to radically limiting and
                    reducing nuclear arms. This is far from imposing conditions. As a matter of
                    fact, what is unfair about the two sides cancelling those measures whose effect
                    was to heighten the level of nuclear confrontation and, conversely, to lessen
                    global security? There can be nothing unfair or damaging for either side in
                    this. A return to the previous situation in the present circumstances would
                    constitute forward movement by both sides toward stabilizing the situation,
                    toward the practical renewal of the entire process of limiting nuclear weapons
                    that is of decisive importance for the future of international relations and for
                    peace as such.</p>
                <p>So far, however, we see no indication that the American side proceeds from such
                    an assumption. Regrettably, nothing new on this major issue of the day can be
                    found in your letter either. I say this not for the sake of polemics, but rather
                    in the hope that you will still find it possible to appreciate the way out of
                    the extremely grave situation that we are suggesting.</p>
                <p>From my correspondence with you, Mr. President, as well as from previous
                    correspondence, one can conclude that, in general terms there seems to be an
                    understanding on your part that there are a number of important questions
                    concerning the problem of security which require solutions and where joint
                    efforts by our two countries are necessary.</p>
                <p>For my part, in my last message I specifically mentioned several of these
                        questions.<note n="4" xml:id="d223fn4">See <ref target="#d197">Document
                            197</ref>.</note> Let me remind you that these included renouncing the
                    construction of large-scale anti-ballistic missile defense systems, entering
                    into negotiations on preventing the militarization of outer space and on banning
                    anti-satellite weapons, a freeze on nuclear weapons, resuming talks on a
                    complete and comprehensive ban on nuclear tests, and some other measures. In
                    other words, we are not for dialogue in a general sense between our two
                    countries, but propose to fill it with concrete, weighty substance. We are
                    convinced that practical <pb facs="0852" n="811" xml:id="pg_811"/> movement in
                    these and other directions and mutual determination to achieve practical results
                    would fundamentally ease the situation in our relations and throughout the world
                    in general. The degree of trust would increase significantly.</p>
                <p>But we have not received a response to these proposals that would enable us to
                    say that the United States is prepared for such concrete actions. I will not
                    make a judgment as to what is the problem here, but I am convinced that,
                    seriously speaking, there is no good reason and, moreover, no justification for
                    avoiding the solution of problems that can play a decisive role in determining
                    the road the world will take in the near future. Awareness of this is growing on
                    the part of the public and the leaders of many states. Graphic evidence of this
                    is the recent appeal by the leaders of six countries from four continents to the
                    governments of the nuclear powers.<note n="5" xml:id="d223fn5">See <hi
                            rend="italic">Documents on Disarmament, 1984</hi>, pp. 420–421.</note>
                    Mr. President, this appeal is a very serious reminder, to our countries as well,
                    of the enormous responsibility they bear for the destinies of the world and
                    mankind. Our common duty is to respond to this appeal honestly, without delay,
                    and through concrete actions. For its part, the Soviet Union is prepared for
                    it.</p>
                <p>In addition to those of our proposals already mentioned, I would also like to
                    draw your attention to additional areas of possible cooperation in the interests
                    of strengthening peace. One of these is the limitation of naval activity and
                    naval armaments. This problem is very urgent; it is no coincidence that the
                    United Nations has attached such importance to it as well. We have specific
                    ideas on what could be done to reduce the growing tensions on the high seas, to
                    ensure freedom of navigation and the safety of international sea communications.
                    We have spoken in favor of discussing this problem within the framework of the
                    Geneva Conference on Disarmament or in separate multilateral negotiations.
                    Taking into account the role of our countries, we also propose to discuss this
                    set of questions on a bilateral basis. We would like to know your opinion on
                    this score.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, the Warsaw Pact countries recently made a proposal to <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> countries to begin multilateral
                    consultations on the subject of concluding a Treaty on mutual non-use of
                    military force and the maintenance of peaceful relations. The essence and the
                    importance of the idea of such a Treaty are well known. Attention to this
                    proposal has been growing from the moment of its introduction. And here our two
                    countries could also play an important part. We are ready to study any ideas the
                    American side might have on this question.</p>
                <pb facs="0853" n="812" xml:id="pg_812"/>
                <p>The Soviet Union will, furthermore, do everything in its power to promote
                    agreements on the problem of banning chemical weapons and on the reduction of
                    armed forces and armaments in Central Europe. Our delegations in Geneva and
                    Vienna will be prepared to cooperate with American representatives. It goes
                    without saying that, within the framework of these fora, we shall also express
                    in detail our views on recent positions advanced by the American side. However,
                    I have to note that the overall impression—and not only ours—is that these
                    positions do not constitute a constructive contribution to the work already done
                    in these fora.</p>
                <p>Recently the Soviet Union introduced at the Stockholm conference a concrete and
                    carefully balanced document directed at attaining a really significant
                    agreement, which would fundamentally strengthen security on the European
                    continent. In preparing this document, we took into account the opinions
                    expressed at the first round of the conference as well as in the course of
                    bilateral consultations, including those with American representatives. We would
                    like to expect that in Stockholm the United States will take a position that
                    would make possible agreement on mutually acceptable solutions.</p>
                <p>As it has already been pointed out on our part in correspondence with you, we
                    favor a bilateral exchange of opinions on regional matters. Our Ambassador is
                    instructed to present to the Secretary of State more specific considerations on
                    these and some other matters. Here I find it necessary to stress the main point:
                    the need for restraint, for refraining from actions—no matter what their
                    motives—which could only intensify dangerous tensions in various regions and
                    make difficult the achievement of a just political settlement. The world has
                    proven more than once that it is a hundred times more difficult to extinguish a
                    fire than to prevent it. To remember this is in everyone’s interests.</p>
                <p>I do not want to conclude this letter on a negative note, but in view of some of
                    the remarks in your letter, I must point out that introduction into relations
                    between states of questions concerning solely domestic affairs of our country or
                    yours does not serve the task of improving these relations—if this is our goal.
                    I wish questions of such a nature did not burden our correspondence, which both
                    of us, as I understand it, value.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CK_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">K. Chernenko</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0854" n="813" xml:id="pg_813"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="strong">Talking Points From Soviet Ambassador <persName
                                corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                        </hi>
                        <note n="6" xml:id="d223fn6">No classification marking. A note in the upper
                            right-hand corner written by an unknown hand reads: “talking
                            points”</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian">undated</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">First</hi>. I would like to draw your attention to the
                        fact that the solution of major questions, including new ones, set forth in
                        the message of <persName corresp="#p_CK_1">K.U. Chernenko</persName> would
                        be of principal importance from the point of view of improving the
                        Soviet-American relations and the international situation in general. Thus
                        we again confirm in the practical way the line toward conducting a
                        businesslike exchange of views with the Government of the United States with
                        the aim of achieving constructive agreements on a wide range of issues in
                        the Soviet-American relations. It concerns both the questions of
                        strengthening security and ending the arms race as well as the area of
                        bilateral relations.</p>
                    <p>Up till now, however, the American side acts in such a way that we do not see
                        its readiness to go forward in practice to improving our relations, though
                        quite a few words about such readiness have been said recently. The repeated
                        promises to do something positive are not followed by anything tangible as
                        yet.</p>
                    <p>At the same time it is often said that the American side allegedly introduces
                        some concrete proposals, but the Soviet side reacts to them negatively. It
                        is stated even as if we consciously counteract to some constructive efforts
                        by the Administration and do not want progress in our relations. It is
                        obvious for us that the situation is just the opposite. It is not clear,
                        however, why a deliberately false impression is created, if, indeed, there
                        is a desire to find a common language.</p>
                    <p>It is known, by whose initiative the Soviet-American relations were brought
                        to such a mediocre shape. If an unbiased approach is used, there cannot be
                        two opinions. Nevertheless, not once we proposed to revive our relations and
                        to fill them with concrete contents. These questions have been discussed
                        with the Secretary of State many times.</p>
                    <p>If businesslike views in this regard were expressed by the American side, and
                        promises of such nature were given many times, then, by all means, we would
                        consider them with due attention.</p>
                    <p>We wish only that it could be something specific and not simply symbolics
                        presented as something positive in the way of formal extension of some
                        agreements which are in fact not working. For example, we are told for some
                        time already that a question of allocating fishing <pb facs="0855" n="814"
                            xml:id="pg_814"/> quotas for us is being considered. But at the same
                        time, as we find out, measures of the opposite nature are being taken. Is it
                        not the decision on limiting the activity of the joint Soviet-American
                        fishing company on the Pacific coast that speaks about it?</p>
                    <p>There are attempts to attribute to us the desire to curtail the contacts and
                        ties, including the area of scientific and cultural exchanges. However, the
                        situation here as well rests on the position and acts of the American side.
                        It rests on its unreadiness to solve the question of providing security for
                        Soviet participants in such exchanges and normal conditions for their
                        presence in the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>. It is a question of
                        principle and it cannot be avoided. It is again proven by recent hostile
                        acts against Soviet people in the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>. The
                        American side also avoids the solution of the question concerning the
                        practical side of such exchanges, connected with the resumption of the
                        flights by the Aeroflot to the United States.</p>
                    <p>Now the American side keeps some kind of rosters of questions, replies to
                        which should be given by this or that side. But even if to approach the
                        situation with this formal point of view, it still turns out that we
                        constructively develop our position and introduce concrete proposals, while
                        the American side limits itself to promises to think about something and to
                        consider something.</p>
                    <p>On the Soviet side there is no lack of desire and efforts to really improve
                        the situation in our relations. It is up to the American side.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>. Questions of security.</p>
                    <p>The Soviet position on the question of <hi rend="italic">preventing the
                            militarization of outer space</hi> has been already presented quite
                        clearly to the Secretary of State. We proceed from the idea that formal
                        negotiations on this matter should start between especially appointed
                        delegations. The organizational side of such negotiations should be
                        discussed through the diplomatic channels. In other words now the question
                        is this: is the American side prepared to solve this urgent problem, which
                        long ago has already gone because of its importance beyond the framework of
                        the Soviet-American relations only?</p>
                    <p>A proposal has been introduced by the Soviet side that both sides should
                        reject the very idea of developing and deploying <hi rend="italic"
                            >large-scale antiballistic missile defense systems</hi>. We would be
                        ready to discuss the means of realization of this proposal—for example to
                        discuss the substance and the form of appropriate statements, the order of
                        making them public, etc.</p>
                    <p>Our position with regard to the question of the treaties of 1974 and 1976 on
                        the limitation of underground nuclear explosions is also clear. The treaties
                        were carefully worked out including the part concerning control. They were
                        signed and should be put in force. There is no necessity in any additional
                        interpretation of any provisions of the <pb facs="0856" n="815"
                            xml:id="pg_815"/> treaties. The questions, should the sides have them in
                        the future as the treaties are in force, could be considered and solved in
                        accordance with relevant provisions of those treaties themselves. The issue
                        now is only whether the American side is or is not willing to ratify these
                        treaties. We favor doing this and as far as possible without further
                        delay.</p>
                    <p>The Soviet side attributes great significance <hi rend="italic">to the
                            banning of chemical weapons, to the reduction of the armed forces and
                            the armaments in Central Europe</hi>. These questions must be solved.
                        Our specific considerations in connection with the latest proposals of the
                        United States concerning these questions will be stated by the Soviet
                        representatives at the appropriate forums.</p>
                    <p>However, it may be said even now that the American position, unfortunately,
                        does not give hope. We would like to think that the American side will
                        properly take into account those observations and remarks which we and not
                        only we shall express in Geneva and Vienna. There the Soviet delegations
                        will be ready to maintain contact with the American side as before.</p>
                    <p>As for discussing these questions in some other manner, now there is no basis
                        for that in view of the character of the latest American proposals.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Third</hi>. Regional problems. We repeatedly expressed our
                        readiness to discuss with the American side regional problems named by it
                        and other ones.</p>
                    <p>In this connection we are prepared to listen to the possible considerations
                        of the American side in response to what has already been said by us on the
                        South of Africa, and also on the situation in the Middle East and on the
                        conflict between Iran and Iraq. In the future, depending on the progress
                        made, we could agree to hold certain special meetings of our representatives
                        as well. We do not exclude this.</p>
                    <p>As we have already pointed out, it is especially important that restraint be
                        shown, no actions which could exacerbate the situation be taken. This
                        concerns the above mentioned as well as other regions.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Fourth</hi>. The Soviet side intends in the nearest future
                        to propose the date of the next round of negotiations <hi rend="italic">on
                            the convention line in the Bering sea</hi>. We expect that the American
                        side has analyzed the results of the previous round and could take the
                        position which would enable us to come to a just and mutually acceptable
                        solution of this question.</p>
                    <p>We also intend to convey in the near future our views concerning the
                        negotiations on <hi rend="italic">cooperation in the search and rescue
                            operations in the Northern part of the Pacific ocean</hi>.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
