<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>295. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                    European and Canadian Affairs (Burt) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of
                    State Shultz</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">295</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1984-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1984-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Arms control</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="295"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d295">
                <head>295. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                    and Canadian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BR_4">Burt</persName>) to Secretary
                    of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d295fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>, Sensitive and
                        Super Sensitive Documents, Lot 92D52, October 1984 Super Sensitive
                        Documents. Secret; Sensitive. A more complete account of this meeting is in
                        telegram 325166 to Moscow, November 1. (Department of State, Central Foreign
                        Policy File, Electronic Telegrams, D840700–0675)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1984-10-25">October 25, 1984</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Soviet Embassy Views on <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-Soviet
                        Relations</item>
                </list>
                <p>Soviet Embassy Minister-Counselor <persName corresp="#p_SV_1">Isakov</persName>
                    invited <persName corresp="#p_PMR_1">Mark</persName> to a working lunch today.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SV_1">Isakov</persName>’s main point seemed to be a
                    desire to explore our thinking on the general direction of the relationship
                    after the elections. In preparing for your meeting with <persName
                        corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> tomorrow, I thought it might be useful
                    for you to know the points <persName corresp="#p_SV_1">Isakov</persName> made
                    today.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SV_1">Isakov</persName> said that <persName
                        corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> had concluded after his talks here that
                    there is now a bridge to the future, an opening for progress. He said that
                    Moscow wants to move ahead. As one indication, he provided the dates for our
                    next round of non-proliferation talks in Moscow (November 28–30, which are
                    acceptable to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KRT_1">Kennedy</persName>).</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SV_1">Isakov</persName> said that Moscow was not clear
                    what we had in mind with the umbrella talks. For example, he asked “on a
                    personal basis”, could there be umbrella space talks, while offensive arms and
                    other matters were being addressed in diplomatic channels. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PMR_1">Mark</persName> responded that our concept of umbrella
                    talks was broader than just space, but that we were in general flexible about
                    how to proceed and in particular that you would be prepared to discuss with
                        <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> how we could use diplomatic
                    channels to move ahead with more concrete discussions on arms control.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SV_1">Isakov</persName> drew particular attention to the
                    recent <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> editorial which noted that our <gloss
                        target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> deployments are a barrier to <gloss
                        target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> negotiations.<note n="2" xml:id="d295fn2">In
                        telegram 13761 from Moscow, October 25, the Embassy reported: “An
                        authoritative unsigned article in <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> October 25
                        justifies Soviet refusal to resume nuclear arms talks. It claims that
                        Western leaders are talking about negotiation in order to deceive the public
                        but are doing nothing to ‘clear away the obstructions’ to those talks. It
                        stops short of calling directly for withdrawal of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1"
                            >NATO</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_LRINF_1">LRINF</gloss> missiles, but maintains that
                        changes in Western policies are needed before negotiations can resume.”
                        (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams,
                        D840682–0817)</note> He said that this is a problem for them, how could we
                    get started when they have stated publicly for so long that the deployments make
                    negotiations <pb facs="1111" n="1070" xml:id="pg_1070"/> impossible. For that
                    reason, <persName corresp="#p_CK_1">Chernenko</persName> had proposed that we
                    get started first on some lesser, easier matters. Moscow could not understand
                    why it was so difficult for the United States to state it would not be the first
                    to use nuclear weapons. Obviously, in an actual war, regardless of what it had
                    said, each side would use the weapons necessary if it found itself losing. In
                    response, Mark said that this was a nonstarter but of the items <persName
                        corresp="#p_CK_1">Chernenko</persName> mentioned, <gloss target="#t_TTBT_1"
                        >TTBT</gloss> was possible if the Soviets were prepared to show some
                    flexibility.</p>
                <p>Finally, <persName corresp="#p_SV_1">Isakov</persName> noted that the United
                    States had said a number of times that we have ideas on offensive arms but we
                    never say what they are. He noted that it is difficult to move ahead on the
                    basis of the previous <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> positions as set forth
                    in Geneva because they are so unacceptable. If the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> side has ideas, it should give the details to the Soviets and
                    this would make a major difference. <persName corresp="#p_PRMH_1"
                        >Palmer</persName> explained that it was not reasonable for the Soviet side
                    to ask us to show our cards before it was clear that the Soviet side was ready
                    for serious detailed talks. <persName corresp="#p_SV_1">Isakov</persName> then
                    asked what would be the Secretary’s response if <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> asked for our specific ideas. Mark said that he did not
                    know, but that it would be better if <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> said that <persName corresp="#p_GA_1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> and the rest of the Soviet leadership were prepared for
                    serious talks and wanted to know our specific ideas.</p>
                <p>Mark asked whether we might begin to see some progress on such human rights
                    concerns as <persName corresp="#p_SN_1">Shcharanskiy</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_SA_1">Sakharov</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_SV_1"
                        >Isakov</persName> noted that he is not in the <gloss target="#t_KGB_1"
                        >KGB</gloss> and therefore did not know anything about these matters. He
                    indicated that it would be better for us to pursue this through our channels to
                    the <gloss target="#t_KGB_1">KGB</gloss> like Vogel in Berlin.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d295fn3">Reference is to Wolfgang Vogel. See <ref target="#d219fn5"
                            >footnote 5, Document 219</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KM_1">Max Kampelman</persName> was also told recently in
                    Moscow that it would be better not to work through <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> and the Soviet Foreign Ministry but rather through
                    special channels.<note n="4" xml:id="d295fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KM_1">Kampelman</persName> met with human rights
                        activists, dissidents, and refuseniks in Moscow from September 15 to 19.
                        While no record of this message regarding <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName> and a private channel was found, it seems likely
                        that a message could have been conveyed during this September visit to
                        Moscow. (Telegram 12028 from Moscow, September 20; Department of State,
                        Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams, D840600–0727) During
                        September, October, and November 1984, <persName corresp="#p_KM_1"
                            >Kampelman</persName> visited European capitals to discuss Soviet human
                        rights violations. See <ref target="frus1981-88v41#d74">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XLI, Global
                            Issues II, Document 74</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
