<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>39. Memorandum From Secretary of State Shultz to President to President
                    Reagan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1983-04-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1983-04-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7XCpI38AIhVpLJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Regional issues</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Confidence-building
                        measures</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recFKwbJC7hOq07wX" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation">Comprehensive Test Ban</term>
                    <term ref="recFUg0jqFk2tUZ15" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Nuclear testing</term>
                    <term ref="recfABRQvTqVuIjoA" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1983-04-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1983-04-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="39"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d39">
                <head>39. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                        >Shultz</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RR_1"
                        >Reagan</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d39fn1">Source: Reagan Library, Executive
                        Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Country File, Europe and
                        Soviet Union, <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> (04/05/83–04/07/83).
                        Secret; Sensitive. <persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clark</persName>’s stamp
                        appears on the memorandum, indicating he saw it.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1983-04-07">April 7, 1983</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Meeting with <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>—April 7,
                            1983<note n="2" xml:id="d39fn2">The Subject line incorrectly dated the
                            meeting as April 7, 1982.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Pursuant to our discussion of yesterday,<note n="3" xml:id="d39fn3">See <ref
                            target="#d37">Document 37</ref>.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_WCW_1">Cap Weinberger</persName> and I met today with
                        <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> for approximately 70
                        minutes.<note n="4" xml:id="d39fn4">See <ref target="#d38">Document
                        38</ref>.</note> We covered the full range of our established agenda for
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-Soviet relations—arms control, regional
                    issues, human rights, and bilateral relations. The tone of the meeting was
                    businesslike and generally constructive, and there will be a number of follow-up
                    actions to be undertaken in coming days.</p>
                <pb facs="0169" n="128" xml:id="pg_128"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">I.</hi> Arms Control:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Confidence-Building Measures:</hi> Cap began by outlining the
                    new proposals for confidence-building measures you have recently approved,
                    emphasizing that our purpose is to reduce the risk of a misunderstanding or
                    accident that could lead to the inadvertent outbreak of war. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> expressed interest in our proposals
                    and asked a number of substantive questions. Cap and I agreed to provide him
                    more details in writing tomorrow and asked that he seek an early response from
                    his government. <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> suggested that
                    our public announcement of the proposals—now scheduled to go to Congress April
                    11—be delayed until Moscow has had an opportunity to respond privately. Cap and
                    I noted that our proposals are, in part, a response to Congressional interest
                    and that their transmission to the <persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Hill</persName>
                    could not be held up for long. Nevertheless, we agreed to see whether a short
                    delay is possible and again urged <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> to seek a quick response from his government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_INF_1"
                            >INF</gloss>:</hi> I noted that we continue to look for ways to make
                    progress and suggested that <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> and
                    I meet separately with <persName corresp="#p_NP_1">Paul Nitze</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_REL_1">Ed Rowny</persName> during the current break
                    between rounds. In offering these meetings, I emphasized that their purpose
                    would not be negotiation but clarification and informal discussion of our
                    respective positions. After noting that he hoped these discussions would not be
                    simply a sterile rehash of our respective positions in Geneva, <persName
                        corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> agreed to go ahead with these
                    meetings.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_TTBT_1">TTBT</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_PNET_1"
                            >PNET</gloss>:</hi> I reminded <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> that we had made a serious proposal to negotiate
                    stronger verification provisions for the Threshold Test Ban Treaty (<gloss
                        target="#t_TTBT_1">TTBT</gloss>) and Peaceful Nuclear Explosions Treaty
                        (<gloss target="#t_PNET_1">PNET</gloss>), and that we had been disappointed
                    by the negative Soviet response. <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    responded with the usual Soviet line that we should first ratify the treaties as
                    they are and then consider whether additional verification measures might be
                    needed. He also asked whether we intended to continue observing the 150 kiloton
                    limit on underground nuclear tests provided for by the unratified <gloss
                        target="#t_TTBT_1">TTBT</gloss>. Finally, he reiterated the suggestion that
                    we resume trilateral negotiations for a Comprehensive Test Ban.</p>
                <p>In response, I noted that we have no plans, at present, for underground tests
                    above the 150 kt. level, but that serious concerns about verification precluded
                    our ratification of the <gloss target="#t_TTBT_1">TTBT</gloss> until these
                    concerns were addressed. I added that the Soviet emphasis on a <gloss
                        target="#t_CTB_1">CTB</gloss> seemed to reflect a desire to run before
                    walking in the field of nuclear testing limitations. Finally, I stated that
                    Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BR_4">Rick Burt</persName> would be
                    calling in one of <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>’s deputies
                    soon on our <gloss target="#t_TTBT_1">TTBT</gloss> proposal. I urged that the
                    Soviet side reconsider our proposal. <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> offered to consider whatever information we provided on
                    our proposal.</p>
                <pb facs="0170" n="129" xml:id="pg_129"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">II.</hi> Human Rights</p>
                <p>After underscoring again the importance we attach to these issues, I told
                        <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> of your personal
                    appreciation for the positive Soviet actions in the Pentecostalist case.<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d39fn5">See <ref target="#d34">Document 34</ref>.</note>
                    Emphasizing the need to keep up the momentum toward final resolution of this
                    problem, I told <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> of your letter
                    to the Pentecostalists in the Embassy and <persName corresp="#p_ROC_1">Olin
                        Robison</persName>’s visit to Moscow. I noted that we had proceeded quietly
                    in this case, as is our general intention in handling human rights issues, and
                    pressed <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> for Soviet action on
                    other “Madrid” issues, such as the level of Jewish emigration.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">III.</hi> Regional Issues</p>
                <p>Noting that Soviet misconduct in regional conflicts had been a major source of
                    tension in our relationship, I pressed <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> for concrete Soviet actions on Afghanistan, in southern
                    Africa, and other regional trouble spots. I reiterated our readiness to play a
                    positive role and told him that <persName corresp="#p_HAA_1">Art
                        Hartman</persName> has instructions to see <persName corresp="#p_GA_1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> on Afghanistan and the Middle East. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> suggested that we identify three or
                    four priority areas for discussion on regional issues and develop specific
                    proposals for solutions. I responded that we had tried to establish such a
                    dialogue, but that the talks had seemed to us more academic than operational.
                    Nevertheless, it would be difficult to move far in improving our relations
                    unless there was concrete evidence of Soviet action to meet our concerns on
                    these regional issues.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">IV.</hi> Bilateral Issues</p>
                <p>Having placed discussion of our bilateral relations in this overall context, I
                    informed <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> of your decisions to
                    extend the fisheries agreement for one year<note n="6" xml:id="d39fn6">See <ref
                            target="#d38fn6">footnote 6, Document 38</ref>.</note> and to propose
                    negotiations for a new grains <gloss target="#t_LTA_1">LTA</gloss>.<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d39fn7">See <ref target="#d32">Documents 32</ref> and <ref
                            target="#d35">35</ref>.</note> Noting that the decision on a grains
                        <gloss target="#t_LTA_1">LTA</gloss> had been a particularly difficult one
                    for us, I told <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> that we intended
                    to make an announcement on Saturday. <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> was noncommittal on a new <gloss target="#t_LTA_1"
                        >LTA</gloss> and again noted that we were planning a public announcement
                    before the Soviets could reply to our proposal. I replied that it would be
                    extremely difficult to maintain the confidentiality of this decision while
                    waiting for a Soviet reply. <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName> did
                    not say when we might expect a reply, but later told <persName corresp="#p_BR_4"
                        >Rick Burt</persName> that our proposal might have to be put on the weekly
                    Politburo agenda—thus delaying a Soviet reply until at least the end of next
                    week. While making no commitments <pb facs="0171" n="130" xml:id="pg_130"/>
                    about the timing of our announcement, I pressed <persName corresp="#p_DA_1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> to seek an early reply from Moscow.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Next Steps:</p>
                <p>I will be taking the following actions to follow-up on today’s meeting:</p>
                <p>1. <persName corresp="#p_BR_4">Rick Burt</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_PR_1">Richard Perle</persName> will call in an appropriate
                    official from the Soviet Embassy tomorrow to convey more information in writing
                    on our <gloss target="#t_CBM_1">CBMs</gloss> proposals and to press for an early
                    Soviet response. Cap and I will confer on whether to delay transmission of the
                    proposals to Congress for a few days in order to give the Soviets an opportunity
                    to reply. Rick will also convey to the Soviet Embassy further information on our
                        <gloss target="#t_TTBT_1">TTBT</gloss> proposal as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>2. I will schedule a meeting with <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    next week to discuss either <gloss target="#t_START_1">START</gloss> or <gloss
                        target="#t_INF_1">INF</gloss> with <persName corresp="#p_NP_1"
                        >Nitze</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_REL_1">Rowny</persName>.</p>
                <p>3. We will take another look at possibilities for dialogue on regional issues in
                    light of <persName corresp="#p_DA_1">Dobrynin</persName>’s suggestion that we
                    identify three or four issues for priority work.</p>
                <p>4. On the grains <gloss target="#t_LTA_1">LTA</gloss>, I believe we should try to
                    give the Soviets a reasonable opportunity to respond before we make a public
                    announcement, despite the difficulties this will cause us. Senators Dole and
                    Percy have agreed to hold off on their legislation. I have already informed
                        <persName corresp="#p_BJR_1">Jack Block</persName> of your decision and
                    asked that it remain confidential for at least a few days. We have therefore
                    told the Soviets that we intend to postpone an announcement for a few days.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
