<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-09-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="326" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d326">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/2344<hi rend="superscript">10/25</hi>
                        </note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern
                                Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-09-15">September 15, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: In your talk with the President
                            this afternoon in regard to the Japanese proposals, you may wish to
                            indicate that the Japanese Government’s explanation, communicated to Mr.
                            Grew on September 13,<note n="27" xml:id="d326fn27">See memorandum by
                                the Ambassador in Japan, September 13, 1941, <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_620">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol.
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 620</ref>.</note> of its
                            proposals of September 6<note n="28" xml:id="d326fn28">
                                <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_608">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 608</ref>.</note> do not appear
                            to dispose effectively of difficulties on any of the points concerning
                            which issues arose in your informal conversation with the Japanese
                            Ambassador. On some points the statements of the Japanese Government are
                            equivocal and ambiguous and some of the statements indicate a
                            disposition on the part of the Japanese Government to narrow down and
                            limit the application of fundamental principles with which the Japanese
                            profess in the abstract to agree. The Japanese proposals are much
                            narrower than one would have been led to expect from the broad gauge
                            assurances given in the statement communicated to the President by the
                            Japanese Ambassador on August 28.<note n="29" xml:id="d326fn29">
                                <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_573">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 573</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Japanese Ambassador has not yet come in with the Japanese
                            Government’s explanation and we are working on drafting comments <pb facs="0458" n="450" xml:id="pg_450"/> that might be offered to the
                            Japanese Ambassador in response thereto. The comments would be in the
                            nature of comparing the earlier Japanese assurances of a broad character
                            with the narrower commitments on specific questions as contained in the
                            Japanese proposals of September 6 and in the subsequent explanations
                            offered by the Japanese Government.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>