<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Joseph W. Ballantine to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d448</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">448</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-11-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="448"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d448">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/2540<hi rend="superscript">15/35</hi>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Joseph W.
                            Ballantine</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-11-17">November 17,
                            1941</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: In connection with the meeting which
                    will take place with the Japanese on November 18, it is suggested that you may
                    care to bring up the following points:</p>
                <p>(1) As Mr. Kurusu knows, we have gone over very exhaustively in our conversations
                    the various questions involved in the proposed settlement between the United
                    States and Japan and have examined these questions from every angle. It will be
                    helpful to have a fresh point of view on the matter and for this reason we would
                    like to hear all the suggestions which Mr. Kurusu may have in mind to offer.</p>
                <p>What Mr. Kurusu may have to say in response to your drawing him out in this way
                    might take up most of the time of the meeting. Opportune occasion may arise,
                    however, for you to bring up any or all of the following points:</p>
                <p>(2) We have noted the contents of the two documents which the Japanese Ambassador
                    presented on November 17.<note n="31" xml:id="d448fn31">
                        <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_739">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan 1931–1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 739</ref> and <ref
                            target="frus1931-41v02#pg_739">740</ref>.</note> In one of these
                    documents the Japanese Government confirms as expressing its general purpose
                    certain excerpts from a statement of the Japanese Government delivered to the
                    President on August 28.<note n="32" xml:id="d448fn32">
                        <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_573">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 573</ref>.</note> While we still do not
                    see the need of the qualifying phrases, the statement of the Japanese Government
                    serves to clarify the point that the present Japanese Government’s attitude in
                    this respect is the same as that of the previous Japanese Government. In the
                    other document there was expressed the willingness of the Japanese Government to
                    apply the principle of political stabilization to the entire Pacific area and to
                    omit the word “southwestern” in the text of Article VI of its proposal of
                    September 25,<note n="33" xml:id="d448fn33">For latter, see <ref
                            target="frus1931-41v02#pg_637">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., pp. 637</ref>, <ref
                            target="frus1931-41v02#pg_640">640</ref>.</note> We wish to inquire
                    whether the Japanese Government would be willing to omit the word “southwestern”
                    throughout the document.</p>
                <p>(3) We shall await with interest the reactions of the Japanese Government to our
                    proposal of November 15 on economic policy.<note n="34" xml:id="d448fn34">
                        <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_736">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 736</ref>.</note> We feel that if we
                    can reach agreement on that aspect of a Pacific settlement it will be helpful
                    toward enabling us to dispose of the other outstanding questions.</p>
                <pb facs="0614" n="606" xml:id="pg_606"/>
                <p>(4) The Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs has on various occasions spoken to
                    the American Ambassador of the latest Japanese proposals as representing
                    material concessions on the part of the Japanese Government and has intimated
                    that this Government was not adopting a concessive attitude. From the outset of
                    our conversations we have talked about a comprehensive and consistent peaceful
                    program. We have neither asked for anything for ourselves nor have we felt that
                    from the long-swing interests of both countries there was any room for
                    compromise on the principles essential to establishing and maintaining such a
                    comprehensive peaceful program. Entirely apart from this aspect of the question,
                    however, it is not clear what the Japanese Government has in mind when it says
                    that its recent proposals represent concessions.</p>
                <p>(5) It would be a very fine thing at this time if Japanese industry could be put
                    actively to work in pursuance of the program for the promotion of peace. There
                    are many ways in which, if we could reach an agreement with Japan on the
                    economic program, Japanese factories could be put into operation for the
                    production of commodities needed by the United States and by other peaceful
                    countries in connection with this program. The problem of demobilizing large
                    numbers of armed forces and making room for the men thus demobilized in peaceful
                    pursuits always presents difficulties, but it is felt that the situation now is
                    exceptionally advantageous for such demobilization in view of the great existing
                    need throughout the world for the products of industry.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J[<hi rend="smallcaps">oseph</hi>] W. B[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >allantine</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
