<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1941v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d499</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">499</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1941-11-28T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1941-11-28T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-11-28T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-11-28T12:00:00-05:00" n="499"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d499">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.94/2490a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-11-28T12:00:00-05:00"
                            >November 28, 1941—noon</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>793. In the light of the attitude of Admiral Nomura and Mr. Kurusu when they were
                    handed on November 26 for consideration the document described in a separate
                        telegram<note n="19" xml:id="d499fn19">Telegram No. 784, November 26, not
                        printed; for document, see <ref target="frus1931-41v02#pg_768">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 768</ref>.</note> and of such
                    indications as we have cumulatively had of the general attitude of the Japanese
                    Government, it appears that the discussions up to the present time have not yet
                    afforded any basis which gives much promise of a satisfactory comprehensive
                    settlement. It is of course too early to adopt any definitive opinion whether
                    the discussions will continue or will lapse, but the probability that they may
                    lapse should not be lost sight of.</p>
                <p>The existence of such probability makes it appear advisable that we give some
                    advance consideration to various problems which may as a consequence arise in
                    connection with our Foreign Service establishments in Japanese territory. As
                    lapse of the conversations might result in withdrawal of our diplomatic and
                    consular representation from Japan, it would seem to us that, without any
                    intention of being alarmist or of too hastily envisaging serious contingencies,
                    this question should be brought to your attention so that you may have it well
                    in mind in case it should become necessary for the Department to consult you in
                    regard to the making of arrangements for the packing of official and personal
                    effects and the expeditious handling of other matters which would be involved in
                    the closing of our Embassy and Consulates. It is, of course, desired that all
                    phases of the matter be considered confidential and that discussion of it be
                    kept to a minimum.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
