<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1941-12-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1941-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="572" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d572">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Pacific War/1519¼</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Minister to Switzerland</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily in the
                            United States</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1941-12-13">December 13, 1941</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Upon the receipt of a confidential report to the effect that Ambassador
                            Nomura<note n="48" xml:id="d572fn48">Adm. Kichisaburo Nomura.</note> and
                        the Naval Attaché of the Japanese Embassy<note n="49" xml:id="d572fn49">Capt. Ichiro Yokoyama.</note> would commit hari kari and that this
                        would be played up by Tokyo as murders, I called by direction upon the Swiss
                            Minister<note n="50" xml:id="d572fn50">Charles Bruggmann.</note> shortly
                        after noon today and inquired whether he had as yet received instructions
                        from his government to assume the protection of Japanese interests in this
                        country. Mr. Bruggmann replied that while he had been instructed to assume
                        the protection of Japanese interests in the Philippines and Samoa, he had as
                        yet no instructions with regard to the continental United States. The
                        Minister also stated that he had not as yet received word from his
                        government of the consent of the Japanese Government to the protection of
                        American interests by Switzerland in Japan although the Japanese radio had
                        announced that the Japanese Government had given their consent.</p>
                    <p>The Minister indicated that although he had not received instructions to
                        assume the protection of Japanese interests here he was quite prepared to
                        handle any matters informally.</p>
                    <p>I then informed the Minister on behalf of Mr. Long<note n="51" xml:id="d572fn51">Breckinridge Long, Assistant Secretary of
                            State.</note> that the Department had received a report to the effect
                        that Ambassador Nomura and the Japanese Naval Attaché intended to commit
                        hari kari and that this would be called murder by Tokyo which might result
                        in attacks on the American diplomatic personnel and in that event lead to
                        unforetellable incidents. Mr. Long had asked me to say to the Minister that
                        if he felt like doing so we would be very glad if he would call on
                        Ambassador Nomura, inform him of this report and advise us of the result of
                        his conversation.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Bruggmann stated that he would be happy to carry out Mr. Long’s request
                        and that he would report the results of his visit to the Japanese Ambassador
                        as promptly as possible.</p>
                    <p>About four o’clock Mr. Bruggmann called upon Mr. Long and said that he had
                        gone to the Japanese Embassy where he had been received by the
                            Minister.<note n="52" xml:id="d572fn52">Kaname Wakasugi.</note> After a
                        brief discussion about the protection of Japanese interests, regarding which
                        the Minister was no better informed, Mr. Bruggmann asked if he might see
                        Ambassador Nomura. The Ambassador then appeared and when it seemed that the
                        Minister <pb facs="0757" n="749" xml:id="pg_749"/> proposed to remain Mr.
                        Bruggmann asked if he might see the Ambassador alone. The Minister then
                        left.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Bruggmann explained to Mr. Long that he had had some difficulty in
                        understanding the Japanese Ambassador as, perhaps for reasons of language,
                        it was difficult to know whether he spoke in the past, present or future
                        tense. However, after he had informed the Ambassador of the report which had
                        reached the State Department, Mr. Nomura had made reply by explaining that
                        he had done his best in an endeavor to maintain friendly relations between
                        the United States and Japan and that his conscience was clear on this point
                        but that, of course, the decision rested with the god Heroun(?).</p>
                    <p>Mr. Bruggmann then had endeavored to clear up this somewhat cryptic and
                        possibly evasive reply. In reply the Ambassador had referred to the fact
                        that in the last war the Japanese Minister to Russia and the Russian
                        Minister to Japan had each returned to his own country.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Bruggmann had appealed to the humanitarian instincts of the Ambassador
                        but had not been able to obtain any definite assurance from him that he
                        would not commit hari kari. However, Mr. Bruggmann had received a somewhat
                        quieting impression of his conversation and, after explaining the hesitation
                        he had felt in presenting the matter to the Ambassador and his hope that he
                        had done so with every appropriate discretion, Mr. Nomura had smiled and
                        their parting had been friendly.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>L[<hi rend="smallcaps">eland</hi>] H[<hi rend="smallcaps">arrison</hi>]</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>