<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-01-11T02:31:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="110" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d110">
                    <head>110. Editorial Note</head>
                    <p>During the first weeks of 1968, Japan and the United States implemented those
                        portions of the <persName>Johnson</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_SE3">Sato</persName> Communiqué aimed at advancing local autonomy and
                        preparing for the eventual reversion of the Ryukyus. By an exchange of Notes
                        the Japanese and the U.S. Governments established the Advisory Committee to
                        the High Commissioner of the Ryukyu Islands effective January 19. The
                        three-member committee, comprised of a representative from the United
                        States, Japan, and the Ryukyus, was responsible for advising and making
                        recommendations to the High Commissioner on social, economic, and other
                        matters within his purview in preparation for reversion as well as to reduce
                        and/or eliminate social and economic differences between the Islands and
                        Japan proper. The committee met for the first time on March 1 in Naha.
                        Copies of the Notes are in airgram A–939, January 22. (National Archives and
                        Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 19 RYU IS)</p>
                    <p>In addition, on January 31 President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> signed an amendment to Executive Order No. 10713
                        Providing for Administration of the Ryukyu Islands authorizing the popular
                        election of the Chief Executive <pb facs="0291" n="255" xml:id="pg_255"/> of
                        the Ryukyu Islands. The amendment went into effect as of the next election,
                        which was to be held on November 10, 1968. The President’s statement is
                        printed in <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United
                            States: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B. Johnson</persName>,
                            1968</hi>, page 123; the text of the Executive Order is in <hi rend="italic">The Weekly Compilation of Presidential Documents, page
                            117, the Federal Register</hi> (33 F.R. 2561), as well as the <hi rend="italic">Code of Federal Regulations</hi> (3 CFR, 1968 Comp., page
                        99).</p>
                    <p>Implementation of Paragraph IX of the <persName>Johnson</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_SE3">Sato</persName> Communiqué addressing cooperation in
                        the peaceful exploration of outer space also began in 1968. In January
                        Ambassador <persName>Johnson</persName> received authorization to open
                        negotiations on a program enabling the United States to supply advanced
                        equipment and technology to Japan in exchange for an agreement certifying
                        their application would be for peaceful goals, in conformity with INTELSAT,
                        and subject to third country oversight. The proposal was designed to benefit
                        Japan, which wanted to develop a space program, as well as the United
                        States, which stood to gain financially by the sale and licensing of
                        technology. (Memorandum to <persName>Rostow</persName>, January 4; <hi rend="italic">
                            <persName>Johnson</persName>
                        </hi> Library, National Security File, Country File, Japan, Vol. VII) In
                        late April 1968 the Japanese Diet passed legislation creating a Space
                        Development Commission and set forth basic laws, which conformed to those
                        proposed by the United States, covering the Japanese space efforts.
                        (Telegram 7873 from Tokyo, April 30; National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, SP 1–1 JAPAN–US) In mid-year
                        the Chair of the Commission, Naotsugu Nabeshima, accepted the invitation of
                        the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission to visit Washington. Between July 13 and
                        17 Nabeshima met with Atomic Energy Commission members as well as officials
                        at the National Air and Space Agency. The meetings allowed both sides to
                        exchange information and prepare for further cooperation in the
                        technological realm. Documents focusing on that visit and its results are
                        ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 JAPAN.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>