<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-06-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-06-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="125" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d125">
                    <head>125. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of the Army (<persName corresp="#p_MGD1">McGiffert</persName>) to the Deputy Secretary of
                        Defense (<persName corresp="#p_VCR1" type="to">Vance</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d125fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                            Center, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>/OASD/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: FRC 330 73 A 1250, Okinawa 452. Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-06-14">June 14, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>B–52 Sortie Rate</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0322" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/>
                    <p>In <gloss target="#t_JCSM1">JCSM</gloss>–333–68<note n="2" xml:id="d125fn2">Not printed. (Ibid., Viet 385.1 ARC LIGHT)</note> the Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff recommend that the ARC LIGHT sortie rate be continued at 1800 per
                        month through December 1968, and that in accomplishing this B–52s continue
                        to be stationed at Kadena Air Base on Okinawa. It is noted that a rate of
                        1710 sorties could be sustained without basing on Okinawa. This is offered
                        as a possibility if the “Korean contingency” is resolved and if the
                        political impact of basing on Okinawa “becomes overriding.”</p>
                    <p>I remain persuaded, as I have stated in previous memoranda to you,<note n="3" xml:id="d125fn3">Among which was <persName corresp="#p_MGD1">McGiffert</persName>’s memorandum of April 15 containing the same
                            argument. (Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>/OASD/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: FRC 330
                            73 A 1250, Okinawa 452)</note> that the continued basing of B–52s on
                        Okinawa has a potential political impact which could seriously affect our
                        administration of the Ryukyus and our relationship with Japan. I have
                        particularly in mind the effect which this situation might have on the
                        November 1968 elections for the legislature and the Chief Executive of the
                        Government of the Ryukyu Islands. If that election comes out unfavorably to
                        us we face the prospect of greatly increased pressure on our administration
                        and bases in Okinawa.</p>
                    <p>The administration elected in the Ryukyus this November will be in office
                        from 1969 through 1972. In those years we can expect that we will have to
                        reach some accommodation with the Government of Japan regarding the return
                        of Okinawa to Japanese administration and the future of our bases there.
                        Those negotiations promise to be most difficult. Our position, and the
                        position of the Government of Japan, will be made much more difficult if
                        there is conflict between our administration on Okinawa and the local
                        government there.</p>
                    <p>My Deputy for International Affairs recently returned from a trip to Japan
                        and Okinawa, where he discussed the election prospects at length with
                        knowledgeable political observers in both areas. To a man these observers,
                        who are favorably disposed to our policies and who desire to see the
                        election come out in a manner satisfactory to us, indicated that the
                        continued presence of the B–52s on Okinawa is a substantial liability to the
                        United States and to the conservative party which we hope will win the
                        election. At Tab A is a recent report from Okinawa, noting that the
                        incumbent Chief Executive continues to press this view.<note n="4" xml:id="d125fn4">Not further identified. The sentiments of Chief
                            Executive <persName corresp="#p_MS1">Matsuoka</persName> on the issue,
                            however, are briefly reported in telegram HC–LN 814404 from the High
                            Commissioner, May 23. (National Archives and Records Administration, RG
                            59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 19 RYU
                            IS)</note> At Tab B<note n="5" xml:id="d125fn5">Not attached.</note> is
                        an excerpt from an April 1968 poll, conducted by a responsible organization
                        in Okinawa, which notes that 86% of the residents there are apprehensive due
                        to the stationing of B–52s at Kadena.</p>
                    <pb facs="0323" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/>
                    <p>We could also have a problem in Japan itself. At Tab C<note n="6" xml:id="d125fn6">
                            <ref target="#d120">Document 120</ref>.</note> is a paper which the
                        State Department Country Director for Japan recently sent to Bill
                            <persName>Bundy</persName>, assessing the Japanese political situation
                        and our relations with Japan. As noted there (page 4) the issue of Okinawa
                        is perhaps the major outstanding problem in U.S./Japanese relations, and an
                        incident involving the B–52s might precipitate a crisis within the governing
                        party of Japan, which has thus far behaved most responsibly with respect to
                        this problem.</p>
                    <p>Insofar as my particular concerns are involved, in question now at most are
                        90 sorties or 15 missions a month, a 5% reduction. I believe that carefully
                        weighed against the potential cost to our position in Okinawa and our
                        relations with Japan such a reduction should be directed. I understand that
                        in fact it may well be that 1800 sorties a month could be sustained from
                        basing at U Tapao and Guam only, by launching more sorties per aircraft per
                        month from U Tapao than are projected in the Joint Staff discussion of
                        alternatives. If this is correct, and if you decide to approve the continued
                        rate of 1800 sorties, I can certainly see no justification for continued
                        basing at Kadena which would override the political price we are paying.</p>
                    <p>Assuming that a decision is made which permits withdrawal of the B–52s from
                        Kadena prior to the Okinawan election, the timing of that withdrawal should
                        be as soon as possible.<note n="7" xml:id="d125fn7">Although the High
                            Commissioner appeared to support restricting or removing the B–52s for
                            political reasons, <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> was
                            strongly opposed to any such move, believing that only “free and
                            unrestricted use of these facilities for B–52 and other forces in the
                            general defense of the Pacific area and in pursuance of our strategy”
                            would allow U.S. forces to carry out its missions in the region.
                            (Telegram 161430Z from <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>, June
                            16; National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files
                            1967–69, DEF 15 RYU IS–US)</note> At the moment, the B–52 issue has been
                        temporarily overshadowed by the nuclear submarine-atomic waste issue flowing
                        from the <hi rend="italic">Swordfish</hi>’s visit to Sasebo and reflected
                        concern in Okinawa.<note n="8" xml:id="d125fn8">Newspaper articles seeming
                            to confirm officially and for the first time that the planes stationed
                            at Kadena were used to bomb North Vietnam further inflamed opposition to
                            the B–52s. (Telegram HC–LN 816605 from the High Commissioner, June 14;
                            ibid.)</note> But as the election comes closer, Ryukyuan pressures for
                        B–52 withdrawal will certainly be reasserted and will continue to rise. We
                        do not want to appear to be withdrawing under this kind of pressure any more
                        than can be helped. Hence the sooner the withdrawal, the better.<note n="9" xml:id="d125fn9">Despite similar recommendations from other quarters,
                            the planes were still based on Okinawa at the end of 1968. (Memorandum
                            to <persName>Bundy</persName>, September 11; ibid., DEF 12 US; letter to
                            Nitze, October 3; Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>/OASD/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: FRC 330 73 A 1250, Okinawa 452)</note>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MGD1">
                                <hi rend="strong">David E. McGiffert</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>