<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>98. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of State (Read)
                    to the President’s Special Assistant () to the President’s Special Assistant
                    (Rostow))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v29p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="98"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                <head>98. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of State
                        (<persName corresp="#p_RBH1" type="from">Read</persName>) to the President’s
                    Special Assistant (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1" type="to">Rostow</persName>)<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d98fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 7 JAPAN. Secret; Exdis. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SRL2">Sneider</persName>; cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BSD1">Berger</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-10-13">October 13, 1967</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE3">Sato</persName> Visit—Preparatory Meeting</item>
                </list>
                <p>A meeting in the White House is scheduled on October 16 at 4:00 p.m. to discuss
                    preparations for the visit of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_SE3"
                        >Sato</persName> on November 14–15.<note n="2" xml:id="d98fn2">Neither the
                        President nor <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> attended this
                        meeting. (<persName>Johnson</persName> Library, President’s Daily Diary, and
                        ibid., <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> Appointment Books, 1967)
                        President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> was given a copy of
                        this document along with a concise summary of its contents prepared by
                        Alfred Jenkins. (Ibid., National Security File, Country File, Japan, Visit
                        of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_SE3">Eisaku Sato</persName>,
                        November 14–15, 1967)</note> A considerable amount of work in spelling out
                    our objectives for this visit was done in preparation for the Cabinet level
                    talks in mid-September. For your background in preparing for the Monday meeting,
                    the key points on the visit are summarized below.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Setting:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SE3">Sato</persName>’s visit takes place at a time when
                    United States-Japan relations are at a high point. They are seriously clouded
                    only by the unresolved territorial issues of the Ryukyus and Bonins, but even
                    here there is recognition of the need to resolve these issues without acrimony
                    and with due regard to the problems involved for both countries and the need to
                    strengthen our bilateral relationship. <persName corresp="#p_SE3"
                        >Sato</persName> also comes to Washington holding strong domestic political
                    cards and with his economy booming. The only threat to his position and that of
                    friendly conservative ruling elements is serious mishandling of the Ryukyu and
                    Bonins issue.</p>
                <p>Finally, <persName corresp="#p_SE3">Sato</persName> has set the stage for his
                    Washington visit by a major swing throughout East Asia demonstrating Japan’s
                    pretentions for regional leadership with due sensitivity to residual local
                    apprehension regarding a revived “co-prosperity sphere.” During his travels,
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE3">Sato</persName> has voiced stronger support for
                    United States Vietnam policies and will <pb facs="0248" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"
                    /> have visited both Taiwan and South Vietnam, areas of particular political
                    sensitivity in Japan.<note n="3" xml:id="d98fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SE3">Sato</persName> traveled throughout Southeast
                        Asia during the autumn. In addition, <persName corresp="#p_MT3"
                            >Miki</persName> spoke before the America-Japan Society in Tokyo on
                        October 5, giving what the Embassy characterized as perhaps the “most
                        forthright public statement to date from high <gloss target="#t_GOJ1"
                            >GOJ</gloss> official in support U.S. policy in Vietnam.” The Embassy
                        continued by noting that <persName corresp="#p_MT3">Miki</persName>’s speech
                        coupled with <persName corresp="#p_SE3">Sato</persName>’s supportive
                        comments during his visit to Bangkok elevated the Japanese position toward
                        the Vietnam war to “new high level of moral support.” (Telegram 2300 from
                        Tokyo, October 5; National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59,
                        Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15–1 JAPAN)
                        Telegram 2289 from Tokyo, October 5, contains the complete text of <persName
                            corresp="#p_MT3">Miki</persName>’s speech. (Ibid., <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 1 JAPAN–US)</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Objectives:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In broad terms our objectives during the <persName corresp="#p_SE3"
                        >Sato</persName> visit look both to the past and to the future: <list>
                        <item>—We want and need to reaffirm Japan as our primary partner in
                            Asia.</item>
                        <item>—Looking to the future, we seek to convert this partnership into a
                            relationship in which the political and economic burdens of regional
                            responsibility are shared more fully.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Spelling out these objectives in more specific terms, we seek: <list>
                        <item>—A greater sense of Japanese commitment to securing free world
                            interests in the region and a more responsible attitude towards the
                            threat posed by the Chinese Communists.</item>
                        <item>—Further concrete expressions by Japan of regional leadership.</item>
                        <item>—Support on key United Nations issues and possibly a role in United
                            Nations peacekeeping in the Middle East if this materializes.</item>
                        <item>—Continued support and responsible action on Vietnam, with greater
                            economic aid to the Government of Vietnam.</item>
                        <item>—Adherence to the Non-Proliferation Treaty.</item>
                        <item>—Further substantial contributions on major East Asian economic
                            development programs, including the Asian Development Bank Special
                            Funds.</item>
                        <item>—Significant reduction in our bilateral balance of payments deficit
                            which results in part from increased military-related expenditures in
                            Japan during the Vietnam conflict.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Major Problems:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Our major problems during the visit will be twofold. First, we will need to
                    obtain, in more concrete terms, commitments from the Japanese on picking up a
                    greater share of the financial burden for regional assistance and redressing the
                    imbalance of our bilateral balance of payments. Secondly, we will need to work
                    out a formula for tidying over <pb facs="0249" n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> the
                    difficult territorial issues. The Japanese apparently recognize that we are not
                    now in a position to make any firm commitment on reversion of the Ryukyus, but
                    they want a “step forward”—the terms of which are still to be worked out. The
                    Japanese would, however, like a commitment on the early return of the Bonins, an
                    issue still to be resolved within our Government.<note n="4" xml:id="d98fn4">The
                        resolution of the reversion issue generated several high-level meetings and
                        various proposals and discussions in an effort to work out differences
                        between diplomatic and military interests and between U.S. and Japanese
                        positions. Documents tracing the evolution of decisions and agreements on
                        that and other issues prepared in advance of the <persName corresp="#p_SE3"
                            >Sato</persName> visit are ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                        JAPAN–US, ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 JAPAN–US, ibid.,
                            <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 17 JAPAN–US, ibid., <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 18 RYU IS, and ibid., <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 19 BONIN IS; and Washington National
                        Records Center, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>/OASD/<gloss
                            target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: FRC 330 72 A 2468, Okinawa, 323.3,
                        ibid., FRC 71 A 4546, 333 Bonin Islands; <persName>Johnson</persName>
                        Library, National Security File, Country File, Japan, Vols. VI and VII,
                        ibid., Visit of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_SE3">Eisaku
                            Sato</persName>, November 14–15, 1967, ibid., Country File—Addendum,
                        Japan, and ibid., Meeting Notes File, November 4, 1967—Meeting with Foreign
                        Policy Advisers.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName>James Walker</persName>
                        </hi>
                        <note n="5" xml:id="d98fn5">Walker signed for <persName corresp="#p_RBH1"
                                >Read</persName> above <persName corresp="#p_RBH1">Read</persName>’s
                            typed signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
