<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>150. Action Memorandum From the Acting Director of the Office of
                    International Scientific Affairs (Pollack) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary
                    of State Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recuHJAjI1jYKqz0s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145612"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Water resources</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recWpOYNUONIWKYCh" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85109354"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Explosion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-06-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-06-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="150"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                <head>150. Action Memorandum From the Acting Director of the Office of International
                    Scientific Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_PH7" type="from">Pollack</persName>)
                    to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d150fn1">Source: Department of State,<gloss
                            target="#t_SCI1">SCI</gloss> Files: Lot 68 D 383. No classification
                        marking. Drafted by Lightner (<gloss target="#t_SCI1">SCI</gloss>) and
                            <persName corresp="#p_PH7">Pollack</persName> and cleared by Kotschnig
                            (<gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>). Also sent to <persName
                            corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis Johnson</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-06-10">June 10, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Water for Peace Program</item>
                </list>
                <p>As you may recall, you and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_USL1">Udall</persName>
                    agreed last November to set up an interdepartmental committee to produce a
                    report recommending what the United States, with other nations, should do to
                    contribute to the solution of water problems throughout the world. (Tab B)<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d150fn2">Not attached; see <ref target="#d144fn5">footnote 5,
                            Document 144</ref>.</note> Interior chairs the committee and you named
                    me to represent the Department. A task force set up for the purpose has prepared
                    a draft report and our committee is now considering final recommendations. The
                    Interior Department is proposing that these recommendations be submitted by you
                    and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_USL1">Udall</persName> jointly to the
                    President. Since we will be at the final drafting within a few days, it would be
                    helpful to have your reactions at this time.</p>
                <pb facs="0302" n="272" xml:id="pg_272"/>
                <p>This endeavor goes back to a speech (Tab C)<note n="3" xml:id="d150fn3">Not
                        attached; see <ref target="#d144fn3">footnote 3, Document 144</ref>.</note>
                    the President made last October 7 at the Desalting Symposium in Washington in
                    which he announced the beginning of a Water for Peace program. This speech has
                    been the main source of guidance for the Interdepartmental Committee and its
                    Task Force. The essence of what he said was to call upon other nations to join
                    us in creating an “international crash program to deal with the world’s water
                    resources” and a special international water fund. He announced his intention to
                    convene within a year an international conference “to deal with all the world’s
                    water problems” and his support for international research programs and other
                    efforts to improve knowledge and skills in the water resources field.</p>
                <p>Our Committee has selected twelve from the comprehensive recommendations in the
                    draft report of the Task Force that seemed especially appropriate for priority
                    attention and action. (Tab A)<note n="4" xml:id="d150fn4">Not printed. The
                        recommendations included establishment of a Water for Peace office and
                        sponsorship of an international Water for Peace conference in May
                        1967.</note> In arriving at these, the following considerations were
                    relevant: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>We singled out community water supply for the direct personal use of
                            people as warranting high priority. This is also fully in line with the
                            emphasis in the President’s speech. However, we recognized that water
                            resources are only one important economic resource and that plans and
                            programs for water projects must be based on each country’s own broader
                            development needs.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>We found that in virtually all developing countries there is a lack of
                            understanding of many aspects of their water problems, lack of basic
                            data, lack of trained personnel and, in short, an inability to deal with
                            their problems. Hence, we placed a high priority on training, education
                            and related efforts to improve this situation.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Capital assistance will be required in larger amounts than in the
                            past, but in the immediate future existing international sources seem
                            adequate. We should be watchful to see that capital sources are
                            replenished if and when needed to finance expanded water development
                            projects. The obstacles to establishing a new international fund for
                            water projects at this time are formidable and it has not been included
                            in the initial program. If normal international sources are ever
                            inadequate, we should, of course, reconsider the idea and explore with
                            others the desirability of forming a special international water
                            fund.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Desalting has an especial appeal; it is dramatic; the United States
                            has a leading position in this field; large-scale projects might well
                            contribute to technological progress. We favor using this technique in
                            areas where it makes good economic sense. The relative costs of other
                                <pb facs="0303" n="273" xml:id="pg_273"/> methods of providing new
                            water must always be weighed. We realize that certain imponderables,
                            including political considerations, should be taken into account. Each
                            case should be judged on its individual merits.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Although the United States has done a good deal to assist other
                            nations to improve their water resources, it is in our interest to
                            follow through on President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                                >Johnson</persName>’s initiatives and to provide new leadership and
                            stimulus to efforts to solve the world’s water problems. International
                            water programs are closely related to food and health programs, in which
                            the United States is very active. We also would appear to have a
                            responsibility and an opportunity to be of all possible assistance in
                            this critical area. We should embrace the opportunity as a contribution
                            to our foreign policy objectives to help bring peace and well-being to
                            mankind.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>The United States is not only doing a big bilateral job through <gloss
                                target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> but it supports the multilateral water
                            programs carried out under the United Nations family and affiliated
                            international banking institutions. Yet our efforts and those of other
                            countries are not keeping pace with global needs. The water problem,
                            like the food problem, is partially the result of the population
                            explosion.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>It is tentatively estimated that the priority recommendations might
                            cost about $30 million the first year, $50 million the second year, and
                            might level off at about $90 million the third year. These are still
                            very rough estimates. We do not plan to suggest any specific year for
                            the first year, leaving the White House strategists to decide whether an
                            FY–67 Supplemental is desirable or practical.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>At the moment it is not clear what sort of draft legislation, including
                    appropriations, should be suggested to the President nor can I indicate very
                    precisely when the report will be in your hands. It is possible you may have it
                    by the end of June.</p>
                <p>In this memorandum I have tried to give you a brief picture of the course we are
                    following and some of the rationale behind it. I would appreciate an indication
                    as to whether you subscribe to the program as it is evolving.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that you</p>
                <p>1. Approve the priority recommendations at Tab A.<note n="5" xml:id="d150fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis Johnson</persName> approved this
                        recommendation on June 16.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">or</hi>
                </p>
                <p>2. Meet with <gloss target="#t_SCI1">SCI</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_IO1"
                        >IO</gloss> to discuss the Water for Peace Program.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d150fn6">No option was checked.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
