<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-01-06T08:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-01-06T08:45:00-05:00" n="187" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d187">
                        <head>187. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Iran</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d187fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Records of the Department of State, Central
                                Files, 1964–66, PET 6 IRAN. Confidential. Repeated to London.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-01-06T13:45:00+00:00">January 6, 1966,
                                1345Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>981. Sharp Decrease in Iran Oil Offtake. PriMin <persName corresp="#p_HAA1">Hoveyda</persName> summoned <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Ambassador <persName>Wright</persName> and me 6th to
                            complain that Iranian oil offtake dropped more than 200,000 barrels per
                            day in December. He said Shah and other <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> leaders suspect this is unwelcome retaliation on part
                            of oil Consortium for recent Kharg Island problem (A–415).<note n="2" xml:id="d187fn2">Airgram A–415 from Tehran is dated December 16,
                                1965. (Ibid., PET 1 IRAN) Iran and Iraq had recently clashed
                                militarily over Kharg Island, Iran’s primary offshore oil loading
                                terminus.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HAA1">Hoveyda</persName> went on to say Iran’s
                            vital plans for development will suffer if anticipated increases in oil
                            offtake do not materialize. Noting greater foreign exchange shortage
                            would result <persName corresp="#p_HAA1">Hoveyda</persName> said Iran
                            would dislike to have to shift to heavier reliance on Eastern Bloc
                            countries for commerce and possibly even arms.</p>
                        <p>Making clear this is issue outside jurisdiction of <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>, I took occasion to recall frequent
                                <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> cautioning over excessively rosy
                            estimates of future Iran income. Noted specifically how during last
                            summer’s economic review Shah had brushed aside realistic estimates his
                            economic advisors as being too conservative. Also explained this pointed
                            up our concern re too much Iranian spending on things military
                                (<persName corresp="#p_HAA1">Hoveyda</persName> cited current
                            flare-up of hostilities with Iraq as justifying <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>’s judgment re military expenditures). In any case, I
                            made clear my conviction oil Consortium worked by laws of supply and
                            demand rather than political vindictiveness (<persName>Wright</persName>
                            says he took same line). I also expressed some doubt about plethora of
                            Iranian barter deals with Eastern Bloc countries, noting how Hitler used
                            these tools for political purposes. Also suggested Iran keep wary eye on
                            its oil sales to Rumania and others for possibility exists Eastern Bloc
                            countries will flog this oil on European market at expense Iranian
                            markets. Noted that Iran would do well to keep in mind its predominant
                            oil market (and inconvertible exchange) must inevitably be with free
                            world countries.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HAA1">Hoveyda</persName> said he realized <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> unable take specific action but
                            expressed hope we might informally encourage oil companies to keep Iran
                            offtakes up. He contrasted this year’s sharp increase in production in
                            Saudi Arabia (I noted year ago Iran percentage of increase was high
                            while Saudi was low) and in Abu Dhabi. We both agreed frank <pb facs="0372" n="342" xml:id="pg_342"/> discussion of these problems
                            of type he undertaking is much preferable to artillery salvo technique
                            employed in Kharg Island issue. <persName corresp="#p_HAA1">Hoveyda</persName> said Consortium Chief John Warder, who was
                            leaving his office when I arrived, is going to London to seek
                            explanation from Consortium members.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="strong">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MAH1">Meyer</persName>
                                </hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>