<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>193. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="193"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                <head>193. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d193fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Records of the
                        Department of State, Central Files, 1964–66, PET 6 IRAN. Secret. Drafted by
                        Newberry. The briefing memorandum for the meeting is in a memorandum from
                            <persName corresp="#p_OJG1">Oliver</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_FER1">Fried</persName>, November 1. (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1966-11-03">November 3,
                            1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Political Aspects of the Iranian Oil Consortium Problem</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                        </hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Willie Morris</persName>, Foreign Office,
                                London</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FJT1">John Fearnley</persName>, Foreign
                                Office, London</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Nigel Trench</persName>, Counselor, Embassy
                                Washington</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Christopher Everett</persName>, First Secretary,
                                Embassy Washington</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Noel Martin</persName>, Counselor (Petroleum),
                                Embassy Washington</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ED1">Derek Eagers</persName>, Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Martin</persName>’s newly arrived
                                replacement</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Robert Alston</persName>, Foreign Office,
                                London</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">US</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Stuart W. Rockwell</persName>, Deputy Assistant
                                Secretary, NEA</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FER1">Edward Fried</persName>, Deputy
                                Assistant Secretary, E</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJWJ1">James W.
                                    Swihart</persName>,<gloss target="#t_EUR1"
                                >EUR</gloss>/BMI</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Theodore L. Eliot</persName>, Jr., NEA/IRN</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_OJG1">John Oliver</persName>,
                                E/FSE</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Daniel O. Newberry</persName>, NEA/IRN</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0385" n="355" xml:id="pg_355"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName>, expressing the hope that our two governments
                    could present a united front, stressed that the Iranians are always quick to
                    perceive differences in our points of view. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1"
                        >Morris</persName> replied that <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> would
                    see the problems in the same way as the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>
                    insofar as possible and he looked upon the day’s task as of finding how and
                    where our two governments differ. He recalled that the importance of Iran to
                        <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> came out strongly in the Defense Review.
                    It had been clear that Britain could not give up its obligations in the area of
                    Iran and the Gulf despite economic pressures to do so. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> thought that the job of keeping Iran on
                    its promising course as long as possible was worth quite a lot of effort. In
                    commercial terms the Consortium companies were now in a strong position. In the
                    longer term, he thought, we both could only be the losers in the event of a
                    confrontation, apart from the ill effects that Iran itself might suffer. He did
                    not question the doctrine of leaving the companies to settle their affairs with
                    the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> but he saw the present situation as one
                    in which the companies would appreciate and would need advice from their
                    governments. Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> remarked that while we in the
                        <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> consult regularly with the U.S.
                    companies, the companies at this time were showing no more disposition than
                    usual to ask our advice.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName>’ analysis of Iranian motives
                    centered around the role of the Shah himself who was master-minding the Iranian
                    effort. While there was a certain logic in the shifting economic arguments put
                    forward by Iran, essentially what they want is more money. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> cited an additional psychological
                    factor influencing the Shah, namely that Mossadeq was still figuratively
                    pointing a finger at the Shah and HIM felt an urgent need to display
                    “independence.”</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> agreed that the Shah was calling the turns for
                    Iran and added that the aim of getting a marketing role for the <gloss
                        target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> figured in Iranian calculations. He also
                    mentioned the Iranian feeling that the Consortium agreement somehow deprived
                    Iran of its sovereignty. There was also a feeling of envy at the
                    disproportionate income from oil enjoyed by neighboring states. The American
                    companies, he believed, seemed to regard the present problem as a continuation
                    of a general dilemma faced by oil companies in other areas as well.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FJT1">Fearnley</persName> added that the companies
                    seemed to take the problem seriously for its own sake. The British companies
                    were looking for a formula to control the eventual erosion of their position in
                    Iran rather than accept “an imposed erosion.”</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> called attention to the draft
                    minute on the Iranian economic situation which had been given to the Department
                    on a rush basis. Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> distributed a companion U.S.
                    memorandum on the Iranian economic position. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1"
                        >Morris</persName> noted that Iran does have a foreign exchange problem
                    which will be especially acute next year. He recalled that the US and <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Ambassadors in Tehran were trying to <pb
                        facs="0386" n="356" xml:id="pg_356"/> persuade the <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> to get an expert to identify the problem; he suggested that we
                    continue to put this idea to the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>, apart from
                    the Consortium problem. Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> agreed that there was
                    a foreign exchange problem but noted that Iran does have considerable capacity
                    to incur medium and long-term debts. He added that the improved economic
                    management performance by such agencies as the Ministry of Economy and the
                    Central Bank made us more optimistic about the <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss>’s ability to control inflation and otherwise to manage its
                    economic planning. Mr. <persName>Eliot</persName> called attention to the annual
                    IMF consultation in December which should also be helpful.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName>, in considering US and <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> strategic interests in Iran, saw no persuasive
                    alternative to the present regime. He felt that if the Shah could be dissuaded
                    from taking suicidal action in the Consortium affair, Iran showed great promise.
                    Britain, he emphasized, continued to depend heavily on over-flight privileges in
                    Turkey and Iran.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> responded that the <gloss target="#t_USG1"
                        >USG</gloss> attached equal if not more importance to Iran than the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>. In an area beset by nationalist irritations, the
                    Shah’s conduct was one element that could be counted on and we find that we have
                    to put up with a great deal to keep the Shah in a reasonably reasonable mood.
                    Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> went on to cite the Iranian apprehensions over
                    the prospect of British withdrawal from the Persian Gulf area.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> related that Foreign Secretary
                    Brown had discussed this subject with Mr. <persName>Aram</persName> in New York
                    recently, at which time Mr. <persName>Brown</persName> reiterated <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> intentions to maintain military dispositions in
                    the area for the foreseeable future. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1"
                        >Morris</persName> recalled that the Foreign Secretary had written a
                    personal letter of reassurance to the Shah while the latter was in Austria,
                    noting that the Shah’s initial reaction to the letter had been good but that
                    later on HIM had displayed some disquiet. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1"
                        >Morris</persName> predicted that the Shah must reconcile himself to not
                    getting sovereignty over the other shore of the Gulf. The Shah could, however,
                    take some satisfaction in having the biggest “fleet” in the area.</p>
                <p>The remainder of the conversation was focused on the risk of unilateral action by
                    the Shah. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> dismissed the
                    thesis that the Shah might be bluffing and predicted that even if Iran had to
                    retreat altogether from its present position vis-à-vis the Consortium, the Shah
                    would harbor so much rancor that he would be very difficult to deal with in the
                    future. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> thought the most
                    likely form that unilateral action might take would be legislation designed to
                    take away part of the concessions, perhaps one or more of the producing areas.
                    The Shah seemed to think that the Consortium would go on producing even while
                    accepting a fait accompli.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> agreed that if Iran decided to take over any of
                    the producing areas, the crisis would take on really serious proportions. <pb
                        facs="0387" n="357" xml:id="pg_357"/> It was not our impression however that
                    the Shah was ready to wreck the 1954 Agreement. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1"
                        >Morris</persName> thought that, although such was not the Shah’s intention,
                    the danger lay in the possibility that the Shah might set in motion a course of
                    events that he could not stop. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1"
                        >Morris</persName> agreed that the Shah was unlikely to pursue such a course
                    knowingly, but <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> felt that we must take
                    seriously the possibility that the Shah might try to out-Mossadeq Mossadeq. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> wondered what were the less
                    drastic possibilities of unilateral action. Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName>
                    thought that it depended on how much the Consortium could absorb. He added that
                    the companies must be the judges of what would be considered drastic and they
                    obviously must make some proposal which the Iranians would not feel that they
                    had to reject out of hand. The companies’ proposal would need to offer some
                    meaningful financial result for the Shah in order to register other than a
                    negative impact. Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> added that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> took no position on what the companies’
                    proposals should be.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FJT1">Fearnley</persName> and Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> felt that the British companies did not
                    want a showdown. They had a public relations problem, not wanting to appear to
                    be “grinding the faces of the poor.” British Petroleum was seeking to find a
                    formulation that would appear to the layman as just, reasonable and fair. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> expressed the hope that the
                        <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> would point out to the US companies the
                    probable consequences of provoking unilateral action by Iran.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> noted that we had already spoken in general
                    terms with the companies and would do so again; he was confident that the US
                    companies were aware of the seriousness of the situation. The Department had
                    told the American companies that we did not want to be involved in the substance
                    of negotiations. We were satisfied that the companies were mindful of <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> interest in the problem and that the companies
                    were resolved to seek a way out of the impasse that would not damage their basic
                    interests.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName> recapitulated the following points of view held
                    by the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> does not wish to become
                            involved in the discussions within the Consortium on possible
                            counterproposals to the Iranians and does not wish to pressure the
                            American companies to make any particular proposals.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>We do not believe that the Shah will go so far as to risk destruction
                            of the 1954 Oil Agreement.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has pushed its military and
                            economic aid programs for Iran to the maximum, and we do not propose to
                            offer any more in the context of the Consortium impasse.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> nevertheless regards the
                            current Iranian demands on the Consortium as a serious matter. We will
                            continue to attempt to restrain the Iranians from any rash action and to
                            persuade them to keep the door open for discussions. We will keep in
                            touch with the <pb facs="0388" n="358" xml:id="pg_358"/> American member
                            companies. We also want to stay in close consultation with <gloss
                                target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and, if there is any way in which
                                <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> believes we might be helpful, we
                            would be happy to have further discussions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MFWJ1">Morris</persName> agreed that the situation does
                    not call for consideration of additional US or <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                    economic or military assistance to the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> and
                    noted that the companies understood this. He observed that the difference
                    between the evaluations of <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> had to do with the probability rather than the
                    consequences of unilateral action by the Shah. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FJT1"
                        >Fearnley</persName> asked whether, if the negotiations were to bog down,
                    the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> would exclude the possibility of
                    speaking in general terms about the seriousness of the situation and urge the
                    companies to get their heads together. Mr. <persName>Rockwell</persName>
                    responded that we did not exclude anything; if the companies were to ask our
                    advice we would give it and they could accept or reject it.</p>
                <p>At the conclusion of the talks, it was agreed that the two governments would
                    inform the companies of the fact that the talks had taken place in the State
                    Department and would ask the companies to regard this as privileged
                        information.<note n="2" xml:id="d193fn2">The two governments were also
                        concerned that the French would find out about the extent of the
                        consultation between them: “British Emb indicated earlier on 1st that FonOff
                        expecting French approach and wanted to coordinate line we take with the
                        French… . [British Emb] indicated he would stress to FonOff the desirability
                        of not informing French of Nov. 2–3 <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>-US
                        talks in Washington and of merely telling French they are being told same
                        thing as <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> is telling <gloss
                            target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>.” (Telegram 76782, November 1;
                        ibid.)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
