<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-11-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-11-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                        <head>226. Research Memorandum From the Director of the Bureau of
                            Intelligence and Research (<persName type="from">Hughes</persName>) to
                            Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d226fn1">Source:
                                National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Records of the
                                Department of State, Central Files, 1967–69, PET 6 IRAN. Secret; No
                                Foreign Dissem; Controlled Dissem; No Dissem Abroad; Limdis.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">RNA–34</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-11-07">November 7, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The Problems and Prospects of the Iranian Oil Consortium</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The temporary settlement in April 1968 of current disputes between the
                            Iranian Government and the group of western oil companies known as the
                            Iranian Oil Consortium gave the companies additional time to determine
                            their joint position for the subsequent round of negotiations, which
                            began on September 30, 1968, at the semi-annual Consortium/National
                            Iranian Oil Company meeting in London. This paper will attempt to
                            present the background and an analysis of the problems involved.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Abstract</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In order to achieve an exceptionally large increase in its oil revenues
                            for several years to come, the Iranian Government will in the next few
                            months bring heavy pressure to bear upon the Iranian Oil Consortium.
                            Wishful thinking plus an error in computation<note n="2" xml:id="d226fn2">See <ref target="#d215fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                    215</ref>.</note> has led the Iranians to plan upon a level of
                            revenue from future Consortium operations that is, in the Consortium’s
                            view, far above the probable figure, and the government has been so
                            informed.</p>
                        <p>The Iranian position, in essence, is that Iran’s development needs (in
                            particular, its fourth five-year development plan, covering the Iranian
                            years 1347–51, roughly 1968–72) require a certain level of funds, that
                            oil is the only Iranian resource capable of generating that level, and
                            that the bulk of the necessary oil must come from the Consortium’s
                            concession area, which contains by far the most prolific known and
                            presently operational deposits. The Iranians would prefer, as the
                            simplest solution (and the only one likely to succeed), that the members
                            of the Consortium lift enough oil to provide, through the usual
                            royalties and taxes, the desired level of governmental revenue.</p>
                        <p>If the Consortium is unable to do this, it must provide the National
                            Iranian Oil Company (<gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss>) with a
                            sufficient quantity of oil from the Consortium area at a low enough
                            price so that <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> could make up <pb facs="0443" n="413" xml:id="pg_413"/> the shortfall in revenue
                            through its own sales or barter arrangements. The oil could be provided
                            by modifying the terms of the Consortium’s 1966 agreement to make barter
                            oil available to <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss>, by turning over
                            to <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> an already producing field in
                            the Consortium area, or by conferring upon the Iranian Government
                            membership in the Consortium. The government has indicated that, in case
                            of refusal, Iran might take unilateral measures to obtain the oil.</p>
                        <p>In spite of the apparent Iranian determination to reach, in one way or
                            another, its revenue goal, the government is very probably aware that
                            this goal is unattainable—that the Consortium is in fact doing its best
                            to increase its offtake but will not be able to meet Iranian demands,
                            that additional sales by <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> could not
                            possibly close the gap, and that any unilateral measures Iran might take
                            in an attempt to reach its goal not only would not accomplish that end
                            but might prove to be disastrous.</p>
                        <p>There have been indications of Iranian hesitation to enter into an
                            irreconcilable confrontation with the Consortium. The Iranians backed
                            down in April 1968 with a “Persian solution” to the problems raised by
                            their demands. They shifted the time frame of the dispute. Their recent
                            offer to discuss production capacity as well as actual offtake of oil
                            has opened up another avenue which could at least postpone a showdown.
                            If the Consortium remains adamant about future commitments on offtake,
                            refusing to promise the levels the Iranians are demanding, the
                            government can back down again by accepting Consortium assurances that
                            the necessary production capacity will be available in case Consortium
                            offtake or a combination of Consortium offtake and <gloss target="#t_NIOC1">NIOC</gloss> offtake for barter purposes should by
                            some chance reach the desired level. The Consortium is apparently in a
                            position to make such a commitment for at least one year and possibly
                            two.</p>
                        <p>With room for the Iranians to retreat, we believe they will probably do
                            so. They will make every effort to better their position, such as by
                            obtaining easier terms for barter oil and some additional minor
                            concessions, as well as the highest possible offtake commitments, but we
                            strongly doubt that they are as yet prepared to resort to unilateral
                            measures of compulsion if their demands are not met.</p>
                        <p>Here follows the body of the 26-page report.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>