<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-07-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="258" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                        <head>258. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d258fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File,
                                Files of the NSC Special Committee, Economic [2 of 2]. Confidential.
                                A July 19 covering note from Robert Cox to Nathanial Davis on White
                                House letterhead reads, “For your information.” The cover note also
                                bears Davis’ handwritten notation: “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>, FYI.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1967-07-18">July 18,
                                    1967</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>With Dr. Alirio A. Parra, Venezuelan Director of Petroleum Economy</p>
                        <p>I believe Tony Parra has traveled more in Arab countries and has more
                            contacts among the Arab leaders than any other Latin American. He gave
                            me the following information today, for the most part in response to my
                            questions: <list>
                                <item>—Venezuela is naturally taking advantage of the Middle East
                                    crisis to maximize its oil revenues, but much of the added
                                    income will be absorbed by the bureaucracy. The Government now
                                    maintains that 30% of oil revenues go to economic and social
                                    development projects, but no one can really trace these funds
                                    and it is probably a much smaller percentage. Minister of
                                    Finance Benito Paul Losada intends to “sterilize” (I suppose
                                    that means segregate) the windfall profits to be used for future
                                    contingencies, but other Government officials are already
                                    planning to use them in current and expanded programs.</item>
                                <item>—The Iraqis recently asked Venezuela to curtail its petroleum
                                    shipments to the West. This was a bi-lateral representation, not
                                    made through the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries.
                                    (Parra left the impression that no other Arab countries had made
                                    similar requests.)</item>
                                <item>—But “the Arabs have not learned their lesson.” They plan to
                                    resume fighting with Israel as soon as they are armed and ready.
                                    They are almost constitutionally incapable of sitting at a
                                    conference table with the Israelis.</item>
                                <item>—From the earliest days of the Arab-Israeli crisis, the Saudis
                                    openly told the diplomatic corps—including the Venezuelan
                                    Ambassador in Jidda—that of course they would permit oil
                                    shipments to go to the West, despite the announced embargo. Only
                                    the Iraqis are naive enough to believe what the Egyptians tell
                                    them and to do what Nasser says.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="strong">
                                    <persName>Robert G. Cox</persName>
                                </hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>