<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-11-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-11-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="271" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d271">
                        <head>271. Memorandum From a Senior Adviser to the Vice President (<persName corresp="#p_RJ3" type="from">Rielly</persName>) to Vice President
                                <persName corresp="#p_HHHJ1" type="to">Humphrey</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d271fn1">Source: Minnesota Historical
                                Society, Papers of <persName corresp="#p_HHHJ1">Hubert H.
                                    Humphrey</persName>, Vice Presidential Files, 1965–68,
                                150.E.12.7 (B). No classification marking. A handwritten note at the
                                top of the page reads “Draft.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-11-27">November 27, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Conference on “Pacem in Terris” sponsored by the Fund for the
                                Republic</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>As the enclosed letter<note n="2" xml:id="d271fn2">Not found.</note>
                            indicates, the conference on Pope John’s encyclical “Pacem in
                                Terris”<note n="3" xml:id="d271fn3">Pope John XXIII’s encyclical,
                                Pacem in Terris, urged international cooperation for peace and
                                justice and committed the Church to a concern for all human
                                problems.</note> will be held in New York on February 17–20. You
                            will recall that we discussed this some months ago and passed the word
                            to Robert Maynard Hutchins<note n="4" xml:id="d271fn4">Hutchins,
                                President of the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions,
                                was the chairman of the convocation. The Center was an American
                                non-governmental organization and was hosting the conference as part
                                of the UN International Cooperation Year.</note> that you were
                            interested in attending and addressing the group. They are now moving
                            ahead with plans to make a definite schedule for the conference. As the
                            enclosed letter indicates, their plans are a bit grandiose. They had
                            hoped to get <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>, the Pope
                            and President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>. I doubt if
                            they are going to end up getting any of them.</p>
                        <pb facs="0511" n="481" xml:id="pg_481"/>
                        <p>As Harry Ashmore’s letter indicates, they want you to put the arm on the
                            President and get him to make a commitment on this. I do not think I
                            would be in any hurry to do so. This strikes me as the type of
                            conference where it might be better to have the Vice-President as the
                            star, rather than the President. I think it is going to be a first-rate
                            conference with very high level people from the intellectual,
                            journalistic and diplomatic world attending.<note n="5" xml:id="d271fn5">Other speakers scheduled to attend included U.S. Permanent
                                Representative to the United Nations Adlai Stevenson, Chief Justice
                                Earl Warren, Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW2">J. William
                                    Fulbright</persName>, Ambassador George Kennan, Israeli Deputy
                                Prime Minister Abba Eban, three former Presidents of the General
                                Assembly, historian Arnold Toynbee, Nobel Prize-winning scientist
                                Linus Pauling, and theology professor Paul Tillich. (UN Press
                                Release <gloss target="#t_ICY1">ICY</gloss>/22, February 9, 1965;
                                Minnesota Historical Society, Papers of <persName corresp="#p_HHHJ1">Hubert H. Humphrey</persName>, Vice Presidential Files,
                                1965–68, 150.F.13.7 (B))</note> But it is designed to be a
                            highpowered intellectuals’ conference, not a conference given to
                            cautious diplomatic statements. I am not at all sure that this is the
                            right medium for the President. I see no harm in having him open the
                            conference but I’m not sure that he would want to schedule a major
                            speech there.</p>
                        <p>To be perfectly blunt, I am somewhat reluctant to see you bypassed as the
                            star of this conference. This would probably be the best foreign policy
                            speaking engagement you would get in the next year. The subject of the
                            conference would permit you to give a very high level speech which would
                            really combine all your major foreign policy interests—arms control and
                            disarmament, relations between the developing and the developed world,
                            foreign aid, international organizations, United Nations, and
                                peace.<note n="6" xml:id="d271fn6">On February 17, 1965, <persName corresp="#p_HHHJ1">Humphrey</persName> delivered a long speech
                                at the conference, in which he explained that statesmen “cannot
                                ignore the implications for the survival of mankind of new
                                discoveries in technology, biology, nuclear physics, and space.” He
                                also clearly enunciated the new threats to peace and security: “In
                                Pacem in Terris John XXIII returned to a theme he had discussed in
                                Mater et Magistra when he stated: ‘Given the growing interdependence
                                among peoples of the earth, it is not possible to preserve lasting
                                peace if glaring economic inequality among them persists.’ If
                                control of nuclear weapons is a central issue in improving relations
                                between East and West, accelerating the economic development of new
                                nations is essential to harmony between North and South.” Humphrey
                                spoke of the need for social justice: “Those who have been ‘more
                                blessed with this world’s goods’ must heed the Pope’s plea to assist
                                ‘those political communities whose citizens suffer from poverty,
                                misery and hunger and who lack even the elementary rights of the
                                human person.’ We must do this out of compassion—for we are our
                                brother’s keeper. And we also do it out of self-interest as well—for
                                our lot is their lot, our future their future, our peace their
                                peace. This planet is simply too small for the insulation of the
                                rich against turbulence bred of injustice in any part of the world.”
                                (Remarks of the Vice President, February 17, 1965; ibid.)</note> If
                            the President is inclined to attend, by all means I would not discourage
                            him. But I don’t think I would exert any pressure at this time.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>