<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-12-30T15:56:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="83" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                        <head>83. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>As the Department of State and the Agency for International Development
                            moved to implement NSAM No. 342, <persName corresp="#p_MLH1">Leonard
                                Marks</persName>, Director of the U.S. Information Agency, informed
                            Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> on <pb facs="0185" n="155" xml:id="pg_155"/> March 7, 1966, that the
                            international common carriers (AT&amp;T, ITT, World Communications, RCA
                            Communications, and Western Union International) had informally
                            expressed their willingness to provide financing for earth stations
                            without recourse to government financing. <persName corresp="#p_MLH1">Marks</persName> suggested that the Attorney General be given
                            clearance to suspend anti-trust considerations to allow the companies to
                            cooperate. (Department of State, NSAM Files: Lot 72 D 316)</p>
                        <p>In an April 27 memorandum to Under Secretary of State for Economic
                            Affairs Mann, Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs
                                <persName corresp="#p_SAM4">Solomon</persName> opined that
                            government financing still should be considered because of the history
                            of unsuccessful efforts of the carriers and less-developed countries
                                (<gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>s) to come to mutually
                            acceptable terms. Since most <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>s chose
                            to work through government or domestic entities, “There is considerable
                            reason to believe that in many countries there will be no rapid earth
                            station construction if the only help available comes from private
                            United States companies.” (Ibid.)</p>
                        <p>On April 22 Mann suggested that the Department of State and the Agency
                            for International Development establish a working group under Deputy
                            Secretary of State for Economic Affairs <persName corresp="#p_LFE1">Frank Loy</persName> to finalize site choices and prepare a report
                            for the President. (Letter from Mann to <persName corresp="#p_MLH1">Marks</persName>, April 22; ibid.)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>