<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Prime Minister Churchill to President Roosevelt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943CairoTehran</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d113</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">113</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-11-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-11-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="113"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d113">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> Papers: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CC2" type="from"
                            >Churchill</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1" type="to"
                            >Roosevelt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d113fn1">Sent by the United States Military Attaché, London,
                        apparently via military channels.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-10">10 November
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_FormerNavalPerson1">Former Naval Person</gloss> to President
                        <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName>. Personal and most secret.
                    Number 500.</p>
                <p>I think it would be best, irrespective of any arrangements which we may be able
                    to make for our own meeting with <gloss target="#t_UJ1">U. J.</gloss>, to cable
                    him at once in the following sense:— <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The British and American Chiefs of Staff are meeting in Cairo about the
                            22nd November to discuss in detail the operations of the Anglo-American
                            Armies and also the war against Japan, for which our long term plans
                            have now been prepared. For the latter subject it is hoped that
                                <persName corresp="#p_CKS1">Chiang Kai Shek</persName> himself and a
                            Chinese Military Delegation may be present. After these domestic and Far
                            Eastern discussions have been concluded we have the hope that the
                            meeting of the three heads of Governments may take place. Besides and
                            apart from this it is proposed that there should be a formal triple
                            conference of the Soviet, United States and British Staffs, starting
                            about the 25th or 26th November, to discuss the whole field of the war
                            in all its aspects. It is much hoped, therefore, that you will send a
                            powerful military delegation to this conference, accompanied if possible
                            by <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">M. Molotov</persName>. All this is
                            separate from and additional to the meeting which we still hope it may
                            be possible to arrange between the three heads of Governments.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>As I feel sure that the above is in accord with your views and wishes, I am
                    sending it off today in order to avoid delay.</p>
                <p>I have just received your 416. A meeting at Malta en route to <gloss
                        target="#t_Sextant1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sextant</hi>
                    </gloss> is clearly out of the question. I shall therefore go direct to
                    Cairo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
