<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="116" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source"><persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> Papers: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1" type="from">Roosevelt</persName> to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CC2" type="to">Churchill</persName></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d116fn1">Sent to the United States Naval Attaché, London,
                                via Navy channels. A notation attached to the source text states
                                that <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> “delayed
                                departure of his party for <gloss target="#t_Sextant1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sextant</hi></gloss> for sufficient time to
                                dictate 418.”</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-11">11 November 1943</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Personal and most secret from the President to the <gloss target="#t_FormerNavalPerson1">Former Naval Person</gloss>. Number
                            418. Your 501.</p>
                        <p>I have just heard that <gloss target="#t_UJ1">U. J.</gloss> will come to
                                Teheran.<note n="2" xml:id="d116fn2">See <persName corresp="#p_SIV1">Stalin</persName>’s message of November 10, 1943, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_78">p.
                                78</ref>.</note> I received a telegram from him five days ago<note n="3" xml:id="d116fn3"><persName corresp="#p_SIV1">Stalin</persName>’s message of November 5, 1943, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_67">p. 67</ref>.</note> which made
                            me think he would not come even to that place—this because his advisors
                            did not wish him to leave Russian soil.</p>
                        <pb facs="0172" n="80" xml:id="pg_80"/>
                        <p>I wired him at once<note n="4" xml:id="d116fn4">See <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName>’s message of November 8,
                                1943, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_71">p.
                                71</ref>.</note> that I had arranged the Constitutional matter here,
                            and therefore that I could go to Teheran for a short meeting with him
                            and told him I was very happy.</p>
                        <p>Even then I was in doubt as to whether he would go through with his
                            former offer to go to Teheran.</p>
                        <p>His latest message has clinched the matter, and I think that now there is
                            no question that you and I can meet him there between the twenty-seventh
                            and the thirtieth.</p>
                        <p>Thus endeth a very difficult situation, and I think we can be happy.</p>
                        <p>In regard to Cairo, I have held all along—as I know you have, that it
                            would be a terrible mistake if <gloss target="#t_UJ1">U. J.</gloss>
                            thought we had ganged up on him on military action. During the
                            preliminary meetings in Cairo the Combined Staffs will, as you know, be
                            in the planning stage. That is all. It will not hurt you or me if
                                <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> and a Russian
                            military representative are in Cairo too. They will not feel that they
                            are being given the “run around.” They will have no staff and no
                            planners. Let us take them in on the high spots.</p>
                        <p>It is only five hours ago that I received <gloss target="#t_UJ1">U.
                                J.</gloss>’s telegram confirming Teheran. Undoubtedly, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> and the military representative
                            will return there with us between the twenty-seventh and the thirtieth
                            and, when and after we have completed our talk with <gloss target="#t_UJ1">U. J.</gloss>, they will return with us to Cairo,
                            possibly adding other military staff to the one representative
                            accompanying <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> on the first
                            trip.</p>
                        <p>I think it essential that this schedule be carried out. I can assure you
                            there will be no difficulties.</p>
                        <p>I am sending you this at the first opportunity of letting you know about
                                <gloss target="#t_UJ1">U. J.</gloss></p>
                        <p>I am just off. Happy landing to us both.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RFD1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Roosevelt</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>