<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of War ( (McCloy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943CairoTehran</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-11-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-11-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recP2zv9bjAjSyYPT" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="242"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Defense Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of War</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_MJJ1">
                        <hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-21">November 21 (?),
                            1943</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum of Talk With Averill</hi> [<persName
                        corresp="#p_HWA2">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">
                            <hi rend="italic">Averell</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </persName>] <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName> November</hi> 21, 1943</p>
                <p>On the evening of the twenty-first I had dinner with Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAC1">Kirk</persName> in his town house in which Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName> was staying. During the course of the
                    evening Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName> asked that I come
                    into another room with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DLW1">Douglas</persName> as he
                    wanted to tell us something about the Soviet situation. He started out by saying
                    that he was here only as a reporter of what the Soviet attitude was, that he did
                    not wish to express himself as being in favor of any particular line of military
                    policy.</p>
                <p>He said the chief impressions he has had during his stay in Moscow had been of
                    the passionate desire of the Soviets to end the war. They were still a mighty
                    force but were growing tired, all their facilities and energies were strained,
                    they felt that a prompt application of all the forces that the United Nations
                    now had available would cause the Germans to crumble quickly and they were
                    desperately anxious to close the war against Germany successfully and
                    immediately. He said they had a very firm belief that it was within our power in
                    some form to take more divisions off their front than we had thus far
                    accomplished. They now took for granted and would insist on the completion of
                        <gloss target="#t_Overlord1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Overlord</hi>
                    </gloss> in full vigor but they wanted more activity this winter. The Autumn war
                    had become merged in the Winter war and it looked for the moment as if the chief
                    force of the Soviet attack had been checked; it would require the further
                    weakening of the German front before they could again break through. They were
                        <pb facs="0358" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/> impressed with the effects of our
                    bombing and did not minimize that contribution but were absolutely convinced
                    that we could substantially add to the German troubles this winter if we went
                    about it. When I pressed <persName corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName> for
                    some indication of what they thought we might do and still prepare ourselves to
                    mount an adequate <gloss target="#t_Overlord1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Overlord</hi>
                    </gloss> he said that neither he nor they were in a position to suggest anything
                    to our planners as neither were sufficiently familiar with the facts to say what
                    we could do. On one point, however, he said the Soviets were quite clear, and
                    that was that we should immediately intensify in the most realistic manner our
                    pressure on Turkey. He felt that it was quite possible that if Turkey came into
                    the war this winter the Soviets would be satisfied. <persName corresp="#p_HWA2"
                        >Harriman</persName> felt that we should apply at least as much pressure as
                        <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> had recently done with some
                        success.<note n="1" xml:id="d242fn1">See <persName corresp="#p_APH1"
                            >Alling</persName>’s memorandum of November 9, 1943, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KRF1">Kelley</persName>’s telegram 1844 of November 10, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName>’s memorandum of November
                        11, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_164">pp. 164</ref>, <ref
                            target="#pg_174">174</ref>, and <ref target="#pg_180">180</ref>,
                        respectively.</note> He said the Soviet government felt that the entry of
                    Turkey into the war would involve a further number of German divisions as well
                    as give great air and psychological advantages to the United Nations position.
                    He felt quite certain that the President and our staffs would find <persName
                        corresp="#p_SIV1">Stalin</persName> and the Soviet delegation united along
                    these lines.</p>
                <p>Before leaving he made it quite clear that in spite of some implications in
                    certain of General <persName corresp="#p_DJR1">Deane</persName>’s cables to the
                    contrary, the Soviets were no less interested in or insistent upon a second
                    front which to them meant a cross-channel operation. They did feel the energies
                    of the U. S. and U. K. could be so organized as to enable a more prompt and
                    greater application of power this winter than was contemplated. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName> said that perhaps the entry of Turkey
                    into the war was all that would be required and that no very substantial
                    diversions need be made to accomplish it, at any rate none that could not be
                    effected by some economies in Italy and elsewhere.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
