<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="275" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d275">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_JCS1">J. C.
                                        S.</gloss> Files</note>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation</hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-26">26 November 1943</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>The Conference began with a demand from the <gloss target="#t_Generalissimo1">Generalissimo</gloss> to maintain
                                    a fixed tonnage of 10,000 tons per month over the hump
                                    regardless of any demands which might be made on the equipment
                                    to support necessary operations in the South East Asia Command.
                                    It was explained to the <gloss target="#t_Generalissimo1">Generalissimo</gloss> (1) that all <gloss target="#t_C461">C–46</gloss> airplanes are being assigned to this service,
                                    (2) that an increase in the efficiency of the service is
                                    expected, (3) that efforts are being made to secure 25 <gloss target="#t_C471">C–47</gloss> airplanes for <persName corresp="#p_MLL1">Lord [Louis] Mountbatten</persName>, and
                                    that with these arrangements, the estimated tonnage over the
                                    hump would probably not only reach but exceed in due course the
                                    10,000 tons target figure, (4) that the difference between the
                                    figure proposed by <persName corresp="#p_MLL1">Lord
                                        Mountbatten</persName> for the next 7 months, 8,900 tons,
                                    and the figures estimated by the <gloss target="#t_Generalissimo1">Generalissimo</gloss> would be
                                    only 1,100 tons. It was explained that under these circumstances
                                    it was possible, even with the diversions asked by <persName corresp="#p_MLL1">Lord Mountbatten</persName>, that there
                                    might still be 10,000 tons for delivery in China.</p>
                                <pb facs="0455" n="355" xml:id="pg_355"/>
                                <p>The <gloss target="#t_Generalissimo1">Generalissimo</gloss>
                                    stated that he felt that his requirements and those of <persName corresp="#p_MLL1">Lord Mountbatten</persName> in the South
                                    East Asia Theater should be divorced and that they should be
                                    handled as separate items. It was explained that owing to the
                                    nature of the operation and the fact that the operations
                                    themselves were designed to push the Japanese back and thus
                                    provide for greater safety of the air route that this could not
                                    be done. It was also explained that all concerned had the
                                    increase in tonnage over the hump very much at heart and that
                                    though only 8,900 tons could be promised, that every effort
                                    would be made to increase this figure not only to 10,000 tons
                                    but to exceed 10,000 tons.</p>
                                <p>The <gloss target="#t_Generalissimo1">Generalissimo</gloss>
                                    concluded the conference by saying that he hoped that <persName corresp="#p_MLL1">Lord Mountbatten</persName> and his
                                    demands could be separated but that he would accept the figures
                                    given to him with the understanding that the <gloss target="#t_ATC1">ATC</gloss> would devote its best endeavors
                                    to securing the greatest possible increase in the tonnage.</p>
                                <closer><signed>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_AHH1"><hi rend="smallcaps">H. H.
                                                Arnold</hi></persName>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SJW1"><hi rend="smallcaps">J.
                                                Stilwell</hi></persName>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SBB1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Brehon
                                                Somervell</hi></persName>
                                    </signed></closer>
                            </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>