<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The President’s Personal Representative ( (Hurley) ) to the President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943CairoTehran</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d331</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">331</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-11-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-11-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="331"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d331">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> Papers: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The President’s Personal Representative</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_HPJ1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hurley</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d331fn1">Sent via Army channels.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-11-26">November 26,
                            1943.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Since wiring you I accompanied General <persName corresp="#p_CDH1"
                        >Connolly</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RJJ1">Rowley</persName>
                    together with the Russian Charge d’Affaires and other Russian security officers
                    for an inspection of quarters which the Russians propose to give to you as their
                    guest. For <persName corresp="#p_RMF1">Reilly</persName>’s information the
                    quarters are in the same building inside the Russian Embassy compound which he
                    inspected and consist of six rooms to the left of the entrance to the building.
                    The suite contains one large reception or assembly room, four smaller rooms that
                    could be used as bedrooms and one large bedroom with adjoining bath. For the
                    other four rooms there is but one bath, making two baths and toilet facilities
                    for the entire suite which is the same number as in the American Legation. In
                    the suite there is also a large dining room and below the main bedroom a kitchen
                    which can be used by your staff for you. The building is steam heated. The suite
                    they are offering you is on the same floor with and adjoins the large conference
                    room. No one else is living in this building but two other rooms are being used
                    as a Russian communications office. There is also a private entrance to the
                    suite. The only work needed to be done on the suite is to re-install bathtubs
                    and toilets which have been removed but can be replaced quickly. List of
                    necessary furnishings being given Russians by <hi rend="smallcaps">Darky</hi>.
                    From the standpoint of your convenience and comfort, from the standpoint of
                    conference communications and security, these quarters are far more desirable
                    than your own Legation. As I told you in my earlier wire, I have advised the
                    Russians that you have definitely decided to use your own Legation. The Russians
                    still most cordially solicit your acceptance of their invitation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HPJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hurley</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
