<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-05T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-05T11:00:00-05:00" n="449" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d449">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 <gloss target="#t_EW1">EW</gloss> 1939/12–2443</note>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">United States–United Kingdom Agreed
                                        Minutes</hi></head>
                                <dateline>
                                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-05T18:00:00+02:00">December 5, 1943, 6 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                                <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="smallcaps">most secret</hi></p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> opened the meeting by suggesting
                                    that Air Marshal <persName corresp="#p_DSS1">Sir Sholto
                                        Douglas</persName> should explain what was proposed since he
                                    had a feeling that the Turks were under a wrong impression.</p>
                                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Numan</hi></persName> thanked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>. He said he would be glad
                                    to listen. He must however make it clear that he could not
                                    commit himself on military matters which were the concern of the
                                    experts and on which he was not competent.</p>
                                <p><persName corresp="#p_DSS1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Sholto
                                            Douglas</hi></persName> said that he was not going to
                                    deal with technicalities. He was merely going to make a general
                                        <hi rend="italic">exposé</hi> to show why we wanted advance
                                    infiltration. In this there were two main objects: the first to
                                    provide adequate defence for the most vulnerable points, and the
                                    second to provide a force for offensive operations in the
                                    Aegean. As regards the first, the vulnerable points were
                                    Istanbul, Izmir and Zonguldak. For these it was proposed to send
                                    in 17 squadrons <pb facs="0831" n="727" xml:id="pg_727"/> (12 of
                                    them <gloss target="#t_Spitfire1">Spitfire</gloss>s) and 5
                                    regiments of light and 5 of heavy anti-aircraft guns. For
                                    purposes of defence it was essential to have an adequate warning
                                    system and also adequate anti-aircraft defence for the air
                                    fields on which would depend the defence of Istanbul and other
                                    vulnerable places. Until these essentials had been secured it
                                    would not be feasible to introduce the necessary squadrons. This
                                    brought the Air Marshal to infiltration and his proposals were: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>For radio location and operations room—200–250
                                            specialists and 20–30 vehicles.</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>Signals personnel for radio location and for linking
                                            air fields with operations room—400 persons.</item>
                                        <label>(3)</label>
                                        <item>Key specialist personnel of anti-aircraft guns—420
                                            persons.</item>
                                        <label>(4)</label>
                                        <item>Additional personnel for radio location, i. e. for
                                            extension of system round the coast from Zonguldak to
                                            Antalya—300 persons.</item>
                                        <label>(5)</label>
                                        <item>Administrative personnel for dumps, etc.—500
                                            persons.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>This represented a total of about 2,000 personnel.</p>
                                <p>The introduction of this personnel was the problem. Until
                                    something like this had been introduced Turkey would not be in a
                                    position of security when the moment of need came.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> remarked that when all this
                                    personnel had been brought in the squadrons could be flown
                                        in<note n="3" xml:id="d449fn3">The <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName> Collection copy
                                        reads “could be produced”.</note> in 24 hours for the
                                    defence of Turkey if Turkey were attacked. The complete
                                    effectiveness of defence would of course also be dependent on
                                    Turkey doing her share<note n="4" xml:id="d449fn4">The <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName> Collection copy
                                        reads “her bit”.</note> as promised with personnel for the
                                    anti-aircraft guns. It was as a result of the promise of this
                                    personnel that the estimated infiltration needs had been reduced
                                    from 7,000 to 2,000. Thus it could be seen what were the
                                    indispensable minimum needs to be introduced during the period
                                    of preparation.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> said that he took the
                                    infiltration to be part of the general minimum plan. He could
                                    not say whether the number of squadrons was adequate, though it
                                    sounded good. He obviously must however make a reservation on
                                    the question of their utility.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> stressed that in our opinion what
                                        <persName corresp="#p_DSS1">Sir Sholto Douglas</persName>
                                    had explained was the minimum necessary for Turkey’s protection.
                                    In addition we should of course be ready to specify the material
                                    which we should be prepared to supply for use by the Turks
                                    themselves.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> remarked that matters were
                                    advancing. There was not an impasse. The arrival of foreigners
                                    was very important. Even a civilian arriving in Turkey to serve
                                    would be known to Germany and the latter would not be
                                    indifferent. He did not want to provoke the Germans before a
                                    certain degree of preparation could be achieved. <pb facs="0832" n="728" xml:id="pg_728"/> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CC2">Churchill</persName> had described this as a vicious
                                        circle.<note n="5" xml:id="d449fn5">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_718">p. 718</ref>.</note>
                                    He (Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName>) did not
                                    agree but saw the problem from a different point of view. He was
                                    ready to accept the requisite number of technicians for the
                                    material supplied. How many technicians these might be he did
                                    not know. That would be a matter for the Turkish General Staff.
                                    He could not however accept personnel additional to the proper
                                    complement of technicians.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> remarked that the Turkish Minister
                                    for Foreign Affairs must have confidence. There surely could be
                                    no question of our wanting to introduce one single specialist
                                    more than was necessary. But how could the Turkish General Staff
                                    say whether particular personnel was necessary or not? During
                                    the preparatory period we did not wish to rush things any more
                                    than the Turks did. But we did want to get the preparations
                                    completed quickly.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> said that the Turks had the same
                                    object. They did not wish to provoke the Germans. He could not
                                    agree to the introduction of personnel but he did agree to the
                                    introduction of technicians, though he must make a reserve
                                    regarding the number of these. What he had said amounted to an
                                    acceptance in principle of technicians for the material
                                    promised.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName></hi> remarked that President
                                        <persName corresp="#p_II1">Inönü</persName> had several
                                    times spoken of Turkey’s minimum defence requirements. He
                                    wondered if he was right in assuming that this did not refer to
                                    infiltration and air material but to other needs. He assumed
                                    that the British had been discussing such questions with the
                                    Turkish General Staff. Had the British any idea of Turkish
                                    minimum requirements? Did they, for instance, include
                                    anti-aircraft guns and aircraft? This brought up the question of
                                    the commitments to be made and he realized that it was necessary
                                    to get personnel introduced in advance. But he wished to be
                                    clear in his own mind about the details.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> thought this was a good question.
                                    It seemed to him that there were two points—the material to be
                                    used by us in order to give protection to Turkey, and the
                                    material to be given to Turkey for use by the Turks
                                    themselves.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName></hi> mentioned that there was also
                                    the Anglo-American force to go into Turkey in the event of
                                    war.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> said that in the first instance
                                    this was air alone—antiaircraft.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> said he wished to make an
                                    observation and to compare what Turkey had got with what she had
                                    asked for. After the Adana Conference<note n="6" xml:id="d449fn6"><persName corresp="#p_CC2">Churchill</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_II1">Inönü</persName> conference at Adana, Turkey, January
                                        30, 1943; see <persName corresp="#p_CC2">Churchill</persName>, <hi rend="italic">The Hinge of
                                            Fate</hi>, pp. 704 ff.</note> the Turks had prepared a
                                    list of requirements which had <pb facs="0833" n="729" xml:id="pg_729"/> been more or less discussed. Later the
                                    British had entered into a definite commitment for delivery on
                                    the basis of that list. The Turkish list had remained a dead
                                    letter. The British list had not been much better (<hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> said that he could not agree). <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> went on to say that only some 4%
                                    of the items on the general list had been delivered to Turkey.
                                    He did not wish to make reproaches. He would only state facts
                                    and mentioned in particular the case of lorries of which 300 a
                                    month had been promised. For some time deliveries had been about
                                    160 or 180 a month. In recent months there had been no
                                    deliveries at all. Deliveries did in fact represent a very small
                                    proportion of promises.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> said that he could not accept Mr.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName>’s figures. He
                                    must make it plain that the position was not the position as it
                                    had been at Adana and he personally would not consider
                                    recommending his Government now to supply to Turkey all of the
                                    material which had been discussed at Adana.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> remarked that his had only been
                                    an observation.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">General <persName corresp="#p_WAR1">Wilson</persName></hi> said that even if it had been
                                    possible to supply all the items on the Turkish Adana lists, it
                                    would have taken the Turkish railways three years to carry them.
                                    As it was, Turkey had since Adana been supplied with 350 tanks,
                                    48 self-propelled guns, nearly 300 anti-aircraft guns (over 100
                                    of them heavy) 300 field and medium guns, 200 mortars, rather
                                    less than 500 anti-tank guns, an enormous quantity (about
                                    99,000) of various guns and automatics, 420 mortars, and about
                                    one million anti-tank mines for the defence of Turkey. It was
                                    unfortunately true that there had been a shortage of delivery on
                                    motor transport. This had happened because the transport did not
                                    exist in the Eastern Mediterranean. The Turks had however said
                                    at Adana that they had enough to defend themselves except for
                                    three anti-tank units and aviation support.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName></hi> expressed surprise at the
                                    extent of material assistance already given since Adana. He
                                    wished however to clear the position up. As he understood
                                    things, the Allies had agreed, in the event of war, to put in
                                    air squadrons and anti-aircraft guns and personnel. How far
                                    removed were we from President <persName corresp="#p_II1">Inönü</persName>’s minimum requirements in the event of
                                    war?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> said that if it were desired to
                                    negotiate on the basis of these past figures, he also could cite
                                    figures. At one moment 40 air squadrons had been promised in the
                                    event of war. This had been reduced by half. The percentage of
                                    deliveries was not impressive. As for circumstances he agreed
                                    that they had changed since Adana, but things had turned out
                                    exactly as they had been foreseen at Adana.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName></hi> said it seemed necessary to get
                                    to grips with the problem. Was he to understand that the Turkish
                                    President considered he <pb facs="0834" n="730" xml:id="pg_730"/> should have twice the air force suggested? Was he to
                                    understand that the anti-tank preparation was not enough? Were
                                    the Turkish railways a limiting factor, insofar as concerned
                                    Turkey coming into the war? He asked because if Turkey was not
                                    coming into the war she must understand that these munitions, so
                                    vitally required elsewhere, would not come into Turkey at
                                    all.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> remarked that there must be some
                                    misunderstanding. The position had been quite clearly stated.
                                    The President had announced his intention of coming into the
                                    war. The question of material had however always been a serious
                                    one. At the time when the Anglo-Turkish Alliance was
                                        negotiated<note n="7" xml:id="d449fn7">The reference is
                                        presumably to the Anglo-<persName corresp="#p_FyBF1">Franco</persName>-Turkish Treaty of Mutual Assistance,
                                        which was signed at Ankara on October 19, 1939 (text in
                                        League of Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cc</hi>, p. 167).</note> there had at first been a
                                    clause which postponed the operation of the Alliance until
                                    supplies were provided. He had realized that the supplies could
                                    not be provided and the clause had been suppressed. Since then
                                    and until now supplies had still not been available. Today
                                    Turkey lacked everything. Not only anti-aircraft guns and tanks
                                    but every sort of war material. He did not suggest that the
                                    Adana lists or any other list or anything like either of them
                                    should be supplied. He did however think that there ought to be
                                    a list of reasonable requirements. The Turks would not ask the
                                    impossible and with a maximum effort a list could readily be
                                    drawn up.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> said we had given the list of all
                                    that we wished to introduce for the defence of Turkey. If this
                                    were agreed we could then fix up what we could provide for use
                                    by the Turks. But we did not want the preparation of defence to
                                    be delayed during the consideration of the second list.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> said he agreed but that it must
                                    be part of a general plan in which the air preparations would of
                                    course take complete precedence. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                                            <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> enquired
                                    what general plan? <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> answered that it
                                    was necessary to decide the minimum requirements of Turkey if
                                    she were to enter the war. A list would be necessary.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName></hi> said he understood that the
                                    limiting factor was motor transport. Was it a limiting factor
                                    for anti-aircraft personnel? There had been talk of years for
                                    the introduction of requirements. We were dealing in weeks.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> pointed to General <persName corresp="#p_WAR1">Wilson</persName>’s statement that two or
                                    three years would have been necessary to introduce the items on
                                    the Adana lists. Had one-third of these been introduced in the
                                    year since Adana?</p>
                                <p><persName corresp="#p_KHSH1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir H.
                                            Knatchbull-Hugessen</hi></persName> suggested that we
                                    were all wasting our time in discussing the past. It was a
                                    wasted effort. In the interval <pb facs="0835" n="731" xml:id="pg_731"/> everything had changed and it would be a
                                    waste of transport even to send to Turkey today the material
                                    contemplated at Adana. Surely we should look at the future and
                                    not at the past.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> welcomed the Ambassador’s
                                    interjection and said he quite agreed. He wanted to propose
                                    something practical. Could we not at once send to Angora the two
                                    Generals (one British and one American) proposed by President
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName><note n="8" xml:id="d449fn8">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_712">p. 712</ref>.</note> so that they could
                                    concert at once with the Turkish General Staff and establish a
                                    list of requirements and work out complete collaboration.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> said that this was something apart
                                    from the fundamental question. We had this afternoon given to
                                    our Turkish friends a list of what we thought necessary for the
                                    defence of Turkey against attack. This must be the basis of
                                    working. In addition we could discuss further material but he
                                    could not accept the delay involved in the addition of other
                                    material quite unknown.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> said that the President had
                                    answered Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>’s point.
                                    He said that 2,000 men and 600 vehicles were not enough for the
                                    defence of Turkey though they were no doubt enough for the
                                    defence of British air bases.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> pointed out that they were not for
                                    the defence of British air bases but for that of Istanbul, Izmir
                                    and Zonguldak.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> remarked that the Turks could not
                                    contemplate Turkish defence being entrusted to the British. What
                                    they would and did contemplate was the defence of Turkey by the
                                    Turks with British help.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Air Marshal <persName corresp="#p_DSS1">Sir
                                            Sholto Douglas</persName></hi> pointed out that air
                                    defence depended essentially on fighters and this must be
                                    defended by antiaircraft guns. The first essential was to get
                                    the fighter defence established.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> said that there were two points.
                                    The first, what we introduced for the security of Turkey and the
                                    second the other things which the Turks must have before Turkey
                                    could take action.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">General <persName corresp="#p_WAR1">Wilson</persName></hi> explained that what had been
                                    mentioned hitherto was for Turkish defence. It was only an
                                    advance guard. Actually the total force contemplated would be
                                    32,000 troops (11,600 of them air), and 6,000 guns and vehicles
                                    (375 guns representing 5 light and 5 heavy anti-aircraft
                                    regiments).</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> said the urgent plan was one for
                                    immediate defence and the execution of this represented the
                                    dangerous period.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> having remarked that he could not
                                    comment on these figures, <persName corresp="#p_KHSH1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir H.
                                        Knatchbull-Hugessen</hi></persName> pointed out that as men
                                    and material were introduced, the danger to Turkey would be <pb facs="0836" n="732" xml:id="pg_732"/> correspondingly
                                    diminished. The first problem was to ensure safety and then to
                                    build up.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> said Turkey was coming into the
                                    war. It was necessary to draw up a plan of preparation and a
                                    plan of collaboration and at the same time to take up political
                                    matters in another direction.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName></hi> having remarked that
                                    reinforcement would be limited by transport facilities and that
                                    as regards priority for air we already give the Turks what they
                                    can take, said he must come to the main point. The war had
                                    reached a critical stage. It was impossible to divert to a
                                    neutral country war material which was not to be used against
                                    Germany. The British Prime Minister had been authorized to
                                    express the hope of the United States and of Russia that Turkey
                                    would enter the war at an early date.<note n="9" xml:id="d449fn9">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_158">p. 158</ref>.</note> We know that when
                                    a nation went to war with Germany she might suffer losses—the
                                    United Kingdom, Russia and the United States had suffered severe
                                    losses. He knew that Turkey wanted to enter the war. In the last
                                    analysis a country went to war in its own interests. We wanted
                                    Turkey in the war even if she could not have all she wanted.
                                    Great Britain, Russia and the United States had not all they
                                    wanted when they entered the war. At this critical period in the
                                    war the entry of Turkey might save the lives of hundreds of
                                    thousands of Allied nationals. January 1st was not a set date
                                    but Turkish participation might not be useful after very long
                                    after that date. We wanted Turkey to enter the war willingly and
                                    whole-heartedly. We should like Turkey to enter the war about
                                    February even though we knew that in doing so Turkey might
                                    suffer. We hoped Turkey would enter because all Allied military
                                    and political opinion considered that her entry would shorten
                                    the war. Only the Turks themselves could speak for Turkish
                                    self-interest. If however discussions were prolonged about the
                                    adequacy of material etc. Turkey’s entry would be futile. Turkey
                                    could be sure that if she came in we would do everything we
                                    could—all possible military and air support would be afforded
                                    her. He knew he was correctly interpreting President <persName corresp="#p_RFD1">Roosevelt</persName> when he said that he
                                    hoped that Turkey would in her own interests come in willingly
                                    and wholeheartedly.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> said that he wished to have the
                                    Turkish position correctly understood and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi>
                                    confirmed that it was as follows: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>Our proposals for infiltration were accepted in
                                            principle but Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName> made a reservation as regards
                                            numbers pending consideration by the Turkish General
                                            Staff.</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>If the programme involving infiltration were accepted
                                            Turkey will not take action which she considers might
                                            lead her into a state <pb facs="0837" n="733" xml:id="pg_733"/> of war with Germany until material
                                            and supplies for her use have been given, and the
                                            figures of these yet remain to be determined.</item>
                                        <label>(3)</label>
                                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                                            understood that Turkey had political questions to raise.
                                            He did not know what these were.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>As regards (3) <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> referred to the
                                    Russian undertaking regarding Bulgaria.<note n="10" xml:id="d449fn10">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_588">pp. 588</ref>, <ref target="#pg_698">698</ref>.</note> He thought that this was the sort of
                                    point which he would like to discuss with the Russians. There
                                    were other points which he would also like to discuss. But these
                                    discussions could take place during the period of preparation
                                    and would in no way delay either preparation or
                                    collaboration.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> enquired whether there were any
                                    other points to be put down.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> said that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HHL1">Hopkins</persName> had spoken of willing
                                    entry. This was also the desire of the Turks. They must however
                                    have a minimum of essential preparations. Moreover this was a
                                    commitment to the Turkish people and to the Party.<note n="11" xml:id="d449fn11">Presumably the Republican People’s
                                        Party.</note></p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName></hi> enquired what Turkey wanted under
                                    (2). Was it not possible for these requirements to be stated
                                    without discussions at Angora?</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> repeated that he was not
                                    competent to say what the military needs were. All he asked for
                                    was comprehension. It lay in our hands to determine when Turkey
                                    could enter the war since this would be determined by the supply
                                    of the necessary material.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Numan</persName></hi> confirmed that, as he had
                                    previously said, the infiltration programme under (1) above
                                    could go ahead while the discussion of (2) was in progress.</p>
                                <p>At this stage (8.15 p.m.) the meeting was adjourned.</p>
                            </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>