<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-11-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="153" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d153">
                        <head>153. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>)
                            to <persName corresp="#p_FGR1" type="to">President Ford</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d153fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> Library, National Security
                                Adviser, Presidential Country Files for East Asia and the Pacific,
                                Box 18, Vietnam (3). Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only.
                                Sent for information.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-11-23">November 23, 1974</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Possible Intensified North Vietnamese Military Activity</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>There are now appearing a number of indicators pointing to the
                            possibility of increased offensive action by the North Vietnamese,
                            perhaps beginning as early as December. It would be useful, in your
                            talks with <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Brezhnev</persName>,<note n="2" xml:id="d153fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Brezhnev</persName> in Vladivostok on November
                                23 and 24.</note> to indicate your concern over these
                            developments.</p>
                        <p>Among the more substantial indicators are the following: <list>
                                <item>—The overall physical support structure (e.g., <gloss target="#t_LOC1">LOC</gloss>’s, supply stockpiles, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>, etc.) for a major offensive is
                                    largely in place.</item>
                                <item>—A major North Vietnamese logistics push to the south began on
                                    a “crash” basis in mid-November.</item>
                                <item>—The <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss> 559 transportation
                                    directorate, a major <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>
                                    <gloss target="#t_HQ1">HQ</gloss>, has moved from southern
                                        <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> into <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> (<gloss target="#t_Cam1">Cam</gloss> Lo) for the first time.</item>
                                <item>—<gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, in mid-October, began
                                    its second conscription drive within four months. On the basis
                                    of past patterns this represents an extra drive in 1974.</item>
                                <item>—Preliminary information on infiltration shows that over 9,000
                                    men probably are bound for <gloss target="#t_COSVN1">COSVN</gloss> in November/December, double the number
                                    detected during the same period last year.</item>
                                <item>—Over the past two months, an unidentified (possibly 338th)
                                    division has been detected subordinate to <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> I Corps, raising the number of
                                        <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> strategic reserve
                                    divisions in <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> to seven (from
                                    six). Additionally, an intelligence report indicates that the
                                        <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> 968th Division, carried
                                    in the Lao panhandle (and, in effect, an eighth “reserve”
                                    division), might be employed in the central highlands of <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>.</item>
                                <item>—A number of communist troop realignments, such as movement of
                                        <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> 5th Division elements
                                    into <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–4 and restructuring of
                                        <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–3 forces, can be read as
                                    preparatory to an offensive. Reassignment of <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> 75th Artillery Division assets
                                    in <gloss target="#t_MR1">MR</gloss>–3 from general to direct
                                    support of <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> divisions in
                                    region is strong indicator of preparations for major
                                    offensive.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>These and numerous signs point to the strong possibility of substantially
                            heavier fighting in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> in near future,
                            but at levels less than <pb facs="0619" n="578" xml:id="pg_578"/> all
                            out offensive which would require committing major portion of strategic
                            reserve.</p>
                        <p>In your discussion with <persName corresp="#p_BL1">Brezhnev</persName>,
                            you could make the following points: <list>
                                <item>—We have received reliable information that North Vietnam has
                                    recently taken a number of steps which clearly point to a major
                                    escalation of North Vietnamese military action in South Vietnam
                                    during the current dry season.</item>
                                <item>—We have, for example, hard evidence of an explicit North
                                    Vietnamese plan for greatly increased military activity to begin
                                    in December in South Vietnam.</item>
                                <item>—There has also been a major and sudden increase in the
                                    infiltration of men and equipment into the south. This latter
                                    action represents a major violation of the Paris accords.</item>
                                <item>—I am compelled to call these disturbing reports to the
                                    Chairman’s attention. The United States as well as the Republic
                                    of Vietnam continue to lend full support to the Paris accords.
                                    We assume that similarly the Soviet Union maintains its support
                                    of the Paris agreement. Thus, we urge the Soviet Union to take
                                    immediate steps to deter North Vietnam from pursuing its plan to
                                    escalate the war and to adopt a policy of reason. The
                                    continuation of the actions which North Vietnam is now setting
                                    in train can only result in grave consequences.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>