<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-04-21T11:15:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-04-21T11:15:00-05:00" n="250" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d250">
                        <head>250. Backchannel Message From the President’s Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>) to the Ambassador to Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_MGA1" type="to">Martin</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d250fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> Library, National Security Adviser, Backchannel
                                Messages, Box 3, <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName>
                                Channel, April 1975, Outgoing (2). Top Secret; Sensitive;
                                Flash.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-04-21T16:15:00+00:00">April 21, 1975,
                                1615Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>WH50736. 1. As a result of the <gloss target="#t_WSAG1">WSAG</gloss>
                            meeting this morning,<note n="2" xml:id="d250fn2">See <ref target="#d249">Document 249</ref>.</note> it is our judgment
                            that as soon as Tan Son Nhut Airport comes under fire the <gloss target="#t_DAO1">DAO</gloss> personnel at the airport should
                            immediately be evacuated by C–130 aircraft and not repeat not rely on
                            the helicopter extraction. You should continue reducing nonessential
                                <gloss target="#t_DAO1">DAO</gloss> people as you are, and then
                            evacuate the remainder by C–130 when in your judgment Tan Son Nhut is in
                            danger of serious attack by fire and certainly before there is danger of
                            it being rendered unusable.</p>
                        <p>2. You should know that we have had absolutely nothing to do with the
                            French initiative.<note n="3" xml:id="d250fn3">On April 21 French
                                diplomats launched an effort to establish a provisional government
                                in Saigon to ease the transition to Communist rule. An undated
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> memorandum, “Communications
                                from the French,” is in the <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> Library, National Security Adviser,
                                Presidential Country Files for East Asia and the Pacific, Box 20,
                                Vietnam (21).</note> We would appreciate your keeping us informed
                            about them to the extent you learn of them.</p>
                        <p>3. With regard to the Soviet Union, we have suggested a temporary (about
                            two weeks) ceasefire in order to evacuate Americans and some Vietnamese
                            and to discuss political arrangements. We have had some indication of
                            serious interest but no substantive reply as yet.</p>
                        <p>4. Warm regards.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>