<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-04-21T18:21:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-04-21T17:41:00-05:00" n="251" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d251">
                        <head>251. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d251fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>
                                Library, National Security Adviser, Memoranda of Conversations, Box
                                11, Chronological File. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>. The meeting was held in the Oval Office. All
                                brackets except those indicating omitted material are in the
                                original. According to the President’s Daily Diary, the meeting
                                lasted from 6:41 to 7:21 p.m. (Ibid., Staff Secretary’s Office
                                File)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-editorial-annotation" calendar="gregorian" from="1975-04-21T18:41:00-04:00" to="1975-04-21T19:21:00-04:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">April 21,
                                1975</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>President <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>,
                                Secretary of State</item>
                            <item>Lt. General <persName corresp="#p_SB1">Brent Scowcroft</persName>,
                                Deputy Assistant to the President for National Security
                                Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: I said how can anyone
                            vote against it. If it does some good, it will ease human suffering; it
                            not it won’t be spent.</p>
                        <p>It wasn’t an unfriendly session, but basically it didn’t make any
                            difference what I said.<note n="2" xml:id="d251fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> testified that day
                                before the House Appropriations Committee.</note> They must know I
                            was right, but . . .</p>
                        <p>President: How do you analyze the <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> speech?<note n="3" xml:id="d251fn3">See <ref target="#d246">Document 246</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The longest version I
                            saw was reasonable. He said he warned me in ‘72 that leaving North
                            Vietnamese troops in the South was dangerous. He said we said we would
                            cut off aid if they didn’t sign. Both of these are true, but to ask them
                            to withdraw when the North had agreed not to reinforce or add equipment,
                            would have been impossible. I don’t think Congress would have stood for
                            continued fighting under these conditions.</p>
                        <p>President: I will get a question on did we force him out.<note n="4" xml:id="d251fn4">Later that evening, at 10 p.m., President <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> held an interview with CBS
                                television journalists. Vietnam was one of the first items raised;
                                see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United
                                    States: <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Gerald R. Ford</persName>,
                                    1975</hi>, Book I, pp. 539–559.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Say no.</p>
                        <p>I would not get into details. I said a new government was not even
                            formed. [Point out it happened in the evening and so nothing has
                            happened since.]</p>
                        <p>Why give aid? The most humane solution requires as controlled a condition
                            as possible. That requires a government with control and some
                            self-confidence. The change of government already indicates a new
                            situation. We should assist in this.</p>
                        <p>We are exploring with several parties. I wouldn’t want to say more in
                            this sensitive situation.</p>
                        <pb facs="0918" n="877" xml:id="pg_877"/>
                        <p>We have reduced our numbers without panic. We are at the bare minimum now
                            for essential functions, but we will continue to cut back as functions
                            become superfluous.</p>
                        <p>We can’t blame the Soviet Union. This is not contradiction. We are
                            talking two different things. The Soviet Union and the Chinese have to
                            know when they introduce arms into dangerous areas they must assume the
                            consequences. They know they would be used for aggressive purposes. But
                            if we had done our part, the parties would have been balanced and the
                                <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> wouldn’t have collapsed.</p>
                        <p>All our commitments are on the public record. It was always
                            understood.</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s correspondence
                            is perfectly normal and reflects his intentions as President. Where they
                            involve national commitments, they must go to the Congress.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is discussion unrelated to Vietnam.]</p>
                        <p>North Vietnam has said that <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName>
                            was the obstacle to a negotiation. If so, his departure should help . .
                            .</p>
                        <p>DeGaulle turned his back on Algeria and was a hero.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>