<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-04-22T07:16:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-04-22T07:16:00-05:00" n="253" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d253">
                        <head>253. Backchannel Message From the Ambassador to Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_MGA1" type="from">Martin</persName>) to the President’s
                            Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d253fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>
                                Library, National Security Adviser, Backchannel Messages, Box 3,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> Channel, April
                                1975, Incoming (2). Secret; Sensitive; Eyes Only; Immediate. Sent
                                with the instruction: “Deliver immediately.”</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-04-22T12:16:00+00:00">April 22, 1975,
                                1216Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>727. 1. I saw new President <persName corresp="#p_TVH1">Huong</persName>
                            for about one hour late this afternoon. A detailed memorandum of
                            conversation will be prepared and forwarded in due course,<note n="2" xml:id="d253fn2">There is no evidence that <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> prepared a detailed
                                memorandum of conversation.</note> but the essential impressions
                            gained are as follows: <list>
                                <item>First, whatever others may have thought <persName corresp="#p_TVH1">Huong</persName> does not think of himself
                                    as an interim President. He realizes Viet-Nam is in enormous
                                    peril. He is prepared to make concessions which few other
                                    Vietnamese politicians would feel able to do in order to
                                    preserve Saigon from “a bath of blood” and hopefully to maintain
                                    for as long as possible an independent South Viet-Nam whose
                                    foreign policies he understands will have to be radically
                                    altered in due course.</item>
                                <item>Second, he received Prime Minister Can this morning who
                                    tendered the resignation of the government. He told him to stay
                                    in place for a week while he considered what personalities might
                                    best serve Viet-Nam in the changing situation. He is very
                                    curious about what particular names in the Vietnamese political
                                    galaxy might be acceptable to Hanoi. He hopes to have some
                                    method of communicating with Hanoi, but knows of none except
                                    through the Four Party mechanism at La Celle St. Cloud.
                                    Ambassador <persName>Phong</persName> who was ordered to come
                                    back on Monday sent word he could not arrive until
                                        Wednesday<note n="3" xml:id="d253fn3">April 23.</note> and
                                    later word that he could not arrive before Friday. I suggested
                                    that the Four Party–Two Party system existing in Saigon
                                    including the liaison flights to Hanoi, might prove a useful and
                                    unobtrusive channel. He is considering this.</item>
                                <item>Third, he would like very much for Washington to be the
                                    inter-locutor with Hanoi in working out the modalities of some
                                    new arrangement in government which Hanoi will accept and with
                                    which South Viet-Nam might live. I said I would convey his
                                    request, but that I thought there would be little disposition in
                                    Washington to again undertake such a domestically politically
                                    dangerous exercise and that in any event, given the array of
                                    enemy forces now marshalled in South Viet-Nam, time was of the
                                    essence. He said he was seeing the French <pb facs="0923" n="882" xml:id="pg_882"/> Ambassador tomorrow morning and
                                    would ask him to convey his forthcoming attitude to Hanoi,
                                    stating that he had to have time to form a Cabinet that would be
                                    reasonably acceptable to the people of South Viet-Nam and also
                                    acceptable to Hanoi. I will try to find out tomorrow morning
                                    what he actually says to the French Ambassador.</item>
                                <item>Fourth, he is still counting on the United States to provide
                                    sufficient military aid now to preserve intact the morale and
                                    capability of the <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> without
                                    which any negotiation would be hopeless and capitulation
                                    inevitable. He asked me to express his gratitude to President
                                        <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> for the clarity
                                    and precision of President <persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>’s support and his steadfastness in
                                    defending past commitments on which Viet-Nam had depended. He
                                    hoped that the nakedness of the North Vietnamese attack might
                                    sufficiently change attitudes in Congress to permit the campaign
                                    being waged by the President and the Secretary to be
                                    successful.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. My impression from the French Ambassador is that the French have
                            advised Hanoi to not press an immediate military attack at the moment
                            and to give a little time to determine whether the resumption of the
                            political and negotiating track might not produce results much more
                            favorable to Hanoi in terms of world public opinion. I gather it is the
                            French opinion that their advice has been heard and the current lull in
                            the fighting would seem to bear this out.</p>
                        <p>3. Regardless of bits and pieces of intelligence information about
                            movements it would seem to be possible that while Hanoi may be moving
                            forces into position they will probably give a little bit more time to
                            see what will happen. I hope, therefore, you can continue to keep the
                            panic button locked up and that we will not ourselves precipitate a
                            final tragedy here by ordering actions which are not yet justified.
                            There is, after all, a telephone between Washington and Saigon and if a
                            decision appears urgent on the basis of so called evidence available to
                            the <gloss target="#t_WSAG1">WSAG</gloss> its implications might be
                            checked out with me before any instructions are issued.</p>
                        <p>4. By midnight tonight, we expect to be down under 1,500 for the total of
                            American citizens remaining and probably down to 1,000 by midnight
                            tomorrow. This was a totally impossible goal to be met but a dedicated
                            staff has achieved it. By the following night, we will have reduced the
                            essential number, including the Diplomatic Corps and others, which I
                            would expect to take out in a one lift cycle. I have just talked today
                            to Gen. Carey, the ground force commander, and I think everything is in
                            order here. Therefore, I hope to God you get your colleagues on the
                                <gloss target="#t_WSAG1">WSAG</gloss> to relax a bit.<note n="4" xml:id="d253fn4">In backchannel message WH50743 to <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName>, April 22, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> replied: “Appreciate the
                                report of conversation with <persName corresp="#p_TVH1">Huong</persName> (Saigon 727). It is good to hear that he
                                thinks he has some staying power. We certainly should do everything
                                possible to avoid any further unraveling of the government until we
                                hear from the Soviets. Without some appearance of steadiness, there
                                will be no chance at all to get anything going with the Soviets. As
                                I told you the other day, we have no other diplomatic game going at
                                the moment. The French are operating completely on their own.”
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName> Library, National
                                Security Adviser, Backchannel Messages, Box 3, <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">Martin</persName> Channel, April 1975,
                                Outgoing, 2)</note>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0924" n="883" xml:id="pg_883"/>
                        <p>5. Warmest regards.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MGA1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Martin</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>