<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>123. Report of the United States Delegation to the Tenth Session of the Third
                    United Nations Conference on the Law of the Sea</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v41</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1981-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1981-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97008889"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Law of the sea</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="reczz1d8j78JEEJZg" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031551"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Continental shelf</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p101XMcUG3dwi" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">Navigation rights</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recjJCaZf5dGFcK7n" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="law-of-the-sea" subject="territorial-sea-limit" lcsh-match="no_match">Territorial sea</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="123"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                <head>123. Report of the United States Delegation to the Tenth Session of the Third
                    United Nations Conference on the Law of the Sea<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d123fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_BDL_1"
                            >Bandow</persName> Files, Report of the U.S. Delegation to the Tenth
                        Session to the Third U.N. Conference to the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1"
                            >LOS</gloss>, March 9–April 24, 1981. Confidential. The document is a
                        classified supplement to an unclassified report of the U.S. Delegation.
                        (Ibid.) Attached but not printed is a “Drafting Committee Report: January
                        12–March 2, 1981.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1981-03-09" to="1981-04-24" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            >undated</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">March 9–April 24, 1981</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">ADDITIONAL COMMENTS ON REACTIONS TO THE U.S. REVIEW</p>
                <p>The overall reaction was cautious, although some developing country
                    representatives—like Venezuela—are evidencing very deep anger.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Union clearly sought to capitalize on the situation. It was an
                    excellent opportunity since the Soviet comments were relatively restrained, and
                    while the Soviet Union threatened us with voting in private, her public posture
                    was one of continuing support for consensus.</p>
                <p>The reaction among US allies was mixed. France was highly enthusiastic in
                    private, although its public positions were quite ambiguous, and her delegates
                    have warned us that she will stop short of overt confrontation with developing
                    countries. The German delegation in general sees our review as an opportunity to
                    obtain improvements in the text, and its Economics Ministry’s enthusiasm for our
                    review is evident to the entire Conference. At the other end of the spectrum,
                    Australia and New Zealand have openly defended the existing pack<pb facs="0415"
                        n="369" xml:id="pg_369"/>age, Australia stating that she has vital national
                    interests at stake in the treaty which the US action is undermining.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> tried to be supportive, but within the
                    context of existing instructions that favored the early completion of the treaty
                    based on the current text.<note n="2" xml:id="d123fn2">Not further
                        identified.</note> Japan was also ambiguous, although it is significant that
                    she received instructions from Tokyo to support us on the procedural question of
                    limiting the summer session to three or four weeks.</p>
                <p>Apparently seeking to discourage the view that the legitimacy of Second and Third
                    Committee texts can be maintained with or without a Convention, some delegations
                    have begun to make statements denying that there is a consensus on some of the
                    Second Committee texts relating to navigation and military uses of the sea.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d123fn3">Documents regarding the Second Committee and Third
                        Committee texts are scheduled for publication in <ref
                            target="frus1977-80v25">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XXV, Global
                            Issues; United Nations Issues</ref>.</note> Although in much more mild
                    and diplomatic form, one finds a similar theme in the opening statement by
                    Secretary General Waldheim that one cannot expect the stabilization in the law
                    of the sea represented by the current texts to be maintained if there is no
                        Convention.<note n="4" xml:id="d123fn4">In telegram 822 from New York, March
                        17, <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss> reported that Waldheim expressed
                        that “any disappointments or delays we are facing will soon be overcome.”
                        (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File, D810124–1128)</note>
                </p>
                <p>The main underlying question preoccupying the delegates is, and will remain,
                    whether to go ahead and vote through a Convention without U.S. support. The
                    factors affecting this decision will include:</p>
                <p>1. Foreign perceptions regarding the negotiability of any new U.S. proposals, and
                    the credibility of an Administration commitment to support ratification of a
                    treaty that accommodates its proposals;</p>
                <p>2. Whether the Soviet Union and a significant number of Western States are
                    willing to join the developing countries in such action; not only in terms of
                    voting, but in terms of ratification;</p>
                <p>3. The effect, if any, of such action by a large number of countries on bilateral
                    relations between the US and any one of those countries.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">COMMITTEE TWO</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The meetings of Committee Two reflected a strong desire to put pressure on the
                    U.S. not to propose changes in texts under the Committee’s mandate. This
                    pressure was reflected in three ways.</p>
                <p>1. Interventions by developing countries led by the Philippines, and
                    stage-managed by Peru, to require prior authorization and notification for
                    warships in the territorial sea, coastal State control of all installations and
                    structures on the continental shelf, and similar kinds of <pb facs="0416"
                        n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/> suggestions aimed at restricting military
                    activities. These interventions were stronger than in previous sessions.</p>
                <p>2. Interventions by other maritime powers and the Eastern Bloc to the general
                    effect that the fundamental elements of the Committee Two package had been
                    negotiated and should not be reopened.</p>
                <p>3. The summary by Chairman <persName corresp="#p_AAM_1">Aguilar</persName> to the
                    effect that there existed in the Committee a practical consensus along the basic
                    lines of the Committee Two package.<note n="5" xml:id="d123fn5">In telegram 914
                        from New York, March 25, <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss> reported
                        that <persName corresp="#p_AAM_1">Aguilar</persName> broached the topic of
                        voting on issues that could no longer be “completed, improved, or
                        perfected.” (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D810139–0761)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Of particular note was the effort by Cape Verde, supported by a substantial
                    number of delegations, for the establishment of a small working group to deal
                    with the warship issue, and also the strength of the attack mounted by Amb.
                    Arias-Schreiber of Peru. This attack was met head on with equal ferocity by the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, which took on Peru on both
                    procedural and substantive grounds.</p>
                <p>On the delimination issue, it was clear that no solution could be achieved at
                    this session, despite strong efforts by President <persName corresp="#p_KTT_1"
                        >Koh</persName> to pressure a solution. The lack of political will on the
                    part of the negotiators was laid in part on the nature of this particular
                    session in the light of the ongoing U.S. review process. Neither side wished to
                    proceed until such time as the U.S. was in a position to participate
                    actively.</p>
                <p>The Committee was held together, once again, by the strong and able leadership of
                    Amb. <persName corresp="#p_AAM_1">Aguilar</persName>. Interventions in plenary
                    on the record following his report were lengthy, followed the same lines as in
                    Committee debates, and constituted a clear indication that many coastal State
                    delegations were ready and willing to do battle on a number of military-related
                    issues should the text be reopened.<note n="6" xml:id="d123fn6">See <ref
                            target="#d123fn5">footnote 5</ref>, above.</note> Peru stated that there
                    was no consensus on certain contentious provisions such as Article 21.<note
                        n="7" xml:id="d123fn7">Article 21 refers to laws and regulations of the
                        coastal State regarding innocent passage.</note> The U.S. stated that our
                    views regarding navigation rights, including those of warships, and other uses
                    of the sea related to international peace and security were well known, and that
                    we reserved our position regarding any effort to alter these rights under
                    customary or conventional law.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">INFORMAL PLENARY</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Participation</p>
                <p>The most sensitive political question raised by the negotiations on participation
                    is the proposal of the Arabs, at least formally endorsed <pb facs="0417" n="371"
                        xml:id="pg_371"/> by the Group of 77, that liberation movements recognized
                    by the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> (in effect the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>) be permitted to sign and become party to the
                    Convention. We have received private hints that the Group of 77 might in the end
                    drop this position if it were agreed that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss>, which is an observer at the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1"
                        >LOS</gloss> Conference and other <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> organs,
                    would be permitted to retain its observer status at any organs set up by the
                        <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> Conference, and if—as in the case of
                    the recent Convention on the Law of War—the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>
                    were permitted to sign the Final Act of the Conference, perhaps on a separate
                    page. The US delegation did not indicate whether it could accept such a
                    result.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Dispute Settlement</p>
                <p>During the tenth session, the Chairman of the Drafting Committee, Ambassador
                    Beesley (Canada), asked his associate Armad deMestral (Canada) to explore the
                    possibility of convening a small group which could do some advance work in order
                    to facilitate the task of the Language Group and the Drafting Committee when
                    dealing with the dispute settlement parts of the Convention. Messrs. Caflisch
                    (Switzerland) and Allott (U.K.) prepared extensive lists of drafting changes
                    required in the French and English texts, respectively. Professor Sohn (U.S.)
                    was asked to join these exploratory talks.</p>
                <p>It proved difficult to reach agreement on the composition of a working group on
                    this subject and on the method of its creation. A preliminary exploration of the
                    problems involved in coordinating the text resulted immediately in extensive
                    debates on the character of the changes proposed (whether they were drafting or
                    substantive). Consequently, it was quickly agreed that the task was more
                    difficult than the proponents of this approach anticipated, and that no
                    shortcuts are possible. The only solution would be to allot sufficient time for
                    the discussion of dispute settlement texts at the next meeting of the
                    Committee.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
