<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>130. Telegram From the Mission to the United Nations to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v41</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d130</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">130</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1981-08-25T08:36:00-05:00" notAfter="1981-08-25T08:36:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft Convention</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110656"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Seabed</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-08-25T08:36:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-08-25T08:36:00-05:00" n="130"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d130">
                <head>130. Telegram From the Mission to the United Nations to the Department of
                        State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d130fn1">Source: Reagan Library,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BDL_1">Bandow</persName> Files, [<gloss
                            target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss>: June-August 1981 Cables]. Secret;
                        Immediate. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RLS_1">Ratiner</persName>;
                        cleared by <persName corresp="#p_MDS_1">MacDonald</persName>; approved by
                            <persName corresp="#p_MJL_1">Malone</persName>. Sent to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BDL_1">Bandow</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GMA_1"
                            >Guhin</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1981-08-25T13:36:00+00:00">August 25, 1981, 1336Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>8569. For Secretary from <persName corresp="#p_MJL_1">Malone</persName>. Subject:
                        <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> Conference Decision on Status of Text
                    and Future Work. Ref: Geneva 8552.<note n="2" xml:id="d130fn2">In telegram 8552
                        from Geneva, August 24, <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss> reported that
                        the Collegium to the General Committee had recommended that the text of the
                        draft convention be revised at the end of the Geneva session; that the
                        revised text no longer be considered informal; that a final intersessional
                        meeting be held in New York from January 18 until February 26, 1982; that a
                        final decisionmaking session be held from March 8 until April 30, 1982, in
                        New York; and that the convention be opened for signature in early September
                        1982. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D810396–0793)</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. (Secret–entire text)</p>
                <p>2. The <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> conference decided in plenary session
                    yesterday on the status of the draft convention and future sessions of the
                    conference. The full text was sent yesterday in Geneva’s 8552. The purpose of
                    this telegram is to analyze that conference decision.</p>
                <p>3. As G–77 and Soviet perceptions of the US position became more clear during
                    this session the desire to formalize the text became widespread. The original
                    arrangement we made with Brazil to keep this session of the conference under
                    control began to look uncertain for <pb facs="0438" n="392" xml:id="pg_392"/>
                        awhile.<note n="3" xml:id="d130fn3">In telegram 7865 from Geneva, August 3,
                            <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss> outlined a proposal from Brazil
                        wherein the “U.S. would agree now that at the end of this session the
                        President of the Conference would issue a new treaty text incorporating the
                        drafting committee’s changes. The new text would be labeled the ‘draft
                        convention on the Law of the Sea’ and the words ‘informal text’ would be
                        dropped from the title. On issuing the text the President would announce
                        that this new text could be changed or amended only in accordance with the
                        same rule of procedure applicable to earlier texts—the rule of consensus.
                        The new text thus would remain informal. If the U.S. agrees now to this
                        result, Brazil will undertake to ensure a quiet session giving ample time
                        for full discussion of the U.S. areas of concern in an atmosphere free of
                        rhetoric, threats of voting, or other G–77 induced crises.” (Department of
                        State, Central Foreign Policy File, D810463–0846)</note> By the middle of
                    last week the Eastern European, Asians, Latin Americans and African groups had
                    all taken decisions in favor of formalization. It was clear to us that these
                    decisions were taken out of the desire to send a message to Washington rather
                    than from a conviction that US concerns should be summarily dismissed.</p>
                <p>4. In the face of these developments, we were able to arrange for a private
                    dialogue last Sunday<note n="4" xml:id="d130fn4">August 23.</note> with many of
                    the conference leaders to put our position in as favorable a light as possible
                    and to urge that flexibility on their part would create a better atmosphere in
                    Washington for continued active participation next year. As a result of these
                    and other efforts it was possible on Monday<note n="5" xml:id="d130fn5">August
                        24.</note> to convert the conference decision reported in reftel 8852 into a
                    document which is in full compliance with our instructions.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d130fn6">Draft instructions and <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1"
                            >Haig</persName>’s comments are in <ref target="#d126">Document
                            126</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>5. The conference decision indicates that the text will have a higher status in
                    the future and characterizes it as the “official draft convention” of the
                    conference. Last minute negotiations yesterday with the conference leadership
                    resulted in removing the words “formal text” and this change is widely known at
                    the conference which improves the record from our point of view. The three
                    conditions explaining the status of the text make clear beyond question at the
                    conference that the text has no status different from the previous texts and
                    cannot be used as a launching platform for submitting formal amendments.<note
                        n="7" xml:id="d130fn7">See <ref target="#d130fn3">footnote 3</ref>,
                        above.</note> Moreover, this decision extends into the next session of the
                    conference.</p>
                <p>6. In order to further hold our feet to the fire, the conference decided that its
                    final decision-making sessions would take place in New York for eight weeks
                    beginning 8 March and the conference ordered the Secretary General of the United
                    Nations to arrange for the signature of the final action in Caracas in early
                    September 1982. It is our belief that if negotiations occur next year and we are
                    active participants with a position which is widely perceived to be tough but
                    reasonable, this <pb facs="0439" n="393" xml:id="pg_393"/> schedule could be
                    postponed until 1983. This view has been privately conveyed to us by the
                    coordinator of the Group of 77’s Contact Group on Seabed Mining Issues.<note
                        n="8" xml:id="d130fn8">Not further identified.</note>
                </p>
                <p>7. To the extent there is any perception that the text has a slightly higher
                    status than before, this tends to reinforce the navigational provisions of the
                    treaty in the event the conference ends without a successful result.</p>
                <p>8. We will be paying particular attention this week to the working out of the
                    work program for the next session of the conference to insure that we are not
                    faced with difficult or artificial deadlines which could hamper our negotiating
                    leverage if our final decision is to renegotiate the convention.</p>
                <p>9. We have consulted with all of our Western allies who agree that the conference
                    decision is an excellent result for fulfilling the collective wishes of the
                    CG–5. Moreover, because the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> completely
                    mishandled the debate over this conference decision,<note n="9" xml:id="d130fn9"
                        >In telegram 8742 from Geneva, August 28, <gloss target="#t_USUN_1"
                            >USUN</gloss> reported that “Soviet position during the session has been
                        unhelpful although in the end they were unable to do any actual damage. They
                        apparently believed the G–77 would decide to turn its back on the U.S. at
                        this session. As a result they publicly supported continued progress on
                        outstanding issues and formalization of the text at this session. Privately
                        they told us they would not create obstacles for the dialogue we sought and
                        would not oppose us on substance. In the final negotiations over
                        formalization of the text they found themselves isolated when the G–77
                        supported the compromise arrangement worked out with us.” (Department of
                        State, Central Foreign Policy File, D810405–0781)</note> the final
                    atmosphere at the conference is that the US and the G–77 managed by working
                    together to develop an approach for the future which left the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> in a corner, totally isolated from the
                    mainstream of the conference. The Soviet move in the debate was sufficiently
                    mismanaged so that by the end of the day yesterday, they were forced publicly to
                    concede that the Group of 77 did not want to formalize the draft convention
                    despite the strong push of the Eastern European countries to do so. The Soviets
                    persistent efforts to make propaganda points with the G–77 have conclusively
                    backfired to their clear disadvantage.</p>
                <p>10. The conference also decided not to extend this session into a fifth week. The
                    session will end on Friday, August 28.</p>
                <p>11. On balance, the entire US delegation is quite satisfied with the result.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Helman</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
