<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-01-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="137" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d137">
                        <head>137. Briefing Memorandum From Assistant Secretary of State for Oceans
                            and International Environmental and Scientific Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MJL_1">Malone</persName>) to Secretary of State
                                <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d137fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, P880121–0781. Secret; Sensitive. Cleared in
                                    <gloss target="#t_IO_1">IO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_PM_1">PM</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_AFI_1">AF/I</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>, L, <gloss target="#t_EARA_1">EA/RA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EB_1">EB</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EURRPE_1">EUR/RPE</gloss>, P, T, and E. “MAM”
                                initialed for all parties clearing the memorandum. A stamped
                                notation on the memorandum indicates <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> saw it.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-01-20">January 20, 1982</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>January 21, 1982 National Security Council Meeting on Law of the
                                Sea</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>A meeting of the National Security Council will be convened January 21,
                            1982 to consider future U.S. participation in the Law of the Sea
                            Conference. The following results should be sought at that meeting:</p>
                        <p>1. A decision to <hi rend="italic">continue to negotiate</hi> at the Law
                            of the Sea Conference.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Avoidance of any decision to require</hi> us to put
                            forward <hi rend="italic">in public an intransigent hardline
                                position</hi>. (This would be construed by the developing countries
                            as identical to a decision to withdraw from the Conference and would be
                            treated as such.)</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Avoidance of a decision which impairs our ability to
                                engage in ad referendum consultations</hi> with other countries
                            between now and the time final detailed instructions are prepared and
                            cleared within the government.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Avoidance of any decision which would have as its
                                underlying premise the assumption that the U.S. can (without first
                                trying to repair the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> treaty)
                                successfully transform any reciprocating states agreement into a
                                permanent alternative regime for seabed mining</hi> which would
                            fully protect our long range interest in access to deepsea minerals.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Agency Views</p>
                        <p>The Departments of Commerce, Defense, Energy, Labor, State,
                            Transportation, and Treasury, the Environmental Protection Agency, and
                            the National Science Foundation recommend continued participation in the
                            negotiations to fulfill these objectives. They recognize that, while
                            there is an opportunity to obtain substantial improvements, it will be
                            extremely difficult to satisfy all of the objectives. Fulfillment of
                            these objectives would be considered mandatory by the US delegation in
                            negotiations.</p>
                        <pb facs="0464" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/>
                        <p>The Department of the Interior supports returning to the negotiation but
                            wishes to instruct the delegation to deliver our “bottom-line” position
                            to the Conference in the form of an ultimatum.<note n="2" xml:id="d137fn2"><persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> wrote
                                “No way!” in the right-hand margin.</note> (see contingency talking
                            points, Attachment A)<note n="3" xml:id="d137fn3">Attached but not
                                printed. See <ref target="#d137fn5">footnote 5</ref>
                            below.</note></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_WJG_1">Jim Watt</persName>, Marty Anderson, Dick
                            Darman and <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Ed Meese</persName> may all
                            believe that we can withdraw now from the Conference and construct an
                            alternative regime that would be adequate if the law of the sea treaty
                            fails. Attachment B, <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> Conference
                            Strategies, is a response to their concerns.<note n="4" xml:id="d137fn4">Attached printed in an attachment to <ref target="#d136">Document
                                    136</ref>.</note> I believe it is important that you read that
                            paper in preparation for this meeting.</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">following issues may arise</hi> at the
                                meeting:<note n="5" xml:id="d137fn5">Talking points for each of
                                these issues are contained at Attachment A. The talking points for
                                the first issue are labelled “Opening Statement.” [Footnote is in
                                the original.]</note></p>
                        <p>—Should the U.S. withdraw from the Law of the Sea Conference immediately,
                            or continue to negotiate reserving until later its decision whether the
                            results of further negotiations are satisfactory?</p>
                        <p>—If the U.S. continues to negotiate, should U.S. negotiators put forward
                            a maximum set of demands and indicate no flexibility—a tactic which
                            produces a climate at the Conference which would ultimately encourage us
                            to withdraw?</p>
                        <p>—If the U.S. continues to negotiate, how should the delegation handle
                            urgent consultations during the balance of January and February while
                            instructions are being developed and cleared in the interagency
                                process?<note n="6" xml:id="d137fn6"><persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> wrote “ad ref” to the right of this
                                paragraph.</note></p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Strategy for the Meeting</p>
                        <p>The attached talking points provide you with a comprehensive opening
                            statement designed to meet the contentious issues likely to be raised
                            and set forth the Department’s perspective. <hi rend="italic">I
                                recommend that you cover all of those points at the outset</hi> and
                            seek to achieve a decision on the basis outlined in those points.
                            Additional <hi rend="italic">contingency talking points are provided for
                                use if more detailed discussions ensue</hi>.</p>
                        <p>As we have agreed, there is no justification for pursuing Option I at
                            this time. Withdrawal from the Conference can be accomplished after the
                            U.S. makes one last effort to improve the treaty to meet its needs.
                            Accordingly, <hi rend="italic">if the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> seems to be moving toward an Option I
                            decision</hi>, every effort available should be made to <hi rend="italic">avoid a final decision <pb facs="0465" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/> pending further informal discussions</hi> with
                            the President and senior White House staff.</p>
                        <p>If the group presses on precisely how we could change the treaty, under
                            Option II, to protect our interests, you might refer them to our paper
                            on the subject (at Tab D).<note n="7" xml:id="d137fn7">Not attached. An
                                undated paper entitled “Implementation of Option II” was sent to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NJW_1">Nance</persName> under a December
                                17 covering memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Bremer</persName>. (Reagan Library, Guhin, Michael A.: Files,
                                12/18/81 [1])</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>