<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-07-23T06:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-07-23T06:45:00-05:00" n="169" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d169">
                        <head>169. Telegram From the Embassy in Belgium to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d169fn1">Source: Reagan
                                Library, Guhin, Michael A.: Files, <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> (Law of the Sea) Reciprocating States Agreement
                                (4). Confidential; Immediate. Sent for information to Bonn. Sent to
                                    <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss> Geneva, London, and
                                Paris. Printed from a copy that was received in the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Message Center.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Brussels</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-07-23T11:45:00+00:00">July 23, 1982,
                                1145Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>9924. From <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> Del for <gloss target="#t_OES_1">OES</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_DAS_1">DAS</gloss> Klonmiller, <gloss target="#t_EB_1">EB</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_DAS_1">DAS</gloss> Calingaert, L Robinson, Dept pass
                            Commerce NOAA/GC. Geneva pass drafting committee Rep Asher. Subject:
                            Reciprocating States Arrangements.</p>
                        <p>1. Confidential—Entire text.</p>
                        <p>2. Consultations were held July 21–22 among US, <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> and French Reps to
                            review draft agreement concerning interim arrangement relating to
                            polymetallic nodules of the deep seabed.</p>
                        <p>3. Text of agreement, not including schedule and annexes, as developed
                            during these negotiations, is contained in para 12 below. Full draft
                            text will be brought to Washington July 23 by US Del member Mary McLeod.
                            With exceptions noted below, there is virtual agreement on text on
                            schedule and annexes and no controversial issues remain.</p>
                        <pb facs="0537" n="491" xml:id="pg_491"/>
                        <p>4. Except for para 8(1)(C) of Part I (see para 10 below), <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>, France and <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> Del were close to ad referendum agreement on text of
                            agreement. <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> could probably agree to
                            text as is or to any reasonable compromise acceptable to others. If
                            solution to para four of agreement is found, <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> will probably agree to text essentially along lines
                            contained para 12 below. France has reserved on several articles and may
                            seek further changes, but except for para four of agreement, all French
                            problems seem capable of quick resolution.</p>
                        <p>5. Main problem during negotiations—and only serious outstanding
                            issue—has been French-<gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> insistence on
                            provision that no <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> could enter into
                            force prior to beginning of January 1983. French-<gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> aim has been to prevent US from
                            negotiating <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> with another country
                            (read <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>) which would enter into force
                            prior to December Caracas <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss>
                                meeting.<note n="2" xml:id="d169fn2">The concluding sessions for the
                                treaty were moved from Caracas to Montego Bay, Jamaica.</note>
                            (During course of negotiations, French/<gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> attempted to block us even from concluding <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> during next few months but gave that
                            effort up in face of strong US and <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                            opposition.) In proposed text, France and <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> would agree to accept in a formal public document
                            possibility of negotiating <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> with US
                            between now and January 1, 1982. This, they have argued, keeps door for
                                <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> open and does not close options
                            for any party. French and <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> Dels
                            repeatedly expressed concern that US might pressure them to conclude
                                <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> in near term before they have
                            completed their <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> review. This, they
                            allege, could drive them into <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss>
                            Treaty. In return for postponing such pressure until 1983, they will
                            agree to consult with us before announcing any decision on <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> as well as accepting publicly
                            possibility of negotiating an <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> with
                            US.</p>
                        <p>6. US Del expressed strong objection to this approach. US Reps attempted
                            to delete provision, to move up date before which <gloss target="#t_RSA_1">RSA</gloss> could not enter into force (e.g.
                            December 1982) or to make commitment reciprocal by requiring other
                            parties to agree not to take any action on <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> Treaty during same period. All US efforts to delete or
                            amend this provision met very strong opposition from French and <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> Reps. US Del agreed to submit text of
                            paragraph four to Washington for review but did not agree to text even
                            on ad referendum basis.</p>
                        <p>7. Comment. In US Del view, if US agrees to provision contained in para
                            four of agreement (see below) or along these lines, it would be possible
                            to conclude agreement quickly. All other outstanding issues can probably
                            be resolved. On other hand, if US insists on deletion or significant
                            change in para four, such as changing January 3 date, it <pb facs="0538" n="492" xml:id="pg_492"/> seems likely that <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> and France will refuse to sign. US Del recognizes that
                            such provision would substantially reduce value of agreement. End
                            comment.</p>
                        <p>8. French have so far reserved on para five of the agreement. French may
                            also wish to add provisions requiring parties to implement results of
                            private industry arbitration procedures. US Reps pointed out US
                            difficulties with this approach and French may not insist. French and
                            Germans have insisted on six months denunciation clause (para eleven of
                            agreement). US asked for thirty day clause. We expect that this issue
                            can be resolved if, and when, para four is settled.</p>
                        <p>9. Agreement contains no accession clause. French Rep pressed for
                            limiting parties to US, <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> and France. <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>, with US support, urged that potential parties include
                            Italy, Belgium, Japan and Netherlands and, possibly, Canada. We expect
                            France ultimately to agree to this view.</p>
                        <p>10. Para 8(1)(c) of Part I (application procedures) has not been agreed
                            upon. US Del proposed that provision read that each party shall accept
                            amendments to applications to which agreement applies only if amendments
                            are filed between July 23 and October 15, 1982, consistent with US
                            regulations. Other dels argued strongly that October 15 date was too
                            early and later date should be substituted or deleted.</p>
                        <p>11. Group of Four will meet in Geneva on Monday, July 26 at 10:00 a.m. in
                            attempt to reach agreement on a text which can be given to likeminded
                            July 27.<note n="3" xml:id="d169fn3">In telegram 7771 from Geneva, July
                                28, <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss> reported on the July 27
                                negotiating session. (Department of State, Marine Law and Policy
                                Division, Subject and Country Files, Law of the Sea, 1981–1982, Lot
                                92D622, 50.12–Background—Sept 2 Agreement) [C] In telegram 7733 from
                                Geneva, July 27, <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss> transmitted
                                the text that the U.S., British, West German, and French delegations
                                had agreed upon. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D820389–0709)[U]</note> If agreement on text can be reached next
                            week, all four countries will undertake to complete internal review and
                            processing of agreement as expeditiously as possible, aiming toward
                            signature by end of August at latest. It was clear that <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss> and France, in particular, wish to
                            avoid signing agreement too close to <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> September plenary.</p>
                        <p>12. Following is text of draft agreement.</p>
                        <p>Begin Text</p>
                        <p>The parties to this agreement:</p>
                        <p>—Having regard to investments made in exploration, research and other
                            pioneer activities relating to the polymetallic nodules of the deep sea
                            bed;</p>
                        <pb facs="0539" n="493" xml:id="pg_493"/>
                        <p>—Noting the adoption by the Third Nations Conference on the Law of the
                            Sea of a Convention on the Law of the Sea and of a resolution governing
                            preparatory investment in pioneer activities relating to polymetallic
                            nodules prior to the entry into force of the Convention on the Law of
                            the Sea, and the provision of that resolution concerning resolution of
                            conflicts among pioneer operators;</p>
                        <p>—Recalling the interim character of legislation with respect to deep sea
                            bed operations enacted by certain parties;</p>
                        <p>—Desiring to make appropriate provisions for avoiding overlaps in the
                            areas claimed for future pioneer activities in the deep sea bed and to
                            ensure that, during the interim period, such activities are carried out
                            in an orderly and peaceful manner;</p>
                        <p>—Emphasizing that this arrangement is without prejudice to the decisions
                            of the parties with respect to the Convention on the Law of the Sea
                            adopted by the Third Nations Conference on the Law of the Sea;</p>
                        <p>—Desiring also to avoid any discrimination among parties in the
                            implementation of this agreement;</p>
                        <p>—Desiring further to ensure that adequate areas containing polymetallic
                            nodules remain available for operations by other states and entities in
                            conformity with international law;</p>
                        <p>Have agreed as follows:</p>
                        <p>1. The object of the present agreement is to facilitate the
                            identification and resolution of conflicts which may arise from the
                            filing and processing of applications for authorizations made by
                            pre-enactment explorers (<gloss target="#t_PEES_1">PEES</gloss>) on or
                            before 12 March 1982 under legislation in respect of deep sea bed
                            operations enacted by any of the parties.</p>
                        <p>2. In the case of a conflict between the areas claimed in such
                            applications, the parties shall afford the applicants adequate
                            opportunity, and shall encourage them, to resolve such conflict in a
                            timely manner by voluntary procedures.</p>
                        <p>3. The parties with whom the applications for authorizations have been
                            made by <gloss target="#t_PEES_1">PEES</gloss> on or before 12 March
                            1982 shall follow the procedures set out in Part I of the schedule
                            hereto in respect of applications to which this agreement applies.</p>
                        <p>4. The parties shall consult together:</p>
                        <quote><p>(A) With a view to coordinating and reviewing implementation of
                                this agreement;</p>
                            <p>(B) Before issuing any authorization under their respective laws
                                relating to deep sea bed operations;</p>
                            <p>(C) In regard to consideration of any arrangement to facilitate
                                mutual recognition of such authorisations, it being understood that
                                any such arrangement shall not enter into force before January 1,
                                1983.</p>
                            <p>(D) Before entering into any other bilateral or any multilateral
                                arrangement between themselves or any arrangement with other states,
                                with respect to deep sea bed operations.</p></quote>
                        <pb facs="0540" n="494" xml:id="pg_494"/>
                        <p>5. In the event that any two or more of the parties enter into an
                            agreement for the mutual recognition of authorisations granted under
                            their respective laws in respect of deep sea bed operations, the parties
                            concerned shall when necessary apply the procedures and impose the
                            requirements set out in Part II of the schedule hereto.</p>
                        <p>6. To the extent permissible under national law, a party shall maintain
                            the confidentiality of the coordinates of application areas and other
                            proprietary or confidential commercial information received in
                            confidence from any other party in pursuance of cooperation under this
                            agreement in accordance with the principles set out in Part III of the
                            schedule hereto.</p>
                        <p>7. The parties shall settle any dispute arising from the interpretation
                            or application of this agreement by appropriate means. The parties to
                            the dispute shall consider the possibility of recourse to binding
                            arbitration and, if they agree, shall have recourse to it.</p>
                        <p>8. The schedule hereto is an integral part of this agreement and Part IV
                            thereof shall apply for the interpretation of this agreement.</p>
                        <p>9. This agreement may be amended by written agreement of all the
                            parties.</p>
                        <p>10. This agreement shall enter into force upon signature.</p>
                        <p>11. Any party may denounce this agreement bracket on six months notice
                            and bracket to the government of the United States of America.</p>
                        <p>[12.] Done at Washington in the English, French and German languages, all
                            three texts being equally authentic, in a single copy which shall be
                            deposited in the Archives of the Government of the United States of
                            America, which will transmit a duly certified copy to each of the other
                            signatory governments.</p>
                        <p>End text.</p>
                        <p>13. Action requested. Please provide guidance in particular on para four
                            issue. Such guidance should, if possible, be received at US Mission
                            Geneva by opening of business July 26. <gloss target="#t_USDel_1">USDel</gloss> feels that final <gloss target="#t_FRG_1">FRG</gloss>-French position on para four is on table. We note French
                            have now modified position to some degree and made some concessions. It
                            is view of <gloss target="#t_USDel_1">USDel</gloss> that French will not
                            move further on substance. Dept. should decide therefore, whether an
                            agreement as set out above is worth written commitment not to have
                            reciprocity agreement enter into force before January 3, 1983.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Price</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>