<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-08-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="171" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d171">
                        <head>171. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d171fn1">Source:
                                Reagan Library, Papers of <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George P.
                                    Shultz</persName>, Law of the Sea. Confidential. There is no
                                indication on the memorandum that <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> saw it.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-08-10">August 10, 1982</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Law of the Sea</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I am transmitting herewith the proposed action plan for US efforts to
                            establish an alternative deep seabed mining regime, as decided upon by
                            the designated Interagency Group (<gloss target="#t_IG_1">IG</gloss>). I
                            agree with the <gloss target="#t_IG_1">IG</gloss>’s recommended action
                            plan except for the recommendation that you personally initiate contacts
                            with other governments on the action plan.</p>
                        <p>I believe that you should not become involved at this initial stage
                            because we want to reserve your intervention and capital for later
                            stages in the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> dialogue and for
                            other major issues. I will urge our allies not to make premature
                            commitments to sign the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> Convention
                            pending the arrival of a special U.S. emissary in early September.</p>
                        <p>I recommend that Under Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_BJL_2">Jim Buckley</persName> be chosen as your emissary because of his
                            familiarity with <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> issues and with
                            the European leaders he would be calling upon, and because his rank will
                            help underscore presidential interest in the issue.</p>
                        <pb facs="0543" n="497" xml:id="pg_497"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head><hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared in the Department of
                                    State</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d171fn2">Confidential.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" when="1982-08-10">undated</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">Law of the Sea Policy</p>
                            <p rend="center">Action Plan to Establish an Alternative</p>
                            <p rend="center">Deep Seabed Mining Regime</p>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> 43 directs the Department of
                                State, in coordination with the interested agencies and the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_OPD_1">OPD</gloss> staff, to
                                prepare an action plan to establish an alternative deep seabed
                                mining arrangement outside the Law of the Sea Convention.<note n="3" xml:id="d171fn3">See <ref target="#d168">Document
                                    168</ref>.</note> Following are the recommendations on near-term
                                actions to establish such an arrangement.</p>
                            <p>All concerned agencies recommend that we initiate this plan of action
                                immediately.</p>
                            <p>Our short-term objectives would be to:</p>
                            <quote><p>• dissuade our allies from making or announcing a decision to
                                    sign the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> Convention or
                                    other action that would prejudice our ability to work out an
                                    alternative seabed mining arrangement and, most importantly, not
                                    to make any commitment to ratify the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> treaty.</p>
                                <p>• engage in a dialogue with our allies and possibly other
                                    countries on the serious problems in the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> seabed mining regime and,
                                    thus, the need for and benefit of an alternative regime; at the
                                    same time, elicit their concerns about protection outside of the
                                        <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> Convention of their
                                    other oceans interests.</p></quote>
                            <p>Our longer-term objective is to convince our allies and other nations
                                not to ratify the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> treaty but,
                                instead, to join us in an alternative regime.</p>
                            <p>If we are to achieve our objectives, the President must be involved
                                in this effort. Head of government to head of government contacts
                                are vital to initiate the action plan and may be necessary again as
                                we implement it. A presidential communication to London, Bonn,
                                Paris, Rome, Brussels, The Hague, and Tokyo should be made as soon
                                as possible. This message would underscore the serious problems of
                                the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> treaty and forecast the
                                arrival of an emissary.</p>
                            <p>A presidential envoy would be sent to foreign capitals in early
                                September. He should be of high rank and be prepared to discuss
                                these <pb facs="0544" n="498" xml:id="pg_498"/> matters with foreign
                                officials of ministerial rank. The envoy would: be prepared with
                                instructions and supporting materials appropriate to the political
                                level contacts he will make; seek to obtain a political commitment
                                from our allies to defer decisions on signing the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> treaty while we explore means of
                                satisfying our law of the sea interests outside of the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> treaty; outline our problems with
                                the <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> seabed mining regime and
                                our proposals for an alternative deep seabed mining regime;
                                emphasize that such a regime, if widely accepted by the seabed
                                mining states, would create a viable legal and practical
                                alternative; and sound out their concerns on non-seabeds <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> issues to enable us to focus
                                clearly our subsequent contacts. After the emissary’s initial
                                visits, further consultations would include appropriate <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> experts.</p>
                            <p>The emissary should initially visit the Federal Republic of Germany,
                                the United Kingdom, France, Japan, Belgium, Italy and the
                                Netherlands. A second tier of countries might, subsequently, be
                                approached by the same or another appropriate emissary.</p>
                            <p>By August 14 the preparatory work for the presidential communication
                                and emissary visits will be completed. This would include:</p>
                            <quote><p>• a draft communication from the President;</p>
                                <p>• instructions for the emissary with talking points; and</p>
                                <p>• background material appropriate for the political nature of the
                                    emissary’s contacts. This paper will include an outline of an
                                    alternative regime and background to enable the emissary to
                                    sound out the concerns of the allies on non-seabed
                                issues.</p></quote>
                            <p>Within this period, suggestions on the emissary will be forwarded to
                                the White House.</p>
                            <p>During the implementation of this action plan we must take advantage
                                of the Secretary of State’s and other cabinet officers’ contacts
                                with their foreign counterparts to press our <gloss target="#t_LOS_1">LOS</gloss> concerns. This effort should be
                                coordinated carefully to ensure that cabinet officers are prepared
                                properly and their contacts used to our fullest advantage.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>