<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-07-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="221" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d221">
                        <head>221. National Security Decision Directive 143<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d221fn1">Source: Reagan Library, African Affairs
                                Directorate, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>: Records, <gloss target="#t_AF_1">AF</gloss> Famine [05/20/84–09/30/84].
                                Confidential.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1984-07-09">July 9, 1984</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">U.S. Third World Hunger Relief: Emergency Assistance
                            (U)</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> 1–84<note n="2" xml:id="d221fn2">See <ref target="#d218">Document 218</ref>.</note> established the
                            terms of reference for a study aimed at producing new, effective
                            initiatives to address Third World hunger problems; that is, both
                            emergency situations and longer-term problems and how U.S. and donor
                            country food aid programs affect these cases. (C)</p>
                        <pb facs="0650" n="604" xml:id="pg_604"/>
                        <p>The study of the emergency food aid situation focused on how to reduce
                            the loss of life caused by grave food crises in the Third World.<note n="3" xml:id="d221fn3">See <ref target="#d219">Document 219</ref>
                                and attachment thereto.</note> This study has reviewed initiatives
                            to meet the following objectives: to respond more rapidly in delivering
                            food to Third World countries experiencing food crises; to distribute
                            food in-country more effectively; to improve the quality of
                            food/transport/distribution information and methods of forecasting acute
                            food crises; to seek greater international cooperation to deal
                            effectively with acute hunger problems through existing public and
                            private fora; to increase public, business and foreign awareness of U.S.
                            hunger relief programs and the hunger problem in the Third World; and to
                            seek greater international cooperation in response to acute hunger
                            problems. (C)</p>
                        <p>In order to meet these objectives to help reduce loss of life caused by
                            acute food crises, ten actions are to be taken as recommended by the
                                <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> 1–84 Study Group:</p>
                        <p>1) The prepositioning of P.L. 480 Title II grain in selected Third World
                            areas for immediate distribution in a starvation situation.</p>
                        <p>2) The establishment of a special no-year, $50 million Presidential fund
                            to permit timely response to aggravated food situations.<note n="4" xml:id="d221fn4">In a June 21 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_MRC_1">McFarlane</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LRB_1">Levine</persName> wrote: “<persName corresp="#p_MMP_1">Peter McPherson</persName> has never
                                supported the Third World Hunger Relief Study,” adding, “<persName corresp="#p_MMP_1">McPherson</persName> will state that this $50
                                million fund should not, as the <gloss target="#t_NSDD_1">NSDD</gloss> states, be funded from our existing budgets. In
                                fact, the $50 million can come from windfalls from shippings savings
                                with our current P.L. 480 program that amount to that sum. Also our
                                P.L. 480 grant program has increased from $515 million in 1982 to
                                $800 million in 1984. There is clearly money for the Presidential
                                fund. <persName corresp="#p_MMP_1">McPherson</persName>, however, is
                                trying to use up the shipping windfall money for <hi rend="italic">non</hi>-emergency food aid programs so that the money may not
                                be applied to our Presidential fund concept. <persName corresp="#p_MMP_1">McPherson</persName>, I understand, is also
                                telling the <persName corresp="#p_HAA_1">Hill</persName> that
                                creation of a Presidential fund <hi rend="italic">within</hi>
                                existing resources will soak up $50 million that would otherwise go
                                into the mouths of the hungry. In fact, if we submit legislation on
                                our initiatives early, as is our intent, the fund will speed matters
                                up.” (Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_RAP_1">Rosenberg</persName> Files, Food for Progress—<persName corresp="#p_KRB_1">Keating</persName> Group [Famine]
                                06/07/1984–08/06/1984)</note></p>
                        <p>3) The amortization of ocean freight charges for P.L. 480 Title I food
                            aid in certain special cases.</p>
                        <p>4) The paying of in-country distribution costs of P.L. 480 Title II
                            emergency food aid for certain of the poorest Third World countries to
                            permit an effective distribution of food aid.</p>
                        <p>5) The refinement of USDA and <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>
                            analytical methods for better estimates of Third World emergency food
                            needs.</p>
                        <p>6) The formation of an interagency Emergency Food Needs Research Working
                            Group, chaired by USDA under the Development Coordination Committee, to
                            develop better analytical techniques and data bases for gauging
                            emergency food requirements and forecasting acute food crises. This
                            group would also consider coordinating steps <pb facs="0651" n="605" xml:id="pg_605"/> with other donor governments and international
                            food organizations on the assessment of emergency food needs.
                            Transportation bottlenecks and inefficiencies should be reviewed with
                            appropriate recommendations forwarded.</p>
                        <p>7) A Special Planning Group meeting on Public Diplomacy is to be held to
                            establish a White House-directed public information program, in
                            conjunction with this year’s observance of the 30th anniversary of P.L.
                            480, to increase U.S. and foreign awareness of <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> food aid initiatives and the nature of the Third World
                            hunger problem.</p>
                        <p>8) The formation of a Third World Food Problems Subcommittee under the
                            State Department’s Advisory Committee on International Investment,
                            Technology and Development, to permit business leaders to share
                            information on Third World hunger problems and to address these concerns
                            in a cooperative manner.</p>
                        <p>9) The <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> 1–84 Working Group will
                            continue to study and clarify what type of coordination, cooperation or
                            actions the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> should seek from other
                            donor governments and international organizations on the emergency food
                            aid problem. This study shall be completed within 2 months with
                            appropriate actions recommended.<note n="5" xml:id="d221fn5">Reference
                                is presumably to <ref target="#d236">Document 236</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>10) The noted study on international cooperation will, in particular,
                            consider recommending a high-level donors meeting or other similar
                            measures to improve international coordination in effectively meeting
                            food aid emergencies. Negotiations and communications with other
                            countries on these matters shall continue through existing, approved
                            methods. (C)</p>
                        <p>These ten actions are designed to improve the efficiency of the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>’s emergency food aid programs. Funding
                            for these ten initiatives will thus come from the projected assistance
                            budgets for fiscal years FY 85 and beyond. An <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss>-chaired interagency task force, under the <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> 1–84 Working Group, will take steps
                            to ensure the timely implementation of these actions. (C)</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"><hi rend="strong">Ronald
                                        Reagan</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>