<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-12-12T19:20:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-12-12T19:20:00-05:00" n="230" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d230">
                        <head>230. Telegram From the Department of State to Secretary of State
                                <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>’s Delegation in
                                Lisbon<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d230fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Subject Files, <persName corresp="#p_DEJ_1">Edward J.
                                    Derwinski</persName>, 1982–1985, Lot 87D258, Famine Relief in
                                Africa. Secret; Nodis. Drafted by LeCocq; cleared in AF/E, <gloss target="#t_AFRA_1">AF/RA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_AF_1">AF</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EURSOV_1">EUR/SOV</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>, C, P, and <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1">Armacost</persName>. Sent to Moscow, <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss>, Addis Ababa, London, Rome,
                                Ottawa, and Khartoum.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1984-12-13T00:20:00+00:00">December 13, 1984,
                                0020Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>366048. Subject: Approach to Soviets on Ethiopian Food Truce.</p>
                        <p>1. S—Entire text.</p>
                        <p>2. Summary and action requested. Dept has decided to make a demarche to
                            the Soviets asking their support for greater free passage of food within
                            Ethiopia. Paragraph 7 of this message contains talking points for use by
                            Ambassador Hartman or <gloss target="#t_DCM_1">DCM</gloss> with highest
                            available Soviet Foreign Ministry official. Paragraph 8 contains points
                            to be used by Embassy Addis to inform the Ethiopians on our various
                            approaches on this subject, including informing them of the Soviet
                            demarche. End summary.</p>
                        <p>3. Background: Given increasingly dire humanitarian needs in Ethiopia and
                            to ease refugee burdens in Sudan and persistent political obstacles to
                            effective delivery of emergency assistance to affected population in
                            Ethiopia, Dept believes it is necessary to investigate fully and
                            urgently the possibility for some sort of a “safe passage” arrangement
                            agreed on by both the Central Government and insurgents.</p>
                        <p>At least three million people, perhaps a majority of those affected by
                            the current drought in Ethiopia, are behind rebel lines and have been
                            receiving only marginal assistance through Ethiopian Government feeding
                            centers and through unpublicized cross-border operations from Sudan. The
                            situation has deteriorated rapidly, with as many as 1700 people in
                            insurgent areas of Eritrea, Tigre and Welo dying each day. Mass
                            migrations are underway, perhaps of several hundred thousand, to Sudan.
                            Both sides appear to have taken actions, for political reasons, which
                            impede the delivery of food to people in need. This is an extremely
                            pressing issue. For example, there have been recent reports that
                            Ethiopian MiGs strafed people migrating from insurgent areas to Sudan.
                            It is essential to provide safe passage for people migrating to Sudan
                            and those walking to feeding centers inside Ethiopia as well as for
                            private voluntary organization (<gloss target="#t_PVO_1">PVO</gloss>)
                            convoys and flights making deliveries in contested areas. We also need
                            Ethiopian agreement not to impede additional, perhaps massive
                            cross-border deliveries into insurgent areas from Sudan. Although
                            Mengistu has said publicly he will not agree to negotiate with
                            “bandits,” and the government has <pb facs="0667" n="621" xml:id="pg_621"/> up to now formally objected to our cross-border
                            feeding programs, both sides have already acceded to free passage by the
                                <gloss target="#t_ICRC_1">ICRC</gloss> and there have been some
                            indications in private from both sides that they would not impede actual
                            deliveries by other PVOs.</p>
                        <p>4. To help address this problem, we have underway a series of diplomatic
                            actions designed to call the attention of the world community to the
                            problem and to encourage the various parties in Ethiopia to enter into
                            de facto safe passage arrangements. We anticipate that implementation
                            would be left to a neutral party such as the <gloss target="#t_ICRC_1">ICRC</gloss> and/or other PVOs. Our plan of action includes an
                            initial approach to the <gloss target="#t_ICRC_1">ICRC</gloss>, the
                            Pope, and <gloss target="#t_UNSYG_1">UNSYG</gloss>, urging them to speak
                            out both privately and publicly for a program of humanitarian safe
                            passage and ultimately to involve other figures in the effort to bring
                            pressure on both the Ethiopian Government and guerrilla forces.</p>
                        <p>5. Given the Soviet Union’s political influence with Chairman Mengistu,
                            we want the Soviets to urge him to cooperate in more complete free
                            passage of food. Mengistu’s planned December 13 visit to Moscow presents
                            us a unique opportunity to urge Soviet cooperation. Dept recognizes that
                            the Soviets would normally be unlikely to press re the Ethiopian leader.
                            On the other hand, <persName corresp="#p_CKU_1">Chernenko</persName>’s
                            statement in his November 16 interview with Marvin Kalb that one area
                            for possible US-Soviet regional cooperation would be drought relief, at
                            least provides us a handle to make an approach. The Soviets may have
                            reasons (e.g. embarrassment at the dilemma of their client state and at
                            the Soviet lack of capability to provide massive help) to encourage
                            cooperation between the rebels and the government. An additional
                            incentive for the Soviets could be our willingness to cooperate in more
                            direct Soviet participation in the larger donor network headed by the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>. We are not interested in
                            offering the Soviets a joint US–<gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>
                            effort in relief activities which would enable Moscow to piggyback on
                            much larger Western response. But we are testing Moscow’s bona fides in
                            asking their help on this key problem where they have clear
                            influence.</p>
                        <p>6. We will inform the Ethiopians in advance of Mengistu’s trip that we
                            are contacting numerous parties, including the Soviets, to gain
                            international support for a safe passage arrangement. Informing the
                            Ethiopians of our talks with the Soviets will prevent the latter from
                            purposely distorting our approach in such a manner as to damage our
                            efforts to pursue a broader political dialogue with Ethiopia. In short,
                            we see cooperation with the Soviets in food relief as important given
                            the situation on the ground, but do not want to enable the Soviets to
                            use this to play a larger role in the Horn.</p>
                        <p>7. Following talking points for use by Ambassador Hartman or <gloss target="#t_DCM_1">DCM</gloss> on an urgent basis (we would like to
                            get to the Soviets prior to Mengistu’s arrival in Moscow on the
                            13th).</p>
                        <pb facs="0668" n="622" xml:id="pg_622"/>
                        <p>—We are concerned that food relief efforts have been seriously hampered
                            by hostilities, especially in the Eritrea and Tigre insurgent areas.</p>
                        <p>—There are continuing reports that the various political elements in
                            Ethiopia, both government and anti-government, are for political reasons
                            hindering in various ways the free movement of food, and of people
                            seeking food.</p>
                        <p>—In order to avert further mass starvation, we believe it might be
                            possible to arrive at some sort of temporary modus vivendi among the
                            parties which would allow free passage of food and other humanitarian
                            relief to all areas of the country and all segments of the
                            population.</p>
                        <p>—It is not only the United States which is concerned and which sees the
                            need for some sort of safe passage arrangement. International
                            organizations, private voluntary agencies and other donor nations share
                            this view.</p>
                        <p>—The Soviet Union is in a unique position, considering its interests in
                            Ethiopia and its role in the Ethiopian relief effort to use its
                            influence with the <gloss target="#t_PMGSE_1">PMGSE</gloss> in favor of
                            such an agreement. We note that Chairman Mengistu will soon be visiting
                            the Soviet Union. In this context, we note that Chairman <persName corresp="#p_CKU_1">Chernenko</persName>, in his November 16 NBC
                            interview with Marvin Kalb, suggested drought relief as a potential area
                            of U.S.-Soviet regional cooperation.</p>
                        <p>—We recognize that neither side in the conflict will likely accede to a
                            general cease-fire. We hope, therefore, that the Ethiopian Government
                            will agree to a de facto safe passage arrangement, whereby food
                            deliveries and people in search of food are not hindered and that food
                            can be delivered in the most direct and efficient manner including from
                            Sudan. We would expect that deliveries would be conducted by apolitical
                            private voluntary organizations to be agreed to by all parties.</p>
                        <p>—The United States interest in safe passage is humanitarian. Our only
                            role in this matter is support for this concept, which has been espoused
                            by several international leaders and the media.</p>
                        <p>—The <gloss target="#t_PMGSE_1">PMGSE</gloss> is aware of our concerns
                            and the need to facilitate food distribution, and we are in touch with
                            other interested parties.</p>
                        <p>—The United States encourages the Soviet Union, in addition to continuing
                            its deliveries of food within Ethiopia, to participate more directly
                            with the donor community in Ethiopia and with the efforts of United
                            Nations Secretary General Special Representative in Ethiopia Kurt
                            Jannson.</p>
                        <p>8. For Addis: Charge should use following points with <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_RRC_1">RRC</gloss> Commissioner <persName corresp="#p_DWG_1">Dawit</persName> prior to Mengistu’s departure for Moscow:</p>
                        <p>—The United States notes the considerable mention being made by the media
                            and international leaders such as Willy Brandt of the <pb facs="0669" n="623" xml:id="pg_623"/> need for a “safe passage” arrangement for
                            food deliveries and for people looking for food.</p>
                        <p>—We feel that some sort of arrangement needs to be made by the Ethiopian
                            parties to facilitate the dispersing of food to all areas and to permit
                            safe passage as well to people in search of food.</p>
                        <p>[The United States?] recognizes and supports the territorial integrity of
                            Ethiopia. We have no desire to interfere with Ethiopia’s internal
                            affairs.</p>
                        <p>—We are aware of Chairman Mengistu’s desire not to enter into
                            negotiations with insurgents. This does not preclude, however, an
                            informal or de facto arrangement whereby each side agrees not to impede
                            the flow of drought victims in search of food or food deliveries. We
                            recall Commissioner <persName corresp="#p_DWG_1">Dawit</persName>’s
                            agreement in the November 2 government-to-government agreement to
                            additional efforts to make food available to all parts of Ethiopia.<note n="2" xml:id="d230fn2">Not further identified.</note></p>
                        <p>—The United States, for its part, maintains its policy of delinking food
                            from politics. Our interest has been and remains assisting Ethiopians in
                            need. We and other donors are concerned that large numbers of Ethiopians
                            in northern area of fighting are not being reached. This problem is of
                            such major concern that it is rapidly becoming the number one problem in
                            Ethiopia and in the concern of the media.</p>
                        <p>—We applaud the Government of Ethiopia’s efforts to assist the drought
                            and famine situation, coordinating with donors, and improving logistics.
                            In that same spirit, we would appreciate any ideas or suggestions by the
                                <gloss target="#t_PMGSE_1">PMGSE</gloss> as to how a safe passage
                            arrangement can be obtained to get food to insurgent as well as
                            government-controlled areas. We need to consider de facto agreements to
                            safe passage of food, free movement of people seeking food, and
                            agreement on new routes for delivering food.</p>
                        <p>—This problem needs to be addressed urgently in light of the increasingly
                            desperate situation in unreachable parts of northern Ethiopia, recent
                            reports of innocent drought victims being caught in the crossfire, and
                            charges that political considerations are involved by various parties to
                            the fighting in food delivery or non-delivery.</p>
                        <p>—In view of the role the Soviets are playing in the relief effort, we are
                            also raising this with them as well as with the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>, other donors, and humanitarian leaders and
                            organizations.</p>
                        <p>9. For Geneva: You should draw on paras 3 and 4 to alert <gloss target="#t_ICRC_1">ICRC</gloss> that we are approaching the Soviets
                            and Ethiopians. You should underscore the need for strict
                            confidentiality.</p>
                        <pb facs="0670" n="624" xml:id="pg_624"/>
                        <p>10. For London, Rome and Ottawa: On strict FYI basis only, you should
                            inform host government of our approaches to Soviets and Ethiopians on
                            this matter.</p>
                        <p>11. For <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss>: Please brief the
                            Secretary General on our plans to approach the Soviets and
                            Ethiopians.</p>
                        <p>12. For Vatican: Septel will follow,<note n="3" xml:id="d230fn3">Not
                                found.</note> asking Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WVA_1">Walters</persName> to brief the Pope on food truce issue and
                            requesting his support for safe passage related to food relief. This
                            cable is for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WVA_1">Walters</persName>
                            background.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_DKW_1"><hi rend="strong">Dam</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>