<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1986-09-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1986-09-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="255" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d255">
                        <head>255. National Security Study Directive 3–86<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d255fn1">Source: National Archives, Collection RR–<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>, Numbered National Security Policy
                                Papers 1981–1989, National Security Study Directives (NSSDs),
                                01/20/1981–1/20/1989 (accessed online). Confidential.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1986-09-19">September 19, 1986</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">U.S. SUPPORT FOR ECONOMIC GROWTH</hi></p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">IN SUB-SAHARAN AFRICA</hi> (U)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Introduction</p>
                        <p>This National Security Study Directive establishes the Terms of Reference
                            for a review of U.S. economic programs and policies which will serve as
                            the basis for implementing the President’s goal of helping to end hunger
                            in Sub-Saharan Africa. This goal takes into account factors such as (1)
                            humanitarian interest in Africa; (2) concern for Africa’s economic
                            problems; (3) commitment to reform by African leaders at the <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss> Special Session on the African
                            Economic Crisis; (4) declining levels of U.S. assistance to Africa; (5)
                            the need to target assistance toward growth, stabilization and debt
                            management; and (6) the review of overseas staffing levels for
                            diplomatic security reasons. (C)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Objectives</p>
                        <p>The President has established a policy goal for the U.S. to help end
                            hunger in Africa through economic growth and private enterprise
                            development. The objective of the <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss>
                            is to orient U.S. economic policies and programs to that end and to
                            support the international effort to help Africa resume economic growth
                            and manage its debts. (U)</p>
                        <pb facs="0730" n="684" xml:id="pg_684"/>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Scope</p>
                        <p>The Task Force Report will be based on existing <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>, World Bank, <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> and
                            other available analyses. No new written material will be requested
                            unless gaps are identified. Working Groups will provide recommendations
                            to the Task Force which will serve as the basis for a report to the
                            President on how to implement his goal for Africa. The report will cover
                            actions already taken as well as recommend further action. (C)</p>
                        <p>Please provide the name of the point of contact for this <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> from your Agency to the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Directorate of African Affairs
                            (395-3391) by COB, Thursday, September 25, 1986. (U)</p>
                        <p>FOR THE PRESIDENT:</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_PJM_1"><hi rend="strong">John M.
                                        Poindexter</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head><hi rend="strong">National Security Study Directive
                                    Outline</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d255fn2">Confidential.</note></head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">U.S. SUPPORT FOR ECONOMIC
                                GROWTH</hi></p>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">IN SUB-SAHARAN AFRICA</hi> (U)</p>
                            <p>The Task Force will address the following, within the context of U.S.
                                political, strategic and economic goals for Africa: (C)</p>
                            <p>1. Economic Assistance. Identify African government policies needed
                                to promote growth through private enterprise; identify policies to
                                improve the impact of stabilization programs on private enterprise
                                and economic growth; identify options or strategies for broadening
                                the benefits of policy reform for the majority of the people; assess
                                role of government and U.S. support to the public sector; identify
                                policies and programs to stimulate local private sector response to
                                growth opportunities and rural linkages; identify optimal blend of
                                assistance, e.g. program/project/<gloss target="#t_PVO_1">PVO</gloss>/food aid/central programs, for different country
                                debt/growth situations. (U)</p>
                            <p>2. Debt Management. Develop programs and policies whereby U.S.
                                actions on outstanding and new debt are leveraged to reenforce
                                growth and private enterprise; identify programs and policies to
                                support African efforts to manage their debt; identify policies for
                                rescheduling, new lending, grant vs. loan assistance and arrears;
                                identify structural causes of budget deficits and policies and
                                programs to address these; identify <pb facs="0731" n="685" xml:id="pg_685"/> financial management tools for alleviating the
                                debt burden; develop a strategy to enlist the support of other
                                creditors. (U)</p>
                            <p>3. Food Aid Policy. Determine how U.S. agricultural resources can be
                                used as incentives for economic growth; maximize food aid and
                                current food stocks to generate resources for Sub-Saharan Africa,
                                consistent with the President’s goal of regional food
                                self-sufficiency; consider monetization of food aid, food for work,
                                use of local currency generation, policy dialogue, and role of food
                                aid in promoting intraregional trade; determine which food aid
                                vehicles (Titles I, II, III, Food for Progress, Section 206) are
                                appropriate to specific development objectives. (U)</p>
                            <p>4. Private Sector Trade, Investment and Role in Economic Assistance.
                                Identify optimal contribution of U.S. private sector for growth in
                                Africa; identify policies to increase U.S. trade and investment with
                                Africa, including consideration of special trade incentives for
                                low-income countries; identify options for U.S. government agencies
                                to better support U.S. private business involvement in Africa;
                                identify administrative and legislative adjustments needed to
                                improve the contribution of the U.S. private sector to Africa’s
                                growth. (U)</p>
                            <p>5. Multilateral Diplomacy and Implications for U.S. Foreign Policy.
                                Identify a framework for enhanced donor coordination on broad policy
                                and program issues; assess relative priority of economic growth with
                                other U.S. political and strategic objectives in Africa; given that
                                economic pluralism is a prerequisite for political pluralism and
                                democracy, identify options for U.S. support to political regimes
                                which do not foster private sector growth policies leading to
                                equitable growth; identify strategy for making shift to countries
                                which support private enterprise and growth. (C)</p>
                            <p>6. Budget Allocation. Develop a structure of budget presentation and
                                implementation that will ensure that 1) budget allocations for the
                                region are evaluated on the basis of the President’s goal by both
                                the Administration and the Congress; and 2) the administrators of
                                this program are given the needed flexibility to implement their
                                tasks in accordance with the goal; identify legislative changes
                                needed to meet the President’s goal for the region. (C)</p>
                            <p>7. Administration: Organizing the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>. Assess administrative changes and follow-up
                                procedures to ensure that the President’s goal for Africa is
                                implemented for the remainder of this century, including orientation
                                of all Executive Branch economic efforts for Sub-Saharan Africa;
                                inter-agency coordination for implementation of growth-oriented
                                policies and programs; continued monitoring and evaluation of the
                                results of the program; policy directives for U.S. agencies and
                                representations; administrative changes, employee training and
                                hiring needed to enhance the capacity of the agencies to implement
                                this policy; and legislative requirements to implement the program.
                                (C)</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>