<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>317. Telegram From the Embassy in Norway to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v41</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d317</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">317</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1986-03-24T10:07:00-05:00" notAfter="1986-03-24T10:07:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="reclIDTRPrn9Z53H4" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94004349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">DCM</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recAEL6tyPTrEjX4P" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004006618"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offshore oil</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil prices</term>
                    <term ref="reclNKKiGeWi0buDd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146352"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Whales</term>
                    <term ref="recUxK0PiRCnqTXts" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000044"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Farming</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="prices" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518" lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1986-03-24T10:07:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1986-03-24T10:07:00-05:00" n="317"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d317">
                <head>317. Telegram From the Embassy in Norway to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d317fn1">Source: Department of State, Dumping; Arctic;
                        Whaling; Antarctic; Scientific Research, 1976–1987, Lot 94D419,
                        Whaling—Norway 1985–86. Confidential; Immediate. Sent for information to the
                        Department of Commerce, Copenhagen, Reykjavik, Tokyo, Moscow, and
                        Ottawa.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Oslo</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1986-03-24T15:07:00+00:00">March 24, 1986, 1507Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1923. Subj: Norwegian Whaling. Ref: Oslo 1692.<note n="2" xml:id="d317fn2">In
                        telegram 1292 from Oslo, October 23, 1985, the Embassy reported that the
                        Government of Norway had filed a reservation to the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1"
                            >IWC</gloss> decision to list the minke whale as a protected stock with
                        a zero quota. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D850757–0517)</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. C—Entire text.</p>
                <p>2. Summary and action requested: Norwegian <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss>
                    Commissioner Tresselt has predicted privately that the <gloss target="#t_GON_1"
                        >GON</gloss> will authorize a modest northeast Atlantic minke whale hunt in
                    1986, hinting the quota will be in the range of 150–350 animals. Tresselt said
                    that the Norwegian scientific studies will be presented to the <gloss
                        target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> Scientific Committee in May. He described the
                        <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> decision last fall to protect the
                    northeast Atlantic minke whale as unreasonable and expressed doubt the <gloss
                        target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> would act differently if the issue were
                    reopened. Tresselt claims to have received indications that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> will not object to Iceland’s plans for
                    continued whaling, and he opined that any <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                    effort to apply stricter standards to Norway would not be understood here.
                    Embassy infers from Tresselt’s remarks that the <gloss target="#t_GON_1"
                        >GON</gloss> intends to authorize a very small whaling quota at about the
                    time of the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> Scientific Committee meeting in
                    the expectation that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> will decide that
                    such a small quota does not justify invoking <persName corresp="#p_PTM_1"
                        >Pelly</persName> Amendment sanctions against Norway.</p>
                <p>3. Foreign Minister Stray will visit Washington April 3–4.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d317fn3">In telegram 116227 to Oslo, April 15, the Department
                        reported that neither Stray nor <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                            >Shultz</persName> raised the issue of whaling during their meeting.
                        (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File, D860286–0561)</note> If
                    Tresselt’s understanding that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> will not
                    object to Iceland’s continued whaling and his expectation that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> would not invoke <persName corresp="#p_PTM_1"
                        >Pelly</persName> Amendment sanctions against a very modest Norwegian
                    whaling quota this year are incorrect, Embassy recommends strongly that Foreign
                    Minister Stray be given an authoritative explanation of <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> views. We would also reiterate our recommendation that the
                        <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> offer to support the <gloss
                        target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> reopening the issue at the <gloss
                        target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss>. End summary and recommendation.</p>
                <pb facs="0932" n="886" xml:id="pg_886"/>
                <p>4. In an informal conversation at a reception, Per Tresselt, <gloss
                        target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> Legal Advisor and Norway’s <gloss
                        target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> Commissioner, told <gloss target="#t_DCM_1"
                        >DCM</gloss> that domestic pressures would in all probability require the
                        <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> to authorize a whaling quota for 1986.
                    The <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss>-sponsored scientific study clearly
                    justified a modest quota. In addition, a second private Norwegian study
                    indicated that even a substantially larger quota would not harm the stock.
                    Tresselt commented that the findings of this second study appeared to be very
                    soundly based. The Whaling Conference in Svolvaer showed strong local support
                    for continued whaling in north Norway, a strategic area which had been steadily
                    losing population because of its declining economy.<note n="4" xml:id="d317fn4"
                        >In telegram 1576 from Oslo, March 11, the Embassy noted that the Government
                        of Norway had publicized a study on the minke whale stock at a conference in
                        Svolvaer. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D860186–0867)</note> (Comment: The communities in north Norway which are the
                    center of the whaling activity have been hit this year by the twin blows of a
                    disastrous fish catch and declining prospects for offshore oil development,
                    resulting from the drop in oil prices.) Tresselt said he expects that any <gloss
                        target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> decision to overrule the Norwegian scientific
                    conclusions by not authorizing a quota would be severely criticized within the
                    government and Storting.</p>
                <p>5. When asked, Tresselt said the <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> did intend
                    to present its scientific data to the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss>’s
                    Scientific Committee which meets next in May. However, he said that the whaling
                    season usually begins in late April or May and that the government would be
                    under pressure to authorize a quota in time for the hunt to commence as usual.
                    When it was noted that if the quota were very small, delaying longer would not
                    prevent completion of the hunt, Tresselt did not respond. <gloss
                        target="#t_DCM_1">DCM</gloss> said that Norway had thus far adhered to
                        <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> decisions and expressed the hope that
                    the <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> would not authorize a quota in defiance
                    of the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss>. Tresselt then noted that the <gloss
                        target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> had decided to protect the northeast Atlantic
                    minke whale despite the Scientific Committee’s approval of a modest quota of
                    about 350 for 1986. He termed the protection unreasonable. Tresselt asked
                    whether the US expected the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> would be more
                    reasonable if the issue were raised again. When <gloss target="#t_DCM_1"
                        >DCM</gloss> demurred, Tresselt commented that he did not see much hope that
                    the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> could be expected to be more
                    reasonable. Tresselt was quick to add that the <gloss target="#t_GON_1"
                        >GON</gloss> had appreciated the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                    attitude when the issue was discussed at the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1"
                        >IWC</gloss> last fall.</p>
                <p>6. Tresselt then said that one question for the <gloss target="#t_GON_1"
                        >GON</gloss> was how big a quota to authorize. Speaking personally, he said
                    that if Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> should indicate
                    to Foreign Minister Stray next week that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> would not object to a quota of 150 and would be prepared to see
                    such a quota continue indefinitely, such views would reinforce those <pb
                        facs="0933" n="887" xml:id="pg_887"/> who were calling for a very low quota.
                        <gloss target="#t_DCM_1">DCM</gloss> said that he did not see how the
                    Secretary would be in a position to do this, particularly in the context of an
                    indefinite continuation of Norwegian whaling.</p>
                <p>7. Tresselt then said that he had received the very strong impression that the
                        <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> would not object to Iceland’s plans for
                    a quota of about 200 whales per year. He also interpreted the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>’s decision to appeal the Japanese whaling
                    issue to the Supreme Court as an indication that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> was optimistic about winning that case.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d317fn5">In telegram 211037 to all East Asian and Pacific diplomatic
                        posts, July 4, the Department reported that Japan had dropped its objection
                        after a June 30 5–4 Supreme Court ruling in favor of the agreement.
                        (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File, D860516–0588)</note> In
                    this context, Tresselt said that any decision by the <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> to single out its ally Norway for particularly stringent
                    treatment would simply not be understood or accepted in Norway. <gloss
                        target="#t_DCM_1">DCM</gloss> replied that he could not comment
                    authoritatively on Iceland, but that there were considerable risks to Norway’s
                    fishing interests implicit in any assumption that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> would in fact have the flexibility not to invoke <persName
                        corresp="#p_PTM_1">Pelly</persName> sanctions if Norway hunted in disregard
                    of an <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> decision.</p>
                <p>8. Tresselt said such a modest hunt might be described as being necessary in
                    order to protect other species or to avoid a growing whale stock becoming a
                    danger to fish farming along the Norwegian coast. He noted that the US-Norway
                    talks in 1984–5 about the possibility of defining Norwegian whaling as
                    non-commercial coastal whaling had broken down and said he would be prepared to
                    resume these talks if the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> wished.</p>
                <p>9. Tresselt said he recognized there were risks but that the issue was an
                    emotional one in Norway. He noted in particular that Prime Minister Willoch had
                    decided views on the matter, and that Willoch was a man of conviction who would
                    not back down under pressure if he was convinced that his position was
                    justified. The conversation was then interrupted, and Tresselt ended by saying
                    he would have no objection to his personal views being reported to
                    Washington.</p>
                <p>10. Comment: Tresselt is a careful diplomat who acts quite deliberately. Embassy
                    infers from his remarks that the <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> will
                    present its scientific data to the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss>
                    Scientific Committee in May and that, at about the same time and almost
                    certainly before the <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> itself meets in June,
                    the <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> will approve a modest quota (probably
                    in the 150–350 range) for 1986, in the belief that there is no hope of favorable
                        <gloss target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> action and the expectation that neither
                    the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> nor the environmentalists will take
                    effective action against Norway for doing so.</p>
                <p>11. Concern that either <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> or environmentalists
                    actions in response to continued Norwegian whaling would harm Norway’s eco<pb
                        facs="0934" n="888" xml:id="pg_888"/>nomically more important fishing
                    exports to the US has not figured prominently in recent discussions of the
                    Whaling issue. This probably reflects the perception that neither the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> or the environmentalists will react in a way
                    that will harm Norway. The <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> has everything
                    to gain domestically from authorizing a modest quota and it perceives that it
                    has little to lose internationally from doing so. While we have urged the <gloss
                        target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> not to expect <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> flexibility under the <persName corresp="#p_PTM_1"
                        >Pelly</persName> Amendment, it is clear that the <gloss target="#t_GON_1"
                        >GON</gloss> believes we will exercise the discretion which is available
                    under the amendment.</p>
                <p>12. The <gloss target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> also believes there is a scientific
                    basis for a modest hunt, a view that was endorsed by the <gloss
                        target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss> Scientific Committee last fall. We are not
                    aware what basis there is for concluding that such a modest quota would
                    “diminish the effectiveness of the International Convention for the Regulation
                    of Whaling.”</p>
                <p>13. Whatever the merits of a hunt, we believe it essential in light of Tresselt’s
                    assertions, that Foreign Minister Stray be given an authoritative statement of
                    the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> attitude toward Iceland’s plans for
                    continued whaling and of the degree of flexibility that we may be able to
                    exercise under the <persName corresp="#p_PTM_1">Pelly</persName> Amendment
                    should Norway authorize a modest quota this year. Given Tresselt’s comments, we
                    believe <gloss target="#t_MFA_1">MFA</gloss> will interpret an absence of
                    comments to Stray as an indication of <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                    acquiesence in a modest Norwegian quota. As recommended previously, we believe
                    the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> should also offer to support a <gloss
                        target="#t_GON_1">GON</gloss> effort to reopen this issue at the <gloss
                        target="#t_IWC_1">IWC</gloss>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Stuart</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
