<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1987-02-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1987-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="89" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d89">
                        <head>89. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Human
                            Rights and Humanitarian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SR_1">Schifter</persName>), the Legal Adviser of the Department of State
                                (<persName corresp="#p_SAD_2">Sofaer</persName>), and the Assistant
                            Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KAL_1">Keyes</persName>) to the Deputy Secretary of
                            State (<persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">Whitehead</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d89fn1">Source: Department of State, Subject
                                Files, Human Rights Files, 1987, Lot 89D186, <gloss target="#t_PREL_1">PREL</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_UNHRC_1">UNHRC</gloss> TORTURE 1987. Unclassified.
                                Drafted by McLeod and cleared in L, <gloss target="#t_HA_1">HA</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_IO_1">IO</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1987-02-05">February 5, 1987</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Torture Convention: Differences with the Department of
                                Justice</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">ISSUE FOR DECISION</p>
                        <p>Whether to convene a meeting of high-level State and Justice Department
                            officials to attempt to obtain Justice Department support for U.S.
                            signature and ratification of the Convention against Torture <pb facs="0314" n="268" xml:id="pg_268"/> and Other Cruel, Inhuman, or
                            Degrading Treatment or Punishment (the Torture Convention).</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">ESSENTIAL FACTORS</p>
                        <p>In our previous memorandum of December 24, we detailed the preliminary
                            objections to the Torture Convention that have been raised by Justice
                            Department officials.<note n="2" xml:id="d89fn2">Not found.</note> We
                            appreciate your offer in response to call Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Meese</persName> or Deputy Attorney General
                                <persName corresp="#p_BAI_1">Burns</persName> to solicit their
                            support for U.S. signature and ratification of the Convention. While
                            such a call would undoubtedly be helpful, we believe an even more
                            effective means of gaining Justice Department support for the Convention
                            would be for you to convene a meeting of high-level officials from
                            Justice and State.</p>
                        <p>We believe the Torture Convention merits such high-level attention. The
                            practice of torture is abhorrent, and the United States should do
                            everything in its power to bring it to an end. While recognizing that it
                            may be difficult for the United States to prosecute those accused of
                            torture abroad, we nonetheless believe that the threat of prosecution
                            will deter some torturers and will prevent the United States from
                            becoming a haven for torturers. Moreover, we are constantly under fire
                            from the Soviet bloc for our failure to ratify human rights conventions.
                            The Convention offers a concrete opportunity to demonstrate that the
                            United States is prepared to sign on to such instruments when they are
                            of sufficient value.</p>
                        <p>The Justice Department objections expressed so far reflect a fundamental
                            disagreement with us over the value of U.S. ratification of the
                            Convention and an underlying pessimism about the Administration’s
                            ability to get the necessary declarations, understandings and
                            reservations from the new Democratic Senate. These are essentially
                            political, and not technical legal, judgments. We need to find out now
                            whether the highest political levels at Justice agree or can be
                            persuaded to agree that the U.S. should move forward with the Convention
                            and are willing to direct their subordinates to review the Department of
                            State package expeditiously and in that spirit. If we cannot obtain
                            political support at Justice, we will be resigning ourselves to letting
                            the Convention languish in the Justice Department bureaucracy for the
                            rest of this Administration. A high-level meeting would allow us to
                            demonstrate to Justice the priority that we place on signature and
                            ratification of the Convention.</p>
                        <p>If you are able and willing to host a meeting, we would propose that the
                            participants from the Justice Department include: Deputy Attorney <pb facs="0315" n="269" xml:id="pg_269"/> General <persName corresp="#p_BAI_1">Burns</persName>, Associate Attorney General
                            Steve Trott, Assistant Attorney General for the Criminal Division
                            William Weld and Deputy Assistant Attorney General, Victoria Toensing.
                            The State participants, besides yourself, would be Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SR_1">Schifter</persName>, Judge <persName corresp="#p_SAD_2">Sofaer</persName> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KAL_1">Keyes</persName>.</p>
                        <p>We have prepared the attached talking points<note n="3" xml:id="d89fn3">Undated, attached but not printed.</note> for your use in a
                            meeting. Also attached is a background memorandum<note n="4" xml:id="d89fn4">Undated, attached but not printed.</note> detailing
                            our responses to the Justice Department objections raised thus far.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">RECOMMENDATION</p>
                        <p>That you convene a meeting of high-level State and Justice Department
                            officials to attempt to reach agreement that the Executive Branch should
                            seek signature and ratification of the Torture Convention.<note n="5" xml:id="d89fn5">There is no indication of approval or disapproval of
                                the recommendation. In an August 8 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_FRW_1">Farrand</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DPJ_1">Dobriansky</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SR_1">Schifter</persName> stated: “I brought the
                                Secretary up to date on our problem concerning the Justice
                                Department position on the Torture Convention. He said that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SAD_2">Abe Sofaer</persName> usually can
                                resolve matters of this kind with the Justice Department and asked
                                me whether I had discussed it with him. I told him that Abe was
                                indeed involved and had struck out. I added that <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">John Whitehead</persName> is now looking into
                                the matter. If he fails, I explained, we need to go to the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>.” (Department of State,
                                Correspondence File—Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SR_1">Richard
                                    Schifter</persName> CHRON and Subject Files, 1984–1991, Lot
                                94D411, <persName corresp="#p_SR_1">R. Schifter</persName>’s Monthly
                                Chron—August 1987)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>