<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>99. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Human
                    Rights and Humanitarian Affairs (Schifter) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary
                    of State Shultz</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v41</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">99</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1987-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1987-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe">Helsinki
                        Final Act</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recyGjAcEpLpFYanH" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107027"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Privacy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recZ240W8VG9BDJBE" type="compound-subject"
                        category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        >Soviet foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recdZke2uFUGdGg1d" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissidents</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005651"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Monitoring</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98003467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democratization</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1987-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1987-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="99"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d99">
                <head>99. Information Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Human
                    Rights and Humanitarian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SR_1"
                    >Schifter</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                        >Shultz</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d99fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Foreign Policy File, P880038–2176. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SR_1"
                            >Schifter</persName>. Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1"
                            >Armacost</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SRH_1">Solomon</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRL_1">Ridgway</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KMM_1">Kampelman</persName>, Abramowitz, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_STW_1">Simons</persName>. A stamped notation on the
                        memorandum indicates that <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> saw
                        it.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1987-10-13">October 13, 1987</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Human Rights Developments in the Soviet Union</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>. In the weeks ahead we shall have to define the
                    irreducible minimum conditions to our agreeing that a Moscow Humanitarian
                    Affairs Conference be held. Before we do so, we need to take inventory on Soviet
                    progress and lack thereof in the field of human rights. What a review of
                    developments in Soviet domestic affairs discloses is that the workings of the
                    hitherto sacrosanct bureaucracy have now been opened for discussion and
                    criticism, for most Soviet citizens a very exciting change. To be acceptable
                    under these new conditions, however, all such discussion must take place within
                    a framework of Marxist-Leninist doctrine. Those that dissent from the system
                    continue to be harassed, but punishment is now more proportionate to the
                    seriousness of the threat posed by these dissenters than was the case
                    heretofore. <hi rend="italic">End Summary</hi>.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Overview</p>
                <p>The willingness of the Soviets during the last year or so to listen when we
                    discuss human rights—and occasionally to respond meaningfully—their
                    significantly more friendly demeanor, and the modest steps they have taken to
                    improve their human rights record may very well have left the general American
                    public with an unrealistically complacent view of the current state of Soviet
                    human rights conditions. What is critically important now, after our human
                    rights policy has registered some modest successes in the Soviet Union, is that
                    we not leave the Soviets with the impression that they have gone far enough,
                    that we will henceforth only mouth phrases about the need for further progress,
                    but no longer mean it. In the process, we will also be able to ensure that the
                    U.S. public, and Congress, have a realistic understanding of what the Soviets
                    have (and have not) done.</p>
                <p>The Soviets can no longer complain that the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                    has ignored the progress they have made. Your recent public statements have
                        acknowl<pb facs="0338" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/>edged it.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d99fn2">For a transcript of <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1"
                            >Shultz</persName>’s September 21 interview on “This Week With David
                        Brinkley,” see Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                        November 1987, pp. 21–23.</note>
                    <persName corresp="#p_ZW_1">Warren Zimmermann</persName> has expressed himself
                    with great care in Vienna.<note n="3" xml:id="d99fn3">Telegram 11072 from <gloss
                            target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> Vienna, July 31, transmitted the text of
                        a press conference, during which <persName corresp="#p_ZW_1"
                            >Zimmermann</persName> discussed negotiations regarding Soviet human
                        rights issues. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D870613–0069)</note>
                </p>
                <p>It is conceivable that the dynamics of change in the Soviet Union will cause the
                    process to continue. But as historians have noted, past liberalization efforts
                    were halted and reversed not only under Khrushchev, but also under Alexander II
                    and before that under Alexander I. In those eras, however, before
                    “interdependence,” Russian authorities could act without reference to the
                    concerns of outside powers. What is different now is that the Soviet Union
                    understands it must be concerned about its world image and about relations with
                    the West. It is because of that concern that we have an opportunity to influence
                    the course of events in the Soviet Union. That is why we need to point both to
                    the filled and the empty portion of the glass and try to make sure that the
                    Western general public is aware of both. Our critical decision on the proposed
                    Moscow Humanitarian Affairs Conference will have to be taken with these
                    considerations in mind.</p>
                <p>Last January I set forth for you some immediate, intermediate and long-range
                    goals of our Soviet human rights policy.<note n="4" xml:id="d99fn4">See <ref
                            target="#d88">Document 88</ref>.</note> Full compliance with the
                    provisions of the Helsinki Final Act, our long-range goal, remains well over the
                    horizon. However, in the intervening months there has been significant progress
                    in reaching our immediate goals and slight progress toward the intermediate
                    goals:</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                    <hi rend="roman">A.</hi> Progress Toward Our Immediate Goals</p>
                <p>• Perhaps as many as 30% of the known prisoners of conscience have been released.
                    Additional releases have been promised. At the same time, we have been told that
                    some of these prisoners, close to 100 of those known to us, will <hi
                        rend="italic">not</hi> be released. They are the people serving long prison
                    sentences, some of them as recidivists, for “anti-Soviet agitation and
                    propaganda.”</p>
                <p>• A few of the separated-spouse, divided-family, and dual-national cases have
                    been resolved this year. The pace is excruciatingly slow, but additional cases
                    may be resolved in the months ahead.</p>
                <p>• <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> is no longer jammed, but jamming of RFE/RL
                    continues.</p>
                <p>• Emigration has been stepped up to an annual rate just short of our minimum
                    immediate goal of 10,000, but there is no present indication of an intent to go
                    further.</p>
                <pb facs="0339" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Progress Toward Our Intermediate Goals</p>
                <p>• There has been a loosening of controls on expression in that dissent, speaking
                    or writing within certain clearly defined limits, is no longer punished with
                    imprisonment, although it is otherwise interfered with through harassment,
                    detainment or confiscation.</p>
                <p>• There has been talk of some limited changes regarding the practice of religion
                    in the Soviet Union. There have also been hints that persons now imprisoned for
                    religious activism may soon be released. But there is no evident intent to
                    change the scheme of state control of religion.</p>
                <p>• There has been some indication that abuses of psychiatry may be brought to an
                    end.</p>
                <p>• There has been no appreciable change in controls on the importation of foreign
                    literature.</p>
                <p>• There has been some relaxation in controls on foreign travel.</p>
                <p>• Steps have been taken toward greater cultural freedom, but the emphasis appears
                    on Russian culture as distinct from that of other ethnic groups.</p>
                <p>• There is no present indication of any likely change in the 1986 Emigration
                    Decree (requiring invitations from immediate relatives).</p>
                <p>• There has been no change in the intrusive status of the secret police or any
                    indication that the right to privacy will henceforth be respected.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Limits of Change</p>
                <p>The Soviets contend that such changes as have occurred recently in Soviet respect
                    for human rights have occurred for purely domestic reasons. We have not tried to
                    argue that point. In fact, some of the changes have indeed been the result of a
                    new Soviet approach to the administration of its domestic affairs. But others
                    have equally clearly been the response to foreign criticism. Generally speaking,
                    the Soviets have taken steps (a) designed to make the Marxist-Leninist system
                    function more efficiently, and (b) to accommodate some Western concerns, so long
                    as such accommodation does not threaten the system.</p>
                <p>The most exciting and for the average Soviet citizen most meaningful changes in
                    Soviet society under <persName corresp="#p_GMS_1">Gorbachev</persName> come
                    under the heading of Glasnost. Bureaucratic failings may now be freely
                    discussed, both in individual speech and in the press. In fact, such discussion
                    is encouraged, <hi rend="italic">but only if it takes place in the context of
                        acceptance of the basic tenets of the Marxist-Leninist system</hi>. Though
                    limited in scope to the day-to-day issues of management of the Soviet
                    administrative system and economy, <hi rend="italic">this new freedom allows for
                        public discussion of almost all the problems of direct concern to the great
                        majority of Soviet citizens</hi>. It similarly <pb facs="0340" n="294"
                        xml:id="pg_294"/> allows for discussion in books, theatrical plays and films
                    of past failings, and thereby permits some rewriting of official history,
                    although only within a Leninist framework.</p>
                <p>Glasnost has not opened up for public discussion such basic policy issues as the
                    war in Afghanistan, other aspects of Soviet foreign policy, the allocation of
                    resources to the defense sector, weapons systems, the composition of the
                    Politburo, or the state’s basic commitment to Marxism-Leninism. But some change
                    has taken place in the Government’s treatment of those who in speaking up or
                    writing act beyond the borders of the permissible. Responding to foreign
                    criticism, the Soviet authorities seem to have recognized that they overreacted
                    in the past, that the punishment meted out against dissent was excessive if
                    measured against the threat they posed. Dissidents whose activities are not
                    deemed to pose a serious danger to the system need not be incarcerated but
                    rather hindered in their work, so that they concentrate on what they are now
                    doing and do not get the notion that they can go further. On the other hand, for
                    dissidents who are deemed a threat, particularly those who advance minority
                    ethnic aspirations, severe punishment remains the order of the day.</p>
                <p>The best assurance that the line between the permissible and the impermissible
                    will not be crossed remains the system’s monolithic control of the media and of
                    all other forms of communications through secret police monitoring of the
                    telephones and mails and other methods of spying on the population.</p>
                <p>Soviet officials say that when they use the term “demokratisatsia” in describing
                    changes now under way in the Soviet Union they do not mean Western-style
                    democratization. That is absolutely true. They mean by democratization an end to
                    the “cult of personality,” an end to excessive privileges and untouchability of
                    the ruling class, and the notion that government officials ought to pay
                    attention to public attitudes in making administrative decisions. They mean a
                    return to Leninist purity, uncontaminated by Stalinist despotism and Brezhnevist
                    sloth. But Lenin was no Western-style democrat and neither are his disciples in
                    the present Soviet leadership.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
