<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Geneva ( (Gilbert) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d189</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">189</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-10-13T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-10-13T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-10-13T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-10-13T06:00:00-05:00" n="189"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d189">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/2077: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-10-13T12:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 13, 1931—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received October 13—11
                        a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>188. With reference to my telephone conversation yesterday with you,<note n="38"
                        xml:id="d189fn38">Memorandum of conversation not printed.</note> last night
                    I talked with Drummond and again this morning upon receiving your 85, October
                    12, 6 p.m., in regard to your views on a Kellogg Pact appeal.</p>
                <p>Your position now is clearly understood by him, and while it is too early yet to
                    state precisely what will eventuate, I expect developments here to be shaped
                    along lines of your policy. All developments will be reported to you as rapidly
                    as they take place. One point I desire at this time to make clear to you. If I
                    am invited to a seat at the <pb facs="0288" n="178" xml:id="pg_178"/> Council
                    table, provided the Kellogg Pact question is raised, it will be (in accordance
                    with an established precedent of the League) not as a member of the Council but
                    in a capacity solely of following the proceedings and taking part in the
                    discussions as an impartial friend. This I think you will deem to be quite
                    [essential?].</p>
                <p>If I do act in this capacity, I will strictly follow the instructions given me in
                    this respect, which I feel now are completely clear to me.</p>
                <p>In addition, I shall be careful not to deliver my acceptance of such an
                    invitation until you have been notified by me of my intention and have been able
                    to give it publicity at Washington.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gilbert</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
