<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Geneva ( (Gilbert) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-10-18T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-10-18T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-10-18T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-10-18T11:00:00-05:00" n="244"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d244">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/2202: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-10-18T17:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 18, 1931—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 8:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>217. I quote below the text of a note addressed to the President of the Council
                    by the Japanese representative. This note was discussed in the private meeting
                    of the Council held at 11 o’clock this morning (Chinese and Japanese
                    representatives being absent).</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Up to the present the Japanese Government has cooperated sincerely in the
                        work of the League and has endeavored to increase its prestige by every
                        possible means. It considers that the League’s action should in every case
                        be strictly in accordance with the provisions of Covenant, and that this
                        action should be both impartial and correct. If there is any departure from
                        these principles for reasons of expediency the Japanese Government is of
                        opinion that the authority of League is likely to suffer.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>When the League Council discussed the question of inviting the Government
                        of the United States of America to send an observer to sit on the Council,
                        the Japanese representative expressed at length his doubts as to the
                        interpretation of the Covenant—that is to say whether the presence in the
                        Council of an observer of a non-member state was or was not compatible with
                        the provisions of the League Covenant, and whether the question of the
                        invitation could be or could not be regarded under the Covenant as a
                        question of procedure. Although the Japanese representative asked the
                        Council to examine these points the latter did not go fully into the
                        questions raised by him <pb facs="0343" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/> and
                        likewise rejected his request that they should be referred to a committee of
                        legal experts for examination. The President of the Council left all these
                        legal questions in abeyance and put the question of the invitation to the
                        note [<hi rend="italic">vote?</hi>], regardless of the opposition of the
                        Japanese Government’s representative; he also decided that this was a
                        question of procedure and stated that the proposal had been adopted by a
                        majority.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The opinion was expressed that as the United States Government was a party
                        to the Paris Pact it should have the opportunity of expressing its opinion
                        before the League Council solely in regard to the application of that
                        treaty. The Japanese Government is not only firmly convinced that the
                        present situation is not such that there is any danger of war between Japan
                        and China but also considers that, as the Paris Pact is a treaty between a
                        large number of states including non-member states, the granting of an
                        opportunity to sit on the Council with the right to express an opinion to
                        the United States representative alone, raises a delicate question. This
                        also shows that the invitation to the United States is not simply a question
                        of procedure.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Japanese Government cannot help feeling the profoundest misgiving as
                        to the correctness of the precipitate adoption of a majority decision and
                        the leaving in abeyance of the preliminary question whether a proposal
                        requires unanimity or whether it can be decided by a majority. It is anxious
                        to know when the legal questions outstanding are to be discussed and how the
                        note [<hi rend="italic">vote?</hi>] of October 15th will affect the result
                        of those discussions.</item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>Before deciding upon the attitude which it will adopt in regard to the
                        questions now raised as a whole the Japanese Government will be happy to
                        have the opinion of the President of the Council on the above-mentioned
                        points.”</item>
                </list>
                <p>After a short discussion it was agreed that Briand as President of the Council
                    should draft a reply. Briand stated that his reply would probably be along the
                    following lines:</p>
                <p>There was nothing in the Covenant to prohibit the Council from calling at any
                    time representatives of governments to the Council table to consult or exchange
                    information. Referring to the fact that the Japanese representative had
                    previously called attention in this connection to article 4 of the Covenant, he
                    would make it clear that inviting the representative of the United States to sit
                    at the Council table did not mean that he was incorporated in the Council body
                    nor had the power to vote. The action taken therefore in inviting the United
                    States was in nowise analogous to action under article 4 of the Covenant. The
                    Council consequently considered that the question of inviting the United States
                    to the Council table for consultation and exchange of information was one of
                    “procedure”. This was particularly true since the matter to be discussed with
                    the representative of the United States was a question which did not concern the
                    members of the League as such, and was not embraced in the provisions of the
                    Covenant.</p>
                <pb facs="0344" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/>
                <p>In regard to the question of the appointment of a committee of jurists to study
                    the legal question cited by the Japanese, Briand stated that in reply to a
                    direct question which he had previously put to the Japanese representative
                    asking whether the Japanese Government would accept as final the conclusions of
                    such a committee the Japanese representative had replied in the negative. Briand
                    stated that in view of this attitude it would mean simply a loss of time to
                    appoint such a committee.</p>
                <p>Respecting the atmosphere of such a part of the discussion relating to this
                    subject, it is natural as you will well understand that certain distress should
                    be felt by some members of the Council, particularly those representing the
                    small states, over any question of such a character being raised in the League.
                    The spirit is, however, that technicalities must be laid aside at this juncture
                    to accomplish a common objective, the maintenance of peace.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gilbert</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
