<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-10-24T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-10-24T16:00:00-05:00" n="292" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d292">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/2324: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-10-24T22:00:00+01:00">October 24, 1931—10
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 11:33 p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>250. Consulate’s 247, October 24, 6 [<hi rend="italic">3</hi>] p.m. The
                            Council convened at 5 p.m. and immediately heard an announcement from
                            Briand that the conferences which he had had this afternoon with the
                            Japanese representative had not led to an agreement. This was followed
                            by a declaration on the part of the Japanese representative restating
                            briefly the Japanese position and the inability of his Government to
                            accept the draft resolution of the Council.</p>
                        <p>The Japanese counterproposal was first put to a vote and rejected 13
                            votes to 1, Japan voting in favor. A vote on the draft resolution was
                            taken by roll call and was adopted by 13 votes to 1, Japan voting
                            against.</p>
                        <p>Briand then expressed his regret that unanimity could not be obtained and
                            went on to point out some of the difficulties in the settlement of this
                            question and the success of the League in confining the conflict within
                            its present limits and eliminating the threat of war. He then spoke as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“May I say how touched we have been and how grateful we are for
                                    the assistance which has been given us throughout by the great
                                    Republic of the United States of America. From the very outset
                                    the United States Government associated itself with our efforts
                                    and exchanged communications with us. Within the limits which it
                                    associates itself and in connection with those points which
                                    concerned it—that is to say, confining its attention to the Pact
                                    of Paris, of which it was the initiator—the United States
                                    Government gave its cooperation within those limits when asked.
                                    I should like to ask the representative of the United States to
                                    convey to his Government our warm thanks for the assistance
                                    which has thus been given us within these limits and to say that
                                    the moral effect of their support has contributed greatly to
                                    circumscribing the conflict.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>After expressing the hope that between now and November 16 the conflict
                            will be settled, Briand added that it should be understood that the
                            resolution which had just been voted upon does not supersede the
                            Council’s resolution of September 30.</p>
                        <p>In the exchange of felicitations that took place at the conclusion of the
                            meeting the representative of Norway associated himself in what Briand
                            had said regarding the United States. I replied to these remarks as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I take this occasion to thank the President of the Council for
                                    the words he was kind enough to address to me earlier this
                                    afternoon, and also for those spoken by the representative of
                                    Norway. These I shall have the honor of transmitting immediately
                                    to my Government.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <pb facs="0423" n="313" xml:id="pg_313"/>
                        <p>Regarding the United States, Madariaga spoke as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I venture to express the hope that we may have reached complete
                                    unanimity by the next meeting. I would like finally to be
                                    permitted to associate myself with what the President has said
                                    on the subject of the collaboration so valuable for us, of the
                                    Republic of the United States, and to hope that if unfortunately
                                    the Council should have to continue its work in this affair,
                                    this collaboration will be again assured us.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>In this regard Sze said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“May I also join in with my colleague from Norway in expressing
                                    our deep gratification in having the cooperation of the
                                    representative of the United States at the Council.[”]</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>The Chinese delegate also expressed himself pessimistically regarding an
                            improvement in the situation in Manchuria in view of the Japanese
                            insistence upon negotiations which China will not enter upon until the
                            evacuation of the troops. Considered the period of adjournment to
                            November 16 too long and reserved the right to request the calling of an
                            earlier meeting should the evacuation not proceed in accordance with the
                            hope expressed by Briand.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gilbert</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>