<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-09-12T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-09-12T04:00:00-05:00" n="3" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d3">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/1790: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peiping</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-09-12T17:00:00+08:00">September 12, 1931—5
                                    p.m.</date><lb/>[Received September 12—11:40
                            a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>578. Referring to Mukden’s despatch 440, August 20 re Nakamura, Agent and
                            Consul General [<hi rend="italic">of Japanese General Staff?</hi>], the
                            following is essential portion of a further report dated September 10th:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“There is good reason to believe that internal Japanese politics
                                    are more responsible for the present threatening aspect of
                                    Sino-Japanese relations than anything that the Chinese have done
                                    or left undone with respect to the case. It is my opinion that
                                    relations between Japanese Army and the Japanese Foreign Office
                                    (representing non-Army elements in the Government) are as much
                                    strained just now as relations between China and Japan, and that
                                    the Army authorities are quite as willing to have the
                                    negotiations fail as the Foreign Office is anxious to have them
                                    succeed. The report of the first Chinese group of investigators
                                    having been wholly unsatisfactory, a second and more capable
                                    group was sent out on September 6th. That group simply reported
                                    that their investigations failed to disclose any evidence to
                                        [<hi rend="italic">in</hi>] support of the Japanese
                                    statement. It was shown, however, that their investigations were
                                    anything but thorough. Despite insistence from Japanese Army
                                    quarters for a prompt settlement, Consul General Hayashi informs
                                    me that no definite time limit has been set with respect to a
                                    reply from the Chinese. The situation is not believed to be as
                                    critical as intimated in the press, although further evidence of
                                    procrastination or insincerity on the part of the Chinese will
                                    make it extremely difficult to avoid a Japanese military display
                                    in Manchuria. It has been impossible to obtain information
                                    concerning the sanction or sanctions which might be applied in
                                    the event of a breakdown of negotiations.”</p></quote></p>
                        <p>The Nakamura case has for several weeks been causing much excitement and
                            while the Legation does not share the alarmist views of many of the
                            newspapers it must be remembered the Sino-Japanese relations since the
                            Korean riots<note n="6" xml:id="d3fn6">For summary of the Wanpaoshan
                                incident in Manchuria and the anti-Chinese riots in Korea, see
                                League of Nations, <hi rend="italic">Appeal by the Chinese
                                    Government, Report of the Commission of Enquiry</hi>, pp. 61
                                ff.</note> have been anything but friendly. Any incident if not
                            carefully handled by both parties may therefore produce a serious
                            crisis. The Legation believes that the Manchurian authorities and
                            probably also Japanese would prefer to settle the case locally through
                            the Japanese Consul General in Mukden rather than through protracted
                            negotiations between Nanking and Tokyo. Marshal Chang Hsueh-liang<note n="7" xml:id="d3fn7">Vice commander in chief of the Chinese National
                                Army, Navy, and Air Forces; commander in chief of the Northeastern
                                Frontier Army; and chairman of the Political Council of the four
                                Northeastern Provinces.</note> is said to be personally sincerely
                            desirous of effecting such local settlement and to that end has
                            designated his <pb facs="0115" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/> adviser Tang Erh-ho
                            to represent him in the negotiations. But if current reports be true
                            that the Japanese military are impatient and are urging the occupation
                            of large portion of Manchuria pending settlement of the case it may
                            prove extremely difficult to restrain existing anti-Japanese
                            feeling.</p>
                        <p>Tokyo informed.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>