<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Forbes) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d451</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">451</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-11-18T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-11-18T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                    <term ref="recOrOM5qitkJb9ky" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-11-18T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-11-18T04:00:00-05:00" n="451"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d451">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/2746: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Forbes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-11-18T18:00:00+09:00"
                            >November 18, 1931—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received November 18—8:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>223. Your 230, November 16, 2 p.m.<note n="43" xml:id="d451fn43">Not printed; it
                        requested further information concerning the action reported in Ambassador’s
                        telegram No. 219, November 16, 11 a.m., <ref target="#pg_452">p.
                        452</ref>.</note> The … Minister’s call was a special one, evidently
                    intended to inform me of the report he sent his Government. Today he has
                    developed further his theme to the effect that pressure, he feels confident,
                    will only consolidate Japanese public opinion and enhance the power of the
                    Japanese military. The very definite opinion was expressed by the … Minister
                    that the present conservative Government here is the most conciliatory which
                    could be organized and should be supported, since any change is likely to tend
                    toward a more militant attitude. Both Ministers confirmed my observation
                    concerning the unanimity of attitude in the diplomatic corps, only one minor
                    exception being noted by the … Minister.</p>
                <p>Rumors of an impending Cabinet change within either a few weeks or months fill
                    the air, but as yet there is little of a definite nature. Three reasons for a
                    Cabinet change are advanced: weak Japanese diplomacy relative to the League of
                    Nations, the Cabinet’s weakness since September 18 with respect to the Japanese
                    military, and the financial situation. As to the Cabinet which will be formed to
                    take the place of the present one, three possibilities are mentioned: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>A “coalition” cabinet will be formed by a part of the Minseito, led by
                            Adachi, now Minister for Home Affairs, and by a part of the Seiyukai,
                            led by Tokonami. Lacking a precedent, this does not appear probable.
                            Both men, especially the latter, are politicians instead of statesmen,
                            are opportunists, and would not enjoy the country’s confidence. Forming
                            a cabinet in consequence of such an intrigue probably would be opposed
                            by powerful personages such as Prince Saionji and Count Makino, men who
                            play an important role at the time of a political change.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The Seiyukai will form a cabinet. At the present time this does not
                            appear probable. The reputation of the Seiyukai still is unsavory as a
                            result of the scandals when it was in office under Baron Tanaka. It is
                            doubtful that the personages mentioned above would find this minority
                            party acceptable at present.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Premier Wakatsuki will continue in office to form a coalition cabinet
                            composed of Minseito, Seiyukai, and independents. This is regarded to be
                            most probable of the three surmises in case the Cabinet falls in the
                            near future.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0585" n="475" xml:id="pg_475"/>
                <p>Undoubtedly the situation is very tense, but it will certainly calm down if given
                    time and in the absence of irritating developments. Rumors flood the press, and
                    the Government daily issues bans against publishing significant items.
                    Yesterday, for example, one ban prohibited any news, except when given out by
                    military authorities, of the movement of two divisions; another banned any
                    information concerning the proposed extension of the South Manchuria Railway; a
                    third banned any comment on Japanese aid in connection with the ex-Emperor of
                    China leaving Tientsin. The newspapers are busily commenting on possible
                    compromises and speculating on conditions. Two days ago the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Japan Advertiser</hi> here published a good deal of the information
                    reported in my 215, November 12, 1 p.m., about the alternative conditions of
                    Japanese withdrawal being given out by the Tokyo Foreign Office. Colonel McIlroy
                    has returned from the maneuvers preparatory to leaving by way of Manchuria. He
                    saw the assembling of numerous transports, as if to move a large force of
                    troops, while troops going to Mukden are coming from the extreme north of Japan.
                    He reports every railway station packed with children waving flags and trains
                    full of troops every 30 minutes; all of this gave the appearance of an organized
                    effort to create wartime enthusiasm.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Forbes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
