<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs ( (Hornbeck) )
                    of a Conversation Between the Secretary of State and the Chinese Chargé (
                    (Yen))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d462</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">462</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-11-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-11-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="462"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d462">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/2892</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a
                        Conversation Between the Secretary of State and the Chinese Chargé</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Yen</hi>)<note n="47" xml:id="d462fn47">Accompanying the new
                        Chinese Chargé, Dr. Hawkling Yen, was the First Secretary of the Chinese
                        Legation, Mr. Yu.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-11-19">November 19,
                            1931</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Dr. Yen called and presented to the Secretary his credentials.</p>
                <p>The conversation turned on the subject of the Manchuria situation. In the course
                    thereof Dr. Yen stated that various Chinese official leaders placed special
                    reliance on the Nine Powers Treaty. He said that W. W. Yen<note n="48"
                        xml:id="d462fn48">Appointed Chinese Minister to the United States.</note> in
                    particular has stressed to him the importance of that Treaty. He inquired what
                    would be the attitude of the American Government if the question of invoking
                    that Treaty were raised.</p>
                <p>The Secretary of State replied that we had had most if not all of various
                    possibilities in mind; that at the time when the trouble began the Council of
                    the League was in session, China had appealed to the Council, the Council had
                    taken full “jurisdiction”, and the American Government had both acted
                    independently and given its moral support to the action taken by the League. For
                    practical purposes there had been and there is going on a conference of the
                    Powers. For that reason there had arisen so far no need for calling a separate
                    and additional conference. Two conferences sitting at the same time to deal with
                    the same question would mean weakness rather than strength. As to what would be
                    our position if the question of invoking the Nine Powers Treaty were raised, it
                    was our consistent practice to keep in mind the saying: “Don’t cross a bridge
                    until you come to the river”. He felt that the representatives of the various
                    Powers were very actively <pb facs="0596" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/> struggling
                    with the Manchuria problem at Paris just now and that we should concentrate our
                    attention on their efforts.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
