<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-11-27T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-11-27T15:00:00-05:00" n="537" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d537">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/2931: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Shaw</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase<note n="3" xml:id="d537fn3">Quotations not paraphrased.</note>]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-11-27T20:00:00+00:00">November 27, 1931—8
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received November 27—7:07 p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>812. From Ambassador Dawes: This afternoon Matsudaira called. The
                            Drafting Committee appears to be considering whether to increase the
                            number of members on the proposed commission from three to seven.
                            Matsudaira feels a larger commission would be unwieldy, and he is
                            somewhat apprehensive lest some of the smaller powers without material
                            interest in the situation should wish to be represented. In his opinion,
                            the commission had best consist of three members, American, British, and
                            French. He would have no personal objection to an Italian in addition,
                            but he has not yet heard on this point from Tokyo.</p>
                        <p>Reasons given in the Council for the larger number were the embarrassing
                            problem which would arise in case of illness of one of the three members
                            and the possibility also of having to form subcommittees for the purpose
                            of covering a large area. Matsudaira commented on this that the smaller
                            the commission is, the greater will its authority be.</p>
                        <p>Matsudaira is discussing another point with the Drafting Committee,
                            namely, the tentative wording of the resolution: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The two parties undertake to give the strictest orders to the
                                    commanders of the respective forces to refrain from any
                                    initiative which may lead to further fighting and loss of
                                    life.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <pb facs="0686" n="576" xml:id="pg_576"/>
                        <p>As it stands, the clause, Matsudaira says, would be subversive of the
                            constitution of Japan, and he wishes the wording to be as follows:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The two parties shall refrain from any initiative which may lead
                                    to further fighting and loss of life.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Though the Council has not decided as yet concerning the number of
                            members for the proposed commission, it is Matsudaira’s impression that
                            a commission of seven members is favored. He is quite certain that his
                            Government will object to a large commission. This information he gives
                            confidentially, because it embarrasses him to mention eliminating the
                            smaller powers as such. [Dawes.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Shaw</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>