<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-12-13T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-12-13T03:00:00-05:00" n="627" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d627">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/3180: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Forbes</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-12-13T17:00:00+09:00">December 13, 1931—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received December 13—9:40 a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>262. Your 262, December 11, 9 p.m.,<note n="85" xml:id="d627fn85"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_62"><hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi></ref>.</note> and 264, December 12, 3 p.m.; and my 260,
                            December 13, 2 p.m.<note n="86" xml:id="d627fn86">No. 260 not
                                printed.</note></p>
                        <p>At 3 p.m. today I called on the Vice Minister for Foreign Affairs, Nagai,
                            and gave him in full the substance of your message. Listening
                            attentively with few comments, he evidently was impressed by your
                            conclusion that in regard to the Chinchow proposition neither side could
                            be charged with lack of faith. Nagai said the Koo proposition had
                            frankly surprised the Japanese Government, which, after accepting it in
                            principle, had done its share by withdrawing Japanese troops, in the
                            expectation that Koo would follow this up. Nagai felt that the Japanese
                            had been treated curtly and perhaps discourteously in not receiving any
                            answer to its suggestion of conferences looking to the arranging of
                            details of the proposal. I made very clear your point concerning the
                            unfortunate effect upon world opinion from further hostilities and
                            inquired whether I should repeat my presentation of this, but Nagai said
                            it was understood perfectly, and when Premier Inukai arrived at the
                            Foreign Office to take charge later in the afternoon, the Vice Minister
                            would not fail to give him the message of the United States Government.
                            Nagai did not say anything which could be construed to indicate an early
                            resumption of hostilities, but he gave the details of sundry abuses
                            which bandits still are constantly perpetrating and which require joint
                            police and military punitive and protective activities.</p>
                        <p>As to the National City Bank’s affairs, I took occasion to ask further,
                            not having had as yet any satisfactory reply. Nagai said he had asked
                            the Japanese Consul General, who was returning to Mukden, to take this
                            up actively. Without revealing the source of my information, I mentioned
                            also numerous arbitrary interferences with civil concerns in Manchuria,
                            ordered by the military to the disadvantage of foreign and Chinese
                            interests and to the direct financial advantage of Japanese interests,
                            and I pointed out that this did not much resemble the Open Door. Nagai
                            was much impressed by this and requested that I supply him with a list
                            of the cases of which I had knowledge.</p>
                        <p>Afterwards I was received by Baron Shidehara, to whom I delivered the
                            personal part of your message; I think this gratified him. <pb facs="0792" n="682" xml:id="pg_682"/> He expressed his cordial
                            appreciation of your attitude and mine. A very high imperial decoration
                            has just been granted him.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Forbes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>