<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-03-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="700" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d700">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.003/550<hi rend="superscript">2/10</hi></note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Castle</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-03-13">March 13, 1931</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The British Ambassador called to tell me of Sir Miles Lampson’s first
                            conference with Mr. C. T. Wang on the subject of
                            extraterritoriality.</p>
                        <p>Lampson began by asking whether it would be well to discuss the big
                            questions or to take up matters of detail. Mr. Wang said he would rather
                            discuss the big questions.</p>
                        <p>Lampson then took up the question of evocation, which he said was of
                            great importance. Mr. Wang refused absolutely to consider it and,
                            without completely giving up the point, Lampson passed on to the
                            question of co-judges. This also was refused by Mr. Wang, but led to a
                            discussion of legal advisers. Mr. Wang said that the Chinese Government
                            would refuse absolutely to be bound by any panel which might be
                            suggested by the Hague Court or by anybody else, but that it probably
                            would be willing to make some kind of satisfactory declaration
                            concerning the rights of legal advisers. There was no agreement reached
                            and no possibility of agreement on either the subject of criminal
                            jurisdiction or that of reserved areas. In the discussion of reserved
                            areas, C. T. Wang said that, to agree, would be “to keep the shell and
                            give the oyster.” During the discussion Lampson held strongly to the
                            point that the British, being already in possession “beati possidentes”
                            were in a very strong position to negotiate and this Wang conceded to be
                            the truth. Lampson also, in his talk, said that it was not the desire of
                            the British, in any suggestions they might make, to derogate from the
                            authority of the Chinese courts, but rather to help build up a judicial
                            system which would be free and above suspicion. When it came to the
                            matter of discussing details, it was agreed that this should be taken up
                            between Teichman and H’su. The Ambassador said that Johnson had already
                            informed Lampson that he could count on his moral support.</p>
                        <p>I asked the Ambassador whether, in using the phrase in his memorandum
                            “international settlement” he had really meant to refer only to that
                            part of Shanghai known technically as the “international settlement.” I
                            told him exactly as I did before that we, in discussing Shanghai, always
                            envisaged it as a port and not as an international settlement and that I
                            did not believe that the American <pb facs="0864" n="754" xml:id="pg_754"/> Government any more than his Government want to
                            throw France and Japan, for example, into the discard. He said that if
                            his Government meant only the “international settlement” it was a
                            thought reaching forward into the almost invisible future, that
                            certainly it could be held only as a final resort to save something out
                            of the wreck, that it is certainly not a question which could arise for
                            a very long time. I told him that unfortunately a rumor had somehow got
                            around that the British had this idea in the back of their heads. He
                            said this was extraordinarily unfortunate and that somebody in London
                            must have been talking loosely.</p>
                        <closer><signed>W[<hi rend="smallcaps">illiam</hi>] R. C[<hi rend="smallcaps">astle</hi>,] <hi rend="smallcaps">Jr.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>