<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the American Minister in China ( (Johnson) ) of a Conversation
                    With the British Minister in China ( (Lampson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1931v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d762</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">762</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1931-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1931-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="762"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d762">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.003/557<hi rend="superscript">8/9</hi>
                </note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the American Minister in China</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Johnson</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conversation With the
                        British Minister in China</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lampson</hi>)<note n="45"
                        xml:id="d762fn45">Copy transmitted to the Department by the Minister without
                        covering despatch; received June 11. Substance reported by the Minister in
                        his telegram of May 9, 1931, noon, from Nanking; received May 9, 6:35 a.m.
                        (893.00/11432)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-05-08">May 8,
                            1931</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I had lunch with Sir Miles today and in the course of conversation he informed me
                    that he had telegraphed his Government in response to their request for an
                    estimate of the situation stating that it was his opinion that he should proceed
                    with the discussions here until they had cleared away all of the articles
                    dealing with legal guarantees and <pb facs="0955" n="845" xml:id="pg_845"/>
                    possibly the preamble to the treaty and that when the point had been reached
                    where they were in agreement on these matters it would then be time for a recess
                    for the summer. He thought that after a summer’s rest during which the Chinese
                    could think over their position and get the People’s Conference and the present
                    political crisis into the background they could resume the negotiations about
                    September with a better chance of success. Sir Miles stated that he felt that
                    the issuance of the regulations covering the adjudication of cases involving
                    foreigners and the mandate putting those regulations into effect on the first of
                    January 1932 was a shrewd move on the part of the Chinese and might be
                    considered as of advantage to us for it not only implemented some of the
                    important guarantees for which we had been negotiating but it would prepare the
                    minds of the Chinese for the treaty. It would put Dr. Wang in a position where
                    he could say that the treaty merely contained provisions already the subject of
                    domestic legislation.</p>
                <p>Sir Miles stated that he was now waiting for his Government’s reply before
                    deciding on his plans.</p>
                <p>I remarked that it was a sad commentary on the whole situation that Dr. Wang
                    Chung-hui, President of the Judicial Yuan, fountainhead of inspiration for the
                    entire judiciary of China, author of constitutions granting protection to the
                    life and property of citizens of China, should desert the Government and flee to
                    the protection of a foreign settlement at the first sign of trouble.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nelson Trusler Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
