<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1931-06-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1931-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="793" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d793">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.003/733</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far
                                Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conversation With the Chinese Minister</hi> (<hi rend="italic">C. C. Wu</hi>)</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1931-06-06">June 6, 1931</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Dr. Wu referred to the proposal which he had made in his last preceding
                            conversation with Mr. Hornbeck, with regard to the exclusion of a
                            Greater Shanghai area, and that only, from the operation of provisions
                            of the treaty on extraterritoriality, and he wished to know whether Mr.
                            Hornbeck could give him an answer. Mr. Hornbeck said that he would
                            prefer to refrain from discussion of excluded areas until the problems
                            of text, upon which Mr. Jacobs and Mr. Weigh have been working, are
                            disposed of, but that he could say, for the moment, that we adhere to
                            the view which we have all along expressed, that the exclusion of areas
                            at four ports is advisable and desirable; he said that we wish, as from
                            the beginning, to make a treaty which will diminish rather than increase
                            the difficulty of the many problems which are inherent in the great
                            constant problem of contacts in China between foreigners and
                            Chinese.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Wu said that he had heard “from a reliable source” that the British
                            do not really consider it important to exclude any area other than one
                            at Shanghai and that they are using the other three ports for bargaining
                            purposes. He inquired whether Mr. Hornbeck had <pb facs="0984" n="874" xml:id="pg_874"/> been informed on this point. Mr. Hornbeck said
                            that, if such were the case, the British Government would not be likely
                            so to inform either this Government or anybody else and that such a
                            view, if advanced, must be somebody’s statement of opinion rather than
                            an authoritative statement upon which reliance could be placed. He said
                            that he could not imagine the British attaching no importance to what
                            happened at Tientsin, Canton and Hankow. He said that we all know that
                            there is such thing as bargaining—even in connection with conceding of
                            points which ought not to be conceded, but that, quite aside from all
                            such questions, the important thing is: what arrangements may reasonably
                            be expected to improve the situation which is being dealt with? He said
                            that, of all the arguments presented by Dr. Wu in their last
                            conversation, the only one which seemed to him to carry weight in
                            relation to the matter of four rather than one reserved areas was that
                            the Chinese Government would be able to say to the Chinese people, on a
                            basis of one rather than four, that it had scored a greater success in
                            the negotiations. This, however, was a problem largely of how the matter
                            might be presented by the Chinese Government. To him, the facts in the
                            situation support overwhelmingly the opinion that there should be four
                            reserved areas. Reverting to the question of procedure, he would suggest
                            that the points on which Mr. Jacobs and Mr. Weigh have not yet agreed be
                            considered by Dr. Wu, and Dr. Wu’s and his efforts be directed toward
                            completion of the text with the exception of the article on reserved
                            areas. Dr. Wu said that this would be agreeable to him.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>