<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany
                        (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d155</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">155</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-05-01T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-01T09:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="armed-forces" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241" lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-01T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-01T09:00:00-05:00" n="155" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d155">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.811/5–146: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-01T16:00:00+02:00">May 1, 1946—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 1—2:17 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1143. For Radius from Rainey. Reference your cable 982, April 26, 5 p.m.<note n="46" xml:id="d155fn46">Not printed.</note> In our discussions leading to
                    preparation of paper on policy recommendation for Danube March 22, we did not
                    contemplate US initiative in bilateral negotiations with Soviet. Information at
                    that time indicated that Soviet representatives would approach US
                    representatives in Vienna to discuss some practical solution for movement of
                    Danube traffic under control of US and Soviet forces. Soviet position at Council
                    of Foreign Minister in London last September that control of waterways was a
                    concern of the respective zone commanders has been reaffirmed at meetings of
                    Transport Directorate, Berlin, with regard to Rhine and Elbe. It is our
                    understanding that Soviet takes some [<hi rend="italic">same</hi>] position in
                    regard Danube and that they are strongly opposed negotiations with French and
                    British who do occupy areas bordering Danube.</p>
                <p>We appreciate the advisability of taking no action which might prejudice French
                    and British interests on Danube or their participation in a permanent Danube
                    regime, but believe that they realize the frontier between US and Soviet forces
                    will remain “frozen” unless agreement is reached between the two occupying
                    forces concerned. This is implied apparently in London’s discussion reported in
                    London’s cable 4302, April 18.</p>
                <p>Representatives Transport Division Berlin agree that establishment of interim
                    traffic committee is most important step to initiate <pb facs="0266" n="248" xml:id="pg_248"/> free movement on Danube as recommended in our paper.
                    Recommended temporary Danube conservancy commission is less significant at this
                    time and might be omitted from US-Soviet discussion if you believe that
                    bilateral establishment of such a body might prejudice French and British
                    participation in some future Danube Commission. However, US-Soviet discussions
                    limited to that stretch of the river where occupying forces are contiguous could
                    result only in opening the Danube in Austria and Germany. This would not permit
                    significant Danube traffic and probably would sacrifice the present US
                    bargaining position. Therefore, believe that any negotiations with Soviets at
                    this time should concern traffic on entire river.</p>
                <p>Reference your paragraph 4, Transport Division Berlin assumes that former enemy
                    vessels are captured enemy equipment. They now fly US flag as property under
                    control of US Forces and therefore Transport Division believes that there is no
                    possibility of claims against US Government in event of loss or damage. At
                    present each vessel on Danube flying US flag has at least one member of US Armed
                    Forces aboard. On Rhine and at Bremen German ships operated without US personnel
                    aboard fly the international “C”. It is not clear under present instructions
                    whether these Danube vessels could move under US flag without US personnel. Will
                    investigate further. We assume vessels would be operated by national crews and
                    by [apparent garble] companies as at present on Rhine and Danube.</p>
                <p>In view of discussion in London and possible discussions meeting Paris, suggest
                    you request me report Washington for consultation to discuss this Danube matter
                    in greater detail before I leave service. [Rainey.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
