<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Director of the
                        Office of Economic Security Policy (Kindleberger)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d248</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">248</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-09-17T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-09-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="248" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d248">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">863.51/9–1746</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Director of the
                        Office of Economic Security Policy</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Kindleberger</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-09-17">September 17,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Acting Secretary Clayton</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Assistant Secretary, General Hilldring</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>US High Commissioner to Austria, General Mark W. Clark</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Minister to Austria, Mr. Erhardt</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>—Mr. Culbertson<note n="55" xml:id="d248fn55">Paul T. Culbertson, Chief of the Division of
                                Western European Affairs.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_ESP1">ESP</gloss>—Mr. Kindleberger</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_AC1">A–C</gloss>—Mr. McGhee</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_AC1">A–C</gloss>—Mr. Howe</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The discussion turned almost entirely on two subjects: <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>US financial aid to Austria in 1947.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Negotiation with the USSR on the question of German assets in
                            Austria.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>On the first of these topics, General Clark stated that his estimates showed that
                    Austria needed approximately $150,000,000 in 1947. He was aware of the War
                    Department proposals for an appropriation meeting the requirements of the US
                    zone for “disease and unrest”. In his view, however, a larger amount was
                    required which should be spent for Austria as a whole. The US, UK and if other
                    countries such as Canada were willing to contribute, should be prepared to make
                    up the entire amount. If this were the case, he thought he could elicit <pb facs="0388" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"/> contributions from the USSR and
                    France. The funds should be made available to the High Commissioner, who could
                    cut off their expenditure in any one zone where domestic resources were drawn
                    off by an occupying power. He agreed with the view that it might be desirable to
                    handle procurement from the United States and the US zone of Germany through the
                    War Department; some free funds should be made available as such to the Austria
                    government for expenditure in Eastern Europe to enable Austria to obtain better
                    bargains there.</p>
                <p>The Acting Secretary agreed that the Department would make an effort to obtain a
                    deficiency appropriation from Congress for the purposes indicated. This effort
                    would commence when Congress met at the end of November, and might even be
                    preceded by individual discussions with members of important congressional
                    committees. General Hilldring agreed to raise the matter with Representative
                    Cannon of the House Appropriations Subcommittee during the course of his rail
                    trip to San Francisco at the end of the month.<note n="56" xml:id="d248fn56">Assistant Secretary of State John H. Hilldring went to San Francisco to
                        address the American Legion Convention on September 30, 1946.</note>
                </p>
                <p>General Clark asked whether the Department had a view as to new steps which might
                    be taken by USACA or the Department regarding the problem of German assets in
                    Austria. He confessed that he had exhausted every avenue for negotiation on this
                    topic which he thought was open without success. General Hilldring suggested
                    that a further announcement might be made to the effect that the US, UK and
                    France renounced their claims to German assets in Austria, possibly excepting
                    such assets as those of <gloss target="#t_DDSG1">DDSG</gloss> in western Austria
                    and the prewar US oil interests in eastern Austria. Mr. Kindleberger suggested
                    that in addition to this suggestion three possible courses lay open: to withdraw
                    our earlier objections to bilateral negotiations between the Austrian government
                    and the USSR; to postpone the whole issue until the treaty with Austria; to
                    propose a new <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> solution to the USSR, based on
                    equities, rather than on past interpretations of the Potsdam Agreement. It was
                    agreed that Mr. Erhardt and Mr. Kindleberger, together with other interested
                    divisions in the Department, would explore these various possibilities. General
                    Clark made, the point that provision of a loan or grant-in-aid to cover the 1947
                    deficit in Austria would strengthen his hand in dealing with the USSR element of
                        <gloss target="#t_ACA1">ACA</gloss> on German assets.</p>
                <p>The point was made that the US aim of creating an economically and politically
                    independent Austria could probably not be achieved by itself and irrespective of
                    other outstanding European problems, due to the fact that Austria lies partly in
                    eastern and partly in western Europe. The US therefore had a choice between
                    backing out of <pb facs="0389" n="371" xml:id="pg_371"/> Austria now, or
                    attempting to keep the position in Austria open for a few years in the hope of
                    reaching a more satisfactory solution later as part of a general settlement.</p>
                <p>General Clark mentioned that he was preparing to negotiate in <gloss target="#t_ACA1">ACA</gloss> a further reduction in the USSR share in
                    Austrian occupation costs—reducing the proportion of total occupation costs from
                    25% to 20% of the government budget, and putting the USSR on the basis of
                    equality with the other forces, as contrasted with 3:1:1:1. He had tried and
                    failed to use occupation costs as a lever to bargain with the USSR on German
                    assets in Austria in July, where the Soviet answer to his initiative was to
                    refuse US forces the opportunity to repair their communications into Vienna from
                    the US zone, and to give an indication of their readiness to shut off supply
                    lines of food.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
