<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting Secretary of State to
                        the Embassy in France</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d27</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">27</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-05-14T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-14T10:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-14T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-14T10:00:00-05:00" n="27" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d27">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/5–1446: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-14T11:00:00-04:00">May 14, 1946—11 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2312. <gloss target="#t_Secdel1">Secdel</gloss> 231. For Matthews from JDH.<note n="52" xml:id="d27fn52">John D. Hickerson.</note> We have received the
                    following telegram dated May 11 from Harriman: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“You will recall you asked me to attempt to get prompt British action on
                            our use of bases. I have had some general talks with Bevin, Evatt and
                            Nash but as Bevin was authorized to discuss the matter with <pb facs="0062" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/> the Secretary in Paris, no
                            consideration could be given here. I understand that the Secretary told
                            Bevin he could not discuss the questions raised by Bevin until his
                            return to Washington but indicated a willingness to see Evatt and Nash
                            there. The British decided no public statement could in dignity be made
                            during the heated Senate debate.<note n="53" xml:id="d27fn53">Presumably
                                reference is to the debates in the United States Senate regarding
                                extension of British loan.</note> On the other hand Orme
                                Sargent<note n="54" xml:id="d27fn54">British Permanent Under
                                Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.</note> suggested to me that
                            they might be willing to make a general statement if the bill passed the
                            Senate and before consideration by the House. Do you wish me to pursue
                            this suggestion and, if so, what kind of statement by the British do you
                            believe would be helpful? I am afraid that because of the Australian and
                            New Zealand attitude it would have to be rather general in
                            character.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>To this we have sent the following reply: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Before your departure we gave you among the papers on bases (<gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 5052, May 11, 2 p.m.<note n="55" xml:id="d27fn55">Not printed.</note>) a copy of the Secretary’s
                            letter of April 19 to Halifax proposing an exchange of notes on bases
                            and disputed islands which we hoped could be reached in two or three
                            weeks and made public immediately. This exchange of notes would be
                            implemented by a formal agreement between the two Governments later on.
                            Bevin discussed the base question with the Secretary in Paris but we
                            have not heard from the Secretary about the details of their discussion.
                            Since they are under such terrific pressure of work in Paris, this is,
                            of course, understandable. I am afraid that until I hear something from
                            the Secretary, it would not be possible for me to ask you to pursue
                            Sargent’s suggestion. I am still hopeful of an early agreement along the
                            lines of the Secretary’s letter of April 19.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>War Dept has given us a copy of Gen. Lincoln’s telegram<note n="56" xml:id="d27fn56">Telegram <hi rend="smallcaps">ns</hi> 56, May 2, <ref target="#pg_36">p. 36</ref>.</note> on the Secretary’s conversation with
                    Bevin. [JDH.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
