<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of the Twenty-ninth Meeting of the National Advisory
                        Council on International Monetary and Financial Problems, Washington, May
                        24, 1946
                    Also designated as meeting No. 11 of the U.S. Top
                        Committee on French Financial Negotiations.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d305</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">305</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-24T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="305" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d305">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 60 D 137 Box 1 (18358)</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Twenty-ninth Meeting of the National Advisory
                        Council on International Monetary and Financial Problems, Washington, May
                        24, 1946</hi>
                    <note n="67" xml:id="d305fn67">Also designated as meeting No. 11 of the U.S. Top
                        Committee on French Financial Negotiations.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-24">May 24, 1946</date>
                </dateline>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Present:</cell>
                        <cell>Secretary Fred M. Vinson (<hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>), Treasury
                            Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. W. L. Clayton, State Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. George Luthringer, State Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Henry R. Labouisse, State Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Hubert Havlik, State Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Clifford Matlock, State Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Thomas B. McCabe, Foreign Liquidation Commissioner, State
                            Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Lt. Col. C. J. Shields, Office of Foreign Liquidation Commissioner,
                            State Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. James Cooley, Office of Foreign Liquidation Commissioner, State
                            Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Arthur Paul, Commerce Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Marriner S. Eccles, Board of Governors, Federal Reserve
                            System</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. J. Burke Knapp, Board of Governors, Federal Reserve System</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Wm. McC. Martin, Jr., Export-Import Bank</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Herbert Gaston, Export-Import Bank</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. August Maffry, Export-Import Bank</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Rifat Tirana, Export-Import Bank</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Hawthorne Arey, Export-Import Bank</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. H. D. White, International Monetary Fund</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. E. G. Collado, International Bank for Reconstruction and
                            Development</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. E. M. Bernstein, Treasury Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Harold Glasser, Treasury Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. James Brooks, Treasury Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. P. P. Schaffner, Treasury Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Frank Coe (Secretary), Treasury Department</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. Andrew Kamarck (Assistant Secretary), Treasury Department</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">French Financial Negotiations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) <hi rend="italic">War Settlement</hi>.</p>
                <p>Secretary Vinson pointed out that the U.S. figure for the balance due from France
                    on war accounts is $455 million whereas the French <pb facs="0472" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/> figure is $410 million. Mr. Labouisse explained that the
                    U.S. Army valued the supplies furnished by the U.S. armed forces to the French
                    military after V–J Bay at $25 million although the French have carried a figure
                    of $70 million. The French want to fix this item at $25 million and their figure
                    of $410 million reflects this proposal; whereas the U.S. figure of $455 million
                    is based on a value of $70 million for this item. The question before the
                    Council was whether to settle this item now at a definite amount or to adopt the
                    figure of $455 million and leave it open to later accounting adjustment for the
                    post <gloss target="#t_VJDay1">V–J Day</gloss> Army–Navy transfer item.
                    Secretary Vinson did not believe a figure of less than $70 million should be
                    used since the French themselves carried this figure and since it might turn out
                    to be considerably higher. It was pointed out that the unbilled balance of post
                        <gloss target="#t_VJDay1">V–J Day</gloss> transfers under the 3(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) agreement was also subject to later accounting
                    adjustment.</p>
                <p>The Council agreed that the figure of $455 million should be regarded as the
                    settlement balance subject to accounting adjustments for the two items in
                    question.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Action</hi>.</p>
                <p>The following action was taken:</p>
                <p>The National Advisory Council accepts the amount of $455 million as the balance
                    due the United States from the Provisional Government of the French Republic in
                    settlement of the war accounts described in Annex 2 of U.S. Top Committee–French
                    Negotiations Document No. 6, subject to accounting adjustments (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) for post <gloss target="#t_VJDay1">V–J Day</gloss>
                    Army–Navy transfers of supplies to the French military, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) for the unbilled balance of post <gloss target="#t_VJDay1">V–J
                        Day</gloss> transfers under the 3(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) agreement with
                    the Provisional Government of the French Republic.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Surplus Property</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. McCabe explained that the $1.5 billion inventory figure for surplus property,
                    declared and undeclared, in France and French North and West Africa had been
                    reduced to $1.4 billion to cover sales to other foreign governments and to
                        <gloss target="#t_UNRRA1">UNRRA</gloss>. The French are being offered this
                    inventory, including all surplus property already sold or committed for sale to
                    the French but not yet paid for by them and a base in Noumea, for $300 million,
                    21 percent of original cost. The French wanted the inventory to include railway
                    rolling stock when such stock was declared surplus, but were refused this
                    request. The French also wanted a guarantee that deficiencies in the Levy List
                    of urgent requirements would be supplied from surpluses in other areas, priced
                    at the same ratio to original cost as surpluses in France. Mr. McCabe offered to
                    use his best efforts to <pb facs="0473" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> supply these
                    deficiencies. Finally, the French claimed they understood the inventory would
                    include surpluses in all French possessions. The larger part of these surpluses
                    is in New Caledonia. A concession was made to them only on the base in
                    Noumea.</p>
                <p>Mr. Clayton moved that the $300 million offer covering surpluses in France and
                    French North and West Africa be made final with the provision that the <gloss target="#t_FLC1">F.L.C.</gloss> will attempt to supply deficiencies in the
                    Levy List at 21 percent of cost. If the French were unwilling to accept this
                    offer, negotiations should be called off.</p>
                <p>Mr. McCabe stated that at the beginning of the negotiations major emphasis was
                    attached to the Levy List which he thought could be substantially filled.
                    However, during the negotiations, the amount and nature of the items included in
                    the inventory changed, so that it was no longer possible to supply as large a
                    percentage of the critical items as was originally contemplated. He felt that
                    the French should be so informed and that he should be permitted to supply
                    railway rolling stock to make up any ultimate deficiency in the list of critical
                    items. He asked for a reconsideration of Mr. Clayton’s motion in order to
                    include the following provision: If railway rolling stock in Europe is declared
                    surplus, the amount allocated as French surplus will be included in the $300
                    million offer to the extent necessary to make up deficiencies in the list of
                    critical items.</p>
                <p>The Council agreed that the French should be advised of any changes in the
                    original estimates of the availability of critical items; but it decided that,
                    in view of the low price at which the surplus was offered, no provisions for
                    including rolling stock should be made. Mr. McCabe acquiesced in this
                    decision.</p>
                <p>The motion proposed by Mr. Clayton was passed. Secretary Vinson remarked that he
                    would rely on the State Department for handling any developments arising from
                    the above settlement.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Action</hi>.</p>
                <p>The following action was taken:</p>
                <p>The National Advisory Council approves the offer, described in Annex 5 of U.S.
                    Top Committee–French Negotiations Document No. 6, made by the Foreign
                    Liquidation Commissioner to the Provisional Government of France for the
                    disposition of surplus property.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Credit Terms</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Labouisse reported that the French want terms of 2 percent for 50 years with
                    a waiver clause in the war settlement credits. Mr. McCabe said he had offered
                    terms of 2⅜ percent for 30 years with a <pb facs="0474" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> deferment of principal repayment for 5 years, but without any waiver clause
                    on interest payments. Secretary Vinson remarked that the French want the same
                    terms as were given the British so as to avoid an unfavorable public reaction in
                    France. Mr. Eccles believed there was no reason for giving the French specially
                    favorable terms, such as 2 percent, particularly since they were probably
                    getting a better overall deal at 2⅜ percent than the British were at 2 percent.
                    The British case, moreover, was unique in many respects.</p>
                <p>Mr. McCabe reviewed the unsatisfactory history of collections on World War I
                    settlements. He thought some distinction was reasonable between countries where
                    large overall settlements were involved and those where the settlement amounts
                    were relatively small. Mr. Clayton said that the main consideration was
                    collection of the principal; that the interest rate was not too important. He
                    suggested that the interest rate be set at 2 percent for all countries with
                    which overall war settlements were made. Mr. Eccles maintained that if any
                    revision of policy were made, it should be consistent with respect to all
                    countries involved. He proposed a 2⅜ percent rate for France unless terms for
                    all other countries were reduced to 2 percent. He thought the easier terms could
                    be justified before Congress on the grounds that it was necessary to give the
                    French such terms, and, therefore, it was also necessary to give them to other
                    countries. Mr. Martin emphasized that the problem should be considered in more
                    detail before any action was taken. Mr. Gaston asked how the proposed reduction
                    would affect Export-Import Bank’s loans on 3(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) terms to
                    France, Belgium and the Netherlands. Mr. McCabe thought that credits for goods
                    under requisition were in a different category from credits on surplus already
                    in France. Mr. Eccles added that the proposed reduction in interest was not
                    intended to refer to the Export-Import Bank’s loans on 3(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) terms.</p>
                <p>After further discussion, the Council agreed that in countries with which overall
                    war settlements were made, any credits granted in connection with these
                    settlements would be at 2 percent for 35 years with a five year period of grace
                    on repayments of principal, but with no waiver of interest. Such terms would not
                    apply to isolated surplus sales; nor would they apply to the Russian pipeline
                    case unless an overall war settlement was made with Russia. Mr. Clayton pointed
                    out that the French Lend-Lease agreement contains a provision for postponement
                    of installments due, upon mutual agreement by the two governments. It was
                    decided that this provision did not interfere with the Council’s action and that
                    it should also be included in the war settlement agreement.</p>
                <pb facs="0475" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Action</hi>.</p>
                <p>The following action was taken:</p>
                <p>The National Advisory Council approves the following terms for the extension of
                    credit by the United States Government to the Provisional Government of the
                    French Republic in the overall settlement of war accounts: Interest at 2 percent
                    per annum; period of repayment, 35 years, with an initial 5 year period of grace
                    on repayments of principal; no provision similar to that in the financial
                    agreement between the governments of the United States and the United Kingdom
                    for waiver of interest payments. Terms should also include the provision
                    contained in paragraph C(3) of Schedule 1 and paragraph 5 of Schedule 2 of the
                    “Agreement between the United States of America and the Provisional Government
                    of France,” dated February 28, 1945.<note n="68" xml:id="d305fn68">59 Stat. (pt.
                        2) 1304.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Credit Terms in Overall Settlements of War Accounts</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Action</hi>.</p>
                <p>The following action was taken:</p>
                <p>The National Advisory Council approves the following terms for the extension of
                    credit by the United States Government in connection with, and only in
                    connection with, overall settlements of war accounts with foreign countries:
                    Interest at 2 percent per annum; period of repayment, 35 years, with an initial
                    5 year period of grace on repayments of principal; no provision for waiver of
                    interest payments. These terms are specifically not to be regarded as applicable
                    to credits involved in separate sales of U.S. surplus property to foreign
                    countries.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) <hi rend="italic">French Tort and Patent Claims, and
                        Claims for Requisitioned French Goods in the U.S.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Labouisse explained that the French have agreed to settle at their own
                    expense, as a reciprocal aid benefit, all tort claims against the U.S. arising
                    out of acts or omissions of U.S. military and civilian personnel up to <gloss target="#t_VJDay1">V–J Day</gloss>; but that they refuse to accept this
                    liability for acts after <gloss target="#t_VJDay1">V–J Day</gloss> unless
                    compensated by an allowance of up to $10 million in the claim settlement. The
                    Army regards this proposed allowance as quite high. With regard to patent claims
                    of French nationals against the U.S., the French are willing to assume a
                    liability, as a matter of reciprocal aid, up to $5 million. With regard to
                    French material and equipment in the U.S. requisitioned by this government for
                    war use, he said that the U.S. Settlement Committee believed that at least the
                    claims of the French Government should be waived.</p>
                <p>Secretary Vinson wanted a final settlement to be reached on all these claims and
                    the Council approved that an amount of up to $15 millon be proposed to the
                    French in settlement of the claims.</p>
                <pb facs="0476" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Action</hi>.</p>
                <p>The following action was taken:</p>
                <p>In the overall settlement of war accounts with the Provisional Government of the
                    French Republic, an amount of up to $15 million is approved by the National
                    Advisory Council to settle (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) all tort and patent claims
                    of the French against the U.S. Government and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) all
                    claims with respect to French material and equipment located in the U.S. and
                    requisitioned by the U.S. Government for war uses after U.S. entry into the
                    war.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Press Release and Joint Declaration
                        on Settlement of French War Accounts</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Council reviewed a draft press release and joint declaration and made several
                    revisions. In connection with the statement concerning the Export-Import Bank’s
                    $650 million credit to France, Mr. Gaston said the French want the credit to
                    cover a $150 million revolving fund and a $150 million expenditure already made
                    by the French for North African supplies. The Bank analyzed a list of French
                    requirements totaling $864 million and found that 67 percent represents current
                    supplies; 21 percent, equipment; and 12 percent, freight and services. The Bank
                    felt the percent of current supplies was entirely too high to finance under a
                    reconstruction and development loan. The French were really asking for an open
                    loan although the Bank is restricted to loans for specific projects, and thus
                    far the French had been unwilling to change the nature of their credit request.
                    The Bank offered the French terms of 3 percent for 25 years with a 5 year period
                    of grace on repayments of principal. In view of the unsettled state of the loan
                    negotiations, the Council decided to use the following statement: “The other
                    provisions of the loan contract are now being worked out between the Provisional
                    Government of France and the Export-Import Bank.”</p>
                <p>The Council agreed to dispense with the press release and approved the revised
                    joint declaration.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Action of the Council</hi>.</p>
                <p>The Council approved a joint declaration of the President of the United States
                    and the President of the Provisional Government of the French Republic. The
                    final text of this declaration is contained in Attachment (B) to the minutes of
                    the meeting of May 28, 1946.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
