<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="315" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d315">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">851.00B/12–2046</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Office of European
                                    Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-26">November 26, 1946</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    December 2.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Doc</hi>: I suggest that you have a look at
                                Norris Chipman’s memorandum no. 345, dated November 23, 1946.</p>
                            <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Jefferson
                                Caffery</hi></signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Norris B. Chipman, Second
                                        Secretary of Embassy in France</hi></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                        <lb/> No. 345</seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-23">November 23, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Tactics of the French
                                        Communist Party According to a Source Maintaining Close
                                        Contacts With Important Communists</hi></p>
                                <p>The former representative of the Italian Communist Party at
                                    Moscow, Rossi (Tasca) who was also formerly an important agent
                                    in <pb facs="0490" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/> Western Europe of
                                    the <gloss target="#t_Comintern1">Comintern</gloss>, has
                                    furnished me the following information based on a recent
                                    conversation which he had with a friend maintaining close and
                                    friendly relations with certain members of the Political Bureau
                                    of the French Communist Party. Since I have confidence in the
                                    political judgment, as well as intellectual honesty of Rossi,
                                    who broke with Moscow on democratic grounds in protest against
                                    the <gloss target="#t_Comintern1">Comintern</gloss>’s brutal
                                    methods and interventions in the affairs of the various
                                    Communist parties abroad, I consider that this highly
                                    interesting report should receive serious attention.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Return of Thorez from
                                        Moscow</hi></p>
                                <p>Thorez returned to Paris from Moscow at the beginning of last
                                    September. His brief trip was clandestine since no mention
                                    thereof was ever made by the Party which, however, by way of
                                    explaining Thorez’s absence from State councils, issued a
                                    laconic communiqué stating that its Secretary General was sick.
                                    His trip was taken at the instance of the Soviet authorities and
                                    in this connection it is noteworthy that it was Thorez and not
                                    Duclos who was summoned to Moscow because the Kremlin desired to
                                    discuss the Communist position within the French Government
                                    rather than strictly to investigate Party matters; if the
                                    problem under discussion had related to internal Party questions
                                    the Kremlin naturally would have summoned Duclos.</p>
                                <p>At the first meeting held by the Political Bureau of the French
                                    Communist Party subsequent to his return to Paris, Thorez
                                    delivered a report on the international situation as viewed by
                                    the Soviet authorities. While he did not indicate, according to
                                    the source under reference, whether he had conferred with the
                                    “boss” that is, Stalin, Thorez left no doubt that his views were
                                    inspired by the highest Soviet authorities. He spoke as
                                    follows:</p>
                                <p>The international situation is favorable in general to the
                                    interests of the Soviet Union but the latter is not in the
                                    position at the present juncture of European affairs to draw the
                                    greatest possible benefit therefrom. The Soviet Union is not
                                    prepared for war and its military preparations will not be
                                    completed for a number of years. Hence, the necessity to <hi rend="italic">gain time</hi> and to avoid situations of a
                                    highly dangerous nature while endeavoring to maintain and even
                                    consolidate positions already acquired. The policy and tactics
                                    of the French Communist Party must follow <hi rend="italic">closely in line with this perspective</hi> and should be
                                    oriented in an intelligent manner with Soviet policies.</p>
                                <p>Because the Soviet Union is in the position of having to avoid
                                    during a relatively long period participation in a major war, it
                                    follows that the French Communist Party should not advance too
                                    rapidly and above all else must not endeavor to seize power by
                                    force <pb facs="0491" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> since to do so
                                    would probably precipitate an international conflict from which
                                    the Soviet Union could hardly emerge victorious. The eyes of the
                                    United States and England are directed towards France and should
                                    the French Communists become too openly aggressive, they would
                                    bring about a major crisis which might too deeply involve the
                                    Soviet Union.</p>
                                <p>At the same meeting of the Political Bureau Duclos spoke for the
                                    purpose of stressing the point that Thorez’s report confirmed
                                    what he had always said, namely, that a Communist party “worthy
                                    of the name must know how to make the necessary sacrifices on
                                    the internal level in order later to reap more substantial
                                    harvests from the international situation”. He indicated in this
                                    way that while the French Communist Party was now in the
                                    position forcibly to seize power, it was obliged to shape its
                                    policies so as not to conflict with the larger interests of the
                                    Soviet Union; in the final analysis the maintenance of Communist
                                    power in France would depend upon the success of the Soviet
                                    Union in Europe.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">The “Reassuring” Declarations
                                        of Thorez</hi></p>
                                <p>The situation as outlined above explains to a considerable extent
                                    the motives behind the interviews given recently by Thorez to
                                    Reuters, the London <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> and the <gloss target="#t_INS1">INS</gloss>. Thorez had not resorted
                                    previously to issuing such “reassuring” statements because
                                    Moscow awaited the results of the elections; since the latter
                                    were even more favorable than the Communist leadership had
                                    anticipated in their most sanguine moments and have rendered the
                                    Communists not only the first National party but also the only
                                    great party on the so-called Left, it was expedient that Thorez
                                    take a public stand on the basis of his Moscow
                                    conversations.</p>
                                <p>These interviews were rendered necessary by the unexpected
                                    success of the Communist Party at the polls on November 10 when
                                    the Communist leadership anticipated that their Party would not
                                    increase its representation in the National Assembly by more
                                    than five or six seats at the most; as a result of this success
                                    the Communists received the order from Moscow to make a serious
                                    bid for the formation of a Cabinet under Communist direction and
                                    consequently the Thorez interviews should be regarded in the
                                    light of the <hi rend="italic">general campaign</hi> of the
                                    Soviet Union at the present juncture to reassure the distrustful
                                    Anglo-Saxons and thus attenuate the existing international
                                    tension. In this manner, the outbreak of the “inevitable” armed
                                    conflict with the British and Americans would be postponed until
                                    the Soviet Union had improved its military strength and had
                                    further consolidated its political position in eastern, central
                                    and southeastern Europe.</p>
                                <pb facs="0492" n="474" xml:id="pg_474"/>
                                <p>While the Soviet authorities wish to avoid the creation of a
                                    French Communist Government which would too greatly alarm
                                    England and America, the French Communists are in the position
                                    now where they must continue to march towards the attainment of
                                    final power because not to do so would break the powerful
                                    current that is advancing their dynamic movement. The Communists
                                    feel certain that this current as well as their organizational
                                    genius will bring them even greater success at the elections on
                                    November 24 for the Council of the Republic than was achieved at
                                    the polls on November 10. Should this success be realized, the
                                    expediency of the Thorez interviews becomes still more
                                    justified.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Realignment of Foreign
                                        Policies</hi></p>
                                <p>It is certain that Soviet foreign policy as executed during the
                                    past six months has often embarrassed and rendered more
                                    difficult the role of various Communist parties in Europe,
                                    especially the French Party with respect to the German problem
                                    and the Italian in connection with Trieste. In conformity with
                                    the general tactics of the Neo-<gloss target="#t_Comintern1">Comintern</gloss>, both parties had successfully exploited
                                    the national and even nationalist sentiments existing within
                                    their countries, but finally found themselves in open
                                    contradiction with the official position of the Soviet Union;
                                    they were thus confronted with the disagreeable alternative of
                                    repudiating the Soviet Union—an impossibility—or of seeing their
                                    patriotic coat of arms somewhat besmirched.</p>
                                <p>The Kremlin has seldom, if ever, seriously worried about the
                                    difficulties thrust upon the various Communist parties abroad by
                                    its foreign policies because it always felt sure that these
                                    parties would re-remain obedient and would finish by faithfully
                                    supporting Soviet interests even if embarrassing explanations of
                                    zig-zag changes of the party “line” became necessary. The law of
                                    self-interest is the only principle that Moscow invariably obeys
                                    but this time Soviet interest itself was at stake and
                                    accordingly it became expedient that the foreign policies of the
                                    French and Italian parties be realigned with “general Soviet”
                                    policy. In this manner the double purpose of aiding Soviet
                                    interests, as well as those of the two greatest Communist
                                    parties in Europe would be served. In view of Soviet
                                    unpreparedness, neither the German nor Adriatic situations could
                                    be pushed to the breaking point.</p>
                                <p>This explains Molotov’s recent attitude at the Security Council
                                    and his search for a direct compromise between Italy and
                                    Yugoslavia announced by Togliatti’s visit to Belgrade.<note n="76" xml:id="d315fn76">For documentation relating to the
                                        visit to Belgrade of Palmiro Togliatti, secretary-general of
                                        the Italian Communist party, see volume <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>.</note> For some time it was clear <pb facs="0493" n="475" xml:id="pg_475"/> that the Soviet Union
                                    was disposed to make certain concessions to Italy rather than to
                                    abandon Trieste to an international regime which might entail
                                    the more or less permanent installation in this strategic
                                    territory of Allied armed control. The Soviet Union in reality
                                    preferred an Italian administration with as little power as
                                    possible in the hands of the city government in order to augment
                                    the pressure which could be exercised by the Slav elements of
                                    the surrounding countryside. Tito proposed the “exchange” of
                                    Trieste for Gorizia for two reasons; first, to dominate
                                    militarily the valley of the Isonzo and the Julian Marches, and,
                                    secondly, to eliminate Anglo-Saxon troops from this vital
                                    area.</p>
                                <p>The coincidence of three important factors should be noted with
                                    respect to the policies outlined above, namely, the Soviet
                                    Union’s desire to gain time, its necessity to maintain already
                                    conquered positions, and its self-interest in re-aligning the
                                    foreign policies of the French and Italian Communist parties in
                                    the aim of ameliorating their internal positions. The results of
                                    the Italian municipal elections indicate that this re-alignment
                                    and conciliatory attitude in the case of Italy was not without
                                    success.</p>
                                <p>In the case of Germany, Stalin perceived the expediency of
                                    reinforcing the position of the <gloss target="#t_SED1">S.E.D.</gloss> (Socialist–Communist group) and disarming
                                    the distrust produced by the policy of the “Iron Curtain” in the
                                    Soviet zone. This explains Stalin’s clear stand on the necessity
                                    of a united political and economic Germany expressed in his
                                    interview with Alexander Werth and the President of the United
                                    Press, Hugh Baillie.<note n="77" xml:id="d315fn77">For
                                        documentation relating to these interviews, see volume <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>.</note> But prior officially to
                                    taking position on the matter, the Kremlin considered it
                                    expedient to reorient the French Communist “line” on Germany
                                    with its own German policy. The Thorez visit to Moscow laid the
                                    groundwork for this reorientation.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">The New German Policy of the
                                        French Communist Party</hi></p>
                                <p>Owing to the possibility that Thorez might direct the new Cabinet
                                    to be formed on the basis of the November 10 and 24 elections,
                                    it became all the more urgent that he begin publicly to clarify
                                    his Party’s views on Germany. While it is true that the new
                                    French Communist position already had been clearly set forth in
                                    the September issue of the theoretical organ of the Communist
                                    Party <hi rend="italic">Cahiers du Communisme</hi>, nevertheless
                                    the French public remained largely ignorant of this latest
                                    corkscrew twist of the Party “line”. (In this connection see
                                    memorandum no. 336 dated October 29, 1946).<note n="78" xml:id="d315fn78">Not printed.</note></p>
                                <pb facs="0494" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/>
                                <p>The Party in other words waited for the election results prior to
                                    making the necessary declaration as set forth by Thorez in his
                                    interview with Reuters in which he insisted that an accord
                                    “should be found” between the Soviet formula of “interallied
                                    control of the Ruhr” and the French Communist demand for
                                    internationalization”. Thus, once more the French Communists
                                    repudiated their own policy, as well as that of the <gloss target="#t_MRP1">MRP</gloss>, without being seriously
                                    attacked even by the latter.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">The French Communist Party and
                                        the <gloss target="#t_MRP1">MRP</gloss></hi></p>
                                <p>At the first meeting of the Political Bureau which took place
                                    subsequent to the November 10 elections, Jacques Duclos
                                    expressed great satisfaction over the results of the elections,
                                    especially since they had placed his Party in first position on
                                    the national scale, as well as on the “Left”. Duclos ventured
                                    the view that had the <gloss target="#t_MRP1">MRP</gloss>
                                    pursued the tendency espoused by Lecourt—one of the most
                                    anti-Communist leaders of the <gloss target="#t_MRP1">MRP</gloss>—it would probably have obtained not less than
                                    200 seats and would have thus remained the first party of
                                    France. Fortunately, added Duclos, the Bidault–Gay tendency had
                                    dominated the Catholics despite the fact that the vast majority
                                    of the <gloss target="#t_MRP1">MRP</gloss> is
                                    anti-Communist.</p>
                                <p>Duclos further insisted that the <gloss target="#t_MRP1">MRP</gloss> would continue to play a very important role in
                                    the political life of France and consequently it was necessary
                                    not only to maintain but also reinforce the liaison now happily
                                    enjoyed between the Communist and the Bidault–Gay tendency.
                                    Duclos added that Bidault remained favorable to collaboration
                                    with the Communists within the Government and that one could
                                    nearly always count on him by “playing on his vanity”; he
                                    explained that the close ties between Bidault and the Communists
                                    had been established in 1943 when an accord was reached on the
                                    basis of Communist support for Bidault as Foreign Minister in
                                    the Government to be formed following the Liberation.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Military Preparations</hi></p>
                                <p>While continuing the policy of “legality” required by the
                                    exigencies of the international situation, the Communists are by
                                    no means slowing up their secret penetration of State
                                    institutions or their clandestine military preparations. On the
                                    contrary the International Brigades are being
                                    reinforced—recently strengthened by two brigades—and in this
                                    connection it should be noted that Marty’s<note n="79" xml:id="d315fn79">André Marty, a French Communist
                                        leader.</note> trip to Moscow last September already has
                                    brought results (see memorandum no. 518<note n="80" xml:id="d315fn80">Not printed.</note>).</p>
                                <pb facs="0495" n="477" xml:id="pg_477"/>
                                <p>Moreover, the Communists now count on fresh sources of
                                    recruitment for their armed groups, namely, among the 200,000
                                    Italian workers who plan to immigrate into France. The
                                    organization of this recruitment in Italy is in the hands of the
                                    Communist dominated Italian <gloss target="#t_CGT1">C.G.T.</gloss> and on the French side is being carried out
                                    by the present Minister of Labor and veteran Communist trade
                                    unionist, Croizat. Since a large number of workers in Northern
                                    Italy are Communist and possess military training the
                                    opportunities offered by this mass inflow of Italians into
                                    France certainly will not be neglected by the Italian and French
                                    Communists.</p>
                                <p>Finally, it is noteworthy that should Thorez head the next
                                    Cabinet the Communists would hold an ace card in extending their
                                    power and influence over the State because the civil service
                                    bill just promoted by Thorez and accepted by the Assembly places
                                    the career of every government official in the last instance
                                    under the control of the President of the Council and not the
                                    Ministry with which the employee is connected.</p>
                                <closer><signed>N[<hi rend="smallcaps">orris</hi>] B. C[<hi rend="smallcaps">hipman</hi>]</signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>