<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="327" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d327">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">862.50/l–2846</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation</hi><note n="24a" xml:id="d327fn24a">Presumably prepared by the Office of European
                                    Affairs.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-28">January 28,
                                        1946</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Lord Halifax<note n="25" xml:id="d327fn25">British Ambassador.</note>
                                called at his request upon the Secretary this afternoon. He referred
                                to a personal note from Mr. Bevin to Mr. Byrnes, dated January
                                    24,<note n="26" xml:id="d327fn26">Quoted in telegram 253,
                                    January 28, to Berlin, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note>
                                regarding German reparations and the level of German industry. He
                                stated that as he understood the problem, the British thought they
                                had reached an agreement with the United States and the Russians and
                                were going to take a certain figure—what they called the retaining
                                level—7.5. That did not mean the Germans would be allowed to make
                                that. The agreement was that we would allow the Germans to make 5.8
                                and see how they got along. Now the question came up what to do with
                                all the other steel using plants. As he understood it, the agreement
                                was that all those plants would be rationed on the basis of 5.8, but
                                not destroyed or dismantled to the level of 5.8 yet. They would be
                                kept in existence at the level of 7.5. Then if we found we couldn’t
                                get along with 5.8 and were faced with mass unemployment, we could
                                always keep an eye on the potential and let it expand to 7.5
                                million.</p>
                            <pb facs="0512" n="494" xml:id="pg_494"/>
                            <p>The Secretary replied that that was his understanding, too. He stated
                                that he discussed the situation with General Clay in London and
                                everything was so definite that it looked like a closed case. The
                                agreement had been reached after months of discussion among the
                                British, Americans, French and Russians—production 5.8 and capacity
                                7.5. General Clay said there was no question about the agreement,
                                but the British representative, Mr. [<hi rend="italic">General</hi>]
                                Roberston, subsequently placed a different interpretation on it.
                                This action on the part of the British representative disturbed
                                General Clay and the French representative, as the Soviets could
                                cite this position as a precedent in subsequent matters and take an
                                interpretation different from the other three members. On the merits
                                of the agreement General Clay said that there was not a chance in a
                                year and a half to reach 5.8 production. Therefore, so far as steel
                                was concerned it was academic. His view was that a peace treaty
                                would fix anything for the future. This agreement could be construed
                                only for the present and for the production during the time we were
                                in control.</p>
                            <p>The Secretary said that he agreed with Mr. Bevin’s views as set forth
                                in his note and would so advise General Clay. Unless it was in
                                conflict with what General Clay positively agreed, this represented
                                his opinion of what it ought to be. The Secretary added that he had
                                explained the whole situation to Mr. Bevin but Bevin was afraid that
                                it is to be used as a yardstick for all industry besides steel.</p>
                            <p>Lord Halifax stated that Mr. Bevin was most anxious that the British
                                and Americans do not take divergent positions on this, which may
                                affect European economy.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>