<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Director of the Office of Military Government of the
                        United States for Germany (
                        Clay
                    ) to the Secretary of State and the Secretary of
                        Agriculture (
                        Anderson
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d359</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">359</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-04-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-04-11T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec577cb840b7a9a75" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="potsdam-agreement">Potsdam Agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="finance" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885" lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="transportation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="wheat" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366" lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="359" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d359">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.5018/4–1146: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Director of the Office of Military Government of the
                        United States for Germany</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clay</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Secretary of State and the Secretary of
                        Agriculture</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Anderson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-11">11 April
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>CC 2931. Action to Sec State Wash DC for Byrnes and Anderson from Fitzgerald<note n="84" xml:id="d359fn84">Dennis A. Fitzgerald, U.S. Department of
                        Agriculture.</note> Political Affairs Div <gloss target="#t_OMGUS1">OMGUS</gloss> from Clay sgd McNarney.<note n="85" xml:id="d359fn85">Gen.
                        Joseph T. McNarney, Military Governor, U.S. Zone of Occupation in Germany;
                        Commanding General, United States Forces, European Theater; U.S. member,
                        Allied Control Council for Germany.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Satisfied that it is of paramount importance to implement Potsdam Agreement
                    regarding establishment of German Central Administrative Agencies for Finance,
                    Transportation, Communication, Foreign Trade, and Industry. French have
                    heretofore refused to concur. Recommend French be informed that unless they
                    prepare to concur immediately in establishment such centralized administrative
                    agencies, all shipments of wheat to French zone of Germany will be discontinued,
                    and furthermore shipments wheat to France will also be discontinued if French
                    still unwilling to agree.<note n="86" xml:id="d359fn86">
                        <p>In regard to this telegram, Acting Secretary Acheson in a letter to
                            Secretary of War Patterson dated April 24 stated his belief that it
                            would be unwise to exert such direct pressure on the French Government
                            in view of the fact that Germany was to be discussed at the Second
                            Session of the Council of Foreign Ministers beginning on April 25
                            (862.5018/4–2446). For documentation on the meetings of the Council of
                            Foreign Ministers, see volume <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Previously, in a memorandum of April 17 to Assistant Secretary of War
                            Peterson, H. Freeman Matthews, Director of the Office of European
                            Affairs, had made the following comments relating to U.S. concern over
                            French reluctance to see German central agencies established:</p>
                        <p>“Further pressure will be brought to bear on the French Government in the
                            course of the present economic and financial negotiations. The French
                            representatives will be informed that in connection with these
                            negotiations, our attitude on economic assistance will be influenced by
                            the French position on central agencies. In addition to the pressure we
                            have been bringing on the French, as recapitulated above, the
                            responsible officers of the Department continue in their day-to-day
                            contacts with the French Embassy to impress upon the French authorities
                            the grave concern which we feel in the continued delay in the
                            establishment of central agencies. For example, it was made plain to the
                            French Ambassador that the French request for additional grain for their
                            zone in Germany and for more coal for France in the allocation of German
                            coal were intimately linked with the problem of central German agencies
                            and that the French intransigence had led to some of the very shortages
                            of which they were complaining.” (740.00119 Control
                            (Germany)/4–1746)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
