<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany
                        (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d361</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">361</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-04-22T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-04-22T14:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-22T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-22T14:00:00-05:00" n="361" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d361">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.50/4–2546: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, [<date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-22T21:00:00+02:00">April 22, 1946—9 p.m.</date>]<note n="90" xml:id="d361fn90">Date of
                            transmission supplied from copy in the files of the U.S. Political
                            Adviser.</note>
                        <lb/>[Received April 25—11:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1080. For Terrill.<note n="91" xml:id="d361fn91">Robert P. Terrill, Associate
                        Chief of the International Resources Division.</note> 1. Coleman<note n="92" xml:id="d361fn92">Creighton R. Coleman, Acting Chief of the Decartelization
                        Branch, Economic Division, <gloss target="#t_OMGUS1">OMGUS</gloss>.</note>
                    reports that last quadripartite meeting on deconcentration law held subsequent
                    to receipt of new State Department instructions<note n="89" xml:id="d361fn89">Not printed.</note> sent through <gloss target="#t_AGWar1">AGWar</gloss> to
                        <gloss target="#t_OMGUS1">OMGUS</gloss> resulted in failure; that British
                    refused to recede from their original position to the effect that a definition
                    of “excess concentration of economic power could not be formulated”. Coleman has
                    contacted the British on two occasions since the quadripartite meeting and is of
                    the opinion that the British in Berlin have had the Washington proposal on the
                    deconcentration law referred to them from London, and have refused to go along
                    with it.</p>
                <p>Coleman further reports that during his conversation with the British, and making
                    it absolutely clear to them that it was not an official position, asked for the
                    British reaction to the following proposal: “Every enterprise which employs in
                    excess of 20,000 persons shall be deemed to be an excess of concentration of
                    economic power and shall take such action as shall be prescribed by the Economic
                    Directorate or by any other agency authorized by the Control Council to take
                    action in such cases.” Added to this he suggested that a list of 35 companies be
                    compiled against which immediate action would be <pb facs="0561" n="543" xml:id="pg_543"/> taken. He states that he pointed out to them that the
                    20,000 figure was a measure for the future, in as much as only a very few
                    enterprises in Germany now employ that many, the 35 companies possible being a
                    sufficient number of reorganizations for present purposes. Coleman reports that
                    the British officials with whom he was conferring became very interested in this
                    proposal and stated they would try to persuade the British delegation to accept
                    a proposition along these lines; that, however, on the following day he was
                    informed by British with whom he had talked that no definition of “excess of
                    concentration” could be accepted. Coleman carried on these talks with British as
                    Acting Chief Decartelization Branch. He states that he also conferred for
                    approximately two hours with General Draper<note n="93" xml:id="d361fn93">Brig.
                        Gen. William H. Draper, Jr., Chief, Economic Division, <gloss target="#t_OMGUS1">OMGUS</gloss>.</note> on the Deconcentration Law,
                    during which time General Draper talked at considerable length over the phone
                    with Sir Percy Mills<note n="94" xml:id="d361fn94">Head of the Economic
                        Division, British Element, Allied Control Council for Germany.</note> in an
                    endeavor to find a solution the problem but without success. Coleman is
                    convinced that there is primarily only one man in the British delegation who is
                    blocking the law and that is Sir Percy Mills. As April Chairman of the working
                    party on Deconcentration Law Coleman will have to report disagreement on the law
                    to the Economic Directorate during the week of April 22.<note n="95" xml:id="d361fn95">Subsequently, telegram 4816, May 6, 6 p.m., from London,
                        reported on a note from the Foreign Office, dated May 4, stating that the
                        British Government expressed disappointment at the failure of the Economic
                        Directorate on April 25 to agree to a compromise proposal by the British
                        representative based largely on the Washington understanding, and indicating
                        that the British Government was prepared to accept a law based on that
                        understanding (862.50/5–646).</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
