<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany
                        (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d434</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">434</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-02-18T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-02-18T10:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-18T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-18T10:00:00-05:00" n="434" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d434">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/2–1846:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-02-18T16:00:00+01:00">February 18, 1946—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received February 18—1:01 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>538. War Department has requested <gloss target="#t_USFET1">USFET</gloss> to
                    comment on a further request from the French for the inclusion of Karlsruhe and
                    Mannheim in the French zone of occupation.<note n="38" xml:id="d434fn38">For
                        earlier documentation on this subject, see telegram 211, December 29, 1945,
                        from Frankfurt, <ref target="frus1945v03#pg_1025">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 1025</ref>.</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_OMGUS1">OMGUS</gloss> has recommended that <gloss target="#t_USFET1">USFET</gloss> include the following comment in its reply
                    to the War Department.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Military Government has organized United States zone of occupation into
                        these units. The separation of any further territory to include Karlsruhe
                        and Mannheim at this time would indicate lack of stability of our state
                        boundaries. If and when central administrative machinery is established, it
                        should be possible to fix permanently state boundaries within Germany. When
                        this is accomplished and state governments are functioning uniformly under a
                        federalized structure, the origin of occupation troops becomes less
                        important. Moreover, existing difficulties in communications between zones
                        would increase greatly with loss of Karlsruhe and Mannheim and importation
                        of civil needs into the United States zone would be made more difficult with
                        our Rhine imports under French jurisdiction. Also, would be removing
                        industrial area which would make United States zone even less independent
                        economically than at present. Prestige of American Military Government
                        necessitates the holding of present boundaries until the future governmental
                        structures of Germany is agreed by the Four occupying powers. Otherwise,
                        execution of our Military Government mission will be made most
                        difficult.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Sent to Department as 538; repeated to Frankfurt as 18.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
