<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-21T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-21T18:00:00-05:00" n="447" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d447">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/8–2146:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss>, at Paris</hi><note n="80" xml:id="d447fn80">The Secretary of State was in Paris as Chairman of the United
                                    States Delegation to the Paris Peace Conference.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-08-21T19:00:00-04:00">August 21, 1946—7
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>4272. <gloss target="#t_Secdel1">Secdel</gloss> 719. For Secretary
                                Byrnes from Benton.<note n="81" xml:id="d447fn81">Assistant
                                    Secretary of State William Benton.</note> Re Russian
                                    broadcasts.<note n="82" xml:id="d447fn82">Reference is to a
                                    projected Department of State program for information broadcasts
                                    in the Russian language to the Soviet Union, making use of
                                    transmitters located in Munich.</note> Assume you have available
                                copy Clay’s cable to War Department number CC–1697 of August 12, and
                                Murphy’s 1911 of August 13 on this subject.<note n="83" xml:id="d447fn83">Neither printed.</note> Both cables restate
                                Clay’s political objections to use of Munich transmitters for State
                                Department broadcasts to Russia as inconsistent with the spirit of
                                quadripartite government.<note n="84" xml:id="d447fn84">General Clay
                                    felt, according to telegram 1911, August 13, from Berlin, that a
                                    radio station such as the one contemplated in Munich would be
                                    subject to rules of censorship approved by the Control Council
                                    (811.42700 (R)/8–1346).</note> This objection of Clay’s was
                                previously reviewed by Staff Committee and not found sufficiently
                                persuasive. I feel this project of such vital importance that Clay
                                should be requested to facilitate it in accordance with his
                                statement of willingness to do so despite recording his
                                objections.</p>
                            <p>In accordance with your earlier expression of views which are
                                confirmed in your telegram 3963 of August 11 quoting Sarnoff’s
                                    memorandum,<note n="85" xml:id="d447fn85">Telegram 3063 not
                                    printed. The memorandum to Secretary Byrnes from Mr. David
                                    Sarnoff, president of <gloss target="#t_RCA1">RCA</gloss>, dealt
                                    with American broadcasting both in Germany and to the Soviet
                                    Union. It urged that a study be undertaken to determine the
                                    technical facilities required to provide American broadcasting
                                    services equal or superior to those furnished the Germans from
                                    the Soviet Zone. Mr. Sarnoff’s memorandum also proposed that a
                                    high powered broadcasting station be set up in Berlin, that the
                                    power of the existing station in Munich be increased and linked
                                    with the proposed station in Berlin, and that the Munich station
                                    be equipped with short wave facilities to enable it to
                                    re-transmit to the Soviet Union Russian language programs
                                    originating in the United States. (811.42700(R)/8–1146.</note>
                                we are thus moving ahead on all technical details anticipating <pb facs="0706" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/> acceptance by Clay of
                                Munich project. Forrestal, Acheson and others in State Department
                                agree.</p>
                            <p>The following message to General Clay has been discussed with
                                Secretary Patterson at meeting with Acheson and Forrestal. Patterson
                                agreed to relay it, after stating that he felt Clay should be
                                supported. I am holding for 48 hours on chance you may want to
                                comment further.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“To Clay from Patterson—Reference your CC–1697, State Department
                                    has reviewed your reservations and appreciates your
                                    willingness-nonetheless to make available two Munich
                                    transmitters. State Department is thus developing plans, staff
                                    and equipment for Munich relays.</p>
                                <p>State Department representatives for this project will be
                                    dispatched Berlin as soon as possible. Technical operating
                                    personnel will be attached to Munich Consulate.</p>
                                <p>Re your discussion with Sarnoff,<note n="86" xml:id="d447fn86">Telegram 1911, August 11, from Berlin, reported on General
                                        Clay’s “… recent conversations with Sarnoff of <gloss target="#t_RCA1">RCA</gloss> who stated that direct
                                        broadcasting: from the US to the USSR is technically
                                        feasible, that equipment is available, and that it is merely
                                        a question of expenditure of funds. Sarnoff indicated that
                                        an expense of approximately two million dollars would be
                                        involved.” (811.42700(R)/8–1346.</note> telegram from
                                    Secretary Byrnes after talking with Sarnoff in Paris,<note n="87" xml:id="d447fn87">Reference is to telegram 3963; see
                                        footnote 85, <ref target="#pg_687">p. 687</ref>.</note>
                                    quotes Sarnoff memorandum urging Munich relays as absolute
                                    technical necessity for effective coverage.</p>
                                <p>Censorship questions would not appear to arise since all State
                                    Department programs will originate New York. No programs of any
                                    kind will be produced or created in Munich. Transmitters are for
                                    boosting signal strength of programs.</p>
                                <p>Department and advisory committee here have thoroughly reviewed
                                    format of broadcasts to eliminate any material which could
                                    logically lead to retaliatory action.</p>
                                <p>Your cooperation in fulfillment of this program is greatly
                                    appreciated by State Department. Ambassador Smith will notify
                                    Russians in Moscow of State Department’s intentions and any
                                    reaction from them will be reported to you.<note n="88" xml:id="d447fn88"><p>Telegram 4344, August 23, to Secretary
                                            Byrnes at Paris, reported that this cable had been sent
                                            to General Clay with the next to the last sentence
                                            revised; to read as follows: “Ambassador Smith will
                                            notify Russians in Moscow of State Department’s
                                            intention shortly before broadcasts are started and any
                                            reaction from them will be reported to you at that
                                            time.” (740.00119 Council/8–2346.</p>
                                        <p>In telegram 3276, August 22, from Moscow, repeated to
                                            Paris for Ambassador Smith, then at the Paris Peace
                                            Conference, the Chargé” (Durbrow) expressed the belief
                                            that possible Soviet objections should not be permitted
                                            to interfere with American plans. He stated that it was
                                            the Embassy’s feeling that the Soviet Union would not
                                            have valid grounds for objecting to relaying of programs
                                            originating in New York, particularly since there was no
                                            reason why the U.S.S.R. should not have similar relaying
                                            rights (811.42700(R)/8–2246).</p></note> Secretary
                                    Patterson supported your position but has yielded to State
                                    Department’s views in line with urgency of the need. Patterson
                                    to Clay.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>General Sarnoff not yet returned and I want to discuss with him his
                                conversation with you and accompanying memo. I agree with him that
                                it is desirable to develop better signals and programs within <pb facs="0707" n="689" xml:id="pg_689"/> Germany. I hope you can
                                find time to discuss this need with General Clay and advise me
                                further how State Department can cooperate with him in proposed
                                Sarnoff studies. I shall report further to you, when I’ve seen
                                Sarnoff. [Benton.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>