<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-03T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-03T08:00:00-05:00" n="488" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d488">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/11–346:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for
                                    Germany</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-03T14:00:00+01:00">November 3, 1946—2
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received November 3—10:57 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>2543. 1. Skrzypczynski, German head of the Soviet Zonal
                                Administration for Industry, said to Heath<note n="4" xml:id="d488fn4">Donald R. Heath, Counselor of Mission, Office
                                    of the United States Political Adviser for Germany
                                    (Murphy).</note> today that he understood that the recent
                                dismantling of the Zeiss and other key industrial plants and the
                                deportation of their technicians and skilled workers was only
                                decided upon when it became evident to the Russians that their plan
                                of dominating the zone—politically and economically—through the
                                    <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss> Party was a failure. He said
                                that according to his information some 7 or 8 thousand workers plus
                                dependents had so far been deported. While he did not believe that
                                the Soviets had definite plans for further deportations and plant
                                dismantlings at the present time, he thought it was very likely that
                                Moscow would continue on this line unless Allied action prevented
                                it.</p>
                            <p>2. He estimated the net output of finished industrial products in the
                                Soviet zone at 2½ billion marks per annum (at 1938 prices). The
                                Soviets were taking reparations out of this current production at
                                the rate of 130 million marks a month or some 60 percent of the
                                total. <pb facs="0763" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> As the Russians
                                were not interested in lumber, cement, glass, and other bulk
                                materials, this take represented an even higher percentage—70 or 75
                                percent—of the zone’s output of consumers goods.</p>
                            <p>3. Skrzypczynski stated the Russians had dismantled and largely moved
                                about 40 percent of the industrial equipment they found when they
                                took over the zone and had destroyed as war industry another 15
                                percent. He estimated that the real value of dismantled plants
                                amounted to from 6 to 8 million marks. The Russians evaluation,
                                however, was based on the annual balance sheets of the concerns
                                after deducting depreciation, etc., and gave a valuation of from ¼
                                to ⅓ of the sale value of a plant in normal times. The Russians were
                                paying for reparations out of current production by marks seized
                                when they first occupied eastern Germany.</p>
                            <p>4. To date the Russians had taken title to and were operating under
                                Russian managers some 220 key industrial concerns in their zone.
                                These 220 plants represented from 30 to 35 percent of the normal
                                industrial output of the Russian zone. Their value on a 1938 basis
                                was from 2½ to 3 billion marks. The Russian evaluation was from ¼ to
                                ⅓ this amount based on the plants balance sheets.</p>
                            <p>5. He assumed that the Russians would try strenuously to avoid any
                                discussion of their action in taking over these plants, at the next
                                meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers. Presumably they would
                                try to maintain and control these plants regardless of final action
                                taken regarding Germany. Thus this, in effect, would be yet another
                                means of obtaining reparations for Russia—especially if these
                                concerns could be excluded from all general arrangements as
                                representing Soviet “property”.</p>
                            <p>6. Koval,<note n="5" xml:id="d488fn5">Konstantin Ivanovich Koval,
                                    Deputy, in charge of economic affairs, to the Chief of the
                                    Soviet Military Administration in Germany.</note> the Russian
                                zonal economic director, described as a very competent engineer and
                                executive, told Skrzypczynski that German administrators had
                                recently been sending in analyses and plans which in effect were
                                criticism of the Russian procedures, and which followed too closely
                                the line of English and American press attacks. Koval said he
                                intended to hold conference of the leading German zonal economic
                                administrators to enjoin on them a wholehearted and disciplined
                                execution of Soviet plans for the zone. Skrzypczynski told him it
                                would be impossible in such a meeting to silence German discussion
                                and criticism of certain happenings. The criticism would be based on
                                a desire to achieve better administration which would be in the
                                interest of both the Germans and the Russians. Koval therefore
                                abandoned his plans for conference.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>