<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-21T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-21T09:00:00-05:00" n="508" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d508">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">862.6362/3–2146: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gallman</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-21T14:00:00+00:00">March 21, 1946—2
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 6:36 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3233. Interim reply now received from Bevin<note n="64" xml:id="d508fn64">Ernest Bevin, British Secretary of State for
                                    Foreign Affairs.</note> to Ambassador’s letter based on <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 11096, Dec 27<note n="65" xml:id="d508fn65">Not printed; this telegram was the same, <hi rend="italic">mutatis mutandis</hi>, as telegram 6047 to
                                    Paris, cited in footnote 55, <ref target="#pg_766">p.
                                    766</ref>.</note> with apologies for delay. He <pb facs="0788" n="770" xml:id="pg_770"/> states he has been informed French
                                have appointed civilian coal adviser<note n="66" xml:id="d508fn66">The French Government had formally accepted the proposal for
                                    appointment of zonal coal advisers on February 19, as reported
                                    to the Department in telegram 803, February 19, from Paris, not
                                    printed (862.6362/2–1946).</note> but understands Russians have
                                not been willing to appoint one. He states British Govt has been in
                                considerable doubt whether similar appointment for British zone
                                would be of real assistance inasmuch as until recently limiting
                                factor on coal exports to liberated areas had been transport rather
                                than production. He continues that measures taken by <gloss target="#t_ECITO1">ECITO</gloss><note n="67" xml:id="d508fn67">For documentation relating to U. S. participation in the
                                    European Central Inland Transport Organization, see <ref target="frus1945v02#pg_1389"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                                        pp. 1389</ref> ff.</note> appear to have been most
                                successful in removing transport difficulties, that British Govt is
                                now giving further consideration to our proposal and that he hopes
                                to give us further reply in near future. He concludes by expressing
                                apprehension that present food situation in Germany will provide new
                                limiting factor on production.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Gallman</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>