<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="53" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d53">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">845.00/9–346</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Acting
                                        Secretary of State</gloss> to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName></hi><note n="35" xml:id="d53fn35">A
                                    marginal notation reads: “Approved Sept. 3 ’46 Harry S
                                    Truman.”</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-08-30">August 30, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Raising of Status of Indian Agency General
                                in Washington, and of the American Mission in New Delhi</p>
                            <p>As a result of negotiations which have been going on between the
                                Viceroy of India and representative Indian leaders, a new Executive
                                Council (Cabinet) is to take office on September 2, 1946. The new
                                Cabinet will be composed of outstanding leaders of the principal
                                Indian political party, [<hi rend="italic">parties?</hi>] together
                                with representative leaders of certain minority groups. The British
                                plan likewise calls for the convening of a Constitutent Assembly in
                                the immediate future, which will <pb facs="0111" n="93" xml:id="pg_93"/> have authority to draft a new Indian
                                constitution providing for the complete severance of India from the
                                Empire and Commonwealth if the Indians so desire. Although the
                                second most important Indian political party has refused to
                                participate thus far in these developments,<note n="36" xml:id="d53fn36">Reference is to the Muslim League.</note> it is
                                believed that the new government will be representative of at least
                                80 percent of the Indian people.</p>
                            <p>It is anticipated that one of the first acts of the new government
                                will be to request the exchange of fully accredited diplomatic
                                representation between India and the United States.</p>
                            <p>While the Viceroy will continue legally to have the power of veto,
                                until the new constitution comes into effect, we feel that
                                representative Indian leaders capable of speaking in the name of the
                                great majority of the Indian people will now be in effective <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> control of the affairs of India in
                                view of the violent repercussions which would probably follow a
                                decision of the Viceroy to act contrary to the advice of his new
                                Cabinet on any important issue. We accordingly believe that if the
                                new government should express a desire for the exchange of fully
                                accredited representatives with the United States, we should without
                                hesitation agree to receive an Indian Ambassador and to send an
                                American Ambassador to India.</p>
                            <p>I should appreciate receiving your views on the subject in order that
                                we may act with a minimum of delay in case the new Indian Government
                                would like to have such an exchange effected.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>