<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chargé in Spain (Bonsal)Transmitted to the
                        Department in despatch 2202, May 24, from Madrid; received June 7,
                        1946.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d547</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">547</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-05-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-22T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="civil-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421" lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="547" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d547">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/5–2646</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chargé in Spain</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bonsal</hi>)<note n="62" xml:id="d547fn62">Transmitted to the
                        Department in despatch 2202, May 24, from Madrid; received June 7,
                        1946.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-22">May 22,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Foreign Minister, Alberto Martín Artajo</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>British Ambassador, Sir Victor Mallet</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>American Chargé, Philip W. Bonsal</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The Foreign Minister received us at 6:20 p.m., May 22, 1946.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Repatriation of Germans</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The British Ambassador and I expressed as forcibly as possible our disappointment
                    at the slow progress which has been made in the <pb facs="0831" n="813" xml:id="pg_813"/> repatriation from Spain of the Germans whom we have named
                    to the Spanish Government. While we recognize the good will which has been shown
                    in this matter by various officials of the Foreign Office, we were constrained
                    to take the position that their good will was by no means reflected by many of
                    the Spanish officials upon whose efforts we must count if effective results are
                    to be obtained. We referred specifically to the arrival of the vessel <hi rend="italic">Marine Perch</hi> at Bilbao on June 6 and expressed the view
                    that a failure to take advantage of the capacity of this vessel (over 900
                    persons) would produce a most unfortunate effect particularly taking into
                    account the fact that since the departure of the <hi rend="italic">Highland
                        Monarch</hi> in early March the Spanish Government in spite of its
                    expressions of good will has been able to produce only twelve candidates for
                    repatriation.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister said that he had on this same day had a conversation with
                    the Minister of the Interior on this subject and that he had urged the necessity
                    for making a good showing on the <hi rend="italic">Marine Perch</hi>. He said,
                    however, that the matter was one in which the Government did not have the
                    support of Spanish public opinion which was unable to see why these Germans had
                    to be removed, particularly those who had resided for many years in the country
                    or who had rendered special services during the Spanish Civil War. Among such
                    services he included the saving of lives of Franco’s supporters from the Reds.
                    He said that the Cardinal Archbishop of Toledo had mentioned the matter to
                    him.</p>
                <p>We furnished the Foreign Minister with figures showing what a small proportion of
                    the important officials and agents whom we named last November have been
                    repatriated or even located. We also pointed out to him that the German
                    Government had had over 2,000 Germans in its employ in Spain, counting officials
                    and agents. The Minister’s attitude throughout was one of endeavoring to make a
                    deal with us whereby we would agree to limit the number of persons in whom we
                    are interested in exchange for greater Spanish cooperation in regard to these
                    people.</p>
                <p>The Minister said that he intended to try to catch and hand over to us almost all
                    the Germans on our first two priority lists which he presumed to be the
                    principal officials and agents. There might be one or two exceptions among those
                    who had rendered special services during the Civil War and of course it might
                    not be possible to find some of those Germans who were in hiding but he would do
                    his best. He obviously wanted us to withdraw our claim for compulsory expulsion
                    of those on the lower list but we gave him no hope whatever that we would agree
                    to this.</p>
                <p>The Minister made the suggestion that it might be desirable for the <hi rend="italic">Marine Perch</hi> to stay several days, perhaps a week, in
                    Bilbao. He <pb facs="0832" n="814" xml:id="pg_814"/> said that he believed that
                    large numbers of Germans were finally making up their minds to leave Spain and
                    that if the opportunity for departure could be held open for them the number
                    going might be increased. The British Ambassador referred to the cost of holding
                    the vessel and to the fact that we had no authority over its movements.</p>
                <p>The British Ambassador then left with the Foreign Minister an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> regarding the case of Meyer Doehner, the German Naval
                    Attaché who failed to show up on the occasion of our last air lift to Germany.
                    The <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> deals with the Minister of Marine’s
                    interference in the matter and his indication to Meyer Doehner that he not
                    depart as he had given his word of honor to do. The Minister said he would look
                    into the matter. I raised the question of DeGrelle and Lagrou.<note n="63" xml:id="d547fn63">Léon DeGrelle and René Lagrou, two Belgians considered by
                        the Belgian Government as traitors, had entered Spain as members of the
                        German armed forces asking for asylum. The Belgian Government requested
                        extradition of the two men.</note> The Minister asked the British Ambassador
                    whether he had received any reply from London regarding the possibility of
                    trying these men by an international tribunal instead of turning them back to
                    the Belgians. The Ambassador replied in the negative but expressed doubt as to
                    whether such a solution would be feasible. The Minister stated that DeGrelle had
                    given some indication of a desire to depart voluntarily from Spain.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
