<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="652" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d652">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24556A/1–1746</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The American Ambassador in the Netherlands</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Netherlands
                                    Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">van Roijen</hi></persName>)<note n="3" xml:id="d652fn3">Copy transmitted to the Department in despatch
                                    568, January 17, 1946, from The Hague; received February
                                    1.</note></head>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: Acting under instructions from
                                my Government, and referring to a Note which I had the honor to
                                address to you on September 21, 1945<note n="4" xml:id="d652fn4">Not
                                    printed.</note> on the subject of use of air bases in Aruba and
                                in Curaçao and Surinam, I now have the honor to inform Your
                                Excellency that the Department of State has been informed by the
                                Joint Chiefs of Staff that the mission of the United States forces
                                in Aruba has now been completed and those forces are being
                                withdrawn; and that with regard to the presence of United States
                                forces in Surinam and Curaçao the situation is as follows:</p>
                            <p>United States forces are now located at Zandery field, in Surinam,
                                and at Hato field in Curaçao. The primary mission of these forces is
                                to provide communication, landing, navigation and servicing
                                facilities for United States military aircraft in connection with
                                operations of <pb facs="0975" n="957" xml:id="pg_957"/> the United
                                States military air route (U.S. Canal Zone–Natal–Dakar) to South
                                America, Europe and the Middle East. These services will continue to
                                be needed so long as the United States maintains substantial
                                occupation forces in Europe. The fields under reference are of
                                particular value during periods when the weather conditions along
                                the east and north coasts of South America are unfavorable.</p>
                            <p>It is considered to be a military necessity that United States
                                military aircraft shall continue to have available to them as long
                                as the United States maintains substantial occupation forces in
                                Europe the use of these fields and auxiliary facilities. However, it
                                is not felt to be essential that United States personnel, either
                                military or civilian, should continue to maintain or operate the
                                fields. It would be entirely agreeable to the United States
                                Government to withdraw its military personnel from these fields were
                                the Netherlands Government to give an undertaking that it will
                                maintain and operate the fields and the required air facilities and
                                make these available to military aircraft of the United States. It
                                would be possible to withdraw United States military personnel as
                                soon as Netherlands personnel would be prepared to assume
                                responsibilities of maintenance and operations in accordance with
                                standards to be jointly agreed upon. Should the Netherlands
                                Government so desire, the United States Government would be glad to
                                provide, as an aid to the Netherlands Government toward its
                                assumption of these responsibilities, technical instruction for
                                Netherlands maintenance personnel. Should the Netherlands Government
                                feel that it is not in position to maintain these facilities, the
                                United States Government would wish to continue maintenance and
                                operation of them by United States personnel during such period as
                                the United States may continue to maintain forces of occupation in
                                Europe.</p>
                            <p>I avail myself [etc.]</p>
                            <closer> [File copy not signed] <lb/>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">The Hague</hi></placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-16">January 16,
                                        1946</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>