<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Portugal ( (Baruch) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d661</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">661</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-05-05T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-05T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="air-safety"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reclDWPzWLFcH99Zg" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-05T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-05T09:00:00-05:00" n="661"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d661">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.34553B/5–546: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Baruch</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-05T15:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 5, 1946—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received May 6—3:25 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>395. For Hickerson. Salazar received Kuter and Culbertson yesterday afternoon.
                    O’Malley was also present.</p>
                <p>Salazar opened by reading a news flash of a story appearing in yesterday’s <hi
                        rend="italic">New York Times</hi>. He was obviously concerned over this
                    leak. This was no doubt same story Horsey<note n="13" xml:id="d661fn13"
                        >Outerbridge Horsey of the Division of Western European Affairs.</note>
                    telephoned about. O’Malley stated <gloss target="#t_AP1">AP</gloss> had
                    approached him. We stated that presence of Kuter and Culbertson in Lisbon was
                    known and newsmen would easily put two and two together. We recalled to Salazar
                    that Kuter had talked to Minister of War<note n="14" xml:id="d661fn14">Lt. Col.
                        Fernando dos Santos Costa.</note> about likelihood of leak and need for some
                    release in order avoid speculation by press as well as avoid Russian press
                    distorting story. Salazar agreed all parties might say something to the effect
                    that present discussions are for the purpose of terminating the wartime
                    arrangement for the use of Santa Maria and arranging for transition of airfield
                    to civilian use. Salazar was not <pb facs="0986" n="968" xml:id="pg_968"/>
                    willing to add any reference to use in connection with our occupation in Germany
                    since we had not yet discussed this point. Salazar then stated he wanted to
                    outline his understanding of our proposal and to give his comments. He read from
                    a paper,<note n="15" xml:id="d661fn15">Apparently this paper was dated May
                        2.</note> a copy of which he gave us. Such side comment as he made was only
                    by way of amplification of this paper. Complete substance in translation,
                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Introduction</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <item>“1. For the further elucidation of the problems presented it
                                appears that we must deduce from the previous explanations given by
                                Mr. Culbertson and General Kuter that: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>The United States and British Governments propose that we
                                        should examine the possibility of the cooperation of the
                                        Portuguese Government, by means of facilities in the Azores
                                        similar to those granted during the recent conflict, in the
                                        hypothesis of a war with Russia.</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>These two Governments, having in mind present necessities
                                        arising from the occupation of Germany and Japan, request
                                        the continuation of the facilities previously
                                        granted.</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>For the purposes of international civil aviation and for
                                        the purposes of subparagraph A [<hi rend="italic">B</hi>?]
                                        above, they propose to assist the Portuguese Government to
                                        maintain the two existing airports in a state of perfect
                                        preparation and equipment. For the better fulfillment of
                                        this objective the United States Government suggests a
                                        special arrangement relating to Santa Maria.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>2. It is necessary to examine the essence of these proposals in
                                detail.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center">I</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The question of greatest political importance is the first, which
                                should therefore be examined first.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>We do not reject <hi rend="italic">in limine</hi> the possibility
                                of Portuguese cooperation in the security of the Atlantic. In more
                                than one public statement the Head of the Government has left the
                                way open for such cooperation. Not only did he affirm on one
                                occasion that the conflict of 1939–1945 was perhaps the last war in
                                which Portugual might be able to remain neutral, but he also said
                                that the shift of the world’s political center westward confronted
                                the Atlantic countries or some of them with the necessity of
                                coordinating their policies. This second affirmation may not of
                                itself require more than the strengthening of existing bonds and an
                                understanding on the problems connected with the security of the
                                Atlantic. The first proposition quoted, however, implies only two
                                possible hypotheses—the obligations assumed towards an international
                                organization, such as <gloss target="#t_UNO1">UNO</gloss>, or a war
                                in which Portugal would feel that she had to make her contribution
                                to the defense of the west, i.e., a war with Russia.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>As we are outside <gloss target="#t_UNO1">UNO</gloss>, at least at
                                the present moment, the question to be faced can only be the
                                latter.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>We must now consider the juridical and political aspects of a
                                possible cooperation.</item>
                            <pb facs="0987" n="969" xml:id="pg_969"/>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The question would be simplified, if within the framework of
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNO1">UNO</gloss>, because of the obligations
                                which the charter imposes on the member states. For the present,
                                however, this road is closed.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>When we examine the same problem outside <gloss target="#t_UNO1"
                                    >UNO</gloss>, we have the following: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>Vis-à-vis ourselves, England has the position of an ally.
                                        Although this alliance is purely defensive, and the
                                        interpretation has been established that each party reserves
                                        the right to judge the <hi rend="italic">casus foederis</hi>
                                        for itself, it is perfectly understandable that we should
                                        confer together in anticipation of a certain hypothesis and
                                        undertake mutual obligations for that eventuality. These
                                        obligations are necessary because Portugal, should she be
                                        outside <gloss target="#t_UNO1">UNO</gloss> or should this
                                        organization not function, is in the event of her
                                        cooperation immediately exposed to risks, whether in
                                        metropolitan Portugal or in her colonial empire. These risks
                                        may be defined as follows: Portugal in the Iberian
                                        Peninsula; Portugal in Africa; Portugal in the Far
                                        East.</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>This is not the position vis-à-vis the United States, and
                                        one may therefore enquire how this aspect of the problem may
                                        be faced. There is no doubt that the intervention of the US
                                        constitutes an element of security for peace loving nations
                                        in general; but this conclusion does not signify any
                                        undertaking in respect of the integrity and independence of
                                        any one nation in particular or of its dominions, nor does
                                        it involve any obligation as to the help to be given to such
                                        a nation to lessen the possibility of loss and damage. One
                                        recalls the case of Santa Maria and the agreement concerning
                                        our participation in the war in the Far East.<note n="16"
                                            xml:id="d661fn16">For text of agreement between the
                                            United States and Portugal establishing form of indirect
                                            participation of Portugal in operations in the Pacific,
                                            signed at Lisbon November 28, 1944, see Department of
                                            State, Treaties and Other International Acts Series, No.
                                            2338; <hi rend="italic">United States Treaties and Other
                                                International Agreements</hi>, vol. 2 (pt. 2), p.
                                            2124. For documentation relating to the Agreement, see
                                                <ref target="frus1944v04#pg_1">
                                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 1</ref>
                                            ff.</note> We also refer to the American undertakings
                                        regarding the Portuguese colonial empire. We recall the
                                        difficulties to the conversations between the General
                                        Staffs.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>The development of these ideas raises the following question: Do
                                you envisage, or regard as possible, any basis for a political
                                agreement on which it might be reasonable and legitimate to build
                                the hypothesis of cooperation in a certain way and for a certain
                                period, against a certain risk or for a definite objective? (The
                                question is asked because we do not have sufficient knowledge of the
                                scope of the American Govt’s powers in this respect.)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center">II</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>In whatever manner the first question is resolved, there remains
                                the second, which may be considered practically independent of the
                                first: There is no doubt that this question remains even if no
                                agreement is reached on the collaboration outlined above: At least
                                certain requirements of the forces of occupation remain. This second
                                problem has not the same weight or political importance as the first
                                but presents its own difficulties.</item>
                            <pb facs="0988" n="970" xml:id="pg_970"/>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In the first place we must state that we have every understanding
                                of what are said to be the needs of the forces of occupation in
                                Germany and in the Far East in the near future. They involve aerial
                                communications, though these are at present at a reduced level,
                                according to the average rate of those passing through Santa
                                Maria.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>But one must make the following points. <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>When the Santa Maria agreement was concluded, the Allies
                                        had already formed plans for the occupation of the enemy
                                        countries;</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>The period of the Santa Maria agreement and its
                                        prolongation were exactly as requested by the American
                                        General Staff, which leads one to suppose that they were
                                        relying on a different solution for their military needs
                                        after the conclusion of the period in question;</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>The Santa Maria agreement was connected with the war in
                                        the Far East and not with the war in Europe, which is a
                                        point that has since been somewhat forgotten.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The American General Staff therefore had in mind in 1944 that
                                their needs which exist today and were already foreseen at that time
                                would be solved by a different formula than that which was adopted
                                during the period of validity of the agreement. We have to see how
                                it will be possible to facilitate or guarantee the passage of
                                military aircraft to Europe and the Far East and reconcile the
                                continuation of this service with the expiration of the Santa Maria
                                agreement.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>As regards English aircraft, it appears that the question does not
                                arise, because: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>England does not need to pass through the Azores as a
                                        necessity of the occupation of the enemy countries;</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>The Lagens Agreement must already be considered to have
                                        lapsed. The Government, having been informed in September of
                                        the British Government’s intention of leaving Lagens, is
                                        only waiting for the clarification of certain details
                                        concerning the handing over of installations.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center">III</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>I now turn to the third question.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>When this problem is examined solely on the plane of civil
                                aviation, and in spite of the fact that the American Govt pays
                                attention to the development of international aviation, we do not
                                see how we can admit that Santa Maria merits its special concern. We
                                are therefore led to believe that the real basis and objective of
                                the proposals regarding Santa Maria, as of the reference which the
                                British “memorandum of oral conversation” makes to Lagens, is the
                                necessity of having two airfields in a state of preparation for the
                                end envisaged in the first question. In one word: they must be in
                                such a condition that from one moment to another they can change
                                from commercial to military use.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>If this is the case, and in the event of agreement being reached
                                on collaboration, we must seek a method of achieving that result
                                which will take into consideration national susceptibilities, the
                                functioning of whichever airport is destined for civil traffic and
                                the continued use thereof.</item>
                            <pb facs="0989" n="971" xml:id="pg_971"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>We start from the following points: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>The Government is anxious to open an airfield in Azores to
                                        commercial aviation. They have not wished to do so as yet in
                                        order not to allow civil flying and military occupation at
                                        the same airfield, and because Lagens as well as Santa Maria
                                        was used for military purposes. The Governments are awaiting
                                        the advice of their experts to make their choice between
                                        them. The other will be used as an emergency landing
                                        ground.</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>The Government does not see [<hi rend="italic">seek?</hi>]
                                        to avoid all or a part of the expenses which it will incur
                                        for the maintenance of the aerodromes, even above the level
                                        required for commercial use, should some agreement be
                                        reached containing the undertaking referred to in the first
                                        question.</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>The principles of Portuguese policy and public
                                        administration do not allow the leasing or exploitation of
                                        civil airports by private entities, whether Portuguese or
                                        foreign. The exploitation of airports is made ‘em regie’
                                        (autonomous administration by government functionaries). As
                                        far as the works or installations are concerned, this is not
                                        always the case; these may be conceded to private entities,
                                        and even to foreign private entities.</item>
                                    <label>D.</label>
                                    <item>The Government does not dispose of sufficiently numerous
                                        and experienced experts to take over at once and alone the
                                        operation of an airport like Santa Maria or Lagens. For this
                                        reason the Government contemplates, and wishes to enter
                                        into, special combinations with the American and British
                                        Governments for technical consultation, the training of
                                        Portuguese personnel, the supply of experts, the supply of
                                        the necessary apparatus and the knowledge of its use, under
                                        conditions to be determined. In the Santa Maria agreement
                                        provision is made for the sale of other than fixed
                                        apparatus, with the exception of secret appliances.</item>
                                    <label>E.</label>
                                    <item>The existence of or necessity for such secret appliances
                                        (should it continue) raises problems which will have to be
                                        considered separately.</item>
                                    <label>F.</label>
                                    <item>It is understood that it will be necessary to define, in
                                        the case of an agreement for military use, the improvements
                                        or alternations [<hi rend="italic">alterations?</hi>] which
                                        the airfields will require for this purpose at any given
                                        moment”.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>After Salazar read the three points covering his understanding of our proposal
                    O’Malley called attention to fact of no reference to Lagens. He then stated very
                    clearly that his Government wants the same arrangement for Lagens that we seek
                    for Santa Maria and furthermore that the British Government fully supports the
                    American proposal.</p>
                <p>We stated at the conclusion of Salazar’s presentation that we would not undertake
                    any reply at this time; that we would study his statement, obtain instructions
                    from our Government and as soon as possible seek another interview with him.
                    Salazar was quite friendly, said to come to him at any time if we wanted further
                    clarification and that he was ready to continue discussions at any time. Please
                    instruct.</p>
                <pb facs="0990" n="972" xml:id="pg_972"/>
                <p>Sent to Dept as 395, repeated to Paris 61 for Matthews<note n="17"
                        xml:id="d661fn17">H. Freeman Matthews, Director of the Office of European
                        Affairs; member of the United States Delegation at the meeting of the
                        Council of Foreign Ministers at Paris.</note> from Culbertson.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Baruch</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
