<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Portugal ( (Baruch) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d687</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">687</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-07-19T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-07-19T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-07-19T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-07-19T07:00:00-05:00" n="687"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d687">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.34553B/7–1946: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Baruch</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-07-19T13:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 19, 1946—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 6:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>633. For Hickerson. Mathias telephoned yesterday to say Salazar had instructed
                    him to start discussions. We naturally assumed he <pb facs="1025" n="1007"
                        xml:id="pg_1007"/> would talk on the political long term proposal in view of
                    what Salazar had told Russell and me last Tuesday.<note n="57" xml:id="d687fn57"
                        >July 16.</note> On the contrary, however, Mathias announced that the long
                    term discussions must await the return of the Minister of War; that he, Mathias,
                    would discuss interpretation of the May 31 [<hi rend="italic">30</hi>]
                    agreement. Immediately said that was not what Salazar had said. He undertook to
                    clarify the question with Salazar and to find out at our insistent request
                    whether long term discussions would have to await the return of the Minister of
                    War scheduled for August 8.</p>
                <p>The conversation alternated back and forth between the long term and May 31
                    agreements, three points developed: (1) Mathias will be strictest possible in
                    interpretation of May 31 Agreement and considers it supersedes 1944 Agreement on
                    questions of materials and supplies; (2) Portuguese are apparently thinking of
                    long term agreement on basis of commitment to make fields available in event of
                    and at time of war; it was made clear to Mathias that we would not consider
                    giving political guarantees in exchange for any such deal; (3) Mathias stated
                    specifically that Portugal would not permit “occupation” by foreign troops in
                    time of peace. I immediately caught him up on this statement and demanded to
                    know whether that was his Govt’s considered position in relation to our proposal
                    as presented by Mr. Russell making clear at the same time we were not proposing
                    “occupation” but joint use and operation. Mathias immediately backed away by
                    trying to explain that he was merely expressing his personal views and that he
                    was not authorized to discuss long term arrangement.</p>
                <p>Kuter and Culbertson feel that in order to head off misunderstanding and
                    quibbling Culbertson should now send Mathias a detailed informal statement of
                    our requirements. The statement will outline the maximum requirements and is in
                    preparation now.</p>
                <p>In telephone conversation this afternoon Mathias explained that Minister of War
                    would while in Azores discuss technical problems arising from May 31 Agreement,
                    Mathias would handle interpretation of Agreement, Minister of War would have to
                    be consulted re long term agreement, not that he would negotiate it; that other
                    Cabinet members would have to be consulted. Looks like negotiations may
                    drag.</p>
                <p>Mathias also said Portuguese had given story to British. Russell said he would
                    let me know what to give British. Are we authorized to keep British fully
                    informed currently?</p>
                <p>Sent Dept 633; repeated Paris as 98 for <gloss target="#t_Delsec1"
                    >Delsec</gloss>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Baruch</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
