<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Spain ( (Bonsai) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d720</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">720</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-03-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="720"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d720">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">852.00/3–1846: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bonsai</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-18">March 18,
                            1946—[?] p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received March 19—8:29 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>551. Foreign Minister<note n="48" xml:id="d720fn48">Alberto Marten Artajo.</note>
                    today handed me copy of pamphlet entitled “Reply to the Publication Made by the
                    Department of State of the United States of America of Documents Relative to
                    Spain”. One copy being sent by air pouch tomorrow and summary by separate
                    telegram.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister stated he was not handing me this pamphlet officially since
                    State Department publication had been in nature of press release but that as
                    matter of courtesy he wished me to have copy before it was made available to
                    press later today.</p>
                <p>He emphasized that in making this publication Spanish Government did not intend
                    to take aggressive or offensive action “which would provoke differences between
                    western nations which must defend our <pb facs="1073" n="1055" xml:id="pg_1055"
                    /> Christian civilization” but that it felt it important to place matters in
                    their true light.</p>
                <p>After ascertaining from Minister that pamphlet was to be published inside Spain,
                    I pointed out to him that Department’s release did not receive such publicity.
                    He replied that it had not yet been decided whether our release would be
                    published here but that he did not consider matter very important since both
                    content and intent of our publication were well known in Spain. He added that
                    although he appreciated freedom and independence of our press, fact is that
                    official statements of Spanish Government receive very slight attention
                    therein.</p>
                <p>I told Minister that I would look forward to later opportunity after I had read
                    pamphlet of discussing matter further with him. Incidentally, this Embassy has
                    not yet received copies of Department’s recent release of 15 documents.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bonsal</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
