<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Argentina ( (Weddell))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d202</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">202</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-07-26T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-07-26T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-07-26T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-07-26T20:00:00-05:00" n="202"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d202">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/3960b: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-07-26T21:00:00-04:00"
                            >July 26, 1934—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>70. The Department was given last night by the Bolivian Minister a copy of the
                    reply addressed by the Government of Bolivia to the Argentine Government.<note
                        n="12" xml:id="d202fn12">See <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Please obtain an interview with Dr. Saavedra Lamas at the earliest opportunity
                    and advise him that this Government would appreciate having his views concerning
                    this reply. You should state that we are addressing a similar inquiry to the
                    Government of Brazil.</p>
                <p>In your conversation you may say that while, of course, the reply is not as
                    satisfactory as could have been hoped for, this Government nevertheless believes
                    that a favorable opportunity is now presented for pressing forward with the
                    conciliation formula.</p>
                <p>The Minister of Bolivia in Washington has given it as his personal opinion that
                    the reply should be construed as an acceptance in principle of the Argentine
                    proposal and this Government believes that it would be helpful to consider it as
                    such. It is hoped that Dr. Saavedra Lamas will see no objection to agreeing to
                    the request made by Bolivia that Chile, Peru, Colombia, Uruguay, Mexico, and
                    Cuba be invited by Argentina, Brazil and the United States to join with these
                    three governments in presenting and in supporting the conciliation formula <pb
                        facs="0228" n="158" xml:id="pg_158"/> of Dr. Saavedra Lamas. It would seem
                    that this step would not only be in accord with the opinion already expressed to
                    us by the Argentine and Brazilian Governments, but that it would at once rally
                    to the support of the conciliation formula the continental public opinion
                    desired by Dr. Saavedra Lamas as indicated in his recent messages to this
                    Government. Such general support of the conciliation formula would have a very
                    great moral weight. Compliance with this request of the Bolivian Government
                    would also unquestionably have a calming effect upon public opinion in
                    Bolivia.</p>
                <p>If Dr. Saavedra Lamas coincides with this belief as above expressed, it is hoped
                    that he will be willing to make the utmost endeavors to obtain the consent of
                    Paraguay, and in such event, the American Minister in Asunción will be
                    instructed to support most earnestly such representations.</p>
                <p>With regard to the additional request of Bolivia that the Argentine Goverment
                    ascertain whether the Government of Paraguay would be willing to agree upon more
                    concrete bases of conciliation, specifying as one of them that the right of
                    Bolivia to a zone along the River Paraguay from Bahía Negra south be recognized,
                    in the opinion of this Government it would seem to be very clear that these
                    points are precisely those which should be taken up for the most ample and
                    careful consideration in the conciliation conversations and it is suggested that
                    if the nations above mentioned accept the invitation to participate in
                    presenting the conciliation formula to Bolivia, they might then appropriately be
                    requested to join in urging upon Bolivia the desirability of instructing the
                    Bolivian plenipotentiaries in the conciliation proceedings to present these
                    points as representing the Bolivian point of view. All of the Governments
                    involved might further appropriately state that the Bolivian Government’s
                    requests will, of course, be given the most friendly consideration during the
                    conciliation proceedings.</p>
                <p>In conclusion please state to Dr. Saavedra Lamas that the views above expressed
                    are transmitted to him confidentially and that no official intimation will be
                    given to the Government of Bolivia of the attitude of the Government of the
                    United States with regard to the Bolivian reply until after we have had the
                    fullest opportunity for consultation with Argentina and Brazil.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
