<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-08-29T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-08-29T14:00:00-05:00" n="239" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/4059a: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-08-29T15:00:00-04:00">August 29, 1934—3
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>101. In the course of a conversation at the Department yesterday, the
                                Bolivian Minister stated that his Government was as yet hesitant as
                                to acceptance of the conciliation formula without reservations
                                because of its belief that Article 7 was so vaguely worded as not to
                                impose the obligation on the part of Paraguay to submit the dispute
                                to the arbitration of the Permanent Court in the event that
                                conciliation endeavors prove unsuccessful, and furthermore, because
                                the said article made no provision for determining the scope of
                                arbitration. The Minister was asked whether in his opinion, were
                                Paraguay formally to ratify the interpretation given Article 7 by
                                Dr. Saavedra Lamas,<note n="24" xml:id="d239fn24">See telegram No.
                                    137, August 23, 6 p.m., from the Ambassador in Argentina, <ref target="#pg_180">p. 180</ref>.</note> the assurance so
                                provided would be sufficient to allay the fears of his Government.
                                Dr. Finot expressed the belief that ratification of this
                                interpretation by Paraguay would be satisfactory to Bolivia and he
                                was requested specifically to confirm his personal understanding of
                                his Government’s view which he promised immediately to do by
                                cable.</p>
                            <p>In discussing the question of conciliation, the Minister asked
                                whether Argentina refused to sound out the viewpoint of Paraguay
                                with regard to the <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> specified by
                                Bolivia. The Minister was informed that in the opinion of the
                                Department Paraguay would feel herself unwilling to make any formal
                                commitment on this point prior to the conciliation conversations,
                                but that this Government saw no reason why the matter might not be
                                brought confidentially to the attention of Paraguay, and the
                                Bolivian Government thereafter be confidentially advised whether
                                this point would prove an insuperable objection in the conciliation
                                negotiations. For your strictly confidential information, the
                                Department’s statement on this latter point was made in view of the
                                conversation between the American Minister at Asunción and President
                                Ayala held on August 17 of which you have been advised by the
                                former.</p>
                            <p>Please discuss the substance of the above with Dr. Saavedra Lamas at
                                the earliest opportunity and advise him that it is the impression of
                                this Government that Bolivia will accept the conciliation formula
                                without reservation, provided Article 7 of the formula is
                                interpreted by Paraguay in the manner set forth by Dr. Saavedra
                                Lamas, and provided Bolivia is given confidentially to understand
                                that the sounding out by Argentina of Paraguay on the question of
                                the <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> has not been productive of
                                completely unsatisfactory results.</p>
                            <pb facs="0258" n="188" xml:id="pg_188"/>
                            <p>The decision of the Bolivian Government will be reached only after
                                President Salamanca returns to La Paz and the intended reply of
                                Bolivia will be first made known to Brazil and to the United States
                                before formal transmission to the Argentine Foreign Office.
                                Favorable and early action on the two points above mentioned may, it
                                is hoped, bring forth an equally favorable decision on the part of
                                Bolivia.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Phillips</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>