<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-09-04T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-09-04T16:00:00-05:00" n="243" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d243">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/4073: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Weddell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                            Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-09-04T17:00:00-04:00">September 4, 1934—5
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 7:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>151. I met the Brazilian Ambassador and the Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs in the latter’s office this morning. The Bolivian Minister
                                who was also present said that he hoped for a reply today from his
                                Government <pb facs="0260" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/> to an urgent
                                message he had sent last night asking for Bolivia’s decision on the
                                peace formula. He urged the necessity for securing Paraguay’s formal
                                acceptance of the interpretation of the formula drafted by the
                                Minister of Foreign Affairs. The latter referred to the solemn
                                statements made by the Paraguayan Minister (see my 137, August 23, 6
                                p.m.) and expressed disinclination to take up the matter again. The
                                Bolivian Minister said that he felt it was highly desirable to
                                clarify doubtful points before proceeding further, emphasizing the
                                desire of his Government for arbitration but stressing the
                                importance of making paragraph 7 entirely clear, while the Minister
                                urged that his Government accept the formula in principle and then
                                ask for the clarification of doubtful points.</p>
                            <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs said that he had just received a
                                visit from the Spanish Ambassador who asked on behalf of his
                                Government for a copy of the peace formula and for full information
                                concerning the negotiations and that he had informed him that the
                                League of Nations was being fully posted to which Spain as a member
                                of the League might apply.</p>
                            <p>The Minister for Foreign Affairs, the Brazilian Ambassador, and I are
                                to meet the Bolivian Minister again tomorrow or as soon as he
                                receives a reply from his Government.</p>
                            <p>My Brazilian colleague thinks that Bolivia is pursuing dilatory
                                tactics and I am inclined to share this view.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Rio de Janeiro.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Weddell</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>