<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-09-21T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-09-21T17:00:00-05:00" n="270" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d270">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">724.3415/4159: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Gibson</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-09-21T18:00:00-04:00">September 21, 1934—6
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>133. The Department has today received by cable from the American
                                Minister in Asunción the following written statement communicated by
                                President Ayala to the American Minister:</p>
                            <p>[Here follows quoted portion of telegram No. 43, September 20, 2
                                p.m., from the Minister in Paraguay, printed <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi>]</p>
                            <p>On September 19, the Department received the following statement of
                                the Minister for Foreign Affairs of Bolivia communicated to the
                                American Minister in La Paz on that date.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“He expressed regret that the United States and Brazil will not
                                    form part of a committee appointed by the League; and stated
                                    that when the pause is ended he hopes the United States and
                                    Brazil will continue the negotiations.”<note n="46" xml:id="d270fn46">For text of complete message, see telegram
                                        No. 63, September 19, 3 p.m., from the Minister in Bolivia,
                                            <ref target="#pg_216">p. 216</ref>.</note></p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>Please advise the Minister for Foreign Affairs fully of the above and
                                state, at the same time, that this information has not been
                                communicated as yet to the Government of Argentina. You should state
                                that this Government would welcome the opinion of the Brazilian
                                Government as to the course which should now be pursued in the Chaco
                                negotiations in view of these two statements by the belligerent
                                nations.</p>
                            <p>In the opinion of the Government of the United States, if the
                                negotiations in which Brazil and the United States are participating
                                are <pb facs="0289" n="219" xml:id="pg_219"/> to be carried on
                                successfully, it would seem advisable that a joint decision be
                                reached by the two Governments as to the course to be pursued
                                immediately after a determination is reached at Geneva as to the
                                exact nature of the League’s activities. The suggestion made by the
                                President of Paraguay that conversations should be commenced between
                                representatives of Bolivia and Paraguay with the participation of
                                the representatives of the mediating powers appears to this
                                Government to offer concrete advantages. It is feared that it might
                                prove a difficult, if not an interminable task to persuade Paraguay
                                to agree to some portion of the modifications of the conciliation
                                formula suggested by Bolivia if such an attempt is made prior to an
                                actual conference. On the other hand, it would be exceedingly
                                difficult for Bolivia now to retreat from the position which she has
                                taken in that regard. There would, however, appear a good ground for
                                hope that in the course of the proposed conference both Bolivia and
                                Paraguay might be persuaded by the mediating powers to agree upon
                                some revised form of the original conciliation formula and likewise
                                to agree upon some arbitral agreement. For obvious reasons, it would
                                further seem desirable to insist that the meeting place of the
                                conference continue to be Buenos Aires, but it would likewise seem
                                advantageous, should such a conference take place, to insist that
                                all of the American Republics composing the original group of nine
                                be represented from the outset in the mediation proceedings.</p>
                            <p>Should the views of the Brazilian Government coincide with the
                                opinions expressed, you may suggest to the Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs that as soon as an agreement has been reached between Brazil
                                and the United States, the proposal be laid by the American and
                                Brazilian Ambassadors at Buenos Aires before Dr. Saavedra Lamas.</p>
                            <p>The time element seems now to be of importance and state to the
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs that this Government would therefore
                                deeply appreciate receiving the views of his Government at the
                                earliest opportunity.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>