<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Costa Rica ( (Sack) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1934v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d585</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">585</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recTUqfVf9DyIITuJ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001281"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconnaissance</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recZfUQWqS4grj8JT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022006054"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">National debt</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="585"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d585">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">810.154/663</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Costa Rica</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sack</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 498</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">San José</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-11-15">November 15,
                            1934</date>.<lb/>[Received November 22.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In further reference to the Department’s
                    Instruction No. 96 of October 17, 1934,<note n="23" xml:id="d585fn23">See
                        footnote 11, <ref target="#pg_476">p. 476</ref>.</note> and my reply thereto
                    of October 26, 1934 (Despatch No. 477<note n="24" xml:id="d585fn24">Not
                        printed.</note>), on the subject of aid by the Government of the <pb
                        facs="0553" n="483" xml:id="pg_483"/> United States to the Government of
                    Costa Rica in the construction of the proposed Inter-American Highway, I have
                    the honor to attach herewith copy and translation of the note of the Foreign
                    Minister in reply to my note No. 134 of October 22, 1934, wherein I transmitted
                    to this Government the instructions of the Department of State with reference to
                    contemplated assistance to countries which are cooperating in the construction
                    of the proposed highway.</p>
                <p>The Department will observe that Mr. Gurdián acknowledges “the very great
                    importance” of the highway and anticipates the benefits which will accrue from
                    its construction. At the same time the Foreign Minister—and his viewpoint is
                    transmitted after conversations, to my knowledge, with President Ricardo Jimenez
                    and other officials of the Government—very frankly points out the financial
                    difficulties immediately confronting actual construction. On this subject Mr.
                    Gurdián says: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“…<note n="25" xml:id="d585fn25">Omission indicated in the
                                original.</note> Costa Rica’s difficult situation has obliged my
                            government to effect inevitable economies in its expenditures in order
                            to avoid budgetary deficits, and to suspend, through a prior arrangement
                            with its American and European creditors, the service on its foreign
                            debt. Under these conditions, the country finds it impossible to assume
                            new obligations, which according to the estimates of the cost of the
                            Inter-American Highway in the country, would mean an increase of one
                            hundred per cent in the external debt of Costa Rica.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>This debt is now approximately twenty-four million dollars upon which no interest
                    is being paid, and upon which the resumption of interest payments and
                    amortization of principle is not even being discussed.</p>
                <p>In an informal conversation with Señor Gurdián on October 22, the day I
                    personally presented the note embodying the Instruction No. 96 of the
                    Department, the Foreign Minister emphasized the financial difficulties
                    confronting construction and he asserted at that time that while the Government
                    is considering all possible solutions of the problem no particular plan of
                    financing up to now has been regarded as feasible. In his conversation Mr.
                    Gurdián said that the Government has considered the revenues to be derived from
                    increased gasoline taxes; from the granting of a concession to an outside
                    corporation for the construction of the road; from proposed bond issues; from
                    toll charges, et cetera, but no plan up to now has been considered feasible.</p>
                <p>In this connection may I direct the Department’s attention to the estimated costs
                    for the proposed highway in Volume 2 of the Reconnaissance Surveys made under
                    the direction of the Bureau of Public Roads of the United States Department of
                    Agriculture.</p>
                <pb facs="0554" n="484" xml:id="pg_484"/>
                <p>These estimates contemplate the construction of 312.7 miles (503.2 kilometers) of
                    road in Costa Rica.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>Table 19, planning merely the grading and surfacing of the road with local
                        materials and the construction of the necessary bridges, estimates the cost
                        at $11,145,206.25.</item>
                    <item>Table 20, contemplating the use of an oil surface, estimates the cost at
                        $11,516,693.85.</item>
                    <item>Table 21, contemplating the use of concrete and the construction of a
                        thoroughly modern highway in every respect, estimates the cost at
                        $25,907,156.</item>
                </list>
                <p>This is a sum, as I recall, greater than the estimated cost of construction in
                    any of the other Central American countries. May I point out at this point that
                    all of the new highway construction in Costa Rica made with current revenue
                    funds is of concrete and that this Government, whether rightfully or wrongfully,
                    is of the opinion that nothing but concrete will survive the terrific downpours
                    which are almost daily occurrences during the eight and a half months of the
                    annual rainy season. It is also true that the United States Bureau of Public
                    Roads contemplates a 20-foot highway as the minimum width for safety and
                    anticipated traffic, whereas most of the present Costa Rican highway
                    construction is confined to the dangerously narrow width of 12 to 16 feet which
                    makes it difficult for speeding cars to pass in safety.</p>
                <p>The Department will agree, therefore, that the estimated cost of $25,907,156, for
                    a properly constructed highway in Costa Rica presents a real problem to this
                    country and one which the Government of a necessity must consider regardless of
                    its desire for the highway. As a matter of fact, construction of a concrete
                    highway through the mountainous terrain of Costa Rica with all modern safety
                    devices and with increased utilities on curves, would unquestionably double
                    Costa Rica’s national debt.</p>
                <p>On the other hand the report of the engineers properly emphasized the great
                    increase of Costa Rican wealth which would result from the construction of the
                    highway and I find myself in complete accord with conclusions which hold that
                    the highway will more than pay for itself through the additional prosperity and
                    the increase in agricultural and economic resources which should result from the
                    opening up of hundreds of miles of territory north of San José toward the
                    Nicaraguan border and south of the capital in the direction of Panamá.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately, this view is not held by a sufficient number of Government
                    officials and leading citizens to stimulate a real public enthusiasm in Costa
                    Rica for the highway. In addition there exists the unquestioned suspicion—and
                    this feeling prevails in official as well as unofficial circles—that the United
                    States Government is keenly interested in <pb facs="0555" n="485"
                        xml:id="pg_485"/> the proposed highway because of its desire to further
                    increase the defenses of the Panama Canal. An important section of Costa Rican
                    public opinion anticipates that economic and political developments will some
                    day force a war between the United States and Japan and that the United States
                    is pushing the highway in order to have an overland means of transportation for
                    our troops. Even such an enlightened Costa Rican as President Ricardo Jimenez
                    has had this suspicion in the back of his mind.</p>
                <p>The note of the Foreign Minister calls attention to the fact that the survey as
                    recommended by the United States engineers routes the highway between the towns
                    of Naranjo and Las Cañas (Plates Nos. 23, 24 and 25 of Volume 2 of the
                    Reconnaissance Survey) too closely parallel to the line of the Government-owned
                    Pacific Railroad, and would thereby create a source of competition for the
                    railroad. The Foreign Minister suggests substitution of a different route, if
                    technically possible, to eliminate this proximity to the railroad. He does not,
                    however, say that Costa Rican engineers will be directed to make a new
                    instrument survey to discover a substitute route.</p>
                <p>May I direct the Department’s attention also to this paragraph of Mr. Gurdián’s
                    note: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Having set forth the economic conditions of the country in relation to
                            the great undertaking referred to in your note, my government expresses
                            its thanks for the valuable cooperation offered by the Government of the
                            United States, and accepts it if Costa Rica is found to meet the
                            situation which the American Congress had in view in passing the
                            appropriation laws cited in the note under reply.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>By way of further exposition of the Costa Rican viewpoint may I call attention to
                    a recent letter by the editor of <hi rend="italic">El Diario de Costa Rica</hi>
                    to the Foreign News Editor of the Associated Press, a copy of which is enclosed
                        herewith.<note n="26" xml:id="d585fn26">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In accordance with the statement in the Department’s Instruction No. 96 to the
                    effect that it will be glad to receive any recommendations I may care to submit,
                    which invitation I assume is inclusive of the entire subject, may I respectfully
                    offer the following thoughts;</p>
                <p>First; I do not believe it will be advisable for the United States Government at
                    this time either directly or indirectly to appear to be hurrying Costa Rica into
                    a decision on the project which will involve a great outlay of cash, or a
                    further increase in the public debt.</p>
                <p>Second; I feel that as the work progresses in other countries of Central America
                    and in Mexico that Costa Ricans of their own accord will come to the conclusion
                    that they are missing something and that they then will manifest more interest
                    in the project than at present and will show a greater desire to participate in
                    its proposed benefits. In other words, I feel that the ultimate success of the
                    project, insofar <pb facs="0556" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/> as Costa Rica is
                    concerned, will be greater if the decision to go forward is one that is dictated
                    by a genuine public and official enthusiasm, and at present no such enthusiasm
                    exists.</p>
                <p>Third; I feel that it will be very inadvisable for the United States Government
                    at this time, and perhaps in the future, to assist directly in the payment of
                    the cost of construction other than is contemplated in the acts of Congress
                    referred to in Instruction No. 96.</p>
                <p>Unquestionably there does prevail in Costa Rica a desire on the part of many
                    people, including land owners, for the very generous United States, as an act of
                    good neighborliness, to come along and say in effect: “Don’t worry Costa Rica,
                    we will build the road for you.” Nothing would please some Costa Ricans better
                    than this, but even if the United States was so generously inclined there are
                    sufficient politicians in the Costa Rican Congress who would not only look such
                    a gift horse in the mouth but would denounce the alleged motives of the United
                    States for such generosity. In such a gesture the Nationalists would again
                    visualize “Yankee Imperialism”.</p>
                <p>I feel that the only justification which might exist for the expenditure by the
                    United States Government in Costa Rica of a sum sufficiently large to finance
                    all or the greater part of the highway in this country, would be the
                    construction of a military highway wherein the ends would justify the means and
                    the question of cost would not be a factor. In such an event the United States
                    could then afford to turn a deaf ear to the protests of the Nationalists, but
                    otherwise I am confident our motives would not be appreciated and would always
                    be questioned.</p>
                <p>Fourth; I do not believe it would be advisable for title United States to make
                    available to Costa Rica any portion of the funds or materials contemplated in
                    the acts of Congress until this Government of its own accord negotiates or
                    commences a definite instrument survey as a substitute for that portion of the
                    highway between the towns of Naranjo and Las Cañas to which objection has been
                    made.</p>
                <p>Fifth; if and when the United States Government should ever extend material
                    assistance to the Government of Costa Rica, and if and when,—should this be
                    done—American capital is employed to assist in the construction of the highway,
                    I would stipulate that all materials purchased and all scientific assistance
                    employed be American. Unfortunately, in the past Costa Rica has been know[n] to
                    finance construction projects with American money (electrification of the
                    Pacific Railroad) and turn right around and expend these dollars in material and
                    equipment purchased in Germany.</p>
                <p>Sixth; in the light of Costa Rica’s present default on its outstanding bonds, and
                    in the light of the apparently indefinite date of resumption of payments of
                    interest on and amortization of these bonds, I feel that the financing of this
                    highway in Costa Rica by the sale of a bond issue to American investors as has
                    been suggested by some people, even if permitted by the Department of State,
                    would be a very risky and perhaps dubious financial venture. I would suggest
                    that if ever the day comes when the Department feels inclined to favor the
                    raising of funds in the United States to finance this project, the transaction
                    be hedged with such restrictions that not only the security of the American
                    investors is assured but the self-respect of the United States Government be
                    also maintained in reference to inevitable subsequent outbursts of political
                    leaders.</p>
                <pb facs="0557" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/>
                <p>In conclusion may I respectfully summarize my reactions to the Costa Rican
                    participation in the Inter-American Highway project based on observations during
                    my 13 months in Costa Rica, and they are that Costa Rica will some day construct
                    its sections of the Inter-American Highway and thereby furnish a complete road
                    from Laredo, Texas, to the “Panama Canal but the impetus should be supplied by
                    the Costa Ricans themselves from the standpoint of their selfish economic
                    interests, and that in no way should the impression prevail that the “Yanquis of
                    the North” are forcing Costa Rica either to accept or to build the road.</p>
                <p>The Department may feel, as a result of my conclusions, that I am not in sympathy
                    with the proposed construction of the Inter-American Highway. If, unfortunately,
                    this opinion should prevail may I enter a denial in advance and say for the
                    record that I not only visualize the actual highway as the greatest prospective
                    economic and cultural development pending in Costa Rica but that I have
                    neglected no occasion to informally and properly convey my enthusiasm to
                    officials of the Government.</p>
                <p>I can not help but feel, however, that the United States Government will make a
                    great mistake if it appears in the light of a philanthropist giving to Costa
                    Rica a gift of all or part of the cost of construction of this highway until
                    such time as Costa Rica shows a determined spirit of effective cooperation in
                    the execution of the project which will justify the financial aid of the United
                    States Government in accordance with the intent of the Congress.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Leo R. Sack</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Costa Rican Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                            (<persName type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Gurdián</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the American Minister</hi> (<persName
                            type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Sack</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 602–B <lb/> 420–31</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">San José</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-11-09">November 9,
                                1934</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MR. Minister</hi>:—I have the honor to acknowledge
                        receipt of your kind note No. 134, dated October 22nd, last, in which you
                        had the kindness to transcribe the text of the laws voted by the Congress of
                        the United States, and approved by His Excellency President Roosevelt,
                        authorizing disbursements to defray the expenses which the President in his
                        discretion may deem necessary to cooperate with the several governments,
                        members of the Pan American Union, in the survey and construction of the
                        proposed Inter-American Highway, this expenditure being subject to the
                        receipt of assurances satisfactory to the President from such governments,
                        of their cooperation in the survey and construction referred to. You add
                        that your government is now considering the places where these funds will be
                        spent and the form of their application in the work planned, with the
                        intention of <pb facs="0558" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/> assisting those
                        countries which are now carrying out or intend to initiate work on the
                        highway, which when completed will unite all the American countries. That
                        for the said purpose, the Government of the United States intends to donate
                        to the governments cooperating in the carrying out of the work, articles and
                        materials for bridges and road construction equipment, to be acquired with
                        the fund of one million dollars voted in the law first referred to
                        above.</p>
                    <p>Your government desires to know if the route marked out in the report given
                        to this government would be accepted by its engineers, and our intentions
                        toward initiation of the instrument survey of the road, in order that my
                        Government may take advantage of the generous offer of the Government of the
                        United States.</p>
                    <p>In reply, I have the honor to inform you that my Government, as much as any
                        other, is convinced of the very great importance of the construction of the
                        Inter-American Highway, which, uniting all the sister nations, will permit
                        the greatest intellectual and commercial “rapprochement” between them, will
                        facilitate a mutual acquaintance and will strengthen the ties of sympathy
                        now existing, at the same time being a factor of great importance in the
                        development of agriculture, industry and commerce in each and every one of
                        the American countries. Nevertheless, Costa Rica’s difficult situation has
                        obliged my government to effect inevitable economies in its expenditures in
                        order to avoid budgetary deficits, and to suspend, through a prior
                        arrangement with its American and European creditors, the service on its
                        foreign debt. Under these conditions, the country finds it impossible to
                        assume new obligations, which according to the estimates of the cost of the
                        Inter-American Highway in the country, would mean an increase of one hundred
                        per cent in the external debt of Costa Rica.</p>
                    <p>It is the firm intention of the Costa Rican Government to continue carrying
                        out a plan of highway construction in accordance with its economic capacity,
                        following the definitive route fixed for the construction of the
                        Inter-American Highway.</p>
                    <p>Having set forth the economic conditions of the country in relation to the
                        great undertaking referred to in your note, my government expresses its
                        thanks for the very valuable cooperation offered by the Government of the
                        United States, and accepts it if Costa Rica is found to meet the situation
                        which the American Congress had in view in passing the appropriation laws
                        cited in the note under reply.</p>
                    <p>The route planned for the highway in Costa Rican territory, according to the
                        plans submitted, holds for this government the obligation of passing through
                        places very near to the port of Puntarenas, and its construction would mean
                        that traffic between this point and San José would go preferably over the
                        highway, with serious prejudice to the Pacific Railway, a public enterprise
                        which represents a large investment for the country.</p>
                    <pb facs="0559" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/>
                    <p>For this reason I take the liberty of suggesting a change in the highway
                        route between the towns of Naranjo and Cañas at a distance from the Pacific
                        Railway line, and substituting for it, if technically possible, a different
                        route which would open up magnificent areas to the north of the “Cordillera
                        Central”.</p>
                    <p>I take [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Raúl Gurdián</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
