<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-12-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="588" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d588">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">810.154/691</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conference Between Representatives of
                                the Departments of State and Agriculture</hi><note n="32" xml:id="d588fn32">Present were Assistant Secretary of State Sumner
                                Welles; Messrs. Edwin C. Wilson, Willard L. Beaulac, and William R.
                                Manning of the Division of Latin American Affairs; Mr. Thomas H.
                                MacDonald, Chief of the Bureau of Public Roads, and Mr. E. W. James
                                of the same Bureau.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-12-07">December 7, 1934</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The object of the conference was to reach a decision between the
                            Departments of State and Agriculture regarding the next step to be taken
                            in extending the cooperation to be given by the United States in the
                            advancement of the Inter-American highway project.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed that the instrument survey through Central America should
                            be undertaken and that assistance in the form of bridges to be placed at
                            points along the route in Central America where they might be of
                            immediate use was desirable.</p>
                        <p>Mr. MacDonald said that he was very anxious, however, not to go ahead
                            with the work contemplated until another effort had been made to bring
                            Mexico into the picture. He had recently returned from the Mexican
                            border and had the impression that there was a real desire on the part
                            of the Mexican highway officials for our assistance. He thought perhaps
                            an acceptance from Mexico of our proffered assistance might be better
                            obtained by working through the highway officials there than by making a
                            direct approach to the Mexican Government. Upon being asked whether or
                            not Mexico was not already doing all it could be expected to do and more
                            than any other Latin American country on the highway project, Mr.
                            MacDonald replied that this was true as far as the section between the
                            American border and Mexico City was concerned. There would be more
                            obstacles in the way of completing the route between Mexico City and the
                            Guatemalan border, however, and we should always remember that Mexico
                            has it within her power to prevent the completion of the highway by
                            failing to construct its southern section. For this reason he thought it
                            highly desirable that we get Mexico’s cooperation in the very
                            beginning.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Welles said that sounded highly reasonable and that he would begin by
                            speaking to the Mexican Ambassador on the subject the same
                            afternoon.</p>
                        <p>Mr. MacDonald said he would also like to continue the Reconnaissance
                            Survey south of Panama. He said that the time element was always the
                            most important in executing such a project. If the Reconnaissance Survey
                            south of Panama is not undertaken now it will mean that the highway
                            project will be delayed by one or two more years. He would like to start
                            the Reconnaissance Survey right away and was certain that there was a
                            desire for the survey to be made on the parts of the South American
                            countries.</p>
                        <pb facs="0563" n="493" xml:id="pg_493"/>
                        <p>Mr. Wilson questioned the advisability of approaching the South American
                            Governments at this time. He suggested that in addition to the
                            desirability of concentrating the work to be done with the limited
                            amount of funds available in the Central American area where some
                            results of our work might become apparent, there was reason to doubt the
                            advisability of approaching Colombia, for example, the first country
                            south of Panama. He was not at all sure that Colombia wanted our
                            engineers down there at the present time. Mr. Welles said he saw no
                            reason why Colombia should object if Colombian engineers accompanied
                            American engineers. Mr. MacDonald agreed that it would be preferable
                            from his point of view if they did this.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Welles agreed that steps should be taken to extend our offer to
                            conduct a Reconnaissance Survey to the countries south of Panama. If all
                            countries did not accept, the survey could be made through those
                            countries accepting. At least it could be begun and Mr. MacDonald said
                            that he had received assurance from members of the next Congress that
                            additional funds for this survey would be made available, if needed. He
                            explained that no appropriations were necessary, that the Bureau of
                            Public Roads had an administrative fund which it was accumulating and
                            that all that was needed was an authorization to make expenditures out
                            of this fund.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed in conclusion that another approach would be made to
                            Mexico, that steps would be taken to offer to make a Reconnaissance
                            Survey in the countries south of Panama, and that until Mexico’s reply
                            had been received no work on the highway should be undertaken in Central
                            America.</p>
                        <closer><signed>W. L. <hi rend="smallcaps">Beaulac</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>