<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-11T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-11T10:00:00-05:00" n="146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/5–1154: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States
                                        Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                        Korea</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential<lb/><gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss></hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-11T16:00:00+01:00">May 11, 1954—4
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>64. Repeated information Tokyo 45, Department <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 170. Department pass Defense.
                                Toyko for <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss>. For <persName corresp="#p_VFJA1">Van Fleet</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HJEMG1">Hull</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s refusal agree so far on draft proposal
                                apparently based primarily on his attitude re withdrawal non-Korean
                                forces creating increasingly difficult situation here. Key point is
                                his insistence Chinese Communist forces be withdrawn and North
                                Korean forces <pb facs="0278" n="252" xml:id="pg_252"/> demobilized
                                before elections. This position totally unrealistic since neither
                                    <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> nor United Nations in
                                position victor in Korea. <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                                must made realize insistence on total Chinese Communist withdrawal
                                can only mean concurrent total <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                                withdrawal.</p>
                            <p>It is possible that part his tactic is to use this position as
                                bargaining lever to get commitments on further military assistance.
                                He has not perhaps fully considered dangers to <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> in complete United Nations
                                withdrawal before testing Communist performance on unification
                                Korea, assuming any agreement here and implementation of agreement
                                possible.</p>
                            <p>I would appreciate anything you may be able to do to explain frankly
                                to President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> from
                                military standpoint problems involved withdrawal all non-Korean
                                forces before elections.</p>
                            <p>In addition point outlined above, following considerations might be
                                advanced: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>Our basic objective here is to challenge Communists with
                                        constructive workable plan for achieving free unified Korea
                                        which Communists probably will never accept.</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>We do not consider total Chinese Communist withdrawal
                                        before elections as crucial element in unification plan if
                                        we obtain acceptance principles outlined paragraph II our
                                        draft proposal. Later provisions designed to insure, among
                                        other things, safeguards against interference by foreign
                                        forces in elections.</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>In reality we are compelled choose between total
                                        simultaneous withdrawal before elections, with danger
                                        Communists upsetting situation after United Nations
                                        withdrawal, or concurrent phased withdrawal before and after
                                        elections to protect against non-performance by Communists
                                        but with danger Communist forces might frustrate free
                                        elections.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>We have accordingly sought formula along lines paragraph IV draft
                                proposal which would require withdrawal bulk Communist forces before
                                elections but would leave <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> in
                                south, although reduced in size, during and after elections in event
                                Communist failure implement unification agreement.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SWB1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>