<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Korea ( (Briggs) ) to the United States Delegation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d171</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">171</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-05-19T01:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-05-19T01:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7MjCJlGL6L85Od" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Joint statement</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-19T01:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-19T01:30:00-05:00" n="171"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d171">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/5–1954: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Korea</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BEO1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Briggs</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">United States
                            Delegation</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>
                            <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-19T15:00:00+08:30"
                            >May 19, 1954—3 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>95. Sent Department 1204, repeated information Tokyo 712. Tokyo pass <gloss
                        target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss>. For <persName corresp="#p_SWB1"
                        >Smith</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_DAH1">Dean</persName>. Acting
                    Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_CCH1">Cho</persName> called early this
                    morning to see if we had received letter from President <pb facs="0311" n="285"
                        xml:id="pg_285"/> delivered last night, text of which is in <gloss
                        target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 94, repeated Secretary of State 1203,
                    Tokyo 711.<note n="1" xml:id="d171fn1">
                        <ref target="#d170">
                            <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> Ambassadors <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">Briggs</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAH1">Dean</persName> called on President <persName
                        corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>, Prime Minister, Acting Foreign Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_CCH1">Cho</persName> at 11 a.m. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAH1">Dean</persName> delivered to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> following letter: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“My dear Mr. President:</p>
                        <p>“On behalf of my government permit me to say I am deeply grateful at the
                            very distinct progress we have made in discussing the proposed joint
                            statement of principles.</p>
                        <p>“In the statement made by you as President of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1"
                                >ROK</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">John Foster
                                Dulles</persName>, Secretary of State of our government, on July 27,
                            1953, you jointly said: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“‘There are no other agreements or understandings stated or
                                    implied resulting from these consultations other than those
                                    herein contained’.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>“The ‘herein’ referred to draft mutual defense treaty between our two
                            governments. That treaty has since been consented to by our Senate and
                            is about to be formally published and ratified between our two
                            governments.</p>
                        <p>“When Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                            was testifying before the US Senate Committee on Foreign Affairs he was
                            asked if there were any secret agreements or understandings and he
                            repeated the paragraph quoted above. The consent of the US Senate
                            followed.</p>
                        <p>“We again recognize the inherent sovereignty of the <gloss
                                target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> to deal with its own affairs in the
                            territory now under its administrative control or hereafter recognized
                            by our government as lawfully brought under its administrative
                            control.</p>
                        <p>“In agreeing to the ‘specific arrangements for the withdrawal of
                            non-Korean forces’ to which you must agree in subdivision 4 of the
                            proposed statement of principles you will, of course, be exercising your
                            own sovereign power, in so agreeing.</p>
                        <p>“As you know we are a signatory to the armistice agreement of July 27,
                            1953, and until it is lawfully superseded we must abide by its terms
                            with which you also agreed to [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] in the joint
                            statement above referred to, to the extent therein set forth.</p>
                        <p>“We are also a signatory to the ‘declaration of the 16 nations’ relating
                            to the armistice of July 27, 1953, in which we affirm that if there
                            should be a renewal of armed attack against your government, challenging
                            the principles of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, we will be
                            prompt to resist.</p>
                        <p>“We believe the achievement of unity of Geneva on the basis of the
                            statement of joint principles will enable us to command the respect of
                            the free world and public opinion at home and will enable us promptly to
                            carry into effect the recommendations of the <persName
                                corresp="#p_VFJA1">Van Fleet</persName> investigation mission now in
                            the Far East to the end that your army will be equipped to repel any
                            attack.</p>
                        <p>“In addition you will have the mutual defense treaty. As to the
                            elimination of subdivision 6, your government has already been
                            recognized <pb facs="0312" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/> by the <gloss
                                target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in its declaration of December 12, 1948,
                            as the only sovereign government in Korea. The extension of your
                            administrative control in North Korea will, of course, have to be
                            established to other governments’ satisfaction and subdivision 6’s
                            inclusion is useful, but I leave that to your good judgment.</p>
                        <p>“I am very sure it will not be in your or our interest to make the
                            further commitment you suggest in your letter of May 18, 1954, but if
                            you will agree promptly to the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> being
                            a party to the joint statement of principles at Geneva it will greatly
                            encouraged the free world and redound to the joint benefit of our
                            respective governments and permit us jointly to go forward on the tasks
                            envisioned by you and President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                                >Eisenhower</persName>.</p>
                        <p>“I again urge the necessity of prompt action as the opportunity for us to
                            act at Geneva may pass from our hands.</p>
                        <p>“With renewed admiration and respect, I am, Mr. President, Faithfully
                            yours, <persName corresp="#p_DAH1">Arthur H. Dean</persName>. Special
                            Ambassador to Korea”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> read letter out loud.
                    President in substance said again had to have guarantee of US in secret letter
                    from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAH1">Dean</persName> that if he marched
                    north against the North Korean Communist Army after withdrawal of Chinese
                    Communist Army we would support him, or we had to insert “North Korean Communist
                    Army” in subdivision 4 as well as non-Korean forces.</p>
                <p>We again explained tremendous advantage our side issuing joint statement of
                    principles promptly and utter impossibility of having any secret agreements or
                    understanding.</p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> said Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> had assured him among our basic
                    objectives was to bring about united and free Korea. He asked could we honestly
                    and realistically believe we could have free elections in north if Chinese
                    Communist Army remained or that he could ever extend his jurisdiction to north
                    if that Army remained?</p>
                <p>We again pointed out what the situation would be if no joint statement issued at
                    Geneva with possible slow disintegration <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    forces, grumbling American opinion at lack of unity and difficulty such fact
                    imposed on administration in maintaining <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                    Army at appropriate level capable of resisting attack.</p>
                <p>President very amicable and reasonable aside from renewed attack on economic aid
                    program and Japanese. He said we were really wasting our time in further
                    discussions unless we were either prepared (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) to bring
                    about withdrawal North Korean Communist Army or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) back
                    him in a military move.</p>
                <p>We again urged him essential necessity his cooperation in order that we could
                    continue our cooperation and continued to emphasize his position made our
                    ability to act much more difficult.</p>
                <pb facs="0313" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/>
                <p>Finally President said he would discuss further with his Cabinet officers and
                    expressed appreciation for the good nature with which the discussions had been
                    conducted on both sides.<note n="2" xml:id="d171fn2">
                        <p>The following additional information was imparted in telegram 97 from
                            Seoul to Geneva, also sent to the Department of State as telegram 1206,
                            May 19: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In description meeting with President <persName corresp="#p_RS1"
                                        >Rhee</persName> this morning contained <gloss
                                        target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1204 neglected to state
                                    with reference to <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>’s
                                    desire delete from paragraph three words ‘supervise and’, we
                                    this morning agreed to this deletion with insertion however of
                                    reference to 1950 <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                                    resolution. Phrase in question now reads, ‘<gloss
                                        target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss> shall observe the
                                    elections in accordance with <gloss target="#t_UNGA1"
                                        >UNGA</gloss> resolution of 7 October 1950, which shall et
                                    cetera’.” (795.00/5–1954)</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BEO1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Briggs</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
