<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-16T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-16T06:00:00-05:00" n="239" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/6–1654: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States
                                    Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-16T12:00:00+01:00">June 16,
                                1954—noon</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_Dulte1">Dulte</gloss> 185. Personal for Secretary from
                            Under Secretary. My personal reactions on final Korean plenary may
                            interest you and supplement our report <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 451.<note n="1" xml:id="d239fn1">Dated June 16. <ref target="#pg_376">p. 376</ref>.</note> In first place,
                            preparatory missionary work and drafting by our own people here was
                            superbly done. It was like herding a flock of rabbits through a hole in
                            a fence, and there were causes for extreme exasperation, but everyone
                            remained patient and persuasive, and it paid off. We had most unusual
                            degree of cooperation from Canada, Australia, and New Zealand even
                            though their basic views on some important matters differed from ours.
                            It might be worth while if you sent a brief and very personal message to
                                <persName corresp="#p_WTC1">Webb</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName> expressing appreciation. You
                            can thank <persName corresp="#p_CRG1">Casey</persName> personally when
                            in Washington. He is not the world’s most brilliant statesman, but he
                            loyally stepped into the breach at last minute when some loss of control
                            of conference by <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> in Chair and
                            bad blunder by <persName corresp="#p_SPH1">Spaak</persName> seemed
                            likely to leave the US alone in declining without further instructions
                            to associate itself with a final resolution which as we saw it would in
                            effect have made the Geneva Conference a self-perpetuating body outside
                            the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> but including Red China.</p>
                        <p>Until <persName corresp="#p_SPH1">Spaak</persName> allowed himself to be
                            baited, the session went very much as planned for most of the more than
                            six hours, and though the final exchanges between <persName corresp="#p_SPH1">Spaak</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PYT1">Pyun</persName>, and others on our side furnished the Communists a
                            good deal of amusement and an excellent propaganda line, the real issues
                            on which the Allies are in some disagreement never came to the surface.
                            On the whole it was about as good as could be expected, though not as
                            good as I had hoped from the unusual success we had during the preceding
                            two days in holding the sixteen together on tactics and wording of final
                            declaration.</p>
                        <p>We have operated under one great disadvantage. The Communists knew, and
                            indeed the whole press knew almost within minutes, everything <pb facs="0416" n="390" xml:id="pg_390"/> that transpired in the
                            meetings of the sixteen, and on the last day particularly were cocked
                            and primed and ready for us. Considering this, I am well satisfied.<note n="2" xml:id="d239fn2"><p><persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> sent the following reply in telegram
                                        <gloss target="#t_Tedul1">Tedul</gloss> 209, June 16, 8
                                    p.m., to Geneva: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“From Secretary for Under Secretary. Re <gloss target="#t_Dulte1">Dulte</gloss> 185. I congratulate
                                            you on bringing Korean matter to so satisfactory a
                                            close. Please also extend my thanks to your associates
                                            on our Delegation. I shall, as you suggest, cable to
                                                <persName corresp="#p_WTC1">Webb</persName> and
                                                <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName> and
                                            thank <persName corresp="#p_CRG1">Casey</persName> when
                                            he is here.</p>
                                        <p>“In view of fact that I shall probably have a very
                                            strenuous time with possible trips to Brussels and
                                            Montevideo during the latter part of this month and the
                                            first of July, I am hoping to get away from Saturday to
                                            Monday, returning Washington Tuesday morning. I may
                                            therefore miss your arrival which I greatly regret but
                                            which I hope you will excuse.</p>
                                        <p>“As you have doubtless heard the President will want to
                                            have a group of Congressional leaders at the White House
                                            after you get back to hear your report. This may be set
                                            up for Wednesday morning [June 23].” (396.1
                                            GE/6–1654)</p></quote></p></note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SWB1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>