<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of Defense ( (Wilson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d263</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">263</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-03-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-03-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="263"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d263">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/3–554</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WCE1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-03-05">March 5,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: There have been several
                    discussions between representatives of our respective Departments regarding
                    preparation for the Geneva Conference and the organization necessary for the
                    expeditious development of position papers and other arrangements for the
                    Conference. This Department is interested in assisting the Department of State
                    in every way possible in preparing for the Conference.</p>
                <p>It is believed that Department of Defense participation can be most effective if
                    the informal views of this Department and necessary military information are
                    available to the Department of State during the preparation of position papers.
                    In this way, also, interested offices in the Department of Defense will be aware
                    of positions being developed and final processing can be handled rapidly.
                    Further, it is believed that the Geneva Conference is of such importance to the
                    interests and the security of the United States in the Far East area that
                    maximum effort should be devoted by all interested agencies to the development
                    of the United States positions for the Conference.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, it is recommended that consideration be given to the following
                    procedure.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                    <item>Establishment of a steering committee consisting of senior Department of
                        State and Defense representatives through which all position papers
                        developed by working groups would be processed.</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                    <item>Establishment of two working groups consisting of working level
                        representatives of both Departments, one working group developing positions
                        on Korea and the second working group, positions on Indochina. Various <hi
                            rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> committees as may be deemed appropriate would
                        consider specific items in each area.</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                    <item>The papers as developed in the working groups would be processed through
                        the steering committee. After approval by the steering committee, they would
                        be cleared formally by the Departments of State and Defense.</item>
                </list>
                <p>If you concur in the above suggestions, the names of Defense Department
                    representatives on the steering committee and working groups will be furnished
                        you.<note n="1" xml:id="d263fn1">In a letter of Mar. 9, Acting Secretary of
                        State <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Walter B. Smith</persName> informed
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> that the Department
                        of State was in agreement with his suggestions as to the procedures for
                        State-Defense coordination and that the Secretary had designated <persName
                            corresp="#p_MAD1">MacArthur</persName> as Coordinator for the Geneva
                        Conference, <persName corresp="#p_YKT1">Young</persName> as Chairman of the
                        Working Group on Korea, and <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> as
                        Chairman of the Working Group on Indochina. (396.1 GE/3–554)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">C. E. Wilson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
