<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-03-22T04:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-03-22T04:30:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/3–2254: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Korea</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BEO1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Briggs</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-03-22T18:00:00+08:30">March 22, 1954—6
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>926. Repeated information priority Tokyo 565. Tokyo pass <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss>. President’s letter delivered
                            this morning to President <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> who
                            received it with equanimity, in great contrast his attitude when last
                            previous communication delivered (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 635, January 6).<note n="1" xml:id="d28fn1">For
                                related documentation, see <ref target="frus1952-54v15p1">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">xv</hi></ref>.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> read letter slowly aloud in
                            presence Prime Minister and Foreign Minister. After asking me to express
                            his thanks and appreciation to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                            talked in mild vein for 15 minutes approximately as follows:</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> said communication called for
                            careful study but that it seems clear to him US now desires reduce
                            American personnel in Korea which <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> called “understandable”. He referred to advantage
                            from US point of view of substituting <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> for American and other <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> personnel observing that he had been greatly impressed
                            by recent <hi rend="italic">Reader’s Digest</hi> article by General
                                <persName corresp="#p_VFJA1">Van Fleet</persName> in which latter
                            discusses <pb facs="0075" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> economy of utilization
                            Korean troops. According to this, <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName> said one American costs as much to put in the field
                            here as 25 Koreans. This led President to rambling observation [garble]
                            possibly of galvanizing Asians themselves to fight Communists, which
                            necessarily is basis his recent activities seeking to bring various
                            Asian leaders together for what he termed informal conference and
                            discussion at Chinhae next month. President also mentioned his impending
                            purchase of powerful radio equipment and expressed disappointment when
                            Prime Minister said it could not be installed and functioning for six
                            months. Shortly thereafter <persName corresp="#p_RS1">Rhee</persName>
                            spoke in almost identical terms during farewell call by Air Force
                            General <persName>Weyland</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d28fn2">Gen.
                                    <persName>Otto P. Weyland</persName>, who had been Commanding
                                General of the U.S. Far East Air Forces, was leaving to become
                                Commander of the U.S. Tactical Air Command.</note> which took place
                            after his meeting with me.</p>
                        <p>President’s mood was benign but he appeared unusually vague. He gave no
                            concrete indication of intentions concerning Geneva conference, other
                            than to declare letter would receive his most careful attention.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BEO1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Briggs</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>