<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Delegation to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d561</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">561</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-05-20T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-05-20T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-20T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-20T12:00:00-05:00" n="561"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d561">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/5–2054: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States Delegation</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-20T18:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 20, 1954—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 267. Repeated information Paris 307,
                    London 191, Saigon 98. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> advised
                        <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> and me of his talks this
                    morning with <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou</persName> along following
                    lines:</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> had argued case for separation of
                    Laos and Cambodia. <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou</persName> had agreed that
                    military and political aspects must be dealt with separately with priority for
                    cease-fire. Cease-fire should take effect in all three States on same date.
                    Political settlements might be different for three. <persName corresp="#p_EA1"
                        >Eden</persName>’s advisers who had accompanied him felt that <persName
                        corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou</persName> wanted an early agreement for cease-fire.
                        <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou</persName> had repeatedly stated that if no
                    progress could be made on one line, another should be tried.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> observed that situation with
                    respect to cessation of hostilities was different in three countries. It could
                    be brought about immediately in Cambodia and Laos where it was simply a problem
                    of external forces, while some regrouping of forces would be essential <pb
                        facs="0890" n="864" xml:id="pg_864"/> in Vietnam. Any extension of this
                    regrouping concept to Laos and Cambodia (as distinct from withdrawal) would
                    complicate their situation by establishing pockets. He did not wish to free
                    conference, but if we abandoned principle of separation, even temporarily, we
                    would not know when or on what level we would be able to take it up again. Laos
                    and Cambodia had said this morning they would not go along if we abandoned
                    separation.</p>
                <p>I said I believed Communists desire to produce troop concentrations which they
                    could point to as areas controlled by resistance movements. It would be
                    difficult to determine whether such concentrations were natives or invaders and
                    much would depend on composition and effectiveness of supervisory commission,
                    which was matter of supreme importance. We must maintain our position regarding
                    separate consideration Laos and Cambodia, but might explore Communist ideas
                    regarding mechanism of an armistice.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> had said West denied so-called
                    resistance movements in Laos and Cambodia had any existence whatever. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou</persName> had said they might be minorities, but
                    they existed and could not be swept out of countries.</p>
                <p>French believed Viet Minh proposal (<gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 259,
                    repeated information Paris 299, London 188, Saigon 93<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d561fn1">Dated May 19, <ref target="#pg_854">p. 854</ref>.</note>)
                    to discuss their point 8(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and French points one and
                    five, indicated possibility Communists might still agree to separation. I said
                    we would fully reserve our position on separation, but having done so, would
                    agree look at these specific points.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> subsequently told me that he had
                    warned <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou</persName> again that Indochina
                    situation was dangerous and might lead to unpredictable and serious results.
                        <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou</persName> had said he was counting on
                    Britain to prevent this happening. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>
                    had warned him not to do so, since even though Britain desired moderation, in
                    event of showdown, she would stand with United States.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
