<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>United States Minutes of the First Meeting of the Drafting Committee on
                    Indochina</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d630</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">630</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-05-28T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-05-28T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-28T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-28T05:00:00-05:00" n="630"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d630">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, <gloss
                        target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 281</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Minutes of the First Meeting of the Drafting
                        Committee on Indochina</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d630fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SCC1"
                            >Stelle</persName>, Minutes indicate that meeting convened at 11 a.m.
                        and adjourned at 1 p.m. Summary of minutes was transmitted to the Department
                        of State in telegram <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 333, May 28.
                        (396.1 GE/5–2854)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss>/DC/1</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-28T11:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 28, 1954—11 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United Kingdom</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AWD1">Allen</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TJG1">Tahourdin</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Vallat</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S.S.R.</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NKV1">Novikov</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TOA1">Troyanovsky</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Vietnam</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NDK1">Dac Khe</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Thanh</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BK1">Buu Kinh</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Cambodia</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_NK1">Nong Kimny</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam Sary</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SS11">Son Sann</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Communist China</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CWT1">Chang Wen-tien</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LKN1">Li Ke-nung</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName>Pu Shou-chang</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <persName>Ch’en Chia-k’ang</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCC1">Stelle</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Roux</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_CC1">Cheysson</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Andronikov</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Laos</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Sananikone</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KP1">Panya</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Viet Minh</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Phan-Anh</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Hoan</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PHQ1">Quat</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> stated that he had had
                    discussions with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> as to the
                    question of Chairmanship. Since this committee was formed in yesterday’s
                    restricted session, they had thought it should be treated <pb facs="0982"
                        n="956" xml:id="pg_956"/> as a carry-over from that session when Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> was in the Chair rather than a
                    committee which would be attached to the next session of the Ministers when Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> would be in the Chair. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> and he had thought,
                    therefore, that it might be appropriate to have him in the Chair. He wondered
                    whether this was generally agreeable to the other delegations.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> stated that the French delegation
                    was in full accord with this idea. If meetings similar to this one should be
                    held, the same arrangement might be carried out. The other delegations signified
                    their agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> stated that he thought the purpose
                    of the meeting as set by the Ministers was to consider three drafts—the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> draft of the day before yesterday, and the French
                    and Chinese Communists’ drafts which had been tabled at yesterday’s sitting. He
                    thought it would be remembered that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> had proposed certain amendments to the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> draft, that these amendments had been discussed,
                    but that in the end it had proved impossible to reach agreement. Lord <persName
                        corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> distributed drafts of a <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal which follows:<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d630fn2">The British proposal was transmitted to the Department of
                        State in telegram <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 332, May 28.
                        (396.1 GE/5–2854)</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In order to facilitate the early cessation of hostilities it is
                            necessary to determine the areas within which the forces of both sides
                            shall be regrouped. To this end it is proposed that: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Representatives of the two commands should meet immediately in
                                    Geneva.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Their first task should be to work out regrouping areas for
                                    Vietnam.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>They should report their findings and recommendations to the
                                    Conference as soon as possible.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                <item>The Conference meanwhile should proceed with examination of
                                    other military matters, beginning with arrangements for
                                    international supervision.”</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>He stated that the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> itself would like to make
                    one amendment. He would like to delete in the preamble the phrase “It is
                    necessary to determine the areas within which the forces of both sides shall be
                    regrouped. To this end”.</p>
                <p>This amendment would leave the effective part of the proposal unchanged.
                        <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> stated he did not want to take
                    advantage of being in the Chair to talk too much, but he would like to make one
                    suggestion on the procedure of this meeting. During the last few days at the
                    restricted meetings we have been making a vigorous effort to arrive at a point
                    where action at last could be taken. It would be a relief and incentive to all
                    of us if we felt we were making genuine progress <pb facs="0983" n="957"
                        xml:id="pg_957"/> towards a settlement. It would also be a satisfaction to
                    the whole world which was watching these proceedings.</p>
                <p>He stated that we have been searching for common ground but to him two points
                    seemed agreed upon. The first was the necessity for direct contacts between the
                    commanders either in Geneva or on the spot, or perhaps preferably both. The
                    second was the extreme desirability for a simultaneous cease-fire throughout
                    Indochina. He wondered whether it was not possible and urgent to get
                    representatives of the commanders together to begin work on the terms and
                    methods of cessation of hostilities while the conference proceeded with other
                    matters. The conference could then at any time enlarge the terms of reference
                    upon which the military representatives could work. The important thing to do
                    was to get them started on something, and we might get them working on something
                    more later on. He thought it well to recall that the commanders or their
                    representatives could only present proposals to the conference. Only the
                    conference itself could approve or disapprove those proposals. He thought the
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal did not conflict in any way with
                    the proposal which had been tabled by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou
                        En-lai</persName> even though the ideas contained in the Chinese proposal
                    were perhaps expressed in different language. He thought that the first two of
                    the Chinese proposals might be referred to the military representatives and that
                    others might be taken up perhaps later on. He was sorry that he had talked at
                    such great length, but he had thought that it might be useful to give expression
                    to the sense of urgency which he was sure all delegations share. He hoped that
                    the other delegations would express their opinions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> gave thanks from the French
                    delegation to the Chairman for a clear and lucid exposition of the task of the
                    committee. He thought the committee was not meant at this level to replace the
                    conference and to repeat its work but rather to facilitate the work of the
                    conference. He thought that if the committee could find points of common
                    agreement it could achieve positive results. He thought the task of the
                    committee should be approached in a positive way and that to this end it should
                    limit the scope of the matters with which it dealt. He thought the committee
                    should address itself to specific matters.</p>
                <p>The last meetings of the Ministers have been concerned with the question of
                    bringing together representatives of the commanders-inchief. He thought the
                    question should be put as to whether the conference wants these representatives
                    to meet and to undertake certain tasks for the conference. He thought it was not
                    very difficult for the committee to arrive at useful results. There were quite a
                    few points of common agreement although the angles from which those points were
                    approached were not necessarily the same. He thought that in the <pb facs="0984"
                        n="958" xml:id="pg_958"/> various proposals some were addressed to immediate
                    tasks whereas some—suoh as, for example, some of those of the Chinese
                    Communists’ proposal—were larger in scope and addressed to principles. Even in
                    the Chinese Communists’ proposal, however, there were certain immediate tasks
                    which were in common with those of the other proposals. He did agree that
                    proceeding toward finding items of common agreement should be the purpose of
                    this meeting. Finally, of the three proposals he thought that Point <hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>, of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal,
                    covered the same ground as the first point of the French proposal; Point <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi> of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal was
                    similar in purpose to the second point of the French proposal; Point <hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi> of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal could
                    be equated with the third point of the French proposal and Point <hi
                        rend="italic">d</hi> of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal with
                    the sixth point of the French proposal.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> stated that the Chinese proposal
                    was much broader in scope and covered very much the whole ground of the
                    discussions of the conference. However, Paragraph 2 of the Chinese Communists’
                    proposal did cover points which were referred to in the British and French
                    drafts. If his memory was correct he believed that <persName corresp="#p_CEL1"
                        >Chou En-lai</persName> had noted the desirability of contact between the
                    commanders in Geneva. The same statement had been made in one form or another by
                    many other delegations. He thought, therefore, that without difficulty this
                    could be extracted as a point of common agreement. He might further say that he
                    had had the feeling that the proposal which the French had made on the 27th of
                    May was not far removed from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName>’s
                    proposal and that it did not conflict with what the Viet Minh representative had
                    put forward.</p>
                <p>The Cambodian, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NK1">Nong Kimny</persName>, took
                    note of the amendment which the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> had made to
                    the proposal which it had itself distributed. He stated that the head of the
                    Cambodian delegation had the other day mentioned that the British proposal might
                    raise certain misunderstandings. The head of the Cambodian delegation had at the
                    same time addressed to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> questions
                    as to whether the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal applied to all
                    three countries or whether it applied only to Vietnam. <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> had replied, he believed, that the preamble
                    applied to all three countries and the rest to Vietnam. The Ambassador thought
                    he should again address these questions to Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1"
                        >Reading</persName>. He believed that to start with the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> draft might again give rise to a series of
                    amendments and objections. He thought it might be better to start with the
                    French plan, particularly since Paragraph 4 of the French plan removed some of
                    the difficulties which were raised by the proposal of the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss> delegation. He would like to propose that the committee begin by
                    considering point by point the French proposal in which <pb facs="0985" n="959"
                        xml:id="pg_959"/> case it might then attack directly the question of
                    achieving contact between the two commands.</p>
                <p>Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> stated that the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposals were general and intended to apply to
                    all three states. Only the specific Paragraph <hi rend="italic">b</hi> was
                    directed to Vietnam since this was a question of the greatest urgency. He
                    thought it was for the meeting to decide which proposal it should consider. He
                    himself had no personal objection to considering the French draft.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> referred first of all to the
                    proposal tabled by the Chinese delegation. He understood that there had been
                    some agreement among the Ministers that these proposals should be considered
                    tomorrow at the next meeting of the Ministers. He thought that at this meeting
                    the committee should begin work at the point where the Ministers had stopped
                    which was, as he saw it, in reconciling the various texts of <persName
                        corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>’s proposal for achieving contacts between
                    the commanders of the two sides. He believed that to save time discussions
                    should be started with the last draft presented by the representative of the
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> which as he understood it had been
                    formulated taking into consideration the various opinions expressed around the
                    table. From the observations of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                    representative he understood that this draft had been also formulated in such a
                    way as to represent the ideas proposed by the French delegate. He would like to
                    speak first about the preamble. He thought it would be desirable to insert the
                    phrase “and simultaneously” between the words “the earliest” and the phrase
                    “cessation of hostilities”. He thought that proceeding from the fact that there
                    had been at one time no objections from other delegations to the insertion of
                    such a phrase he did not see why such a very general statement should be
                    unacceptable to any delegation. He thought that if all delegations concurred,
                    the committee could agree on the preamble in its new form.</p>
                <p>As to Paragraph <hi rend="italic">a</hi> of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                    proposal he would suggest the addition of the phrase “and also to establish
                    contact on the spot”. He proceeded from the fact that this addition had also
                    been discussed in various meetings and had not evoked disapproval. He believed
                    that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> had spoken of the
                    desirability of contacts on the spot.</p>
                <p>At this point Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> raised the
                    question as to whether the Russian amendment might read more smoothly if it read
                    “and contact also be established on the spot”. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> acquiesced in <persName corresp="#p_RM1"
                        >Reading</persName>’s revision.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> proposed that Paragraph <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi> of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> text be
                    amended to read “their task should be to work out regrouping areas for the two
                    sides” or alternatively it should be amended to read, “their task should be to
                    work out regrouping areas for the two sides beginning <pb facs="0986" n="960"
                        xml:id="pg_960"/> with Vietnam”. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName> accepted Paragraph <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. He stated
                    that he still held the view that there was no need at all for Paragraph <hi
                        rend="italic">d</hi>. He justified his feeling that there was no need at all
                    for Paragraph <hi rend="italic">d</hi> by stating that the Ministers had agreed
                    that the re-establishment of peace should begin with a discussion on how to
                    bring about a cessation of hostilities. There had been already considerable
                    discussion on this point and this committee was addressing itself to these
                    matters. The conference had still to talk political matters.</p>
                <p>The question of when they should discuss these was something which the Ministers
                    themselves should decide. There was no reason for the committee to commit them
                    in that respect. In his own view, <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>
                    said, if the French and the <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> delegations were
                    agreeable he thought it might be well to give a date when the contacts between
                    the commanders should be established and to amend the British draft on that
                    respect. <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> concluded by advocating
                    that it was advisable to take up the last <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                    draft read, to take into consideration the amendments he had proposed, and to
                    prepare a text for consideration by the Ministers.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName> raised a point of inquiry as to
                    whether the USSR had accepted the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> deletion in
                    the preamble of the British draft. Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1"
                        >Reading</persName> thought the USSR had accepted that amendment and read
                    the text including the Russian amendments and deletion of the phrase the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> had recommended to be deleted. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said he had had in mind the Russian
                    text which had been distributed and that the text as he had it in mind would
                    read “in order to facilitate the earliest and simultaneous cessation of
                    hostilities it is necessary to determine the areas within which the forces of
                    both sides shall be regrouped”. (This made it evident that <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> did not accept the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> deletion.)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> asked whether <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> would have objection to the amended
                    form which he stated was intended only to simplify the proposal. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> said that simplification was good
                    within certain limits but it was not useful when the limits were surpassed. He
                    therefore thought that it was more useful to use the fuller formula of the
                    original <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> text.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Sananikone</persName>, the Laotian representative,
                    stated his pleasure that after two weeks the conference was about to reach a
                    constructive stage. As to which paper the committee should consider the Laotian
                    thought that it was preferable to extract common points of agreement. He thought
                    that all were agreed on the desirability of the meeting of the commanders. He
                    quesioned why that point should not be presented to the conference for a
                    decision. He had one question, however, to address to Lord <persName
                        corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName>. He had understood <persName
                        corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> to say that all except Paragraph <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi> of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal
                    applied to all of Indochina. If this <pb facs="0987" n="961" xml:id="pg_961"/>
                    were so, he wanted to know what commanders were referred to in Paragraph <hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>. If the reference were to the Laos commander and the
                    Viet Minh commander, he thought it should be again made clear that there was in
                    Laos no question of any regrouping but merely a question of simple withdrawal of
                    Viet Minh forces.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_NDK1">Dac Khe</persName> thought that progress could be
                    made by leaving the level of the abstract and progressing to the concrete. He
                    thought that progress had been made by beginning a concrete examination of the
                    problems of Vietnam leaving aside for the moment those of Cambodia and Laos,
                    which would be settled later on their merits. He pointed out that the French
                    proposal clearly refers to Vietnam and only Vietnam. Moreover Paragraph 4 of
                    that proposal contained elements which he thought it was necessary for the
                    commanders to have for guidance in their work. He therefore proposed that the
                    committee take the French draft as a basis for discussion.</p>
                <p>Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> stated that he fully realized
                    the reasons advanced by the representatives of Laos, Cambodia and Vietnam, but
                    he wondered whether in view of the fact that the British proposal was so similar
                    to the French, and since it had been already commented upon by the USSR whether
                    it would not be useful for the committee to come back to the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> text and to deal with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1"
                        >Gromyko</persName>’s amendments as well as certain other amendments which
                    he himself was prepared to make, and amendments which others might care to make.
                    He thought the question needed considering, but he wondered if we could not
                    return for the moment to the British text.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> commented that he had no pride of
                    authorship, that he did think that the French proposal, particularly with the
                    points which were made in Paragraphs 4 and 5, had some advantage and that there
                    was also an advantage in the fact that the French proposal had no preamble. His
                    mind, however, was open to any text. As regards the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss> text, he endorsed the deletion in the preamble which the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> had recommended. He thought that whatever text
                    the committee considered it was running the risk of making no progress unless it
                    realized that principles were one thing and implementation another. He thought
                    it was important to begin with the problems of Vietnam which was the most
                    important theatre of operations. If it were attempted at the same time to deal
                    with the problems of Laos and Cambodia, this might temper whatever draft was
                    arrived at and complicate it. He thought the committee should limit its
                    objective and start with Vietnam. It could immediately thereafter address itself
                    to work on Laos and Cambodia if the conference should so decide. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> commented that if we were dealing with
                    Vietnam alone the notion of a simultaneous cease-fire had no application or
                    meaning. He was concerned that the committee <pb facs="0988" n="962"
                        xml:id="pg_962"/> should reach a practical conclusion. If the conference
                    wanted military people to meet and to take up the problems of Vietnam, we should
                    say so simply. If at a later date the conference wanted the same military people
                    to take up the problems of Laos and Cambodia, it could say so at that time. With
                    regard to the question of simultaneous cease-fire the French delegation admits
                    this as a practical possibility, and as a matter of fact, the first part of the
                    French proposal contained mention of the possibility. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1"
                        >Chauvel</persName> thought that it would be an improvement if the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal could be clearly headed “Proposal for
                    Vietnam”.</p>
                <p>As to the question of timing which had been raised by Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CJ1"
                        >Chauvel</persName> would like to inform the committee that military
                    representatives of the Franco-Vietnamese High Command would be arriving in
                    Geneva Monday.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName> stated that his understanding of
                    the terms of reference of the committee was that the committee was to examine
                    the various proposals and the discussions concerning those proposals which had
                    been put forward in the last few days and to extract from them those points on
                    which there was agreement. It was not the task of the committee to make
                    suggestions on matters on which there had been no meeting of the minds. From
                    examination of the proposals and the discussions of the last few days it seemed
                    to him that there were only two clear points on which there was general
                    agreement. First there was general agreement that representatives of the
                    Franco-Vietnamese commanders should meet in Geneva. Second there was agreement
                    that these military representatives should explore means and methods of working
                    out regrouping areas for Vietnam. If there were general agreement on these two
                    points it should be possible to find a way to express this agreement clearly and
                    simply.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName> said it was equally clear from an
                    examination of the discussions and proposals that there was not a meeting of the
                    minds on two subjects: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) There was no agreement that
                    the three countries should be treated in the same manner. (<hi rend="italic"
                        >b</hi>) There was no general agreement that there must be a simultaneous
                    cessation of hostilities. There might eventually be agreement to that effect but
                    as yet there existed no such agreement. It therefore seemed to him that all
                    language which referred to agreement on simultaneous cessation of hostilities
                    should be excluded from proposals drafted by the committee. Application of the
                    test as to areas of agreement lead him to the view that as amended by the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal
                    was one which clearly stated points on which there was general agreement. It is
                    clear that the task of the military commanders applied solely to Vietnam. The
                    amendments suggested by the USSR on the other hand introduced matters on which
                    there had not been agreement and therefore he did not think that the amendments
                    proposed by the Russian representative should <pb facs="0989" n="963"
                        xml:id="pg_963"/> be acceptable. <persName corresp="#p_PH1"
                        >Phleger</persName> stated that in a desire to be helpful he made the
                    suggestion that the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal be restricted to
                    Paragraphs <hi rend="italic">a, b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, that the
                    preamble be dropped and that in line with the views of the Russian
                    representative Paragraph <hi rend="italic">d</hi> be omitted also. He thought it
                    would be useful if the names of the commanders referred to were inserted. The
                    proposal would therefore read: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>“Representatives of the Franco-Vietnamese and Vietminh commands should
                            meet immediately in Geneva.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>“Their first task should be to work out regrouping areas for
                            Vietnam.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>“They should report their findings and recommendations to the
                            conference as soon as possible.”</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> stated that several
                    delegations had requested to speak, that there was a plenary on Korea this
                    afternoon, that since it was one o’clock already he did not believe agreement
                    could be reached on the various proposals at this meeting. He recommended an
                    adjournment and asked whether it would be agreeable to the others to meet again
                    at 1030 Saturday morning. The other delegations indicated readiness to meet on
                    Saturday morning. Lord <persName corresp="#p_RM1">Reading</persName> stated that
                    there was just one point he would like to make in closing the meeting—the
                    military representatives would be here Monday, and he thought it would be
                    absolutely a tragedy if we did not have something for them to do.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
