<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sixth Plenary Session on Indochina, Geneva, June 9, 3:05 p.m.: The United
                    States Delegation to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d709</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">709</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090020"
                        lcsh-match="exact">National liberation movements</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="709"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d709">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/6–954: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Sixth Plenary Session on Indochina, Geneva, June 9, 3:05 p.m.:
                        The <gloss type="from">United States Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-09">June 9,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 412. Repeated information Paris 409,
                    London 262, Saigon 156, Tokyo 120, Moscow unnumbered. Department pass Defense.
                    Under Secretary’s statement at sixth Indochina plenary Wednesday, June 9:</p>
                <p>“Mr. Chairman, Fellow Delegates, as I listened yesterday to Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>’s statement, and to that of Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName> today, I felt a
                    disappointment—shared, I am sure, by other delegations—at their unconstructive
                    character. I had hoped for some definite response to our efforts toward
                    compromise on basic issues. Since this has not been forthcoming and since we
                    have had only a reiteration of accepted formulas which have been given us on a
                    number of previous occasions, I feel that it is necessary now for me to comment
                    on the charges reiterated on several occasions by Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> and more intemperately repeated by Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> and Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName> of aggressive designs and
                    imperialistic intentions and deliberate deceptions and obstructions on the part
                    of the US and of our friends and allies.</p>
                <p>These charges are part of a familiar pattern. I’m quite sure that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>, and probably Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName>, do not themselves actually believe
                    that they will be taken seriously, except possibly in those countries where the
                    instrumentalities of government are devoted to the suppression of the
                    distribution of accurate and unbiased information.</p>
                <p>I would assume, therefore, that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> was not actually speaking to us, but rather the
                    regimented audience in Europe and <pb facs="1117" n="1091" xml:id="pg_1091"/>
                    Asia which accepts the Cominform line. I believe, therefore, that it is
                    sufficient for me, in reply, to say that the record of my country during and
                    since the second world war is well known to the whole free world. We are quite
                    willing to have our present and our future intentions judged from this record
                    and I am sure that the confidence of our associates will not be diminished, and
                    that of less fortunate people, if they were permitted to examine the record,
                    would be restored.</p>
                <p>We sometimes overlook the fact that we know a great deal, also, about the record
                    of the Soviet Union during this same period and, in judging the present and
                    future intentions of the Communist states and in assessing the validity of their
                    proposals, I suggest we can learn more from reviewing this record than from such
                    statements as those which our Communist colleagues have permitted themselves to
                    make. For example, when Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> and
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou En-lai</persName> speak of the national
                    liberation movements of the peoples of Asia, I am at once moved to recall what
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> and the government he has so
                    long represented have actually done to affect the national aspirations of
                    various smaller nations.</p>
                <p>I would therefore remind you all of the mutual assistance treaties which the
                    Soviet Union made in 1939 with Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania. On October 31,
                    1939, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>, as reported in the
                    Soviet press, said of these treaties that they in no way imply any interference
                    on the part of the Soviet Union in the affairs of Estonia, Latvia or Lithuania …
                    on the contrary all of these pacts of mutual assistance strictly stipulate the
                    inviolability of the sovereignty of the signatory states and the principle of
                    noninterference in each other’s affairs … we stand for the scrupulous and
                    punctilious observance of the pacts on the basis of complete reciprocity, and we
                    declare that all the nonsensical talk about the Sovietization of the Baltic
                    countries is only to the interest of our common enemies and of all anti-Soviet
                    provocateurs.</p>
                <p>The fate which overtook Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania very soon after this
                    verbally admirable statement by our eminent colleague is well known to all of
                    us.</p>
                <p>Have any of my colleagues forgotten the pact between the Soviet Union and Nazi
                    Germany dated August 23, 1939. Probably at one time Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> considered this pact a diplomatic
                    achievement, but I’m sure he must later have shared with the rest of us the
                    bitter conviction that it paved the way first for the Nazi victories of the
                    early years of World War II and then for the Nazi assault on the Soviet Union
                    which cost the grave, long-suffering and wholly admirable Russian people so many
                    millions of lives and such wide-spread destruction.</p>
                <pb facs="1118" n="1092" xml:id="pg_1092"/>
                <p>I have examined this pact and particularly the secret annex thereto, which has
                    since been revealed, and I remain deeply impressed by the following words from
                    the second numbered paragraph of this annex to which Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> appended his signature on August 23,
                    1939.</p>
                <p>They read as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>‘The question of whether the interests of both parties make desirable the
                            maintenance of an independent Polish state and that such state should be
                            bounded can only be definitely determined in the course of further
                            political developments. In any event, both governments will resolve this
                            question by means of friendly agreement.’</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>No attempts to justify this international immorality on the ground of exigencies
                    existing at the time can possibly be acceptable and read in the light of this
                    paragraph, the history of Eastern Europe between 1939 when Poland was destroyed
                    and 1948 when Czechoslovakia lost her proud place as a free nation becomes
                    unmistakably clear. The national aspirations of small, weak countries are to be
                    subject to what is called the ‘interests’ of large aggressive powers with
                    designs of world domination. What took place in Poland, Latvia, Lithuania,
                    Estonia, Hungary, Rumania, Bulgaria, Albania and Czechoslovakia constitutes in
                    each case a chapter in the Soviet record.</p>
                <p>It now begins to appear that one of the next chapters in this record may reveal
                    an intention to subordinate the national aspirations of the people of Indochina
                    to what has been termed the ‘interest of both parties’ as they may be
                    represented by the treaty relationship between the Soviet Union and Communist
                    China.</p>
                <p>I should like at this point to bring to your attention another interesting
                    quotation which will be familiar to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CEL1">Chou
                        En-lai</persName>: ‘Truce is the military counterpart of the political
                    tactic of coalition govt. It is the means to an end, not the ultimate
                    objective’. In the words our colleague, the Foreign Minister of Communist China,
                    gave to the familiar military truce a meaning entirely new in the history of
                    war. That meaning was spelled out in a war of aggression in Korea and the same
                    concept hangs over the battlefields of Indochina and it will be understood that
                    it is for this reason, among others, that the majority of us have insisted on
                    definite understandings regarding some of the vital issues that we are
                    considering in our effort to bring peace in Southeast Asia.</p>
                <p>Our objective and our hope are peace and security. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> himself will recall that at our first
                    formal conference in Moscow in 1946 I stated that the vital question in the mind
                    of the entire free world was, ‘how much further is the Soviet Union going to
                    go’.</p>
                <p>I said also at that time that if the aggressive expansionism, which the Soviet
                    Union had already demonstrated, were to continue, the free <pb facs="1119"
                        n="1093" xml:id="pg_1093"/> world, purely in self-defense, would if
                    necessary draw closer together.</p>
                <p>The repressive effect of Soviet armed might was not so soon felt in South or
                    Southeast Asia as it was in Eastern Europe. Consequently, therefore, we saw,
                    since the end of the last war, the peoples of this area make giant strides in
                    attaining independence and the control of their own destinies. Burma, Ceylon,
                    India, Indonesia, Pakistan, and the Philippines have taken their place in the
                    family of free nations. These developments have been viewed with the greatest
                    satisfaction by the people of my country.</p>
                <p>Cambodia, Laos and Vietnam have more recently joined the other free South and
                    Southeast Asian nations in the achievement of independence, and it is our
                    sincere hope that they will attain peace and security based on a true respect
                    for the national aspirations of their peoples. Those national aspirations should
                    not be subordinated as has occurred in the case of the unfortunate nations
                    mentioned at the beginning of this statement, to the interests of a large
                    aggressive power or powers.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Union today is the great Asian imperial power, holding vast colonial
                    territories in the Caucasus and Central Asia. The solicitude I have heard
                    expressed by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> of the people of
                    Southeast Asia apparently does not extend toward the Armenians, the Kazakhs,
                    Mongols, and I think it might be worth the while of all my colleagues to recall
                    the circumstances under which the former small independent state of Tanatuva
                    disappeared completely from the map.</p>
                <p>I might say also to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Pham Van Dong</persName> that
                    accusations against the use of aggressive intentions and imperialist designs
                    come rather strangely from his lips when we recall that the troops of the Viet
                    Minh have invaded the peaceful countries of Cambodia and Laos, and have spread
                    death and destruction there.</p>
                <p>But, Mr. Chairman, and gentlemen, I intensely dislike these charges and
                    countercharges. I have, so far, refrained from replying myself because of the
                    really serious and important business facing this conference.</p>
                <p>Having now recorded my testimony with regard to the matter of imperialism, I
                    should like to return to consideration of the specific proposals before us. At
                    this moment we are still confronted with three important issues which have been
                    debated at length at a number of meetings and without result. The first of these
                    is, as I and others of my colleagues said yesterday afternoon, the special
                    nature of the problem existing in Laos and Cambodia.</p>
                <p>I believe that both Mr. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> and Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName> unanswerably demonstrated the
                    necessity of separate treatment for those two countries <pb facs="1120" n="1094"
                        xml:id="pg_1094"/> where peace would automatically be restored by the
                    withdrawal of the invading Viet Minh force.</p>
                <p>The second issue is that of the powers of the international supervisory
                    commission for Vietnam. This commission must, obviously have the authority and
                    facilities to settle any problems or differences which cannot be adjusted by the
                    joint commissions of the belligerents, and, logically, therefore, its decisions
                    must be binding on those joint commissions.</p>
                <p>The third vital issue is the composition of the international supervisory
                    commission. As I and others of us said before, a commission containing states
                    unable to meet the test of impartiality e.g. that is, a commission, the
                    counterpart of that set up in Korea, on which Communist state members have been
                    able by veto to prevent effective supervision, is obviously an unsatisfactory
                    and an unacceptable proposal. Yesterday the representative of the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposed the Colombo powers. I welcomed that
                    proposal. This afternoon the representative of Vietnam proposed the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. That would be acceptable.</p>
                <p>Both are reasonable proposals. The proposal of the Soviet Union from my point of
                    view, and I think from that of the majority of my colleagues, is not
                    reasonable.</p>
                <p>I am obliged to state that the Soviet, the Chinese Communists, and the Viet Minh
                    Delegations have, so far, shown no signs of willingness to resolve these issues
                    on any reasonable basis which could be acceptable to this conference, or which
                    would inspire and insure the return of peace to Indochina. I hope that I am
                    wrong, but the negative results of our last meeting seems to support this
                    conclusion.</p>
                <p>I thank you, Mr. Chairman.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
