<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-13T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-13T08:00:00-05:00" n="736" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d736">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/6–1354: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States
                                        Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                        secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-13T14:00:00+01:00">June 13, 1954—2
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_Dulte1">Dulte</gloss> 178. During <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName>’s visit yesterday I read to him
                                suitably expurgated extracts your <gloss target="#t_Tedul1">Tedul</gloss> 185,<note n="1" xml:id="d736fn1">Telegram 1 from
                                    the Secretary of State to the Department of State, June 10,
                                    repeated to Geneva as <gloss target="#t_Tedul1">Tedul</gloss>
                                    185, June 11, <ref target="#pg_1117">p. 1117</ref>.</note>
                                emphasizing particularly the importance of collective action and the
                                time already lost without serious talks. I said this represented the
                                strong view of the President and yourself, and that while I realized
                                sensitive position of Britain re own public opinion India and Burma,
                                et cetera, I was sure that in this matter we had been right from
                                beginning. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> repeated that
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CSWLS1">Churchill</persName> “would not
                                send troops to Vietnam”. I said that if French could hold
                                Hanoi-Haiphong area, or Haiphong and an enclave along coast, we
                                should decide where to draw line on which we take our stand in south
                                of Vietnam and elsewhere in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>. If
                                the military talks in Washington were making any progress they
                                should at least have the alternatives ready for consideration and
                                decision at the time of the <gloss target="#t_PM1">PM</gloss>s
                                visit.</p>
                            <p>I then spoke of the political and psychological factors re withdrawal
                                part of <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> forces from Korea and
                                critical nature of period after Geneva. <persName corresp="#p_EA1">Eden</persName> said there was nothing imminent on this and
                                they intended to leave it for discussion in Washington.</p>
                            <p>New subject. I have just had long talk with <persName corresp="#p_CRG1">Casey</persName> and conveyed message your
                                    <gloss target="#t_Tosec1">Tosec</gloss> 406.<note n="2" xml:id="d736fn2">Dated June 12, <ref target="#pg_1125">p.
                                        1125</ref>.</note> He plans to return via Washington and
                                will let you know. He is convinced of necessity of collective
                                guarantees on Cambodia, Laos, and what can be saved of Vietnam. Also
                                convinced that there must be, as he put it “teeth in those”
                                guarantees. He had expressed these views strongly to <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName>, saying that he hoped that
                                same group Asiatic and European nations that gave the guarantees
                                would provide the teeth, and that India and Pakistan would associate
                                themselves with such a group. <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName> did not reject this, and had apparently
                                discussed it later and at length with <persName corresp="#p_PNR1">Pillai</persName> and Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_PMSVL1">Pandit</persName>, who were present at dinner that evening
                                where discussion continued. <persName corresp="#p_CRG1">Casey</persName> felt that when he left, <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName> was favorable, but that the
                                influence of <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>, with
                                whom he talked last night, would continue to be bad.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SWB1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>