<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-26T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-26T11:00:00-05:00" n="830" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d830">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/6–2654: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States
                                        Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-26T17:00:00+01:00">June 26, 1954—5
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 534. Department pass Saigon
                                if desired; repeated information Paris 511. Following is Ambassador
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HDR1">Heath</persName>‘s account of his
                                farewell call on <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName>
                                today: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“<persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> asked me to
                                        say in Washington that from his own recent consultations
                                        with <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes-France</persName>,
                                        he was certain that it was not the latter’s intention to
                                        ‘evacuate’ Indochina but to make a viable settlement which
                                        France would support. While <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> had not definitely accepted the idea of
                                        the Haiphong enclave and some sort of protective <pb facs="1279" n="1253" xml:id="pg_1253"/> arrangement over
                                        the bishoprics of Phat Diem and Bui Chu, he had expressed no
                                        hostility to the idea nor had he suggested any counter
                                        territorial concession for the Viet Minh in the south. With
                                        a foot-hold in the north and holding the south and part of
                                        the center, the Vietnamese would have the foundation on
                                        which to build a solid durable state with the possibility of
                                        regaining complete control of national territory from Viet
                                        Minh provided it developed the necessary political dynamism
                                        and capacity. The latter was the great question mark.
                                        Certainly the regime had so far failed to show energetic
                                        capacity and it was the general impression in Paris that
                                            <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Ngo Dinh Diem</persName> did
                                        not have the necessary qualities to unite his country. The
                                        latter’s speech on arrival in Saigon had not impressed the
                                        French Government.</p>
                                    <p>“It would be the task of France cooperatively aided by the
                                        United States to try to build a solid state structure in the
                                        new Vietnam. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName>
                                        went on to say that he had not been favorably impressed by
                                        the Ministry of Associated States and did not think its
                                        personnel had the necessary drive and imagination to
                                        undertake successfully such a task. In any case it would be
                                        a mistake to send an ex-colonial official to Vietnam.
                                            <persName corresp="#p_LCG1">La Chambre</persName>, the
                                        new Minister of Associated States, seemed to be a very good
                                        and intelligent chap but entirely new to the problem.</p>
                                    <p>“<persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> thought it was
                                        of the utmost importance that <persName corresp="#p_EPG1">Ely</persName> be seconded immediately by an
                                        outstanding diplomatic counselor. He had urged on <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes-France</persName> and hoped I
                                        would urge on <persName corresp="#p_LCG1">La
                                            Chambre</persName>, if I saw him, the advantage of
                                        sending <persName>Georges-Picot</persName>, now at <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, at once to Indochina. The
                                        latter knew Indochina and was excellent at dealing with
                                        Asiatic peoples. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName>‘s other candidate for the job,
                                        Baudet, former French Ambassador to Yugoslavia, was no
                                        longer available since <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Mendes-France</persName> had taken him to be his
                                        Director of Cabinet. When I told <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> that I expected to see <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> before leaving for
                                        Washington, he shrugged his shoulders over the political
                                        shortcomings of His Majesty but made no suggestions as to
                                        what might be said to the latter. He said he would
                                        appreciate, however, if I would pass on anything important
                                            <persName corresp="#p_BD1">Bao Dai</persName> said to me
                                        through <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> in
                                        Paris.</p>
                                    <p>“<persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> said it was
                                        altogether possible in eight or ten days that, in their
                                        secret talks, the French would arrive at tentative agreement
                                        with the Viet Minh. He hoped that this agreement would be
                                        one that the United States might accept. It would be,
                                        however, difficult to sell to the Vietnamese who might
                                        unrealistically and irresponsibly oppose it. He had hoped
                                        that I would stay on at Geneva to help explain to the
                                        Associated States delegations, if a reasonable solution were
                                        found, that they should accept it and go on from there to
                                        build up their national strength. I made no comment on this
                                        or his other statements beyond observing that from my
                                        acquaintance the situation, the military position of France
                                        in Indochina was not as weak as was thought in many
                                        quarters.</p>
                                    <p>“<persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> said he
                                        regretted that the new government was opposed to <persName corresp="#p_DM1">DeJean</persName> coming to Geneva as
                                        advisor which <persName corresp="#p_BG1">Bidault</persName>
                                        had opposed, except possibly towards the end of the
                                        conference.”</p></quote></p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JUA1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>