<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Nineteenth Restricted Session on Indochina, Geneva, June 29, 1954, 3 p.m.:
                    The United States Delegation to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d839</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">839</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-06-28T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-06-28T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-28T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-28T18:00:00-05:00" n="839"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d839">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/6–2954: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Nineteenth Restricted Session on Indochina, Geneva, June 29,
                        1954, 3 p.m.: The <gloss type="from">United States Delegation</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d839fn1">A set of minutes of this session (<gloss
                            target="#t_IC1">IC</gloss> Restricted/19) are in Conference files, lot
                        60 D 627, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 279. The minutes indicate that
                        the session convened at 3 p.m. and adjourned at 5:45 p.m. The minutes are
                        also printed in <hi rend="italic">Conférence de Genève</hi>, pp.
                        347–355.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-29T00:00:00+01:00"
                            >June 29, 1954—midnight</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 545. Repeated information Paris 520,
                    London 334, Saigon 227, Tokyo 164, Moscow 151, Vientiane, Phnom Penh unnumbered.
                    Tokyo for <gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss>. Department pass Defense.
                    Nineteenth Indochina Restricted Session Tuesday, June 29, with <persName
                        corresp="#p_KVV1">Kuznetsov</persName> in Chair.</p>
                <p>Qam [<persName corresp="#p_PVD1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pham</hi>
                    </persName>] <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Van Dong</persName> (Viet Minh) opened
                    with reference Soviet suggestion first meeting that after certain agreement on
                    principles armistice control question could be referred to committee. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> then, without contributing any new ideas,
                    proceeding to comparison Soviet June 14 proposal and French (<persName
                        corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName>) statement June 25 to show wide area
                    agreement. He stated “object” of control was terms armistice agreement. Noted
                    that military talks making progress but political questions barely started;
                    although he did not pursue this question he seemed to indicate necessity
                    embodying political terms in agreement.</p>
                <p>Basing claims on French statements of June 2 and June 25 and Soviet June 14
                    proposal; <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> concluded no disagreement
                    in principle on: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Regroupment,</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Establishment demarcation lines,</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Establishment demilitarized zones,</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Liberation prisoners and civil internees, and</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>Prohibition on introduction arms and troops after armistice.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> noted detail of Soviet proposal and
                    stated it was good basis for discussion, although certain precisions and
                    additions necessary. For <pb facs="1288" n="1262" xml:id="pg_1262"/> example,
                    question of duration of control not yet considered. Certain aspects such as
                    regroupment of forces and exchange of prisoners would require control only until
                    accomplishment, but with other aspects, such as prohibition of introduction of
                    arms, control would not terminate automatically. How long this control to be
                    maintained, for example, until final peace treaty or new agreement, should be
                    considered.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> described guiding principles of
                    control as efficiency and impartiality but there were other aspects. Communist
                    delegates had stressed necessity for respecting sovereignty of three states.
                    This question most important in connection control. Efficiency of control
                    mechanism must not impair sovereignty of states or rights of people. Control
                    bodies with compulsory authority might become foreign administrations detracting
                    from this sovereignty.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> again referred indivisibility of
                    peace in Indochina. This must apply to control of armistice since violation in
                    one state could seriously affect other two.</p>
                <p>On question organization of control, <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName>
                    claimed following areas agreement Soviet and French proposals: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <p>All recognized necessity joint and international commissions
                                operating parallel manner and in different fields. Although
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> statement June 25
                                and Soviet proposal close, agreement still remains on functions and
                                relationship. Basically, responsibility of carrying out agreement up
                                to both sides, this must be recognized. Sides will settle
                                differences between themselves. Therefore, joint committees should
                                be responsible for control and implementation. In case of
                                differences would refer problem to international commission but this
                                unlikely since both sides have equal interest in success of
                                agreement.</p>
                            <p>Functions of international commission on other hand would comprise
                                supervision and particularly of non-introduction [of new troops and
                                equipment into Indochina, to]<note n="2" xml:id="d839fn2">These and
                                    following words in brackets supplied from the verbatim record of
                                    the Nineteenth Restricted Session.</note> note violations and
                                communicate to both sides, and to make suggestions to amendments to
                                agreement.</p>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Between joint and international commissions, <persName
                                corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> stated, no question of
                            subordination, rather coordination and different tasks. He noted Soviet
                            proposal this effect and <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName>
                            statement June 25 that commissions would begin “juxtaposition”.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>On question of unanimous or majority decisions by international
                            commission, he reiterated Communist insistence that decisions not be of
                            unilateral (i.e, majority) character. He again quoted <persName
                                corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> statement June 25 to show that
                            in serious cases international commission might submit majority and
                            minority reports to guarantor states but they would not have force of
                            unanimous reports.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>With reference control for Cambodia [and Laos] he noted all agreed
                            necessary. Reserved position on Cambodian proposal for separate
                            commissions for each of three states. He thought <persName
                                corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName>‘s suggestion three control
                            bodies with additional coordinating body not too far from Communist
                            position.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1289" n="1263" xml:id="pg_1263"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> finally stated belief conference now
                    has basic factors with which to reach agreement in principle on control, and
                    questions could now be referred to committee as proposed by Soviet delegate.</p>
                <p>US delegate then made statement <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 542.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d839fn3">
                        <ref target="#d840">
                            <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> followed with preliminary comment
                    on <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName>‘s statement. He asked for copy
                    for more thorough study and noted several problems or deficiencies in <persName
                        corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName>‘s speech: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>To avoid confusion, term “control” should probably not be used with
                            reference to the joint commission but rather terms such as “execution”
                            and “implementation”. “Control” is more relevant to international
                            aspects of problem.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName>‘s analysis omitted reference
                            to mediation or arbitration by international control body. Even though
                            that body may have only few occasions to act, it must have power to make
                            compulsory recommendations.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_PVD1">Dong</persName> said that control machinery
                            must respect national sovereignty. This is very well in normal peace
                            time but we are dealing with abnormal situation.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Concerning <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Johnson</persName>‘s statement on Korean
                    experience, <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> agreed conference must
                    benefit by this and other experience, but observed all experiences not
                    absolutely comparable. <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> then made
                    somewhat cryptic remark about guarantees of settlement, saying this is
                    complicated problem on which some data may still be lacking. He suggested this
                    problem might well be reserved for return of heads of delegations.</p>
                <p>In closing, <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Chauvel</persName> remarked French
                    delegation now engaged on work on entire control question and welcomes
                    suggestions from other delegates.</p>
                <p>After recess, Cambodian delegate, <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam Sary</persName>,
                    spoke briefly. He endorsed French proposal for establishment of committee of
                    experts and agreed with Soviet recommendation that conference provide experts
                    with a list of questions. He saw no need, however, for more restricted
                    conference sessions to formulate such questions, as Soviets had proposed.</p>
                <p>Cambodian delegate then made following points concerning supervision of
                    armistice: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Each Indochinese state should have separate international control
                            commission. He agreed with French suggestion that coordination between
                            three commissions could be achieved by special body, but hoped that such
                            body would act solely in liaison capacity and have no authority over
                            country commissions. Liaison body could, he suggested, work through
                            secretariats of three country commissions.</item>
                        <pb facs="1290" n="1264" xml:id="pg_1264"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>In Cambodia, joint commission representing belligerent sides would be
                            needed only for a short period of withdrawal of foreign troops.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>International control commission should be set up under aegis of
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and composed of really neutral
                            states. It is hard for Cambodia to believe Poland and Czechoslovakia
                            [are neutral], since they have [recognized] <gloss target="#t_DRV1"
                                >DRV</gloss> and not Cambodia.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Conference agreed next restricted session would be July 2.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
