<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Delegation to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d972</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">972</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-18T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-18T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-18T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-18T17:00:00-05:00" n="972"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d972">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/7–1854: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">United States Delegation</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d972fn1">Message transmitted in two sections.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret<lb/>priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-18T23:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 18, 1954—11 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 657. Repeated information Paris 97,
                    Saigon 66. Department pass Defense. Following is translation (done by British)
                    of text working paper on control in Vietnam prepared by Soviet delegation. Paper
                    dated July 9 although only received today. Soviet paper follows closely French
                    paper July 7 (<gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 575, repeated Paris 25,
                    Saigon 17<note n="2" xml:id="d972fn2">Dated July 8, <ref target="#pg_1305">p.
                            1305</ref>.</note>). Most important changes from French text appear in
                    paragraph three of numbered paragraph eight, numbered paragraph nine (<hi
                        rend="italic">d</hi>), numbered paragraphs 15 and 18.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <list>
                        <item>“1. The responsibility for implementing the agreement on the cessation
                            of hostilities is placed on the parties.</item>
                        <pb facs="1468" n="1442" xml:id="pg_1442"/>
                        <item>“2. Control and supervision over this implementation is ensured by the
                            international commission.</item>
                        <item>“3. In order to facilitate, under conditions shown below, the
                            implementation of provisions concerning joint actions by the two parties
                            a joint commission will be set up in Vietnam.</item>
                        <item>“4. The joint commission is composed of an equal number of
                            representatives of the commands of the two parties.</item>
                        <item>“5. The presidents of the delegations of the joint commission will
                            hold the rank of general. The joint commission will set up joint roups,
                            the number of which will be determined by mutual agreement between the
                            parties. The joint groups will be composed of an equal number of
                            officers from both parties. Their activity on the demarcation lines
                            between the zones of regroupment will be determined by the parties
                            whilst taking into account the powers of the joint commission.</item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“6. The joint commission will ensure the implementation of the
                                following provisions of the agreement on the cessation of
                                hostilities: <list>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>A simultaneous and general cease-fire in Vietnam for all
                                        regular and irregular armed forces of the two
                                        parties.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>A regroupment of the armed forces of the two
                                        parties.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Observance of the demarcation lines between the zones of
                                        regroupment and the demilitarized sectors.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>It will help the parties to implement the said provisions, will
                                ensure liaison between them for the purpose of the working out and
                                putting into effect of plans for the application of these
                                provisions, and it will endeavor to solve controversial questions
                                which may arise between the parties during the implementation of
                                these provisions.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“7. An international commission will be set up for control and
                                supervision over the application of the provisions of the agreement
                                on the cessation of hostilities in Indochina. It will be composed of
                                an equal number of representatives of the following states:
                                (blank)</p>
                            <p>It will be read by the chairman (blank)</p>
                            <p>Its location will be (blank)</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“8. The international commission will set up permanent and mobile
                                inspection brigades, composed of an equal number of officers
                                appointed by each of the above-mentioned states. The permanent
                                brigades will be located at the following points (blank). These
                                points of location may, at a later date, be altered at the request
                                of the joint commission, or of one of the parties, or of the
                                international commission itself by agreement between the
                                international commission and the command of the party concerned.</p>
                            <p>The field of action of the mobile brigades will be the dimilitarized
                                zones. Within the limits of these zones they will have the right to
                                move freely and to receive from the local civil and military
                                authorities all facilities they may be in need of for the
                                fulfillment of their tasks (supply of personnel, placing at their
                                disposal documents necessary for control, summoning witnesses
                                necessary for investigation, ensuring the security and freedom of
                                movement of the inspection brigades, etc.…) they will have at their
                                disposal the necessary modern means of transport, supervision and
                                communication. Outside the zones and points of activity shown above,
                                the mobile brigades may, by agreement with the command of the party
                                concerned, make trips within the limits of the tasks given them by
                                the present agreement.</p>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="1469" n="1443" xml:id="pg_1443"/>
                        <item>“9. The task of supervising the implementation by the parties of the
                            provisions of the agreement will be placed on the international
                            commission. For this purpose it will fulfill the tasks of control,
                            supervision, inspection and investigation connected with the application
                            of the provisions of the agreement on the cessation of hostilities,
                            namely, it must, <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Control the movement of the armed forces of the two parties,
                                    effected within the framework of the regroupment plan.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Supervise the demarcation lines between the zones of
                                    regroupment, and also the demilitarized zones.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Control the operations of releasing prisoners of war and
                                    civilian internees.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>To watch over the implementation of the provisions of the
                                    agreement on the cessation of hostilities, concerning the ban on
                                    the introduction into the country from abroad, of armed forces,
                                    military personnel and of all kinds of arms, ammunition,
                                    military equipment, in the zones and points shown in Article
                                    8.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>“10. The international commission shall, through the medium of the
                            mobile brigades mentioned above, and as soon as possible, either at its
                            own initiative, or at the request of the joint commission, or of one of
                            the parties, have recourse to necessary investigations by documents and
                            on the spot.</item>
                        <item>“11. The inspection brigades will submit to the international
                            committee the results of their control, their investigation and their
                            observations, furthermore they will draw up special reports which they
                            may consider necessary or which may be requested from them by the
                            commission. In the case of a disagreement within the brigades, the
                            conclusions of each member will be submitted to the commission.</item>
                        <item>“12. If any one inspection brigade is unable to settle an incident or
                            considers that there is a violation or a threat of a serious violation
                            the international commission will be informed; the latter will study the
                            reports and the conclusions of the inspection brigades and will inform
                            the parties of the measures which should be taken for the settlement of
                            the incidents, ending of the violations or doing away with the threat of
                            violation.</item>
                        <item>“13. When the joint commission is unable to reach an agreement on the
                            interpretation to be given to some provision or on the appraisal of a
                            fact, the international commission will study the controversial
                            question. Its conclusions will be sent directly to the parties and will
                            be notified to the joint commission.</item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“14. Recommendations will be adopted or passed by the international
                                commission by majority vote, reservation being made for the
                                provisions contained in Article 15. If there is a split of votes the
                                chairman’s vote will be decisive.</p>
                            <p>The international commission may pass recommendations concerning
                                amendments and additions which it may be necessary to make to the
                                provisions of the agreement on the cessation of hostilities in
                                Vietnam, in order to ensure a more effective implementation of that
                                agreement. These recommendations will be adopted unanimously.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“15. When dealing with questions concerning violations of the <pb
                                    facs="1470" n="1444" xml:id="pg_1444"/> agreement, or threats of
                                violations, which might lead to a resumption of hostilities, namely: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Refusal by the armed forces of one party to effect the
                                        movements provided for in the regroupment plan;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>Violation by the armed forces of one of the parties of the
                                        regroupment zones, territorial waters, or air space of the
                                        other party;</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>The decisions of the international commission must be unanimous.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>“16. If one of the parties refuses to put into effect a recommendation
                            passed by the international commission, the commission or one of the
                            parties address themselves to the guarantors. If the international
                            commission does not reach unanimity in the cases provided for in Article
                            15, it will submit a majority report and one or more minority reports to
                            the guarantors. The international commission will address itself to the
                            guarantors in all cases where its activity is being hindered.</item>
                        <item>“17. The international control commission will be set up at the time
                            of the cessation of hostilities in Indochina in order that it should be
                            able to fulfill the tasks provided for in Article 9.</item>
                        <item>“18. The international commission for control and supervision in
                            Vietnam will act in close connection with the international control
                            commissions in Cambodia and Laos. A body for coordinating the activities
                            of the three commissions will be set up by agreement among them, in the
                            form of a coordination international commission for control and
                            supervision in Indochina.</item>
                        <item>“19. The coordination international commission for control and
                            supervision in Indochina will adopt decisions concerning a progressive
                            decrease in the activities of the international commissions for control
                            and supervision in Laos and Cambodia, taking into account the evolution
                            in Vietnam. These decisions will be adopted unanimously.”</item>
                    </list>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
