<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-05-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="312" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">824.00/908</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Messrs. <persName type="from">George S.
                                    Knight</persName> and <persName>Richard W. Flournoy</persName>,
                                of the Office of the Legal Adviser, to the Legal Adviser</hi>
                                (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Hackworth</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-05-03">May 3, 1939</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Hackworth</hi>: It is gathered from the
                            memorandum of April 29, 1939,<note n="3" xml:id="d312fn3">Not
                                printed.</note> prepared in KA,<note n="4" xml:id="d312fn4">Division
                                of the American Republics.</note> that Señor Busch still bears the
                            title of President of Bolivia. Also, it is noted that President Busch’s
                            Cabinet remains unchanged. Apparently the main change in the Bolivian
                            form of government is that President Busch has assumed “complete power
                            in the state” and has dissolved the Bolivian Congress. That is to say,
                            President Busch is still the head of the Bolivian Government but has
                            taken to himself more extensive governmental power than he had
                            formerly.</p>
                        <p>In the somewhat analogous case which recently arose in Brazil,<note n="5" xml:id="d312fn5">See <ref target="frus1937v05#pg_312">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1937, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 312</ref> ff.</note> President
                            Vargas, before his term of office expired, abrogated the Brazilian
                            Constitution and proclaimed a new Constitution by which he was to
                            continue in office subject to a plebiscite at some undetermined date. In
                            your memorandum of January 7, 1938,<note n="6" xml:id="d312fn6">
                                <ref target="frus1937v05#pg_315">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 315</ref>.</note> you said:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“As I understand the situation with respect to political changes
                                    that have taken place in Brazil, no occasion arises for
                                    extending recognition to the present government. It seems to me
                                    that the question whether the abrogation of the former
                                    Constitution and the promulgation of a new one, and the
                                    continuance of President Vargas in <pb facs="0314" n="306" xml:id="pg_306"/> office under the new Constitution have
                                    been brought about by appropriate processes is a matter
                                    primarily for consideration by that country and its people. The
                                    situation is not analogous to that presented where the
                                    recognized government has been ousted by a <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> or revolution and a new régime set up
                                    contrary to constitutional methods.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>In a memorandum prepared by you on January 11, 1938,<note n="7" xml:id="d312fn7">
                                <ref target="frus1937v05#pg_316">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1937, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 316</ref>.</note> it was
                            concluded that: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <list>
                                    <item>“1. Where a new régime is established through a <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi> or revolution, some form
                                        of recognition is necessary. It may, of course, take the
                                        form of our treating with the government in the regular way
                                        or some more formal act.</item>
                                    <item>“2. A formal act of recognition is not required where the
                                        existing government has executed a <hi rend="italic">coup
                                            d’état</hi> displacing the Constitution by a new one or
                                        setting it aside. If that government has already been
                                        recognized by us it will continue to be so recognized by the
                                        mere continuance of our relations with it.”</item>
                                </list>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>From the facts of the Bolivian case, as heretofore presented, there would
                            apparently be no cause for this Government to go through any formal act
                            of recognition. As in the Brazilian case, the continuance of our
                            relations with the Bolivian Government will, it is believed, amount to a
                            continuance of recognition of the present régime in Bolivia. The terms
                            “recognize” and “recognition” are used in two senses with regard to
                            foreign governments: (1) with reference to an act or declaration
                            indicating an intention to deal with a completely new régime as the
                            government of a state, and (2) an act or series of acts indicating an
                            intention to continue to deal with a government already recognized.
                            While considerable changes in the Government of Bolivia were recently
                            made by President Busch, it seems reasonable to hold that the Government
                            now in control is a continuation of the Government which was carried on
                            under him before the <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi>, especially in
                            view of the fact that his cabinet has not been changed.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>