<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of the American
                    Republics ( (Duggan))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d327</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">327</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-08-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recQZssarRbcJz7o2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil company</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-08-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-08-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="327"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d327">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">824.51/950</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        the American Republics</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Duggan</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-08-07">August 7,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Bolivian Minister<note n="14" xml:id="d327fn14">Luis Fernando
                        Guachalla.</note> stated that his Government desired to enter into
                    discussions to secure a credit from this Government. In response to my inquiries
                    as to additional details concerning the desire of the Bolivian Government, the
                    Minister was unable to furnish further information. I informed the Minister,
                    first, that it would be necessary for the Bolivian Government to present
                    concrete proposals to this Government for its consideration, and secondly, that
                    it appeared to me very doubtful whether this Government would wish to extend
                    credits to the Bolivian Government until that Government had taken steps to
                    clear up certain well known differences with American citizens.</p>
                <p>The Minister stated that he agreed that it would probably be difficult, if not
                    impossible, for this Government to move in the credit matter until the
                    differences were straightened out. In this connection he inquired whether, as a
                    result of further discussions between the Department and the Standard Oil
                    Company, he could expect to receive in the near future a new draft of the
                    proposed settlement.<note n="15" xml:id="d327fn15">See <ref target="#pg_322">pp.
                            322</ref> ff.</note> I informed the Minister that I had not had an
                    opportunity to acquaint myself with the status of the negotiations concerning
                    the Standard Oil dispute since my return, but that I would do so and inform him
                    next Monday when he returned to town.</p>
                <p>The Minister informed me that he would request further information from his
                    Government as to its interests in a fcredit and what the credit would be used
                    for if granted, et cetera.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
