<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. H. Gerald Smith of the Division of Trade
                    Agreements</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d458</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">458</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-12-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-12-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="458"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d458">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.2531/605</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. H. Gerald Smith of the
                        Division of Trade Agreements</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-12-09">December 9,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Assistant Secretary Grady</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Señor Guillermo Gazitúa, Counselor, Chilean
                            Embassy</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Smith</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Señor Gazitúa called on the Assistant Secretary by appointment, to receive the
                    proposals on Schedules I and II which had been formulated by this Government for
                    the proposed trade agreement between the United States and Chile.</p>
                <p>In giving the proposals to Señor Gazitúa, Mr. Grady noted that copper had not
                    been included in Schedule II for the principal reason that the trade-agreements
                    organization, after a very thorough study of the subject, had come to the
                    conclusion that a reduction in the import tax to the extent permitted in a trade
                    agreement would be of little value to the Chilean Government. Señor Gazitúa
                    admitted that his Government had not, in the original stages of the
                    conversations, placed particular emphasis on copper, but stated that in view of
                    the extreme opposition which had developed in the United States against any
                    concession on copper and the considerable comment which had appeared in the
                    Chilean press, his Government might feel it necessary to explain why that item
                    would not appear in the proposed trade agreement. <pb facs="0439" n="431"
                        xml:id="pg_431"/> Mr. Grady suggested that we might be able to supply Señor
                    Gazitúa with some information for such an explanation.</p>
                <p>Señor Gazitúa noted particularly the absence of dried beans and onions from the
                    list of products on which the United States was prepared to offer concessions
                    and stated that he believed his Government would find it extremely difficult to
                    conclude an agreement which did not contain concessions on those products. Señor
                    Gazitúa was assured that onions and beans had been the subject of thorough
                    investigation by the trade-agreements organization and it was finally concluded
                    that, in view of the existing domestic situation of crop surpluses and purchases
                    by the Federal Surplus Commodity Corporation of excess stocks, no concessions
                    could be offered.</p>
                <p>Upon leaving Mr. Grady’s office the conversation was continued in the Trade
                    Agreements Division and Señor Gazitúa was supplied with statistical information
                    on those products appearing in the published list of October 2 which had not
                    been included among those on which concessions had been offered by the United
                    States. Señor Gazitúa stated that he would transmit the proposals to his
                    Government by airmail on December 11 and he was informed that, in accordance
                    with a previous oral understanding, the lists of concessions offered and
                    requested by this Government were being sent to our Embassy in Santiago for
                    expeditious presentation to the Chilean Government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
