<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in Chile ( (Frost))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d474</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">474</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-08-26T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-08-26T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recAHt1IiF33Lofk6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Development program</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-08-26T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-08-26T16:00:00-05:00" n="474"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d474">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">825.51/1136: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Frost</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-08-26T17:00:00-04:00"
                            >August 26, 1939—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>108. Your 127, August 24, 1 p.m. As you are aware the activities of the
                    Export-Import Bank are severely restricted as a result of the failure of the
                    House of Representatives to consider a bill including a provision which would
                    have increased the lending power of the Bank. Nevertheless, the Export-Import
                    Bank has indicated that it is prepared to consider the extension of credits of
                    up to $5,000,000 to facilitate exports during the next 6 months of American
                    equipment urgently required by the Chilean development program. Under the
                    present circumstances the Export-Import Bank is not in a position to undertake
                    any commitments beyond this amount, but it would, of course, consider further
                    credits if its lending functions were increased at some subsequent date.</p>
                <p>The operation would take the form of facilitating the financing of specific
                    exports by American concerns, and would in no sense be a “direct” credit which
                    would place freely disposable funds in the hands of the Chilean authorities.
                    There would be no objection to sales of American products to the Corporation of
                    Fomento, but it would be assumed that this was a governmental agency. The
                    mechanism would probably be a discounting by the Export-Import Bank, with or
                    without partial or full recourse, of notes received by American exporters from
                    the Chilean purchaser. It is assumed that provision would be made for amortizing
                    the notes out of the proceeds of the new copper and other revenues.</p>
                <p>It will be necessary for this Government to have full information as to what
                    materials and equipment would be included in the $5,000,000 amount, and the
                    relation of these specific requests to the whole Chilean development program. It
                    is assumed that first purchases will be for the most urgent purposes.</p>
                <p>The rate of interest on such credits of 8 years is a matter for discussion with
                    the Chilean authorities. The rate of interest for similar arrangements with
                    other countries has been set at 5 percent. There is at present some discussion
                    of moderate reduction in this rate, but a rate of three percent appears to be
                    out of the question.</p>
                <p>Regarding your inquiry concerning a visit by the Minister of Finance to
                    Washington, this Government has already invited Wachholtz to come to this
                    country, and will be pleased to receive him.</p>
                <pb facs="0459" n="451" xml:id="pg_451"/>
                <p>Extensive informal preliminary discussions regarding a trade agreement are taking
                    place between members of the Department and the Chilean Counselor of Embassy.
                    Information regarding this phase of possible discussions with the Minister of
                    Finance will be made available to you shortly.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
