<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-07-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="499" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d499">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">821.51/2349</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Colombia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Braden</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 222</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bogota</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-07-18">July 18,
                                1939</date>.<lb/>[Received July 21.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the
                            Department’s telegram No. 66 of July 15, 5 p.m. and to report that
                            pursuant to my request the Minister of Finance, Dr. Lleras Restrepo,
                            received me yesterday afternoon and read to me a cable he had just had
                            from the Colombian Ambassador in Washington.</p>
                        <pb facs="0497" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/>
                        <p>This message, although somewhat longer, approximated the information
                            contained in the Department’s telegram under reference, except that the
                            Ambassador interpreted Mr. White’s refusal to recommend the Colombian
                            proposal to the Council’s Executive Committeee as a definite rejection
                            thereof. He added that Mr. Laylin,<note n="24" xml:id="d499fn24">John G.
                                Laylin, Washington attorney, acting as counsel to the Colombian
                                Ambassador.</note> who also was present at the meeting, inquired
                            whether Mr. White would recommend a settlement on a 3½ percent basis.
                            Mr. White said he would not and that moreover he objected to further
                            questioning along this line since it would commit him—something he could
                            not accept since he was acting without authority from the bondholders.
                            The Ambassador quoted Mr. White as declaring that the Colombian offer
                            was incommensurate with present capacity to pay and still more with
                            future prospects. In this latter connection, he had particularly
                            stressed the development by American capital of the petroleum industry
                            in Colombia. Mr. Laylin’s inquiry regarding 3½ percent is, of course,
                            significant.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Lleras said that he had been so discouraged by the Ambassador’s
                            telegram as almost to reply that nothing else remained to be done with
                            the Council and that the Colombian Government would seek other methods,
                            than through that organization, of dealing with the bondholders.
                            However, just then he received my request for an interview and he hoped
                            I would have some more encouraging information.</p>
                        <p>The Minister said Mr. White’s rejection of the Colombian offer made it
                            impossible for the Government to make another, i. e., presumably through
                            the Foreign Bondholders Protective Council. Also it prevented his
                            including any item for debt service in the budget since it would become
                            generally known that the Colombian offer had been rejected. When I
                            doubted this, he insisted that everything was known in Bogota within
                            twenty-four hours, which, I must say, is largely true. He frankly
                            expressed his discouragement because it was evidently impossible by the
                            present method of negotiation to reach a conclusion since Mr. White
                            “assumed the dual role of negotiator and non-negotiator, that is, he
                            took all of the advantages of a negotiator but none of the obligations,
                            which placed the Government at a serious disadvantage—it was futile to
                            continue discussions with White”. I indicated that Mr. White had not
                            “rejected” but merely “refused to approve”. But the Minister insisted
                            another offer could not be made.</p>
                        <p>In reply to my question, Dr. Lleras stated that Mr. White’s suggestion to
                            make the offer a temporary one for one year was utterly unacceptable.
                            Also he had requested Ambassador López and his financial advisers to
                            submit a plan looking to the refunding of Colombia’s <pb facs="0498" n="490" xml:id="pg_490"/> internal issues. This they had done but
                            the Minister was now satisfied that the thought of refunding internal
                            issues should be abandoned.</p>
                        <p>The Minister asked what information I had. I replied that unfortunately
                            it was similar but even more brief than his, although I was encouraged
                            by one factor: I understood Mr. White was disposed perhaps to consider
                            the possibility of making increases in debt service contingent on
                            increases in the Colombian budget. I added that since the Minister
                            thought it unwise to follow my suggestion (see Section 7, Page 5, of my
                            despatch No. 206 of July 13, 1939) of an X percentage of the budget
                            being assigned to debt service, he might do so with an X percentage of
                            revenues (both royalties and taxes) received from the petroleum
                            industry. I pointed out that, while large sums were being spent on
                            exploration, there was as yet no guarantee that these operations would
                            be successful nor that Colombia would receive any substantial additional
                            income from this source. Nevertheless it was a possibility with which
                            Mr. White was impressed, according to the Ambassador’s cable, and by
                            such an arrangement the bondholders would receive a speculative fillip
                            which might compensate thtoi for a somewhat lower return than otherwise
                            they would be willing to accept, also it would answer Mr. White’s
                            arguments respecting Colombia’s ability to augment future payments. The
                            Minister estimated that approximately 12 to 14 percent of the revenues
                            presently received from the oil industry are equivalent to 1 percent on
                            the debt service. He calculated that the earmarking of 15 percent of oil
                            revenues to debt service might in a few years give the bondholders a
                            substantial increase in interest but felt in any case they should be
                            limited to the 4½ percent rate received by the holders of Uruguayan
                            securities. I replied that I could not discuss the details of such a
                            plan and had merely stated my personal opinion as favoring it in
                            principle. But he should bear in mind that the Uruguayan bondowners were
                            assured of a minimum of 4½ percent and moreover had received interest at
                            that rate for some time past; therefore, I felt if the Colombian
                            bondholders were to be asked to take any less, they should be
                            compensated by the possibility of receiving a higher rate if the oil
                            industry developed as we all hoped it would. Also I could not believe he
                            would encounter much opposition in Congress on such a plan because in
                            the final analysis Colombia would benefit even more than the bondholders
                            from the development of the petroleum industry since, aside from local
                            wages and purchases, if his figure were taken, 85 percent of the
                            additional government income would be retained here. Dr. Lleras was
                            receptive to this idea, which may therefore be pursued to advantage by
                            Mr. White.</p>
                        <p>Dr. Lleras went on to say that by law he was obliged to submit the budget
                            to Congress within ten days from its opening. He was now <pb facs="0499" n="491" xml:id="pg_491"/> estopped, as described above, from
                            including an item for foreign debt service and if it were not in the
                            budget it would be extremely difficult later to reopen the budget in
                            order to insert a special appropriation.</p>
                        <p>I observed that, according to his statements and excepting for the
                            possibility of an X percentage of petroleum revenues being assigned to
                            the debt service, apparently an impasse had been reached. This gravely
                            concerned me as being highly unfortunate both for Colombian good name
                            and credit and for the bondholders. Therefore, pursuant to his
                            suggestion of last week that imagination be used, I begged him to put on
                            his thinking cap and exercise the maximum of imagination to resolve the
                            impasse.</p>
                        <p>The Minister replied that in the final analysis Mr. White would be in
                            none too good a position when it became known to the bondholders that he
                            had rejected a Colombian offer without making any constructive counter
                            suggestions. I warned the Minister he should not count on Mr. White’s
                            being embarrassed thereby as it would only appear to the bondholders and
                            in the financial press in the United States that Colombia had made an
                            offer which had been refused approval by the Council because it was not
                            commensurate with this country’s ability to pay and compared unfavorably
                            with debt settlements reached with others. Dr. Lleras said a similar
                            situation had existed respecting Chile’s unilateral offer but
                            subsequently based on insignificant changes in the Chilean undertaking
                            Mr. White had been forced to give his approval in order not to appear,
                            alone, as disapproving the Chilean offer which the bondholders
                            themselves were by then ready to accept. I again mentioned the fact that
                            Chile in 1938 at least devoted 22 percent of its budget to foreign debt
                            service, to which Dr. Lleras rejoined that as soon as the departments
                            and other Colombian debtors began servicing their loans the percentage
                            of total budgets would be comparable to Chile’s. I observed that this
                            was perhaps a subject we could discuss more intelligently when we knew
                            exactly what the total service was to be.</p>
                        <p>When I again insisted that the Minister make some suggestion as to how
                            the present impasse might be solved, he replied that it would be helpful
                            if he could obtain, in some way, an indication as to what interest rate
                            would be approved by the Council. I said I did not see how this would
                            greatly assist him since, judging by his remarks, he still seemed to be
                            pretty far away in his ideas from a figure which the Council would
                            approve.</p>
                        <p>At one point I inquired whether there would be any advantage in
                            Ambassador López and Mr. White coming to Colombia since the members of
                            the debt commission, and of the Senate and House Committees, and other
                            influential people might thereby obtain a better understanding of the
                            situation as it existed in the United States and in turn Mr. White would
                            sense the atmosphere here. The Minister <pb facs="0500" n="492" xml:id="pg_492"/> agreed my reasoning was sound but said there were
                            other considerations why it would be unwise for the negotiations to be
                            transferred to Bogota. While of course I did not mention it to the
                            Minister, one disadvantage of negotiating in the States is illustrated
                            by the fact that while Messrs. López and White continued to discuss the
                            refunding of internal bonds that subject never was very seriously
                            considered by the Government here.</p>
                        <p>While I am satisfied it would be extremely difficult for the Colombian
                            Government to include the departmental, municipal and bank debts in a
                            settlement along with the national debt, I nevertheless asked the
                            Minister whether by doing so it would not be possible to make a proposal
                            on better terms than the one already submitted. This suggestion he
                            rejected.</p>
                        <p>It will be noted from the foregoing that so far about the only point
                            which appears encouraging is the X percentage of petroleum revenues
                            being assigned to debt service. Several times throughout the interview I
                            emphasized that Colombia’s credit would be seriously damaged with
                            consequent embarrassment to all concerned if the Government left matters
                            in the present impasse. I believe the Minister was impressed by my
                            argument, but unfortunately not enough so to induce him to make another
                            offer on terms anywhere near acceptable to the Council. I would feel
                            more sanguine about my possibly bringing the matter to the attention of
                            President Santos had he not already admitted to me that he knew little
                            about finance and relied entirely therefore on his Minister.</p>
                        <p>Our interview ended by my urging that Dr. Lleras give serious thought to
                            the finding of a solution to the impasse and by his promising to call a
                            special meeting of the Debt Commission this week to consider the
                            situation, after which he would advise me of what conclusions had been
                            reached by the Commission and himself.</p>
                        <p>I shall, of course, appreciate being informed promptly of Mr. White’s
                            proposal, mentioned in the last paragraph of the Department’s telegram
                            under reference. It may at least, I hope, be of such a nature as to
                            silence Dr. Lleras’ criticism respecting Mr. White’s dual role. Of
                            course the ideal would be for it to be along the same general lines as
                            the Colombian offer and with an interest rate within trading range of
                            the Colombian.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Spruille Braden</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>