<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Under Secretary of State ( (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d511</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">511</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-09-29T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-09-29T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recjP7nK0m2r7YYXK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-09-29T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-09-29T19:00:00-05:00" n="511"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d511">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">821.51/2383: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the Under
                        Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-09-29T19:00:00-05:00"
                            >September 29, 1939—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>31. Your 16, September 26, 3 p.m. The Department has again discussed with the
                    Treasury and Messrs. Jones and Pierson the broad problem of economic and
                    financial cooperation with the other American republics, with special reference
                    to your suggestion that you be authorized to extend invitations to the
                    Governments of Colombia and Peru to send special representatives to Washington
                    to discuss their situations with this Government. Our conversations indicate
                    general agreement on a number of phases of the problem:</p>
                <p>1. That it will be possible to proceed with Export-Import Bank and Stabilization
                    Fund operations within the limitations discussed by you with the Treasury and
                    Mr. Jones. Prior to your departure Mr. Jones indicated that additional
                    Export-Import Bank operations might be undertaken to the extent of 15 to 20 or
                    even possibly 30 million dollars, while the Secretary of the Treasury indicated
                    that he was prepared to use the Stabilization Fund in operations secured by gold
                    deposited <pb facs="0517" n="509" xml:id="pg_509"/> in this country. Since that
                    time the Export-Import Bank has agreed to commitments with Brazil, Chile, and
                    Panama amounting to 11 million dollars. Within these limitations, however, it
                    will be possible to go ahead with certain of the most urgent requests for
                    assistance.</p>
                <p>With specific regard to Colombia, it is the Department’s impression that the
                    amounts of assistance in the form of a line of credit for the Banco de la
                    Republica would probably be considerably greater than present availabilities
                    would make possible. The Treasury has already indicated to the Colombian
                    Government that it is prepared to make available dollars against gold collateral
                    (Colombia has $20,000,000 of gold). Beyond this it might be possible to consider
                    favorably modest Export-Import Bank transactions. It is not immediately obvious
                    how much the assistance requested by Peru might involve, but it would seem
                    possible that assistance to tide over the emergency might be effected within the
                    limits of Export-Import Bank powers mentioned above.</p>
                <p>2. That as soon as you return it will be essential and desirable for this
                    Department, the Treasury and the Federal Loan Agency to collaborate in the
                    preparation of a broad program for economic and financial cooperation with the
                    other American republics to be presented to the Congress for its approval. Such
                    a program would probably involve increased lending powers for the Export-Import
                    Bank, specific congressional authorization for the type of Stabilization Fund
                    Transactions, other than against gold which we have discussed, and possibly
                    authorization to make long term loans of gold in connection with reorganizations
                    of their monetary systems. It is generally hoped and believed that with the full
                    presentation of all aspects of the situation widespread approval of such a
                    program would be forthcoming.</p>
                <p>The Treasury also suggests that the Under Secretary of the Treasury should fully
                    discuss the situation and such a program with you as well as other officials of
                    the three agencies prior to his going to the Guatemalan conference in
                    November.</p>
                <p>3. That it would be unwise from the immediate internal political point of view,
                    as well as in relation to the broad program mentioned in (2) above, to have
                    during the near future visits here of special representatives with inevitable
                    attendant publicity. For this reason it is not believed desirable at the present
                    time to invite the Governments of Colombia and Peru to send special
                    representatives or missions to Washington to carry on economic discussions with
                    us.</p>
                <p>4. That due consideration be given to debt default situations and other problems
                    outstanding between this country and individual other American republics. The
                    emergency situation arising out of the war <pb facs="0518" n="510"
                        xml:id="pg_510"/> naturally calls for reexamination of the previous attitude
                    assumed by this Department and other Government agencies. The Department
                    believes that where a country is in a position to conclude a reasonable and
                    equitable debt settlement, or at least to enter into a reasonable transitional
                    arrangement, this Government would not be justified in extending credits unless
                    this operation was preceded by or accompanied by a satisfactory debt
                    arrangement. (The Treasury feels strongly that the negotiations for such an
                    arrangement should not be linked closely to the credit discussions, nor the
                    credits possibly considered as an inducement for the debt arrangement.) In those
                    cases where a country is utterly unable to make any payment that would be
                    considered by the bondholders as reasonable even transitionally, the Department
                    would be prepared to recommend to other agencies the extension of credit
                    facilities to tide over the emergency and possibly pave the way for a future
                    settlement of the debt situation.</p>
                <p>It is noted that the Colombian Delegation has indicated that the Colombian
                    Government would be prepared to make some sort of service of the existing debt.
                    For your information the Colombian Ambassador on September 26 inquired under
                    instructions whether it was correct that the Export-Import Bank had opened a
                    credit of five million dollars to Chile and had participated in the financing of
                    the sale of ships to Brazil. The Colombian Government desired to know whether it
                    was still on the “blacklist” because of inability to come to an agreement with
                    the Council. The correctness of his Government’s information with regard to the
                    Chilean and Brazilian transactions was confirmed. The Ambassador then asked
                    whether this Government would be prepared to receive proposals regarding
                    Export-Import Bank assistance. The Ambassador was informed that the Department
                    was now in the process of reexamining its policy, and that while no definite
                    statements could be made the possibility of Export-Import Bank credits for
                    Colombia was no longer out of the question.</p>
                <p>With regard to Peru, you will recall that last June the Peruvian Government was
                    informed that this Government would be happy to welcome a mission to discuss
                    further economic cooperation between the two countries.<note n="50"
                        xml:id="d511fn50">See telegram No. 39, June 13, 1 p.m., to the Chargé in
                        Peru, <ref target="#pg_776">p. 776</ref>.</note> At the time it was
                    suggested that full preliminary exploration of the possibilities for cooperation
                    be carried out and that Peru submit as soon as possible the projects which it
                    believed desirable and feasible. Since that time the Peruvian Government has
                    given no evidence of any desire to go forward with this matter.</p>
                <p>Among the matters taken up at that time with the Peruvian Government was the debt
                    situation, and the Embassy repeated the statement made by the Under Secretary to
                    the Peruvian Ambassador that “in view of our knowledge of the very favorable
                    economic and financial <pb facs="0519" n="511" xml:id="pg_511"/> situation of
                    the Peruvian Government, in which we all rejoice, it was very difficult to
                    understand why no real effort had been made by the Government to reach an
                    agreement for the adjustment of the legitimate obligations to the
                    bondholders”.</p>
                <p>It is suggested that you discuss the situation quite frankly with the Colombian
                    and Peruvian Delegations, pointing out why it would be undesirable at this time
                    to arouse any widespread publicity such as would follow upon an invitation for
                    special representatives to come to Washington. You may indicate that within the
                    limitations of present powers, this Government would be pleased to consider
                    immediate assistance to tide over emergency situations, and that such assistance
                    might be followed by broader cooperative arrangements early next year if wider
                    powers are authorized by the Congress. It is suggested that you indicate that
                    this Government will be pleased to take up the immediate matters with regular
                    diplomatic representatives in Washington, and that we should welcome all
                    possible information regarding the existing situation in each country and plans
                    for requests for the future. Mr. Jones has indicated that if it will assist you
                    in your discussions at Panama, he is prepared to send representatives of this
                    Government to Colombia and to Peru, and you are authorized to state that this
                    Government will do so if you feel that such a course is desirable. Although it
                    is not felt that such visits by American representatives are really necessary,
                    and there is some danger that such visits might lead to expectations which might
                    later not be realizable, such a course might enable this Government to postpone
                    final decisions until broader powers to act in the situation have been
                    obtained.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
