<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to President Roosevelt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d559</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">559</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="559"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d559">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">839.51/4724</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-08-03">August 3,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I enclose a draft letter in
                    reply to a communication addressed to you by General Trujillo, Chief of Staff of
                    the Dominican Army and former President of the Republic, in which the suggestion
                    was made that the aspirations of the Dominican Government with respect to the
                    liquidation of the existing special financial relationship between that
                    Government and ours would in large measure be met should you agree either to
                    appoint a Dominican citizen as Receiver General of Dominican Customs or else to
                    leave that post unfilled.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner Welles</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0594" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Draft of Reply to Communication From the Chief of Staff of
                            the Dominican Army</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Trujillo</hi>)</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear General Trujillo</hi>: In acknowledging the
                        receipt of your letter of July 26, 1939, I desire to say that the officials
                        of this Government have been only too glad to extend to you friendly
                        courtesies. I am pleased that you found your stay in this country
                        enjoyable.</p>
                    <p>Your reiteration that the foreign policy of the people and Government of the
                        Dominican Republic is pledged to the aims of continental solidarity cannot
                        but evoke a feeling of gratification on the part of this Government.</p>
                    <p>I sincerely appreciate your frankness in making your suggestion with respect
                        to the existing Convention of 1924 between the Dominican Republic and the
                        United States and wish to assure you that for my own part personally, I
                        welcome them in the spirit in which I know they have been made. I feel sure
                        that you realize that this Government no less than that of the Dominican
                        Republic has been desirous of finding a solution which would, while honoring
                        the contractual obligations of both Governments towards third parties, clear
                        away the remaining vestiges of the former special financial relationship
                        between the two countries.</p>
                    <p>While the method that you suggest, namely, that the President of the United
                        States either appoint a Dominican citizen as Receiver General of Dominican
                        Customs or else leave that post unfilled, has much to recommend it on the
                        grounds of simplicity, such a solution could only be partial in its
                        effects.</p>
                    <p>Under the Convention of 1924, and in the contracts of the Dominican external
                        bonds, the two Governments assumed certain responsibilities toward the
                        purchasers and owners of these bonds. Merely to appoint a Dominican citizen
                        as Receiver General of Dominican Customs, even were that gesture
                        satisfactory to the Dominican people and Government, would not in effect
                        transfer any of the responsibility of the Government of the United States to
                        the Dominican Government, which has been one of the chief objectives of both
                        Governments. Furthermore, it is my understanding that there are several
                        other provisions of the Convention, including that mentioned by you with
                        regard to alterations in the Dominican Customs Tariff, which stand in need
                        of revision.</p>
                    <p>It was with the view to effecting a complete revision of the provisions of
                        the Convention of 1924 in an effort to respond to the aspirations of the
                        Dominican Government and people while safeguarding the obligations assumed
                        towards the holders of Dominican external bonds, that the Government of the
                        United States first agreed to undertake <pb facs="0595" n="587"
                            xml:id="pg_587"/> negotiations for a new instrument which might be
                        substituted for that Convention.</p>
                    <p>It was my hope that these informal negotiations, which had proceeded to what
                        was believed to be the point of mutual agreement, might be brought to a
                        successful conclusion.</p>
                    <p>Finally, I need hardly bring to your attention the fact that while the
                        Executive Branch of this Government is charged with the responsibility of
                        negotiating treaties and conventions, under our Constitution it must submit
                        these instruments to the Senate for its advice and consent.</p>
                    <p>In closing may I take the opportunity again to assure you that this
                        Government is sincerely desirous of concluding an agreement to replace the
                        Convention of 1924 which will respond to Dominican aspirations and will
                        dissolve the remaining direct financial relationship between the two
                        Governments without prejudice to the interests of third parties. To this end
                        this Government is prepared either to continue with a discussion of existing
                        proposals or to examine with sympathetic understanding any new proposal
                        which may be proffered by the Dominican Government.</p>
                    <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
