<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-07-14T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-07-14T16:00:00-05:00" n="604" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d604">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.38/306: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Minister in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Mayer</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-07-14T17:00:00-04:00">July 14,
                                    1939—5 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>71. Personal for the Minister from the Under Secretary. Your 94, July 11,
                            10 a.m.<note n="10" xml:id="d604fn10">Not printed.</note> and despatches
                            564, July 5 and 566, July 8.<note n="11" xml:id="d604fn11">Latter not
                                printed.</note> For the reasons set forth below, you should call
                            immediately upon President Vincent and express the following views:</p>
                        <p>Please inform him that the Government fully appreciates the motives which
                            have led him once again to advance a concept for a mutual assistance
                            pact in the Caribbean. This Government is deeply gratified to have this
                            renewed assurance of M. Vincent’s support of the doctrine of continental
                            solidarity, and this further evidence of his friendship, and that of his
                            country, for the United States.</p>
                        <p>You should tell him that the President and this Government are working
                            day and night to avoid the holocaust of war. At the same time, and in
                            order to be prepared for any emergency, prudence naturally dictates that
                            all possible measures shall be taken for the defense of this hemisphere.
                            With this in view, suggestions for mutual assistance pacts have been put
                            forward from time to time. President Vincent has again put forward this
                            suggestion.</p>
                        <p>As the result of the careful consideration that has been given to these
                            projects, the statement of policy was developed as set forth in the
                            Department’s telegrain no. 28 of March 30, 3 p.m. In as much as
                            President <pb facs="0652" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/> Vincent has once
                            again raised his suggestion despite your best efforts, I believe the
                            time has come for you to make it unmistakably clear to him that since
                            the earliest days of this Republic, it has been and still is a basic
                            principle of policy to decline, irrespective of circumstances, to enter
                            into any offensive or defensive alliance. This cardinal principle of
                            policy has invariably received the fullest support of the American
                            people. Please, therefore, state unequivocally that the United States
                            cannot consider participating in any pact or alliance for mutual
                            assistance even with its nearest neighbors.</p>
                        <p>The present policy of this Government with respect to consultation,
                            collaboration and cooperation for the defense of this hemisphere in case
                            of any threat to peace is clearly stated in the Declaration of Lima.
                            Exchanges of views with the President of Haiti and with other Haitian
                            officials on this subject will always be welcome but this Government
                            cannot enter into commitments of the sort contemplated.</p>
                        <p>You should, of course, reiterate this Government’s high appreciation of
                            the sentiments which have motivated President Vincent in this matter and
                            assure him that due note has been taken of his laudable interest in
                            making available facilities for the common defense of this hemisphere,
                            an interest which this Government hopes will continue unabated.</p>
                        <p>For your strictly confidential information, I realize that despite your
                            best efforts the recent announcement of President Vincent was unexpected
                            and possibly unavoidable. It would be most unfortunate were he to
                            proceed further with this project by endeavoring to enlist the
                            participation of neighboring countries. I feel sure that you will be
                            able to convince President Vincent to abandon his proposal thereby
                            avoiding embarrassment both to the Haitian Government and to the United
                            States. [Welles.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>