<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-06-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="607" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d607">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">838.51/3803</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Haiti</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Mayer</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 548</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-06-12">June 12,
                                1939</date>.<lb/>[Received June 15.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the
                            Department’s cablegram No. 56, dated June 7, 7 p.m., 1939,<note n="15" xml:id="d607fn15">Not printed.</note> suggesting certain alterations
                            in the draft note of the Haitian Minister for Foreign Affairs relating
                            to an extension of the moratorium.<note n="16" xml:id="d607fn16">Loan
                                contract of October 6, 1922, between the Republic of Haiti and the
                                National City Company and the National City Bank, both of New York;
                                for text, see <hi rend="italic">Le Moniteur, Journal Officiel de la
                                    République d’Haiti</hi>, October 30, 1922; for correspondence
                                relating to the loan, see <ref target="frus1922v02#pg_472">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 472</ref> ff.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>A note dated June 12, 1939, has just been received from the Haitian
                            Foreign Office requesting the extension for one year of the moratorium
                            which resulted from the Accord of July 1, 1938.<note n="17" xml:id="d607fn17">Department of State Executive Agreement Series No.
                                128, or 53 Stat. 1923.</note> This note with translation is
                            enclosed.</p>
                        <p>The Department’s suggestion to insert “and such amounts as may be deemed
                            necessary by the Fiscal Representative, etc.” in the body of the note
                            has been slightly altered in the note so as to read “and such amounts as
                            may be deemed necessary by the Secretary of State for Finance in accord
                            with the Fiscal Representative, etc.”</p>
                        <p>As soon as Mr. de la Rue<note n="18" xml:id="d607fn18">Sidney de la Rue,
                                Fiscal Representative of the Haitian Government.</note> has had an
                            opportunity to carry through the negotiations with the Foreign
                            Bondholders’ Protective Council, I would appreciate receiving
                            authorization to sign a supplemental <pb facs="0655" n="647" xml:id="pg_647"/> executive agreement extending the Accord of July
                            1, 1938, for one additional year.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ferdinand L. Mayer</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Haitian Minister for Foreign Affairs</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Laleau</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the American Minister</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Mayer</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Port-au-Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-06-12">June 12,
                                    1939</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: Since the letter of June 14,
                                    1938,<note n="19" xml:id="d607fn19">
                                    <ref target="frus1938v05#pg_596">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1938, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 596</ref>.</note> from my
                                Department, the situation in the Republic of Haiti has not changed
                                materially, and I am therefore obliged to request your Government to
                                accept prolongation of the Accord of July 1, 1938, for another
                                year.</p>
                            <p>Haiti is obtaining a better comparative price for her coffee, but the
                                size of the crop seems to have suffered a permanent reduction. The
                                cause is not known, but it is generally ascribed to over aged trees.
                                The five-year average of exports of coffee has fallen from
                                31,919,197 kilos at the end of the fiscal year 1933–1934 to
                                27,803,960 kilos at the end of the fiscal year 1937–1938. On the
                                other hand, banana production is increasing, and exports will
                                probably reach 2,200,000 stems this year, or an increase of 837,000
                                stems in comparison with the exports of last year. Sugar prices have
                                improved somewhat, but an export quota has been fixed which
                                precludes much help from that source of revenue. Cotton is still
                                subject to attack from the Mexican boll weevil, and unless this year
                                brings another drought, which is unfavorable to the boll weevil,
                                increased damage to our cotton is expected. Furthermore, both cotton
                                and sisal are quoted at depressed prices.</p>
                            <p>At the end of April revenues had failed to meet estimates by Gdes.
                                842,559.06. If a further reduction in an already inadequate budget
                                is to be avoided, revenue trends must change from those existing
                                from October through April, 1939; inasmuch as the treasury balance
                                is inadequate to meet such a deficit, continuing unsatisfactory
                                revenues will require a reduction in expenditures approximating the
                                amount of the deficit in the budget of ways and means.</p>
                            <p>The May receipts have been raised in an abnormal fashion exceeding
                                the average, with reference to this month, of better years. This is
                                perhaps due to certain unexpected and extraordinary factors. For
                                example, a large importation of gasoline, a large importation of
                                material for the J. G. White Company<note n="20" xml:id="d607fn20">This company, with headquarters in New York City, had a
                                    contract with the Government of Haiti for the execution of a
                                    program of public works. For text of contract, see <hi rend="italic">Le Moniteur, Journal Officiel de la République
                                        d’Haiti</hi>, July 7, 1938.</note> and exportations of
                                coffee bought <pb facs="0656" n="648" xml:id="pg_648"/> during the
                                past few months but held for preparation over and above the ordinary
                                time for expedition.</p>
                            <p>I cannot therefore hope that this exceptional situation of the month
                                of May may continue, nor that it might be the proof of a permanent
                                state of Haitian Government receipts. It is why at the present
                                moment our firmest desire is to be in a position to adopt a budget
                                for the fiscal year, 1939–1940, which will not require any further
                                reductions in our reduced appropriations for the essential public
                                services.</p>
                            <p>As a result, however, of the friendly attitude that the holders of
                                the bonds of the 1922 loan have always shown towards the Haitian
                                Government and of their desire to maintain its credit at the highest
                                point, I can assure your Government that all additional receipts
                                which we will collect during the fiscal year 1939–1940 over and
                                above the amount carried in the budget 1938–1939 and all other
                                amounts which may be deemed necessary by the Secretary of State for
                                Finance, in accord with the Fiscal Representative, to be expended as
                                extraordinary appropriations to meet serious emergencies, will be
                                employed for the amortization of the 1922 [loan?].</p>
                            <p>In requesting your Government to agree to prolong the Accord of July
                                1, 1938, for a duration of one year, the Haitian Government confirms
                                its willingness to continue to execute during the period of
                                prolongation, all the obligations contained in the letter from my
                                Department of January 11, 1938.<note n="21" xml:id="d607fn21">
                                    <ref target="frus1938v05#pg_582">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1938, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 582</ref>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>I take [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Leon Laleau</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>