<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom ( (Holmes) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-01-25T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-01-25T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-25T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-25T14:00:00-05:00" n="11"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d11">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/1–2549:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_HJC1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Holmes</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-25T19:00:00+00:00"
                            >January 25, 1949—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>305. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 210, January 18<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d11fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_12">p. 12</ref>.</note>
                    Following memorandum submitted by <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> at end
                    today’s occupation statute meeting.<note n="2" xml:id="d11fn2">
                        <p>At the sixth meeting on the occupation statute, occupation costs were
                            again discussed with the French retaining their position. The United
                            States and British delegations finally persuaded the French delegation
                            to submit to its Government the following paragraph for consideration:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The costs of occupation represent a heavy although diminishing
                                    burden on the German economy. This temporary charge should not
                                    lead to an excessive and permanent concentration of financial
                                    power in the federal state. The circumstances that
                                    responsibility has been placed on federal state with respect to
                                    payment of occupation costs is not intended to prejudge the
                                    question of the method by which the taxes will be levied.”
                                    (Telegram 307, January 25, from London, not printed, 740.00119
                                    Control (Germany)/1–2549)</p>
                                <p>In telegram 325, January 28, to London, not printed, the
                                    Department of State indicated its acceptance of the proposal
                                    (740.00119 Control (Germany)/1–2549).</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                    </note> Matter will <pb facs="0050" n="20" xml:id="pg_20"/> be discussed at
                    subsequent meeting. Initial British reaction to whom we showed advance copy was
                    favorable although they indicated certain concern with respect to paragraph (<hi
                        rend="italic">c</hi>) re scope of operations of tripartite inspectorial
                    teams operating throughout zones.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> desires to invite the attention
                        of British and French delegates to desirability of reaching an agreement in
                        principle concerning manner in which the military governors will exercise
                        powers reserved to them by occupation statute.</p>
                    <p>My government considers that firm understanding re fundamental principles to
                        be observed by three military governors in reaching their decisions must be
                        arrived at before definitive approval can be given to text of draft
                        occupation statute. While this meeting is not prepared consider details of a
                        trizonal fusion agreement or an agreement on control machinery, it is felt
                        that certain aspects of such agreements should and can be determined
                        now.</p>
                    <p>In particular, the US desires assurance with respect to the following
                        matters: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the reserve powers should be exercised by majority vote of
                                the three representatives of the occupying powers except with
                                respect to matters relating to German foreign trade and foreign
                                exchange. While the US is contributing the major share of German
                                imports or making the major financial provision therefor out of
                                public funds, the representatives of the US in agencies dealing with
                                German foreign trade and foreign exchange, or exercising the powers
                                reserved to the occupation authorities for the control thereof,
                                should have a voting strength proportionate to the funds made
                                available by the US Government for these purposes, on a basis
                                similar to that now recognized in agreements re Joint Export-Import
                                Agency.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the exercise of powers under (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) above
                                be subject to right of any of the military governors who considers
                                that action decided upon conflicts with major policies of his own
                                government, to request that matter be referred to three governments
                                for consideration. Except when decision which is appealed concerns
                                disapproval of German legislation, such an appeal would serve to
                                suspend the action for not longer than 30 days. With respect to
                                decisions concerning exercise of power to disapprove German
                                legislation, action would be suspended for not longer than 21 days
                                from day when legislation in question had been submitted to
                                occupation authorities. Such suspension, however, would not prevent
                                the taking of the action appealed from unless governmental agreement
                                on the appeal was reached within the time limits mentioned.</item>
                            <pb facs="0051" n="21" xml:id="pg_21"/>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the three military governors constituting a tripartite board,
                                be supported by staff or committee organization which would function
                                throughout trizonal area, details of such organization and its
                                procedures to be decided upon by them. In any event, such an
                                organization would include adequate inspectorial and supervisory
                                group to determine German food requirements, and supervise
                                production and distribution of German food and proper utilization of
                                imported food.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That such a trizonal agreement continue in effect at least for
                                part of period of occupation during which the US is, as compared
                                with other two occupation powers, making the major contribution for
                                imports into Germany.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <p>My government believes that these matters are so inseparably related to
                    occupation statute as to require concurrrent agreement in principle.”</p>
                <p>State please pass Army. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> please pass
                    to <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 305; repeated Berlin 58.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Holmes</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
