<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-11-11T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-11T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067357"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">International organizations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-11T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-11T09:00:00-05:00" n="132"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Council/11–1149: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-11T15:00:00+01:00"
                            >November 11, 1949—3 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4724. From Secretary. Following is text of directive to US, UK and French High
                    Commissioners on general questions concerning Germany approved by three Foreign
                    Ministers in session concluded early this morning.</p>
                <p rend="center">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Conclusions of the Tripartite Meeting Held in
                        Paris on November</hi> 9 <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi> 10. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Directive to the High Commissioners.</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">i. general lines of policy towards germany</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>This directive is intended to establish a programme for the
                            development of allied policy in Germany which aims eventually at
                            creating a more normal situation in Germany and at the establishment <pb
                                facs="0340" n="307" xml:id="pg_307"/> of more normal relations
                            between Germany and other countries subject to these measures which are
                            necessary for security, including the retention of supreme
                            authority.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The occupation statute will remain in force until reviewed.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Meanwhile the ground for a smooth evolution should be prepared by a
                            programme for 1950 which will include measures outlined in the following
                            paragraph.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">ii. association of germany with the western world</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(A) <hi rend="italic">Council of Europe.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The admission of Germany to the Council of Europe as an associate member has
                    already obtained support in principle in the Committee of Ministers. It has been
                    approved by the standing committee of the assembly and also by the three
                    Ministers at this meeting. Final decision on the point is expected at the next
                    meeting of the Committee of Ministers. It is hoped that before then the
                    governments may be able to advise the high commissioners that they can inform
                    the Federal Chancellor that a request for admission as an associate member could
                    opportunely be made together with the necessary declarations accepting the basic
                    principles on the statute of the Council of Europe.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(B) <hi rend="italic">International organizations.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Ministers gave approval in principle to the report of a working party set up
                    in Washington to examine the question of German participation in certain
                    international bodies.<note n="1" xml:id="d132fn1">Not printed.</note> The high
                    commissioners will take this report as a guide and will, in conjunction with the
                    German Federal Government, examine each proposal for the participation of
                    Germany in an international body on its merits. In addition to the bodies listed
                    in the working party’s report, Ministers decided that consideration should be
                    given to the admission of Germany to the Central Rhine Commission on the basis
                    of the Mannheim Convention of 1868.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">iii. the saar</hi>
                </p>
                <p>For the information of the high commissioners, the Ministers recorded that they
                    could agree with the admission of the Saar territory with the Council of Europe
                    as an associate member on the understanding that the definitive status of the
                    Saar shall await the peace settlement.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">iv. german internal problems</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(A) <hi rend="italic">Germany’s representation abroad.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The high commissioners should inform the Federal Chancellor that they are
                    authorized to permit the gradual establishment by the German Federal Republic of
                    consular and commercial representatives in those countries which are prepared to
                    receive them. They may also approve the authorization of a bureau, probably
                    forming part of the Federal Chancellor’s office, to control these officials and
                    to coordinate instructions to German representatives attending international
                    organizations and conventions. These measures do not affect the powers reserved
                    to the high commission in the field of foreign affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="0341" n="308" xml:id="pg_308"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">(B) <hi rend="italic">Termination of the state of war.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Foreign Ministers decided that each government concerned including the
                    Benelux and Commonwealth nations should examine the problem and exchange views
                    preparatory to an eventual meeting of a committee of jurists. In the event that
                    this question is raised by the Federal Chancellor, the high commissioners will
                    inform him that the continuation of the state of war involves technical and
                    legal problems of a very complicated nature. They may further advise him in
                    strict confidence that the Ministers have decided to have this question examined
                    carefully by jurists; at the same time they should warn him that at the present
                    time the legal difficulties appear to be considerable.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">(C) <hi rend="italic">Attitude to the so-called German
                        democratic republic.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Foreign Ministers agreed that it was desirable that the governments of the
                    Western world should adopt a common attitude towards the so-called German
                    democratic republic and should as far as possible avoid any action involving the
                    express or implied recognition of that republic as a de <hi rend="italic"
                        >facto</hi> or <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> government. They agreed that
                    when the permanent commission in London of the Brussels Treaty powers considers
                    the problems arising from trade agreements between the Soviet Zone of Germany
                    and other countries, or other matters which might raise the question of such
                    recognition, the United States Government should send a representative to the
                    meetings. They also agreed that the United States Government and the governments
                    represented on the permanent commission would if necessary make representations
                    to other interested Western European Governments.</p>
                <p>Finally the Foreign Ministers agreed that the high commissioners should inform
                    the Federal Government of the Ministers’ concern in regard to this problem and
                    use their influence to assure that the action of the Federal Government
                    conformed.”</p>
                <p>Sent Department 4724; repeated London 816.</p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
