<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-01T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-01T18:00:00-05:00" n="14" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d14">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/2–149:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HJC1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Holmes</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-01T23:00:00+00:00">February 1, 1949—11 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>383. French made strenuous efforts at today’s occupation statute
                                    meeting<note n="1" xml:id="d14fn1">The minutes prepared by the
                                    United States delegation for this eighth meeting on the
                                    Occupation Statute for Germany were transmitted in despatch 217,
                                    from London, not printed (740.00119 Control
                                    (Germany)/2–849).</note> to chisel away from <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> agreement on occupation (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 354, January 29, repeated
                                Berlin 68<note n="2" xml:id="d14fn2">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note>). Despite understanding of
                                both US and UK delegations that agreement envisaged retention
                                original US–UK wording pararaphs 20 and 21 except for deletion final
                                sentence paragraph 21 and substitution therefor of statement
                                mentioned <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>, French maintain
                                that they had contemplated use of wording contained in revision of
                                these two paragraphs put forward by British in first day’s session
                                and subsequently withdrawn. Wording paragraph 20 in this suggested
                                compromise is as follows:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Powers of occupying authorities under Article II include power
                                    to require appropriate German authorities to make such financial
                                    or other provisions as military governments may deem necessary
                                    for discharge their responsibilities and satisfaction their
                                    requirements. German authorities will be consulted as to
                                    procedure to be followed for satisfaction such
                                    requirements.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>US delegation agreed to this change on <hi rend="italic">ad
                                    referendum</hi> basis and on condition French acceptance
                                provision in paragraph 21 clearly fixing on federal state
                                responsibility for payment of all costs arising under Article
                                VII.</p>
                            <p>US delegation refused to accept UK suggested revision of paragraph 21
                                mentioned above which in our opinion would be entirely inadequate
                                and insisted on retention wording contained in original US–UK draft
                                except for deletion final sentence and substitution following: “The
                                federal state will be responsible for payment to occupying
                                authorities of all costs arising under this article.”</p>
                            <p>US delegation blocked French suggestion that “responsible” be
                                translated French phrase “se retenu d’assurer.” French then
                                suggested substitution “appropriate German” for “federal state”
                                authorities first <pb facs="0056" n="26" xml:id="pg_26"/> sentence
                                paragraph 21. He asserted latter phrase would preclude consultation
                                with <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> authorities on any matter
                                relating to occupation requirements covered by Article VII and also
                                would lead to creation of enormous central bureaucracy. US
                                delegation stated that consultation with any <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> authority on any subject not prohibited and
                                therefore permissible. He refused accept substitution as
                                inconsistent with and inferential weakening of provisions last
                                sentence paragraph 21 above quoted. British delegation suggested as
                                compromise elimination phrase “after consultation with federal state
                                authorities.” French delegation agreed. US delegate refused but on
                                request consented to refer matter to his Government.</p>
                            <p>French and US delegations accepted on <hi rend="italic">ad
                                    referendum</hi> basis following British proposed text of
                                paragraph in report to accompany draft statute (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 326, January 26. Repeated
                                Berlin 67<note n="3" xml:id="d14fn3">Not printed.</note>) re
                                occupation costs:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Text of paragraph 20 and 21 aims at leaving open question
                                    whether occupation and mandatory costs will be collected by
                                    federal state or by <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>. Agreement
                                    was reached that responsibility to occupying powers for payment
                                    these costs must definitely be laid on federal state. As
                                    imposition this responsibility, interpreted in light paragraph
                                        (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) of Annex H of report of six-power
                                    conference of June 1, 1948, might lead Parliamentary Council to
                                    feel compelled to vest in federal state financial powers which
                                    occupying powers might think excessive, it was considered
                                    prudent to agree on an explanation of attitude of occupying
                                    powers to be issued to Parliamentary Council. It is recommended
                                    that military governments should be instructed to issue their
                                    statement (Annex B this report) at same time they transmit draft
                                    occupation statute to Germans.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>Text Annex B is as follows:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Costs arising under Articles 20 and 21 of occupation statute
                                    represent heavy though diminishing burden on German economy.
                                    This temporary charge should not lead to a concentration of
                                    excessive financial power in federal government. The
                                    circumstance that responsibility has been placed on federal
                                    state with respect to payment of these costs is not intended to
                                    prejudge in any way the method by which, under basic law,
                                    federal state will obtain the funds necessary for their
                                    payment.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>Department will note that foregoing varies slightly from text
                                contained <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 307, January 25,
                                repeated Berlin 59,<note n="4" xml:id="d14fn4">Not printed, but see
                                    footnote 2 to telegram 305, January 25, <ref target="#pg_19">p.
                                        19</ref>.</note> but changes are not considered of
                                substantive nature.</p>
                            <p>We recommend approval Annex B and paragraph in report as well as
                                elimination from paragraph 21 phrase consultation since entire <pb facs="0057" n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/> compromise involved therein
                                does not in our opinion represent any substantive departure from our
                                original position.</p>
                            <p>Sent Department 383, repeated Berlin 70.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Holmes</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>