<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-10-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-10-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="181" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">862.00/10–1749</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Secretary of State</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-10-17">October 17,
                                        1949</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Meeting With the President</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">item 4.</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d181fn1">Other
                                    topics discussed with the President were: Korean aid, United
                                    Kingdom recognition of China, ambassadorial appointments, and
                                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName>’s
                                    contemplated tour of the Far East</note>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">berlin</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>I gave the President a report on developments relating to Berlin. He
                                was anxious to know what our thought was on the struggle with the
                                Soviet Union for Germany and how we thought we were moving in the
                                latest developments. I told him that it seemed to us that the matter
                                hinged on so many issues that it was very hard to make predictions.
                                One question was whether the American people would have the
                                determination to stay with the matter with the military and
                                financial implications which were involved, both in Germany and in
                                Western Europe. If we were, that was one hurdle passed. Another
                                important question was the direction in which the French leadership
                                moved. I had had great hopes that <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> understood and would press for an
                                understanding with Germany. It was uncertain as yet what his
                                position in the new government would be. Reports are that the new
                                    Premier,<note n="2" xml:id="d181fn2">
                                    <persName>Georges Bidault</persName>.</note> for understandable
                                personal reasons, has an angry and uncompromising attitude toward
                                the Germans. This would make the task of integrating Germany into
                                Western Europe much more difficult. In the third place, the fate of
                                Tito would have a very important bearing on whether the Soviet Union
                                intended to reduce some of its activities in Western Europe, or
                                whether it would be encouraged by a failure of Tito to expand some
                                    further.<note n="3" xml:id="d181fn3">For documentation on the
                                    United States attitude toward the Yugoslav–Comintern dispute,
                                    see <ref target="frus1949v05">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>
                                    </ref>.</note> All one can say is that the issue is by no means
                                clear and depended almost equally upon ourselves and upon
                                others.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>