<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the United Nations ( (Austin))to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d351</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">351</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-03-11T19:43:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-03-11T19:43:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-11T19:43:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-11T19:43:00-05:00" n="351"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d351">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/3–1149:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>)<hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-11T19:43:00-05:00"
                            >March 11, 1949—7:43 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>315. <persName corresp="#p_SST1">Sir Terence Shone</persName>, Mr. <persName>De
                        La Tournelle</persName> and I called on Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_AAI1">Alvarez</persName>, <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>
                    President, this afternoon in regard to the Berlin case. Speaking for the group,
                    I explained our position to the President, emphasizing that in view of the
                    nature of the committee’s report we did not believe that consideration of that
                    report by the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> at this time would serve any
                    useful purpose. We explained that we thought this phase of the proceedings which
                    had been instituted by Dr. <persName>Bramuglia</persName> might be brought to a
                    close by publication of the committee’s report at an early date, together with a
                    statement by the President indicating that no further action is contemplated. We
                    explained the nature of the statement which we had in mind the <pb facs="0732"
                        n="691" xml:id="pg_691"/> President might issue at the time of the
                    publication of the report and, at his request, left with the President a copy of
                    a proposed text.</p>
                <p>The President, after some discussion, said he thought the procedure we suggested
                    was quite satisfactory and said he would institute action along these lines
                    immediately. He proposed to instruct the secretariat to have the report
                    duplicated immediately and thought it might be made public this weekend. He
                    asked whether we had consulted the Canadians. We indicated we had informed them
                    in general of what we had in mind and that they had not objected. He indicated
                    he would probably get in touch with them.</p>
                <p>The President was quite clear that the matter would not be brought before the
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> in any way and that it would not be made
                    into an S/document. Question was raised whether the Russians would ask for a
                    meeting. I suggested that if this occurred the President might ask the Russians
                    whether they now accepted the jurisdiction of the <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss>. The President did not indicate that he planned to consult the
                    Russians before taking the contemplated action with regards publication.</p>
                <p>The following is the text we handed to the President:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The President is making public the report of the committee of Neutral
                        Experts established by the President of the Council, Dr.
                            <persName>Bramuglia</persName>, on November 30, 1948, which with its
                        annexes gives full account of the work of the committee for the study of the
                        Berlin currency and trade problems. As the report indicates, the committee
                        held long and detailed discussions lasting several weeks. Despite its
                        laudable efforts, the committee was unable to arrive at a solution of the
                        problem acceptable to both sides. Accordingly there would appear to be no
                        further contribution which the President’s Committee of Experts can make at
                        this time. The Council remains seized of the Berlin matter, however, and the
                        President of the Council as well as other members not directly involved in
                        the dispute hold themselves ready to render such assistance to the parties
                        as would be most helpful.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Protitch<note n="1" xml:id="d351fn1">Dragoslav Protitch, Principal Director,
                        Administrative and General Division, United Nations Secretariat.</note>
                    telephoned and said that <persName corresp="#p_AAI1">Alvarez</persName> had
                    telephoned alerting Protitch to expect instructions Monday morning to prepare
                    the report immediately for release Tuesday.</p>
                <p>Ignatieff<note n="2" xml:id="d351fn2">
                        <persName>George Ignatieff</persName>, Canadian Alternate Representative to
                        the Security Council.</note> informed us Cubans consulted them, and
                    Canadians who meanwhile had received instructions from Ottawa to support us
                    fully, informed Cubans they were thoroughly in favor of procedure envisaged.
                    Canadians advised Cubans to consult other neutrals, and Canadians had impression
                    Cubans would do so immediately by telephone.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
