<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Embassy in the United Kingdom</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d374</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">374</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-04-30T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-04-30T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-04-30T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-04-30T13:00:00-05:00" n="374"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d374">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/4–3049:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">no distribution in department</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-30T14:00:00-04:00"
                            >April 30, 1949—2 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1476.<note n="1" xml:id="d374fn1">Repeated to Paris as 1392, Moscow as 282, and
                        Berlin as 490.</note> For Ambassador and <persName corresp="#p_HJC1"
                        >Holmes</persName> Eyes Only.</p>
                <p>[The first paragraph of the cable reported on <persName corresp="#p_JPC1"
                        >Jessup</persName>’s talk with <persName corresp="#p_MYA1">Malik</persName>,
                    April 29, and repeated the text of <persName corresp="#p_MYA1"
                    >Malik</persName>’s draft communiqué printed <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.]</p>
                <pb facs="0786" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/>
                <p>In our opinion most difficult question at moment is reconciliation of British
                    view with that of French and US concerning lifting restrictions. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CSA1">Cadogan</persName> reports <persName corresp="#p_BE1"
                        >Bevin</persName> strongly supporting <persName corresp="#p_RNA1"
                        >Robertson</persName>’s view from Berlin that Military Governors must work
                    out detailed agreement covering rights in the air, on canals, etc., before
                    blockade is lifted. <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> cites formula of
                    Moscow August 30 directive<note n="2" xml:id="d374fn2">Under reference here is
                        the August 30 directive, to the Military Governors in Berlin, printed in
                            <ref target="frus1948v02#pg_1086">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 1086</ref>.</note> as precedent. We
                    consider this most unhappy precedent. We and French much prefer broad reference
                    lifting restrictions, providing sufficient interval before <gloss
                        target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> to test sincerity of Russian intentions.
                    Preliminary indication <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>’s view leads
                    us believe he agrees this approach but we are confirming with him and will ask
                    him to discuss with <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Robertson</persName>. We are
                    favorably disposed toward <persName corresp="#p_CJ2">Chauvel</persName>’s
                    suggestion yesterday that two dates might be used;<note n="3" xml:id="d374fn3"
                        >See footnote 7 to the memorandum of conversation by <persName
                            corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName>, April 29, <hi rend="italic"
                            >supra</hi>.</note> one two weeks in advance of <gloss target="#t_CFM1"
                        >CFM</gloss> for initial lifting of restrictions and one a week later for
                    completion of lifting. We strongly hope <persName corresp="#p_BE1"
                        >Bevin</persName> will agree with our view that it would be most unfortunate
                    to get bogged down in technical details.</p>
                <p>Concerning date for <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>, despite reasonable
                    argument advanced by <persName corresp="#p_MYA1">Malik</persName> for June date
                    it seems clear Russians are seeking to delay <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>
                    so that it will still be in session when we are ready to establish Western
                    German Government. We feel strongly we should not fall for these tactics and
                    still prefer May 23 as target date although we might compromise on May 30. From
                    communication just left with <persName corresp="#p_JPC1">Jessup</persName> by
                    British Embassy<note n="4" xml:id="d374fn4">Not printed.</note> we are glad to
                    note <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> fully agrees with this general
                    line.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> has indicated objection to
                    mentioning Berlin currency question as included on agenda. We agree entirely
                    that in further four-party conversation with <persName corresp="#p_MYA1"
                        >Malik</persName> we must emphasize that general description of agenda in
                    communiqué does not affect order of discussion of topics at <gloss
                        target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss>. In statement read <persName corresp="#p_MYA1"
                        >Malik</persName> April 5 which was cleared by Secretary, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SR1"
                        >Schuman</persName> we described the meeting of the <gloss target="#t_CFM1"
                        >CFM</gloss> as being one to discuss “matters arising out of the situation
                    in Berlin and matters affecting Germany as a whole”. We consider <persName
                        corresp="#p_MYA1">Malik</persName>’s formula quoted above in paragraph two
                    of his text as being better. This formula is very similar to <persName
                        corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName>’s suggested in foregoing communication
                    from British Embassy. However, if we suggested <persName corresp="#p_BE1"
                        >Bevin</persName>’s formula, “all questions relating to Berlin” we would
                    have to admit to <persName corresp="#p_MYA1">Malik</persName> that this included
                    currency and would find it difficult to argue why we should not expressly say
                    so. We would prefer following formula “questions relating to Germany and
                    problems arising out of the situation in Berlin including the question of
                    currency”.</p>
                <pb facs="0787" n="746" xml:id="pg_746"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CSA1">Cadogan</persName> has already made clear to
                        <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> that both we and French prefer
                    not include Austria on advance agenda although recognizing that Ministers could
                    bring it in during course <gloss target="#t_CFM1">CFM</gloss> if desired and
                    undoubtedly would do so if favorable progress made on Germany.</p>
                <p>Repeating to you telegram to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> NY for
                    communication to <persName corresp="#p_CSA1">Cadogan</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJ2">Chauvel</persName> giving details our proposals next
                        steps.<note n="5" xml:id="d374fn5">Telegram 238 (to London as 1477), April
                        30, to New York, not printed, proposed that <persName corresp="#p_JPC1"
                            >Jessup</persName> write an informal note to <persName corresp="#p_MYA1"
                            >Malik</persName> stating that he had informed the British and French of
                        the Soviet proposal and agreed to Paris as the setting for the Council of
                        Foreign Ministers but suggested May 23 for its opening and May 9 for the
                        lifting of the restrictions which had been imposed since March 28, 1948. The
                        informal note would also contain a draft four-power communiqué. (740.00119
                        Control (Germany)/4–3049)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
