<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Department of the Army to the United States Military Attaché in France (
                    (O’Hare))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d425</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">425</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-05-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="425"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d425">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of Defense Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of the Army</gloss> to the
                        United States Military Attaché in France</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">O’Hare</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-28">28 May
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_WAR1">WAR</gloss> 89370. Personal for <persName
                        corresp="#p_DG2">Dorr</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MMGCB1"
                        >Magruder</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_VTS1">Voorhees</persName>.
                    We are naturally much concerned here about Berlin rail tie-up. Have consulted
                    with <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>, who is reluctant to express
                    any views because he does not want to interfere in any way in problems which
                    have been passed on to others. However, at my urgent request he did give me the
                    following comments which I pass on for your information and any appropriate
                    action:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>The strike of the West Germans for West marks could not be solved by the
                        Reichsbahn which has no West marks at its disposal. Hence the demand of the
                        strikers could only be met provided Soviet military administration made West
                        marks available. The Three Western Powers took the position that this was a
                        German matter. The East German strike breakers were not allowed in the West
                        sector railway stations. Obviously, this resulted in closing Berlin to rail
                        traffic from the West. Soviet military administration then had only to agree
                        with the position of the Western Powers that this was a German matter to in
                        effect reimpose at least in part the blockade. Now we are accusing Soviet
                        military administration of blocking traffic to Berlin whereas in fact we are
                        really blockading ourselves. It does seem that to call this purely a German
                        affair is to the disadvantage of the Western Powers and the blockade thus
                        created is probably much more expensive to the Western Powers than their own
                        assumption of responsibility for payment of employees in West marks. Judging
                        from press reports, it would seem that the Western Powers are maintaining a
                        principle of doubtful validity at great cost to themselves. In any event,
                        the situation has defeated the important project of building up maximum
                        reserves in Berlin before the adjournment of the Council of Foreign
                        Ministers. In case it should become necessary to revert to air lift alone,
                        any loss in capacity devoted to building up reserves will prove most
                        costly.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Above ends <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>’s suggestion to me. Under
                    arrangements by which our authorities in Berlin can deal directly with you,
                    suggest you discuss matter with them in light of these remarks. Also that you
                    feel free to discuss them with <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Acheson</persName>
                    Delegation.</p>
                <pb facs="0887" n="846" xml:id="pg_846"/>
                <p>State requests that above analysis by <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1"
                        >Clay</persName> be called to attention of the Secretary as they have
                    likewise been concerned with aspects he raises.</p>
                <p>[Here follow <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>’s views on attempts to
                    unify Berlin and Soviet participation in the economic affairs of a united
                    Germany.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<persName corresp="#p_VTS1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Voorhees</hi>
                        </persName>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
