<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-05T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-05T09:00:00-05:00" n="599" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d599">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">863.00/5–549: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Austria</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Yost</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-05T15:00:00+01:00">May 5,
                                        1949—3 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>495. Reference <gloss target="#t_Legtel1">Legtel</gloss> 477, May
                                    2.<note n="1" xml:id="d599fn1">Not printed; it summarized
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HO1">Helmer</persName>’s speech to
                                    Socialist Party functionaries in which the Minister of the
                                    Interior stated that the formation of new Austrian political
                                    parties could not be prevented under Austrian law and that they
                                    would therefore have to be recognized and allowed to function.
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HO1">Helmer</persName> claimed the
                                    Allied Council decision of 1945 pertained to the 1945 election
                                    alone and the 1946 Control Agreement did not include approval of
                                    political parties among the prerogatives of the Allied Council.
                                    (863.00/5–249)</note>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HO1">Helmer</persName>’s rash statement on <pb facs="1251" n="1210" xml:id="pg_1210"/> fourth party question
                                has created considerable confusion in People’s Party but seems to
                                have strengthened opposition of western occupation powers to
                                Socialist stand.</p>
                            <p>During call on Vice Chancellor May 3 to introduce <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Dowling</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d599fn2">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DWC1">Walter C. Dowling</persName> had
                                    been appointed Counselor of the Legation in Austria on May
                                    1.</note> Schaerf raised question on his own initiative and made
                                quite clear <persName corresp="#p_HO1">Helmer</persName> statement
                                represents official position Socialist Party and that party has no
                                intention of withdrawing from this position. In reply to query as to
                                attitude of People’s Party, he said no Austrian could contest legal
                                position based on Austrian constitution and that only unanimous
                                action Allied Council could prevent new parties from appearing on
                                ballot. He repeated this statement several times and it was obvious
                                he did not expect any such unanimous action. As to previous action
                                of <gloss target="#t_AC1">AC</gloss> he took position that it
                                forbade parties to campaign but not to appear on ballot. He
                                maintained that it would be impossible for any Austrian official to
                                refuse to inscribe on ballot any party not excluded by Austrian law.
                                Schaerf was most friendly but it was quite obvious he was determined
                                by hook or by crook to thwart our efforts to prevent new parties
                                from participating in elections.</p>
                            <p>Matter has been discussed with both <persName corresp="#p_FL1">Figl</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber</persName>, who of course insist that <persName corresp="#p_HO1">Helmer</persName>’s statement does not
                                represent Austrian Government position, that it is not justified
                                legally and that it is most unfortunate. They seem, however,
                                somewhat at a loss to know what position their party should take and
                                avoided discussion of the issue at this week’s cabinet meeting.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GK1">Gruber</persName> reiterated to us at
                                length arguments against the fourth party with which Department is
                                fully familiar but seemed to hope that action by Allied Council
                                would relieve People’s Party of necessity of taking public stand on
                                this issue. Fact is of course that Socialist emphasis on “sovereign
                                democratic rights of Austria” is naturally popular with Austrian
                                opinion and People’s Party does not wish to appear publicly as
                                champion of overriding authority of Allied Council.</p>
                            <p>We feel that prompt action must be taken to reassert authority of
                                Allied Council on this issue. British element here, which has always
                                favored our point of view on this issue, also desires to take quick
                                action, presumably to forestall further manoeuvers in London by
                                Labor Party supporters of Austrian Socialists. We understand
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Bevin</persName> had intended to
                                reply May 2 to question in Parliament on this subject by indicating
                                that British were prepared to abandon <gloss target="#t_AC1">AC</gloss> control over formation new Austrian parties if other
                                occupation powers would agree. <persName corresp="#p_HO1">Helmer</persName>’s statement, however, caused him to put off
                                reply until next week.</p>
                            <p>Our present intention is to raise question in regular meeting of
                                    <gloss target="#t_AC1">AC</gloss> Political Directorate taking
                                place today and endeavor to obtain agreement immediate despatch of
                                letter to Minister of Interior from US <pb facs="1252" n="1211" xml:id="pg_1211"/> chairman of Directorate inviting attention to
                                    <gloss target="#t_AC1">AC</gloss> decision of September 11,
                                1945, and stating that this decision remains in full effect and that
                                no new Austrian parties may campaign or participate in elections
                                without prior notification to and approval by <gloss target="#t_AC1">AC</gloss>. If Soviets will not agree to despatch of such
                                letter by Directorate, matter will probably have to be referred to
                                Executive Committee.</p>
                            <p>Sent Department; repeated London for <gloss target="#t_USDel1">USDel</gloss> 131.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_YCW1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Yost</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>