<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>List of Papers Agreed by the Foreign Ministers of France, the
                        United Kingdom, and the United States</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d66</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">66</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-04-08T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-04-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-04-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="66" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/4–849</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">List of Papers Agreed by the Foreign Ministers of France, the
                        United Kingdom, and the United States</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Agreements on Germany</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Foreign Ministers of France, the United Kingdom and the United States of
                    America, having met in Washington, have reached agreement on the documents
                    listed below:<note n="1" xml:id="d66fn1">A photograph of the three Foreign
                        Ministers following the signing of the agreements on Germany will be found
                        following <ref target="#pg_642">page 642</ref>.</note>
                    <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>Agreed Memorandum regarding the Principles Governing Exercise of
                            Powers and Responsibilities of US–UK–French Governments following
                            Establishment of German Federal Republic.</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>Occupation Statute Defining the Powers To Be Retained by the
                            Occupation Authorities.</item>
                        <label>C.</label>
                        <item>Agreement as to Tripartite Controls.</item>
                        <label>D.</label>
                        <item>Agreed Minute respecting Berlin.</item>
                        <label>E.</label>
                        <item>Agreed Minute on Claims against Germany.</item>
                        <label>F.</label>
                        <item>Agreed Minute on Wuerttemberg–Baden Plebiscite.</item>
                        <label>G.</label>
                        <item>Agreement regarding Kehl.</item>
                        <label>H.</label>
                        <item>Message to the Military Governors from the Foreign Ministers of the
                            US, UK and France.</item>
                        <label>I.</label>
                        <item>Message to the Bonn Parliamentary Council from the Foreign Ministers
                            of the US, UK and France.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The Foreign Ministers confirmed and approved the agreements made on plant
                    dismantling, prohibited and restricted industries, and the establishment of the
                    Ruhr Authority, all of which were recently negotiated in London.<note n="2" xml:id="d66fn2">For reference to these agreements, see <ref target="#pg_173">p. 173</ref>, footnote 9.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <table cols="3" rows="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SR1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Schuman</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BE1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Ernest Bevin</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RD1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs of the French
                                        Republic</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs United
                                        Kingdom</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State of the United States of
                                        America</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8, 1949</date>, <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>.</dateline>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0208" n="178" xml:id="pg_178"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper A]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Agreed Memorandum Regarding the Principles Governing
                            the Exercise of Powers and Responsibilities of</hi> US-UK-<hi rend="smallcaps">French Governments Following Establishment of German
                            Federal Republic</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">final text</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The Governments of the United States, United Kingdom, and France
                                retain the supreme authority assumed by them under the Declaration
                                signed at Berlin on June 5, 1945,<note n="3" xml:id="d66fn3">For the
                                    text of the Declaration regarding the Defeat of Germany and the
                                    Assumption of Supreme Authority with respect to Germany by the
                                    Governments of the United Kingdom, the United States, the Soviet
                                    Union, and France, see Ruhm von Oppen, <hi rend="italic">Documents on Germany</hi>, pp. 29–35, or Department of
                                    State, Treaties and Other International Acts Series (TIAS) No.
                                    1520.</note> including the right to revoke or alter any
                                legislative or administrative decisions in the three Western zones
                                of Germany.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The German governing authorities, whether Federal or <hi rend="italic">Land</hi>, shall be at liberty to take
                                administrative and legislative action, and such action will have
                                validity if not vetoed by the Allied Authority. This means that
                                military government will disappear, and that the function of the
                                Allies shall be mainly supervisory.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>There will be certain limited fields in which the Allies will
                                reserve the right to take direct action themselves, including the
                                issuance of orders to German officials at both the Federal and local
                                levels. However, these fields will be restricted to a minimum; and
                                aside from security matters, the exercise of direct powers by the
                                Allies should be regarded as temporary and self-liquidating in
                                nature.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Upon the coming into being of the German Federal Republic, the
                                responsibility for supervision of the utilization of funds made
                                available by the Government of the United States to the German
                                economy for purposes of relief as well as of recovery shall rest
                                with the Economic Cooperation Administration. It is understood that
                                the German Federal Republic should become a party to the Convention
                                for the European Economic Cooperation and execute a bilateral
                                agreement with the Government of the United States. Such
                                contributions as the Government of the United Kingdom agrees to make
                                shall be through the intra-European payments agreement.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>With the establishment of the German Federal Republic and the
                                termination of military government, the functions of the Allied
                                authorities shall be divided, military functions being exercised by
                                a Commander-in-Chief, and all other functions by a High
                                Commissioner. Each of the Allied establishments in Germany, aside
                                from occupation <pb facs="0209" n="179" xml:id="pg_179"/> forces,
                                shall come under the direction of the High Commissioner. The three
                                High Commissioners together will constitute the Allied High
                                Commission.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>It is the aim of the three governments to restrict to a minimum
                                the size of the staffs maintained within Germany for the above
                                purposes.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>It is a major objective of the three Allied Governments to
                                encourage and facilitate the closest integration, on a mutually
                                beneficial basis, of the German people under a democratic federal
                                state within the framework of a European association.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper B]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Occupation Statute Defining the Powers To Be Retained
                            by the Occupation Authorities</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">final text</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>In the exercise of the supreme authority which is retained by the Governments
                        of France, the United States and the United Kingdom,</p>
                    <p>We, General <persName corresp="#p_K1">Pierre Koenig</persName>, Military
                        Governor and Commander-in-Chief of the French Zone of Germany,</p>
                    <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Lucius D. Clay</persName>, Military
                        Governor and Commander-in-Chief of the United States Zone of Germany,
                        and</p>
                    <p>General <persName corresp="#p_RGSB1">Sir Brian Hubert Robertson</persName>,
                        Military Governor and Commander-in-Chief of the British Zone of Germany,</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Do Hereby Jointly Proclaim the Following Occupation
                            Statute</hi>: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>During the period in which it is necessary that the occupation
                                continue, the Governments of France, the United States and the
                                United Kingdom desire and intend that the German people shall enjoy
                                self-government to the maximum possible degree consistent with such
                                occupation. The Federal State and the participating <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> shall have, subject only to the
                                limitations in this Instrument, full legislative, executive and
                                judicial powers in accordance with the Basic Law and with their
                                respective constitutions.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In order to ensure the accomplishment of the basic purposes of the
                                occupation, powers in the following fields are specifically
                                reserved, including the right to request and verify information and
                                statistics needed by the occupation authorities: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>disarmament and demilitarization, including related fields
                                        of scientific research, prohibitions and restrictions on
                                        industry, and civil aviation;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>controls in regard to the Ruhr, restitution, reparations,
                                        decartelization, deconcentration, non-discrimination in
                                        trade matters, foreign interests in Germany and claims
                                        against Germany;</item>
                                    <pb facs="0210" n="180" xml:id="pg_180"/>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>foreign affairs, including international agreements male
                                        by or on behalf of Germany;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>displaced persons and the admission of refugees;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>protection, prestige, and security of Allied forces,
                                        dependents, employees, and representatives, their immunities
                                        and satisfaction of occupation costs and their other
                                        requirements;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>respect for the Basic Law and the <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> constitutions;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>control over foreign trade and exchange;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">h</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>control over internal action, only to the minimum extent
                                        necessary to ensure use of funds, food and other supplies in
                                        such manner as to reduce to a minimum the need for external
                                        assistance to Germany;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">i</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>control of the care and treatment in German prisons of
                                        persons charged before or sentenced by the courts or
                                        tribunals of the occupying powers or occupation authorities;
                                        over the carrying out of sentences imposed on them; and over
                                        questions of amnesty, pardon or release in relation to
                                        them.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>It is the hope and expectation of the Governments of France, the
                                United States and the United Kingdom that the occupation authorities
                                will not have occasion to take action in fields other than those
                                specifically reserved above. The occupation authorities, however,
                                reserve the right, acting under instructions of their Governments,
                                to resume, in whole or in part, the exercise of full authority if
                                they consider that to do so is essential to security or to preserve
                                democratic government in Germany or in pursuance of the
                                international obligations of their governments. Before so doing,
                                they will formally advise the appropriate German authorities of
                                their decision and of the reasons therefor.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The German Federal Government and the governments of the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> shall have the power, after due
                                notification to the occupation authorities, to legislate and act in
                                the fields reserved to these authorities, except as the occupation
                                authorities otherwise specifically direct, or as such legislation or
                                action would be inconsistent with decisions or actions taken by the
                                occupation authorities themselves.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Any amendment of the Basic Law will require the express approval
                                of the occupation authorities before becoming effective. <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> constitutions, amendments thereof, all
                                other legislation, and any agreements made between the Federal State
                                and foreign governments, will become effective twenty-one days after
                                its official receipt by the occupation authorities unless previously
                                disapproved by them, provisionally or finally. The occupation
                                authorities will not disapprove legislation unless in their opinion
                                it is inconsistent with the Basic Law, a <hi rend="italic">Land</hi>
                                Constitution, legislation or other directives of the occupation
                                authorities themselves or the provisions of this Instrument, or
                                unless it constitutes a grave threat to the basic purposes of the
                                occupation.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Subject only to the requirements of their security, the occupation
                                authorities guarantee that all agencies of the occupation will
                                respect the civil rights of every person to be protected against
                                arbitrary arrest, search or seizure; to be represented by counsel;
                                to be admitted to bail as circumstances warrant; to communicate with
                                relatives; and to have a fair and prompt trial.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Legislation of the occupation authorities enacted before the
                                effective date of the Basic Law shall remain in force until repealed
                                or <pb facs="0211" n="181" xml:id="pg_181"/> amended by the
                                occupation authorities in accordance with the following provisions: <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>legislation inconsistent with the foregoing will be
                                        repealed or amended to make it consistent herewith;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>legislation based upon the reserved powers, referred to in
                                        paragraph 2 above, will be codified;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>legislation not referred to in (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                                        and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) will be repealed by the
                                        occupation authorities on request from appropriate German
                                        authorities.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Any action shall be deemed to be the act of the occupation
                                authorities under the powers herein reserved, and effective as such
                                under this Instrument, when taken or evidenced in any manner
                                provided by any agreement between them. The occupation authorities
                                may in their discretion effectuate their decisions either directly
                                or through instructions to the appropriate German
                                authorities.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>After 12 months and in any event within 18 months of the effective
                                date of this Instrument the occupying powers will undertake a review
                                of its provisions in the light of experience with its operation and
                                with a view to extending the jurisdiction of the German authorities
                                in the legislative, executive and judicial fields.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper C]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Agreement as to Tripartite Controls</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">final text</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The Governments of the United Kingdom, France and the United States agree to
                        enter into a trizonal fusion agreement prior to the entry into effect of the
                        Occupation Statute. The representatives of the three occupying powers will
                        make the necessary arrangements to establish tripartite control machinery
                        for the Western zones of Germany, which will become effective at the time of
                        the establishment of a provisional German government. The following
                        provisions agreed by the Governments of the United Kingdom, France and the
                        United States shall form the basis of those arrangements: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>An Allied High Commission composed of one High Commissioner of
                                each occupying power or his representative shall be the supreme
                                Allied agency of control.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The nature and extent of controls exercised by the Allied High
                                Commission shall be in harmony with the Occupation Statute and
                                international agreements.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>In order to permit the German Federal Republic to exercise
                                increased responsibilities over domestic affairs and to reduce the
                                burden of occupation costs, staff personnel shall be kept to a
                                minimum.</item>
                            <pb facs="0212" n="182" xml:id="pg_182"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In the exercise of the powers reserved to the Occupation
                                Authorities to approve amendments to the Federal Constitution, the
                                decisions of the Allied High Commission shall require unanimous
                                agreement.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>In cases in which the exercise of, or failure to exercise, the
                                powers reserved under paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>) of the
                                Occupation Statute would increase the need for assistance from
                                United States Government appropriated funds, there shall be a system
                                of weighted voting. Under such system the representatives of the
                                Occupation Authorities will have a voting strength proportionate to
                                the funds made available to Germany by their respective governments.
                                This provision shall not, however, reduce the present United States
                                predominant voice in <gloss target="#t_JEIA1">JEIA</gloss> and
                                    <gloss target="#t_JFEA1">JFEA</gloss> while these organizations,
                                or any successor organization to them, continue in existence and are
                                charged with the performance of any of their present functions. No
                                action taken hereunder shall be contrary to any inter-governmental
                                agreement among the signatories or to the principles of
                                non-discrimination.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>On all other matters action shall be by majority vote.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) If a majority decision alters or
                                    modifies any intergovernmental agreement which relates to any of
                                    the subjects listed in paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and
                                        2(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of the Occupation Statute, any
                                    dissenting High Commissioner may appeal to his Government. This
                                    appeal shall serve to suspend the decision pending agreement
                                    between the three governments.</p>
                                <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) If a High Commissioner considers that
                                    a majority decision conflicts with any inter-governmental
                                    agreement which relates to any of the subjects in paragraph
                                        2(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and 2(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                                    of the Occupation Statute or with the fundamental principles for
                                    the conduct of Germany’s external relations or with matters
                                    essential to the security, prestige, and requirements of the
                                    occupying forces, he may appeal to his Government. Such an
                                    appeal shall serve to suspend action for 30 days, and thereafter
                                    unless two of the Governments indicate that the grounds do not
                                    justify further suspension.</p>
                                <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) If such appeal is from an action of
                                    the Allied High Commission either declining to disapprove or
                                    deciding to disapprove German legislation such legislation shall
                                    be provisionally disapproved for the duration of the appeal
                                    period.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>A High Commissioner who considers that a decision made by less
                                than unanimous vote involving any other matter reserved by the
                                Occupation Statute is not in conformity with basic tripartite
                                polices regarding Germany or that a <hi rend="italic">Land</hi>
                                constitution, or an amendment thereto, violates the Basic Law, may
                                appeal to his government. An appeal in this case shall serve to
                                suspend action for a period not to exceed twenty-one days from the
                                date of the decision unless all three governments agree otherwise.
                                If such appeal is from an action of the Allied High Commission
                                either declining to disapprove or deciding to disapprove German
                                legislation, such legislation shall be provisionally disapproved for
                                the duration of the appeal period.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>All powers of the Allied High Commission shall be uniformly
                                exercised in accordance with tripartite policies and directives. To
                                this end in each <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> the Allied High
                                Commission shall be represented by a single <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> Commissioner who shall be solely responsible to it
                                for all tripartite affairs. In each <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> Commissioner shall be a <pb facs="0213" n="183" xml:id="pg_183"/> national of the Allied
                                Power in whose zone the <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> is situated.
                                Outside his own zone each High Commissioner will delegate an
                                observer to each of the <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> Commissioners
                                for purposes of consultation and information. Nothing in this
                                paragraph shall be construed to limit the functions of bodies
                                established pursuant to inter-governmental agreement.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>To the greatest extent possible, all directives and other
                                instruments of control shall be addressed to the federal and/or <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> authorities.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>The Trizonal Fusion Agreement will continue in force until altered
                                by agreement among the governments.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper D]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Agreed Minute Respecting Berlin</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">final text</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>It was agreed that the provisions of the Agreement as to Tripartite Controls
                        shall be applied as far as practicable to the Western sectors of
                            Berlin.<note n="4" xml:id="d66fn4">
                            <p>Following the agreement on the occupation statute for Western
                                Germany, the three Western Military Governors discussed a separate
                                statute for the Western sectors of Berlin, which would assume the
                                same principles as far as practicable. This statement of principles
                                governing the relationships between the Allied Kommandatura and
                                Greater Berlin, promulgated by the Western Military Governors on May
                                14, is printed in <hi rend="italic">Germany 1947–1949</hi>, pp.
                                324–326. Documentation relating to its negotiation is in file
                                740.00119 Control (Germany)/4–849 through 5–1449.</p>
                            <p>At the same time the internal procedures of the Allied Kommandatura
                                were revised to conform to the agreement on tripartite controls. The
                                text of the new procedures, agreed on May 14, was transmitted in
                                telegram 729, May 14, from Berlin, not printed (740.00119 Control
                                (Germany)/5–1449).</p>
                            <p>A photograph of the signing of the new Berlin statutes will be found
                                following <ref target="#pg_642">page 642</ref>.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper E]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Agreed Minute on Claims Against Germany</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">final text</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The governments of France, the United Kingdom and the United States will
                        proceed, in consultation with other governments concerned, to develop
                        proposals for the settlement of financial claims against Germany, claims
                        arising out of the war which remain unsettled, claims with respect to Allied
                        property in Germany, and other questions of an economic or legal character
                        arising out of the existence of a state of war between Germany and the
                        Allied Powers. There should also be appropriate consultations with the
                        German Federal Republic. Prior <pb facs="0214" n="184" xml:id="pg_184"/> to
                        the relinquishment of reserved powers in the field of foreign exchange, the
                        three governments will give consideration to the desirability of obtaining
                        from the German Federal Government formal recognition of such claims.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper F]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Agreed Minute on Wuerttemberg–Baden Plebiscite</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">final text</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>It was agreed that the status quo in Wuerttemberg and Baden would be
                        maintained for the time being and that the plebiscite recommended by the
                        German Ministers President would be postponed in the interest of avoiding
                        any possible delay in the establishment of the German Federal
                        Government.</p>
                    <p>It was further agreed that the question of the Wuerttemberg–Baden <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> boundaries would be reexamined after the
                        establishment of the German Federal Government.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper G]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Agreement Regarding Kehl</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">final text</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The French control authorities with the assistance of the Strasbourg French
                        authorities will maintain under existing conditions jurisdiction over the
                        Kehl port zone until establishment of the German Federal Government and
                        conclusion of negotiations between the French and German Authorities with
                        respect to a joint port administration for Kehl.</p>
                    <p>It was agreed, on a proposal of the French Government, that the city of Kehl
                        would gradually be returned to German administration. It was foreseen that
                        the French temporarily domiciled in Kehl might remain during a four-year
                        period required for the preparation of additional housing in Strasbourg.
                        Around one-third of the French inhabitants will be able to leave Kehl within
                        several months, and the remainder progressively thereafter as housing
                        becomes available.</p>
                    <p>The final decision with respect to the Kehl port zone will be made in the
                        peace settlement. If the port authority develops harmoniously, the US and UK
                        will be willing at the time of the peace settlement to bring an attitude of
                        good will toward the establishment of a permanent joint authority.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0215" n="185" xml:id="pg_185"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper H]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Message to the Military Governors From the Foreign
                            Ministers of the</hi> US, UK <hi rend="smallcaps">and France</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>To the Military Governors:</p>
                    <p>For your guidance the Foreign Ministers of the US, UK and France transmit
                        their views on the Basic Law. It is left to the Military Governors to
                        determine the time they may consider it appropriate to communicate these
                        views to the Parliamentary Council, but the Foreign Ministers wish that they
                        be transmitted before opinion in the Parliamentary Council has crystallized,
                        in order that the views given below may be reflected in the Basic Law.</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <list>
                                <item>“(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The Foreign Ministers are not able
                                    to agree at this time that Berlin should be included as a <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> in the initial organization of the
                                    German Federal Republic.</item>
                                <item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) In the financial field any
                                    provisions put forward by the Parliamentary Council in the
                                    direction of securing financial independence and adequate
                                    strength for both the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> and Federal
                                    Governments in operating in their respective fields will receive
                                    sympathetic consideration.</item>
                                <item>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) On the question of Article 36
                                    (Article 95 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)) they will also give
                                    sympathetic consideration to any formula which <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">i</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>eliminates from the federal powers those matters
                                            definitely excluded by the London agreement.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">ii</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>assures to the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>
                                            sufficient powers to enable them to be independent and
                                            vigorous governmental bodies.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">iii</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>assures to the Federal Government sufficient powers in
                                            the important fields of government to enable them to
                                            deal effectively with those fields in which the
                                            interests of more than one <hi rend="italic">Land</hi>
                                            are substantially and necessarily involved.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <item>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) Finally, the Foreign Ministers
                                    request that the Military Governors indicate to the
                                    Parliamentary Council, at an appropriate time, that they are
                                    ready to contemplate a suggestion for a right of the Federal
                                    State to supplement, from its own revenues, appropriations made
                                    by the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> from revenues from their
                                    own taxes levied and collected by them, by grants for education,
                                    health and welfare purposes, subject in each case to specific
                                    approval of the Bundesrat.”<note n="5" xml:id="d66fn5">A paper
                                        in the Department of State files, apparently prepared in the
                                        Department of the Army, dated April 6, not printed, traces
                                        the development of the Basic Law and the Military Governors’
                                        respective positions on it through the end of March. In this
                                        paper it was suggested that two courses of action could be
                                        taken: the Foreign Ministers could change their policy which
                                        required a federal structure for Germany and accept the
                                        German proposals or adhere to the position of the Military
                                        Governors which required further changes by the Germans. If
                                        the second alternative were taken the Military Governors
                                        would either decline further discussion with the Germans or
                                        propose further discussions with the idea of clarifying the
                                        Military Governors’ position. The paper proposed that if the
                                        latter step were taken a proposal should be made by the
                                        Military Governors to indicate their views and gave the text
                                        of such a statement. The content of this proposal reflects
                                        exactly the ideas and wording of sub-paragraphs <hi rend="italic">a, b, c i–iii</hi>, of Paper H, although
                                        its drafting form is different. (740.00119 Control
                                        (Germany)/4–649)</note>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0216" n="186" xml:id="pg_186"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Paper I]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Message to the Bonn Parlimentary Council From the
                            Foreign Ministers of the</hi> US, UK <hi rend="smallcaps">and
                            France</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-08">April 8,
                                1949</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>To the Military Governors:</p>
                    <p>The Foreign Ministers of the US, UK and France request you to transmit to the
                        Parliamentary Council at Bonn the following message on their behalf:</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Foreign Ministers have considered the problem of a Federal German
                            Republic in all its aspects in Washington and have come to a number of
                            important decisions of policy in regard thereto. They have decided that,
                            in general, the German authorities shall be at liberty to take
                            administrative and legislative action, and that such action will have
                            validity if not vetoed by Allied authorities. There will be certain
                            limited fields in which the Allies will reserve the right to take direct
                            action themselves and which are set out in the Occupation Statute, a
                            copy of which is attached hereto.<note n="6" xml:id="d66fn6">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_179">p.
                                179</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>With the establishment of the German Federal Republic, Military
                            Government as such will terminate and the functions of the Allied
                            Authorities will be divided—control functions being exercised by a High
                            Commissioner and Military functions by a Commander-in-Chief. The three
                            High Commissioners together will constitute an Allied High Commission,
                            and it is the aim of the three governments to restrict to a minimum the
                            size of the supervisory staffs attached to their respective High
                            Commissioners.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Ministers further affirm that it is a major objective of the
                            three Allied Governments to encourage and facilitate the closest
                            integration on a mutually beneficial basis of the German people under a
                            democratic Federal State within the framework of a European
                            association.</p>
                        <p>Nevertheless, before the far-reaching developments which they contemplate
                            can be put in hand, it is essential that an agreement should be reached
                            by the Parliamentary Council upon a Basic Law for the German Federal
                            Republic.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
