<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        United States Political Adviser for Germany (
                        Murphy
                    ), at Berlin</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d72</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">72</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-02-07T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-02-07T19:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-07T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-07T19:00:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.011/2–749: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MRD1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">at Berlin</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-07T19:00:00-05:00">February 7, 1949—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>151. Personal for <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>. No
                    distribution outside of Department.</p>
                <p>In <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1546, Aug 28,<note n="1" xml:id="d72fn1">
                        <ref target="frus1948v02#pg_416">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 416</ref>.</note> Dept concurred in Mil
                    Govrs position that Berlin reps shld not vote at Bonn Parliamentary Council
                    although they might otherwise participate in deliberations. While we recognize
                    paramount role played by Berlin population and democratically elected municipal
                    administration and realize advantages of association democratic elements of
                    Berlin with Western Ger Govt, nevertheless believe basic considerations
                    obtaining last Aug still apply, making ill-advised full voting participation of
                    Berlin delegates in West Ger provisional Govt.</p>
                <p>Western Allied position at Berlin is based on fundamental rights embodied in
                    Four-Power agreements. Although these rights are not respected by Soviets,
                    nevertheless it wld seem unwise to permit Berlin reps formal association with
                    West Ger Govt of such nature as to contradict conception on which Allied
                    affirmation of rights at Berlin is based. Incorporation of Berlin, i.e. Western
                    sectors, as <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> in Western Ger state under present
                    air-lift circumstances, does not make good sense to us, and wld greatly
                    complicate any solution of Berlin problem. Its inclusion in Western Ger state
                    wld involve so many special complications of administrative and governmental
                    nature that mistake to burden new Western Ger Govt with whole weight of Berlin
                    issue.</p>
                <p>Circumstance that city has been effectively split by Soviet action would appear
                    make particularly artificial incorporation Western sectors as <hi rend="italic">Land</hi> in Western Ger Govt.</p>
                <p>We believe that Berlin reps shld be associated with Western Ger Govt but cannot
                    see how they can properly enjoy other than non-voting status. Although it wld
                    have been preferable for Gers themselves propose solution along non-voting
                    lines, we believe Mil Govt will have to insist on such solution. (Urtels 133 Jan
                    26; 175, Feb 3; 183, Feb 4.<note n="2" xml:id="d72fn2">Telegrams 133 and 175 not
                        printed; 183, <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi>
                    </note>)</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AD1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
