<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany ( (Murphy) ) to the Director
                    of the Office of European Affairs ( (Hickerson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HPZNpQil9Rnjj" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-civil-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026387"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil Service</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recOAfZ9FRSJKK76a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Income tax</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="82"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/3–449</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName corresp="#p_MRD1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Office of European
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HJD1" type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-04">March 4,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Jack</hi>: With reference to the attached memorandum
                    of the meeting of the three Western Military Governors at Frankfurt on March 1,
                    I feel that the result on the whole was a happy one which promises well for the
                    future. The discussion of the provisions of the Basic Law started off in a
                    rather difficult atmosphere by a statement from General <persName
                        corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> with a reference to the London Agreement
                    providing <pb facs="0242" n="212" xml:id="pg_212"/> that the Basic Law would
                    have a federal character and that the Military Governors were to determine
                    whether the text was satisfactory in that respect. General <persName
                        corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> said that, after an examination of the
                    text, it did not take much time to appreciate that it is a federal document in
                    appearance only—that it is hypocritically federal but actually centralist. With
                    that as an opening statement, I began to fear that the chances of French
                    approval were dim indeed. However, General <persName corresp="#p_K1"
                        >Koenig</persName> continued on that, while the Military Governors could
                    veto on the ground that it did not conform to the London Accord, he nevertheless
                    suggested that the Military Governors not leave [<hi rend="italic">let</hi>] the
                    draft break down and that he would be willing to consider listing certain
                    changes and modifications with the assurance that his government would be
                    willing to consider them. For this purpose the report of the Political
                        Advisers<note n="1" xml:id="d82fn1">Transmitted in telegram 144, February
                        25, <ref target="#pg_207">p. 207</ref>.</note> would provide a suitable
                    basis.</p>
                <p>At this point General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> pointed out a
                    feature relating to the present text—that there was no official text before the
                    Military Governors and in view of General <persName corresp="#p_K1"
                        >Koenig</persName>’s remarks it might be better to await a vote of the
                    Parliamentary Council at Bonn. The Germans would then publish the document as an
                    official text which would enable the Military Governors to benefit by the
                    opinion of world constitutional experts. He suggested that the Germans be
                    advised to vote their text immediately and the Military Governors would then
                    examine it in accordance with the London Agreement. The discussions then would
                    concern a public document. This suggestion was not happily received by <persName
                        corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName>, who said that such procedure would lead
                    to a test of force between the Germans and ourselves and which would not be
                    desirable. I think that General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>’s
                    suggestion had the effect of stimulating the French to a more conciliatory
                    attitude which was apparent after they had consulted Paris by telephone.</p>
                <p>Yours ever,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bob</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]<note n="2" xml:id="d82fn2">Attached to
                                the source text was another memorandum by <persName
                                    corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName>, March 3, not printed,
                                which reported the Military Governors’ discussion of Berlin
                                currency, the Military Security Board, travel control, and the
                                administration of Spandau prison.</note>
                        </seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Counselor of Mission at Berlin</hi>
                            (<persName corresp="#p_RJW1" type="from">
                            <hi rend="italic">Riddleberger</hi>
                        </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the United States Political Adviser for
                            Germany</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MRD1" type="to">
                            <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                        </persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-03">March 3,
                                1949</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Military Governors’ Consideration of Draft
                        Constitution.</p>
                    <p>The three Western Military Governors met three times in Frankfurt on March
                        1–2, 1949 and devoted the major part of their deliberations <pb facs="0243"
                            n="213" xml:id="pg_213"/> to an examination of the draft basic law as
                        developed by the Parliamentary Council at Bonn. The Military Governors had
                        before them at their first meeting on March 1 the report of the Political
                        Advisers dated February 24 which was cabled textually to the Department in
                        Frankfurt’s 144 and 145 of February 25.<note n="3" xml:id="d82fn3">Telegram
                            144, <ref target="#pg_207">p. 207</ref>; regarding telegram 145, see
                            footnote 5 to telegram 144.</note> The draft constitution had been
                        previously transmitted to the Department by your Frankfurt Office under date
                        of February 12, 1949.<note n="4" xml:id="d82fn4">Not printed; for the text
                            of the draft constitution, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on the German
                                Federal Constitution</hi>, pp. 88–105.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> opened the discussion on
                        the Political Advisers’ report in stating that he thought the report was a
                        good one which clearly expressed the differences between the Military
                        Governors. <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> at once replied in a
                        statement which was severely critical of the draft constitution. He argued
                        that under cover of federal appearance, the Germans have constructed a draft
                        which completely opens the way for reestablishment of a highly centralized
                        government. The work at Bonn was not sincerely federalist in nature and
                        would be condemned by those who wanted a truly decentralized government. The
                        Military Governors should therefore declare the Bonn draft incompatible with
                        the London decisions and disapprove it. However, as <persName
                            corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> did not wish to see an immediate break
                        down, he was prepared to envisage amendments and corrections which might
                        make possible acceptance of the constitution. He was also prepared to
                        concentrate upon amendments to articles which, while few in number were
                        essential to a federal state.</p>
                    <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> then reminded <persName
                            corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> that as there was no official. German
                        constitution before the Military Governors there are two ways of proceeding.
                        The first would be to defer discussion until the Parliamentary Council
                        formally submitted the constitution which would then be a public document
                        and the Military Governors together with their governments would have the
                        reaction of constitutional experts throughout the world on the work which
                        had been done in Bonn. The Military Governors could then suggest that the
                        Germans be told to finish their work and the discussion would be on a public
                        document. <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> stated at this point
                        that while <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>’s principle was
                        probably a good one it was not practicable in that it would lead to a test
                        of strength between the Parliamentary Council and the Military Governors.
                        Therefore, it was wise to move in a more conciliatory way and he would agree
                        to discuss the report of the Political Advisers. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> said that his second point would be a
                        discussion of the report and that he was prepared to do so. He, however,
                        reserved the right, if no agreement was reached by the Military Governors,
                        to tell the Germans to go ahead and finish the constitution. <persName
                            corresp="#p_RNA1">Robertson</persName> agreed with <persName
                            corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> that the Germans have the <pb
                            facs="0244" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/> right to continue but favored
                        giving the views of the Military Governors to the Germans now if possible.
                        He thought it would be tragic to reject the constitution and it must be
                        remembered that the document would have to be ratified. If the Germans
                        accepted modifications it would have a better chance of ratification.</p>
                    <p>This proposal of General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>’s to
                        have the Germans finish their work and publish the constitution obviously
                        took the French by surprise and in my opinion was influential in modifying
                        materially their negative attitude toward the document. The Military
                        Governors then proceeded to discuss the report paragraph by paragraph.
                            <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> led off by making strong
                        objections to Articles 36 and 36(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of the
                        constitution. The tenor of his argument was that there should be only two
                        categories of federal legislation: (1) exclusive, as in Article 35, and (2)
                        nominal, as in Article 36(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>). Furthermore, Article 36
                            (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) should embody the formula devised by the
                        Political Advisers for Article 36(2). General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1"
                            >Clay</persName> responded that no government could operate under such
                        restrictions. He could accept Article 35 and agreed that Article 36 lacked
                        clarity and should be amended to give legislative powers on the matters
                        enunciated therein when they clearly affect more than one state. General
                            <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Robertson</persName> suggested that a
                        compromise might be found by transferring the redraft of Article 36(2) to
                        the head of the article and then combining Articles 36 and 36(<hi
                            rend="italic">a</hi>). After a somewhat extended discussion as to the
                        effect of this it was eventually agreed that this compromise might be
                        acceptable and the question was passed to the Political Advisers for
                        drafting.</p>
                    <p>Paragraph 2 of the report respecting police powers was accepted in principle
                        on the understanding that if the occupation authorities are ultimately
                        responsible for security the powers in Article 118(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)
                        cannot be exercised until specifically approved.</p>
                    <p>Consideration was then given to the question of financial powers. <persName
                            corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> stated this was a most important
                        subject and that he concurred in the suggestions of the Political Advisers
                        with one reservation. He believed that the federal government should
                        administer only federal taxes and not concurrent taxes which should be
                        administered by the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> even if the federal
                        government takes over entirely concurrent taxes. He stated that if this
                        proposal was acceptable, the French would abandon their reservation on
                        occupation costs. <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Robertson</persName> strongly
                        urged that the federal government should have the right to collect taxes
                        which it legislates and that once it has decided to take over a concurrent
                        tax it becomes a federal tax. Such was the provision of the Letter of
                        Advice. At this point <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> proposed
                        the formula which eventually led to agreement on the financial articles. He
                        said that except in the field of excise, income, inheritance and gift <pb
                            facs="0245" n="215" xml:id="pg_215"/> taxes, all other concurrent taxes
                        should be administered by the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>. By skillful
                        and persuasive argument, and with frequent reference to our own tax system,
                        he eventually convinced <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> that
                        federal taxes should be administered by federal administration. He argued
                        that the French desire to avoid federal tax administration could only lead
                        to having the federal government interfere more and more in the financial
                        affairs of the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> in that it would be giving
                        instructions to the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> financial authorities on
                        taxes over which it exercised jurisdiction. If the French wanted financial
                        autonomy for the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> they could not have it both
                        ways by opposing federal administration of federal taxes while
                        simultaneously opposing federal instructions to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Laender</hi> finance administrations. It was far better in his opinion
                        to segregate the taxes and let federal taxes be administered federally and
                        state taxes administered by the <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi>. <persName
                            corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> eventually agreed to this line of
                        argument subject to draft.</p>
                    <p>With respect to the independence of the judiciary the UK Military Governor
                        was not entirely satisfied with Article 129(1) and wished to draw the
                        attention of the Parliamentary Council to possible safeguards in connection
                        with the dismissal of judges. After a short discussion this was agreed.</p>
                    <p>On the powers of the federation to establish its own agencies and the French
                        reservation thereto, General <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>
                        made a very cogent argument to the effect that there is less danger in
                        [allowing] federal agencies to enforce federal law than there is allowing
                        the federal government powers to give orders to the states. A long exchange
                        ensued between him and <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> in which
                            <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> by drawing upon American
                        precedence [<hi rend="italic">precedents?</hi>] eventually succeeded in
                        obtaining <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName>’s agreement to
                        withdrawing the French reservation provided the drafting on Articles 36 and
                            36(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) was satisfactory.</p>
                    <p>With respect to civil service it was eventually agreed that if the Germans
                        decided to retain Articles 27(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) and 62 in the
                        constitution they must conform to the principles enunciated in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire.</hi>
                        <note n="5" xml:id="d82fn5">For the text of the <hi rend="italic"
                                >aide-mémoire</hi> of the Military Governors to the Bonn
                            Parliamentary Council, November 22, 1948, see <ref
                                target="frus1948v02#pg_240">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 240</ref>.</note> The Military
                        Governors do not insist, however, that the constitution contain such
                        provisions as the question can be dealt with by legislation.</p>
                    <p>On the question of <hi rend="italic">Laender</hi> reorganization, it was
                        decided to repeat precisely what the Ministers President had been told on
                        July 20, 1948 and to reiterate that the position is still the same.<note
                            n="6" xml:id="d82fn6">The minutes of the meeting between the Military
                            Governors and the Ministers-President of the Western zones of Germany,
                            at Frankfurt, July 20, 1948, are printed <ref
                                target="frus1948v02#pg_403">
                                <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 403</ref>.</note> Incidentally,
                            <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> informed <persName
                            corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> in a meeting on March 2 that he
                        intended to raise this question at the next meeting of the Military
                        Governors in order to get <pb facs="0246" n="216" xml:id="pg_216"/> a
                        decision on what the Germans can be told respecting the Ministers
                        President’s proposal on Wuerttemberg–Baden.</p>
                    <p>The debate then turned to a formula for Berlin. <persName corresp="#p_K1"
                            >Koenig</persName> announced the French opposition to Berlin’s inclusion
                        but indicated some desire to move for a compromise. Here again <persName
                            corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> came forward with a proposal which
                        was eventually accepted and which is incorporated in paragraph 10 of the
                        statement to the Germans. There was some discussion of how many Berlin
                        representatives might attend but for the time being the question is left
                        over. In any case it would not be more than what Berlin would be entitled to
                        in proportion to its population. At this point the discussions on the
                        constitution were concluded and it was arranged that the Political Advisers
                        would meet in the afternoon to be followed by another session of the
                        Military Governors in the evening on March 1.</p>
                    <p>At the evening meeting the Military Governors had before them a draft
                        statement to be communicated to representatives of the Parliamentary Council
                        which had been prepared by the Political Advisers. This statement was cabled
                        to the Department by our Frankfurt Office on March 1.<note n="7"
                            xml:id="d82fn7">Transmitted in telegram 178, March 1, from Frankfurt,
                            not printed. (862.011/3–149)</note> Additional discussion followed on
                        paragraph 1 of Article 36 as redrafted by the Political Advisers. <persName
                            corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> was still holding out for the French
                        brackets and <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> suggested the
                        compromise proposal which emphasized the right of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Laender</hi> to retain legislative authority in the fields listed
                        except where the matter clearly involved more than one <hi rend="italic"
                            >Land.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>On the financial provisions, <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName>
                        returned once more to the charge by claiming the federal power in concurrent
                        taxes was still too large. <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName>
                        eventually obtained <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName>’s agreement
                        by stipulating that the income tax would be administered by federal
                        authorities to the extent that such a tax is for federal purposes. This
                        compromise disposed of the financial provisions although <persName
                            corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> was still protesting that too much
                        taxing power was given to the federal government.</p>
                    <p>The other paragraphs of the statement were agreed to down to the final one
                        dealing with Berlin. <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> again
                        balked at Berlin participation in federal legislature and it looked
                        momentarily as if the discussion would break down on this point. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> then stated that such participation
                        was not prohibited by the London decisions but he was not disposed further
                        to argue the matter. He proposed that the Parliamentary Council be informed
                        that agreement could not be reached and the decision was up to it whether to
                        adopt the constitution in plenary session. Faced with this statement,
                            <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> then said that he would not
                        object to having a small number of representatives designated to attend.
                            <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1">Clay</persName> stated he could accept
                        “designated” but could not forbid <pb facs="0247" n="217" xml:id="pg_217"/>
                        consultation and pointed out that it would be difficult to prevent
                        attendance in any case. <persName corresp="#p_K1">Koenig</persName> promised
                        an answer by midnight.</p>
                    <p>Following this evening session the Political Advisers reconvened on the
                        morning of March 2 to prepare a clean draft of the statement to be
                        communicated that same day to representatives of the Parliamentary Council,
                        who had been advised the night before to come to Frankfurt. This draft was
                        ready for consideration by 11 o’clock on March 2, 1949.<note n="8"
                            xml:id="d82fn8">For the text of the clear draft, see telegram 183, <hi
                                rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>At the meeting of the Military Governors <persName corresp="#p_CGLD1"
                            >Clay</persName> stated he was ready to accept the statement as a whole.
                            <persName corresp="#p_RNA1">Robertson</persName> was likewise prepared
                        to do so but wished to clarify the interpretation of paragraph 10 on Berlin.
                        He said that he wished no misunderstanding and that his position was that
                        the number of representatives is not determined and the Berlin
                        representatives can speak. His understanding of the French interpretation
                        was that the Berlin representatives would not speak. If the Germans inquired
                        about this, it was agreed that no definite answer would be given. The
                        Military Governors then discussed the type of statement which <persName
                            corresp="#p_RNA1">Robertson</persName> would make if the representatives
                        of the Parliamentary Council inquired whether the statement must be accepted
                        in its entirety. The line that <persName corresp="#p_RNA1"
                            >Robertson</persName> would take was reported from Frankfurt by telegram
                        of March 2, 1949.</p>
                    <p>The Military Governors then discussed the question of the electoral law and
                        their decision was likewise reported in the same telegram. The text of the
                        electoral law was previously transmitted from Frankfurt.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">J. W. R[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                    >iddleberger</hi>
                            </persName>]</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
