<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-10-24T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-10-24T09:00:00-05:00" n="133" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                        <head>133. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission in Berlin</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d133fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 762A.00/10–2457. Confidential; Priority; Limited
                                Distribution. Repeated to Bonn.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-10-24T15:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">October 24,
                                        1957—3 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>483. For the Secretary from Bruce. Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> has been confirmed in power for another four
                            years. Even in the event of his death or retirement, his party, the
                                <gloss target="#t_CDU1">CDU</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CSU1">CSU</gloss>, could be expected to maintain its position as the
                            dominant force in West German politics during that period.</p>
                        <p>The question as to who might succeed him, if he should relinquish his
                            office, remains unanswered. It has frequently been posed. On one
                            occasion, he is said to have responded: “Look at Churchill. He had
                            designated <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName> as his heir
                            apparent; I shall not make a similar mistake.”</p>
                        <p>It is to be anticipated and hoped that the United States will, for a
                            considerable span of time, be dealing with <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>, who will control a majority in the West German
                            parliament. If the “old fox” remains on the scene we can make
                            assumptions that might well be unwarranted in case of his removal from
                            it.</p>
                        <p>The recent <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> campaign was
                            characterized by a frank and repeated avowal of his loyalty to American
                            foreign policy. The assertions of independence of the United States, of
                            suspicion of its motives and intentions, so clearly manifested in
                            certain other European countries, evoked no imitation in the Federal
                            Republic. The Chancellor was constant in his theme: namely, that there
                            are two great power complexes in the world, the USSR and the USA.
                            Germany, a second, or even third rate power, must make its choice
                            between the two, and its selection must be alliance, friendship and
                            fidelity to the USA and an unswerving adherence to the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> alliance. In private, <pb facs="0344" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> he expressed the opinion that the United
                            States should exercise greater leadership in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, and cease to be so tender about the national
                            susceptibilities of other members.</p>
                        <p>In short, while <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> continues
                            in authority, and directs his almost authoritarian prerogatives to the
                            ends in which he sincerely believes, it is probable that occasions will
                            seldom arise likely to precipitate a marked division of interest or
                            objective between our two countries. Even if there should occur clashes
                            of temperament or opinion, they should be capable of sub rosa
                            settlement.</p>
                        <p>The position occupied by the <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> in
                            Europe, geographically, economically and financially, together with its
                            as yet unrealized military potential, would be disturbing if one
                            entertained doubts as to <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>’s future attitudes toward foreign policy. These
                            will be determined, I believe, by his estimate of the wisdom with which
                            he thinks American foreign policy is being conducted. He must be fully
                            sensible of the peculiar and favorable posture of his own country, and
                            how a tempting oscillation between East and West might contribute to its
                            superficial benefit.</p>
                        <p>No such hesitation, however, as far as one can presently speculate, has
                            been cherished by him (though it may have entered into his
                            calculations). Moreover, despite its startling achievements in other
                            fields, the <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> has not yet
                            regained its prestige in political affairs. Its governors are ambitious
                            to serve as mediators, or as second best to influence the play of events
                            in the Middle East, as well as in Africa. Freed of the erstwhile taint
                            of colonialism, no longer possessors of territories, their brutal
                            management of dependent peoples almost forgotten, they toy with the
                            pleasing idea that they are less suspect in the Arab and African
                            countries than are other nations still exercising suzerainty in those
                            murky localities.</p>
                        <p>Torn by a feeling of guilt toward the Jews, to whom they are in course of
                            making periodic financial atonement, they have not yet decided whether
                            to accord diplomatic recognition to Israel, or to rationalize their
                            refusal to do so by asserting the greater usefulness of their role as
                            impartial and uncommitted observers of regrettable national
                            rivalries.</p>
                        <p>In relation to the Soviet satellites in Eastern Europe, their future
                            course of action is also not resolved. Intrigued by the possibilities
                            inherent in the Polish situation, and, in lesser degree, elsewhere, much
                            study has been pursued by them as to how best they might maneuver to
                            their own and allied advantage by an increase in their trade, and more
                            formal relationships in that area. The recent recognition by Yugoslavia
                            of the so-called East German Republic and the swift Federal Republic
                            riposte to this action has postponed whatever plans were being evolved
                            by <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> and his counselors in
                            this connection. Nevertheless, it may be expected that a resumption of
                            attention <pb facs="0345" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/> to such
                            relationships will again be brought under advisement. The historical
                            trend of preoccupation with Turkey and lands farther east has begun to
                            reassert itself. Delegations of responsible Germans have begun to
                            investigate commercial opportunities, especially in Turkey and Iran, and
                            their government can be expected to support, with ample credits,
                            undertakings of a nature which might promise ultimate advantages to its
                            citizens.</p>
                        <p>Everywhere, the <gloss target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> is expanding
                            its thrust outward, taking moderate but adventurous risks. Its preferred
                            partner in these fields would be the United States. I believe we should
                            have intimate conversations at an early date with German administrators
                            to ascertain whether a combination in some places of our outlays might
                            not be of mutual benefit, and likely to advance our political
                            objectives. In the domain of economic aid, consultation, and possibly
                            joint action, with the Germans might multiply the effectiveness of our
                            present programs. In conjunction with them and other allies, we might
                            enter into arrangements with rich native governments, such as those of
                            Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Iraq and Iran to sponsor and participate in area
                            development schemes, instead of bearing alone the burden of supplying
                            manpower and funds for such purposes, with little assurance our efforts
                            will be rewarded even by so evanescent a tribute as short-lived
                            gratitude.</p>
                        <p>It would be idle to dwell on the possibilities of fruitful cooperation
                            between the Germans and ourselves if the result would be to weaken our
                            indispensable ties with older and more proven allies. But such would not
                            be the case, if we could arrive at an understanding with Germany,
                            prosperous of [<hi rend="italic">to</hi>?] our associates, subject to
                            the multilateral endorsement and participation of others. It seems to me
                            unwise to await longer a concerted movement, of which there are no
                            apparent signs, conducive to a broadening of Western influence in the
                            satellite and other worlds, when a commencement to that end might be
                            made in partnership with the only friendly nation now [able?] to afford
                            like ourselves a venture of this scope.</p>
                        <p>There is much talk of “grand designs” and careless paternity of other
                            resounding phrases. But while <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> is still alive and active, should we not search
                            out his designs, if any? To do so would not be difficult, for the
                            Germans are not the least vocal of peoples. They labor under a subdued
                            sense of guilt, and will not be the first to extend an invitation. Their
                            dynamism is extraordinary, but it has been chiefly devoted to an
                            animation of their domestic concerns. I think it can be harnessed to
                            broader uses, consonant with US aims. I shall not in this telegram
                            suggest how this might be done, but call your attention to an
                            imperfectly utilized source of strength and <pb facs="0346" n="318" xml:id="pg_318"/> energy, which, although at present not being
                            dissipated, is too exclusively devoted to narrow national
                                aspirations.<note n="2" xml:id="d133fn2">In telegram 1165 to Bonn,
                                October 28, <persName>Dulles</persName> told Bruce: “Thanks for your
                                thought piece No. 483. This is stimulating and helpful.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 762A.00/10–2457)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName>Hillenbrand</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>