<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>213. National Security Council Report</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d213</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">213</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recu0jAoErrAESV42" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002775"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Airlift</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recPnftMNhM1QKAYO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Stockpile</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recUInGVZ0Y3MeuOS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recCsCQEIVOqq2438" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recykDuvfC6iFH3Xe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="213"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d213">
                <head>213. National Security Council Report<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d213fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_SS1"
                            >S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot 63 D 351,
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5727 Series. Top Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="italic">Supplement I to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            5727</hi>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d213fn2">
                            <ref target="#d136">Document 136</ref>.</note>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-12-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 13, 1957</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">STATEMENT OF POLICY ON U.S. POLICY ON BERLIN</p>
                <p rend="center">General Considerations</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Under existing treaties and U.S. policies, an attack on Berlin would
                        involve the United States in war with the USSR. The Soviet rulers probably
                        would not use Soviet forces to drive the Western powers from Berlin unless
                        they had decided on war for reasons other than their desire to control the
                        city.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Short of direct military attack, the USSR has the capability of making the
                        Western position in Berlin untenable by restricting Western access to the
                        city.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The United States, the U.K. and France demonstrated their determination to
                        stay in Berlin when the USSR blockaded the city in 1948. Although the
                        military posture of the Allies was too weak at that time to permit the
                        forceful assertion of the Allies’ right of surface entry into Berlin,
                        counter measures were taken by the Allies, especially the Berlin airlift,
                        which caused the Soviet Union to lift the blockade. In view of the past and
                        of outstanding commitments, the Allies could not afford to permit themselves
                        to be driven from Berlin.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Since the end of the blockade in 1949, there have been several
                        developments which affect Western capabilities in Berlin. <pb facs="0550"
                            n="522" xml:id="pg_522"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>The military readiness of the Allies in Europe has
                                improved.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>The Kremlin leaders have been put on notice that the United States
                                is determined to remain in Berlin and will use the necessary
                                measures to protect the Western right of access. (See Annex)<note
                                    n="3" xml:id="d213fn3">Not printed.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>The Soviet Foreign Minister in 1949 joined in a “quadripartite
                                gentlemen’s agreement” which was a “moral and political undertaking”
                                not to reimpose restrictions on access to Berlin. Reimposition of a
                                blockade would violate the Soviet Government’s acceptance of this
                                agreement, which was embodied in the modus vivendi for Germany of
                                June 20, 1949.<note n="4" xml:id="d213fn4">For text, see <ref
                                        target="frus1949v03#pg_1062">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1949, vol. III, p.
                                        1062</ref>.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Since 1949 the Soviets have taken various measures which would
                                reduce the effect of the counter-blockade measures used by the
                                Allies in 1949.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>A stockpile has been accumulated in Berlin to lessen the
                                vulnerability of the city to a blockade. Emphasis has been placed on
                                commodities difficult to airlift, those of great bulk such as grain
                                and coal and selected industrial materials. The present plan for the
                                composition of the uncompleted portion of the stockpile presupposes
                                that the stockpile will be supplemented by an airlift during a
                                blockade.</item>
                            <label>f.</label>
                            <item>Soviet capabilities of interference with an airlift, particularly
                                in the field of electro-magnetic warfare, have considerably improved
                                since 1949, but now, as then, the possibility of imposing a total
                                blockade depends upon the readiness to force down Allied planes in
                                agreed corridors, with all the implications of such acts. In
                                addition, an airlift would involve high costs in military readiness.
                                A full-scale airlift with the stockpile could sustain Berlin for a
                                considerable period of time; but nonetheless it is doubtful that the
                                institution of an airlift would cause the Soviets to discontinue a
                                blockade which might be imposed now.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Therefore the reimposition by the USSR of a blockade or severe harassing
                        measures would be a deliberate challenge to the Western powers’ position in
                        Berlin. Moreover, the prestige of the United States as the leader of the
                        free world is deeply committed in Berlin. If the Soviets initiate harassing
                        measures to restrict access to Berlin, it will be of crucial importance to
                        demonstrate at once the firm intent of the United States not to tolerate
                        such action. If Soviet harassment nonetheless continues to threaten Western
                        access to Berlin, the security interests of the United States and its Allies
                        will require them to take immediate and forceful action to counter the
                        Soviet challenge, even though such countermeasures might lead to general
                        war.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>At this time, the U.K. and France will not be willing to go to war or to
                        support actions likely to lead to war until they are satisfied: <pb
                            facs="0551" n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>That the Soviet blockade has been imposed for the purpose of
                                forcing the Allies to abandon Berlin; and</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>That the Soviet Union cannot be forced to lift the blockade by
                                measures short of those which might lead to general war.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>In taking actions to maintain the Allied position in Berlin and to avoid
                        war, or to show the actual nature of the Soviet purpose, the following
                        factors should be taken into account. <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>If either side miscalculates, the situation could grow into war,
                                even though neither side desires it.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Most courses of action can be carried out only with the united
                                effort of the Allies. Divergence of views with the U.K. and France
                                or with other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> powers must be
                                reconciled on the basis of a clear understanding that the Soviet
                                aggression is serious and that united Western support of local or
                                general action is essential to a collective security of the free
                                world. Although U.S. actions must seek to retain Allied cooperation,
                                the United States must be prepared to act alone if this will serve
                                its best interests.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>The Soviets may seek by every means to obscure their
                                responsibility for renewed tensions in Berlin, by alleging that they
                                are merely reacting to Western moves or by using East German
                                forces.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Because the world situation is different from that during the
                                previous blockade, the period between initiation of aggressive
                                actions and the “show down” is likely to be short. During this
                                period, therefore, diplomatic, military and mobilization actions
                                should be speeded up.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">Major Policy Guidance</p>
                <list>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>In the existing situation, and unless the USSR further restricts access to
                        Berlin, the United States should: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Continue to make clear, as appropriate, to the USSR that the
                                Western powers will maintain their position in Berlin and that
                                Soviet measures challenging that position will be forcefully and
                                promptly resisted and will have the gravest consequences.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Vigorously react to any local or minor Soviet harassments by
                                lodging prompt Allied protests and undertaking any feasible
                                reprisals.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Support all feasible measures, including limited economic aid, to
                                bolster the morale and economy of the city and reduce
                                unemployment.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Continue to provide funds for special projects designed to
                                influence the people of the Soviet Zone and Sector, such as the food
                                program in the summer of 1953.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>Review the present stockpile program in the light of the
                                likelihood that, in the event of a new blockade, the Allies would
                                resort to an airlift only as a supplement to other more positive
                                measures.</item>
                            <label>f.</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>Continue to exploit the unrivaled propaganda advantages.</p>
                                <p>[<hi rend="italic">Subparagraph g (1 line of source text) not
                                        declassified</hi>]</p>
                            </item>
                            <pb facs="0552" n="524" xml:id="pg_524"/>
                            <label>h.</label>
                            <item>Seek to persuade the U.K. and France to adopt the U.S. policy on
                                Berlin and seek to widen the areas of agreement with regard to
                                future plans and emergency measures.</item>
                            <label>i.</label>
                            <item>Perfect plans and practicable preparatory measures for future
                                contingencies. Some of this can be done unilaterally, some requires
                                the cooperation of our Allies or the German authorities or both.
                                Keep under review: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>Possible retaliatory measures and the means of quickly
                                        concerting action against specific local harassments.</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>Conditions affecting security and necessary remedial
                                        measures.</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>German Federal Republic financial and other support for
                                        Berlin.</item>
                                    <label>(4)</label>
                                    <item>Condition of the stockpile and equipment held in reserve
                                        for emergencies.</item>
                                    <label>(5)</label>
                                    <item>Plans for increased use of air transport in case of
                                        partial blockade.</item>
                                    <label>(6)</label>
                                    <item>Improvement of relations with the local authorities, in
                                        keeping with the new relationship to the Federal Government
                                        which the Allies have under the Bonn Conventions subject to
                                        essential Allied security requirements.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>If the Soviets or East Germans impose, or threaten imminently to impose, a
                        blockade, or increase harassment to the point of seriously impeding Western
                        access to Berlin, the United States should consult with its Allies and be
                        prepared to: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Make a determined effort in Berlin to end the restrictions by
                                vigorous protests from Allied Commanders to the Soviet
                                Commander.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Instruct the U.S. Ambassador in Moscow to join with the U.K. and
                                France in presenting an agreed declaration stating their intention
                                to use force if necessary and the risk to world peace occasioned by
                                the Soviet action in Berlin. If the U.K. and France cannot agree to
                                such a declaration, the U.S. should then consider making a
                                unilateral declaration.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Continue to hold the Soviet Union responsible for any Communist
                                action against the Western position in Berlin whether the action is
                                taken by the Soviets or by East Germans or other satellites.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>In the meantime, make use at an accelerated rate of the means of
                                access remaining open, in order to provide an opportunity to gain
                                support of our Allies and world opinion.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>Initiate appropriate mobilization measures with the dual purpose
                                of convincing the Soviets of the seriousness of the situation and of
                                getting the United States and its Allies in a “ready” state in the
                                event resort to general war is required.</item>
                            <label>f.</label>
                            <item>In agreement with the other occupying powers, use limited military
                                force to the extent necessary to determine Soviet intentions and to
                                demonstrate the Allied refusal voluntarily to relinquish their right
                                to access to Berlin. If Soviet reaction to this course indicates
                                their intent forcibly to deny Allied access to Berlin, the United
                                States should consider implementing the course of action set forth
                                in para. 9–i below.</item>
                            <pb facs="0553" n="525" xml:id="pg_525"/>
                            <label>g.</label>
                            <item>Seek to solidify the free world behind the U.S. position,
                                including appropriate action in the United Nations and in <gloss
                                    target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>h.</label>
                            <item>Start evacuation of U.S. dependents at an appropriate time.</item>
                            <label>i.</label>
                            <item>In the light of all the circumstances, including the general
                                security situation, use limited military force to attempt to reopen
                                access to Berlin. In doing so, recognize that Berlin is not
                                militarily defensible and that if determined Soviet armed opposition
                                should develop when U.S. units attempt to force their way into or
                                out of Berlin, no additional forces would be committed, but resort
                                would have to be made to general war. Prior to the use of force on a
                                scale which might lead to general war, however, measures as
                                enumerated in subparagraph 9–a through –g above should be taken to
                                make clear to the USSR the nature of our determination.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>If the USSR should attack Berlin with its own forces, the United States
                        will have to act on the assumption that general war is imminent. In addition
                        to resisting the initial attack and to placing itself in the best possible
                        position for immediate global war, the United States should, if
                        circumstances permit, address an ultimatum to the Soviet Government before
                        full implementation of emergency war plans.<note n="5" xml:id="d213fn5">See
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1664–c. [Footnote in
                            the source text. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1664–c
                            is in Department of State, <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss
                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> (Miscellaneous) Files: Lot 66 D
                            95.]</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Because an attack on Berlin by East German forces alone might not
                        necessarily carry the same implications as an attack by Soviet forces, the
                        United States (in addition to resisting the initial attack) should consider
                        at that time whether or not to treat such an attack in the manner stated in
                        paragraph 10 with respect to an attack by Soviet forces.<note n="5"
                            target="d213fn5">See <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No.
                            1664–c. [Footnote in the source text. <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss> Action No. 1664–c is in Department of State, <gloss
                                target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            (Miscellaneous) Files: Lot 66 D 95.]</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
