<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-10-19T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-10-19T13:00:00-05:00" n="291" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d291">
                        <head>291. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in
                                Yugoslavia</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d291fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 768.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/10–1956. Secret. Repeated to London, Paris, and
                                Moscow.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Belgrade</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-10-19T19:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">October 19,
                                        1956—7 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>508. Pass Army, Navy, Air. Embassy telegram 500.<note n="2" xml:id="d291fn2">In telegram 500 from Belgrade, October 18,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName> reported on
                                a press release issued by the Yugoslav Government on October 17 in
                                reaction to the resumption of U.S. aid. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 768.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/10–1856)</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Have just concluded 2-hour session with <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Prica</persName> where as not unexpected Foreign Office press
                                release October 17 was subjected to considerable interpretation. He
                                said he would like my comment on press release first, particularly
                                as it represented Yugoslav Government viewpoint on President’s
                                report which while welcome in some respects had given certain shock
                                in others. I then spoke along following lines.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Press release in my opinion could be criticized primarily on
                                grounds inconsistency and inaccuracy on certain points. If Yugoslav
                                Government found certain sections letter unpalatable or even
                                unacceptable, it should recall first that President had made
                                affirmative response to three points. In view highly generalized
                                information hitherto given us re Yugoslav-Soviet relations and
                                recent developments it was not unnatural United States should have
                                some reserves on ultimate Soviet aims. Seriousness of developments
                                at Brioni and apparent Soviet intention to reverse line laid down in
                                Moscow declaration had been emphasized to us only by Yugoslav
                                Government and in particular by <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Prica</persName> in our conversation October 1 (Embassy
                                telegram 437, paragraphs 3 and 4).<note n="3" xml:id="d291fn3">Telegram 437, October 2, reported on an October 1 conversation
                                    between <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName> and
                                        <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Prica</persName>. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 768.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/10–156)</note> Subsequently little information
                                had been offered how this “wide gap” had been bridged at Yalta and
                                we were still unaware what compromise had been arrived at. I said
                                threats to independence could take various forms and Tempo, in
                                course of wheat discussions, had underlined danger for Yugoslavia in
                                becoming too dependent on USSR in trade relations. Therefore I found
                                lack of logic in contention of no threat to Yugoslav independence by
                                Soviet Union. Yugoslav Government desire for long-term economic
                                arrangements was of course well-known to us but this raised several
                                problems which we had discussed lengthily with Tempo. I reminded
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Prica</persName> we had extended
                                under authorization stipulated by law and further I had told Tempo
                                only recently question of long-term credits would naturally raise
                                same type political issues with which we now concerned. Furthermore
                                generalized Yugoslav proposals to date envisaged sale of surplus
                                agricultural products under long-term credits <pb facs="0781" n="753" xml:id="pg_753"/> eventually payable “in dollars or some
                                other currency”. Emphasis seemed to be on latter which raised host
                                of problems. Perhaps next year administration would have new
                                proposals to present to Congress but at present we must operate
                                under existing laws.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Re statement on military aid, I could only remark release was
                                inaccurate and quoted figures mentioned Embassy telegram 500,
                                paragraph 4 amplifying these with numerous illustrations on variety
                                of deliveries in addition to spare parts.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_PS1">Prica</persName> said would try explain
                                Yugoslav Government position in existing circumstances. Difficult
                                accept President’s report without comment; although Yugoslav
                                Government knows aid given under United States laws, it thinks
                                situation now greatly changed. President had in effect repeated what
                                was formerly true but it no longer corresponds to facts, i.e.,
                                danger from Soviet Union has lessened or is disappearing. Yugoslav
                                Government is attempting to find balance between East and West which
                                is different from Presidential formulation which implies Yugoslavia
                                in same danger as five years ago. Yugoslav Government does not want
                                to be bound to one side and would be difficult for it to admit it
                                accepting aid on basis danger from Soviet Union. These formulations
                                therefore offensive to Yugoslav Government which is striving for
                                good economic relations with both sides. Also mention of possibility
                                of cutting off aid worries Yugoslav Government as it places it in
                                position insecurity for future while its duty must be provide food
                                for its people. Yugoslav Government hopes US will therefore
                                understand its motives in accepting aid, and its standpoint is set
                                forth in press release.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_PS1">Prica</persName> then said Yugoslav
                                Government in difficult position on wheat. It wants to plan for more
                                than one year’s supply and with United States it cannot be certain
                                in view of President’s letter whether it can count on more than one
                                year. (I interrupted to say our record of covering deficits spoke
                                for itself and <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Prica</persName> admitted
                                this was true.) He said he would be entirely frank about present
                                status of negotiations with USSR. Soviet system was rigid as was
                                based on state planning and Soviets were demanding to know Yugoslav
                                requirements for 4 to 5 years ahead before concluding agreements.
                                Yugoslav Government had postponed and was still postponing decision
                                on this because it wanted to investigate again possibility of longer
                                term arrangements with United States for agricultural surpluses. He
                                referred to our recent agreement with India as example of what
                                Yugoslav Government had in mind and it hoped very much we would
                                examine some such possibilities for them. He entered strong plea on
                                basis necessity Yugoslav Government plan future economic
                                development, assure food supply over next 4 to 5 years, remove
                                friction from our economic relations and put them on some loan or
                                credit basis as not to cause such criticism in Congress. Although he
                                    <pb facs="0782" n="754" xml:id="pg_754"/> understood limitations
                                under which we worked he hoped we could give some indication of our
                                attitude when we commenced discussions of wheat needs which were
                                urgent. I replied I would submit his observations and would be in
                                position to discuss immediate wheat needs within few days.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Discussion re military aid and comment will follow in separate
                                    telegram.<note n="4" xml:id="d291fn4">Telegram 508 from
                                    Belgrade, October 19. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                        768.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/10–1956)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>