<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>83. Letter From Chancellor Adenauer to President to President
                    Eisenhower</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="83"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                <head>83. Letter From Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1" type="from"
                        >Adenauer</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1" type="to"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d83fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> Library, Whitman File. Secret. The source text
                        indicates it is a translation. It bears no indication how it was transmitted
                        to Washington.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bonn</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-12-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 4, 1956</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: I am especially grateful that
                    you, although preoccupied right now with so many acute problems, found the time
                    to give such extensive consideration to my worries reported to you by General
                        <persName corresp="#p_GGAM1">Gruenther</persName>.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d83fn2">President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>’s message to <persName corresp="#p_AK1"
                            >Adenauer</persName> is printed as <ref target="#d81">Document 81</ref>;
                        for the Chancellor’s message to the President, see <ref target="#d80"
                            >Document 80</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The particularly close interdependence of all European affairs should serve as an
                    explanation for my deep concern, though at a first glance the Federal Republic
                    is not immediately affected by all pending questions. Permit me, my dear Mr.
                    President, to express to you two additional ideas:</p>
                <p>After your re-election by such an overwhelming majority, your leadership is more
                    than ever the strong and only hope for the free nations that they will survive
                    in this dangerous period of mankind. Our heartfelt prayers are with you.</p>
                <p>Let me make, my dear Mr. President, one other point: The developments of the last
                    months, the brutal actions of the Soviet Union everywhere, with arms and other
                    means confirm my opinion that Europe remains the main target of Soviet policy
                    and aggression. P[ar] e[xample], there are more than 7000 tanks in the Soviet
                    occupied zone pointing towards Germany and Western Europe. If the Soviet Union
                    holds Europe, she will control Asia as well. If her position in Europe will be
                    reduced to natural proportions by restricting her power, she can no longer
                    entertain any hope to gain Asia, too. Therefore, the Soviet Union still strives
                    for the control of Europe, in spite of all deviating maneuvers and all present
                    assurances which she will break at a time she considers opportune. The
                    domination of Europe would give to the Soviet Union the key to the control of
                    the world she strives for.</p>
                <p>I hope you will understand, my dear Mr. President, why I have reiterated these
                    ideas and convictions. I do so because I believe that the freedom of the world
                    was never—not even in Hitler’s time—so much endangered as in these years.</p>
                <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d83fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                        signature.</note>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
