<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in India ( (Henderson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-01-27T01:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-01-27T01:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec_korean_war" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="korean-war" subject="korean-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073119" lcsh-match="exact">Korean conflict</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-27T01:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-27T01:30:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/1–2751: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">
                            <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-27T12:00:00+05:30"
                            >January 27, 1951—noon.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1837. 1. Am seeing Bajpai noon today and leaving document with him in form
                    memorandum containing summary of statements made <pb facs="0154" n="138"
                        xml:id="pg_138"/> by me to him. This summary contains substance of <gloss
                        target="#t_Depcirtel1">Depcirtel</gloss> 395, January 17<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d106fn1">Not printed. Circular telegram 395 was virtually identical
                        with circular telegram 387, January 15, <ref target="#pg_83">p. 83</ref>; it
                        was sent principally to the Embassies in the Arab and Asian countries
                        (795.00/1–1751).</note> and <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1131,
                    January 23<note n="2" xml:id="d106fn2">Not printed. It urged the Ambassador to
                        take up with Bajpai, in the absence of Nehru, the points set forth in
                        circular telegram 395 (795.00/1–2151).</note> without, however, referring to
                    the alternative contained in <gloss target="#t_Depcirtel1">Depcirtel</gloss> 395
                    to point 1 of proposed resolution of UN. In the latter part of the memorandum,
                    however, I have elaborated on the possible effect of American opinion upon
                    failure of UN to pass resolution condemning the action of Communist China in
                    Korea. Latter part of this memorandum reads as follows:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Ambassador added his government realized other governments also had problem
                        meeting their public opinion. It hoped other governments would have in mind
                        failure UN recognize present action Communist China in Korea for what it was
                        and face squarely might create wave isolationism in US so powerful it might
                        affect some of basic foreign policies of US. American public would fail
                        understand why UN should hesitate condemn forces which had attacked those of
                        UN and had killed thousands of UN soldiers, including those of US, which
                        were in Korea in response to call from UN. Regardless of any explanations
                        might be made, large section of American people would interpret such failure
                        on part of UN as placing of soldiers of US, and of other countries who
                        entered Korea halt aggression at request of UN, on same level as those
                        forces which entered Korea in order support aggressor and attack UN forces
                        opposing aggressor.</p>
                    <p>“Feelings of injustice which such failure on part of UN would create would
                        not be assauged by arguments Peiping regime had had grievances against US
                        because various policies of US in <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> were not
                        to its liking. American people had come believe aggression gave rise war;
                        failure collectively condemn aggression, and if necessary take other steps
                        oppose it, would encourage aggressive tendencies and eventually lead to
                        future world wars. Many of them might take view if aggression against forces
                        of UN were to be overlooked by UN merely because aggressor might feel itself
                        to have a grievance against one or other members of UN attempts discourage
                        aggression in future by collective action would indeed be futile, with
                        consequent increased danger world peace.</p>
                    <p>“Ambassador concluded by stating although he had endeavored faithfully set
                        forth what he understood be his government’s views, and describe some
                        problems facing his government, nevertheless he would like make clear his
                        government did not pretend it had found any panacea for situation in <gloss
                            target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>. His government was anxious consult with
                        other members of UN and loyally work with them in finding ways and means for
                        preventing spread hostilities and for bringing to an end Korean conflict,
                        without at same time weakening UN to such extent as to endanger its efficacy
                        in maintenance world peace.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>2. I hope Department will approve this section my statement. Any suggestions for
                    supplementary conversation would be appreciated.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
