<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-27T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-27T17:00:00-05:00" n="109" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d109">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/1–2651: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Kingdom</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">
                                    <gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-27T17:00:00-05:00">January
                                    27, 1951—5 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3557. Reurtel 4135 Jan 26<note n="1" xml:id="d109fn1">Not printed; the
                                content of this telegram is covered in the memorandum of
                                conversation by Raynor, January 26, <ref target="#pg_134">p.
                                    134</ref>.</note> and previous tels. Another full discussion UN
                            problem between Franks and Dept officers last night. Brit informed some
                            revision Para 2 possible which <gloss target="#t_USUN2">USUN</gloss>
                            authorized work out with Jebb.<note n="2" xml:id="d109fn2">According to
                                telegram 1082, January 29, from New York, not printed, the U.S.
                                Delegation at the United Nations suggested to Jebb on January 27 a
                                change in Paragraph 2 substituting the words “has not accepted” for
                                “has rejected all”. This proved acceptable to the U.K. Delegation
                                and to the British Government. (795.00/1–2951)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Re Para 8, yesterday morning <gloss target="#t_USUN2">USUN</gloss>
                            authorized submit to <gloss target="#t_UKUN1">UKUN</gloss> fol addition
                            Para 8: “taking into account in its report the results of the efforts of
                            the good offices committee provided for in the fol <pb facs="0159" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/> Para”. Jebb turned this down and submitted
                            following counter-language which Franks also gave us last night: “Sets
                            up a committee composed of members of the <gloss target="#t_CMC1">CMC</gloss> to consider, whenever the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> shld find that the efforts made by the good offices
                            committee referred to in the aforesaid Para have failed, additional
                            measures to be employed to meet the situation resulting from the armed
                            intervention in Korea by the <gloss target="#t_CPG1">CPG</gloss> of the
                                <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>”.</p>
                        <p>Franks and Jebb informed above language completely unacceptable US as we
                            feel strongly we must stand on principle that <gloss target="#t_CMC1">CMC</gloss> at least begin study of further steps. We have
                            indicated to Brit that we wld be willing to put some brake on the time
                            of the <gloss target="#t_CMC1">CMC</gloss> reporting to the <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> and last night submitted to Franks
                            unofficially indicating draft not approved by Sec fol language as
                            addition present wording para 8 US Res: “…, it being understood the
                            Committee is authorized to defer its report if the good offices
                            committee, referred to in the fol Para, reports satisfactory progress in
                            its efforts”. Pres has this morning approved our accepting above
                            language if by so doing UK can vote favorably on Para 8 or if it will
                            mean that French and other West Europeans will vote for Para 8 rather
                            than abstaining.</p>
                        <p>Major issue between us is whether or not <gloss target="#t_CMC1">CMC</gloss> begin study of question. US cannot yield on this point.
                            If UK cannot accept language such as above, probably better proceed even
                            though UK forced to vote against US Res. Emb instructed inform Brit that
                            language such as that handed Franks last night is our irreducible
                            minimum beyond which we cannot make further concessions. One trouble
                            with Brit approach is that it is almost impossible to determine when a
                            conciliation effort “has failed”. Argument could always be advanced by
                            those who wish to do so that there is still hope. Our approach along the
                            line of “satisfactory progress” is more practical.</p>
                        <p>A further general argument you are authorized to use in your discretion
                            is as follows: The US wld greatly regret to see an open split in UN on
                            voting on US Res as this is exactly what Soviets want. Furthermore we
                            believe it important to avoid such split because of probable
                            repercussions on US efforts to strengthen the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries in view of current sensitive state of US
                            public opinion. In particular, it wld be most unfortunate for this split
                            to occur on eve of Eisenhower’s report to American people on his
                            European tour. You cld express hope Brit have given adequate
                            consideration to these factors. You cld add that for our part, we have
                            made one concession after another on Res such as revision agreed last
                            week wording Para 3 and two suggestions referred to above re Para 8 but
                            that point has been reached where we can concede no more.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>