<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-03-21T13:24:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-03-21T13:24:00-05:00" n="177" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d177">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/3–2151: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy Representative at the United
                                Nations</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gross</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-03-21T13:24:00-05:00">March 21,
                                    1951—1:24 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1309. Re Korea: In compliance with draft <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> telephoned by Henkin this morning,<note n="1" xml:id="d177fn1">
                                <p>The draft telegram under reference was transmitted to New York at
                                    2 p. m. on March 21 as telegram 800, which read as follows:</p>
                                <p>“Dept concerned over probable effects if Limb shld act on Rhee’s
                                    instructions, <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss> 1305, Mar
                                    20. If Limb comes, Rusk will seek to persuade him that formal
                                    request to UN re bombing Manchuria wld seriously damage cause
                                    for which <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and US both
                                    striving.</p>
                                <p>“In Dept’s view, proposed <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                                    letter to Entezam urging time limit on <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> is both inappropriate and undesirable. Under
                                    Feb 1 Res, functioning of <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>
                                    does not prevent <gloss target="#t_AMC1">AMC</gloss> from
                                    proceeding with its work and US has been urging their view in
                                        <gloss target="#t_AMC1">AMC</gloss>. Time limit on <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> wld give impression that UN
                                    gives up policy of seeking peaceful settlement in Korea which UN
                                    and US have repeatedly expressed. Publicity and propaganda
                                    effect cld only harm UN effort and do great damage to <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> position. Also, Feb 1 Res
                                    provided that <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> shld be
                                    available to exercise good offices at any ‘suitable
                                    opportunity’, implying continuing efforts by <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>, and only <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> has authority to limit or change
                                    these terms of reference. US cld not support any proposal to
                                    limit <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> and other nations wld
                                    certainly oppose it.</p>
                                <p>“Dept believes it desirable that proposed <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> communication to Entezam shld not be made and
                                    requests you to express these views to Limb.”
                                    (795.00/3–2151)</p>
                            </note>
                            <gloss target="#t_USUN2">USUN</gloss> informed Colonel Limb that Dept
                            believes proposed <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> letter to Entezam
                            urging time limit on <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> is both
                            inappropriate and undesirable, giving reasons set forth in second para
                            of <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Colonel Limb agreed to postpone sending letter to Entezam and to discuss
                            both it and proposed formal request re UN bombing in Manchuria with Rusk
                            March 21. He will this afternoon request Korean Emb to obtain
                            appointment for him with Rusk tomorrow. He remains worried about his
                            failure to comply promptly with Pres Rhee’s instructions.</p>
                        <p>Limb feels obliged to take some action in connection with Pres Rhee’s tel
                            re UN bombing of Manchuria and, therefore, this afternoon will send tel
                            to Rhee pointing out that existing <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> and
                                <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> resolutions may already contain
                            some authority for bombing Manchuria and that discussion this subject
                            logically should first be held with <gloss target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss>.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gross</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>