<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the United Nations ( (Austin) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-01-06T12:57:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-01-06T12:57:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-06T12:57:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-06T12:57:00-05:00" n="22"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d22">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">320/1–651: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-06T12:57:00-05:00"
                            >January 6, 1951—12:57 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 490. Re Korea. Following reports Ross
                    conversations Jamali, Charles Malik, Padilla Nervo,<note n="1" xml:id="d22fn1"
                        >Mohammed Fadhil Jamali, Charles Malik, and Luis Padilla Nervo were
                        Representatives at the United Nations of Iraq, Lebanon, and Mexico,
                        respectively.</note> Fawzi Bey yesterday afternoon.</p>
                <pb facs="0045" n="29" xml:id="pg_29"/>
                <p>Jamali was given copy of our memo. He expressed very strong discontent with delay
                    occasioned by Rau, cease-fire group, British Commonwealth meeting. He said they
                    were supposed to have a 12-power Asian group. This in turn was tried through Rau
                    to cease-fire group which was not getting anything done because of Rau. The
                    Asian group was also tried through Rau and Nehru to the Commonwealth group. The
                    Commonwealth, after all, represented only 8 members of UN and in effect, Jamali
                    summarized, he was getting fed up with the paralysis which for these reasons had
                    overtaken the Asian group and the UN. He said he had expressed the foregoing
                    views at an Asian group meeting Friday morning<note n="2" xml:id="d22fn2"
                        >January 5.</note> and had been supported by Pakistan and Iranian
                    representatives and by most of the Arabs. He said he thought we should not delay
                    beyond Monday filing of some intermediate step. He thought, however, that
                    agreement between US and UK on a program of action was very important.</p>
                <p>The speech made by Eban in the First Committee outlining points as basis for
                        <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> action<note n="3" xml:id="d22fn3">See the
                        editorial note, <ref target="#pg_26">p. 26</ref>.</note> seemed mildly to
                    have gotten under Jamali’s skin. He said there is nothing new in these points;
                    that they had all been encompassed in the thinking of Asian group. He did not
                    say so, but he seemed to feel that the Israelis were stealing a march by moving
                    into vacuum left by Asian group inactivity.</p>
                <p>Jamali said that in Asian group meeting Friday morning, he had asked Rau whether
                    India would be able to go along with a resolution condemning the aggression in
                    Korea if a further intermediate step proved a failure. He said Rau had replied
                    that India would not even in those circumstances be able to go along with a
                    condemnatory resolution.</p>
                <p>Charles Malik, with whom Ross had brief conversation after Committee One meeting
                    giving him copy of our memo, is full of beans and more and more irritated over
                    delay on the one hand and viciousness Malik’s<note n="4" xml:id="d22fn4"
                        >Reference here is to Yakov Malik, Soviet Representative at the United
                        Nations.</note> and Soviet satellites speeches on the other.</p>
                <p>Fawzi Bey was given copy of our memo. He is maintaining a rug-dealer attitude not
                    being nearly as forthright in his comments as Charles Malik or Jamali.</p>
                <p>Padilla Nervo said that he understood Pearson to say at Canadian luncheon
                    yesterday that Nehru was holding up authority to Rau to go along with cease-fire
                    statement of principles until Indian Government had found out from Chinese
                    Communists whether such statement would be acceptable. As Padilla understood it
                    Nehru would not authorize Rau to associate himself with such principles if
                    Chinese <pb facs="0046" n="30" xml:id="pg_30"/> Communists would not go along.
                    Asked concerning this, Riddell said he did not think situation was that Nehru
                    was waiting for Chinese Communists concurrence, although he said he knew
                    statement of principles had been sent to Pannikar.</p>
                <p>Padilla observed that he thought that in present situation the votes of the
                        <gloss target="#t_LA1">LA</gloss> delegates, which were pretty well assured
                    for a condemnatory resolution, were not nearly as important as getting the votes
                    of India in particular, as well as other countries which recognize Peiping
                    regime. If we did not get these votes, he said a condemnatory resolution would
                    lack political force. He expressed himself very strongly in favor of an
                    intermediate step.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
