<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-06-22T19:48:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-06-22T19:48:00-05:00" n="354" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795B.5/6–2251: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy Representative at the United
                                Nations</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gross</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-06-22T20:48:00-04:00">June 22,
                                    1951—8:48 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1703. Re Korea: Appeal for additional ground forces. UN issued advance
                            press release today of UNSYG’s letter transmitting appeal of <gloss target="#t_UC1">UC</gloss> for additional troops in Korea. (Press
                            release time 7 a. m., June 23). Press release states letter, together
                            with <gloss target="#t_UC1">UC</gloss>’s communication, has been sent
                            following 39 countries: Afghanistan, Argentina. Bolivia, Brazil, Burma,
                            Chile, China, Costa Rica, Cuba, Denmark, Dominican Republic, Ecuador,
                            Egypt, El Salvador, Guatemala, Haiti, Honduras, Iceland, India,
                            Indonesia, Iran, Iraq, Israel, Lebanon, Liberia, Mexico, Nicaragua,
                            Norway, Pakistan, Panama, Paraguay, Peru, Saudi Arabia, Sweden, Syria,
                            Uruguay, Venezuela, Yemen and Yugoslavia. Following is text of
                            letter:</p>
                        <p>“I have received from the US Govt, acting in its capacity as the <gloss target="#t_UC1">UC</gloss>, a communication concerning the need for
                            additional ground troops from member govts of the UN for the collective
                            effort in Korea.<note n="1" xml:id="d354fn1">The text of the
                                communication from the Unified Command is printed in the Department
                                of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, July 9, 1951, p. 53; it is
                                the same text as that embodied in telegram 964, June 5, to New York
                                (p. 513) except that it was sent to Secretary-General Lie from Mr.
                                Gross rather than from Secretary Acheson.</note> The <gloss target="#t_UC1">UC</gloss> is conducting extensive discussions in
                            connection with this problem. Particularly with states which are already
                            contributing armed forces. It has requested me to send communications on
                            its behalf to member govts which previously gave a favorable reply to
                            either the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> res of 25 June 1950 or to
                            its res of 27 June 1950, but which have not yet contributed armed forces
                            for the collective effort in Korea.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to transmit herewith a communication from the <gloss target="#t_UC1">UC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>As <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> I respectfully request your govt
                            to give earnest consideration to this appeal in the light of the
                            necessity of strengthening the collective effort in Korea so long as the
                            aggressors continue to fight against the UN forces there.</p>
                        <p>I should be grateful if you would inform me of the decision of your govt
                            and would communicate with the <gloss target="#t_UC1">UC</gloss> about
                            any detailed arrangements.”</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gross</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>