<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-06-27T18:09:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-06-27T18:09:00-05:00" n="371" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d371">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/6–2751: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States Deputy Representative at the United
                                Nations</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gross</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-06-27T19:09:00-04:00">June 27,
                                    1951—7:09 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1729, Lie’s views re Malik statement; troop appeal. I saw Lie this
                            afternoon at his request. He told me he had decided to return because of
                            the Malik statement and also because of the problems rising re troop <pb facs="0579" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/> appeal. Concerning former, he
                            expressed complete agreement with procedure we were following and
                            expressed hope that it would lead to mtg between reps and military
                            commanders in the field. He is convinced Malik’s statement must be taken
                            very seriously. In his view, great significance should be attached to
                            repeated references in statement to “the Soviet people” which he thinks
                            indicate that statement was designed primarily for consumption of Soviet
                            dominated populations to prepare them for end of Korean war.</p>
                        <p>Just prior to seeing me he had talked with Entezam, Padilla Nervo and Rau
                            together. Padilla apparently had suggested a new approach to Chi Corns
                            which Lie vigorously opposed. Entezam appeared embarrassed by Malik
                            refusal to see him and wished to beat a graceful retreat to Washington.
                            Lie encouraged him to do so.</p>
                        <p>Rau apparently had no suggestions to offer but expressed view that Malik
                            statement indicated real Soviet desire for peace in Korea.</p>
                        <p>I gave Lie frank account of our efforts to see Malik. He pressed me very
                            hard for info re Kirk talk with Gromyko. I told him I had no info. (This
                            excuse will wear thin very quickly and I should appreciate Dept’s
                            guidance as to how frank I should be with Lie, who wants to see me again
                            tomorrow.)</p>
                        <p>Re troop appeal, Lie, while in Europe, had talked with Swedes, Danes and
                            Norwegians. Malik speech hit like a bomb-shell and in Lie’s judgment put
                            to an end for the time being at least any hope of getting troop
                            assistance from these countries. He urged that we talk to these dels
                            here as well as selected others to recommend that they do not transmit
                            negative replies. I recommend that we be authorized to take this action
                            here promptly.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gross</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>