<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Joint Chiefs of Staff to the Commander in Chief, United Nations Command (
                    (Ridgway))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d392</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">392</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-06-29T23:25:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-06-29T23:25:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-06-29T23:25:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-06-29T23:25:00-05:00" n="392"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d392">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/6–3051: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss> to the
                        Commander in Chief, United Nations Command</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ridgway</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-06-30T00:25:00-04:00"
                            >June 30, 1951—12:25 a. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 95354. Noforn. Personal for General Ridgway
                    eyes only from <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>This message cancels our previous directives regarding armistice terms and
                        contains instructions regarding such terms for your guidance in any
                        conversations which might develop between you and the Commander in Chief of
                        the Communist forces in Korea. It is believed that the chance for a
                        successful conclusion of such negotiation may depend upon secrecy in at
                        least the opening stages; it is not, therefore, intended to make these
                        instructions public.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>General policy. <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Our principal military interest in this armistice lies in a
                                cessation of hostilities in Korea, an assurance against the
                                resumption of fighting and the protection of the security of United
                                Nations forces, as set forth in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                    48/5,<note n="1" xml:id="d392fn1">Dated May 17; see the
                                    memorandum containing the sections on Korea, <ref
                                        target="#pg_439">p. 439</ref>.</note> copy of which you have
                                received. General policy and background guidance is found in the
                                same paper.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>We lack assurance either that the Soviet Union and Communist China
                                are serious about concluding reasonable and acceptable armistice
                                arrangements or that they are prepared to agree to an acceptable
                                permanent settlement of the Korean problem. In considering an
                                armistice, therefore, it is of the utmost importance to reach
                                arrangements which would be acceptable to us over an extended period
                                of time, even though no progress is made in reaching agreement on
                                political and territorial questions.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Discussions between you and the commander of opposing forces
                                should be severely restricted to military questions; you should
                                specifically not enter into discussion of a final settlement in
                                Korea or consideration of issues unrelated to Korea, such as Formosa
                                and the Chinese seat in the United Nations; such questions must be
                                dealt with at governmental level.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>You are authorized to adopt, for negotiating purposes, initial positions
                        more favorable to us than the minimum conditions set forth in these
                        instructions. However, great care should be used, in putting forward a
                        negotiating position, not to allow talks to break down except in case of
                        failure to accept our minimum terms; not to appear, to over-reach to an
                        extent to cause world opinion to question our good faith; and not so to
                        engage US prestige in a negotiating position as to make retreat to our
                        minimum terms impossible. Our minimum position is essential to us but we
                        must recognize that it will not be <pb facs="0615" n="599" xml:id="pg_599"/>
                        easy for opponents to accept; the difficulty of your negotiation is fully
                        appreciated here.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Pursuant to the above, the armistice agreements: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Shall be confined to Korea and strictly military matters therein,
                                and shall not involve any political or territorial matters.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Shall continue in effect until superseded by other
                                arrangements.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Shall require the commanders concerned to order a cessation of
                                hostilities and all acts of armed force in Korea; shall require the
                                establishment of a demilitarized area across Korea; and shall
                                require all ground forces in Korea to remain in position or be
                                withdrawn to the rear except that all forces which may be in advance
                                of the demilitarized area shall be moved to positions in the rear
                                thereof;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Shall provide for supervision over the execution of and adherence
                                to the terms of the armistice arrangements by a Military Armistice
                                Commission of mixed membership of an equal basis designated by the
                                Commander in Chief of the United Nations command and by the
                                Commander in Chief of the Communist forces. The Commission and teams
                                of observers appointed by the Commission shall have free and
                                unlimited access to the whole of Korea and shall be given all
                                possible assistance and cooperation in carrying out their
                                functions.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Shall require the commanders concerned to cease the introduction
                                into Korea of any reinforcing air, ground or naval units or
                                personnel during the armistice. This shall not be interpreted as
                                precluding the exchange of units or individual personnel on a
                                man-for-man basis;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Shall require the commanders concerned to refrain from increasing
                                the level of war equipment and material existing in Korea at the
                                time the armistice becomes effective. Such equipment and material
                                will not include those supplies required for the maintenance of
                                health and welfare and such other supplies as may be authorized by
                                the Commission nor the vehicles, ships or aircraft used to transport
                                such supplies.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The following specific details are essential to the above armistice
                        arrangements: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The Military Armistice Commission must be empowered to inspect to
                                insure that the terms, conditions, and arrangements as agreed to are
                                carried out by all armed forces, including guerillas. It shall be
                                provided with competent assistants designated equally by the
                                Commander in Chief. United Nations Command, and the Commander in
                                Chief of the Communist forces in Korea, in numbers sufficient to
                                enable it to carry out its duties and functions;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The armistice arrangements should not become effective until the
                                Commission has been organized and is ready to exercise its
                                functions;</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The demilitarized area shall be a zone on the order of 20 miles in
                                width, to be determined by the Commander in Chief, United Nations
                                Command and the Commander in Chief of the Communist forces in Korea,
                                based generally upon the positions of the opposing forces at the
                                time the armistice arrangements are agreed upon. For purposes of
                                negotiation your initial demand might be that the Communist <pb
                                    facs="0616" n="600" xml:id="pg_600"/> forces must withdraw 20
                                miles or more along the entire front. If it becomes necessary for
                                purposes of bargaining for you to agree to some withdrawal of United
                                Nations forces, you may do so to the extent that your present strong
                                military position and your ability to carry out your military
                                mission are not placed in jeopardy. You may agree to continued
                                Communist control of the Ongjin and Yonan Peninsulas for purposes of
                                the armistice only. If the Communist Commander refers to statements
                                attributed to United States Government officials that the United
                                States is prepared to accept a settlement on or around the 38th
                                parallel, you should take the position that such statements are not
                                applicable to an armistice in the field but are properly the subject
                                for governmental negotiation as to a political settlement. Further,
                                you should state that in any event the military arrangements you
                                propose involve certain areas under Communist military control south
                                of the 38th parallel and certain areas under UN control north
                                thereof. The net result, while military in character, does not
                                prejudice political and territorial questions which would be for
                                further consideration by appropriate authorities.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The armistice arrangements shall apply to all opposing ground
                                forces in Korea. These forces shall respect the demilitarized zone
                                and the areas under the control of the opposing force.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The armistice arrangements shall apply to all opposing naval
                                forces. Naval elements shall respect the waters contiguous to the
                                demilitarized zone and to the land areas under the control of the
                                opposing force, to the limit of three miles off-shore.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The armistice arrangements shall apply to all opposing air forces.
                                These forces shall respect the air space over the demilitarized zone
                                and the areas under the control of the opposing force.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Vehicles, naval units and aircraft required for special missions
                                authorized by the Commission shall be excepted from subparagraphs
                                    <hi rend="italic">d, e</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">f</hi>,
                                above.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">h</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Prisoners of war shall be exchanged on a one-for-one basis as
                                expeditiously as possible. Until the exchange of prisoners is
                                completed, representatives of the International Committee of the Red
                                Cross shall be permitted to visit all <gloss target="#t_POW1"
                                    >POW</gloss> camps to render such assistance as they can.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Organized bodies of armed forces including guerillas initially in
                                advance of the demilitarized zone shall be moved back or passed
                                through to the area of their own main forces.<note n="2"
                                    xml:id="d392fn2">
                                    <p>The following addition to the directive was forwarded to
                                        General Ridgway by the Joint Chiefs of Staff in telegram
                                            <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 95843, dated July
                                        9:</p>
                                    <p>“Add new para 6 to JSC 95354, 30 Jun 51:</p>
                                    <p>“‘Para 6. The foll provision is considered desirable, though
                                        not essential, for inclusion in the Armistice
                                        Arrangement:</p>
                                    <p>“‘Graves Registration personnel of the mil services shall be
                                        permitted free and unlimited access to all of Korea for the
                                        purposes of search, recovery, and evacuation of deceased and
                                        missing mil personnel. Provision for such matters as
                                        identification of Graves Registration personnel and escorts
                                        therefor shall be arranged as mutually agreed between <gloss
                                            target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss> and the Commander,
                                        Communist Forces in Korea.’”(Lot 55D128: Black Book, Tab
                                        44)</p>
                                </note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
