<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-07-17T05:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-07-17T05:45:00-05:00" n="449" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d449">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 55D128: Black Book, Tab 78:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, United Nations Command</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Ridgway</hi></persName>)
                                <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of
                                    Staff</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">flash</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Korea</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-07-17T20:15:00+09:30">17 July
                                    1951—8:15 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>HNC–108. This msg in five parts. Subj: Armistice conference at Kaesong 17
                            July 1951.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Part 1</hi>. Summary: Morning session of 50 minutes
                            taken up by Communist attempt to get United Nations Comd delegation to
                            divulge specific info on substance of items and to determine whether we
                            might concede add points. United Nations Comd delegation held firm on a
                                <pb facs="0708" n="692" xml:id="pg_692"/> rqst that Communists
                            provide us with their formal views on United Nations Comd proposed
                            revised agenda. (HNC 104 part 2.) Communists asked for two hour recess
                            to study United Nations Comd revised agenda. Afternoon session opened by
                            Communists and consisted of 35 minutes of reiteration of their views on
                            each item of their agenda. At the conclusion of their speech they
                            proposed a revised agenda for the adoption (part 2). Next meeting
                            scheduled for 1000, 18 Jul 1951.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Part 2</hi>. Progress made:</p>
                        <p>Based on revised agenda submitted by United Nations Comd delegation (ref
                            HNC 104, 16 Jul 51). Communist delegation submitted a proposed agenda.
                            This agenda approaches United Nations Comd views more closely than past
                            Communist agenda on all items except their item on withdrawal of foreign
                            troops from Korea. Communists proposed this agenda.</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Item 1</hi>. Adoption of agenda.</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Item 2</hi>. Fixing a demarcation line between both
                            sides so as to establish a demilitarized zone as a basic condition for
                            the cessation of hostilities in Korea.</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Item 3</hi>. Withdrawal of all armed forces of foreign
                            countries from Korea to insure against the resumption of hostilities and
                            acts of armed force in Korea.</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Item 4</hi>. Concrete arrangements for the realization
                            of cease fire and armistice in Korea, including the composition,
                            authority and functions of a supervising organization for carrying out
                            the terms of cease fire and armistice.</p>
                        <p>“<hi rend="italic">Item 5</hi>. Arrangements relating to prisoners of
                            war.”</p>
                        <p>The Communist delegation spent much time building a case for the
                            withdrawal of foreign troops from Korea and indicated that forceful and
                            persistent efforts would be continued to insure this item’s inclusion on
                            the agenda.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Part 3</hi>. Communist attitudes.</p>
                        <p>Nam Il’s opening remarks at the morning session was in question form
                            designed to insure that the United Nations Comd delegation would take
                            the floor. He attempted to keep the United Nations Comd delegation on
                            the floor and thus obtain a more concise statement of our views on his
                            preliminary opinions. This might well have been a play for time while
                            awaiting direction which would permit him to firm up his formerly
                            expressed preliminary opinions.</p>
                        <p>The afternoon session opened in a changed atmosphere. Nam Il took the
                            initiative and in a positive manner led up to the presentation of his
                            agenda. His approach however, was to present firm statements rather than
                            to argue or discuss the problem in detail. It appeared that definite
                            official instruction had been received since the noon recess.</p>
                        <pb facs="0709" n="693" xml:id="pg_693"/>
                        <p>The regular English translator read faster and used better English than
                            normally, indicating either a more studied approach or the possibility
                            that the translation had been furnished him and prepared by an
                            individual having better comd of the English language.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Part 4</hi>. Sequence of events.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Communist delegation opened morning session at
                            1100K stating they were ready to listen to further remarks of United
                            Nations Comd delegation. United Nations Comd delegation rqstd the formal
                            opinion of Communists concerning the proposed revised United Nations
                            Comd agenda which had been submitted the day before. It was obvious the
                            Communists were not prepared to present their views on this matter
                            during the morning session and stalled for time by asking questions
                            about the armistice commission and observer teams. United Nations Comd
                            delegation held firm to its rqst that they state their views on United
                            Nations Comd revised agenda. After 50 minutes, Communists rqstd two hour
                            recess for further study of United Nations Comd agenda. Just prior to
                            recess Nam Il stated that United Nations soldiers fired towards town of
                            Pan Mun Jom during period 1850–1905K, 16 Jul. He stated this was in
                            violation of the agreement on neutral zone. We responded that this
                            matter would be investigated. Morning session recessed at 1150K.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. Communist delegation opened afternoon session
                            at 1400K by a discussion of their agenda items and explaining more fully
                            why they should be adopted. The main point stressed was the withdrawal
                            of foreign troops from Korea. Communists maintained this is the basic
                            point in guaranteeing against the resumption of hostilities in Korea
                            once the cease fire has been ordered. They insist that this matter is a
                            military matter and must be discussed by the delegates present. They
                            stated it was the responsibility and duty of the delegates at this cease
                            fire conference to make arrangements for this matter. After this long
                            explanation the Communists presented a revised agenda which they
                            recommended be adopted. (See part 2). United Nations Comd delegation
                            rqstd the meeting adjourn until tomorrow in order that new Communist
                            agenda could be studied. Meeting adjourned at 1437K with agreement that
                            next meeting would be held at 1000K, 18 Jul.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Part 5</hi>. Conclusions: We conclude that:</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Communists still desire to reach early
                            agreement on agenda in spite of delays today. They were either
                            uninstructed or unprepared for the morning session.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. They intend to stand firm for the present at
                            least, on the point that withdrawal of foreign troops from Korea is a
                            military matter and must be on the agenda for discussion. However, it is
                            too early to predict whether this will be a breaking point.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>