<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commander in Chief, United Nations Command ( (Ridgway) ) to the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d521</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">521</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-08-17T07:58:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-08-17T07:58:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-17T07:58:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-17T07:58:00-05:00" n="521"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d521">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 55D128: Black Book, Tab 43: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, United Nations Command</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ridgway</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of
                            Staff</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-17T22:58:00+10:00">17
                            August 1951—10:58 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>C–69108. This msg in 3 parts. “Subj is meeting of subdelegation at Kaesong 17
                    Aug.</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">Part 1</hi>. Summary:</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Subdelegation first met very informally around two
                    foot round table. Hodes explained possible ways break deadlock such as
                    Communists give up 38th parallel or we give up our proposed zone or they suggest
                    adjustments to our zone or go to another agenda item. Communists asked for our
                    specific proposal. Hodes countered with trying to get agreement on these 3
                    points: <list>
                        <item>“(1) Military armistice has nothing to do with ultimate territory
                            arrangements in Korea.</item>
                        <item>“(2) Demilitarized zone should be positioned so that balance of
                            military advantages existing at time of armistice is not upset.</item>
                        <item>“(3) Each side should have defensible positions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">b</hi>. They would not state specifically whether they agreed
                    or not but did state they wanted equitable armistice based on 38th parallel.
                    Hsieh Fang proposed we all look at a map. Looked at United Nations map showing
                    their proposed zone, our proposed zone and battle lines. <pb facs="0846" n="830"
                        xml:id="pg_830"/> Much repetition covering same ground as plenary sessions
                    but faster and more direct. They maintain: <list>
                        <item>“(1) 38th parallel only sound solution.</item>
                        <item>“(2) Battle line does not represent military situation. I say again
                            for emphasis ‘that the ground battle line now existing does not
                            represent military situation’.</item>
                        <item>“(3) Their ground forces can push us south of 38th parallel at any
                            time and therefore balance of power is now on their side.</item>
                        <item>“(4) We should accept their word as a guarantee they will not attack
                            during armistice.</item>
                        <item>“(5) Air and Navy have some minor effects on war but only on position
                            of battle line (we did not like that either).</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. We explained reasons for our original zone and
                    possible hypothetical adjustments such as narrowing zone and adjusting southern
                    boundary. Asked them for proposal. They discussed 38th parallel as military
                    demarcation line showing adjustments in demilitarized zone possible in width of
                    zone and adjustments of boundaries to fit terrain but keeping 38th parallel as
                    military demarcation line within the demilitarized zone.</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. In discussion of other agenda items they asked what
                    could be decided unless demilitarized zone was first decided. We replied
                    exchange information on location prisoner of war camps, number prisoners in each
                    camp, names of prisoners, inspection of camps by Red Cross and even exchange was
                    possible. They not interested. In discussing inspection teams it evident they
                    now thinking only of inspection within demilitarized zone and not behind it
                    stating we have to take their word in good faith. They refused to discuss other
                    agenda items until item 2 decided. Our subdelegation made it very plain several
                    times that the United Nations, the United Nations Command, our main delegation
                    and our subdelegation would not accept the 38th parallel as a military
                    demarcation line. A demilitarized zone including the 38th parallel would not be
                    acceptable. We would discuss any zone or any military demarcation line based on
                    the present military situation. Subdelegation meetings continue tomorrow.</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">Part 2</hi>. Progress: None.</p>
                <p>“<hi rend="italic">Part 3</hi>. Conclusions:</p>
                <p>“The <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> Delegation feels that they expect to
                    milk us for as much information as possible before giving up 38th parallel or
                    breaking conference. Chinese apparently prefers subdelegation method of meeting
                    because they can then talk. Hsieh spoke frequently and poured oil when waters
                    got troubled. Maybe Chinese will be willing to discuss some zone other than one
                    based on 38th parallel but evidence of that extremely slight so far.”</p>
                <p>I concur.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
