<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commander in Chief, Far East ( (Ridgway) ) to the Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d582</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">582</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-09-24T04:09:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-09-24T04:09:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-09-24T04:09:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-24T04:09:00-05:00" n="582"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d582">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 55D128: Black Book, Tab 80: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, Far East</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ridgway</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of
                            Staff</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">operational immediate</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-09-24T18:09:00+09:00">24
                            September 1951—6:09 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>C–51500. Urmsg <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 82085.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d582fn1">Dated September 21, <ref target="#pg_924">p.
                        924</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. Concur in desirability of introducing a new <gloss target="#t_UNC1"
                        >UNC</gloss> proposal in writing after resumption of mil armistice
                    discussions.</p>
                <p>2. On renewal of substantive talks <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> delegation
                    intends to submit a specific proposal in writing, accompanied by a map, showing
                        <pb facs="0950" n="934" xml:id="pg_934"/> demilitarized zone approx 20
                    kilometers wide generally north of battle line. Demilitarized zone will be
                    essentially a more exact specification of the informal proposal presented in the
                    sub-committee prior to the 23 Aug recess.</p>
                <p>3. Should the Communists retreat from their previous arbitrary psn on 38th
                    parallel, the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> delegation will be prepared to
                    modify <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> psn above and to make concessions
                    towards a psn more favorable to Communists. During all discussions <gloss
                        target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> delegation will emphasize its willingness to
                    discuss modifications providing Communists are willing to abandon their adamant
                    stand that the 38th parallel is the only acceptable demarcation line.</p>
                <p>4. Believe it important that initial psn taken by <gloss target="#t_UNC1"
                        >UNC</gloss> delegation should be such that Communists will not interpret it
                    as a weakening of our psn. If psns more favorable to Communists were initially
                    offered, Communists would conclude that long recess engineered by them resulted
                    directly in considerable reward to their side. They would be encouraged to
                    instigate similar delays in future in expectation of obtaining similar
                    results.</p>
                <p>5. In addition <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> present bargaining psn should
                    be considerably improved as a result of the more advantageous mil psn <gloss
                        target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> now enjoys due to recent mil action.</p>
                <p>6. Ref your para 3. Demilitarized zones discussed thus far by the <gloss
                        target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> delegation have been negotiating psns and have
                    not approached the final <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> psn. The initial
                    proposal to the Communists when negotiations resume is not one which we should
                    prematurely publish to the world but is one from which we can bargain with the
                    Communists. When the Communists indicate that they are willing to drop their
                    firm stand on the 38th parallel and begin to talk in terms of mil realities, the
                        <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> delegation can withdraw as nec to other
                    psns. Our minimum psn should only be given in final and unalterable “take it or
                    leave it” terms unless Communists first give up 38th parallel. Otherwise
                    Communists will consider it simply as major concession in process of
                    negotiations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
