<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Position Paper, Prepared in the Department of State, for the United States
                    Delegation to the United Nations General Assembly</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d629</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">629</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-10-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-10-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="629"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d629">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/10–1251</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Position Paper, Prepared in the Department of State, for the
                            <gloss type="from">United States Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">United Nations General Assembly</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/> SD/A/C.1/368</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-10-12">October 12,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">United Nations Action in Korea</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Alternative</hi> II—<hi rend="smallcaps">If an Armistice Is
                    Achieved</hi>)</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">the problem</hi>
                </p>
                <p>To determine the position of the United States as to the steps to be taken by the
                    Sixth Session of the General Assembly after an armistice in Korea.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. The United States should continue to play a leading role in General Assembly
                    consideration of the Korean question and should direct the efforts of the
                    Assembly towards the achievement of a satisfactory political settlement of the
                    Korean problem.</p>
                <p>2. The United States should support a resolution which would reaffirm that it
                    remains the purpose of the United Nations to seek to bring about by peaceful
                    means a unified, independent and democratic government in Korea. To that end,
                    the resolution should appoint a United Nations delegation with broad terms of
                    reference which would enter into discussions with interested parties designed to
                    achieve agreement on a political settlement for Korea. The delegation would not
                    be authorized to discuss problems other than Korea. Any agreement which it
                    reaches would be subject to approval by the General Assembly.</p>
                <p>3. In the first instance, we should prefer a small delegation consisting of the
                    representatives of the United States and two other countries from among those
                    which have participated in the fighting in Korea, e.g., Thailand and Australia.
                    If informal discussions indicate that the United Kingdom and France strongly
                    desire a place on the delegation, the delegation is authorized to agree to
                    including them.</p>
                <p>4. The resolution should call on <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss>
                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>) to advise the new United Nations Delegation as
                    requested, and <hi rend="italic">b</hi>) to continue to exercise its functions
                    under the General Assembly resolution of October 7, 1950 in such a manner as to
                    support the efforts of the United Nations Delegation. Except in this regard, the
                    composition and character of <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss> would not
                    be changed at this time but the future of <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1"
                        >UNCURK</gloss> would be reviewed in the light of the report to be submitted
                    by the United Nations Delegation on its efforts to achieve a peaceful settlement
                    in Korea.</p>
                <pb facs="1037" n="1021" xml:id="pg_1021"/>
                <p>5. The proposed resolutions should also refer to past resolutions by the Security
                    Council and General Assembly on the United Nations action in Korea, note the
                    approval of the armistice by the Security Council, express the Assembly’s own
                    satisfaction over the conclusion of the armistice and the successful
                    accomplishment by United Nations forces of their mission in Korea. Friendly
                    delegations may feel, however, that such provisions will antagonize the
                    Communists and jeopardize the possibility of a political settlement, and the
                    delegation is authorized to omit or reverse these provisions if consultations
                    indicate strong opposition. In that event, we should reach an understanding with
                    other delegations that a stronger General Assembly resolution leaving the record
                    clear as to the character and purpose of the United Nations action in Korea
                    would be introduced at a later date, if efforts to achieve a political
                    settlement break down.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">A. <hi rend="italic">Political Settlement for Korea</hi>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Objective is Unification</hi>. An armistice in Korea will
                    bring about a cessation of the fighting and make provisions against its
                    resumption. It will constitute only the first step towards the achievement of a
                    permanent peace in Korea and a political solution of the Korean problem by
                    peaceful means.</p>
                <p>The United Nations is committed to seeking the establishment in Korea of a
                    unified, independent and democratic government. Such unification has also been
                    the policy of the United States, and represents the desires of the Korean
                    people. Every effort should be made, therefore, after an armistice, to bring
                    about such unification under United Nations auspices, in accordance with United
                    Nations principles, and under conditions which would provide maximum assurance
                    against Communist aggression and subversion. At the same time it is the United
                    States position that it is preferable to have Korea divided on an indefinite
                    basis under an armistice agreement than to have a unification under conditions
                    which would not give maximum assurance against Communist domination.</p>
                <p>The Communists have also taken the position that the armistice is only the first
                    step and a political settlement must follow. They have also championed the
                    unification of Korea. It is extremely unlikely, however, that the Communists
                    would agree to a truly independent and democratic Korea to free elections under
                    United Nations auspices, and a process of unification under the guidance of a
                    United Nations commission. More likely they will seek a political settlement on
                    terms which would permit them to gain control of all Korea. Failing that, as
                    they have already indicated, they may seek an agreement for the <pb facs="1038"
                        n="1022" xml:id="pg_1022"/> mutual withdrawal of non-Korean troops. At the
                    same time, the United States could not support any political settlement which
                    gives up the goal of unification and accepts the division of the country as
                    permanent. It would be better to have the armistice continue in effect as an
                    armistice only. The United Nations troops would stay as long as was necessary in
                    order to ensure the defense of the Republic of Korea against renewed aggression.
                    The United Nations would keep alive the principle of unification and continue
                    its efforts through appropriate machinery to achieve it.</p>
                <p>Whatever the prospects of success, the General Assembly should, after an
                    armistice, reaffirm unification as the only acceptable solution for Korea and
                    extend every effort to achieve a unified Korea on a United Nations basis. It is
                    important also that the United States take the initiative in this regard and not
                    allow the Communists the propaganda advantage of posing as the principal
                    proponents of a unified Korea.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Participants in a Korean Conference</hi>. The United Kingdom
                    has indicated its view that following an armistice, a political solution of the
                    Korean problem should be sought at a Five-Power Conference (United States,
                    United Kingdom, USSR, France, Communist China) or Seven-Power Conference (the
                    same powers plus, presumably, India and Egypt), with some kind of “associate”
                    participation by the Republic of Korea and the North Koreans. (After agreement
                    is reached on a Korean settlement, the United Kingdom has in mind that the same
                    conference might also deal with other Far Eastern problems). We have informed
                    the United Kingdom that we do not accept this approach which contemplates a
                    solution of the Korean problem by the Great Powers without any participation by
                    the United Nations or by other countries vitally interested in the Pacific
                    (e.g., Australia, New Zealand, the Philippines) and only a secondary
                    participation for the Koreans, the real parties in interest. We also indicated
                    that we could not agree to any arrangement which might give the impression that
                    we were treating Peiping as the Government of China. (With regard to a
                    discussion of other Far Eastern questions, we informed the United Kingdom that
                    neither the Five- nor the Seven-Power conference would be representative of the
                    United Nations membership on such questions as Chinese representation and
                    Formosa, but that after a Korean settlement, we would be prepared to discuss
                    other Far Eastern questions in an appropriate forum which would include all the
                    parties with interests in the questions to be discussed).</p>
                <p>As the United Kingdom was informed, it is our position that the Korean problem
                    should be solved by the parties in interest. Strictly, this would mean that the
                    question should be discussed by representatives <pb facs="1039" n="1023"
                        xml:id="pg_1023"/> of the Republic of Korea and of the North Koreans; the
                    United Nations should participate also in view of its continuing interest in the
                    Korean problem and the role it must play both in achieving a settlement and in
                    supervising its implementation. It is foreseeable, however, that the Soviet
                    Union and the Chinese Communists might both claim a voice in the solution of the
                    Korean problem basing their claim on their interests as neighbors and a long
                    history of relations with Korea. Since, as a realistic matter, no agreement for
                    a Korean settlement could be achieved without their consent or acquiescence,
                    particularly with Chinese Communist and perhaps some Soviet troops remaining in
                    Korea even after an armistice, the United States is prepared to agree to their
                    participation in a conference to discuss a Korean settlement.</p>
                <p>From statements made during the armistice negotiations, it would appear that a
                    conference generally along these lines is the kind which the Communist would
                    agree to. Most likely, the Chinese Communists would wish to participate,
                    particularly since in the past, it has been indicated that they insist on a role
                    in a political settlement for Korea. Whether the Soviet Union desires to
                    participate is more questionable. They may prefer, as in other cases, to deal
                    through a satellite so that while they are represented in fact they are not
                    formally bound by the results of the conference. Nevertheless, they should be
                    offered the opportunity to participate. It is contemplated that we would
                    approach the Russians either at the United Nations or in Moscow to inform them
                    of our proposed plan for a political conference and to ascertain their attitude
                    on participation and on other aspects of the proposed resolution.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United Nations Delegation</hi>. The proposed resolution
                    would have the General Assembly appoint a delegation to represent the United
                    Nations in discussions of a possible political settlement for Korea. The United
                    Nations Delegation would have full freedom to discuss with anybody it wishes,
                    arrange an appropriate conference, and attempt to reach an effective
                    agreement.</p>
                <p>The Delegation we envisage would consist of the United States, which has played a
                    principal role in the recent history of Korea and in the United Nations action
                    there, together with two other members of the United Nations from among those
                    who have participated in the fighting in Korea, preferably from the Far East.
                    Thailand and Australia appear to be logical choices, but the Delegation may
                    agree to substitute others which are acceptable from the US point of view.</p>
                <p>Every effort should be made to persuade other delegations, and particularly the
                    French and the British to agree to such an arrangement. If they agree, we would,
                    of course, keep them informed as to the progress <pb facs="1040" n="1024"
                        xml:id="pg_1024"/> of any moves or negotiations by the United Nations
                    Delegation. The British and French, however, may insist that they participate,
                    in view of their general Far Eastern interests and their role in the fighting in
                    Korea. While we would seek a conference of the kind indicated including the
                    concept of a United Nations Delegation, if the French and the British insist, we
                    would have little choice but to agree to their participation in such a
                    Delegation. In any event, it should be clear that the delegation represents the
                    United Nations, that its purpose is to achieve a unified, independent and
                    democratic Korea, and that it is not to deal with questions other than Korea.
                    The Delegation would report to the General Assembly and any agreement it might
                    reach for a Korean settlement would be subject to General Assembly approval.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Relation to <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss>
                    </hi>. Since the United Nations Delegation would be performing in effect one of
                    the principal tasks assigned to <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss>, the
                    resolution should set forth the relationship of the delegation to <gloss
                        target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1"
                        >UNCURK</gloss> would be called upon to advise the delegation as requested.
                        <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss> would also continue to carry out
                    its other functions under the October 7 resolution so far as consistent with the
                    activities of the United Nations Delegation and in such a manner as not to
                    interfere with the Delegation.</p>
                <p>If the United Nations Delegation succeeds in achieving agreement for a political
                    settlement in Korea, that settlement will undoubtedly include reference to the
                    kind of United Nations body which would be agreeable for implementing the
                    settlement. The future of <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss> would,
                    therefore, have to be reviewed at that time in the light of the agreement
                    reached. If the United Nations Delegation reports failure, the Assembly will
                    nevertheless wish to keep alive its objective of achieving a unified Korea and
                    will want appropriate machinery to that end. Whether it should be <gloss
                        target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss>, in its present form and with its present
                    terms of reference, is a question which the Assembly will want to consider in
                    the light of the report of the United Nations Delegation on the failure of the
                    settlement talks and of the history and record of <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1"
                        >UNCURK</gloss> to date. See Position Paper SD/A/C.1/369.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">Approval of the Armistice</hi>.</p>
                <p>It is expected that if an armistice is reached, a resolution will be introduced
                    in the Security Council noting the armistice with approval. Some of our allies
                    would like to see a resolution which does that and no more. The United States
                    would wish the resolution, as a minimum, to refer to and reaffirm past
                    resolutions of the United Nations in regard to the action and objectives in
                    Korea, in order to avoid the impression that we were giving up the United
                    Nations version of what has happened in Korea and were willing to rewrite or
                    forget that <pb facs="1041" n="1025" xml:id="pg_1025"/> history. The United
                    States would also like a provision which would explicitly refer the problem of
                    the political settlement of Korea to the General Assembly.</p>
                <p>The action in the General Assembly would, of course, have to take account of any
                    resolution which might be adopted in the Security Council. The proposed
                    resolution should refer to the Security Council resolution and also indicate the
                    Assembly’s approval of the armistice. Particularly since some countries have
                    already indicated a desire for a simple uncontroversial resolution in the
                    Security Council in the hope of getting Soviet support for that resolution, the
                    United States would like the subsequent action of the General Assembly to set
                    the record straight on the whole Korean episode. We would not wish to leave the
                    world confused and uncertain as to the real character and purpose of the action
                    in Korea. It must remain clear that there was Communist aggression in Korea,
                    that the United Nations action was designed solely to meet this aggression and
                    that the United Nations has succeeded in this mission, and has not altered or
                    abandoned its original objectives in Korea as a result of the conflict.</p>
                <p>It may be anticipated that there will be objection to such provisions. It will be
                    argued that such a resolution would antagonize the Communists and jeopardize the
                    possibility of achieving a political settlement in Korea. If consultations
                    reveal strong views to this effect, it may be necessary to omit or soften these
                    provisions. In doing so, however, it should be made clear that we consider this
                    only a postponement and that if efforts to achieve a political settlement break
                    down, we will wish a stronger resolution along these lines.</p>
                <p>In this regard, the delegation should warn other delegations against the dangers
                    of assuming that the achievement of an armistice means a radical change in
                    Soviet objectives. Such an attitude could have serious consequences going beyond
                    the question of United Nations action in regard to Korea. The United States is
                    always ready to welcome true Soviet cooperation in support of the United Nations
                    Charter; we have no concern or desire to maintain cold war tension. We would
                    have to have much more and stronger evidence of Soviet change of heart, however,
                    before we were persuaded that the USSR had suddenly decided to give up all ideas
                    of aggression and Communist imperialism and has started on the path of peaceful
                    cooperation. The Soviet attitude to the armistice in Korea must not be allowed
                    to engender false and dangerous impression that all will be sweetness and light
                    on the international scene. Such an impression would lull us into a false
                    security, and jeopardize all our efforts to build up the strength of the free
                    world and to maintain free world unity against aggression in and out of the
                    United Nations. Within the United Nations it might tend to <pb facs="1042"
                        n="1026" xml:id="pg_1026"/> paralyze action on almost any subject which some
                    delegations might feel would antagonize the Russians.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
