<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="674" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d674">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/11–251</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by H. O. H. Frelinghuysen and Walter
                                Treumann of the Office of Northeast Asian Affairs</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-02">November 2, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Item No. 3 of the Armistice Agenda</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is recommended that:</p>
                        <p>(1) General Ridgway’s proposal, contained in <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss>’s C52227<note n="1" xml:id="d674fn1">Dated October
                                4, <ref target="#pg_997">p. 997</ref>.</note> remain our initial
                            position in the negotiations on Item 3.</p>
                        <pb facs="1098" n="1082" xml:id="pg_1082"/>
                        <p>(2) In the event that negotiations threaten to break down on this
                            proposal this Government adopt as its <hi rend="italic">minimum</hi>
                            position on Item 3 “joint inspection of the demilitarized area.”</p>
                        <p>(3) The following additional provisions be considered as desirable lesser
                            alternatives, which are not essential but which could be used for
                            bargaining purposes:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Inspection teams located at strategic points within an area 100
                                miles each side of the demarcation line with necessary rail, air and
                                sea access to their own area. This provision would avoid Communist
                                opposition to inspection along the Sino-Soviet border and our
                                opposition to inspection in the Pusan area.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Reciprocal aerial and naval inspection of all of Korea.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Failing agreement on (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) reference of the subject of inspection and
                                supervisory machinery to a special armistice committee which might
                                continue the discussion after the termination of hostilities for the
                                purpose of arranging periodic inspections of vital areas.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>(4) In the event that recommendation (2) is accepted as governmental
                            policy, preparatory propaganda action be taken to obtain the full
                            support of <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>, US and UN public opinion
                            and at the same time to demonstrate to the Communists that our failure
                            to insist on inspection in no way lessens our determination to resist
                            any renewed aggression.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Item 3 on the Armistice Agenda provides for concrete arrangements for the
                            realization of the cease-fire and armistice in Korea, including the
                            composition, authority and functions of a supervising organization for
                            carrying out the terms of a cease-fire and armistice”. <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss>’s message C52227, October 4,
                            suggests modifications to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> message
                            95354 of June 30 on the same subject.</p>
                        <p>According to <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss>’s C52227 the
                            purpose of inspection is to insure that “there is no buildup of troops
                            or supplies in such significant quantities as would, if continued,
                            substantially impair the security of the UN forces, as that security
                            existed when the armistice became effective.” Although the only real
                            deterrent to a renewed attack in Korea is the strength of the free world
                            and its determination to resist aggression, inspection is designed to
                            serve as an additional deterrent to Communist aggression and to gather
                            intelligence which could give UN forces sufficient time to prepare
                            against an enemy attack.</p>
                        <p>Since the Communist mode of operation is basically opposed to the concept
                            of inspection or supervision in the satellite areas and since Communist
                            negotiators may adamantly oppose inspection in north Korea and thereby
                            risk the break-down of the armistice talks, consideration should be
                            given to the question whether and to what extent <pb facs="1099" n="1083" xml:id="pg_1083"/> an inspection of north Korea can
                            actually accomplish these purposes and what concomitant advantages we
                            could derive from the inspection.</p>
                        <p>The presence of joint inspection teams in north Korea would be of some
                            value in inhibiting preparations for renewed Communist aggression. The
                            mere fact of their being in north Korea might deter the more flagrant
                            violations of the cease-fire terms. Their report to the UN of Communist
                            violations might rally the free world into taking defensive
                            measures—short of military action—to meet the new threat. Such reports
                            would also have a propaganda value in pointing up Communist bad faith
                            and aggressive intentions.</p>
                        <p>Joint inspection teams would contribute to the acquisition of
                            intelligence, thereby keeping the UN Command apprised of Communist
                            capabilities and intentions. This factor might also have a deterring
                            effect on Communist aggressive designs.</p>
                        <p>Inspection teams would provide an added sense of security to the Republic
                            of Korea and might lessen somewhat the opposition of the Korean
                            Government and people to a cease-fire in a divided Korea.</p>
                        <p>However, the accomplishment of the purposes for which inspection under
                            Item 3 was designed will be severely limited by a number of serious
                            weaknesses. Even in the event of a Communist buildup and reports of the
                            inspection teams to the UN to that effect, it would be most difficult to
                            earn UN support for taking the military initiative in renewing
                            hostilities and smashing the buildup. By its very nature the UN would
                            probably have to wait for an overt act of aggression before taking
                            military countreaction. Failure of the UN to initiate punitive action
                            might be interpreted as a sign of its weakness, would tend to vitiate
                            the propaganda and psychological advantages derived from the inspection
                            reports, and might encourage the Communists to commit further
                            violations.</p>
                        <p>In the event of Communist bad faith it is doubtful that the presence of
                            the inspection teams could assure against a Communist buildup. The
                            Communists would probably neither permit teams of sufficient size nor
                            grant them adequate freedom of movement and observation to prevent
                            surreptitious evasion of the armistice terms. Moreover, the Communists
                            could increase their military capabilities by building up storage areas,
                            repairing airfields, and rebuilding their lines of communications under
                            the guise of civilian rehabilitation.</p>
                        <p>UN members of inspection teams would be under constant administrative
                            difficulties in north Korea, since Communists would make every effort to
                            hamstring and embarrass them. In case the Communists wanted a particular
                            area free from inspection they would undoubtedly find ways to prevent
                            free access to the teams and thereby impede the acquisition of
                            intelligence. The inability to define in advance the exact functions of
                            the teams would make for additional difficulties. In event <pb facs="1100" n="1084" xml:id="pg_1084"/> of Communist efforts to
                            embarrass the teams the prestige of the UN might be adversely
                            affected.</p>
                        <p>The presence of Communist inspectors in south Korea might impede our
                            attempts to rebuild the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> forces. In
                            this case the USSR, Communist China and north Korea could utilize
                            reports from their observers in south Korea to point up the “aggressive
                            designs” of the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and pave the way for
                            an attempted justification of what they would term a “defensive” buildup
                            of Communist forces in north Korea. Communist inspectors would also
                            derive a broad range of intelligence about our forces in the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>, particularly if they were stationed in
                            the Pusan area. There would be inevitable friction between Communist
                            observers and the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> Government, since
                            the latter would probably make every effort to circumscribe the
                            activities of the teams.</p>
                        <p>Unless the provisions for inspection can be so strengthened in the
                            negotiations as to eliminate these weaknesses and unless definite
                            punitive provisions are written into the agreement to assure its
                            implementation, inspection would probably not adequately fulfill the
                            purposes for which it is designed. From a political point of view, we
                            should be wary of committing ourselves to a course of action whose
                            implementation would be accompanied by innumerable embarrassing
                            incidents; whose enforcement through a renewal of hostilities would be
                            difficult to justify, would necessitate renewed fighting, thus
                            increasing the threat of World War III, and be a source of friction with
                            our allies; and whose non-enforcement would adversely affect the
                            prestige of the UN. From the practical standpoint, the ultimate sanction
                            against a renewal of the aggression is not the presence of inspection
                            teams in north Korea but the clear likelihood that renewed fighting
                            cannot and will not be limited in scope as the present hostilities have
                            been.</p>
                        <p>It is therefore not believed that we should insist so rigidly on our
                            initial bargaining position (C52227) as to risk the break-down of the
                            armistice talks and a continuation of hostilities. A final governmental
                            decision on this question must, of course, also rest on an assessment by
                            the Department of Defense of the military value of inspection and its
                            effect on the security of the United Nations forces.</p>
                        <p>It must be recognized that any subsequent modification of our position on
                            Item 3 might result in an unfavorable reaction by American public
                            opinion, segments of which may consider inspection necessary to the
                            security of the UN forces and may charge appeasement, particularly if a
                            renewed Communist attack threatens our military position. Every effort
                            will therefore have to be made to publicize the reasons for our stand
                            and to emphasize the adverse consequences of a break-down of the
                            armistice talks—whether the result is a prolonged <pb facs="1101" n="1085" xml:id="pg_1085"/> period of indecisive conflict or a
                            widening of the area of hostilities.<note n="2" xml:id="d674fn2">
                                <p>On November 5, U. Alexis Johnson forwarded this memorandum to
                                    Messrs. Matthews, Hickerson, Bohlen, and Nitze under cover of a
                                    brief memorandum which read in part as follows:</p>
                                <p>“I am circulating this memo for your concurrence or comments in
                                    the hope that we can arrive quickly at a Departmental position.
                                    I believe that we should consider carefully the method and
                                    timing of our presentation of this position to Defense.”</p>
                                <p>The question of inspection was taken up at a State–<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> meeting on November 16; see
                                        <ref target="#pg_1141">p. 1141</ref>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>