<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-02T05:31:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-02T05:31:00-05:00" n="675" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d675">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 55D128: Black Book, Tab 49:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, Far East</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Ridgway</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-02T19:31:00+09:00">2 November
                                    1951—7:31 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>C–56468. HNC 417. “Sub-delegation reports as follows: Morning session
                            devoted to:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Communist prepared statement upholding their proposal and
                                denouncing our proposal as unfair, etc, with emphasis on Kaesong
                                area.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>In order to clarify a remark of Lee’s to the effect that their
                                proposal was their maximum effort we asked, ‘Is that an ultimatum?’
                                Lee would not give a direct answer and developments indicated
                                clearly that he did not in any way want to infer that he was issuing
                                an ultimatum.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>Demonstration on our part by referring to the map to consider
                                certain adjustments closely coinciding or coinciding exactly with
                                their zone in the eastern three fourths of the battle line.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>“The afternoon session began with a firm re-statement of our position
                            with emphasis on its fairness and our requirement for the Kaesong area,
                            Hsieh of course refuted again all arguments to our justification for
                            this area. The Communists insist on avoiding all consideration at this
                            time of islands as an additional bargaining point possibly with the
                            intent of having us drop them at a later day as unimportant. Although no
                            visible progress made today, this was only second day after their
                            proposal and therefore too soon to expect any sign of Communist
                            weakening.”</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>