<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Joint Chiefs of Staff to the Commander in Chief, Far East (
                    (Ridgway))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d684</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">684</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-11-06T18:27:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-11-06T18:27:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-06T18:27:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-06T18:27:00-05:00" n="684"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d684">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 55D128: Black Book, Tab 57: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Joint Chiefs of Staff</gloss> to the
                        Commander in Chief, Far East</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ridgway</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">operational immediate</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-06T18:27:00-05:00">6
                            November 1951—6:27 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>–86291. From <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                        >JCS</gloss>.</p>
                <p>1. Ur C 56546, CX 56598, C 56601, C 56667 and C 56713 considered.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d684fn1">Dated respectively, November 3, 4, 4, 5, and 6, <ref
                            target="#pg_1086">pp. 1086</ref>, <ref target="#pg_1087">1087</ref>,
                            <ref target="#pg_1089">1089</ref>, <ref target="#pg_1090">1090</ref>,
                        and <ref target="#pg_1091">1091</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. Line of action as described in CX 56598 considered sound.</p>
                <p>3. In support of your contentions in CX 56598 re Kaesong <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                        >JCS</gloss> feel that line in this area proposed by Communists is one which
                    we would rather accept than let negotiations break down or reach a stalemate.
                    Consequently, if Communists flatly reject your latest approach and negotiation
                    on this point appears fruitless, the quicker we accept a <pb facs="1109"
                        n="1093" xml:id="pg_1093"/> compromise the less it will appear as an
                    important backdown both here and as far as Communist propaganda is
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>4. Throughout we have taken as basic principle that demarkation line should be
                    generally along battle line. Communists now appear to have accepted this
                    principle. We feel that in general this adequately meets our minimum position re
                    demilitarized zone.</p>
                <p>5. Judging from press reaction here it would be hard to make the people
                    understand why negotiations broke down, if such should happen, over Kaesong in
                    face of recent Communist concessions. This fact has been mentioned several times
                    in last few days both on radio and in press.</p>
                <p>6. If your latest proposal to postpone agreement on a line of mil demarkation and
                    demilitarized zone is rejected completely by Chinese-<gloss target="#t_NK1"
                        >NK</gloss> delegation, and further negotiation along this approach appears
                    fruitless, early agreement generally along proposed Chinese-<gloss
                        target="#t_NK1">NK</gloss> line in Kaesong area is advisable.</p>
                <p>7. However, <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> are concerned over latest
                    Communist proposal as expressed in C 56713 since agreement to such a proposal
                    would have practical effect of curtailing further UN ground advances beyond
                    agreed line of contact. This would be militarily unacceptable unless agreement
                    on all other agenda items also was reached shortly thereafter. Accordingly,
                    although latest Communist proposal insofar as location of demilitarized zone is
                    concerned meets our basic position and is thus acceptable, such acceptance must
                    be qualified by a time limitation for completion of all agenda items, preferably
                    a definite period in which major forward UN ground operations are not otherwise
                    contemplated. It would be stipulated that in the event agreement is not reached
                    on all agenda items within the definite period specified, location of the
                    demilitarized zone is subject to revision. Your comments are requested <gloss
                        target="#t_ASAP1">ASAP</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d684fn2">
                        <p>General Ridgway transmitted the following reply in his telegram C–56767,
                            November 7, from Tokyo:</p>
                        <p>“Am forwarding your <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 86291 to Adm Joy
                            immediately. I plan to spend tomorrow night, 8 November, in Korea. Will
                            discuss this msg with Adm Joy at that time and submit my views to you
                            soonest thereafter.” (Black Book, Tab 58)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
