<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Northeast Asian Affiairs (
                    (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d700</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">700</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="700"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d700">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 55D128: Black Book, Tab 77</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of Northeast Asian
                        Affiairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-12">November 12,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Notes for Discussion with</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Nov.</hi> 12<note n="1" xml:id="d700fn1">For the record of
                        the State–<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> meeting, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >infra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">background</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Opinion in US and elsewhere is confused as Commies have made major
                        concession on demarcation line and remaining differences are too subtle for
                        general understanding.</item>
                    <pb facs="1137" n="1121" xml:id="pg_1121"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Participating UN nations have thus far fully supported our position in
                        negotiations and free world opinion has, in general, been behind us.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>However, present situation has elements capable of exploitation by Commies
                        to our disadvantage by reversion to 38th parallel or other such proposal
                        which would be simple and readily understandable, and might appear
                        reasonable in face of inability to reach agreement apparent details of
                        present proposals. Vishinski speech may have presaged such a reversion in
                        event no early agreement item 2. It may, of course, merely have been bluff
                        to hurry us into an agreement less favorable to us.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Understanding of Department in [<hi rend="italic">is</hi>] that, apart
                        from Kaesong question, essential difference between present Commie and
                            <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposals is that <gloss
                            target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> proposals leave to later agreement
                        adjustments in line of demarcation based upon present line of contact, while
                        under Commie proposals line demarcation would be unchanged in absence
                        subsequent agreement by both sides to adjustments.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Ridgway has now proposed and we have concurred in simply proposing
                        reaching agreement now line demarcation will be line contact effective date
                        armistice (presumably without adjustments unless agreed to by both sides.)
                        Question whether Commies will accept as in view importance they have
                        attached to Kaesong may suspect that <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>
                        intention is to outflank or cut off Kaesong.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>If this correct, appears only basis for agreement is agreeing line
                        demarcation will be approximately present line of contact with only such
                        subsequent adjustments as agreed upon by both sides.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>We are therefore faced with the two alternatives of standing firm on our
                        proposal and accepting the risk of a break-down or of accepting the Commie
                        proposal. If we follow latter alternative, we should do so as soon as
                        possible from standpoint public opinion and prestige and our position on
                        other items on agenda.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>If second alternative would in fact tend to establish conditions <hi
                            rend="italic">de facto</hi> cease-fire on ground, advantages or
                        disadvantages to <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> must be fully explored. <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Advantages: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Continuation armistice talks.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Full support allies.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Some assurance of line considerably in advance of line
                                        Kansas in event of forced withdrawal of <gloss
                                            target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> forces as a result
                                        successful Commie attack.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Giving our ground forces respite while air and naval war
                                        (in which we have advantage) continues in full force.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>Commies are, in effect, giving up ground force arm which
                                        is only arm they can presently use to bring effective
                                        pressure on us while we retain full use of air and navy
                                        arms.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <pb facs="1138" n="1122" xml:id="pg_1122"/>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Disadvantages: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Guaranty of line to Commies who have been gradually forced
                                        to withdraw as result continued UN offensive and then
                                        possibly a lessening of pressure on Commies to agree to
                                        other agenda items.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Morale UN forces.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Propaganda advantage to Commies (bargaining
                                        victory).</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Certain freedom of movement of Commie forces. Commies
                                        could weaken their own forces somewhat if they so
                                        desired.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>US public opinion event Commie bad faith.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>While disadvantages appear outweigh advantages these can be minimized by the
                    placing of a time limit upon completion of other agenda items as suggested in
                    paragraph 7 <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 86291.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d700fn2">Dated November 6, <ref target="#pg_1092">p.
                        1092</ref>.</note> Ridgway objects to this on ground that we would
                    inevitably be compelled to accept extensions of the period. This is not
                    necessarily true and as it appears best alternative we should urge its
                    reconsideration by Ridgway. Such a formula would be readily understood and
                    accepted by public opinion and it would be difficult for the Communists to show
                    that it is not reasonable.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
