<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commander in Chief, Far East ( (Ridgway) ) to the Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d752</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">752</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-11-28T08:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-11-28T08:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-28T08:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-28T08:30:00-05:00" n="752"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d752">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Lot 55D128: Black Book, Tab 146: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, Far East</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ridgway</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Joint Chiefs of
                            Staff</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-28T22:30:00+09:00">28
                            November 1951—10:30 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>C–58207. <gloss target="#t_CINCUNC1">CINCUNC</gloss> Adv HNC 491 for info.</p>
                <p>“Further to HNC 490:<note n="1" xml:id="d752fn1">Dated November 28, <ref
                            target="#pg_1194">p. 1194</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>“1. Nam Il opened afternoon session with strong refutation of 3 and 4 principles
                    proposed by <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss>. He said the <gloss
                        target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> seeks to delay solution of Korean problem
                    through a prolonged armistice and that to attempt to substitute an armistice for
                    a peaceful settlement is to disclose an unwillingness to settle the problem
                    peacefully. He said there is a possibility of an armistice not primarily because
                    there exists a balance of force but because of the wishes of the people of the
                    world, including those of the US. Moreover, he said, there is a possibility of
                    further solutions immediately after the armistice; however, setting up a
                    permanent balance of force in Korea will not lead to a peaceful solution. The
                    resumption of hostilities in Korea can be prevented not by a state of balance of
                    war but by the elimination of war through the withdrawal of foreign troops and
                    subsequent steps for peaceful settlement of the Korean problem. Therefore, he
                    said, as soon as the armistice is realized, the governments concerned should
                    negotiate the withdrawal of troops and discuss other ways and means for peaceful
                    settlement of Korean problems and speedily put them into practice. This, he said
                    is the only real guarantee against resumption of hostilities and the third
                    principle of the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> is groundless. He said if
                    the <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> insists upon starting broad discussions
                    now on preventing resumption of hostilities his side is in favor of doing so,
                    but the question of the withdrawal of foreign forces within a definite period
                    must come first. He said again that the concrete measures proposed by the <pb
                        facs="1215" n="1199" xml:id="pg_1199"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> were inappropriate and impracticable and
                    that his side could not agree to the third principle and the 4 which follows
                    from it.</p>
                <p>“2. Balance of session was spent in defense by <gloss target="#t_UNC1"
                        >UNC</gloss> delegation of its 3 principle and continuous refutation by Nam
                    Il along the lines indicated above. Among significant statements are the
                    following. ‘We hold that all foreign troops should be withdrawn immediately. We
                    are not attempting to increase our forces, but we oppose any attempt to avoid
                    the withdrawal of troops and hamper final settlement of the Korean problem.’
                    ‘Your side seeks to discuss problems beyond the scope of a military armistice
                    but related to the withdrawal of troops. By this means you seek to avoid the
                    withdrawal of troops in the future.’</p>
                <p>“3. ‘The maintenance of an armistice through the maintenance of a balance of
                    forces is not possible. It lies in the sincerity of both sides, the basic and
                    permanent solution is the withdrawal of troops. We insist on the withdrawal of
                    all foreign troops. Your side under pretext of maintenance of balance of forces
                    seeks to continue a state of war and evade solution of the Korean problem.’</p>
                <p>“4. ‘Principles 3 and 4, are beyond scope of 3 item of agenda. They are closely
                    related to withdrawal of troops. Without solving the basic question of
                    withdrawal these questions cannot be settled. Therefore, we completely oppose
                    principles 3 and 4. We insist in carrying on discussion within scope of agenda.’
                    Repeated several times in varying forms was the statement that principles 3 and
                    4 cannot be considered until the problem of foreign troops is settled. When
                    pinned down Nam Il stated that ‘withdrawal of foreign troops will settle
                    principles 3 and 4.’</p>
                <p>“5. In summary the Commie position is that withdrawal of foreign troops will make
                        <gloss target="#t_UNC1">UNC</gloss> principles 3 and 4 unnecessary and so
                    far this is the strong stand of the Communists on agenda item 3. The delegations
                    meet tomorrow 29 November at 1100 hours.</p>
                <p>“Sgd Joy.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
