<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>10. Letter From the Secretary of State to the to the President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="10"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                <head>10. Letter From the <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d10fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Conference Files: Lot 63 D 123, CF 991. Secret; Priority. Transmitted in
                        Dulte 8, which is the source text, with the note: “Eyes only Acting
                        Secretary for President from Secretary.” Dulte 8 was drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Manila</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-03-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 13, 1958</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: We have now finished the <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> aspect of the trip and our Manila visit
                    except for a final dinner being given tonight by President <persName
                        corresp="#p_GCP1">Garcia</persName>. I may have a chance at the dinner to
                    finalize the date for his visit to Washington.<note n="2" xml:id="d10fn2">This
                        visit took place June 17–20.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Everything went extremely well at the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                    meeting and the series of talks made in closed session by the foreign ministers
                    was of particularly high character and marked this meeting of the Council as
                    superior in my opinion to any yet held.</p>
                <p>Following the meeting I had a highly confidential talk with <persName
                        corresp="#p_LS1">Lloyd</persName> and Casey about the situation in
                    Indonesia. It did not produce any very bright or constructive ideas but was I
                    think useful particularly in giving Casey, who was quite jittery on this
                    subject, some idea of our own concern and of our own activity.</p>
                <p>Our plane, while resting here at Manila, lost an engine in some strange way, so
                    that we will go on to Taipei tomorrow morning in a C54, hoping that a substitute
                    can be installed and the Constellation can pick us up somewhere as we turn from
                    Taipei eastward.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Doug MacArthur</persName> is here and seems to be in fine shape. I
                    asked him to come so that we could have a quiet talk together about the
                    situation in Japan and Okinawa, which I think requires some of the enlightened
                    statesmanship of which we often talk.</p>
                <p>Your prayers with reference to the communiqué were answered,<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d10fn3">In Tedul 13 to Manila, March 12, marked “For Secretary from
                        President” and concerned mainly with arrangements for <persName
                            corresp="#p_GCP1">Garcia</persName>’s visit, the President concluded:
                        “With warm regards and my prayers that your patience will outlast the
                        preparation of the communiqué.” (Department of State, Conference Files: Lot
                        63 D 123, CF 991)</note> and after three nerve-wracking hours, a reasonably
                    satisfactory agreement was reached. At least it was not as bad as when we made
                    the communiqué at Bermuda with Winston and Laniel.<note n="4" xml:id="d10fn4"
                        >Reference is to the tripartite meeting of heads of government held in
                        Bermuda December 4–8, 1953, attended by President <persName
                            corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>, British Prime Minister Winston
                        S. Churchill, and French Prime Minister Joseph Laniel.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Foster</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="5" xml:id="d10fn5">Dulte 8 bears this typed signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
