<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-08-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-08-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="243" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d243">
                        <head>243. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_PJG1" type="from">Parsons</persName>) to
                            the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d243fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 751J.00/8–1759. Secret. Drafted by
                                    <persName>Chapman</persName> and cleared with <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> was
                                Acting Secretary.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-08-19"><hi rend="italic">August 19,
                                1959</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Situation in Laos</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Royal Lao Government decided last week to send a special
                            representative to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> to discuss the
                            situation in Laos with the Secretary General and possibly to make an
                            appeal to him to send an observer. The representative, <persName corresp="#p_NS1">Ngon Sananikone</persName>, brother of the Prime
                            Minister, arrived this morning in New York, Wednesday, August 19.</p>
                        <pb facs="0595" n="561" xml:id="pg_561"/>
                        <p>The Lao Government’s decision to appeal to the Secretary General was
                            triggered by the British presentation of their proposal to have the
                                <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, as co-Chairmen of the Geneva Conference, request the
                            Secretary General to send an observer to Laos who would report both to
                            the co-Chairmen and the Secretary General. The co-Chairmen then would
                            consider the matter further to see what additional action was required.
                            Upon being informed of this proposal, the Lao Government feared that
                            unless it took some action first the world would have the impression
                            Laos was in the wrong and had something to hide.</p>
                        <p>On the afternoon of Monday, August 17, the British presented their
                            proposal to Soviet Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MYA1">Malik</persName>, who argued for the return of the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> and only grudgingly agreed to forward
                            the proposal to his Government.<note n="2" xml:id="d243fn2">Reported in
                                telegram 884 from London, August 18. (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.,
                                751J.00/8–1859)</note> The Soviet Government has not yet given its
                            answer.</p>
                        <p>We seriously doubt that the Soviets will accede to the British proposal.
                            Such an agreement would mean a reversal of the position that the
                            Communist Bloc has so far taken, namely, that the situation in Laos can
                            only be resolved by the recall of the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>. As an indication of Soviet attitudes, the Soviet
                            Ministry of Foreign Affairs on Tuesday, August 18, issued a lengthy
                            statement attacking the Royal Government primarily and the U.S.
                            secondarily for violating the Geneva Agreement.<note n="3" xml:id="d243fn3">Reference is to a statement of the Soviet Foreign
                                Ministry, August 1 7, charging that the Royal Government of Laos had
                                violated the Geneva Agreement of 1954 by delaying the integration of
                                the Pathet Lao, by evading the obligation for <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> control over the introduction of
                                foreign military personnel into Laos, and by violating the November
                                1957 agreement for a political settlement with the Pathet Lao. The
                                Soviet Union also charged that the Lao Government was flooding the
                                country with U.S. servicemen. The Soviet statement is summarized in
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, September 7,
                                1959, p. 344, <ref target="#d243fn2">footnote 2</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>We are concerned that (1) the Lao representative might make a premature
                            formal request for an observer to the Secretary General and (2) that the
                            Soviets will turn down the British proposal. Since we believe that the
                            Secretary General will not accede to a unilateral request from the Lao
                            Government and will only agree to send an observer if this request were
                            backed by the co-Chairmen, the effect of a Soviet refusal would be to
                            force the Secretary General to turn down the Lao request and to put the
                            British in a highly embarrassing position. (The British already consider
                            themselves to be in a difficult—if not ludicrous—position.)</p>
                        <p>If, as we expect, the Soviets turn down the British proposal and if our
                            analysis of the causes of the fighting in Laos is correct, then we
                            should expect a further outbreak of fighting in northern Laos following
                            a Soviet refusal. The purpose of creating new tensions would be to add
                            further pressures for the recall of the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>.</p>
                        <pb facs="0596" n="562" xml:id="pg_562"/>
                        <p>While diplomatic moves are probably the only ones which have a real
                            chance of bringing peace to Laos, nevertheless we feel we should help
                            strengthen the Lao Army in order to maintain its morale and will to
                            resist, as well as to strengthen its security posture. Our
                            representatives in Laos and <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>
                            have strongly supported a Lao request for raising the force levels as
                            follows: <list>
                                <item>Army from 25,000 to 29,000</item>
                                <item>Auto-defense from 16,000 to 20,000.<note n="4" xml:id="d243fn4">In a memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_BJO1">Bell</persName>, August 19, Weiss
                                        described a meeting on the morning of August 19 among
                                            <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PJG1">Parsons</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GM1">Green</persName>, other <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> staff, and himself, in which
                                        Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> queried the rationale and cost behind
                                        the request for raising Lao force levels. Murphy required
                                        the recommendation of Ambassador <persName>Smith</persName>
                                        before definite action was taken. (Department of State, G/PM
                                        Files: Lot 64 D 351, Laos; included in <ref target="frus1958-60v15-16mSupp1">the microfiche
                                            supplement</ref>)</note></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The proposal is under urgent study.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>