<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>261. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d261</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">261</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-01-13T14:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-12-31T11:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-31T11:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-13T14:30:00-05:00" n="261" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d261">
                <head>261. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>At the request of the Royal Government of Laos, Secretary-General <persName
                        corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjöld</persName> asked the President of the Security
                    Council to convene the Council to consider the situation in Laos. The Security
                    Council agreed on September 7, by a vote of 10 to 1 (<gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss>), to include the item on its agenda. The U.S. Representative
                    then introduced a draft resolution sponsored jointly by France, the United
                    Kingdom, and the United States to appoint a factfinding subcommittee of
                    representatives of Argentina, Italy, Japan, and Tunisia whose task it was to
                    examine the situation in Laos and report back to the Council. By a vote of 10 to
                    1 (<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>), the Security Council ruled that the
                    draft resolution <pb facs="0640" n="606" xml:id="pg_606"/> was of a procedural
                    nature and was not subject to veto. This finding was supported by the President.
                    The Security Council then voted 10 to 1 (<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>),
                    to adopt the joint draft resolution.</p>
                <p>The adopted resolution, <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> document 8/4216,
                    September 7, reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Security Council</p>
                        <p>“Decides to appoint a sub-committee consisting of Argentina, Italy, Japan
                            and Tunisia, and instructs this sub-committee to examine the statements
                            made before the Security Council concerning Laos, to receive further
                            statements and documents and to conduct such inquiries as it may
                            determine necessary and to report to the Security Council as soon as
                            possible.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>After the adoption, the Soviet Representative declared that the resolution had
                    been approved in violation of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> Charter
                    and all existing rules of procedure. He therefore regarded it as illegal and not
                    binding.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
