<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>272. Special National Intelligence Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">272</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-09-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="272"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d272">
                <head>272. Special National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d272fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1"
                            >INR</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> Files. Secret. A note
                        on the cover sheet indicates that the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>, and the intelligence organizations
                        of the Army, Navy, and The Joint Staff participated in the preparation of
                        this estimate, which was submitted to the U.S. Intelligence Board on
                        September 18. All members of the Board concurred with the exception of the
                        representatives of the AEC and FBI who abstained on the grounds that the
                        topic was outside their jurisdiction.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> 68–2–59</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-09-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 18, 1959</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">THE SITUATION IN LAOS</p>
                <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                <p>To estimate Communist capabilities and short-run intentions in Laos, and to
                    estimate the reactions of Communist and non-Communist countries to certain
                    contingent developments.</p>
                <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>We believe that the Communist resumption of guerrilla warfare in Laos was
                        primarily a reaction to a stronger anti-Communist posture by the Laotian
                        Government and to recent US initiatives in support of Laos. We consider that
                        it was undertaken mainly to protect the Communist apparatus in Laos and to
                        improve Communist prospects for gaining control of the country. (Paras.
                        7–8)</item>
                    <pb facs="0659" n="625" xml:id="pg_625"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The Communists probably believed: (a) that guerrilla warfare offered some
                        prospects—at low risk—of promoting Communist objectives in Laos even if the
                        Laotian Government received substantial moral and material support from the
                        outside, and (b) that military forces which the West would be likely to
                        commit inside Laos would be indecisive against the flexible Communist
                        guerrilla tactics. (Para. 18)</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>We estimate that the Communists intend to keep the risks and the costs of
                        their action on a low level and they are not likely in the near future to
                        resort to large-scale guerrilla activity, at least so long as the <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> fact-finding mission is in Laos. (Para.
                        19)</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Most uncommitted and anti-Communist countries would probably support
                        Western intervention in Laos if they were convinced that the Laotian
                        Government’s position was grave and that there was direct Communist Bloc
                        support of the Laotian rebels. In that event, they would prefer that such
                        action be taken under <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> auspices. (Paras.
                        24–26)</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Hanoi and Peiping have warned that any foreign military intervention in
                        Laos would be considered as a direct threat to their national security.
                        However, depending partly on the scale and nature of the military move, the
                        Communist military reaction to the Western intervention, whether under
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                            >SEATO</gloss>, or US auspices, initially would probably take the form
                        of further covert North Vietnamese intervention rather than overt invasion.
                        There probably would be less effort than at present to camouflage this
                        intervention. This Communist action might, in the first instance, be limited
                        to seizing substantial territory in Laos—such as Sam Neua and Phong Saly
                        provinces—which we believe they could do under existing conditions with an
                        augmentation of present guerrilla forces, and then using this situation for
                        political bargaining purposes. The Communists would probably be prepared to
                        accept prolonged and unresolved struggle, particularly if the country were
                        geographically divided. If non-Asian forces were committed in Laos, the
                        likelihood of an overt Communist invasion would increase.<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d272fn2">The Director of Intelligence and Research, Department
                            of State; the Assistant Chief of Staff for Intelligence, Department of
                            the Army; the Assistant Chief of Naval Operations for Intelligence,
                            Department of the Navy; and the Director for Intelligence, The Joint
                            Staff, would delete this sentence, believing it oversimplifies the
                            factors which might lead to an overt Communist invasion. [Footnote in
                            the source text.]</note> (Para. 21)</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>If the Communists should come to believe that a Western intervention
                        appeared capable of resolving the conflict and establishing firm
                        anti-Communist control over Laos, they would then face the difficult
                        decision of whether to raise the ante further, possibly to the point of
                        openly committing North Vietnamese or Chinese Communist forces to the
                        fighting. We estimate that both Communist China and the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> wish to avoid serious risk of expanding
                        into the Far East or <pb facs="0660" n="626" xml:id="pg_626"/> beyond. We
                        believe, therefore, that the Communists would seek through various uses of
                        diplomacy, propaganda, covert action and guerrilla warfare to cause the West
                        to back down. If, however, the Communists became convinced during the course
                        of a series of actions and counteractions that the US intended to commit
                        major US combat forces into Laos, we believe that the odds would be better
                        than even that the Communists would directly intervene in strength with
                        North Vietnamese and possibly Chinese Communist military forces.<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d272fn3">
                            <p>The Assistant Chief of Staff, Intelligence, <gloss target="#t_USAF1"
                                    >USAF</gloss> believes that the likelihood of overt intervention
                                by Chinese Communist or North Vietnamese forces would be
                                significantly reduced if the Communists were convinced that the US
                                would not limit its counteroperations in an expanding conflict to
                                the territory of Laos.</p>
                            <p>The Director of Intelligence and Research, Department of State; the
                                Assistant Chief of Staff for Intelligence, Department of the Army;
                                and the Assistant Chief of Naval Operations for Intelligence,
                                Department of the Navy, believe that the last sentence of this
                                paragraph overstates somewhat the willingness of North Vietnam and
                                Communist China to use major military force against the US in the
                                Laos situation, and therefore would delete the sentence and
                                substitute the following: “If these measures failed, North Vietnam,
                                and possibly Communist China, might resort to at least a show of
                                military force in a last effort to make these pressures on the West
                                effective, and the risks of overt Communist military intervention
                                would thus increase. In the end, however, the Communists would be
                                unlikely to press such use of force to a point which in their
                                estimation would approach serious risk of large-scale hostilities.”
                                The Assistant Chief of Staff for Intelligence, Department of the
                                Army, would add the following clause: “particularly if they were
                                convinced that the US would not limit its counteroperations in an
                                expanding conflict to the territory of Laos.” [Footnote in the
                                source text.]</p>
                        </note> (Para. 22)</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follows the “Discussion” section, which is included in <ref
                        target="frus1958-60v15-16mSupp1">the microfiche supplement</ref>.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
