<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>426. Memorandum of Discussion at the 463d Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, October 13, 1960</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d426</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">426</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-10-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-10-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="426"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d426">
                <head>426. Memorandum of Discussion at the 463d Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, October 13, 1960<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d426fn1"
                        >Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, Whitman
                        File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records. Top Secret. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_JRH1">Johnson</persName> on October 18.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-10-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 13, 1960</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follow a paragraph listing the participants at the meeting and item 1. The
                    discussion on Laos was part of item 2, “Significant World Developments Affecting
                    U.S. Security.”]</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> then briefed the Council on the
                    situation in Laos. He noted that we did not yet have a full report on the
                    mission of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PJG1">Parsons</persName>, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RVAHD1"
                        >Admiral Riley</persName>. They had gone initially to Bangkok, then to
                    Vientiane, and were just now arriving in Luang Prabang. A preliminary report on
                    their talk with <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> had been
                    received this morning but there had not been time yet to analyze it.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d426fn2">Apparent reference to telegram 729, <ref target="#d425">
                            <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The President inquired whether they had seen <persName corresp="#p_PNBG1"
                        >Phoumi</persName> while they were in Bangkok. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> stated that they had not. Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> went on to point out that we
                    had not decided where or when they will see <persName corresp="#p_PNBG1"
                        >Phoumi</persName>. They would try to get him to come to Luang Prabang. If
                    they could not see him there, they would attempt to arrange a meeting in
                    Bangkok, and if that proved impossible, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IJNII1"
                        >Irwin</persName> would go to see him in Savannakhet. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> went on to say that <persName
                        corresp="#p_PNBG1">Phoumi</persName>’s fortunes were up somewhat. Troops in
                    Plaines des Jarres had disassociated themselves from the Vientiane group
                    although we were not sure whether they had lined up fully with Phoumi. The
                    situation in the First Military Region was also better. According to the latest
                    report, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> stated, the
                    government had agreed to move to Luang Prabang. This had been suggested to them
                    as a result of instructions from Washington. We were not sure whether <persName
                        corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> was playing straight on this.
                    However, the agreement would help us smoke him out; if he did not move, we could
                    draw certain conclusions.</p>
                <pb facs="0932" n="898" xml:id="pg_898"/>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> noted that a preliminary
                    meeting between the government and the Pathet Lao had taken place and that
                    another was scheduled today. The new Soviet Ambassador, who is also the Soviet
                    Ambassador to Cambodia, was arriving today in Vientiane. However, in order to be
                    formally accredited, he had to go to Luang Prabang. Thus all of the forces
                    involved in this situation were coming together and a denouement could be
                    expected in the next day or two. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        >Dillon</persName> went on to observe that one difficulty in getting
                        <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> to go to Luang
                    Prabang was the fact that he was engaged in negotiations with the Pathet Lao. We
                    had asked him to postpone these negotiations. He had not acceded but had stated
                    that no agreements would be reached on hard terms.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> resumed his briefing, stating
                    that we think the Soviet Ambassador will make some kind of offer to the Laotian
                    Government. <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> had been
                    warned of this possibility by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName>
                    and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PJG1">Parsons</persName>. It looked as though
                    General Ouane, the senior military commander in <persName corresp="#p_SPP1"
                        >Souvanna Phouma</persName>’s camp, was breaking away from him more and
                    more. We may be able to induce him to go to Luang Prabang. This would permit the
                    possible fusion of his forces with those of <persName corresp="#p_PNBG1"
                        >Phoumi</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName>
                    concluded that the military situation had improved.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> noted that we had made
                    representations to our allies on our plan for dealing with the situation. The
                    French had come along best; they had bought it. They did not think it was
                    possible to avoid the first meeting between <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna
                        Phouma</persName> and the Pathet Lao but they agreed that after this
                    meeting, <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> should disengage
                    and go to Luang Prabang. The British reaction had been the worst. They feared
                    that if <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> leaves Vientiane,
                    it would mean turning Vientiane over to the Pathet Lao. They also believe that
                    great care should be taken in breaking off negotiations with the Pathet Lao,
                    although they agree that no agreements should be made in the present weak
                    situation. These views had been conveyed to us as the considered views of the
                    British Foreign Office. In the view of the Foreign Office, the conclusion of a
                    cease-fire between the Pathet Lao and the government was the overriding
                    consideration. The Foreign Office believed that gradual progress should be made
                    toward a neutralist government as the only solution in the long run. The Foreign
                    Office had told the British Ambassador not to support the U.S. plan but it had
                    asked him to listen to the U.S. and to go along generally but not on details of
                    the plan.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> pointed out that 200
                    paratroopers trained in Thailand were now in the Fourth Military Region in Laos.
                    He also noted that there was a press report that all Thai nationals in Vientiane
                    had been ordered back to Thailand. A figure of 20,000 such nationals had been
                    mentioned. There are not that many Thai in Vientiane. It was more <pb
                        facs="0933" n="899" xml:id="pg_899"/> like the total for all of Laos. We do
                    not know why the Thai Government has taken this action. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> observed that it sounded a little
                    ominous. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Dulles</persName> noted that this
                    report had not been confirmed but that the indications were that the Thai
                    Foreign Ministry had made such an announcement.</p>
                <p>[Here follow discussion of subjects unrelated to Laos and the remaining agenda
                    items.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JRH1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Robert H. Johnson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
