<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-31T11:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-13T14:30:00-05:00" n="439" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d439">
                        <head>439. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>At a meeting at the Pentagon beginning at 11 a.m. on October 28,
                            representatives of the Department of State, the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
                            and the Department of Defense conferred on Laos. The first topic they
                            discussed was a memorandum prepared by Assistant Secretary of Defense
                            Irwin proposing four courses of action to improve the military
                            capability of anti-Communist forces in Laos. Irwin’s memorandum called
                            for: 1) a speed-up of delivery of supplies to <persName corresp="#p_PNBG1">Phoumi</persName> and the Lao Armed Forces in
                            Military Region 1; 2) assistance to <persName corresp="#p_PNBG1">Phoumi</persName>’s forces in regrouping, reorganization, and
                            training; 3) help for <persName corresp="#p_PNBG1">Phoumi</persName> in
                            military and political planning, and 4) stationing of <gloss target="#t_PEO1">PEO</gloss> personnel as Lao military advisers at
                            the battalion level. (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_GTSJ1">Gates</persName>,
                            October 28; Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> Files: FRC 64 A
                            2093, Laos 091; included in <ref target="frus1958-60v15-16mSupp1">the
                                microfiche supplement</ref>)</p>
                        <p>Under Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>
                            made two comments on <persName corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName>’s
                            memorandum. First, he asked the representatives at the meeting to
                            remember that it was U.S. policy to achieve a political settlement in
                            Laos without a civil war. Second, Merchant agreed with Irwin’s first
                            three points, but not the last. U.S. advisers at the battalion level,
                                <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> stated, risked the
                            threat of “volunteers” from North Vietnam and worldwide damage to U.S.
                            interests should their role be made public. There was general
                            disagreement by the participants along agency lines whether or not the
                            Lao wanted U.S. advisers. The disagreement then moved to the most basic
                            issue: whether the United States should work through <persName corresp="#p_PNBG1">Phoumi</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> and who was more trustworthy.</p>
                        <pb facs="0968" n="934" xml:id="pg_934"/>
                        <p>The discussion returned to the issue of U.S. advisers at the battalion
                            level. Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_PJG1">Parsons</persName> suggested that members of the Royal Thai Police
                            Aerial Resupply Unit (<gloss target="#t_PARU1">PARU</gloss>s) should be
                            used as advisers in Laos. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> agreed that the <gloss target="#t_PARU1">PARU</gloss>s were preferable to U.S. officers, but suggested that
                            this was an issue for the President and the Secretaries of State and
                            Defense to decide.</p>
                        <p>The group then discussed a draft of telegram 466, <ref target="#d440"><hi rend="italic">infra</hi></ref>. <persName corresp="#p_PJG1">Parsons</persName> again raised the need for a political settlement
                            in Laos and suggested that the draft telegram provided a legal way to
                            support Lao anti-Communists. Irwin thought the action proposed in the
                            draft was “excellent” Asked what would be <persName corresp="#p_KLC1">Kong Le</persName>’s and the Pathet Lao’s response to the proposed
                            government, and how would the United States react, Parsons suggested
                            that if <persName corresp="#p_KLC1">Kong Le</persName> and the Pathet
                            Lao attacked with North Vietnamese support, the United States would use
                                <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> and the United Nations.
                            Parsons also raised the possibility of unilateral U.S. action. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> summarized the sense of the
                            meeting by stating that there was agreement on the course of action in
                            the draft and that the Departments of State and Defense would take a
                            hard look at the problem of battalion advisers. (Memorandum of
                            discussion at the State–<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> meeting,
                            October 28; Department of State, State–<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Meetings: Lot 70 D 328; included in <ref target="frus1958-60v15-16mSupp1">the microfiche
                            supplement</ref>)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>