<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-11-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="442" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d442">
                        <head>442. Memorandum From the Secretary of Defense’s Special Assistant for
                            Special Operations (<persName corresp="#p_LCEG1" type="from">Lansdale</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                            International Security Affairs(<persName corresp="#p_IJNII1" type="to">Irwin</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d442fn1">Source:
                                Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: FRC 64 B 2170, 092 Asia. Top
                                Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-11-04"><hi rend="italic">November 4,
                                1960</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>State Outgoing Cable 466<note n="2" xml:id="d442fn2"><ref target="#d440">Document 440</ref>.</note> and Vientiane’s
                                    861<note n="3" xml:id="d442fn3">In telegram 861, November 2,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BBGR1">Brown</persName> stated that
                                    before responding to the plan set forth in telegram 466 to
                                    Vientiane, he thought it useful to stress the gradual emergence
                                    of a neutralist anti-Communist faction in Laos which was
                                        pro-<persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> and
                                    anti-Pathet Lao. <persName corresp="#p_BBGR1">Brown</persName>
                                    thought that telegram 466 “overstated U.S. ability accomplish
                                    desired results” in Laos and recommended that the United States
                                    continue to press <persName corresp="#p_PNBG1">Phoumi</persName>
                                    and <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna</persName> to reach an
                                    accommodation. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                    751J.00/11–160; included in <ref target="frus1958-60v15-16mSupp1">the microfiche
                                        supplement</ref>)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The subject cables point up the need for firmness on our part so that the
                            policy of establishing a pro-US government in Laos is not denigrated.
                            State’s 466 is a start in the right direction but <persName corresp="#p_BBGR1">Brown</persName>’s <pb facs="0973" n="939" xml:id="pg_939"/> reply is lengthy repeat of his consistent feeling
                            that <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Souvanna Phouma</persName> is the man
                            we should support. In the gratuitous initial comments of his 861,
                                <persName corresp="#p_BBGR1">Brown</persName> seems to characterize
                                <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Phouma</persName> as the wave of the
                            future—as the emerging personality on the Laotian scene.</p>
                        <p>If we support <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Phouma</persName>, as <persName corresp="#p_BBGR1">Brown</persName> suggests, we will in effect be
                            supporting the establishment of a neutralist government in Laos. A
                            neutralist government is a dangerous political vehicle for furthering US
                            interests in the area. Furthermore, Laos is too weak to remain neutral
                            long, especially in the hands of a vacillating leader like <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Phouma</persName>.</p>
                        <p>An understandable policy for Laos would be to support elements friendly
                            to the US and seek to establish them in power. What the Ambassador seems
                            to propose is that we support an unfriendly element on the ground that
                            that element is more popular in the country. [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] Incidentally, I am not convinced that <persName corresp="#p_SPP1">Phouma</persName> is the most popular man on the
                            scene in Laos.</p>
                        <p>Since State’s 466 is an effort to put a known, friendly element in power
                            in Laos, I hope we will be able to hold State to it and not let a good
                            policy be watered down.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>