<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>73. Telegram From the Embassy in Cambodia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d73</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">73</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-07-07T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-07-07T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-07-07T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-07-07T05:00:00-05:00" n="73"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                <head>73. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Cambodia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d73fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 651G.51H/7–758. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Niact1">Niact</gloss>.
                        Repeated to Saigon, London, Paris, <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1"
                            >CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>, Bangkok,
                        and Vientiane.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Phnom Penh</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-07-07T17:00:00+07:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 7, 1958—5 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>30. It is difficult to sort out the many things that have happened last few days
                    but one fact seems to emerge prominently, namely, that Cambodia is at a
                    crossroads. I am convinced <persName corresp="#p_NSP1">Sihanouk</persName> has
                    wanted and still wants a solution of his problems with Vietnam through the
                    instrumentality of Western powers. Considerable evidence is accumulating that he
                    is playing with the idea of support of some kind from Red China but I am still
                    sure he believes that Cambodia’s true friends are in the West and that a closer
                    approach to Communist bloc would be basically distasteful to him.</p>
                <p>However, <persName corresp="#p_NSP1">Sihanouk</persName> feels put upon and
                    abandoned. He believes that Cambodia’s Western friends have been indifferent in
                    his time of trouble. In speech at Kompong Cham July 5 he said “For our
                    tranquility we ought to choose a great ally who is not too far from us and who
                    is ready to aid us. I do not mean that we want an ally as in the time of <pb
                        facs="0268" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/> the protectorate. I do not think we
                    ought to go as far as that. Our peaceful means have not yet been exhausted. On
                    the other hand we should not hesitate to find flesh-and-bones ally to prepare
                    ourselves against every eventuality”.</p>
                <p>Later in speech he complains bitterly request for help addressed to US of no
                    avail. “While <gloss target="#t_RKG1">RKG</gloss> has asked US to go to verify
                    facts on the spot, US contents itself to say, of what use? The incident is
                    closed as has been established. The free world insults us and we are to blame
                    but it refuses to verify our charges. How can they say we are guilty if they
                    refuse to check? The US considered my meeting with <persName corresp="#p_Diem1"
                        >Diem</persName> a good idea but sensing that this meeting might bear fruit
                    and that new violations might not recur they pushed the (Vietnamese) newspapers
                    and the members of the government to oppose the meeting. These acts wound us but
                    do not discourage us. The basic means of our neutrality are not exhausted. If
                    they were we would be obliged to seize whatever means there might be at our
                    command in order to live”.</p>
                <p>The solution of this problem would clearly seem to be settlement between Cambodia
                    and Vietnam. This is desired by all the Western powers represented here, US,
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, France and Australia, and certainly by
                    Cambodia. <persName corresp="#p_NSP1">Sihanouk</persName> seemed to have removed
                    the greatest difficulty, namely the question of who should make the first
                    approach, by volunteering to go to Saigon. However, after having been told he
                    would be received, whole project fell through as result bitter and vicious
                    attack on <persName corresp="#p_NSP1">Sihanouk</persName> in semi-official <hi
                        rend="italic">Vietnam Presse</hi> July 3.<note n="2" xml:id="d73fn2"
                        >According to telegram 39 from Saigon, the article was entitled, “A Ninny’s
                        Policy.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 751H.11/7–758) This article was
                        followed on July 4 by a Times of Viet-Nam piece entitled, “What Is <persName
                            corresp="#p_NSP1">Sihanouk</persName> Up To,” possibly written by
                            <persName corresp="#p_NDN1">Ngo Dinh Nhu</persName>, that while not
                        “inflammatory” was “disobligingly blunt.” (Telegram 29 from Saigon, July 5;
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 751H.11/7–558)</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> Foreign Minister issued official communiqué
                    July 6 whose first paragraph was mollifying in tone but which in its effect did
                    not improve situation (Saigon’s 31 to Department).<note n="3" xml:id="d73fn3"
                        >This telegram, July 6, contained a summary of the official Vietnamese
                        communiqué of July 6. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 751H.11/7–658)</note>
                </p>
                <p>I have twice recommended US intervene in strong and unequivocal fashion with
                        <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> to require them to settle their
                    difficulties with Cambodia.<note n="4" xml:id="d73fn4">In telegrams 1312 and
                        1338 from Phnom Penh, June 20 and 25. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                        751H.00/6–2058 and 651G.51H/6–2558)</note> Department has replied that US
                    cannot tell <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> what to do.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d73fn5">See <ref target="#d72">
                            <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> However, in absence firm action by US, <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> has acted and, in effect, established policy
                    for West vis-à-vis Cambodia which is exactly contrary to policy desired by all
                    Western powers represented here. Even if negotiations can be rescheduled, they
                    will not succeed unless <persName corresp="#p_Diem1">Diem</persName> can be
                    persuaded <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>’s self-interest makes success
                    desirable. I <pb facs="0269" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> do not believe we have
                    any choice except to present matter to <persName corresp="#p_Diem1"
                        >Diem</persName> as vital to his own interest and to that of West and to
                    insist on negotiations with Cambodia in good faith.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SCW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Strom</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
