<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-08-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.00101/146</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Minutes of the Daily Meetings of the Commissioners
                            Plenipotentiary, Saturday, August 30, 1919</hi></head>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1919-08-30">August 30, 1919</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <item>Present: <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Polk</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. White</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">General Bliss</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Harrison</hi></item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>I. Memorandum No. 558, suggesting that the Commissioners recommend Major J.
                        Ronald McCrindle, commanding No. 2 Communication Squadron, be recommended
                        for the award of the Distinguished Service Medal, was read.</p>
                    <p>The Commissioners approved and directed that a letter be sent to the State
                        Department requesting the Secretary of State to submit the matter to the
                        Secretary of War.</p>
                    <p>Award of Distinguished Services Medal to Major McCrindle, R. A. F.</p>
                    <p>II. The Secretary read for the information of the Commissioners a telegram
                        transmitting Mr. Hoover’s reply to the Department’s telegram No. 9058 of
                        August 25, 9:00 a.m., regarding the shipment of flour to General
                            Yudenitch.<note n="31" xml:id="d146fn31">For the Department’s telegram,
                            see <ref target="frus1919Russia#pg_705"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi>, 1919, Russia, p. 705</ref>. For the reply as
                            sent, see <ref target="frus1919Russia#pg_707"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 707</ref>.</note>
                        <seg type="margin">Food Supplies for Gen. Yudenitch</seg></p>
                    <p>III. The Secretary read a draft telegram in reply to the Department’s
                        telegram No. 2948 of August 26, 2:00 p.m., with regard to the immediate
                        repatriation of some 55 invalid German prisoners of war now held at Fort
                        McNulty, Georgia. <seg type="margin">Repatriation of Invalid German
                            Prisoners of War in the United States</seg></p>
                    <p>The Commissioners approved.</p>
                    <p>IV. Memorandum No. 559 regarding a request through the Department of Commerce
                        by the Commercial Attaché of the American Embassy at Paris, for certain
                        reports of the Supreme Economic Council and other sections of the Peace
                        Conference, which bear on economic conditions in France, and for a copy of
                        General McKinstry’s report, was read. <seg type="margin">The Information for
                            the Commercial Attaché of the Embassy at Paris</seg></p>
                    <pb facs="0437" n="401" xml:id="pg_401"/>
                    <p>The Commissioners approved in principle the suggestion contained in Paragraph
                            “<hi rend="italic">a</hi>” of the memorandum in question and requested
                        that Mr. Dresel assemble the information in question and submit it for the
                        Commissioners’ approval before delivery to the Commercial Attaché.</p>
                    <p>The Commissioners also approved the recommendation contained in Paragraph
                            “<hi rend="italic">d</hi>” of the memorandum in question, with regard to
                        General McKinstry’s report.</p>
                    <p>V. The Secretary read the Department’s telegram, No. 2980 of August 28, 3:00
                            p.m.,<note n="32" xml:id="d146fn32"><ref target="frus1919v01#pg_7"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 7</ref>.</note> and also Memorandum
                        No. 560 with regard to participation in committee work in anticipation of
                        the Treaty. <seg type="margin">American Participation in Committee Work in
                            Anticipation of the Treaty</seg></p>
                    <p>In view of the contents of Section 2 of the Department’s telegram in
                        question, the Commissioners reconsidered their decision of August 29 with
                        regard to American participation on the sub-Committee of the Committee on
                        Execution of the Treaty with Germany and approved the recommendation
                        submitted by Mr. Dresel in the memorandum in question.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>